<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0105" class="p">Our data indicate that feed intake and growth performance were improved in rabbits fed a standard ration supplemented with olive oil and thyme oil under hot environmental conditions. These observations can be regarded as being mainly due to the active components in thyme oil which have been reported to improve, for broilers, production efficiency and promote general health status in high temperature environments (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Attia et al., 2017</xref>). Moreover, supplementation of thyme and oregano as phytogenic additives to rations of broilers (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hippenstiel et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Abdel-Wareth et al., 2012</xref>) and rabbits (
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cardinali et al., 2015</xref>) have increased feed intake and growth performance. Furthermore, herbs and their constituent essential oils are often supposed to improve flavor and, indirectly, palatability of feeds, thus increasing voluntary feed intake which, in turn, results in improved BW gain and FCR (
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zeng et al., 2015</xref>). In the current study, FCR was improved by thyme essential oil supplementation under hot environmental conditions in a dose-dependent manner. These results may be attributable to the positive effect of the thyme compounds on digestive efficiency, which leads to improved FCR (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gerencser et al., 2014</xref>). Essential oils are often claimed to being digestive enhancers and having antimicrobial activity as well as promote general health, yet studies typically lack quantification of active components and elucidating their mode of action and, thus, standardization will be imprecise (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hippenstiel et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bozkurt et al., 2014</xref>). Therefore it is not surprising that other authors (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fallah and Mirzaei, 2016</xref>) have reported that thyme leaves at 1, 1.5 and 5 g/kg ration did not affect the feed intake and FCR of broilers, yet active components of thyme leaves were not quantified. In the present study dietary thyme oil yielded a positive response in terms of production performance of Californian rabbits in a hot environment which may be attributable to the active components of thyme essential oil as analysed in the hydro-distilled thyme essential oil of this study.
</p>
