<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We explored how plant–soil microbe interactions varied across current and future temperatures, as well as current and future ranges for the nonnative study species. We expected that warming would enhance nonnative plant growth, and that the effect of warming on plant growth would be enhanced by plant–microbe interactions because microbial activity increases with temperature. While warming significantly enhanced growth of the nonnative plant species grown in central and northern soils, the opposite was found for plants grown in southern soils. Given that the interaction between climate and soil, and site and soil were not significant, these results do not necessarily reflect plant–soil microbe interactions. The increased biomass of the nonnative species in central and northern soils, under warmer conditions, may reflect some other aspect of the soils from the different parts of the range. Additionally, we expected that there would be fewer negative interactions from co-evolved soil pathogens outside of its current range and a net positive plant–soil microbe interaction in the new range, which we did not find. In accord with our study, conducted in growth chambers with a difference of 1 °C, a greenhouse study comparing plant–microbe interactions of native and nonnative species in the Netherlands found a temperature difference of 5 °C did not influence net plant–microbe interactions of either the native or closely related nonnative species (
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">van Grunsven 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>). In a meta-analysis of natural area responses to global change drivers, mycorrhizal abundances have been found to increase under warmer conditions, however mycorrhizal activity has been found to decrease under warmer conditions (
 <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Mohan 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2014
 </xref>), which may explain this pattern. Given that the plant–microbe interactions for this invasive species did not change under different temperature conditions, it is unlikely that warming significantly increased below-ground pathogens (
 <xref rid="CIT0075" ref-type="bibr">Van der Putten 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>), relative to soil microbiota with positive effects.
</p>
