<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A recent morpho-anatomical local study focused on the morphological and anatomical investigation of 
 <italic>S. virgaurea</italic> from flora of the Republic of Moldova, and its herbal product 
 <italic>Solidaginis virgaureae herba,</italic> was done by Calalb T. et al. [
 <xref rid="B13-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The anatomical features of the highest interest for the exact identification of 
 <italic>S. virgaurea,</italic> established in this study, include: repartition of stomata on both sides of the leaf, anomocytic arrangement of stomata, cone-shaped or fan-shaped multicellular trichomes on both epidermises, as well as glandular trichomes, dorsiventral structure of the leaf with vascular bundles collateral and open, and secretory ducts in the stem. The anomocytic stomata reported for the leaf is consistent with the findings of Szymura M. and Wolsky K. [
 <xref rid="B14-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], who also established that anomotetracytic stomata were the most widespread type in other 
 <italic>Solidago</italic> taxa collected from Poland. The presence of two categories of multicellular trichomes (cone-shaped and fan-shaped) on the goldenrod leaf was also reported by other sources [
 <xref rid="B14-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]: by Buynov MV. on 
 <italic>S. dahurica</italic> leaf [
 <xref rid="B16-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], by Douglas M. et al. on 
 <italic>S. chilensis</italic> leaf [
 <xref rid="B17-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], and by Fedotova VV. on 
 <italic>S. caucasica</italic> leaf [
 <xref rid="B18-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Care is needed for a correct identification, because in the 19th century, a scientific paper written by a medical doctor (based on his personal experience repeated several times) drew the attention to the risks of confusing this medicinal plant with a non-effective (and likely dangerous for the health) 
 <italic>Senecio nemorensis</italic> L. [
 <xref rid="B19-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]
</p>
