<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Gram-positive bacteria 
 <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> (food isolate), 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 11632 and 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> NCTC 7973, and the Gram-negative bacteria 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC 35210, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATCC 27853 and 
 <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium ATCC 13311 were used in order to determine the potential antibacterial activity. For determination antifungal activity 6 strains of fungi were used: 
 <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> ATCC 1022, 
 <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic> ATCC 6275, 
 <italic>Trichoderma viride</italic> IAM 5061, 
 <italic>Penicillium verrucosum</italic> var. 
 <italic>cyclopium</italic> (food isolate), 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> (oral isolate) and 
 <italic>Candida krusei</italic> (oral isolate) were tested for their susceptibility. The bacterial strains were cultured on solid Tryptic Soy agar (TSA), while micromycetes were cultured on solid malt agar (MA) and yeast were sustained on Sabouraud dextrose agar (SDA) medium. The cultures were sub-cultured once a month and stored at 4 °C for further utilization. All the tested microorganisms are deposited at the Mycological Laboratory, Department of Plant Physiology, Institute for Biological Research “Siniša Stankovic”—National Institute of Republic of Serbia, University of Belgrade, Serbia. The antimicrobial activity of samples was determined by the modified microdilution method [
 <xref rid="B42-molecules-26-02124" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-molecules-26-02124" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The results were presented as minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) and minimum bactericidal/fungicidal concentrations (MBCs/MFCs). Streptomycin (Sigma-Aldrich S6501, St. Louis, MO, USA) and ketoconazole (Zorkapharma, Šabac, Serbia) were used as positive controls, and blank-glycerosome (Blank-GS) and blank-propylene glycol-nanovesicles (Blank-PGV) were used as negative control. All the experiments on antimicrobial activity were repeated in triplicate.
</p>
