<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Objective</title>
  <p class="p">Evaluate the effects of i) dehulling of lupine seed on chemical composition and apparent metabolizable energy (AME) and ii) soybean meal substitution by dehulled lupine seed in broiler diets with enzymes on productive performance, size of digestive organs and welfare-related variables.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p class="p">Experiment 1, chemical composition and AME were determined in whole and dehulled lupine seed. Experiment 2, two hundred eighty-eight one-day-old male Ross 308 broilers were used. The experimental diets were maize-soybean meal (MS), MS with enzymes (MSE) and maize-dehulled lupine seed with enzymes (MLE). Diets were assigned to the experimental units under a completely randomized design (eight replicates per diet). The body weight (BW) gain, feed intake, feed conversion, digestive organ weights, gait score, latency to lie down and 
   <italic class="italic">valgus</italic>/
   <italic class="italic">varus</italic> angulation were evaluated.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p class="p">The dehulling process increased protein (25.0% to 31.1%), AME (5.9 to 8.8 MJ/kg) and amino acid contents. The BW gain of broilers fed the MLE diet was similar (p&gt;0.05) to that of those fed the MS diet, but lower than that of those fed the MSE diet. Feed intake of broilers fed the MLE diet was higher (p&lt;0.05) than that of those fed the MS diet and similar (p&gt;0.05) to those fed the MSE diet. Feed conversion of broilers fed the MLE diet was 8.0% and 8.7% higher (p&lt;0.05) than that of those fed the MS and MSE diets, respectively. Broilers fed the MLE diet had the highest (p&lt;0.05) relative proventriculus and gizzard weights, but had poor welfare-related variables.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusion</title>
  <p class="p">It is possible to substitute soybean meal by dehulled lupine seed with enzymes in broiler diets, obtaining similar BW gains in broilers fed the MLE and MS diets; however, a higher feed intake is required. Additionally, the MLE diet reduced welfare-related variables.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
