<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>
   <italic>Terminalia mantaly</italic> is used in Cameroon traditional medicine to treat malaria and related symptoms. However, its antiplasmodial efficacy is still to be established. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Objectives</title>
  <p> The present study is aimed at evaluating the 
   <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
   <italic>in vivo</italic> antiplasmodial activity and the oral acute toxicity of the 
   <italic>Terminalia mantaly</italic> extracts. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Materials and Methods</title>
  <p> Extracts were prepared from leaves and stem bark of 
   <italic>T. mantaly</italic>, by maceration in distilled water, methanol, ethanol, dichloromethane (DCM), and hexane. All extracts were initially screened 
   <italic>in vitro</italic> against the chloroquine-resistant strain W2 of 
   <italic>P. falciparum</italic> to confirm its 
   <italic>in vitro</italic> activity, and the most potent one was assessed in malaria mouse model at three concentrations (100, 200, and 400 mg/kg/bw). Biochemical, hematological, and histological parameters were also determined. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p> Overall, 7 extracts showed 
   <italic>in vitro</italic> antiplasmodial activity with IC
   <sub>50</sub> ranging from 0.809 
   <italic>μ</italic>g/mL to 5.886 
   <italic>μ</italic>g/mL. The aqueous extract from the stem bark of 
   <italic>T. mantaly</italic> (
   <italic>Tm</italic>sb
   <sup>w</sup>) was the most potent (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 0.809 
   <italic>μ</italic>g/mL) and was further assessed for acute toxicity and efficacy in 
   <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic>-infected mice. 
   <italic>Tm</italic>sb
   <sup>w</sup> was safe in mice with a median lethal dose (LD
   <sub>50</sub>) higher than 2000 mg/kg of body weight. It also exerted a good antimalarial efficacy 
   <italic>in vivo</italic> with ED
   <sub>50</sub> of 69.50 mg/kg and had no significant effect on biochemical, hematological, and histological parameters. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p> The results suggest that the stem bark extract of 
   <italic>T. mantaly</italic> possesses antimalarial activity.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
