<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In seeking non-antibiotic microbicides, we have screened dozens of EOs from Chinese indigenous aromatic plants/spices because EOs have been long recognized as one of the most promising natural products for safe microbicides in folk medicines (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lu et al., 2013a</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">b</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">c</xref>). The selection was initially based on their antiseptic applications in the food industry and in agricultures after an extensive database search. Among the dozen EOs tested, about one third showed significant antibacterial activities against clinically and agricultural important microbes (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lu et al., 2013a</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">b</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">c</xref>). Oregano oil stood out as one of the best ones in terms of safety and efficacy. We thus detailed the bactericidal activity of oregano oil against 11 MDR clinical isolates of 
 <italic class="italic">P. aeruginosa, A. baumannii</italic> and MRSA as well as two bioluminescent strains of 
 <italic class="italic">P. aeruginosa</italic> PA01 and MRSA USA300 in the current study. Oregano oil effectively killed all the bacterial strains tested, with the MICs ranging from 0.08 to 0.64 mg/ml and at an order of sensitivity of 
 <italic class="italic">A. baumannii &gt;</italic> MRSA 
 <italic class="italic">&gt; P. aeruginosa</italic> (
 <bold class="bold">Table 
  <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>
 </bold>). The finding is in agreement with previous studies demonstrating that oregano oil and its main component carvacrol had a higher MIC against 
 <italic class="italic">P. aeruginosa</italic> compared to other species, such as 
 <italic class="italic">S.</italic> spp. (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nostro et al., 2007</xref>), 
 <italic class="italic">Chromobacterium violaceum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella typhimurium</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burt et al., 2014</xref>). Similar to the clinical isolates, oregano oil also inactivated standard strains of 
 <italic class="italic">A. baumannii</italic> ATCC 19606 (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rosato et al., 2010</xref>), 
 <italic class="italic">P. aeruginosa</italic> ATCC 27853 and 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> ATCC 29213 (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bouhdid et al., 2009</xref>), with the MICs 0.15 mg/mL, 1 mg/mL, and 0.33 mg/mL, respectively, which are comparable to our investigation. Previous studies suggested that Gram-negative bacteria appeared to be more resistant than Gram-positive bacteria in response to EO (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tepe et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Longaray Delamare et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gilles et al., 2010</xref>). This relative resistance of Gram-negative over Gram-positive bacteria may be ascribed to their cell wall structure and outer membrane arrangement. The outer membrane of Gram-negative bacteria is rich in lipopolysaccharide molecules, relatively impermeable to lipophilic compounds, thereby presenting a barrier to penetration of EO antimicrobial substances (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gao et al., 2011</xref>). It may be also associated with the enzymes in the periplasmic space, which are capable of breaking down the antimicrobial substances upon their entrance of the cells (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nikaido, 1996</xref>). However, our studies disagreed with these observations and found Gram-negative 
 <italic class="italic">A. baumannii</italic> was more sensitive to oregano oil than Gram-positive MRSA. This different outcome suggests that antibacterial activity of oregano oil may not depend on the type of Gram reaction in contrast to other EOs, a possibility that is supported by the studies of 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gao et al. (2011)</xref>. In their studies, Gram-negative bacteria 
 <italic class="italic">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> was the most sensitive bacteria whereas the Gram-positive bacteria 
 <italic class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</italic> was the most resistant strain to the 
 <italic class="italic">Sphallerocarpus gracilis</italic> seed EO (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gao et al., 2011</xref>).
</p>
