<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to negative interactions, a large number of plant species establish symbiotic associations with soil microorganisms (in particular with mycorrhizal fungi and nitrogen-fixing bacteria, [
 <xref rid="pone.0163930.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0163930.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]). In this experiment we detected a higher proportion of ectomycorrhizal fungi in soil samples from oak woodland habitats. This result is expected as ectomycorrhizal fungi are important to oak trees for acquiring nutrients and for increasing root absorptive area [
 <xref rid="pone.0163930.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0163930.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Our results also show that oak litter (rather than shade) influence overall soil fungal community composition and richness, but not soil bacterial community composition and richness. Although plant litter inputs can change important environmental conditions for soil bacteria such as pH and base cation content [
 <xref rid="pone.0163930.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], soil fungi are key decomposers of plant necromass and depend more directly on leaf litter than bacteria [
 <xref rid="pone.0163930.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. We also observed a significantly higher proportion of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi in open grasslands. Given the generally non-specific interactions with arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi, it has been proposed that several invasive plants make use of these fungi to enhance their success [
 <xref rid="pone.0163930.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0163930.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]; but see [
 <xref rid="pone.0163930.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Other invasive plants (for example, the garlic mustard 
 <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>) inhibit mycorrhizal fungi on which natives depend [
 <xref rid="pone.0163930.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Collectively, this work suggests that biocontrol and management initiatives should consider the potentially beneficial plant-microbe interactions rather than just focusing on antagonistic relationships.
</p>
