<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Basil (
 <italic class="italic">Ocimum basilicum</italic> L.) is an annual herb growing in several regions around the world. The genus 
 <italic class="italic">Ocimum</italic> consists of more than 150 species whereof basil is cultivated in many countries as a major essential oil crop [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. The species most commonly used as spices and medicinal herbs are 
 <italic class="italic">O. basilicum</italic> L., 
 <italic class="italic">O. americanum</italic> L. (syn. 
 <italic class="italic">O. canum</italic> Sims.), 
 <italic class="italic">O. gratissimum</italic> L., 
 <italic class="italic">O. kilimandscharicum</italic> Guerke, 
 <italic class="italic">O. tenuiflorum</italic> L. (syn. 
 <italic class="italic">O. sanctum</italic> L.), and 
 <italic class="italic">O. africanum</italic> Lour. (syn. 
 <italic class="italic">O.</italic> × 
 <italic class="italic">citriodorum</italic> Vis.), that is a hybrid of 
 <italic class="italic">O. basilicum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">O. americanum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. The taxonomy of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Ocimum</italic> is very complicated due to the occurrence of interspecific hybridization, polyploidy, aneuploidy, the existence of numerous botanical varieties, and chemotypes, as well as the many synonymous names [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Plants of the species 
 <italic class="italic">O. basilicum</italic> have square stems, fragrant opposite leaves, and whorled flowers on spiked inflorescences [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">O. basilicum</italic> L. is widely used in the culinary arts and in the food processing industry [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Traditionally, it has been used as medicinal plant for the treatment of headaches, coughs, diarrhea, constipation, warts, worms, and kidney malfunction [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. A plethora of biological activities have been attributed to basil essential oils like antimicrobial, insecticidal, and recently was found to exhibit in vivo anti-malarial activity [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. In addition, extracts from leaves and flowers can be used as aroma additives in food, pharmaceutical, and cosmetic industry [
 <xref rid="B10-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Economical data clearly indicate the commercial importance of basil essential oil, since the world production is estimated to 1,200,000 € [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Basil essential oils contain a broad array of chemical compounds depending on variations in chemotypes, flower, and leaf colours, aroma and especially the origin of the plant [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. The essential oil constituents vary among sweet basil cultivars, with linalool, methyl chavicol, eugenol, 1,8-cineole, geranial, neral, methyl cinnamate recognized as main components [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Several scientists have classified basil to different chemotypes according to the main components of the essential oil. Thereby, Marotti et al. (1996) divided essential oil from Italian basil varieties to three chemotypes “linalool”, “linalool-methyl chavicol”, and “linalool-eugenol” [
 <xref rid="B14-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. According to the plant origin, basils are grouped to European chemotype that has linalool and methyl chavicol as main components and Tropical chemotype having methyl chavicol as a main compound [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Concerning the cultivation of basil, the plants can be harvested one to three times during cropping season depending on the climate [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Generally, basil is harvested for the leaves that are sold fresh or dried. In the cases that basil is cultivated for dried leaves and extraction of essential oil, the plants are cut just prior the appearance of the flowers [
 <xref rid="B17-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Scientific data concerning how harvest and number of harvests during the cultivation of aromatic plants affect essential oil quality and composition are lacking either in field or greenhouse conditions. To the best of our knowledge, so far Carlo et al. (2013) studied the effect of cut number in quality traits of sweet basil [
 <xref rid="B18-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Also Zheljazkof et al. (2008) studied the effect of harvests in 
 <italic class="italic">O. basilicum</italic> L. (cvs. German and Mesten) and 
 <italic class="italic">O. sanctum</italic> L. (syn. 
 <italic class="italic">O. tenuiflorum</italic> L.) (cv. Local) cultivated in Mississippi [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Taking into account that geographic position and the environmental characteristics of the habitat should be taken as factors affecting the chemical composition of the essential oils [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>], the current study is the first including total chemical analysis of the essential oils from five basil varieties cultivated and harvested in the field and greenhouse in the island of Kefalonia, (Greece). The aim of our study is the chemical analysis of essential oils from the five varieties of basil considering also the cultivation site as well as how the ability of the plant to rejuvenate after successive cuttings during growing cycle, affects the obtained essential oil yield and composition. In order to simulate the natural growing conditions, successive cuttings were performed in every variety just before flowering stage, as done practically from aromatic plants’ growers. Moreover the cluster analysis of all basil varieties for greenhouse and field samples is given. 
</p>
