<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>, El-Alfy et al. isolated bio-active molecules which include seven flavonoids [quercetin (
 <bold class="bold">12</bold>), chrysoeriol-7-
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>-rhamnoside (
 <bold class="bold">14</bold>), apigenin (
 <bold class="bold">21</bold>), rhamnetin (
 <bold class="bold">22</bold>), Quercetin-3 -
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>-rutinoside (
 <bold class="bold">24</bold>), Rhamnetin-3-
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>-utinoside (
 <bold class="bold">25</bold>) and 6-methoxy-acacetin-8-C- β-glucoside (
 <bold class="bold">26</bold>)], three triterpenoids [lupeol acetate (
 <bold class="bold">16</bold>), β-amyrin (
 <bold class="bold">17</bold>) and α-amyrin (
 <bold class="bold">18</bold>)], two thytosterols [β-sitosterol (
 <bold class="bold">19</bold>) and β-sitosterol-3-
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>-glucoside (
 <bold class="bold">20</bold>)] and one polyphenol [neochlorogenic acid (
 <bold class="bold">23</bold>)]. The isolated compounds were also investigated for anti-cancer activity against breast and colon cancer cell lines and all the compounds found to be good cytotoxic potential on the cell lines tested. Various other pharmacological activities of the above mentioned compounds have been well-documented in the previous studies. For example, lupeol acetate was reported for analgesic, anti-inflammatory, cardioprotective and hepatoprotective potentials (Andrikopoulos et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2003</xref>; Preetha et al., 
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>; Saleem, 
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). β-amyrin and α-amyrin molecules had close structural relationship with lupeol acetate and known for biological activities such as anti-cancer, anti-ulcer, anti-microbial, and anti-inflammatory (Carretero et al., 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; Holanda-Pinto et al., 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; El-Alfy et al., 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Jabeen et al., 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Rosas-Acevedo et al., 
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Apigenin is a natural flavonoid and has many pharmacological activities (anti-oxidant, hypotension, lipid-lowering activity, anti-osteoporosis, hypoglycemia, and immune regulation potential) which are recently reviewed by Zhou et al. (
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). A study performed by Razavi et al. (
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>) indicated that quercetin-3-
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>-rutinoside had antimicrobial, cytotoxic, antioxidant and phytotoxic potential. Rhamnetin-3-O-rutinoside also a flavonoid showed good antihyperglycemic activity on alloxan induced diabetic rats (Merina et al., 
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Ayyari et al. (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) isolated three thiocarbamate [
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>-methyl-4-[(α-L-rhamnosyloxy)benzyl] thiocarbamate (
 <bold class="bold">27</bold>), 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>-ethyl-4-[(α-L-rhamnosyloxy)benzyl] thiocarbamate (
 <bold class="bold">28</bold>) and 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>-butyl-4-[(α-L-rhamnosyloxy)benzyl] thiocarbamate (
 <bold class="bold">29</bold>)] and one isothiocyanate [4-(α-L-rhamnosyloxy) benzyl isothiocyanate (
 <bold class="bold">30</bold>)] glycosides from the aerial parts of 
 <italic class="italic">M. peregrina</italic>. The isolated compounds were studied for 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> cytotoxicity in rat skeletal myoblasts and anti-trypanosomal efficacy against 
 <italic class="italic">Trypanosoma brucei rhodesiense</italic>. The results revealed that thiocarbamate glycosides had moderate 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> effect, whereas, 4-(α-L-rhamnosyloxy) benzyl isothiocyanate showed significant anti-trypanosomal and cytotoxic potential. Many plant molecules have been isolated and reported for biological activities. But, only few compounds were successfully forwarded from the laboratory to clinical trials. This is due to inadequate information on structure characterization and pharmacological efficacy (Kannathasan et al., 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Therefore, sufficient studies on the biological and cytotoxic potential of isolated molecules from 
 <italic class="italic">M. peregrina</italic> are suggested for their safe clinical use.
</p>
