<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Diarylurea MMV665852, the structural analog of TCC mentioned above, was also studied for antimalarial activity and showed an EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 1160 nM against 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> 3D7 (
 <xref rid="antibiotics-10-00092-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Plasmepsins are aspartic proteases that malarial parasites use to digest hemoglobin during the intraerythrocytic stage. Diphenylurea derivative WR268961, obtained from the Walter Reed chemical inventory, was found to inhibit recombinant plasmepsins, which possess kinetic similarity to the native enzymes, with a 
 <italic>K</italic>
 <sub>i</sub> value between 1 and 6 µM. It inhibited the growth of 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> strains W2 and D6, with IC
 <sub>50</sub> ranging from 0.03 to 0.16 µg/mL and showed low toxicity to mammalian cells. Some derivatives of WR268961 in which the amidine moiety was replaced by a sulfonic acidic group, retained plasmepsin inhibitory activity but were poor inhibitors of 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> growth in vitro (figures not shown) [
 <xref rid="B76-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Zhang et al. 2010 studied a large library of diarylureas for antimalarial activity against chloroquine-sensitive (3D7) and chloroquine-resistant (K1) strains of 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic>. PQ401, showed the same potency of chloroquine (EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.053 μM versus 0.047 μM) against the 3D7 cell line in vitro. Compounds 
 <bold>28</bold> and 
 <bold>29</bold> showed higher activity than the parent compound, showing EC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 0.32 and 0.031 μM, respectively, against the same cell line. The most interesting compound of the series was 
 <bold>33</bold> which was 3-fold more potent than chloroquine (EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.016 μM). Compounds 
 <bold>29</bold> and 
 <bold>30</bold> also showed high activity against chloroquine resistant K1 strain (EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.11 and 0.079 μM, respectively, versus 1,23 μM of chloroquine) [
 <xref rid="B20-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Compound 
 <bold>31</bold> demonstrated EC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 0.037 µM and 0.055 µM against in vitro cultured parasite 3D7 (drug-sensitive) and Dd2 (resistant to chloroquine and pyrimethamine–sulfadoxine) 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> strains, respectively. It also demonstrated in vivo efficacy in a 
 <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic> antimalarial mouse model, with &gt;50% survival at day 31 post-treatment after subcutaneous administration at 256 mg/kg [
 <xref rid="B77-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>].
</p>
