<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The heterogeneous intrinsic resistance of Bcc bacteria to a wide range of antibiotics, including the antipseudomonal colistin, has been well documented (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]). Infections are normally treated with a combination of two or three antibiotics, commonly including tobramycin and meropenem, which may be delivered IV, orally or via a nebuliser [
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. However, such treatments do not have a good foundation in terms of clinical data [
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Due to widespread multidrug resistance in Bcc strains, new treatment options are needed [
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Novel antimicrobial strategies against the Bcc recently proposed have included the use of antisense technologies to modulate essential gene expression and the use of plant-derived essential oils [
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Essential oils (EOs) are complex hydrophobic liquids containing multiple volatile low molecular weight compounds (often terpenes or terpenoids) and obtained by distillation, mechanical expression or solvent extraction from plant matter. Essential oils and essential oil components (EOCs) have been previously shown to have potentially useful antimicrobial activities against gastrointestinal and other pathogens [
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Recently, 3 essential oils, from 
 <italic class="italic">Eugenia caryophyllata</italic> (clove, synonym: 
 <italic class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</italic>), 
 <italic class="italic">Origanum vulgare</italic> (oregano) and 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</italic> (thyme), were found to be strongly active against Bcc strains, including environmental and clinical strains and antibiotic resistant isolates [
 <xref rid="pone.0201835.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>].
</p>
