<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The results of the literature survey were analyzed by categorizing published studies on the 16 medicinal plant species. A new indicator was introduced: the Degrees of Publication (DoPs). DoPs were defined as “Traditional Use,” “Bioactivity,” “Structure Elucidation,” “Other,” and “Total (without &lt;other&gt;).” “Traditional use” are sources stating that a plant species 
 <italic>i</italic> is used traditionally in an ethnopharmacological context. The DoP “Bioactivity” describes the number of published studies investigating a potential pharmacological activity of an extract from a plant 
 <italic>i</italic>. “Structure elucidation” includes studies that resulted in isolation of (bioactive) secondary metabolites and their structure elucidation. These three DoPs are consecutive steps in the bioassay-guided discovery of novel bioactive natural products based on the ethnopharmacological approach of investigating traditional use reports. This classification, therefore, may lead to an assessment of the degree to which each plant species has been studied so far. The DoP “Other” classifies all publications mentioning a plant species 
 <italic>i</italic> in a non-ethnopharmacological context (e.g., studies on the morphology of the species, on the distribution of species, or on non-medicinal traditional use of a species). The DoP “Total (without &lt;other&gt;)” summarizes the three ethnopharmacologically relevant DoPs and is defined as the sum of “Traditional Use,” “Bioactivity,” and “Structure Elucidation.” For each DoP, absolute numbers were given as value 
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>all</italic>
 </sub> and 
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>COPE</italic>
 </sub>, whereas 
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>all</italic>
 </sub> describes all publications discovered in the literature survey, and 
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>COPE</italic>
 </sub> lists all publications in scientific journals whose publishing houses are members of the Committee on Publication Ethics (COPE, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.publicationethics.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.publicationethics.org</ext-link>). Members of the COPE must accept the international standards and best practice in the ethics of scholarly publishing, meaning that membership of the COPE is an appropriate indicator for high-quality research. A DoP “Total (without &lt;other&gt;)” of 
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>all</italic>
 </sub> ranging from 0 to 14 classifies a plant species as being “highly understudied,” while 15–29 is “understudied,” 30–44 is “moderately studied,” and 45-∞ is “highly studied.”
</p>
