<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Herpes virus belongs to the family of viruses that are most dangerous pathogens for humans and comprises of HSV-1 and HSV-2. HSV-1 can cause encephalitis and orofacial infections while HSV-2 infections cause injury and inflammation around genital area and is sexually transmitted. Lesions and infection in sensory neurons are inflicted in both of these cases, while the extent of pathogenicity is based on increased lesions and latency. The herpes simplex virus (HSV) is composed of about 84 different polypeptides and each single protein can encoded in numerous ways and perform various functions. The infection is initiated as soon as HSV attaches to surface of cell receptor and fuses with plasma membrane in order to release viral DNA inside the nucleus [
 <xref rid="B55-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The replication of HSV involves three rounds of transcription. HSV has the ability to cause infections including neuroinvasiveness, neurotoxicity and latency period during which it invades inside brain, destroys the neurons of brain, and then settles to a dormant state. Majority of HSV infections are mainly caused by HSV-2 during sexual transmission, as well as from mother to fetus transfer. The symptoms appear after a time period of 2–12 days. The different types of lesions in symptomatic oropharyngeal disease include intraoral lesion during primary infection, followed by recurrent orolabial lesions that may present with increased pain, itching and swelling of the lips. The other skin infections related to HSV-1 include eczema herpeticum and atopic dermatitis. The HSV-2 is responsible for genital herpes that generally is characterized by macules and papules subsequently turn to vesicles, ulcers and pustules. The lesions in vesicle genital area generally last for 8–10 days [
 <xref rid="B57-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Actually, there are no effective vaccines or prophylaxis providing a complete protection or immunity from virus, which is endemic worldwide. As regards pharmacological treatment of HSV-2, antivirals are currently used to control viral replication. The most commonly used drugs are Acyclovir, its analogue Valacyclovir and Famcyclovir (prodrug of Pencyclovir). Their mechanism of action, as nucleoside analogues, is to specifically inhibit the DNA polymerase of herpesvirus [
 <xref rid="B58-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. We can conclude that, to date, first-choice drugs used for the treatment of HSV-1 and HSV-2 are still represented by second generation of antivirals based on acyclic nucleosides such as aceaciclovir, valacyclovir, ganciclovir, penciclovir, and famciclovir.
</p>
