<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on the results obtained, a possible mechanism of action is derived as follows. It is well established that feeding with a high-fat diet develops insulin resistance,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>
 </sup> a model for the type-2-diabetic studies. However, recently, an alternate model wherein a high-fat diet fed for 2–3 months with a single dose (60 mg/kg body weight) of STZ would develop a suitable type-2 diabetic model.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>
 </sup> The high-fat diet alters lipid metabolism and develops insulin resistance. The intraperitoneal injection of STZ further alters the insulin level and glucose absorption, resulting in a suitable condition for type-2 diabetes. In this study, a significant increase in fasting blood glucose and a decrease in plasma insulin indicate the induction of insulin resistance after a high-fat diet + STZ injection. This further resulted in the development of the diabetic condition. As a secondary complication of diabetes, there was a significant damage/disruption in the liver and kidney function. Insulin plays a vital role in glucose absorption through glucose transporter (Glut). Glut 4 is an insulin-dependent glut transporters present in the muscle and adipose tissue. Because of insulin resistance and decreased plasma insulin levels, the glut transporters present in muscle cannot function normally, hence altering the function or physiology of the muscle. Altered physiology in muscle further resulted in oxidative stress as evident by increased concentration of ROS and NO with a significant decrease in the activities of SOD and CAT in the muscle. Further, the polyphenol-rich methanolic extract of the 
 <italic>C. auriculata</italic> root could manage the alterations due to high-fat diet + STZ-induced diabetes similar to that of metformin. This may be because of its rich −OH groups and an efficacy to increase the insulin sensitization as the plasma insulin levels were similar to the levels of control mice in extract-treated mice.
</p>
