<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Attempts to remediate hydrocarbon-contaminated soil are a priority in national development plans of many oil-producing countries in order to counteract the harmful effects of PHC [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. South Sudan is not exceptional. The techniques deployed in remediation of PHC polluted soil are fivefold: chemical, physical, electrical, thermal, and biological [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The use of chemical treatment involves chemical precipitation, membrane separation, ion exchange, carbon absorption, aqueous chemical oxidation, and surfactant enhanced recovery [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. With regard to physical treatment, the main treatment measures involve land filling, pumping and treating, dual phase extraction as well as air sparging, and dual phase extraction [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. For electrical remediation, electrical principles are applied to decontaminate particular sites though only limited to granular type of soil contaminated with heavy metals [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The thermal methods are largely used in environments where the contaminants are highly volatile and include 
 <italic>in situ</italic> vitrification, incineration, and electrical pyrolysis. However, the above-mentioned techniques are not largely used at present because they are associated with various shortcomings such as high cost, handling of the generated excess waste, and secondary contamination [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. This has given way to biological remediation techniques. It is not by surprise therefore that in recent times, in most crude oil producing countries, biological remediation techniques are dominating any efforts for ecorestoration of PHC contaminated soils [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], bioremediation inclusive [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].
</p>
