<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Age-related macular degeneration (AMD) is a disease that causes progressive loss of central vision as a consequence of the macular region degeneration (Muangnoi et al. 2019). The development of this disease is related to histopathological features, which include pigmentary disturbances, drusen, Bruch’s membrane thickening and basal laminar deposits. Drusen are lipid material deposits that accumulate underneath the retinal pigment epithelium (RPE) and can be observed as pale yellow spots on the retina (Evans and Lawerenson, 2017). The RPE is formed by specialized cells that constitute the outer blood-retinal barrier. This epithelium lies on the interface between the neural retina and the choriocapillaris. The presence of drusen causes pigment epithelium disturbances and represents a significant risk factor for AMD. AMD could be assorted according to its severity, but is most frequently classified into early and late stages (Muangoi et al., 2019; 
 <bold>
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>
 </bold>). The early stage, with slow progression, commonly causes mild vision distortion or is asymptomatic. Small- or medium-sized drusen are formed at the back of the eye, and no retinal pigmentary changes appear. Late-stage AMD includes the neovascular form that rapidly progress, and the atrophic form that more slowly develops. As its name suggests, the neovascular form implies the presence of the choroidal neovascularisation complex, which is associated with retinal lesions such as pigment epithelial detachments, presence of intraretinal and subretinal fluid, macular haemorrhage, hard exudates, or subretinal fibrous scars (Mitchell et al., 2018). It is also known as wet AMD. Athropic AMD, also termed dry AMD, is associated with outer retinal thinning that surrounds the central macula region. Advanced stages (geographic atrophy) are characterized by the degeneration of photoreceptors and their supporting tissues (RPE, Bruch’s membrane and choriocapillaris; Li et al., 2018). The RPE, which maintains retinal homeostasis, is particularly prone to oxidative stress, which contributes to AMD development (Li et al., 2019). Cells from this tissue possess great metabolic activity and, thus, high energy requirements, and therefore large numbers of mitochondria. Mitochondrial activity, mainly oxidative phosphorylation, leads to reactive oxygen species (ROS) generation. In addition, light exposure increases eyes’ vulnerability to oxidative stress. Superoxide dismutase, catalase or glutathione peroxidise, are antioxidant enzymes that neutralise these reactive species. An imbalance between ROS production and neutralization leads to oxidative stress, which affects macromolecules (proteins, lipids, DNA), and untimely tissue damage or cell apoptosis (Bungau et al., 2019). Furthermore as humans become older, there is an increasing risk of the oxidation of cellular constituents and, as a consequence, malfunctions and tissue degeneration. The RPE and retinal macula are tissues affected by oxidative stress (Datta et al., 2017). Other risk factors for AMD related to oxidative stress are alcohol consumption, cigarette smoking or dietary factors (Kim et al., 2017). Treatment of wet AMD focuses on antioxidants that prevent or diminish oxidative stress, and also anti-vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) compounds to reduce neovascularization by lowering VEGF release and/or expression (Alshamani et al., 2019). Beneficial effects of plant extracts are related to bioactive phytochemicals, such as carotenoids and polyphenols, and their synergistic combinations. Such phytochemicals are able to reduce oxidative stress, and modulate angiogenesis and inflammation, by protecting the RPE from damage (Peddada et al., 2019). Furthermore, the keen interest shown in them is also related to their good tolerability (few secondary effects) and efficacy. Nutritional dietary supplements of a botanical origin can affect several pathways at the same time by reducing inflammation, oxidative stress or neurodegeneration (Heitmar et al., 2019). They can also improve ocular blood flow and signal transduction, or reduce apoptosis in the RPE (Xu et al., 2017). Even anti-VEGF and antioxidant treatments have had positive results, but there is no cure to date for wet AMD and no treatment for dry AMD, being this disease the leading cause of blindness and visual impairment in the elderly population (older than 70 years of age) in industrialized countries (Hanus et al., 2015). Wong et al. (2014) have estimated that around 196 million of people in 2020, which will increase to 288 million people in 2040, will develop this disease worldwide. Nowadays 8.7% of the world’s adult population has AMD. Thus implementing eye care programs to prevent or treat AMD has become a global health priority.
</p>
