<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In fact, systems biology approaches and other advanced methods are gaining traction in the field of nanosafety research [
 <xref rid="B51-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], though regulatory acceptance is needed in order to implement such approaches in hazard assessment of NBMs for MDs and ATMPs. ECHA identified relevant toxicological endpoints of concern for nanomaterials (e.g., cytotoxicity, inflammation, oxidative stress, genotoxicity), and a list of related appropriate in vitro and in vivo tests (e.g., in vitro mammalian cell gene mutation test, bacterial reverse mutation test) [
 <xref rid="B52-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Furthermore, the adverse outcome pathway (AOP) framework provides pragmatic insights to promote the development of alternative testing strategies [
 <xref rid="B54-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Several EU-funded projects, not least in FP7 (e.g., SUN, MARINA, NANOMILE, NANoREG projects [
 <xref rid="B55-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]), have developed and evaluated different in vivo and in vitro protocols for investigating the hazard of nanomaterials, in principle applicable also to NBMs. These efforts have addressed the importance of assessing in vitro assays with respect to material interference [
 <xref rid="B56-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Furthermore, the importance of using multiple cell types to properly evaluate the toxicity of NMs has been demonstrated in the MARINA and NANOMILE projects, and high-throughput screening approaches have been developed [
 <xref rid="B57-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. It is important to point out that while there is a strong (scientific and societal) incentive to move towards an animal free testing and the development of alternative test methods is highly recommended, these assays nevertheless need to be validated. The current situation however is that there are only a very limited number of validated in vitro and in silico test methods that can be used in regulatory toxicology. The exception might be the availability of in vitro (and ex vivo) approaches to evaluate acute effect on the skin. 
</p>
