<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot3-insects-09-00020" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Protein Properties</div>
 <sec id="sec3dot3dot1-insects-09-00020" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.1. Protein Content and Yield of Extracted Fractions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Yield and protein recovery of the three fractions, plus the protein content of LM and extracted fractions are displayed in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="insects-09-00020-t003" href="#insects-09-00020-t003">Table 3</a>. The protein contents of the three fractions were not significantly different to each other (
   <span class="italic">p</span> &gt; 0.05, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.073). After processing, their combined average protein content (73.6%) was 23.8% higher than the LM, illustrating significantly higher (
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.000) protein content than whole locusts.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similar to the current findings, Zhao et al. [
   <a rid="B11-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-insects-09-00020">11</a>] and Purschke et al. [
   <a rid="B19-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-insects-09-00020">19</a>] found protein content to 82% for yellow mealworm and migratory locust. Alternatively, research investigating other insect species found slightly lower values ranging from 65–75% for insoluble, 58–69% for soluble, and 50–61% for supernatant fractions [
   <a rid="B12-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-insects-09-00020">12</a>,
   <a rid="B16-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-insects-09-00020">16</a>]. Chitin and chitin-bound protein that is consequently indigestible, are likely to contribute to the protein content found in ILF [
   <a rid="B10-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-insects-09-00020">10</a>]. Although not the focus of the current study, this can lead to lower digestibility compared to supernatant and pellet (soluble) fractions, as documented by Yi et al. [
   <a rid="B13-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-insects-09-00020">13</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The protein recovery of each fraction is expressed as a percentage compared to the initial protein content of the sample (DLM). The total protein yield (101.66%), ILF yield, and ILF protein recovery was similar to other literature investigating various insects [
   <a rid="B12-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-insects-09-00020">12</a>,
   <a rid="B16-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-insects-09-00020">16</a>]. However, the low SLF (9.83%) and high SF yield (56.60%) was unexpected. Purschke et al. [
   <a rid="B19-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-insects-09-00020">19</a>] identified a protein recovery of 51.7% of migratory locust protein concentrate after solubilisation at pH 9. Other insect studies documented soluble yields ranging from 22% to 46% [
   <a rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-insects-09-00020">15</a>,
   <a rid="B16-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-insects-09-00020">16</a>] and supernatant protein yields between 17% and 23% [
   <a rid="B12-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-insects-09-00020">12</a>]. Experimental conditions in the present study could have impacted findings. The soluble proteins may not have aggregated efficiently at pH 4, causing a large proportion to remain in the supernatant fraction, leading to a higher SF yield and protein percentage. pH 4 was used to precipitate the soluble locust protein following Bußler et al. [
   <a rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-insects-09-00020">15</a>] methodology on five different insects. Purschke et al. [
   <a rid="B18-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-insects-09-00020">18</a>] later identified pH 4 as the isoelectric point for enzymatic hydrolysed migratory locust protein. pH 10 was used to solubilise the proteins following the method by Tirgar et al. [
   <a rid="B28-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-insects-09-00020">28</a>] and pH used by Bußler et al. [
   <a rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-insects-09-00020">15</a>]. However, Purschke et al. [
   <a rid="B19-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-insects-09-00020">19</a>] identified the minimum solubility at pH 5 and maximum at pH 9. Therefore the pH used based on other insect species by Bußler et al. [
   <a rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-insects-09-00020">15</a>] may not have been the optimal pH. Furthermore, other experimental conditions such as NaOH concentration, pH, temperature, run time, and water to sample ratio are known to have an effect on protein yields, possibly affecting the results found in the present study [
   <a rid="B11-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-insects-09-00020">11</a>,
   <a rid="B12-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-insects-09-00020">12</a>,
   <a rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-insects-09-00020">15</a>,
   <a rid="B18-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-insects-09-00020">18</a>,
   <a rid="B19-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-insects-09-00020">19</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot3dot2-insects-09-00020" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.2. Colour</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The colour of the various fractions can impact the consumer perceptions and acceptance when it is used in products, so is important to consider before product development. The colour of each fraction and LM are shown in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="insects-09-00020-t004" href="#insects-09-00020-t004">Table 4</a>. Processing of the LM did affect the appearance of the three fractions for L*, a*, b* and ∆E values (
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.000). SF was the lightest sample, followed by ILF, SLF, and finally LM was the darkest.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To the authors knowledge no other literature has investigated 
   <span class="italic">L. migratoria</span> protein isolate colouration. Overall, the locust fractions were darker compared to 
   <span class="italic">A. domesticus</span> (house cricket) aqueous extracted fractions (L* 58.53–65.50) investigated by Ndiritu et al. [
   <a rid="B16-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-insects-09-00020">16</a>]. The same study also found no difference between fractions, unlike Bußler et al. [
   <a rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-insects-09-00020">15</a>] that identified lighter insoluble samples, similar to current findings.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The extracted fractions were slightly more yellow compared to the LM. The brown and yellow colour could be due to lipophilic melanoidins, which during defatting and consequent protein extractions may be removed, creating higher a* and L* values [
   <a rid="B37-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-insects-09-00020">37</a>]. This idea is consistent with other studies, that found a lighter defatted sample compared to whole and extracted fractions [
   <a rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-insects-09-00020">15</a>,
   <a rid="B16-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-insects-09-00020">16</a>,
   <a rid="B38-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-insects-09-00020">38</a>]. Colour change could also be attributed to enzymatic browning as a result of processing conditions such as extraction at certain pH values degrading proteins producing brown pigmentation [
   <a rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-insects-09-00020">15</a>,
   <a rid="B38-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-insects-09-00020">38</a>]. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, ILF also had much lower a* value (1.67) compared to all other samples, indicating greater green colouration. Consequently, ILF also had a higher overall colour change (∆E 23.44) compared to SLF and SF, and much higher than insoluble yellow mealworm colour change (∆E 9.1) identified by Bußler et al. [
   <a rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-insects-09-00020">15</a>]. The green colouration could be due to a common green pigment identified in insects called insectoverdin. It is a mixture of two chromoproteins, one yellow component from carotenoids and the other a bile component (blue) creating the green colour in locusts [
   <a rid="B39-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-insects-09-00020">39</a>]. However, pigmentation in insect changes depending on species, life stage, and habitat therefore differences in colour is expected [
   <a rid="B38-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-insects-09-00020">38</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot3dot3-insects-09-00020" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.3. Water and Oil Holding Capacity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The water (WHC) and oil holding capacity (OHC) is expressed as the amount of water or oil (mL) that can be held per gram of sample. As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="insects-09-00020-f002" href="#insects-09-00020-f002">Figure 2</a>, WHO and OHC values of LM, DLM and SLF were not significantly different to one another, as well as other insect species investigated [
   <a rid="B11-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-insects-09-00020">11</a>,
   <a rid="B16-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-insects-09-00020">16</a>]. Unexpectedly, the ILF had significantly higher (
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.000) WHC and OHC of 5.17 mL/g and 7.31 mL/g, respectively. A study conducted by Bußler et al. [
   <a rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-insects-09-00020">15</a>] found whole and defatted yellow mealworm samples had higher WHC compared to the insoluble and soluble fractions, contradictory to the present study.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ability to hold water against gravity is an important application in certain food areas. The water includes bound, hydrodynamic, capillary and physically entrapped water [
   <a rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-insects-09-00020">15</a>]. The ability to hold this water is dependent on many factors such as the amino acids, charges, conformation, and hydrophobicity of the protein, pH, temperature, ionic strength and protein concentration [
   <a rid="B11-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-insects-09-00020">11</a>]. The reason for the high WHC of the insoluble locust fraction is unknown. The porous structure or large particle size, due to absence of sieving during preparation, could have caused greater entrapment of water into the particle domains. Furthermore, larger particle size has been linked to higher contents of chitin, as found in 
   <span class="italic">T. molitor</span> grist [
   <a rid="B40-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-insects-09-00020">40</a>], which could additionally entrap the water into the ILF matrix, creating the high WHC result found. Ability of locust fractions to hold water illustrates protein-water interactions and can be used to interpret other functional properties such as solubility, emulsification, viscosity, gelation, and foaming [
   <a rid="B11-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-insects-09-00020">11</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The high ILF OHC result is also inconsistent with the literature. Contradicting the current results, Bußler et al. [
   <a rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-insects-09-00020">15</a>] found fat binding capacity (g/g) was significantly higher in the soluble and lower in insoluble fractions of yellow mealworms. The current findings could again be due to the larger particle size and porous structure, causing physical entrapment of oil [
   <a rid="B11-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-insects-09-00020">11</a>]. Additionally, higher OHC is linked to non-polar side chains in the protein structure, which was not investigated in the current study. Research on this is limited and further information on the water and oil holding capacity of protein extracts from 
   <span class="italic">L. migratoria</span> and insects in general is needed. Nevertheless, the WHC and OHC findings indicate the possible food applications of each fraction.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In another consumer study conducted by the researcher, it asked thirty-five participants to design an ideal hypothetical solid and liquid food product containing the ILF and SLF fractions. Participants who were open to trying new or novel foods were screened prior to investigation in order to gain insights from potential end consumers. The liquid product designs (containing soluble locust fraction) designed by participants included chocolate flavoured health drinks, protein powders, an ice cream, and a coconut yoghurt product. Solid food products (containing insoluble locust fraction) included protein packed breadcrumbs, muesli bars, cereals, bread, cookies and a nut substitute. The majority of these products were designed as a healthy, convenient, and eco-friendly snack or breakfast for active consumers or children. These results indicate the exciting future of whole or extracted locust protein as a value-added ingredient.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
