<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Stilbenes are a group of phenolic compounds that share a similar chemical structure to flavonoids, in which the two aromatic rings (A and B) are linked by a methylene bridge. One of the most aroma compounds stilbenes is present mostly in glycosylated forms is 
 <italic>trans</italic>-resveratrol (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="foods-10-00106-f010">Figure 10</xref>). Resveratrol is a phytoalexin that has been particularly studied as it shows several biological activities, reduces the formation of atherosclerotic plaque, present neuroprotective, antidiabetic, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, anticarcinogenic effects, and antiviral activity [
 <xref rid="B60-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. It was also shown in several studies that 
 <italic>trans</italic>-piceid a 3-β-glucosylated form of 
 <italic>trans</italic>-resveratrol could inhibit platelet aggregation [
 <xref rid="B62-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] and oxidation of human low-density lipoprotein (LDL). Peng et al. [
 <xref rid="B64-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] showed that 
 <italic>trans</italic>-piceid was the major form existing in most vegetables, and most of the samples contained higher 
 <italic>trans</italic>-piceid than 
 <italic>trans</italic>-resveratrol. The concentration of 
 <italic>trans</italic>-resveratrol in μg/100 g fresh weight lies between 1.14 and 0.70 in cauliflower and 1.78 and 23.12 in celery, as well as 8.8 and 19.74 in black soya bean. As for 
 <italic>trans</italic>-piceid, it is between 43.04 and 783.29 in celery, 0.80 and 9.22 in leaf lettuce, 1.10 and 12.0 in tomato, and 18.16 and 194.40 in red radish [
 <xref rid="B64-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. According to Sebastià et al. [
 <xref rid="B65-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], the concentration of 
 <italic>trans</italic>-resveratrol in tomatoes is 0.2 µg/g.
</p>
