<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>XRD is the most popular technique used to investigate the chemical compound as well as determine the crystal structure [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B107-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,
 <xref rid="B181-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>] and size of MNPs [
 <xref rid="B182-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>]. It is worth noting that, through XRD, shape features relating to different materials such as glasses, high conductors. and biomolecules could be explored [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Revealing of the MNPs’ characteristics by XRD goes through specific steps starting from casting a beam of X-rays on the crystals, then the fallen beam dispersed via the atoms, which leads to the emergence of diffraction patterns followed by the interference of beams with each other [
 <xref rid="B160-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>]. Bragg’s Law could be used to detect the interference to observe the crystal material’s characteristics [
 <xref rid="B183-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>]. Domain size of the crystal material can be calculated using the Scherrer formula [
 <xref rid="B184-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>]. Diffraction patterns are crucial since the analysis of crystal materials relies on them; these patterns imply the physical characteristics and chemical composition of the materials [
 <xref rid="B185-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>]. XRD confirmed that the nature of synthesized FeNPs mediated using 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> leaf extract is predominantly amorphous [
 <xref rid="B98-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Rahimi-Nasrabadi et al. [
 <xref rid="B87-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>] examined the purity level and the composition of AgNPs synthesized from 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> via XRD. Mo et al. [
 <xref rid="B93-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>] reported the crystalline structure of AgNPs derived from 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> using XRD. Meanwhile, Ali et al. [
 <xref rid="B81-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>] demonstrated the crystalline structure of NiNPs by XRD recorded patterns. Additionally, Wu et al. [
 <xref rid="B186-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>] confirmed the crystalline structure of FeNPs derived from the hybrid species of 
 <italic>E. urophylla</italic> and 
 <italic>E. grandis</italic>.
</p>
