<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0055">
 <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic>, 
 <italic>M. oleifera,</italic> L. (Moringaceae) is an herbal plant having enormous medicinal and nutritional uses. The plant was native to the sub-Himalayan tracts of India, Pakistan, Bangladesh, and Afghanistan. It is now widely distributed all over the world. Drumstick tree, horseradish tree and suhanjna are some common namesfor
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic>. All parts (bark, leaf, root, seeds, gum, pod, fruit and flowers) are immensely nutrimental but leaves are the greatest nourishing part with high content of vitamins, minerals, antioxidants, nitrile glycosides, proteins, and phenolics (
 <xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr">Younus et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Ashraf et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> contains a rare combination of important bioactive components like zeatin, quercetin, beta-sitosterol, caffeoylquinic acid, kaempferol etc. Various parts of this plant have been reported to act as antiviral, antibacterial, cardiac and circulatory stimulants, anti-diabetic, hypolipidemic, antiulcer, antipyretic, antispasmodic, anti-inflammatory, antihypertensive, diuretic, antioxidant, and antifungal activities (
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Nworu et al., 2013</xref>) Therefore, it has a great appeal as folk or Ayurvedic traditional medicine in different cultures of the world. Due to its divergent nutritional, pharmacological and industrial applications, the plant is recognized as a “miracle tree” or a “wonder tree”, which bears a significant socio-economic importance. In the Philippines, the plant is known as ‘mother's best friend’ because of its use to increase women's milk production and sometimes it is also prescribed for anemia (
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Estrella et al., 2000</xref>). Besides its diverge range of medicinal use, the massive antiviral activity is due to the presence of alkaloids, saponins, glycosides, niazimin, terpenoids, and phenolic compounds (
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) (
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Nworu et al., 2013</xref>). Previous reports showed that thiocarbamate and niaziminin isolated from 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> were highly efficient to inhibit the activation of tumor promoting virus, Epstein Barr virus (EBV) (
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Murakami et al., 1998</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Lipipun et al. (2003)</xref> suggested that the leaf of 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> may be considered as a prophylactic or therapeutic medicine for HSV-1 infection and may be effective against the virus of acyclovir-resistant variant (
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Lipipun et al., 2003</xref>). Accumulating evidence revealed that the fruit extract of 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> showed significant anti-hepatitis B virus (HBV) activity, whereas the seed of this plant showed potential antiviral activity against Newcastle Disease Virus (NDV) and Infectious Bursal Disease (IBD) virus (
 <xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">Waiyaput et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Chollom et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 2014</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr">Younus et al. (2015)</xref> reported that 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> exhibited potent antiviral activity against Foot and Mouth disease virus (FMDV), equine herpes virus, rhinovirus (positive sense ssRNA virus), and influenza virus H9 (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Ashraf et al., 2017</xref>). Interestingly, some studies suggested that 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> leaf can be used to support people living with HIV/AIDS (PLWHA) due to its nutritive and immune-boosting properties. In African traditional medicine, the plant is popularly used against AIDS and related secondary infections associated with HIV (
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Biswas et al., 2020</xref>). The proceedings of the 14
 <sup>th</sup>International AIDS Conference held in Barcelona, Spain in 2002 included a recommendation that the powder of 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> can be considered as an alternative treatment for HIV-positive patients in Africa to boost their immune systems, where patients are not taking antiretroviral drugs or any treatment at all (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Burger et al., 2002</xref>). Experimental evidence of 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> showed antiviral efficacy against various viruses, including RNA virus/enveloped virus, thus, it can also be a prominent source for searching therapeutic agents against coronavirus.
</p>
