<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This work is part of a bigger study aiming to identify compounds of interest in the wide flora available in the Comoros archipelago. In this specific case, an anti-tyrosinase activity is interesting when willing to treat issues such as melasma [
 <xref rid="B29-biomolecules-10-01347" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. This kind of skin condition implies the local application of compound is destined to regulate melanogenesis. Treatments used nowadays can be very dangerous as they often contain hydroquinone and steroids. Those compounds have shown adverse effects such as dermatitis, black and blue skin pigmentation, blindness, skin thinning, bruises and stretch marks. This means that there is room for effective treatment without any adverse effect especially when taken for a long period of time, as it is often requested for those types of diseases [
 <xref rid="B30-biomolecules-10-01347" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In addition, the antioxidant potency of the samples were tested, as it is also beneficial when working with topical treatments. Through a bio-guided purification followed by molecular characterization of extracts from the roots of 
 <italic>Litchi chinensis</italic> Sonn., the structure of cinnamtannin D2 responsible for the biological activity was obtained. It is the first time that this class of compounds was highlighted in 
 <italic>L. chinensis’</italic> roots. Lychee roots appear to be a promising source of raw material that could be used for the development of effective skin treatment. The fact that 
 <italic>L. chinensis</italic> roots are used in this study may raise questions in terms of the plant’s conservation. However, technologies exist to enhance the value of root plant compounds [
 <xref rid="B31-biomolecules-10-01347" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In the end, our study has allowed the purification and the characterization of a proanthocyanidin A-type in 
 <italic>L. chinensis</italic> roots for the first time. This study also revealed a consensus among the chemical structure, biological activities and the traditional uses of 
 <italic>Litchi</italic> roots in Mayotte to treat skin pigmentation issues and soften the skin.
</p>
