<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Globally, the search of information resulted in 25 species (∼16.6% of the genus), for which written evidence of traditional uses is available. Clearly, this list cannot be exhaustive as in many traditional medicine systems a vast knowledge on medicinal plants exists as oral information only. The majority of medicinal plants used over the world are harvested from wild resources in increasing volumes. Given their integral role in basic healthcare in many developing countries, their conservation and sustainable use are a necessity. The information of the IUCN (International Union for Conservation of Nature) Red List Categories, assessing the conservation status of species, was accessed for 
 <italic>Eriosema</italic> species from 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.iucnredlist.org/fr/search?query=EriosemasearchType=species" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.iucnredlist.org/fr/search?query=Eriosema&amp;searchType=species</ext-link>. At the moment, only 22 
 <italic>Eriosema</italic> species (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) are included in this list. Information for the vast majority of species widely used in traditional medicine such as 
 <italic>E. chinense</italic>, 
 <italic>E. cordatum</italic>, 
 <italic>E. glomeratum</italic> and 
 <italic>E. psoraleoides</italic> and others depicted in 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> is still missing. Only the three traditionally used species 
 <italic>Eriosema crinitum</italic> (Kunth) G. Don, 
 <italic>Eriosema englerianum</italic> Harms and 
 <italic>Eriosema montanum</italic> Baker f. are listed, characterized by a stable population with least concern. Nevertheless, the most popular species with traditional use should be assessed to avoid a negative impact on the size of the populations. Root and whole-plant harvesting is more destructive than collecting leaves and flowers or buds (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2016</xref>). Among the 25 species traditionally used and reported in this review, mainly roots are utilized (18 species), followed by leaves (11 species), bark and whole plant (3 species), seeds or fruits (2 species) and twigs (1 species) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Rather to use roots, leaves can be an alternative to avoid the destruction and high-speed disappearing of 
 <italic>Eriosema</italic> species. In case roots are unavoidable for the use, non-destructive harvest protocols such as partial-root harvest should be applied.
</p>
