<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The effects of LAB on the release of PC and modification of phenolic profiles in both cereals and pseudocereals have been reported. They depend mainly on the grains types, species of microorganisms, fermentation conditions, particularly time, temperature, and pH values (
 <xref rid="B159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">159</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B183" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">183</xref>–
 <xref rid="B185" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">185</xref>). Some studies have highlighted the capacity of lactic fermentation of pseudocereals to enhance the PC in bread (
 <xref rid="B159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">159</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B161" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">161</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B186" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">186</xref>), beverages (
 <xref rid="B173" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">173</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">187</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B188" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">188</xref>), tarhana soup (
 <xref rid="B189" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">189</xref>) and pasta (
 <xref rid="B190" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">190</xref>). The PC metabolism in LAB has two important physiological functions, it is an efficient mechanism to detoxify such compounds (
 <xref rid="B191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">191</xref>), and can have a role in the cellular energy balance because LAB employ hydroxycinnamic acids as external acceptors of electrons (
 <xref rid="B192" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">192</xref>). The metabolism of PC by LAB was described principally in 
 <italic class="italic">L. plantarum</italic> strains, and only few studies were reported in 
 <italic class="italic">Weissella</italic> spp., 
 <italic class="italic">Leuconostoc mesenteroides, L. paracollinoides, L. hilgardii</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Oenococcus oeni</italic> (
 <xref rid="B192" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">192</xref>–
 <xref rid="B194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">194</xref>). The enzymes involved in the PC metabolism by LAB such as decarboxylases (PAD), reductases (PAR), esterases and/or glycosidases were reported [
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>; (
 <xref rid="B176" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">176</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">179</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">196</xref>–
 <xref rid="B198" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">198</xref>)]. The production of vinyl-phenol, vinyl-guaiacol and vinyl catechol from the 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-coumaric, ferulic and caffeic acids, respectively, by PAD activities, are the most relevant (
 <xref rid="B176" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">176</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B177" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">177</xref>). Subsequently, these hydroxycinnamates by action of reductase are transformed to their corresponding phenylpropionic acids (
 <xref rid="B199" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">199</xref>).
</p>
