<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0037">
 <italic>Tithonia diversifolia</italic> (Hemsl) A. Gray, commonly known as tree marigold or Mexican sunflower (Asteraceae: Heliantheae), is a shrub-like perennial or annual invasive plant, native from North and Central America. Traditionally, its leaves are widely used by indigenous people for treating a wide spectrum of diseases, including diabetes mellitus. Several 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies have stated the antioxidant antidiabetic, hypolipidemic and antiobesity effects of 
 <italic>T. diversifolia</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Ajao and Moteetee, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0124" ref-type="bibr">Tagne et al., 2018</xref>). Germacranolides, eudesmanolides and guaianolides are some of the major components occurring in this plant (
 <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Ajao and Moteetee, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0124" ref-type="bibr">Tagne et al., 2018</xref>) and because of their previously described activity, they apparently are involved in the important spectrum of bioactivity reported for 
 <italic>T. diversifolia</italic>. Tirotundin (
 <bold>7</bold>) and tagitinin A (
 <bold>8</bold>) (
 <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) isolated from the ethyl acetate soluble fraction of 
 <italic>T. diversifolia</italic> are related to the activation of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptors (PPARs) (
 <xref rid="bib0079" ref-type="bibr">Lin, 2012</xref>). PPARs are members of nuclear hormone receptors superfamily involved in the metabolic regulation of lipid and lipoprotein levels, blood glucose, and abdominal adiposity. In mammals, three isoforms of PPARs have been recognized namely PPAR-α, PPAR-β/δ and PPAR-γ. Activation of PPAR-α by hypolipidemic fibrate class of drugs decreases TG levels and raises HDL-C in dyslipidemic individuals, whereas activation of PPAR-γ by antidiabetic thiazolidinedione agents causes insulin sensitization to enhance glucose metabolism (
 <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Botta et al., 2018</xref>). Currently, dual PPARα/γ agonists, which stimulate both PPARα and PPAR-γ isoforms to similar extents, are gaining popularity since it is believed that they are able to ameliorate the unwanted side effects of selective PPAR-α and PPAR-γ agonists; and may also be used to treat dyslipidemia and T2DM simultaneously (
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Balakumar et al., 2019</xref>). Tirotundin (
 <bold>7</bold>) and tagitinin A (
 <bold>8</bold>) have been suggested being dual PPARα/γ agonists after the evaluation of their agonistic activity against PPARs employing a transient transfection reporter assay in HepG2 cells (
 <xref rid="bib0079" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2012</xref>).
</p>
