<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Medicinal plants have been used as therapeutic agents since ancient times, and more than 10,000 plants are used for medicinal purposes [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-05733" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The medicinal value of plant depends on the active compounds found within them; however, natural active compounds often tend to be poorly absorbed, chemically unstable, and not particularly hydrophilic, and high doses and repeated administration may, therefore, be required to achieve therapeutic effects. A suitable delivery system is needed in order to improve the absorption of bioactive compounds from plant sources and thus to reduce the dose required and unwanted side effects. Nanoemulsions (NEs) can be effective carrier systems as therapeutic agents and have attracted attention in the food, cosmetic, and pharmaceutical industries. Recent studies have shown better solubility, permeability, and absorption of the active compound when formulated as an NE than as the free extract [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-05733" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-05733" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Nanoemulsions are submicron sizes emulsion ranging from 5 to 200 nm and are mostly developed using low- or high-energy methods comprising two immiscible phases with help of appropriate emulsifying agent [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-05733" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Moreover, thermodynamic and kinetics both stability properties of nanoemulsion considered it as a safer drug carrier than other drug delivery system. Nanoemulsion formulations may be of the oil-in-water (O/W) or water-in-oil (W/O) type, depending on whether the water is dispersed on oil or 
 <italic>vice versa</italic>. In O/W NE systems, oil and surfactant molecules are dispersed in an aqueous medium in which the surfactant acts to reduce the interfacial tension between the two immiscible liquids and make them fully miscible. The O/W NE type is more commonly used when preparing commercial products owing to its high kinetic stability (when formulated with nonionic surfactants and polymers), smaller droplet size, better lipophilic encapsulation components, ability to increase drug bioavailability of encapsulated active ingredients in an aqueous environment, and greater resistance to Ostwald ripening [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-05733" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-05733" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In this article, we focused on using ultrasonication to prepare an O/W NE combining a fungus extract, plant oil, nonionic surfactant (widely used in industry), and co-surfactant. An ultrasound method was adopted primarily because in this method, better encapsulation, higher yields, control of delivery, and smaller droplet size can be obtained using less energy than for any other conventional method [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-05733" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. An ultrasonic probe was used to produce a smaller NE compared with other ultrasonic baths. The O/W NE system we used consisted of a 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> extract (COR-Ex), 
 <italic>Hippophae rhamnoides</italic> (sea buckthorn) fruit oil, Tween 80 as surfactants, and chitosan from crab shells as a co-surfactant. 
 <italic>Cordyceps militaris</italic>, widely known as parasitic fungus in China, has been extensively used as a traditional medicine. The active components of 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> have been identified as cordycepin (3′-deoxyadenosine), D-mannitol (cordycepic acid), and polysaccharides, and these are thought to have potential antiaging, whitening, antitumor, anti-inflammatory, immunomodulatory, and/or blood glucose and cholesterol lowering activities [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-05733" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-05733" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. However, the active component cordycepin can degrade in vivo due to degradation by enzyme adenosine deaminase and also others environmental factors like sun light, UVB light, and high temperatures [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-05733" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Given the potential medicinal value, we chose 
 <italic>Cordyceps militaris</italic> fungus extract as the aqueous media in our O/W system. 
 <italic>Hippophae rhamnoides</italic> or sea buckthorn is a well-known medicinal plant in Asia, and the oil from its fruit contains ellagic acid, polyunsaturated fatty acids, tocopherols, carotenoids, sterols, amino acids, carbohydrates, and vitamin E. The potential health benefits of sea buckthorn fruit include whitening, antiaging, anticancer, antioxidant, cardiovascular, antidiabetic, anti-inflammation and anti-microbial activity [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-05733" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-05733" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-05733" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Therefore, the objective of this research was to combine the hydrophobic and hydrophilic part of the bioactive compound from 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> extracts using surfactant to increase potential efficacy for biomedical applications.
</p>
