<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our results suggest that the kind of biofilm modulation depends on EO chemical composition although the fractions were obtained from the same plant. Remarkably, an important influence on the modulation of biofilm production is related to the harvesting period. Furthermore, in some cases, the same EOs seem to exert opposite influences (stimulation or inhibition of biofilm growth) depending on sample dilution. This is clearly related to the concentration of specific chemical compound as highlighted by the classification models. Since the action is not related to a bacteriostatic/bactericidal activity on 
 <italic class="italic">P. aeruginosa</italic>, the biofilm change of growth in presence of the EOs is possibly due to a modulation of the phenotype that switches from biofilm to planktonic. The latter could be explained with the presence in EOs of small molecules presumably acting as quorum sensing inhibitors [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-23-00482" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. In any case, moderation on conclusion has to be undertaken since interactive and synergistic effects among the EO chemical comnponents—including minor ones—can affect biological potency. Application of a in house python based machine learning protocol led to definition of a classification model able to discriminate essential oils in active and inactive at a cut-off value of 50% of biofilm formation using a concentration of 48.8 µg/mL. Investigation of the most important components by means of feature importance and partial dependence plots seems to indicate estragole and phellandral as the chemical components mostly related to biofilm inhibition, while 
 <sc class="sc">d</sc>-limonene, pulegone, and chrysanthenone seem to be related to biofilm production. The classification model as validated by five performance metrics are an example showing machine learning as tool to investigate complex chemical mixtures and possibly in prospective experiments it could enable scientists to understand the mechanism by which EOs act.
</p>
