<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">The primers employed in the amplification reactions ITS2F-5′AATTGCAGAATCCCGTGAAC3′ and ITS2R-5′GGTAATCCCGCCTGACCT3′ were designed based on ITS2 sequences of some Verbenaceae species from the GenBank database at the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI), namely 
 <italic class="italic">Aloysia gratissima</italic> (DQ463782.1), 
 <italic class="italic">A. gratissima var. schulziae</italic> (AY178651.1), 
 <italic class="italic">A. triphylla</italic> (EU761080.1), 
 <italic class="italic">Lippia alba</italic> (EU761076.1), 
 <italic class="italic">L. alba</italic> (EU761078.1), 
 <italic class="italic">L. salsa</italic> (FJ867399.1), and 
 <italic class="italic">Phyla dulcis</italic> (EU761079.1). Polymerase chain reaction was performed as described by Chen et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>] and the resulting amplified fragments were sequenced using a Thermo Sequenase™ Cycle Sequencing kit (Affymetrix, Inc, Cleveland, USA), following manufacturer recommendations, with e-Seq™ DNA Sequencing version 3.1 (LI-COR Biosciences). Consensus sequences were assembled with the aid of LI-COR Biosciences AlignIR software (version 2.1) and aligned with ClustalW. The sequence alignments were edited using the BioEdit software (version 7.2) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>]. Phylogenetic trees were inferred by the NJ method based on the Kimura-2 parameter using PHYLIP software version 3.69 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>]. The alignment quality of the final phylogenetic tree was verified by the presence of saturation of the nucleotide substitutions, and sequences exhibiting high genetic similarity were excluded from the phylogenetic analysis using DAMBE software version 4.0.36 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>]. Thirty-three sequences of the ITS2 region deposited in the NCBI GenBank were selected as references (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>). 
</p>
