<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">
 <italic>Salvia</italic> species used in this study included 
 <italic>Salvia nemorosa</italic> L., and 
 <italic>Salvia reuterana</italic> Boiss. Commercial seedlings (15–20 cm height), purchased from a commercial nursery (Pakan Seed Institute of Isfahan, Iran), were transplanted (two per pot) into plastic pots (11 cm diameter and 8.5 cm height). The experiment was carried under controlled environment conditions in the experimental greenhouse at Isfahan University of Technology (Iran) during 2018. Environmental parameters were 20°–15 °C day-night temperature, 60% relative humidity and 16 h photoperiod with a constant average Photosynthetic Active Radiation (PAR) of 300 µmol m
 <sup>−2</sup> s
 <sup>−1</sup> as previously suggested by Caser 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. The study was conducted in a greenhouse with uniform environmental conditions; therefore, the experiment was arranged as a completely randomized design (RCD) with two factors (irrigation and foliar applied melatonin). Each treatment contained nine plant samples of three biological replicates. Each replicate consisted of a pot (three plants/pot). For each measurement, three samples were randomly separated from different parts of the plant. The experimental factors were irrigation treatments at 3 levels; irrigation to 80% field capacity (control), 60% field capacity (mild stress) and 40% field capacity (severe stress) according to the method reported by Sedaghat 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>. The irrigation treatments were associated with foliar applied melatonin at five levels (0, 50, 100, 150 and 200 μM). Melatonin concentrations were selected based on the experiments reported by Zhang 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>, in two 
 <italic>Salvia</italic> species (
 <italic>Salvia nemorosa</italic> L., and 
 <italic>Salvia reuterana</italic> Boiss). The melatonin (Sigma–Aldrich) solutions were prepared according to Li 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup> by dissolving the solute in ethanol followed by dilution with phosphate buffered saline (PBS) to concentrations of 0, 50, 100, 150 and 200 μM. To improve uniformity of the spray application, for every 100 ml of solution two drops of surfactant (Twin 20) was added to the solution. Melatonin solutions were applied using a manual pump (30 ml per plant), two times per week for 45 days. The control treatment was sprayed with distilled water. The experiment was started after 15 days from the transplanting of the seedlings, after acclimation of the plants to the media and the greenhouse conditions. 
 <italic>Salvia</italic> plants were grown in sandy loam soil according to Pourmeidani 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. To determine the amount of water needed for each irrigation regime, at the beginning of the experiment the soil field capacity (FC) was determined for each pot using the weighing method
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. The collected data was used to determine the different amount of water to apply as percentage of the field capacity (FC). Four kg of soil was placed in the oven at 103 °C for 48 hours to determine soil dry weight. Afterwards, the pots were filled with the oven-dried soil and irrigated until water saturation. After 24 hours the pots were weighed every two hours. To avoid evaporation, the pot was covered with a plastic cover. The percentage of water in soil under FC condition was determined by the following equation:
 <disp-formula id="Equa">
  <alternatives>
   <tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$percentage\cdot of\cdot water\cdot in\cdot the\cdot soil=(Soil\cdot fresh\cdot weight-Soil\cdot dry\cdot weight/Soil\cdot dry\cdot weight)\times 100$$\end{document}</tex-math>
   <math id="M2" display="block">
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mi>c</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>g</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mo>⋅</mo>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mo>⋅</mo>
    <mi>w</mi>
    <mi>a</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <mo>⋅</mo>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>n</mi>
    <mo>⋅</mo>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mi>h</mi>
    <mi>e</mi>
    <mo>⋅</mo>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>i</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mrow>
     <mo stretchy="true">(</mo>
     <mrow>
      <mi>S</mi>
      <mi>o</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
      <mi>l</mi>
      <mo>⋅</mo>
      <mi>f</mi>
      <mi>r</mi>
      <mi>e</mi>
      <mi>s</mi>
      <mi>h</mi>
      <mo>⋅</mo>
      <mi>w</mi>
      <mi>e</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
      <mi>g</mi>
      <mi>h</mi>
      <mi>t</mi>
      <mo>−</mo>
      <mi>S</mi>
      <mi>o</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
      <mi>l</mi>
      <mo>⋅</mo>
      <mi>d</mi>
      <mi>r</mi>
      <mi>y</mi>
      <mo>⋅</mo>
      <mi>w</mi>
      <mi>e</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
      <mi>g</mi>
      <mi>h</mi>
      <mi>t</mi>
      <mo>/</mo>
      <mi>S</mi>
      <mi>o</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
      <mi>l</mi>
      <mo>⋅</mo>
      <mi>d</mi>
      <mi>r</mi>
      <mi>y</mi>
      <mo>⋅</mo>
      <mi>w</mi>
      <mi>e</mi>
      <mi>i</mi>
      <mi>g</mi>
      <mi>h</mi>
      <mi>t</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mo stretchy="true">)</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mo>×</mo>
    <mn>100</mn>
   </math>
   <graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_63986_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
