<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec0025" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Behavioral assay</div>
 <p id="par0055" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For behavioral assays, sexually immature creek chub were transferred to a room with low levels of light—windows and white floors were covered with black cloth to minimize transmission and reflection of light, respectively. Fish were matched for age by size and 3 fish were placed in an aerated glass aquarium. Their activity was digitally recorded with a Sony HDR-CX210 camcorder (
  <a rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0010">Fig. 2</a>).
  <div id="fig0010" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Experimental set-up and behavioral assays. Behavioral trials took place under low light conditions—dark cloths were used to minimize the transmission and reflection of light (2A). Behavioral experiments took place in aerated tanks; 3 fish were tested per trial (2B).</p>
   </div>
   <span id="at0125" class="alt-text">Fig. 2</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="par0060" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fish were recorded in the untreated environment for 3 min, in the presence of a control solution (distilled water) for 3 min, and finally, in the presence of 1.5 mL media, which was taken from epithelial cells after 24 h of culture (
  <a rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0010">Fig. 2</a>). Seconds of darting behavior by each fish under each condition was calculated from the digital record. In our model, darting was the most robust antipredatory behavior observed. Different species may exhibit other behaviors more prominently. Therefore, quantify the most consistently expressed antipredatory behavior. Darting behavior for each fish was measured; nine trials were completed. Data were analyzed using a 
  <span class="italic">t</span>-test in GraphPad Prism. p values of ≤0.05 were considered statistically significant.
 </p>
 <p id="par0065" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Darting behavior in fish was significantly increased following addition of cell culture media as compared to darting behavior after addition of distilled water (
  <a rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0015">Fig. 3</a>). Responses were acute, beginning immediately after addition of the media to the tank and lasting approximately 40 s.
  <div id="fig0015" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Primary cell culture media induces darting behavior in Creek Chub. Juvenile Creek Chub were observed in the absence of treatment, in the presence of a control solution (distilled water), and in the presence of 1.5 mL media from cultured epithelial cells (after 24 h). Observation time was 180 s. Seconds of darting behavior was averaged for 9 trials; means were compared using a 
     <span class="italic">t</span>-test. *, significantly different from control, p &lt; 0.05.
    </p>
   </div>
   <span id="at0130" class="alt-text">Fig. 3</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
