<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another less well known subgroup of the aromatic polyketides that are attracting considerable research interest are the diarylheptanoids. They are formed by the condensation of coumaroyl-CoA and a single malonyl-CoA unit, with an additional cinnamoyl group added in the last step, hence the name diarylheptanoids. Curcumin (
 <bold>43</bold>), 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-03846-f011">Figure 11</xref>, is the best studied member of this subgroup. It is found in the rhizomes of the turmeric plant, 
 <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> (Zingiberaceae), where it is responsible for the typical yellow colour. It is used in the food industry as a colourant and assumed shelf life prolonger (under code E100). There is extensive evidence that curcumin has anti-inflammatory, anti-ulcer, anti-Alzheimer’s, anticancer, anti-arthritic and preventive properties against cancer, though none of its medicinal activities have been confirmed in clinical trials [
 <xref rid="B123-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>,
 <xref rid="B124-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>,
 <xref rid="B125-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. Its activity in vivo is limited by its instability, poor water solubility and low bioavailability, with nearly all the ingested amounts being rapidly excreted. Few authors discuss its non-selective pan-assay interference (PAIN) character, interacting with almost every pharmacological target and thus showing false positive results in many drug discovery assays [
 <xref rid="B126-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>,
 <xref rid="B127-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. Turmeric rhizomes contain other constituents besides curcumin that might be responsible for some of the therapeutic benefits of the plant in Ayurveda. Based on the evidence so far, it is very improbable that curcumin will provide an important lead for drug development. A few side effects such as nausea, diarrhoea and skin rash were observed [
 <xref rid="B128-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. Quite recently, curcumin is also available in the form of micronized powder. This formulation is considered to have increased bioavailability and therefore a higher rate of side effects can probably be expected [
 <xref rid="B129-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. Additionally, there have also been reports of deaths upon the intravenous application of curcumin as a part of naturopathic practice [
 <xref rid="B130-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>].
</p>
