<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some diarylheptanoids are alternatively formed via the incorporation of fatty acyl thioester (rather than another coumaroyl-CoA group) to the terminal chain of the cinnamoyl-CoA. Resulting compounds include gingerols and shogaols found in the rhizomes of ginger (
 <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic>; Zingiberaceae) that are responsible for its pungency. The chain lengths in the fatty acyl group may differ, giving rise to variants analogous to the parent compounds—e.g., 6-, 8-, or 10-gingerol and 6-, 8-, 10-shogaol (utilizing six-, eight-, or ten-carbon fatty acid fragments, respectively; 
 <bold>44</bold>–
 <bold>49</bold>), 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-03846-f012">Figure 12</xref>. Ginger has been utilized for centuries as a culinary and medicinal plant, being traditionally used in the treatment of a wide range of human diseases, including colds, pulmonary disorders, rheumatic pain, headache, gastrointestinal problems, and motion sickness (kinetosis). Its medicinal properties have been, to some degree, confirmed in clinical trials such as in the case of migraine. Again, various studies assume that gingerols and shogaols are responsible for much of the therapeutic activity of ginger, though the clinical trials used ginger extracts, not the pure compounds. Gingerol-standardized extract of ginger demonstrated anti-inflammatory activity in an animal model of rheumatoid arthritis, though non-standardized extract showed efficacy as well [
 <xref rid="B131-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]. Shogaol was shown to inhibit one of the serotonin receptors, 5-HT
 <sub>3</sub>, which appears to be associated with the anti-nausea (anti-kinetosis) activity of ginger [
 <xref rid="B132-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. Recently, 6-gingerol and 6-shogaol showed pain-relieving activity via the inhibition of voltage-activated Na
 <sup>+</sup> currents in an in vivo model [
 <xref rid="B133-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>]. Ginger also contains other constituents, including terpenoids, such as the sesquiterpene zerumbone, that have also displayed significant anti-inflammatory and agonistic activity toward 5-HT
 <sub>1A/B</sub>) [
 <xref rid="B132-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>,
 <xref rid="B134-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. This suggests that gingerols and shogaols are not the only active principles of ginger rhizome.
</p>
