<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pain is one of the most pervasive problems and results due to multiple nociceptive and inflammatory mediators activation such as prostaglandin, bradykinin, histamine, tumour necrosis factor-α, IL-1β, IL-8, which ultimately helps to form edema, inflammation and invasion of leukocytes [
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Various available marketed anti-inflammatory and anti-nociceptive drugs include non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, opioids and glucocorticoids are widely used for their significant action at peripheral sites, but these drugs show adverse effect and inefficient sometimes; therefore, investigation of new drugs is needed to overcome those limitations. AFMV extract in the current was investigated against the central and peripheral acting analgesia model by acetic acid-inclined writhing test and formalin-inclined paw licking assay, respectively. Although the acetic acid-induced test showed good sensitivity, sometimes this test showed poor specificity. Research has been suggested that the intraperitoneal administration of acetic acid injection into the peritoneal cavity leads to an elevated level of COX-2 and lipoxygenase. In the present study, AFMV extract significantly decreased acetic acid-induced writhing in a dose–response manner, and these results were found parallel with the reference drug. Therefore, present outcomes in acetic acid-induced mice model suggested that the anti-inflammatory activity of AFMV might be linked partly with the reluctance of COX-2, lipoxygenase and other inflammatory mediators in peripheral tissue hence hindering with the signal transduction pathways in main afferent nociceptors. The formalin-induced paw licking test was also employed in the present study to confirm the action of AFMV against central and peripheral anti-nociceptive pain. This is a biphasic model characterised by two distinct phases, neurogenic pain (0–5 min) and inflammatory pain (15–30 min), respectively [
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. After administration of formalin, early phase indicates acute response caused by the direct effect of formalin on the sensory C-fibers, while the late phase reveals delayed response by the release of inflammatory mediators [
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In this present study, oral administration of AFMV significantly (
 <italic>P&lt;0.001</italic>) suppressed pain sensation in both phases as confirmed by reduced licking behaviour, but the impact in the late phase was more prominent. Phytochemicals in AFMV such as alkaloids and flavonoids might be responsible for its inhibitory activity against pain in the experimental model.
</p>
