<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although decoctions of fruits, leaves and stems are used for medicinal preparations, the root decoction is by far the most utilized part of the plant [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Over the past few decades, the benefits of 
 <italic>T. sericea</italic> have transcended African borders and the stem bark has also been sold to the European market [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Extracts of the plant, standardised with reference to sericoside (a major constituent), or pure sericoside, are sold for their anti-inflammatory activities, with claimed anti-wrinkle or anti-aging effects [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In Africa, 
 <italic>T. sericea</italic> root decoctions are administered for the treatment of a range of conditions, such as stomach ailments, diabetes, asthma, and constipation, but the main applications are associated with bacterial infections, including diarrhoea, sexually transmitted diseases, coughs, fever and wound infections [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The antibacterial activities of the crude polar organic and aqueous extracts against both Gram-positive and Gram-negative pathogens have been investigated extensively [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Some studies [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-03683" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] proposed that anolignan b, termilignan b and arjunic acid are the main constituents responsible for the antibacterial activity of the root extract, since they were highly active against several bacterial pathogens (
 <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic>, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>), with minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) in the range of 1.9–31 µg/mL. However, these studies considered samples from a single population, thus not accounting for possible chemotypic variation that could lead to correlated variation in the biological activity. 
</p>
