<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">In this study, we modeled the dynamics and interactions of populations of three maize stemborer species and the fall armyworm, as well as their associated parasitoids, in either single or multi-species systems. The population dynamics of single pest species systems presented S-shaped growth with overshoot logistic form of the well-known Lotka–Volterra prey predator system
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. The S-shaped form could be due to the negative feedback in the loop diagram that slowly limits the growth as the growth rate reaches the limit. However, the negative feedback contains time delays due to the variability of available resources (host plants) leading to intra-specific competitive interaction that affected the abundance of the pest. The time delay in the negative feedback causes the system to exceed the limit value and exhibit oscillation behavior around the limit value as previously reported by Sterman
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, the presence of parasitoids influences the host population dynamics leading to a cyclical relationship between a host (pest) and its associated parasitoids as previously demonstrated by the Lotka-Volterra predator–prey model function
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. For each of the three stemborer species systems, the associated parasitoids populations grew faster than their respective host populations. Din and Donchev
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup> reported that in a host-parasite interaction, if a host population is a pest, then according to the Leslie–Gower model, a fast-growing parasite population with a growth rate larger than that of the host significantly reduces the host population. Therefore, the present model indicates a significant effect of parasitoid on stemborers population regulation. Despite high outbreaks reported for 
 <italic>S. frugiperda</italic>, its population dynamics in our single-species system was actually the lowest which might be due to its high cannibalism rate reported in the literature
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup> and also because the high outbreaks across SSA was reported during the first months of infestation when equilibrium was not yet established; whereas stemborers have been present for decades.
</p>
