<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">Overall, the outputs of the simulations indicated that 
 <italic>C. partellus</italic> and 
 <italic>S. frugiperda</italic> species were competitively superiors over 
 <italic>B. fusca</italic> and 
 <italic>S. calamistis</italic>. However, in three or four multi-species involving 
 <italic>C. partellus</italic> with 
 <italic>S. calamistis</italic> and 
 <italic>S. frugiperda</italic>, 
 <italic>S. calamistis</italic> took the advantage and dominated 
 <italic>S. frugiperda</italic>. 
 <italic>Chilo partellus</italic> and 
 <italic>S. frugiperda</italic> are exotic species in Africa while 
 <italic>B. fusca</italic> and 
 <italic>S. calamistis</italic> are indigenous. Invasive insect pest species have the potential to rapidly establish and spread to new areas
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. The organisms that arrive and establish themselves in a new range of hosts are positioned to have adverse effects on the surrounding fauna and also results in the extinction of other species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. They often affect native species populations and systems by competing for the same resource
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. For example, the Asian adelgid, 
 <italic>Pineus boemeri</italic> Annand, has been shown to be competitively superior and to displace a native congener, 
 <italic>P. coloradensis</italic> (Gilette) in red pine (
 <italic>Pinus resinosa</italic> Aiton) plantation in Eastern USA, possibly through the reduction of host plant quality and forcing 
 <italic>P. coloradensisto</italic> to less suitable sites
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. The invasive fruit fly 
 <italic>Bactrocera invadens</italic> Drew, Tsuruta &amp; White (Diptera: Tephritidae), has displaced the indigenous mango fruit fly, 
 <italic>Ceratitis cosyra</italic> Walker (Diptera: Tephritidae) 4 years after invasion in Kenya and become the dominant fruit fly pest of mango
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>. Temperature and resource pre-emption were demonstrated to be key factors contributing to the competitive success of the invasive fruit fly 
 <italic>B. invadens</italic> over the indigenous mango fruit fly, 
 <italic>C. cosyra</italic> in Kenya
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>. Fabre et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup> demonstrated a form of resource competition between native and exotic seed chalcids, 
 <italic>Megastigmus</italic> spp. and displacement of the native species. Similarly, the African stemborer 
 <italic>B. fusca</italic> seems to have been displaced from sorghum fields by the Asian invasive stemborer 
 <italic>C. partellus</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup> possibly due to deterrence of the native species by the invasions or due to differences in host plant phenology.
</p>
