<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <p id="Par1" class="p">The chicken gut is constantly exposed to harmful molecules and microorganisms which endanger the integrity of the intestinal wall. Strengthening intestinal mucosal integrity is a key target for feed additives that aim to promote intestinal health in broilers. Recently, dietary inclusion of resin-based products has been shown to increase broiler performance. However, the mode of action is still largely unexplored. Coniferous resin acids are known for their anti-microbial, anti-inflammatory and wound-healing properties, all properties that might support broiler intestinal health. In the current study, the effect of pure resin acids on broiler intestinal health was explored. Ross 308 broilers were fed a diet supplemented with coniferous resin acids for 22 days, after which the effect on both the intestinal microbiota as well as on the intestinal tissue morphology and activity of host collagenases was assessed. Dietary inclusion of resin acids did not alter the morphology of the healthy intestine and only minor effects on the intestinal microbiota were observed. However, resin acids-supplementation reduced both duodenal inflammatory T cell infiltration and small intestinal matrix metalloproteinase (MMP) activity towards collagen type I and type IV. Reduced breakdown of collagen type I and IV might indicate a protective effect of resin acids on intestinal barrier integrity by preservation of the basal membrane and the extracellular matrix. Further studies are needed to explore the protective effects of resin acids on broiler intestinal health under sub-optimal conditions and to elaborate our knowledge on the mechanisms behind the observed effects.</p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Electronic supplementary material</title>
  <p class="p">The online version of this article (10.1186/s13567-019-0633-3) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
