<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>P. harmala</italic> is a species known by the presence of specific harmala alkaloids, which are at least 5.9% of the dry weight [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-09-01086" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In the current study, the extracts of 
 <italic>P. harmala</italic> contained four phenolic acids, with hydrocaffeic and protocatechuic acids as the major compounds. In addition, high amount of one flavonoid (cynaroside) were detected (
 <xref rid="plants-09-01086-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Sodaeizadeh et al. [
 <xref rid="B38-plants-09-01086" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] studied the Iranian 
 <italic>P. harmala</italic> using HPLC and determined seven phenolic acids in leaves and four phenolic acids in roots. 4-Hydroxybenzoic acid was the dominant compound some plant parts (leaves and roots), whereas caffeic acid was the highest in other parts such as the stems. In the current study, we investigated Arabian origin leaf extracts and characterized different phenolic acid components (only caffeic acid was a common compound between the two studies). We, additionally, confirmed hydrocaffeic, rosmarinic and protocatechuic acids. From flavonoids, Sharaf et al. [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-09-01086" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] studied the leaf extracts of the Egyptian 
 <italic>P. harmala</italic> and confirmed other compounds including peganetin, acacetin 7-0-rhamnoside, 7-0-[6”-O-glucosyl-2”-O-(3”‘-acetylrhamnosyl)glucoside, 7-O-(2”‘-0-rhamnosyl-2”-O-glucosylglucoside) and glycoflavone 2”‘-O-rhamnosyl-2”-O-glucosylcytisoside using TLC, and NMR methods. In the current study, and from our collection of widely distributed flavonoids, we tentatively determined only cynaroside (luteolin 7-glucoside). Previous investigation showed that environmental factors may influence the chemical composition of this species [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-09-01086" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. They reported elevated composition of vasicine, choline and sucrose in May as well as increases in betaine, lysine, 4-hydroxyisoleucine and proline in August. Furthermore, increases in phosphorylcholine, glucose, acetic acid and vasicinone were reported in December.
</p>
