<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0290">The present-day proximate analysis of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. supports the use of the plant as an important ingredient in food since the Egyptian era. Alongside biomolecules, the rich diversity of phytochemicals present in the 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. plant may be accountable for major health benefits. The ethnomedicinal uses of the plant have revealed the importance in treating various diseases. Several studies conducted 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> using cell lines and animal models with induced pathological conditions have proved the efficiency of the plant as a therapeutic agent. 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. is found to be effective against both infectious and foodborne pathogens. Both the oil and extract of the plant were evaluated for their effects on inflammation and cancer. Along with the proven pharmacological aspects, there are several activities that are yet to be reported. For example, the literature survey could find only 2 studies with significant results on anti-diabetic potential of the plant. Furthermore, inhibition of acetylcholine esterase could be assessed for more physiological aspects, especially with diabetes. The extensive inhibitory effect on foodborne and oral pathogens has proved its possible use as a preservative agent and an important drug for dental caries, respectively. Meanwhile, 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. also possesses anti-helminthic property, which can make it a prominent therapeutic agent against parasitic infections. Also, a great amount of work needs to be done with respect to its skin protection activity. The promising evidence on the cell proliferation post-exposure to UV rays suggests its clinical trials for establishing a potent product. Pre-clinical studies at a large scale including 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> cytotoxicity assays are suggested for the evaluation of accurate dosage levels of different plant fractions. Pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of the compounds need to be focused. In addition, interactions with dietary molecules and drugs need to be assessed for the development of nutraceuticals. The pharmacological analysis at the genetic and proteomic level, along with commercially available drugs would determine the beneficial and harmful effects of the plant extracts or individual compounds. In total, 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L
 <italic>.</italic> can open the doors to the development of many prominent therapeutic agents with diverse nature of applications to resolve several health maladies.
</p>
