<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Flavonoids and stilbenes are derived from a 
 <italic>p</italic>-coumaroyl-CoA starter unit that is extended by the addition of three units of malonyl-CoA. A group of plant enzymes that belongs to the family of type III polyketide synthases (PKS) controls the extension reaction, as well as further modification steps such as cyclisation, enolization, and decarboxylation. The initially formed polyketide may be subsequently folded in two different ways, giving rise to either stilbene (through aldol and ester hydrolysis by stilbene synthase) or naringenin chalcone (via a Claisen-like reaction catalysed by chalcone synthase in the formation of 
 <italic>p</italic>-coumaroylcyclohexantrione). Naringenin-chalcone can then undergo enolization and a Michael-type nucleophilic attack of OH-group onto the α,β-unsaturated ketone (through chalcone isomerase), forming a general 15-carbon flavonoid structure consisting of two phenyl rings (A and B) and a six-membered heterocyclic ring (C) [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Alternatively, the action of chalcone reductase in the early steps of the flavonoid biosynthetic pathway may generate isoliquiritigenin (chalcone), subsequently leading to liquiritigenin (
 <bold>1</bold>), 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-03846-f002">Figure 2</xref>, precursor of many isoflavonoids. It is worth noting, though, that the majority of flavonoid structures are derived from naringenin chalcone. The primary forms of flavanone structures (e.g., naringenin) may give rise to a wide range of variants on this basic skeleton, including flavons, flavonols, dihydroflavonols, catechines, and anthocyanidins [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Each of the named subgroups can undergo a different degree of hydroxylation of the aromatic rings and these groups can be further modified by methylation, prenylation, glycosylation, or dimethylallylation [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Some flavonoid structures (such as liquiritigenin) may lose one of the hydroxyl groups. A large range of flavonoid-derived compounds exists with more than 8,000 stillbenoid and flavonoid structures described thus far [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Stilbenes and flavonoids are found mainly in vascular plants, primarily in angiosperms. However, some flavonoid structures have been isolated from algae, molluscs, fungi, corals, and bacteria [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Animals lack the enzymatic apparatus required for their biosynthesis and obtain these compounds through diet. Stilbene synthase has a much more restricted distribution in the plant kingdom compared to chalcone synthase. This is supported by the fact that nearly every higher plant contains flavonoids, but stilbenes are found in only a few genera. Some flavonoids, however, may undergo specialized conversions and these might also have a rather unique distribution in higher plants (and other organisms) [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].
</p>
