<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In another example presented by Lin et al., the authors prepared anti-oil-fouling superoleophobic (SHI)–superhydrophilic (SOP) cotton fabrics utilizing F-SiNPs [
 <xref rid="B47-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. The coatings were prepared by dip-coating the cotton fabric in two different solutions; the first containing bare SiNPs with a diameter of 200 nm, and the second containing a reactive fluorinated phosphate oligomer and 1
 <italic class="italic">H</italic>,1
 <italic class="italic">H</italic>,2
 <italic class="italic">H</italic>,2
 <italic class="italic">H</italic>-perfluorodecyltriethoxysilane (PFTES). In addition to containing a fluorinated block, the phosphate oligomer contained a polyethylene glycol (PEG) block, giving it both hydrophobic and hydrophilic properties. An analysis of the surface chemistry of the fabrics pre- and post-dip-coating by FT-IR and X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS) indicated that the cotton fabric had been successfully functionalized. Furthermore, scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and atomic force microscopy (AFM) analysis showed a clear change in the morphology of the cotton fibers and an increase in the root mean square (RMS) surface roughness, as a result of the dip coating, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00684-f005" class="xref">Figure 5</xref>a. The authors then evaluated the cotton fabrics wetting properties with a variety of oils and water by contact angle analysis. The coated cotton fabrics were determined to be SHI-SOP in a dry state, pre-wetted, and submersed. Additionally, further testing showed the coated fabrics exhibit strong fouling resistance to oils, and maintained their SHI-SOP properties, even after 1000 cycles of Martindale abrasion testing, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00684-f005" class="xref">Figure 5</xref>b. The authors attributed the SHI-SOP characteristics of the coated cotton to the increased surface roughness imparted by the SiNPs and the presence of hydrophilic and oleophobic functional groups.
</p>
