<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chemical analysis by GC/MS of essential oil from aerial parts (stems and leaves) of 
  <span class="italic">S. macrostema</span> obtained from hydrodistillation indicated that the essential oil mainly contains pulegone, a monoterpene ketone, with a content of 22.08 μg/g weight fresh; which coincides with reports of other medicinal plants from Lamiaceae. Pulegone is the major terpene in 
  <span class="italic">Mentha pulegium</span>,[
  <a rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref30">30</a>] 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span>,[
  <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">31</a>] and 
  <span class="italic">Satureja</span> species as 
  <span class="italic">Satureja parvifolia</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Satureja odora</span>.[
  <a rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref32">32</a>] However, linalool and thymol were also found at high contents with 14.39 and 12.68 μg/g weight fresh, respectively. In addition, major volatiles were accompanied by less abundant terpenes as limonene (4.79 μg/g weight fresh), caryophyllene (3.45 μg/g weight fresh), and menthone (2.68 μg/g weight fresh). These are constituents from essential oils of medicinal plants from Lamiaceae such as 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span>,[
  <a rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref33">33</a>] 
  <span class="italic">M. longifolia</span>,[
  <a rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref34">34</a>] 
  <span class="italic">Minthostachys verticillata</span>,[
  <a rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref35">35</a>] 
  <span class="italic">Schizonepeta tenuifolia</span>,[
  <a rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref36">36</a>] and 
  <span class="italic">Agastache rugosa</span>.[
  <a rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref37">37</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Generally, the major components determine the biological properties of the essential oils of medicinal plants. Depending on the type and concentration of terpenes, they can exhibit different biological activities such as antimicrobial, anticancer, and antidiabetic; they have also been associated with hepatoprotective, cardiovascular diseases, spasmolytic, and carminative activities. Recent reports suggest that, at least in part, the encountered beneficial effects of essential oils are due to the pro-oxidant effects at cellular level.[
  <a rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref7">7</a>
  <a rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref38">38</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil from 
  <span class="italic">S. macrostema</span> showed high antioxidant activity 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> (&gt;50%) at 1 mg/mL with DPPH (53.11%) and ABTS (92.12%), activities higher or similar that those ejected by 1 mg/mL of BHT showing 30.39% and 97.23% of activity, respectively. However, at 0.1 mg/mL, the essential oil reached at 98.25% of TAC, one value greater than the effect observed with ascorbic acid (62.43%).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antioxidant activity produced at 0.1 or 1 mg/mL of the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">S. macrostema</span> is greater that the activity reported for the essential oil of diverse medicinal plants from Lamiaceae (
  <span class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</span>, 
  <span class="italic">M. officinalis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Pogostemon cablin</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span>), which showed antioxidant activity &gt;50% at 3 mg/mL.[
  <a rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref39">39</a>
  <a rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref40">40</a>
  <a rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref41">41</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antioxidant activity of essential oil from 
  <span class="italic">S. macrostema</span>, demonstrated by the three methods of free radical scavenging used in the present research, was attributed to the high content of terpenes. The most powerful scavenging constituent by DPPH and ABTS was found to be thymol showing 94.07% and 99.52% of activity, respectively, percentages of antioxidant activity higher than BHT (30.39% and 97.23%, respectively) at 1 mg/mL. Thymol and limonene shown the higher antioxidant activity determined by TAC method with 98.57% and 98.74%, respectively, percentages higher than ascorbic acid (62.43%) at 0.1 mg/mL.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The synergistic effect between terpenes of 
  <span class="italic">S. macrostema</span> essential oil can be due to the interaction of monoterpenes with hydroxyl substituents, such as thymol and linalool. In addition, the combination of limonene and caryophyllene enhances this effect as has been reported for essential oil from many medicinal plants.[
  <a rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref42">42</a>
  <a rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref43">43</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The high content of thymol (36.5%) is responsible of the antioxidant activity (&gt;80%) of 
  <span class="italic">T. spathulifolius</span>,[
  <a rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref10">10</a>] 
  <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span>,[
  <a rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref44">44</a>] and oregano essential oil (
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> ssp. 
  <span class="italic">hirtum</span>).[
  <a rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref9">9</a>] In fact, thymol is responsible for the antioxidant activity of many essential oils where it is present.[
  <a rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref44">44</a>
  <a rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref45">45</a>] However, in the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">Thymus caespititius</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Thymus camphoratus</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Thymus mastichina</span>, the antioxidant activity is related to the high contents of linalool, while thymol is almost absent;[
  <a rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref7">7</a>
  <a rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref46">46</a>] neral/geranial, citronellal, isomenthone, and menthone in 
  <span class="italic">M. officinalis</span>[
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">11</a>] and menthone and isomenthone in 
  <span class="italic">M. longifolia</span> and 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span>[
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">11</a>] are related to the antioxidant activity. Some alkene terpenes such as terpinene and caryophyllene also show antioxidant capacity by retarding the peroxidation of linoleic acid.[
  <a rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref47">47</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pulegone is an oxygenated monoterpene with a ketone group which gives a low reactivity. The essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">M. pulegium</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Mentha suaveolens</span> shown a low free radical scavenging activity due to the high content of pulegone.[
  <a rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref48">48</a>
  <a rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref49">49</a>] In agreement with this, in the present work, we detected that although pulegone is the major terpene of the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">S. macrostema</span>, it shows a lower antioxidant activity. Thus, this activity could be attributed to thymol content, which is in agreement with other reports.[
  <a rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref9">9</a>
  <a rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref10">10</a>
  <a rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref44">44</a>
  <a rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref45">45</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With these results, it is possible to establish that the pharmacological effects attributed to 
  <span class="italic">S. macrostema</span> in Mexican folk medicine are due in part to the antioxidant activity, which has also been linked to other species of 
  <span class="italic">Satureja</span>.[
  <a rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref18">18</a>
  <a rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref19">19</a>
  <a rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref20">20</a>
  <a rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref50">50</a>] The essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">S. macrostema</span> may be considered as potential natural antioxidants and used to prevent oxidative stress that contributes to many degenerative diseases.
 </p>
</sec>
