<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Methicillin-resistant 
  <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) is a major cause of hospital- and community-acquired infections worldwide. Therefore, this study was conducted to explore the antibacterial activity of the two medicinal plants 
  <italic>Epaltes divaricata</italic> and 
  <italic>Vetiveria zizanioides</italic> against strains of MRSA which were isolated from patients with skin and soft tissue infections. Hexane, ethanol, and water extracts of 
  <italic>E. divaricata</italic> (whole plant) and 
  <italic>V. zizanioides</italic> (roots) were prepared. Clinical isolates of MRSA strains (
  <italic>n</italic> = 20) were used for the study. Bacterial susceptibility was tested using a disc diffusion assay. Minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) was determined by a broth microdilution method. Vancomycin was used as the positive control. Hexane, ethanol, and water extracts of 
  <italic>E. divaricata</italic> showed inhibitory zones against MRSA. Except for water extract, both hexane and ethanol extracts of 
  <italic>V. zizanioides</italic> showed inhibitory zones. MIC ranges of hexane, ethanol, and water extracts in 
  <italic>E. divaricata</italic> were 0.012–0.32 mg/mL, 0.019–2.4 mg/mL, and 0.019–0.48 mg/mL, respectively. Respective MIC ranges of hexane and ethanol extracts of 
  <italic>V. zizanioides</italic> were 0.003–0.032 mg/mL and 0.019–2.4 mg/mL. The hexane extract of 
  <italic>V. zizanioides</italic> inhibited 55% of the selected MRSA strains at a relatively low MIC value of 0.012 mg/mL. The hexane extract of both plants demonstrated inhibition of 75% of MRSA strains at a MIC value of 0.064 mg/mL. Ethanol extract of 
  <italic>V. zizanioides</italic> and 
  <italic>E. divaricata,</italic> respectively, inhibited 70% and 45% of MRSA strains at the MIC of 0.096 mg/mL, whereas water extract of 
  <italic>E. divaricata</italic> inhibited 80% of MRSA strains at the same MIC. Both 
  <italic>E. divaricata</italic> and 
  <italic>V. zizanioides</italic> were equally effective against MRSA at a MIC of 0.064 mg/mL. But 
  <italic>V. zizanioides</italic> was more effective since the hexane extract inhibited more than 50% of MRSA strains at significantly a lower MIC value of 0.012 mg/mL. Fractionation, purification, and identification of active compounds will warrant further evaluation of the therapeutic potential of both plant extracts.
 </p>
</abstract>
