<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One way to obtain electromagnetic waves is by using microwave tomography [
 <xref rid="B98-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B101-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>,
 <xref rid="B102-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>]. A microwave tomographic sensor consists of both receiving and transmitting antennas [
 <xref rid="B103-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>]. By using an electromagnetic field the electromagnetic waves will be transmitted at different angles and hereby create an image of the flow inside the pipe, while comparing with an uniform permittivity background at the receiving part [
 <xref rid="B77-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>]. The hardware of a microwave sensor consists of a source that generates the microwave signals, a detection part that detects and measures the microwaves, a routing part that converts the signals into multi-views (images) of the flow and lastly microwave transmitting and receiving antennas [
 <xref rid="B77-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>]. The microwave tomography technology is not widely used for multi-phase flow measurements due to the image reconstruction algorithm, as this is too slow for real-time imaging of the dynamic behavior of the multi-phase flow [
 <xref rid="B103-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>]. An experimental MWT system is presented in [
 <xref rid="B104-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>], where an 8-port sensor is designed for oil-gas-water flows. The image construction is not yet accurate enough to be implemented for industrial and commercial application, as the image quality and hereby meter accuracy decreases with increasing frequency. Further investigation is essential to present an accurate MWT meter for multi-phase flow measurements at offshore installations.
</p>
