<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Preclinical studies: Nahata et al. [
 <xref rid="B190-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>] reported learning and memory enhancing property of its ethanolic extract and ethyl acetate and aqueous fractions in rats. The ethanolic extract (100 mg/kg, p.o) also protected against scopolamine induced dementia in rats [
 <xref rid="B188-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">188</xref>]. Three days oral treatment with 
 <italic>E. alsionoides</italic> (100 mg/kg) was effective in decreasing scopolamine induced deficit in adult male Swiss mice [
 <xref rid="B188-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">188</xref>]. Pretreatment with hydro-alcoholic extract at the doses of 100, 300 and 500 mg/kg, p.o ameliorated the ICV-STZ induced cognitive impairment by decreasing the oxidative stress and rho kinase (ROCK II) expression in the rat brain [
 <xref rid="B15-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B145-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. In-vitro, aqueous and hydroalcoholic extracts of 
 <italic>E. alsinoides</italic> showed free radicals scavenging, anti-inflammatory and enzymes (cholinesterase, glycogen synthase kinase-3-β, Rho kinase (ROCKI I), prolyl endopeptidase, catechol-o-methyl transferase and monoglycerol lipase) inhibitory activity, all of which are involved in the pathophysiology of AD [
 <xref rid="B15-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Previous studies also indicated the memory enhancing effect of 
 <italic>E. alsionoides</italic> in the experimental model of amnesia [
 <xref rid="B191-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>,
 <xref rid="B192-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>]. The methanol and water extract of 
 <italic>E. alsinoides</italic> documented to exhibit acetylcholinesterase activity, supporting its potential in reverting neuronal dysfunctions and thus in management of AD [
 <xref rid="B193-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>]. 
 <italic>E. alsionoides</italic> has not been studied systematically for clinical efficacy and toxicological effects.
</p>
