<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4">
 <label>Table 4</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Summary of clinical trials of 
   <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> preparations.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="alttext0050">Table 4</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Pharmacological activity</th>
    <th>Type of study</th>
    <th>Models</th>
    <th>Plant part/material</th>
    <th>Type of Extract/compound</th>
    <th>Doses</th>
    <th>Controls</th>
    <th>Mechanisms</th>
    <th>Results</th>
    <th>References</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>Adipogenetic and anti-aging</td>
    <td>
     <italic>in vitro</italic>
    </td>
    <td>Humans</td>
    <td>Leaves and flowers</td>
    <td>ThymLec gel 2% prepared from leaf and flower extract (1.0%–3.0%) + water, propanediol, glycerine +5.0%–13.4%) lecithin (additive) + benzyl alcohol, potassium sorbate, tocopherol (preservatives)</td>
    <td>2 mg/cm
     <sup>2</sup> of the facial skin applied with 2% concentration (20 mg/g w/w), gently spreading, twice a day (morning and evening).
    </td>
    <td>Placebo (formulation containing the same vehicle of ThymLec gel) and Benchmark 2%</td>
    <td>ThymLec topical application leads into the adipogenesis and lipid production, further augmenting cell volume and better remodelling of face oval features. ThymLec modulates the PPAR-γ signalling pathway, increasing adiponectin production and adipocyte lipid accumulation.</td>
    <td>Reduction of area (7.0%), depth, and length (10.2%) of the perioral wrinkles on day 60, whereas benchmark produced a reduction of 5.4% and 7.5%, respectively in case of humans. Length of the nasolabial lines (8.9%), Crow's feet wrinkles' area (8.9%), breadth (3.9s%), and length (11.1%) were also decreased. Face oval remodelling evaluation resulted in the reduction of total face volume (4.9 fold) in comparison with benchmark on day 60. 
     <italic>In vitro</italic> adiponectin synthesis increased in 3T3-L1 embryonic fibroblasts treated with ThymLec 2% (122% at 0.0195% concentration) and (137% at 0.039% concentration).
    </td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Anti-dysmenorrhea</td>
    <td>
     <italic>in vitro</italic>
    </td>
    <td>Humans</td>
    <td>Not defined</td>
    <td>Essential oil</td>
    <td>25 drops of essential oil</td>
    <td>Ibuprofen, Placebo (Ibuprofen 200mg + oil 25 drops)</td>
    <td>Anti-prostaglandin and antispasmodic activity of 
     <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L.
    </td>
    <td>Pain intensity mean values reached lowest point (6.57–1.14 VAS) in case of oil consumers' group in comparison with placebo (6.13–3.45) and ibuprofen (5.3–1.48) (p &lt; 0.05). No significant results were obtained in case of bleeding control by both oil and placebo. Oil was able to reduce clinical symptoms like lower abdominal pain, nausea, mood swing, and fainting after 48 h of consumption (p &lt; 0.05).</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Anti-bronchitis</td>
    <td>
     <italic>in vitro</italic>
    </td>
    <td>Humans</td>
    <td>Whole plant extract</td>
    <td>Dry powder extract</td>
    <td>160 mg oral dose along with 60 mg primrose (
     <italic>P. vulgaris</italic>) root extract for 11 days
    </td>
    <td>Placebo tablet without ingredients</td>
    <td>Not defined</td>
    <td>The extract reduced the cough symptoms on day 9 with an efficacy of 73.7% in comparison with placebo (day 11; 57.8%) (p &lt; 0.0001). Reduction of bronchitis severity score was observed only after 4 days in case of extract (-6.2) in comparison with placebo (-4.1) (p &lt; 0.05). The extract also reduced minor symptoms like disturbance in sleeping, rising body temperature, chest pain, and difficulty in breathing.</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
