<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In agreement with previous studies, we identified instances of hybridization between 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> species in both native (e.g. see 
 <xref rid="CIT0079" ref-type="bibr">Saidman 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2000
 </xref>) and non-native ranges (e.g. see 
 <xref rid="CIT0107" ref-type="bibr">Zimmermann 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0098" ref-type="bibr">van Klinken 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2006
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Mazibuko 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Muturi 2012</xref>). The success of many plant invasions has been attributed to hybridization (
 <xref rid="CIT0083" ref-type="bibr">Schierenbeck and Ellstrand 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0106" ref-type="bibr">Zalapa 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Gaskin 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>) and this may also be the case for some 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> invasions such as those in Australia and South Africa (
 <xref rid="CIT0098" ref-type="bibr">van Klinken 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2006
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Mazibuko 2012</xref>), but not in Eastern Africa. In the native range, hybridization between 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> species seems to be promoted by certain environmental conditions (
 <xref rid="CIT0101" ref-type="bibr">Vega and Hernández 2005</xref>), with hybrids frequently found in disturbed areas (
 <xref rid="CIT0102" ref-type="bibr">Verga 2005</xref>). Considering this, interspecific hybridization between 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> species in the invaded range may not only be dependent on the genetic relatedness of species, but also on whether certain habitat features facilitate co-occurrence of, and interbreeding between, them. It may also be that only certain 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> genotypes, or hybrid combinations, are successful under particular environmental conditions, or that only hybrid genotypes are able to spread extensively in new environments. In Australia, 
 <italic>P. pallida</italic> occurs widely in the north of the country, from the east coast of Queensland through the Northern territory, to the west coast of Western Australia (
 <xref rid="CIT0097" ref-type="bibr">van Klinken and Campbell 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">CRC Weed Management Guide 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0096" ref-type="bibr">van Klinken 2012</xref>). However, this species is not found in the cooler southern states of Australia, where 
 <italic>P. velutina</italic> and hybrids between this species and 
 <italic>P. glandulosa</italic> var. 
 <italic>torreyana</italic> seem to dominate (
 <xref rid="CIT0097" ref-type="bibr">van Klinken and Campbell 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">CRC Weed Management Guide 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0096" ref-type="bibr">van Klinken 2012</xref>). While these biogeographic patterns may reflect the initial introduction of only certain species to certain areas (
 <xref rid="CIT0097" ref-type="bibr">van Klinken and Campbell 2001</xref>), they may also be indicative of variation in soil or climate preferences of these species and their hybrids.
</p>
