<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In plants, SA- or JA-dependent defense responses are generally activated by non-pathogens and pathogens with different lifestyles, such as biotrophy and necrotrophy (
 <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Paparu et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2018</xref>). SA and JA are important signaling molecules in plant defense responses. Through signaling transduction, SA and JA signaling mediates 
 <italic>NPR1</italic> expression (
 <xref rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr">Stein et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Nic-Matos et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Ali et al., 2017</xref>), further eliciting distinct sets of resistance gene expression. SA signaling involves 
 <italic>PR</italic> genes encoding PR proteins including β-1,3-glucanase and chitinase (
 <xref rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr">Stein et al., 2008</xref>). JA signaling involves some genes encoding defense-related proteins, such as defensin (
 <xref rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr">Tiwari et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar, Jana &amp; Sikdar, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Brown et al., 2003</xref>). Previous studies have shown that non-pathogenic 
 <italic>F. oxysporum</italic> and 
 <italic>F. fujikuroi</italic> induce up-regulation of 
 <italic>PR1</italic> genes expression (
 <xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">Veloso &amp; Díaz, 2012</xref>) and activities of chitinase and β-1,3-glucanase (
 <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Fuchs, Moënne-Loccoz &amp; Défago, 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Patil et al., 2011</xref>) and improve pathogen resistance of host plants. However, our results showed that, in contrast to the control, although 
 <italic>F. oxysporum</italic> and 
 <italic>F. fujikuroi</italic> alone and in mixture induced significantly higher SA content in leaves of 
 <italic>I. cairica</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">Fig. 7A</xref>), the transmission efficiency of SA signaling between the three treatments was largely different. Colonization by 
 <italic>F. fujikuroi</italic> failed to transmit SA signaling and did not up-regulate 
 <italic>NPR1</italic> expression (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">Fig. 7C</xref>), chitinase and β-1,3-glucanase activities (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Figs. 6B</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6C</xref>), whereas colonization by 
 <italic>F. oxysporum</italic> and the mixture of both fungi successfully transmitted SA signaling, significantly up-regulated 
 <italic>NPR1</italic> expression (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">Fig. 7C</xref>), chitinase and β-1,3-glucanase activities (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Figs. 6B</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">6C</xref>). Interestingly, compared with 
 <italic>F. oxysporum</italic> and the mixture of both fungi, 
 <italic>F. fujikuroi</italic> induced significantly higher JA content but significantly lower β-1,3-glucanase activity in leaves of 
 <italic>I. cairica</italic> plants (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Figs. 6B</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-7">7B</xref>). The results showed that excessive JA content in 
 <italic>I. cairica</italic> plants induced with 
 <italic>F. fujikuroi</italic> antagonized SA signaling defense pathway and suppressed SA-dependent β-1,3-glucanase activity. Previous studies have suggested JA signaling cross-talk with SA signaling defense pathways 
 <italic>via NPR1</italic> (
 <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Spoel et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-73" ref-type="bibr">Withers &amp; Dong, 2016</xref>) antagonizes SA signaling and suppresses SA-dependent genes expression (
 <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Kachroo et al., 2001</xref>). Therefore, our findings showed that 
 <italic>F. oxysporum</italic> played a dominant role in inducing pathogen resistance of 
 <italic>I. cairica</italic> against 
 <italic>C. gloeosporioides</italic> because its presence alone or coexistence with 
 <italic>F. fujikuroi</italic> alleviated the antagonism of JA signaling on SA-dependent β-1,3-glucanase activity.
</p>
