<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Samples were collected from five symptomatic plants and three asymptomatic plants in May 2018 from Geno Mountain, Hormozgan province, Iran (N27º38′92″; E56º16′55″) (
 <xref rid="f1-ppj-35-274" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>). Total DNA was extracted from symptomatic and asymptomatic 
 <italic class="italic">A. sieberi</italic> plants by cetyltrimethylammonium bromide (CTAB) extraction procedure described by 
 <xref rid="b23-ppj-35-274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sahu et al. (2012)</xref> with some modifications. Genomic DNA was used as the template for PCR analysis. 16S rDNA fragment was amplified the using phytoplasma universal primer P1/P7 (
 <xref rid="b6-ppj-35-274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Deng and Hiruki, 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="b24-ppj-35-274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schneider et al., 1995</xref>), then with nested PCR primer pair R16F2n/R16R2 using the prior PCR amplicons (1:30 dilution) as the template (
 <xref rid="b8-ppj-35-274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gundersen and Lee, 1996</xref>). Leaf tissue infected with “
 <italic class="italic">Candidatus</italic> Phytoplasma trifolii” (a member of 16SrVI group) was used as a positive control (
 <xref rid="b10-ppj-35-274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hemmati et al., 2018</xref>). The 16S rDNA fragment was cloned into pMD
 <sup class="sup">™</sup> 18-T cloning vector (TaKaRa, Dalian, China) and inserted into 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> strain DH5a competent cells (TaKaRa). Three positive transformants were selected and sent to Macrogen Sequencing Service (Republic of Korea) for sequencing. Sequences received in this study were assembled and aligned using software: DNAstar and ClustalX. The sequences from infected samples were identical, and three consensus sequences were deposited into the GenBank database (GenBank accession MK299844-6). Phylogenetic analyses were conducted by neighbor joining (NJ) method using MEGA 6.0 software (
 <xref rid="b25-ppj-35-274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tamura et al., 2013</xref>) with 10,000 replicates for bootstrap analysis. 
 <italic class="italic">Acholeplasma laidlawii</italic> was used as out-group to root the tree. The sequences of 16S rDNA of different phytoplasma groups used in comprehensive phylogenetic analyses were downloaded from GenBank database.
</p>
