<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. (Lamiaceae) is an aromatic and medicinal plant containing essential oil and is widely used all over the world for its expectorant, antibroncholitic, antispasmodic, and other properties. Antimicrobial properties of plant essential oils were revealed a long time ago, but researches are expanded and complements acknowledged findings. Recent articles present the beneficial properties in nature as biofungicide: thyme essential oil is active against
 <italic> Mycosphaerella graminicola</italic>—the pathogen today causes one of the most important diseases of wheat [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Activity against microorganisms is widely published: against
 <italic> Staphylococcus aureus</italic>,
 <italic> Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>,
 <italic> Salmonella typhimurium</italic>,
 <italic> Escherichia coli</italic>,
 <italic> Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>,
 <italic> Enterococcus faecalis</italic>, and
 <italic> Candida albicans</italic> [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>];
 <italic> Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic>,
 <italic> Streptococcus </italic>sp., and
 <italic> Pantoea </italic>sp. [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]; and
 <italic> Bacillus </italic>spp.
 <italic>, Shigella </italic>spp.
 <italic>, Trichophyton </italic>spp. (nail and scalp isolated),
 <italic> Microsporum </italic>spp.
 <italic>, Aspergillus niger, </italic>and
 <italic> Rhodotorula rubra </italic>[
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The essential oils are natural, nontoxic, nonpollutive, and biodegradable compounds with broad spectrum of antimicrobial activity, low risk of side effects after their use, and low risk of resistance development by microorganisms [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In this investigation, the main goal was focused on activity against
 <italic> Candida albicans. </italic>Yeasts may act as opportunistic pathogens and can cause candidiasis at several different anatomical sites [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Essential oils demonstrating noteworthy activity against this organism are quite extensively investigated and most oils used in dermatology have been tested against this pathogen [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
</p>
