<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some recent discoveries on the final GNR product in the plant helped to create improvements. The resin is adhesive [
 <xref rid="B76-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], and its presence in the final rubber induces early and rapid degradation during processing and storage [
 <xref rid="B77-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Rubber is present in the form of a colloidal suspension in the plant. It must be completely and correctly coagulated [
 <xref rid="B78-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. A lot of improvements were proposed:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>Improvement to clean the raw material: extraction of the rubber with a mixture of acetone, amyl oxyhydrate, methyl oxyhydrate, and alcohol while heating. The resin, oil, and wax can be then separated from solvents by distillation [
    <xref rid="B79-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Another option is to distillate water and essential oil from the obtained rubber [
    <xref rid="B80-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Improvement of the grinding method: replace the rubs or grinds by a suitable comminuting cut. The main advantage of the process is that it makes possible the use of continuously operating machines.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Elimination of the resin with a solvent before the original process. The crude woody material can be treated preliminarily with a volatile solvent in which the resin is soluble while the rubber is insoluble (acetone, ethyl alcohol, methyl alcohol), made a much-shortened grinding operation possible, and the particles of rubber display a greater tendency to cohere together than to adhere to other materials [
    <xref rid="B70-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
    <xref rid="B81-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
    <xref rid="B82-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Improvement of the separation of the rubber stuck in bagasse: decreasing the specific gravity of the rubber particles, by making them lighter and thus increasing their buoyancy in separating fluid, by adding petroleum-distillate.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>To avoid rubber deterioration, the shrub can be treated with a preservative or stabilizing agent which will stabilize or preserve the rubber: immersion in a tank containing a solution of 1% of dimethyl-paraphenylenediamine [
    <xref rid="B71-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Improvement of the liberation of the rubber by exposing the shrub to suitable gaseous agent, which penetrates the cells and raises enough pressure to expand instantaneously, like an explosion [
    <xref rid="B74-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
