<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Protein is an essential nutrient required for growth and organ development in humans and animals. It helps in the repair of body tissue, synthesis of enzymes and hormones and also contributes to energy supply. Although roots and tubers are known for their low protein content when compared to pulses/legumes (beans 15%–38%, pea 14%–36%, cowpea 20%–34%, soya bean 29%–50% and groundnut 17%–31%) and cereals such as maize (9.4%), sorghum (11.6%), rice (7.1%), wheat (12.6%) [
 <xref rid="B40-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B101-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>], yam is reported to have higher dietary protein compared to other root and tuber crops including cassava [
 <xref rid="B102-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. Yam species like 
 <italic>D. alata</italic> have been reported to have comparable higher protein levels (18.7%) than grains [
 <xref rid="B56-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Contrary to the high protein reported in 
 <italic>D. alata</italic>, Alinnor and Akelezi [
 <xref rid="B78-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>] recorded very low protein content (0.09%) in 
 <italic>D. rotundata</italic> as against 8.28% reported in the same species by another study [
 <xref rid="B77-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Yam tubers are a considerably good source of essential amino acids including phenylalanine and threonine but are limited in tryptophan and sulphur amino acids [
 <xref rid="B102-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. In addition, a more recent study on amino acid profiling of different yam species including 
 <italic>D. alata</italic>, 
 <italic>D. bulbifera</italic>, 
 <italic>D. esculenta</italic>, 
 <italic>D. oppositifolia</italic>, 
 <italic>D. pentaphylla</italic>, 
 <italic>D. spicosa</italic>, 
 <italic>D. tomentosa</italic> and 
 <italic>D. wallichi</italic> revealed the prevalence of aspartic acid (5.21–9.36 g/100 g) and glutamic acid (3.20–8.12 g/100 g) in all the yam species investigated [
 <xref rid="B104-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. In Africa, consumption of starchy staples, primarily yam and cassava, contributes a great proportion of protein intake in the region ranging from 5.9% in the Southern and Eastern Africa to 15.9% in West Africa [
 <xref rid="B102-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. 
</p>
