<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The emulsions were obtained by the phase inversion temperature method.[
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] The preparation of W/O emulsions by the PIT method is a widely used technique in obtaining emulsified systems, in particular, emulsions containing the essential oil.[
 <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] According to studies presented by Esquena, Sankar,[
 <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] the PIT method requires the system whose phase inversion temperature is above the freezing point of water, and below the temperature where degradation of substances occurs. This can be achieved by choosing the surfactant with the nonionic appropriate HLB value for the system. The oil in water emulsion composition was 5% (w/w) of PaEO, 2% (w/w) of surfactants, and 93% (w/w) of water. Initially, the continuous phase was prepared by dispersing the required Tween 20
 <sup>®</sup> in distilled water. The dispersed phase was obtained by adding Span 80
 <sup>®</sup> into the essential oil. Both phases were heated separately to 70°C and one phase dispersed within the other. The studies report the use of up to 70°C to obtain emulsions containing essential oil.[
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
 <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
 <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] The final emulsions were obtained after homogenization using an Ultra-Turrax [IKA, model T-18, Frankfurt, Germany] at 15,500 rpm for 10 min. Two batches of 14 emulsions with varying HLB values [
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>] were obtained and stored at 25 ± 2°C and 5 ± 1°C in tube assay to evaluate the IC. Furthermore, 14 flasks of 50ml each, were stored at room temperature to complete the pH and conductivity tests.
</p>
