<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The bioactive compounds of 
 <italic>Curcuma</italic> species have been well-documented in clinical and preclinical studies for their anti-inflammatory activities. Curcumin is a major constituent of 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> and its therapeutic potential against numerous diseases has been reported. A dosage of 50 mg/kg of curcumin for ten days before inducing colitis with 1,4,6-trinitrobenzene sulphonic acid contributed to substantial improvements in diarrhea, produced an amended colonic architecture, and caused a significant reduction in lipid peroxidation and neutrophil penetration. Decreased levels of NO and O
 <sub>2</sub> radicals, as well as suppressed activation of NF-κB in the colonic mucosa, reduced inflammation, and improved symptoms, have also been documented [
 <xref rid="B75-plants-10-00063" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Atoskar et al. investigated the impact of curcumin on spermatic cord edema relative to placebo and phenylbutazone after an operation for inguinal hernia or hydrocele. Here, 45 patients were regularly administered three times for 6 days following treatment, where group A was given 400 mg curcumin, group B was given 250 mg lactose powder placebo, and group C was given 100 mg phenylbutazone. The severity score dropped by 84.2%, 61.8%, and 86% in groups A, B, and C, respectively, by day 6. While on day 6, the severity scores for phenylbutazone and curcumin were identical, curcumin was demonstrated to be superior by decreasing all four inflammation parameters [
 <xref rid="B76-plants-10-00063" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-plants-10-00063" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. In addition, Kim et al. tested the anti-inflammatory and antihyperglycemic effects of xanthorrhizol and 
 <italic>C. xanthorrhiza</italic> extract with consistent xanthorrhizol on (HFD)-induced obese mice. Xanthorrhizol, at dosage levels of 10 mg/kg/day or 25 mg/kg/day, greatly reduced the glucose levels of blood, as well as inhibited the development of inflammatory cytokines, such as TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-6, etc., in HFD-induced obese mice [
 <xref rid="B53-plants-10-00063" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Chen et al. examined the anti-inflammatory properties of curcumol (bioactive compound of 
 <italic>C. wenyujin</italic>) in lipopolysaccharide-induced RAW264.7 cells. Throughout this study, the authors investigated how curcumol obstructs lipopolysaccharide-induced nitric oxide production at concentrations ranging from 12.5–200 µM via the suppression of iNOS mRNA expression and the protein level. In addition, curcumol interrupts the LPS-induced development of TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL-6, both during the transcriptional and translational stages, and primarily works by disrupting JNK-mediated AP-1 instead of NF-κB. These findings include experimental molecular confirmation that curcumol, owing to its inhibitory role in the synthesis of multiple inflammatory drugs, could be a potential leading compound for a novel anti-inflammatory medication [
 <xref rid="B78-plants-10-00063" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>].
</p>
