<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although EO
 <italic>s</italic> of 
 <italic>O. vulgare</italic> and 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> have acquired Generally Recognized as Safe (status from the Flavour and Extract Manufacturers Association and got approved by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for safety food use [
 <xref rid="B79-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]), there is limited published research on the safety of EO vapors 
 <italic>per se</italic> [
 <xref rid="B51-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. As EOs are complex blends of components, individual volatile compounds need to be assessed as potential allergens. Currently, 26 ingredients that may trigger allergic reactions, including, e.g., linalool and limonene, are listed in the seventh amendment of directive 76/768 CEE (directive 2003/15/CE); however, these are all based on skin contact and not inhalation [
 <xref rid="B81-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Regarding inhalation toxicity, which is a crucial aspect of inhalation administration, median lethal concentration (LC
 <sub>50</sub>) values were determined neither for oregano nor for thyme EOs for the inhalation route. However, the data on their predominant compounds, carvacrol and thymol, might suggest their possible inhalation safety. The European Chemicals Agency reported that the LC
 <sub>50</sub> of carvacrol in rats was estimated to be greater than 20 mg/L when rats were treated with the given test chemical via inhalation route for 6 h exposure period. Similarly, the reported LC
 <sub>50</sub> value for thymol was 7.57 mg/L, when mice were exposed to a test chemical via inhalation by vapor for 2 h [
 <xref rid="B83-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Furthermore, neither data from literature nor results from chronic toxicity studies presented in the study by Xie et al. (2019) [
 <xref rid="B84-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>] provide any evidence for chronic toxicity of inhaled thymol. In an acute oral toxicity study, the median lethal dose (LD
 <sub>50</sub>) of carvacrol and thymol in rats was found to be 810 and 980 mg/kg of body weight (bw), respectively, and carvacrol-rich EO obtained from the leaves of 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> spp. showed the oral LD
 <sub>50</sub> to be 1850 mg/kg bw; therefore, they are all classified as category 4 (H302) according to the Classification, Labelling and Packaging Regulation N° 1272/2008 and the Globally Harmonized System of Classification and Labelling of Chemicals [
 <xref rid="B83-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>] which means that it might be “harmful if swallowed”. Moreover, thymol is FDA approved when used as a synthetic flavoring (21 CFR 172.515), a preservative and indirect food additive of adhesives [
 <xref rid="B84-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>], and is a common ingredient in many products such as perfumes, food flavorings, mouthwashes, pharmaceutical preparations, and cosmetics [
 <xref rid="B85-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Similarly, carvacrol is generally considered safe for human consumption. It has been approved by FDA for its use in food and is included by the Council of Europe in the list of chemical flavorings that can be found in several food products, such as alcoholic beverages, baked goods, chewing gums, condiment relish, frozen dairy, gelatine puddings, non-alcoholic beverages, and soft candies [
 <xref rid="B86-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Moreover, EO derived from 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> has been approved by the Committee on Herbal Medicinal Products of the European Medicines Agency as a traditional herbal medicinal product used for relief of cough associated with cold [
 <xref rid="B87-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>].
</p>
