<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">EOs are a complex mixture of volatile biochemical compounds, mostly terpenoids, where synthesis and end yield are influenced by different factors. Figueiredo et al. [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] stressed the external and internal factors that might influence chemical composition and yield of EO: physiological variations, environmental conditions, geographic variation, genetic factors and evolution, storage conditions, amount of plant material and space, and extraction techniques. Standardization of the quality and quantity of essential oils can be achieved by optimized cultivation conditions and time of harvest as well as genetic engineering [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>]. The isolation and identification of bioactive compounds are important for accurately determining the underlying mechanism of the biological effects of EOs on animals. As such, trials where PFA efficacy is assessed must contain detailed information about plant chemotype and chemical composition [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>]. Also, considering chemical complexity of EOs, the wide microbiological diversity of gut microbiome, and the numerous functions of the gut, using a comprehensive approach in determining mode of action is necessary, as stated in the review paper of Zeng et al. [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. The simultaneous examination of genomes, metagenomes, transcriptomes, and proteomes can lead to better understanding PFA mechanisms. Special attention in the process of standardization for PFA testing should be focused on doses and the time required to see the effect of the additive [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>].
</p>
