<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The reported rise in the global prevalence of MetS and in the development of risk factors associated with it has been attributed to genetic, epigenetic, and environmental factors [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-02669" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Also culpable in this epidemic is the adoption of sedentary lifestyles that are characterized by low physical activity or exercise and the consumption of high-energy diets [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-02669" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-02669" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Current management approaches for the risk factors associated with MetS involve changes in lifestyle and the use of pharmaceutical drugs that mainly target specific biochemical pathways involved in the metabolism of nutrients [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-02669" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The pharmaceutical drugs are often expensive and characterized by poor patient compliance and have been implicated in the development of several undesirable side effects due to prolonged use. Moreover, they are monotherapeutic, usually targeting a few health outcomes associated with metabolic dysfunction. There is an urgent need to research and develop alternative and complementary approaches to the management of metabolic disorders. These alternative management strategies of MetS risk factors should involve the use of medicinal plants. Medicinal plants are defined as any plant or plant preparation(s) which provides health-promoting characteristics and temporary relief or has beneficial therapeutic and or prophylactic properties [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-02669" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. It has become acceptable to healthcare practitioners that medicinal plants have a role to play in the management and prevention of metabolic disorders [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-02669" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-02669" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The use of herbal medicines is not confined to developing countries but has become a multibillion-dollar industry spanning across all demographic and socio-economic strata [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-02669" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
</p>
