<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">Plasticizer is an important plastic additive, which has been widely used around the world. It plays an essential role in many types of plastic products. As the main plasticizer in plastic industry, phthalate esters account for large parts of the additives. The truth is that plasticizer industry is a large scale chemical industry taking phthalate esters as center based on petrochemical resources
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup>. Phthalate esters are easily extracted by solvent. The loss of plasticizer will reduce performance of PVC products and properties of the PVC products will change with increasing time
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, flammable nature of phthalate esters further limits its application in plastic products with high fire protection requirements. Almost all of phthalate esters derive from petrochemical resources, the industrial model is not sustainable with the depletion of fossil resources. To solve these problems, many alternatives to phthalate plasticizers have been studied. Bio-based plasticizers have been developed or used commercially such as cardanol-based plasticizer
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>, epoxidized safflower oil
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>
 </sup>, glycerol esters
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup>, and triethyl citrate
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup>. In order to improve flame retardancy of bio-based plasticizer, a series of vegetable oil based phosphate plasticizer have been synthesized in the previous studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>. Castor oil is an important chemical raw material, because its hydroxylated fatty acid structure can be used to prepare different chemical products
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup>. Vegetable oil based additive containing phosphorus groups
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup>, phenanthrene ring groups
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup> and 1,3,5-Tris (2-hydroxyethyl) cyanuric acid (THEIC) groups
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup> were synthesized and used as plasticizers for preparing flame retardant PVC materials respectively. However, all of these plasticizers are easily leached. The use of internal plasticizers can avoid migration of plasticizer from PVC products. Internal plasticizers are connected to the chemical structure of PVC matrix by chemical modification, because they are the inherent parts of the PVC chains
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>. “Click chemistry” is an efficient chemical synthesis method to prepare internally plasticized PVC materials
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>. It has been paid many attentions for the preparation of internally plasticized PVC materials
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
