<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0105">In this contribution we found that all the studied samples are rich in terpenoid compounds, whose majority metabolite in most of the samples was limonene, from which there are commercially available larvicides (
 <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Showler et al., 2019</xref>). A LC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 2.18 ppm has been reported for limonene in 
 <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (
 <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2016</xref>), these authors reported the lethal 50 concentrations for the following monoterpenes: linalool (0.35 ppm), β-citronellol (0.82 ppm), terpineol (0.31 ppm) carvone (0.54 ppm), α-pinene (4.12 ppm), and β-pinene (1.41 ppm). Knowing the LC
 <sub>50</sub> values and the concentrations of metabolites reported in 
 <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, it was observed that by decreasing the limonene concentration, the larvicidal action decreased (see 
 <xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). As discussed above, the application of electric pulses caused changes in the proportion of the appearance of metabolites in the different samples. These changes caused a modification in the larvicidal action of the oils; since it is possible to favor the concentration of metabolites with lower LC
 <sub>50</sub> values or to cause the presence of compounds with chemical activity that protect the larvae. Activity of essential oils depends on complex interaction among their compounds, which might exhibit additive, synergistic or antagonistic effects (
 <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Mitic et al., 2018</xref>). Sample 3 presents a different behavior from the other modified samples because although it decreases the concentration of limonene to 49.1%, the larvicidal action does not decrease, in fact the highest larvicidal action was found in this sample at 500 ppm. The possible loss of larvicidal activity by reduction in the concentration of limonene could be compensated by an increase in the concentration of the following sesquiterpenes: caryophyllene (5.5%), α-humulene (1.3%), β-elemene (7.1%) and α-copaene (2.9%); metabolites to which biological activities have been reported as insecticide 
 <italic>in Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (
 <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Case et al., 2003</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">Bucio et al., 2016</xref>); controlling dengue and vectors of mosquitoes of 
 <italic>filariasis</italic> a stephensi, ae. 
 <italic>Aegypti</italic> and cx 
 <italic>Quinquefasciatus</italic> (
 <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Govindarajan et al., 2016</xref>); as a potential larvicide against 
 <italic>A aegypti</italic> (
 <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Neves et al., 2017</xref>). Other studies highlight the role that plays together with the cariofilene and alpha- hemulene, affirming a synergic action between these being the first one a potentializer of the biological activity associated with the second one (
 <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Suazo et al., 2012</xref>). According to what has been exposed, it is important to recognize that the application of electrical pulses to the different samples can cause the appearance of compounds with physicochemical characteristics that enhance or decrease the biological activity according to the variants applied to the oils modification process.
</p>
