<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Glassware was cleaned and kept in a hot air oven at 160 °C for 2 h. The media were sterilized and the solutions of standard drugs (Benzyl penicillin and fluconazole) and A and B series of compounds were kept ready. In the meantime, nutrient agar medium was prepared (composition: peptone 0.5%, meat extract 0.3%, sodium chloride 0.5%, agar 2%, distilled water to make up to 100 mL, and pH adjusted to 7.2). The weighed quantities of peptone, meat extract, and sodium chloride were dissolved in 1000 mL of distilled water and the pH of the medium was adjusted to 7.2. After the dissolution of agar, the medium was distributed into conical flask each containing 25 mL. The media and sterile water were sterilized by autoclaving at 121 °C temperature and 15 lbs/sq. inch pressure for 20 min. Petri plates, test tubes, pipettes, and borer required for experiment were sterilized by dry heat sterilization using hot air oven. Cultures of respective organisms (18 h old) were taken and suspension of these microorganisms was made using sterile water. Later, 0.5 mL of this suspension was used as inoculum and pour plate technique was used for estimation of bacterial load in each sample. The inoculated agar medium was poured into sterile 10 cm-diameter petri dishes and the medium in the plates was allowed to solidify. The solutions of the test compounds in concentrations of 0.1 µg/mL were prepared in DMSO. The cups of 5 mm diameter were prepared using a borer in the corresponding medium. In each plate, 5 wells were prepared. Three wells were for test compounds, one for standard compound and another one was used as control. In each well, samples were poured and then plates were left for 45 min in a refrigerator for diffusion. After incubation for 18 h at 37 °C, the plates were examined for inhibition zones. The experiments were done in triplicate on the same day with the same conditions in order to minimize the experimental errors. The zone of inhibition values was calculated using vernier caliper and represented as a mean of three values and standard deviation was applied [
 <xref rid="B10-pharmaceuticals-13-00375" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
</p>
