<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Encapsulation efficiency (EE) and total recovery (R) of OOEO and STEO loaded inside nanovesicles were evaluated in terms of carvacrol content, the marker constituent of both the essential oils. 
 <italic>EE</italic> was calculated according to the following equation:
 <disp-formula id="FD1-molecules-26-02124">
  <label>(1)</label>
  <math id="mm1">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>E</mi>
     <mi>E</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mrow>
      <mo>(</mo>
      <mrow>
       <mfrac>
        <mrow>
         <mi>e</mi>
         <mi>n</mi>
         <mi>c</mi>
         <mi>a</mi>
         <mi>p</mi>
         <mi>s</mi>
         <mi>u</mi>
         <mi>l</mi>
         <mi>a</mi>
         <mi>t</mi>
         <mi>e</mi>
         <mi>d</mi>
         <mo> </mo>
         <mi>c</mi>
         <mi>a</mi>
         <mi>r</mi>
         <mi>v</mi>
         <mi>a</mi>
         <mi>c</mi>
         <mi>r</mi>
         <mi>o</mi>
         <mi>l</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
         <mi>i</mi>
         <mi>n</mi>
         <mi>i</mi>
         <mi>t</mi>
         <mi>i</mi>
         <mi>a</mi>
         <mi>l</mi>
         <mo> </mo>
         <mi>c</mi>
         <mi>a</mi>
         <mi>r</mi>
         <mi>v</mi>
         <mi>a</mi>
         <mi>c</mi>
         <mi>r</mi>
         <mi>o</mi>
         <mi>l</mi>
        </mrow>
       </mfrac>
      </mrow>
      <mo>)</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mo>×</mo>
     <mn>100</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <italic>encapsulated carvacrol</italic> is the concentration of the single component after the purification step. In fact, vesicles were purified from free EOs by the dialysis bag method [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-26-02124" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], using Spectra/Por
 <sup>®</sup> regenerated cellulose membranes with 3.5 KDa molecular weight cut-off, by Repligen Europe B.V. (Breda, The Netherlands). The dialysis bag was stirred in 1 L of ultrapure water, at room temperature for 1 h. After that, the purified formulations were diluted in methanol, in order to break vesicles and release the encapsulated EOs. Samples were centrifuged at 14,000 rpm for 10 min and supernatants were analyzed by HPLC-DAD. OOEO and STEO total recovery (
 <italic>R</italic>) was determined using the same procedure without the purification step by dialysis, and it was calculated according to the following equation:
 <disp-formula id="FD2-molecules-26-02124">
  <label>(2)</label>
  <math id="mm2">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>R</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mrow>
      <mo>(</mo>
      <mrow>
       <mfrac>
        <mrow>
         <mi>t</mi>
         <mi>o</mi>
         <mi>t</mi>
         <mi>a</mi>
         <mi>l</mi>
         <mo> </mo>
         <mi>r</mi>
         <mi>e</mi>
         <mi>c</mi>
         <mi>o</mi>
         <mi>v</mi>
         <mi>e</mi>
         <mi>r</mi>
         <mi>e</mi>
         <mi>d</mi>
         <mo> </mo>
         <mi>c</mi>
         <mi>a</mi>
         <mi>r</mi>
         <mi>v</mi>
         <mi>a</mi>
         <mi>c</mi>
         <mi>r</mi>
         <mi>o</mi>
         <mi>l</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
         <mi>i</mi>
         <mi>n</mi>
         <mi>i</mi>
         <mi>t</mi>
         <mi>i</mi>
         <mi>a</mi>
         <mi>l</mi>
         <mo> </mo>
         <mi>c</mi>
         <mi>a</mi>
         <mi>r</mi>
         <mi>v</mi>
         <mi>a</mi>
         <mi>c</mi>
         <mi>r</mi>
         <mi>o</mi>
         <mi>l</mi>
        </mrow>
       </mfrac>
      </mrow>
      <mo>)</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mo>×</mo>
     <mn>100</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <italic>total recovered carvacrol</italic> is the concentration of the single component after the preparation of the formulation, determined by chromatographic analysis.
</p>
