<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Hericium erinaceus</italic> is one of the medicinal mushrooms that has been most extensively studied in animal models [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. For example, its ethanol extract was able to inhibit gastric, liver and colon cancer in mouse xenograft tumors [
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] while its water extracts has been shown to possess anti-metastatic activity by inhibiting the migration of colon carcinoma cells to lungs [
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Two compounds isolated from 
 <italic>H. erinaceus</italic> were demonstrated to possess anti-cancer activity in pre-clinical mouse models. The cyanthine diterpenoid Erinacine A has shown inhibition of DLD-1 human colorectal adenocarcinoma xenograft tumor growth in nude mice [
 <xref rid="B59-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. A protein isolated from 
 <italic>H. erinaceus</italic> called HEP3 also showed ability to inhibit growth of colon cancer cells in mouse xenograft tumors [
 <xref rid="B60-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Animal studies have also been conducted with 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic>, 
 <italic>Trametes versicolor</italic> and 
 <italic>Phellinus linteus</italic>. A proteoglycan isolated from 
 <italic>P. linteus</italic> was able to potentiate immune system as well as inhibit cancer in HT-29-bearing BALB/c-nu/nu mice by inhibiting Reg IV/EGFR/Akt signaling pathway [
 <xref rid="B61-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. As for 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic>, its extracts were capable of inhibiting tumor growth in human melanoma B16-F10 cells- and sarcoma-180 cells-derived xenografts in mice [
 <xref rid="B62-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Specific compounds isolated from 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic> have shown anti-cancer activity in vivo. Two unique lanostane-type, inonotodiol and inonotsuoxides, have demonstrated anti-carcinogenic effects on mouse skin and human leukemia-derived mouse xenograft tumors [
 <xref rid="B64-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. For 
 <italic>T. versicolor</italic>, the β–glucan-based polysaccharopeptide fraction PSP exhibited growth-inhibitory effect on a number of cancer cells in mouse xenograft tumors [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In addition, a new glucan isolated from the water extract of 
 <italic>T. versicolor</italic> was able to inhibit the xenograft sarcoma growth in mice [
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>].
</p>
