<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Camellia</italic> species are unanimously considered a natural source of antioxidant compounds. Most of the studies focus on 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic>, 
 <italic>C. japonica</italic> and 
 <italic>C. oleifera</italic> being the leaves the best characterized part of the plant through their extracts or purified compounds (
 <xref rid="molecules-26-02178-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Extracts were obtained from aqueous or organic solvents (methanol, ethanol, butanol, acetone, ethyl acetate, 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane, chloroform, acetonitrile, isopropanol) under different experimental conditions of temperature and extraction time. Chromatographic fractions of the extracts are also frequently investigated. 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> var assamica seems to be the best characterized species due to the commercial relevance of their leaves. Indeed, the comparison between seeds and leaves extracts (aqueous and organic) as well as their eluted fractions revealed a higher TPC and DPPH scavenging activity in the leaves [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Despite the apparently lower antioxidant potential of the seeds, a seed saponin was reported as possessing a significant H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> scavenging activity at different pH values [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Beyond the differences in the antioxidant activity reported in the different plant structures, the extraction solvents and the maturity of the plant structure (namely of the leaves) highly impact the results. A study comparing the TPC and DPPH scavenging activity of green and fresh tea, aqueous and organic extracts, eluted with ethyl acetate and water [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] reported higher antioxidant potential of the organic extracts eluted with ethyl acetate for both kinds of leaves. Regarding the leaves maturity, a high antioxidant potential was encountered in fresh leaves. Black, green and white teas were also compared regarding their TPC, TFC, total tannin content (TTC), ABTS and DPPH scavenging activities. Globally, green tea was reported as possessing higher phenolic, flavonoid and tannin content [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] as well as ABTS scavenging activity [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] than black tea, while white tea seems to possess a middle activity [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Among black teas, several differences were also reported in the TPC, TFC and DPPH scavenging activity [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] being the results impacted by the extraction solvent [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] as already reported [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. A 50% organic extraction solvent seems to be able to extract more phenolics than the corresponding absolute solvent [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Other studies reported 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> as possessing high antioxidant potential when compared with other plant extracts [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].
</p>
