<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite being the same species, 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> var assamica, is a quite different plant which possess wider and larger leaves and is frequently found in warmer regions with tropical climates. This variety is frequently pointed as possessing higher polyphenol and lower amino acids content. Several studies reported its antioxidant properties which seems also to be highly impacted by the extraction solvent [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The higher TPC and TFC contents seems to be obtained with simple alcohols as methanol and ethanol [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] as well as the radical scavenging activity. As reported for 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic>, the kind [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] of leaves, their maturity [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and the processing methods [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] also lead to significant differences in the antioxidant properties of 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> var assamica. Despite the low consistency of the results (highly dependent on the solvent used), the TPC seems to be lower for mature leaves [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] while the TFC seems to be higher [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Differences among the antioxidant potential of the leaves were also correlated with the drying process [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and with the decaffeination process [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Higher TPC, TFC and DPPH scavenging activity were reported for dried leaves (mostly oven dried ones) than for fresh leaves [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The decaffeination process seems to decrease the antioxidant activity of the tea [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Two additional studies were found in literature focused in soluble and insoluble phenolics [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and flavanones [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Yang and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] explored in depth the antioxidant activity of Chinese mistletoes from 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> var. assamica identifying eighteen phenolic compounds. Soluble phenolics clearly exhibited higher TPC and TFC and also higher radical scavenging activity. Regarding the work developed by Zhou et al. [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], five novel and seven already known flavanones were identified with high α-glucosidase activity.
</p>
