<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another popular 
 <italic>Camellia</italic> species due to its ornamental flowers, 
 <italic>C. japonica</italic>, was the target of some studies aiming at characterizing its antioxidant potential. Leaves aqueous and alcoholic extracts [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] as well as multiple organic solvent extracts from flowers were investigated [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Aqueous leaves extracts demonstrated antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] in FRAP and DPPH assays in a dose dependent manner (DPPH assay). The remaining studies including leaves of 
 <italic>C. japonica</italic> were undertaken using organic solvents; however, the different or non-specified maturity of the leaves and cultivars diversity used prevents a direct comparison among the obtained results. Páscoa and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] performed a thorough study on the antioxidant properties of this species through its TPC, TFP and ABTS assays comparing around 31 different cultivars from two gardens. These authors concluded that the antioxidant potential of this species is highly dependent on the cultivars studied as well as on the geographic origin, being quite different even among trees of the same cultivar. In this context, care is needed when assigning these properties to a particular species in a general manner. A study comparing mature and green leaves concluded, similarly to the results obtained with 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic>, that green leaves possess higher scavenging activity [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Regarding the results obtained with alcoholic extracts, higher TPC, TFC, superoxide, hydrogen peroxide radical scavenging and ferrous ion chelating activities were obtained with ethanol (an observed trend among other species) while higher total carotenoids and L-ascorbic acid contents were obtained with methanol [
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Steam plus leaves acetone and methanol extracts were also compared and acetone extract presented a higher activity in the DPPH and β-carotene-linoleic acid assays [
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Three additional studies [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] were found in the literature focused on the flowers of this species involving different assays and extraction methodologies. Although no direct comparisons could be performed, all authors concluded that this part of the plant also possesses considerable antioxidant activity deserving additional studies to better characterize it.
</p>
