<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While a previous study demonstrated the critical role of H
 <sub>2</sub>S in plant adaptation to environmental stress, its role in invasive plant adaptation was unknown.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>
 </sup> Here, the proteomic data revealed that several proteins associated with the H
 <sub>2</sub>S metabolism were upregulated after the plants were exposed to salt stress. Further analysis showed that salt stress induced the activity of 
 <sc>l</sc>-CD and the generation of H
 <sub>2</sub>S in 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic>, and removing endogenous H
 <sub>2</sub>S accumulation by pretreatment with a H
 <sub>2</sub>S scavenger resulted in the salt stress causing more damage to the leaves, as indicated by the increased ion leakage and MDA content and reduced 
 <italic>F</italic>
 <sub>v</sub>/
 <italic>F</italic>
 <sub>m</sub> ratio. These data suggest that H
 <sub>2</sub>S enhances the tolerance to salt stress in 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic>. Compared with 
 <italic>C. malaccensis</italic>, the rates of K
 <sup>+</sup> efflux were lower in 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic>. This lower efflux of K
 <sup>+</sup> would result in higher levels of cytosolic K
 <sup>+</sup> and maintain the Na
 <sup>+</sup>/K
 <sup>+</sup> balance in 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic>. In agreement with this, suppressing H
 <sub>2</sub>S generation increased the K
 <sup>+</sup> efflux and the Na
 <sup>+</sup>/K
 <sup>+</sup> ratio, and reduced salt-induced antioxidant enzyme activity to increase ROS accumulation in the leaves, which possibly caused the lower 
 <italic>F</italic>
 <sub>v</sub>/
 <italic>F</italic>
 <sub>m</sub> ratio in the leaves. Furthermore, H
 <sub>2</sub>S-mediated salt-induced GSNOR activity reduced SNO damage in 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> after exposure to salt stress, and suppressing H
 <sub>2</sub>S generation reduced salt-induced GSNOR activity increases SNO generation. This finding is in agreement with the results of a previous study
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>
 </sup> and supports the conclusion that H
 <sub>2</sub>S enhances 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> tolerance to salt stress through increasing GSNOR activity.
</p>
