<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Once the bioactive compound is encapsulated, it can be incorporated into the film-forming solution directly [
 <xref rid="B30-polymers-12-02518" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-polymers-12-02518" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-polymers-12-02518" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B127-polymers-12-02518" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>] with later deposition of the resulting solution onto drying plates, or by sprinkling as recently reported by Nogueira et al. [
 <xref rid="B29-polymers-12-02518" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-polymers-12-02518" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-polymers-12-02518" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. In the second method, the film-forming solution is initially deposited onto support plates and, then, the encapsulated bioactive compound is added by sprinkling through a stainless-steel sieve over the entire surface area of the film-forming solution already arranged on the plates. The authors studied this second method because they believed that, due to the hydrophilic characteristic presented by the blackberry pulp microparticles (water solubility of approximately 60%, [
 <xref rid="B118-polymers-12-02518" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]), there was a great possibility that they would dissolve when added and homogenized in the film-forming solution, which also had a hydrophilic characteristic. Taking that into consideration, in this second method, the stage that consisted of homogenizing the microparticles in the film-forming solution was eliminated, which allowed the microparticles to remain intact. Cross-sectional images of the films obtained by Scanning Electron Microscope revealed the presence of dispersed and/or agglomerated blackberry microparticles within the starch matrix when incorporated directly, and predominantly dispersed and/or agglomerated blackberry microparticles within the starch matrix when incorporated by sprinkling. Regardless of the incorporation method, it was observed that the microparticles remained mostly intact [
 <xref rid="B29-polymers-12-02518" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-polymers-12-02518" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. The location of the microparticles in the starch matrix was influenced by the method used for their incorporation into the film-forming solution, while the location of the microparticles in the polymeric matrix influenced the bioactive, barrier and mechanical properties.
</p>
