<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <p>This work is dedicated to the memory of the late Dr Vétek Gábor, a co-author of this paper.</p>
 <p>We would like to thank Drs David Waite and Luciano Rigano from the Plant Health and Environment Laboratory (PHEL), Ministry for Primary Industries (MPI) for critically reviewing the manuscript. We would like to thank Drs Zhidong Yu, Claire McDonald and Sue Escott-Brown for their support, suggestions, and feedback to the project. Our special thanks go to the Entomology team members of the PHEL of MPI for supplying the BMSB specimens intercepted at the New Zealand border or from the post-border surveillance and assisting in morphological identification of the specimens. Finally, we would like to thank the following researchers for providing the BMSB specimens from a range of different countries:</p>
 <p>Dr. Catherine Duthie of Readiness Programmes, MPI, New Zealand; Ms. Xinyao Gu from Institute of Entomology, Guizhou University, China; Ms. Jianyun Wang from Environment and Plant Protection Institute, Chinese Academy of Tropical Agriculture sciences, China; Dr. Shu-Jun Wei from Institute of Plant and Environmental Protection, Beijing Academy of Agriculture and Forestry Sciences, China; Dr. Jun Ma from Institute of Plant Quarantine, Guangzhou Customs Technology Center, China; Dr. Yongliang Fan from Northwest A &amp; F University, China; Dr. Dong Liu from Chines Academy of Sciences, China; Dr. Xiaofen Xue from Nanjing Agricultural University, China; Dr. Lixia Xie from Shandong Agricultural University, China; Dr. Gonzalo Avila from Plant &amp; Food Research, New Zealand; Dr. Kyo Itoyama from Meiji University, Japan; Valerio Mazzoni from Edmund Mach Foundation, Iris Bernardinelli from Servizio fitosanitario e chimico, ricerca, sperimentazione e assistenza tecnica, Italy; Drs Laura Nixon and Kim Hoelmer from US Department of Agriculture, the USA; Dr. Roxana Ciceoi from University of Agricultural Sciences and Veterinary Medicine of Bucharest, Romania; Dr. Ilania Astorga Leiva from Subdepto Vigilancia y control de plagas agrícolas, División Protección Agrícola y Forestal, Servicio Agrícola y Ganadero, Gobierno de Chile; Dr. Attila Torma from University of Szeged, Dr. Ákos Varga from Government Office of Pest County, Hungary; Dr. Temel Göktürk from Artvin Coruh University, Turkey; Dr. Maka Murvanidze from Agricultural University of Georgia, Georgia; Dr. Wolfgang Rabitsch from University of Vienna, Austria.</p>
 <p>This research was partly supported by the Hungarian Ministry for Innovation and Technology within the framework of the Higher Education Institutional Excellence Program (NKFIH-1159-6/2019) in the scope of plant breeding and plant protection research of Szent István University, and the NKTH 2017-2.3.3-TÉT-VN-2017-00006 (Biological control of invasive pest species in Vietnam and Hungary) research project. Finally, we would like to thank the editor and two anonymous reviewers for their suggestions in improving the manuscript.</p>
</ack>
