<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the quest to identify other benefits of 
 <italic>Dioscorea</italic> species, studies have revealed yam therapeutic potentials as a result of its bioactive compound content. A bioactive compound is defined as a substance that can exert biological effect, thus, causing a reaction or triggering a response in a living tissue [
 <xref rid="B20-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. A study on seven different varieties of yams (
 <italic>Dioscorea</italic> spp.) reported reasonable quantities of these compounds including flavonoids, phenols, saponins, tannins and alkaloids [
 <xref rid="B21-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Another study described the pharmacological activities of yam peptides and proteins such as antioxidant, immunomodulatory, estrogenic, angiotensin I-converting enzyme inhibiting, carbonic anhydrase and trypsin inhibiting, chitinase, anti-insect, anti-dust mite, lectin and anti-proliferative activities [
 <xref rid="B22-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. These authors reported the therapeutic potentials of peptides and proteins isolated from several species of yams including 
 <italic>D. alata</italic>, 
 <italic>D. cayenensis</italic>, 
 <italic>D. japonica</italic>, 
 <italic>D. pseudojaponica</italic> and 
 <italic>D. polystachya</italic> (formerly known as 
 <italic>D. opposita</italic> or 
 <italic>D. batatas</italic>), as well as the possible clinical applications for the treatment of inflammatory diseases, cardiovascular diseases, aging disorders, menopause, cancers and osteoporosis. Furthermore, the use of different species of 
 <italic>Dioscorea</italic> for birth control and skin infections has been reported [
 <xref rid="B23-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Nashriyah et al. [
 <xref rid="B25-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] reported the use of 
 <italic>D. hispida</italic> in cosmetics for pigmentation remedy. This is not surprising as since time immemorial, the utilization of natural products with therapeutic potentials including mineral, plant and animal substances as main sources of drugs have existed [
 <xref rid="B26-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. This long standing historic use of plants as therapeutic resources serves as a proof of their efficacy. The diversity in yams has the potential to enrich the human body with starch and energy [
 <xref rid="B27-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], as well as supplemental metabolites while serving as a source for medicinal use at level of traditional therapeutics and industrial medical pharmacy. The therapeutic potential of yam is of interest especially in developing countries where a majority of the population lacks access to standard health care, which even when available is far beyond the reach of many locals due to the financial burden, thus, yam may contribute to providing health benefits beyond its nutritive values.
</p>
