<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21" class="p">Milk thistle (
 <italic class="italic">Silybum marianum</italic> L.) is an important medicinal plant from the family 
 <italic class="italic">Asteraceae</italic>. The bioactive compounds are mainly concentrated in its seeds which have been used for more than 2000 years to treat liver diseases. Milk thistle seeds contain 17.5–30.5% of lipids rich in unsaturated fatty acids and 1–3% of silymarin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>].. Recently, certain 
 <italic class="italic">Silybum marianum</italic> accessions have begun to be cultivated in several countries and the specie is undergoing domestication for making the supply of silymarin sustainable [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>]. Previously published studies examined the triacylglycerol, fatty acid, tocopherol, sterol and polyhpenol composition of milk thistle seeds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>]. Significant differences were observed between milk thistle cultivars for the content of bioactive compounds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>]. Also, the antioxidant properties of ethanolic extracts of milk thistle seeds and methanolic extracts of cold-pressed milk thistle seed oil have been reported [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>].To the best of our knowledge, however, no data has been published on the policosanol composition and the anti-arthritic activity of milk thistle oil. Therefore, this study aimed to examine the policosanol profile, anti-arthritic and antioxidant activities of milk thistle oil at different stages of seed maturity. Such data could serve for the evaluation of nutritional and health impact of milk thistle oil and for the development of new source of natural bioactive compounds.
</p>
