<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In diabetes, oxidative stress interrupts glucose metabolism’s normal coupling to insulin secretion by activating stress signaling nuclear factor-κB (NF-κB) and p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathways. The activation of NF-κB causes the production of inflammatory cytokines that promote insulin resistance whilst activating MAPK to reduce insulin receptor substrate-1 (IRS-1) serine phosphorylation, thereby causing insulin resistance [
 <xref rid="B43-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. A series of studies have proven Gelam honey’s protective effect on diabetes through this insulin resistance signaling pathway mechanism. Gelam honey exerts protective effects against diabetes and hyperglycemia-induced oxidative stress through improving insulin content and insulin resistance by producing the differential expression of insulin signaling pathways MAPK, NF-κB, IRS-1 (ser307) and Akt in HIT-T15 cells [
 <xref rid="B45-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Gelam honey had been shown to attenuate the oxidative stress-induced inflammatory pathways when pretreatment with Gelam honey or quercetin reduced the expression of phosphorylated jun-N-terminal kinase, IkappaB kinase and IRS-1, thereby significantly reducing the expression of proinflammatory cytokines, such as tumour necrosis factor alpha (TNF-α), interleukin-6 (IL-6) and interleukin-1β (IL-1β). A significant increase in phosphorylated Akt was also found, indicating the protective effects against inflammation and insulin resistance [
 <xref rid="B46-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Batumalaie et al. (2014) reported that pretreatment of HIT-T15 cells with Gelam honey before culturing in hyperglycemic media yielded a significant decrease in the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS), glucose-induced lipid peroxidation and a significant increase in insulin content and the viability of cells cultured under hyperglycemic condition [
 <xref rid="B47-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. This series of studies demonstrated the potential anti-oxidative role of Gelam honey in managing diabetes through improving pathway-related insulin resistance and production.
</p>
