<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>UFAs have attracted the interest of researchers in the areas of skin cosmetics and food due to their numerous known benefits to human health. The intake of UFAs increases the amount of high-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol [
 <xref rid="pone.0249919.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], promoting a reduction in LDL levels. Oleic acid (C18:1, ω-9, 40% of RPLO), which is abundant in olive oil used in the Mediterranean diet and RPLO, has been described to regulate immune and anti-inflammatory functions [
 <xref rid="pone.0249919.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0249919.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], reduce depressive symptoms [
 <xref rid="pone.0249919.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], and exert positive effects on the prevention and treatment of cardiovascular, autoimmune and metabolic diseases, and cancer [
 <xref rid="pone.0249919.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Dietary supplementation of diabetic mice with palmitoleic acid (C16:1 [ω-7] 6.3% of RPLO) promoted a reduction in body weight, hyperglycemia, and hypertriglyceridemia [
 <xref rid="pone.0249919.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], and is an important positive modulator of glucose uptake [
 <xref rid="pone.0249919.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In the study by Souza et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0249919.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], the intake of palmitoleic acid promoted a reduction in hepatic steatosis and the levels of inflammatory mediators and improved peripheral insulin resistance in mice, attenuating the production of hepatic glucose induced by a high-fat diet [
 <xref rid="pone.0249919.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Linoleic acid (C18:2 [ω-6] 1.1% of RPLO), although it is a minor constituent of RPLO, is a precursor of important endogenous fatty acids, such as arachidonic and eicosapentaenoic acids, which have shown cardioprotective properties [
 <xref rid="pone.0249919.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0249919.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and may attenuate the inflammatory process involved in metabolic syndrome, as well as cell adhesion, apoptosis, and cancer [
 <xref rid="pone.0249919.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0249919.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
</p>
