<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study we opted to use ecological niche models (ENMs), spatial analysis and spread modeling to determine the potential invasive range of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>zonata</italic>. We include additional occurrence records of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>zonata</italic> for Sudan in our ENM and merge the derived probability of occurrence with host availability data to map areas that are potentially vulnerable. A simple natural dispersal model that mimics the classical spread modeling approaches is developed to determine the potential dispersal pattern of the fruit fly. Ecological niche models link species occurrence and abundance data at known locations with the spatial and environmental properties of those sites to predict the potential distribution of the species across a landscape [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] and are being used extensively [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. One of the ENM algorithms which has been widely employed in modeling potential species distributions in recent years is maximum entropy (MaxEnt) [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The machine learning algorithm MaxEnt [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] offers a platform to determine areas that are climatically suitable to invasive pests and many such applications are available in literature [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Coupling ENMs with spatial analysis methods to map areas that are potentially vulnerable and spread modeling strengthens the ability to understand the potential invasive range of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>zonata</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Several approaches have been developed to model the dispersal of invasive species ranging from the classical reaction-diffusion models which address short distance dispersal [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] to those which focus on long distance and stratified dispersal and other different aspects of dispersal [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The reaction-diffusion models which assume the Gaussian dispersal kernel are used as reference against which other models with different dispersal kernels can be compared [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].
</p>
