<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="abs0010">
 <sec>
  <title>Background and objectives</title>
  <p>
   <italic>Kigelia africana</italic> is a medicinal plant growing naturally in many parts of Africa. In Kenya, a water concoction of the plant is used to treat breast and prostate cancers. Laboratory data on its anti-cancer activity and active principles is limited, hence no scientific rationale for its medicinal use. This study reports on 
   <italic>in-vitro</italic> toxic activities of dichloromethane and methanol extracts of the plant against human breast cancer cells and phytochemical screening of the two extracts.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methodology</title>
  <p>Plant extracts were obtained by sequential solvent extraction of dry plant material (stem bark) using analytical grade dichloromethane: methanol (1:1) and methanol (Sigma Aldrich). 
   <italic>In-vitro</italic> anti-cancer activities of the extracts were determined using the suphorhodamine (SRB) assay against a human breast cancer cell line (HCC 1937). Preliminary Thin layer chromatography of plant extracts was done using POLYGRAM® SIL G/UV
   <sub>254</sub> plates (Merck) to establish presence of different classes of secondary metabolites.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>
   <italic>In-vitro</italic> cytotoxic activities of the two extracts were significantly different (
   <italic>P</italic> = 0.05). The methanol extract exhibited higher activity (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 26.02 μg/ml) compared to that of dichloromethane: methanol (1:1) (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 55.01 μg/ml). Phyto-chemical screening of the two extracts revealed the presence of terpenoids, phenols, steroids and flavonoids.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p>The high 
   <italic>in-vitro</italic> anti-cancer activities of solvent extracts of 
   <italic>Kigelia africana</italic> justify its use in traditional medicine to manage breast cancer. Phytochemical analysis of the extracts reveal similar profiles hence the differences in their anti-cancer activities can be attributed to quantitative variations of various classes of secondary metabolites.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
