<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the use of small molecules as MTDLs is the most common approach towards the discovery of new treatments for AD, it may be interesting to spend a few words on the role of synthetic peptides as novel agents against AD. A
 <italic>β</italic> oligomers, protofibrils, and prefibrillar aggregates are pivotal players in the toxic insult leading to brain damage. Other neurodegenerative disorders, such as ALS, prior disease, or HD, are characterized by the aggregation of misfolded proteins. Synthetic peptides offer the possibility to modulate this process by interacting with endogenous peptides or interfering with protein aggregation. In the past decades, the use of peptide-based drugs has emerged as a valuable tool to treat different pathologies [
 <xref rid="B139" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>–
 <xref rid="B141" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>] and increasing interest has been paid to their effects as disease-modifying tools. They can also serve as probes and diagnostic tools for an early diagnosis or discovery of neurodegeneration [
 <xref rid="B142" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. Potential targets for peptide-based therapies could be the cognitive impairment (e.g., neuroprotective effect of insulin) or the modulation of A
 <italic>β</italic> formation and aggregation through protein-protein-like interactions. These peptides can be either natural or modified A
 <italic>β</italic> derivatives, capable of interfering with the A
 <italic>β</italic> structure and aggregates, and/or bearing nonnatural amino acids, which have already proven their ability of inhibiting A
 <italic>β</italic> aggregation and attenuating mild cognitive impairments [
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. Nevertheless, these agents have to penetrate in the brain; thus, they have to be evaluated for their ability to cross BBB and reach their targets. Interestingly, some oligopeptides have already shown significant effects in animal models of dementia [
 <xref rid="B144" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>] and an even narrowed set has been progressed into clinical studies [
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. Despite the fact that they may not perfectly fall under the definition of MTDLs, synthetic peptides have the potential to hit or modulate multiple targets associated with AD dysfunctions, and thanks to their versatility, they can also serve as disease-modifying agents, giving new perspectives and opportunities in the search for novel AD treatments.
</p>
