<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For the fulfilling of nutrition demand of growing population, the number of domesticated animals increasing rapidly. This high number of animals is directly proportional to CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> production. In developed countries, it often recommends culling of nonproductive and low-producing animals to reduce CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> budget [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. They maintained high-producing animals in herds for reducing CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions per unit of product. Conversely, this is often impractical for poor countries due to their socioeconomic and religious background. It is well established that with the increasing animal productivity, CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions also decrease per unit of products. There are many options for enhancing the productivity of animals such as the proper formulation of diets, supplementation of protein and energy to low-quality forages, ionophores, bovine somatotrophin, and probiotics [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Lately, both the increasing of animal production as well as decreasing the methane emission by the animal especially ruminants are the main focus among researchers throughout the world. A number of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> abetment strategies from ruminants have been revised earlier [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>–
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. However, these strategies summarized more concreate and cumulative approaches to set up future research needs for sustainable methane mitigation strategies in ruminants focusing direct-feed microbials. As a part of cumulative approach, accurate estimation of methane production is also very important in order to make a suitable methane mitigation strategy. Therefore, this review also summarized the methods of enteric methane measurement and their applications.
</p>
