<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Analysis of the chemical composition of the selected essential oils was performed by using a comprehensive two-dimensional chromatography with Agilent 7890A equipment (Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA, USA) and the time-of-flight mass spectrometry Pegasus IV detector (LECO Corp., St. Joseph, MI, USA). Analysis was provided using a conventional Equity 1 column (30 m × 0.25 mm i.d, 0.25 µm film thickness, SUPELCO Co., Bellefonte, PA, USA), while the secondary fast column was a SGWAX (2 m × 0.10 mm i.d., 0.10 µm film thickness, SUPELCO Co., Bellefonte, PA, USA). The operational conditions for the first oven were: 40 °C (3.5 min), temperature rise 7 °C/min; 250 °C (9.3 min), second oven 70 °C (3.5 min), temperature rise 7 °C/min; 250 °C (9.3 min); detector temperature 250 °C. The injector was working in splitless mode at temperature 250 °C. Helium (N6.0 grade; Linde AG, Munich, Germany), was used as a carrier gas with a flow rate of 1 mL/min, ionization energy of 70 eV, and ion source temperature of 250 °C in the 
 <italic class="italic">m</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">z</italic> range 40–400. One milliliter of each essential oil was transferred to a 20-mL vial and sealed with a cap with PTFE-lined silicone septum. Headspace solid-phase microextraction (HS-SPME) was used to extract volatile compounds. A divinylbenzene/carboxen/polydimethylsiloxane (DVB/CAR/PDMS) SPME fiber of 50/30 μm thickness and 2 cm length (Sigma-Aldrich) was used. The samples were kept at 40 °C for 5 min and agitated with a magnetic stirrer (450 rpm). Extraction was conducted at 40 °C for 25 min. After the extraction, the fiber was transferred to the injector of a gas chromatograph for thermal desorption of the analytes for 2 min. Identification of components was carried out using a system equipped with commercial libraries (NIST 2011 (NIST, Gaithensburg, MD, USA) and Wiley 11 (WILEY-VCH, Hoboken, NJ, USA) and by comparison of linear temperature-programmed retention indices (RI). The mixture of C
 <sub class="sub">7</sub>
 <monospace class="monospace">–</monospace>C
 <sub class="sub">30</sub> n-alkanes (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, MO, USA) was used for the calculation of RI. A semi-quantitative analysis (expressed as percentages of each component) was carried out by peak area normalization measurements without correction factors. Each sample of essential oil was analyzed in triplicate. The total number of analyzes was 18.
</p>
