<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">However, no matter how good a food is for the general public to consume, if that food does not have acceptable taste, texture, appearance, colour and aroma qualities, then the majority of people will not eat it. Flaxseed has several characteristics that could negatively affect its flavour profile and that are cause for concern. The two most important are the potential for the very high omega-3 fatty acid content in flaxseed to become rancid through oxidation, and the propensity for bitterness. The high content of alpha linolenic acid (ALA) renders it highly susceptible to oxidation. The oxidation and subsequent rancidity will lead to off flavours and a musty aroma that would be rejected in taste tests. The antioxidant content in flaxseed, provided in turn by its secoisolariciresinol diglucoside (SDG) content, is of great value in curtailing any oxidation process. In addition, flaxseed has been described as possessing a “nice nutty smell and aroma” [
 <xref rid="B4-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>], and is potentially ideal for the incorporation into a variety of foods. In research studies, flaxseed has been incorporated successfully into snack bars, muffins, bagels, bread, buns, tea biscuits, cinnamon rolls and pasta [
 <xref rid="B5-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. The concentration of flaxseed in the food will, of course, influence its flavour characteristics. Flaxseed has been incorporated into foods for human consumption at concentrations of 5–28% of total ingredients (by weight) before baking [
 <xref rid="B7-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. The amount of flaxseed ingested daily over an extended period of time has been as much as 40 to 50 g [
 <xref rid="B8-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Clinical trials having patients ingesting a food each day for up to one year have been successfully completed with drop-out rates of approximately 20% in both placebo and flax groups [
 <xref rid="B5-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. This demonstrates that it is not the flaxseed that induces non-compliance 
 <italic class="italic">per se</italic>, but instead a great number of different flax-containing foods are needed to allow variety in the daily choices if one is to maintain subjects in a trial with an extended duration. 
</p>
