<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With the aim of combining the effect on HDACs and other AD-related proteins, Cuadrado-Tejedor et al. have explored the effect of a concomitant inhibitor of HDAC6 and PDE5, namely compound 
 <bold>51</bold> (CM-414, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig17">Figure 17</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. Previously, a cocktail of two different drugs acting on these two enzymes (Vorinostat and Tadalafil) gave 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> positive effects, by alleviating cognitive deficits in AD mice and by reversing the reduced density of hippocampal neurons [
 <xref rid="B125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. In this case, a single compound is responsible for the dual activity, with a moderate class I HDAC activity and a potent inhibition of HDAC6 and PDE5. Compound 
 <bold>51</bold> is a pyrazolopyrimidinone that was inspired by known HDAC and PDE5 inhibitors and bears some key elements endowing it with the essential pharmacophoric features. It also possesses favorable ADME properties and a safe profile in terms of toxicity and cardiovascular safety. CM-414 has IC
 <sub>50</sub> against HDAC1-3, HDAC6, and PDE5 of 310, 490, 322, 91, and 60 nM, respectively, with the hydroxamic acid moiety being responsible for the HDAC activity. The synergic effect of HDAC/PDE5 inhibition is responsible for an increase of histone 3 lysine 9 (AcH3K9) acetylation in WT neurons at 10 nM, which correlates with the same effect on SH-SY5Y starting from 64 nM. In Tg2576 neurons, similar effects were observed at 100 nM, where also the effect on hAPP processing and pTAU were evaluated, highlighting a decrease in A
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>42</sub> precursors and pTAU levels. When preincubated with hippocampal slices (200 nM), compound 
 <bold>51</bold> rescued the synaptic plasticity impairment in APP/PS1 AD mice, with synaptic potentiation. After the evaluation of PK parameters, toxicity, and BBB penetration in the in vitro PAMPA assay, this analogue was tested in Tg2576 mice, choosing the dose of 40 mg/kg as the optimal one for having acceptable brain concentration and half-life. After 2 weeks of treatment, compound 
 <bold>51</bold> was able to rescue the memory impairment in the fear conditioning (FC) test, with a freezing response similar to WT mice, while a 3-week treatment followed by the Morris water maze test demonstrated a positive effect on spatial memory. To further explain these activities, the authors found that soluble A
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>42</sub> and pTAU levels decreased in treated mice (but not in WT ones), paralleled by an increase of the inactive form of GSK-3
 <italic>β</italic>. Moreover, 
 <bold>51</bold> increased the spine density on apical CA1 dendrites, upregulated markers of synaptic plasticity, and induced the restoration of some of the downregulated genes in Tg2576. A 4-week treatment also led to an enrichment of gene expression and related synaptic transmission in the hippocampal region, and these changes were triggered by an epigenetic mode of action. Overall, compound 
 <bold>51</bold> represents an optimal starting point in the discovery of novel HDACs and PDE5 inhibitors as novel and promising agents to treat AD-related dysfunctions.
</p>
