<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the highest amount of electrophysiologically active compounds were found in lavender, it proved to be the least effective in deterring egg-laying behaviour. Lavender oil has been tested as a potential oviposition deterrent agent against BTM [
 <xref rid="B34-insects-11-00465" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], where lavender did not show any effect on ovipositing behaviour. The different outcomes of our study could be explained with the different concentrations and dispersion methods used. In both studies, linalool was the most abundant component. In our study, the highest EAD response was also evoked by linalool; moreover, (±)-linalool occurred in all three EOs tested in this study, and gave high EAD responses in every measurement. It would be logical to infer that this component, alone or in combination with other antennal active components, may be the compound underlying the observed behavioural effect (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="insects-11-00465-f005">Figure 5</xref>). Molnár et al. [
 <xref rid="B15-insects-11-00465" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] showed that a synthetic blend of linalool, guaiacol and veratrol identified from BTM larval frass could also deter oviposition. To account for this discrepancy between the lower efficiency of lavender oil and these previous findings, it is important to consider that this compound is a common component of floral scents and we used a lavender oil extracted from the flowers of the plant. Odours of the lavender flower can also act as feeding attractants for the female BTM [
 <xref rid="B51-insects-11-00465" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-insects-11-00465" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]; however, the flower emits these compounds in a lower concentration compared to the commercial EOs, and deterrence just as attraction can be dose-dependent. Therefore, the high concentration of linalool could still be a deterrent for females. We have to consider that linalool can evoke different behavioural effects in the case of different species: for instance, in the case of sphinx moth (
 <italic>Manduca sexta</italic> L.) linalool did not affect the feeding behaviour; however, the females laid fewer eggs on plant emitting one of the enantiomers of linalool [
 <xref rid="B53-insects-11-00465" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].
</p>
