<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phytomedicnes have shown potentials as immunoadjuvants for their ability to increase the effectiveness of vaccines while plant-derived chemical compounds including ellagic acid 
 <bold>(80)</bold>, curcumin 
 <bold>(72)</bold>, flavonoids and quercetin possess anti-infective properties that work either by directly attacking the pathogen or indirectly by stimulating innate and acquired defense mechanisms of the host (
 <xref rid="B249" ref-type="bibr">Sodagari et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Afolayan et al., 2020</xref>). Chemically diverse antiviral compounds including primary plant metabolites such as polysaccharides, proteins, lectins, protein hyrolysates and aminoglycans (
 <xref rid="B186" ref-type="bibr">Monzingo et al., 1993</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Bouckaert et al., 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B238" ref-type="bibr">Sankaranarayanan et al., 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">Harata and Muraki, 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B175" ref-type="bibr">Meagher et al., 2005</xref>) as well as secondary metabolites including alkaloids, phenylpropanoids, tannins, flavonoids, lignans, coumarins, glycosides, steroids, terpenes, polypeptides, antimicrobial peptides, defensins, cyclotides (
 <bold>1–7</bold>) and many other plant-derived cystine-knot peptides (
 <xref rid="B130" ref-type="bibr">Kapoor et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B229" ref-type="bibr">Rex et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B287" ref-type="bibr">Younas et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Berit et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">Ghildiyal et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2020</xref>) have been detected and isolated from African medicinal plants 
 <bold>(1–172)</bold>. The role of these antiviral compounds and their main molecular target have been presented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> while plant families native to Africa which abundantly express and accumulate these phytocompounds that have found uses as anti-infective agents in TAM are presented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>.
</p>
