<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A typical medicinal plant is a biological factory of a plethora of complex bioactive metabolites and most of the phytomedicines used in TAM are polyherbal with potential multiple targets in host and/or pathogen structure. Expectedly, complex phytotherapeutics which target both the pathogen as well as the host structure required for infection of viruses without a significant cytotoxicity to the host, could represent an alternative way to develop new and effective antiviral phytotherapies (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Bekerman and Einav, 2015</xref>). Illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> are some important molecular targets identified in SARS-CoV-2 and featuring druggable structural components capable of fostering interaction with nature-inspired antiviral metabolites biosynthesized from both primary and secondary metabolic pathways presented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">da Silva Antonio et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">Ghildiyal et al., 2020</xref>). Bioactive protein hydrolysates and cysteine-rich polypeptides target viral membrane and proteins, alkaloids and glycosides target viral proteins and RNA, terpenes target viral membrane while steroids and flavonoids target viral RNA synthesis (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). For instance, the interaction between the spike glycoproteins of SARS COV-2 and the host cell angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptors which leads to viral attachment and entry, culminating in COVID-19 could be prevented or blocked effectively [
 <bold>Level V</bold>] by antiadhesive phytocompounds such as phenolics, tannins and polysaccharides (
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr">Jassim and Naji, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Hensel et al., 2020</xref>) reported in some African antiviral plants including 
 <italic>Adansonia digitata</italic> L., 
 <italic>Andrographis paniculata</italic> (Burm.f.) Nees, 
 <italic>Combretum micranthum</italic> G.Don, 
 <italic>Macaranga barteri</italic> Müll. Arg
 <italic>.</italic>, 
 <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic> A. Juss. (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). These antiviral metabolites accumulate in high amounts in several plant families used in TAM including the Lamiaceae, Meliaceae, Asteraceae, Arecaceae, Acanthaceae, Combretaceae, Zingiberaceae, Euphorbiaceae and Malvaceae (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). However, further mechanistic studies, safety investigation as well as clinical studies are required for their clinical applications.
</p>
