<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recently, pharmacologists, research scientists, and biologists have given considerable attention to 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> because of reports of it having a wide-spectrum of pharmacological importance and beneficial for human health [
 <xref rid="B21-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The leaves, roots, seeds, and stems of 
 <italic>D. moribifera</italic> have been extensively used in traditional folk medicine for several diseases. Notably, the two-dimensional cell migration wound-healing assay showed significant reduction of RAoSMCs migration induced by serum in nanoparticle-synthesized leaf and stem extracts of 
 <italic>D. moribifera</italic> of more than ∼50% [
 <xref rid="B54-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. The leaves of 
 <italic>D. moribifera</italic> can be administered to reduce irritating odors and improve mouth freshness over a long period, and subsequently, microorganism growth is prevented, and storage stability is improved [
 <xref rid="B35-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> leaf extracts also remarkably decrease melanin content, showing potential for application as a skin-whitening agent [
 <xref rid="B55-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], while the extracts of 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> stems and roots have antioxidant and antiaging effects [
 <xref rid="B56-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. There are also reports of 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> leaf extracts, potentially inhibiting cell proliferation in both the MDA-MB-231 and MCF-7 cell lines [
 <xref rid="B57-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Song et al. reported that 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> hot-water extracts showed significant anti-stress effects on sleep and stress-related hormones caused by chronic stress [
 <xref rid="B58-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. In other research, the crude extracts of 
 <italic>D. moribifera</italic> leaves seemed to exhibit higher immune activation activities and were used as an immunomodulatory agent [
 <xref rid="B59-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> leaf extracts also appear to be a useful natural resource for the management of sexual function [
 <xref rid="B60-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Meanwhile, 
 <italic>D. moribifera</italic> is also used in multi-therapeutic applications. More specifically, isolated ββ-sitosterol from 
 <italic>D. moribifera</italic> yielded results in terms of both skin whitening and moisturizing, and in preventing hair loss and improving hair density [
 <xref rid="B61-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Hence, there is a need to evaluate the medicinal applications of 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> through the phytochemical and pharmacological validation of both the crude extracts and compounds associated with the species. The different plant parts of 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> have been shown by researchers to date to have a series of pharmacological activities, that is antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, anti-amnesic, neuroprotective, anti-cancer, anti-diabetic, hepatoprotective, immunomodulatory, antimicrobial, antiplasmodial, and cytotoxic functions (
 <xref rid="antioxidants-09-00962-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).
</p>
