<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Clinical 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) utilizes the difference in relaxation properties of the water molecules present in biological systems to obtain an image and typically requires contrast agents to improve resolution and sensitivity [
 <xref rid="B58-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. An alternative to traditional contrast agents is to employ heteronuclear atoms, like fluorine (
 <sup class="sup">19</sup>F), that exhibit what are known as a “hot spots” in the MRI, providing a more detailed image with improved contrast and resolution. The use of fluorine is also advantageous because of its 100% natural abundance and high MR sensitivity (83% relative to 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H). Fluorine also resonates at a similar frequency as 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H, so little modification is required to transition from 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H to 
 <sup class="sup">19</sup>F detection. Furthermore, because there are only trace amounts of fluorine already in biological tissue, the MRI generated using 
 <sup class="sup">19</sup>F contrast agents will have low background signals [
 <xref rid="B58-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. Silica based nanomaterials for biological applications are also advantageous because they are known to have good biocompatibility, water solubility, low toxicity, a range of pH tolerances, and can be fluorescent [
 <xref rid="B61-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. As a result, F-SiNPs have been utilized for biological probes, including MRI and fluorescent imaging. 
</p>
