<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Recently, Zhou and co-workers employed F-SiNPs as an imaging and detection tool for small cell lung tumors in mice [
 <xref rid="B59-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. The authors synthesized F-SiNPs using a bottom-up method with (3-aminopropyl)trimethoxysilane and perfluoro-
 <italic class="italic">tert</italic>-butyl alcohol. The particles were prepared by reducing the methoxy groups to silanols, using trisodium citrate dihydrate in a one-pot microwave assisted reaction. The F-SiNPs had a diameter of 3.85 +/− 1.57 nm, and had good solubility in water, with little aggregation as a result of the surface amine groups. The incorporation of fluorine was verified by XPS, energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy, and FT-IR spectroscopy. In order to use the F-SiNPs as an imaging tool for tumor cells, they were functionalized with the arginylglycylaspartic acid (RGD) peptide, which is known to bind to various types of tumor cells containing integrin α
 <sub class="sub">v</sub>β
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> (A549), 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00684-f010" class="xref">Figure 10</xref>a. The functionalized F-SiNPs were then evaluated both in vitro and in vivo. With the former, it was found that the functionalized particles had non- or low-cytotoxicity, and were selectively incorporated into the A549 tumor cells, as indicated by an increase in the fluorescence signal and 
 <sup class="sup">19</sup>F MRI signal from the lysed cells, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00684-f010" class="xref">Figure 10</xref>b. In the in vivo studies, the RGD functionalized F-SiNPs were injected into the A549 tumors of mice. The 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H MRI showed the anatomic structure and tumor profile, while the 
 <sup class="sup">19</sup>F MRI showed the “hot spot” of the tumor, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00684-f010" class="xref">Figure 10</xref>c. Furthermore, histopathologic analysis of the heart, liver, lung, kidney, and spleen indicated no toxic effect on the mice from the F-SiNPs. 
</p>
