<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Moreover, various preclinical and clinical studies of these compounds were conducted to have an extensive understanding to recondite the mechanism of action and anticancer activities on in vivo rat and human models. However, these compounds possess certain physicochemical issues particularly issues pertaining to its low solubility and bioavailability, therefore, attempts to revamp the anticancer activities by numerous encapsulation techniques help conceal the debits of these curcumin-free compounds. Proper selection of delivery systems for non-curcuminoids are promising, especially with PNS technology, which has successfully identified these compounds, along with curcumin components without any distortion of shape or size. In fact, this technology is a feather in the cap of these versatile non-curcuminoids, which prove promising benefits when used in combination with a more bioavailable form of curcumin. Clinical studies were also conducted on these formulations based non-curcuminoids which consolidate promising results that make them strong contender in the medicinal market to fight numerous diseases especially cancer. However, more studies on the exclusive therapeutic benefits of these components through more clinical trials on varied catalogs such as by considering larger group of cancer patients, extending treatment regimen duration and monitoring safe effective dose can promulgate its universal acceptance. This review tries to unveil the promising effects of non-curcuminoids by giving an insight on researches conducted up until now. Nevertheless, more studies including the bioavailability, drug interactions, effect on multi drug resistance and chemopreventive activities when used alone or in combination with other cancer treatment drug can provide them as an epitome of economical cure and relief in the discipline of medicine. These benefits acknowledge a wide scope for various cancers, late or early stage cancers and recurrent cancers, which would help in the decline of relapses and death rate. To summarize, this review is an integrative approach to promote these natural compounds as an affluent and benevolent source for future studies.</p>
