<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par52">The annual shrub, 
 <italic>Tribulusterrestris</italic> has been used as medicine for a long time to treat various types of ailments. Different parts of shrub contain a range of medicinally important chemical constituents which as flavonol, spirostanol and furostanol saponins (tigogenin, neotigogenin, hecogenin, neohecogenin, gitogenin, neogitogenin, chlorogenin, sarsasapogenin, ruscogenin, and diosgenin), flavonoids, alkaloids and glycosides (quercetin 3‑
 <italic>O</italic>‑rutinoside, quercetin 3‑
 <italic>O</italic>‑glycoside and kaempferol 3‑
 <italic>O</italic>‑glycoside) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR214">214</xref>]. These active constituents showed immunomodulatory, aphrodisiac, antiurolithic, diuretic, hypolipidemic, antidiabetic, hepatoprotective, analgesic, absorption enhancing, cardiotonic, anti‑inflammatory, antibacterial, antispasmodic, anticancer, anticariogenic, larvicidal and anthelmintic activities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR214">214</xref>]. According to Chui et al. and Lu et al
 <italic>. Tribulus terrestris</italic> herb used habitually for the treatment of coronary heart disease, cerebral arteriosclerosis, myocardial infarction, thrombosis and hypertension [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR215">215</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR217">217</xref>]. Aqueous and methanolic extracts of gokhru possess an imperative antihypertensive effect directly by membrane hyperpolarization and relaxation of arterial smooth muscle in impulsive hypertensive rats [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR214">214</xref>]. Adaikan
 <italic>et al</italic>. reported that beneficial effects for the treatment of different ailments are credited to its capability to boost up the discharge of nitric oxide (NO) from the nitrergic nerve endings and endothelium [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR218">218</xref>]. Also, Sharifi, et al. recommended that the antihypertensive effect of gokhru may be associated with its angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitor action [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR217">217</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR219">219</xref>].
 <graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="13659_2020_281_Figx_HTML" id="MO30" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</p>
