<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1-medicines-04-00063" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Essential Oil Extracted from Rosemary (R
  <sub>EO</sub>)
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The demand for essential oils from medicinal plants has increased in recent years, especially in the case of oil from rosemary, which is used as a natural food preservative (listed by the European Food Safety Authority and the US Food and Drug Administration). </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The genus 
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus</span> includes popular herbs of the Lamiaceae family with potent antioxidant activity. It has aromatic and medicinal species (for example 
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span> L.) with antimicrobial and antioxidant activities [
  <a rid="B41-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-medicines-04-00063">41</a>,
  <a rid="B42-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-medicines-04-00063">42</a>,
  <a rid="B43-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-medicines-04-00063">43</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rosemary is a plant which can be used in different ways as an aromatic medicinal and as a culinary plant. Accordingly, it is grown all over the world, particularly in Spain, France, England, Russia and Portugal. This genus is extremely rich in essential oil, although there are large intraspecies differences in terms of the yield and quality of the essential oil produced.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rosemary is the only herb commercially available for use as an antioxidant in Europe and the United States [
  <a rid="B21-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-medicines-04-00063">21</a>]. Its extract contains antioxidant compounds, the most active being phenolic diterpenes, such as carnosic acid, carnosol, rosmanol, epirosmanol, isorosmanol, methylcarnosate, and rosmarinic acid. The biological activities of 
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span> essential oil (
  <span class="italic">R
   <sub>EO</sub>
  </span>) have been reported in numerous studies, mainly focussing on its antioxidant [
  <a rid="B44-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-medicines-04-00063">44</a>], antibacterial [
  <a rid="B45-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-medicines-04-00063">45</a>], and antifungal properties [
  <a rid="B46-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-medicines-04-00063">46</a>]. This plant has a high availability and low cost.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antimicrobial effect of 
  <span class="italic">R
   <sub>EO</sub>
  </span> has been reported in several studies testing its antibacterial activity. Gomez-Estaca et al. [
  <a rid="B47-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-medicines-04-00063">47</a>] reported that rosemary essential oil totally inhibited the growth of 
  <span class="italic">Salmonella choleraesuis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Shigella sonnei</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Yersinia enterocolitica</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Bacillus cereus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Clostridium perfringens</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Aeromonas hydrophila</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Photobacterium phosphoreum</span>. These bacteria are common food pathogens and bacteria contributing to food spoilage. In addition, Burt [
  <a rid="B34-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-medicines-04-00063">34</a>] also reported a good inhibitory in vitro effect of 
  <span class="italic">R
   <sub>EO</sub>
  </span> against 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Bacillus cereus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span>. In general, Gram-negative bacteria are less sensitive to essential oils (due to the hydrophilic cell wall structures which block the penetration of hydrophobic components through the cell membrane) than are Gram-positive bacteria [
  <a rid="B48-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-medicines-04-00063">48</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One example of incorporation of rosemary into meat was reported in 2013 by Sirocchi et al. [
  <a rid="B49-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-medicines-04-00063">49</a>]. These authors incorporated 
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span> EO at 4 (
  <span class="italic">w</span>/
  <span class="italic">w</span>) in active packaging of meat. This EO inhibited the increase of putrefaction products, such as cadaverine and the development of bacteria, such as 
  <span class="italic">Enterobacteriaceae</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Brochothrix thermosphacta</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Along similar lines, Estévez and Cava [
  <a rid="B50-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-medicines-04-00063">50</a>] showed that the effect of 
  <span class="italic">R
   <sub>EO</sub>
  </span> on the oxidative stability of frankfurters depended partly on the level of essential oil used and partly on the origin of the meat used to make frankfurters (made either from Iberian or non-Iberian pork). An antioxidant effect was observed when 150 ppm of 
  <span class="italic">R
   <sub>EO</sub>
  </span> were added to the frankfurters made with non-Iberian pork, and no effect was observed on lipid oxidation with doses of 300 and 600 ppm. In contrast, rosemary essential oil inhibited the development of lipid and protein oxidation in a concentration-dependent manner in frankfurters made with Iberian pork.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The acceptance among consumers of the use of essential oils is growing, and more than 150 essential oils are listed as GRAS (generally recognized as safe) by the US Food and Drug Administration. However, the protective effects of natural antioxidants, such as essential oils, against protein oxidation have been little investigated, as recognized by Nieto et al. [
  <a rid="B39-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-medicines-04-00063">39</a>], who studied the mechanisms behind the protection of protein against oxidation by natural antioxidants in meat patties. For this study, two levels (0.05% and 0.4%) of rosemary essential oil were added to pork patties, and their effects on the protein oxidation occurring in the patties during storage were studied. The oxidative stability of the meat proteins was evaluated by the loss of thiols and the formation of myosin cross-links. These authors reported that essential oils of rosemary retarded protein oxidation. 
 </p>
</sec>
