<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pomegranate (
 <italic>Punica granatum</italic> L.) belongs to the family of Punicaceae and is widely cultivated in many tropical and subtropical countries. Overall, many studies reported health-promoting properties (including antioxidant, anticancer, and antimicrobial) of pomegranate peel and fruit extracts [
 <xref rid="B324-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">324</xref>]. Moreover, the main components responsible for antiviral activity of pomegranate are four major polyphenols, namely ellagic acid, caffeic acid, luteolin, and punicalagin [
 <xref rid="B325-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">325</xref>]. Interestingly, pomegranate peel (considered as agro-food waste), is also a great source of different flavonoids with both antibacterial and antiviral activities. The antiviral activity of 
 <italic>P. granatum</italic> extracts against HSV-2 has been investigated by Arunkumar and Rajarajan in a recent paper [
 <xref rid="B326-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">326</xref>]. Authors found a significant inhibitory activity of tfruit peel ethanolic extract, with punicalagin showing 100% anti-HSV2 31.25 μg/mL and strongly interacting with targeted proteins of HSV-2 (as revealed by molecular docking analysis). Moeover, [
 <xref rid="B327-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">327</xref>] studied the anti-influenza virus activity of total phenolics characterizing pomegranate peel extract and other fractions. The authors showed that the crude peel extract and its 
 <italic>n</italic>-butanol and ethyl acetate fractions were characterized by the higher inhibitory effects against influenza A virus. In particular, the authors reported IC50 values of 6.45, 6.07 and 5.6 μg/mL in MDCK cells, respectively, with a significant reduction in the production of virus in a dose-dependent manner. Punicalagin and pomegranate peel extract in conjunction with zinc (II) salts were tested against HSV in another in vitro study conducted in epithelial Vero host cells [
 <xref rid="B328-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">328</xref>]. The antiviral action of the extract against HSV-1 in association with different concentrations of ZnSO4 confirmed the ability of this association to fight the virus by enhancing their virucidal activity by over five-fold. From the studies available in the literature, it therefore appears that antiviral activity, especially on HSV-1 and HSV-2, may be closely related mainly to high concentrations of punicalagin.
</p>
