<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the present investigation, seeds of 
 <italic>D. chryseum</italic> were inoculated on the MS basal medium alone and in combination with phytohormones BAP and NAA or with CW as additives. The initiation of seed germination was marked by the formation of green small protocorms. Germination was observed on all MS media. The earlier seed germination was found on 1/2 MS medium alone and FMS medium supplemented with 5% CW and 10% CW within three weeks of culture. Seeds on FMS medium supplemented with BAP (0.5 mg/L) and NAA (0.5 mg/L) took the most time to germinate. The size of protocorms varied depending upon the nature of the nutrient. Small protocorms were observed on 1/4 MS, 1/2 MS, and FMS media with both 5% and 10% CW. These small protocorms developed directly into shoots. In contrast, the protocorms which developed on FMS supplemented with NAA (0.5 mg/L) and BAP (0.5 mg/L) grew quite large by the 24th week but did not develop shoots. Maximum seed germination occurred on 1/2 MS medium which later developed into young protocorms. The result of mass propagation of 
 <italic>D. chryseum</italic> by using protocorm culture is already reported by us [
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. A similar result for the micropropagation of other 
 <italic>Dendrobium</italic> species with a high percentage of germination and protocorm formation included 67% MS [
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. 
 <italic>D. transparens</italic> seeds germinated 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> on a 1/2 MS recipe with 2.0 mg/L of 6-benzyladenine (BA) [
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Half strength MS medium was effective for the seed germination of both 
 <italic>Vanda dearei</italic> (45%) and 
 <italic>Taprobanea spathulata</italic> (92.73%). Based on the germination result, the present study revealed that all different strengths of MS medium favored seed germination up to the protocorm development. A similar result was also found for the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> germination of orchid seeds of 
 <italic>Phaius tankervilleae</italic> and 
 <italic>Cymbidium iridioides</italic> [
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].
</p>
