<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The cells were seeded in a six-well plate (3.5 × 10
 <sup>5</sup> cell/well) in DMEM containing 5.5 mM glucose (normoglycemic condition) during 24 h. Subsequently, the medium was removed and cells were treated with each plant extract (10 µM GAE) or a pure polyphenol, namely caffeic acid, chlorogenic acid, gallic acid, or quercetin (10 μM) in hyperglycemic condition (33 mM glucose), or in normoglycemic condition (5.5 mM glucose) for 3 h. Next, the medium was removed and cells were washed with PBS, scrapped, and pooled in a phosphate buffer containing KH
 <sub>2</sub>PO
 <sub>4</sub> (100 mM) and DTT (1 mM), pH 7.4. Next, a freeze-thaw step consisting on four cycles of fast freezing in liquid nitrogen and subsequent thawing in 37 °C water bath was done in order to lyse cells, as we reported previously [
 <xref rid="B42-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. After centrifugation at 500× 
 <italic>g</italic> for 4 min. at 25 °C, supernatants containing proteins were collected. The protein contents were determined using the bicinchoninic acid assay (BCA) [
 <xref rid="B43-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] and a calibration curve built with standard bovine serum albumin. The SOD activity of protein lysates were measured according to the method that was described by Bitar et al. [
 <xref rid="B44-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], by calculating the reduction of acetylated cytochrome C by superoxide radicals produced by the xanthine/xanthine oxidase system. Total SOD activity was measured in a reagent buffer at pH 7.8 with xanthine oxidase (1–2 U/mg protein), xanthine (0.5 mM), cytochrome C (0.2 mM), KH
 <sub>2</sub>PO
 <sub>4</sub> (50 mM), and EDTA (2 mM). MnSOD activity was determined similarly, after the addition of NaCN (1 mM) that leads to a specific inhibition of Cu/ZnSOD activity. Enzymatic activities were measured every 5 s during 3 min. at 25 °C, at a wavelength of 550 nm (FLUOstar Optima, BMG Labtech, Cambridge, UK), and they were expressed as U/g protein. 
</p>
