<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Such disturbances together with human-induced propagule input support invasions especially along roadsides, railways (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Becker et al., 2005</xref>) or urban areas (
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr">Sjöman et al., 2016</xref>) and make them the highly invaded sites even in unfavored landscapes (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Kalusová et al., 2013</xref>). According to the study by 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Kalusová et al. (2013)</xref>, 47 different IAS species are documented in disturbed European forest and woodlands. Alien plant species are capable of altering species composition and species richness of the ground vegetation. Understanding the processes affecting invasion dynamics is crucial for promoting the successful regeneration of native tree species. The complexity of alien plant invasion processes in temperate forests is driven by the invasibility after disturbances of the individual forest ecosystem and the species-specific characteristics of the involved native and non-native species. Most studied species exhibit particular traits that are linked to habitat-independent invaders of disturbed and nutrient-rich areas, such as large seed numbers, anemochore seed dispersal, light demand, and rapid growth rates (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Dreiss and Volin, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">Schmiedel et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Medvecká et al., 2018</xref>). Relatively few alien plant species with long life spans and slow growth rates that can form a persistent seed bank and have life histories similar to those of native plant species have been studied. The primary focus of the research examined for our synthesis lies on alien plants that rapidly invade canopy gaps rather than on “slower” invaders of closed canopy forests that might compete with native tree species in their later life stages. 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Closset-Kopp et al. (2007)</xref> conclude that the invasion success of alien plant species, e.g. of 
 <italic>Prunus serotina</italic>, in closed canopy forests is supported by the ability of those IAS to follow a “sit and wait strategy”. Accordingly, alien species following this strategy can invest quickly into growth and reproduction at a favorable moment after a long time waiting for a suitable canopy gap to open up. The “sit and wait” strategy may also support the success of other invasive alien tree and shrub species such as 
 <italic>Ailanthus altissima, Acer platanoides, Robinia pseudoacacia</italic> and 
 <italic>Quercus rubra</italic> in Europe, Asia and North America (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Knapp and Canham, 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">Sanford et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2004</xref>). According to 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Ewald (2009)</xref>, no annual IAS apart from 
 <italic>Impatiens</italic> spp. has the potential to establish itself in closed forests due to its shadow tolerance. We conclude that processes affecting the invasion of temperate forests with closed canopies are as yet poorly understood and should be studied in more detail given the changing forest management practices. The recent trend toward continuous cover forestry of temperate forests in Europe supports increased canopy closure (
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr">Vera, 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">Schultze et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Kirby and Watkins, 2015</xref>), which may require further knowledge on its ecological effects such as biological invasibility.
</p>
