<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Ethnobiology and Ethnomedicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1746-4269</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7866673</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">433</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-021-00433-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>What&#x02019;s in a name? Revisiting medicinal and religious plants at an Amazonian market</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Geertsma</surname><given-names>Isabela Pombo</given-names></name><address><email>tinde.vanandel@naturalis.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fran&#x000e7;ozo</surname><given-names>Mariana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4951-1894</contrib-id><name><surname>van Andel</surname><given-names>Tinde</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>Mireia Alc&#x000e1;ntara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7177.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000084992262</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Science, </institution><institution>University of Amsterdam, </institution></institution-wrap>Science Park 904, Amsterdam, 1098 XH the Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5132.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2312 1970</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Archaeology, </institution><institution>Leiden University, </institution></institution-wrap>Einsteinweg 2, Leiden, 2333 CC the Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5132.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2312 1970</institution-id><institution>PI ERC BRASILIAE project, Faculty of Archaeology, </institution><institution>Leiden University, </institution></institution-wrap>Leiden, the Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5132.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2312 1970</institution-id><institution>Clusius chair in History of Botany and Gardens, IBL, </institution><institution>Leiden University, </institution></institution-wrap>Leiden, the Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.425948.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2159 802X</institution-id><institution>Naturalis Biodiversity Center, </institution></institution-wrap>PO Box 9517, Leiden, 2300 RA the Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4818.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0791 5666</institution-id><institution>Biosystematics Group, </institution><institution>Wageningen University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wageningen, 6708&#x02009;PB the Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>9</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">In spite of an increasing number of ethnobotanical market surveys in the past decades, few studies compare changes in plant species trade over time. The open-air market Ver-o-Peso (VOP) in Bel&#x000e9;m, located near the mouth of the Amazon River in the state of Par&#x000e1;, Brazil, is known for its wide variety of medicinal plants. A survey of VOP was published in 1984, but it remains unknown to what extent its botanical composition changed over 34&#x02009;years. Furthermore, in northern Brazil, little attention has been given to the origins of the vernacular names of these plants. Our aim is to give an up-to-date overview of the VOP medicinal plant market, concentrating on changes in species composition and vernacular names over time.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">We collected medicinal plants and vernacular names at VOP in August 2018. We identified most plants at the Museo Paraense Emilio Goeldi Herbarium, where we also deposited vouchers and specimen labels. We compared our species composition data to the 1984 inventory by Van den Berg. Furthermore, we investigated the etymologies of the vernacular plant names.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">We recorded 155 plant specimens and 165 corresponding vernacular names, and collected 146 specimens from the medicinal and ritual stalls of VOP reporting 86 species formerly not recorded at this market. Vernacular names had mostly Portuguese roots, followed by Tupi and African ones. We found 30 species also documented in 1984, and vernacular names that overlapped between both surveys were used for the same botanical species or genus, indicating that vernacular names have changed little in the past decades. Lastly, we found 26 more introduced species sold at VOP compared to 1984.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Forest degradation and deforestation, prevalence of diseases, and methodological factors may play a role in the differences we found in our survey compared to 1984. Of the plants that did overlap between the two surveys, vernacular names of these plants were hardly different. Lastly, the lingual origins of the vernacular names in our survey and the origins of the plant species reflect the history of the intricate syncretism of medicinal plant practices of indigenous, Afro-Brazilian and European origins in Bel&#x000e9;m.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s13002-021-00433-4.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Afro-Brazilian religion</kwd><kwd>Medicinal plants</kwd><kwd>Ritual plants</kwd><kwd>Market survey</kwd><kwd>Ethnobotany</kwd><kwd>Candombl&#x000e9;</kwd><kwd>Tupi</kwd><kwd>Brazil</kwd><kwd>Vernacular names</kwd><kwd>Ver-o-Peso</kwd><kwd>Amazonia</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100010663</institution-id><institution>H2020 European Research Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>715423</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Fran&#x000e7;ozo</surname><given-names>Mariana</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par9">Many people around the world rely on traditional healthcare systems involving medicinal plants, which are often sold at open-air markets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. This is also the case in Brazil, where a great variety of medicinal plants are still traded at open-air markets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. These markets are hosted and visited by Brazilians and tourists from various cultural backgrounds. This cultural diversity is reflected in the number of available plant species and their uses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. It is easy to establish which medicinal plants are popular in the region through market surveys, as markets give an overview of local demand [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par10">There has been an increasing number of ethnobotanical market surveys in the past decades [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Although there are a number of studies that compare different markets to each other in terms of availability of plant species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], few studies have repeated ethnobotanical surveys in markets that were already monitored decades before to examine changes in species composition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Likewise, few market surveys have included an analysis of vernacular names of medicinal species being sold [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The availability of plant products at markets changes over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], indicating the importance of periodically conducting market surveys for a more complete picture of plant availability and to assess possible impacts of social and environmental factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Furthermore, the analysis of vernacular names associated with plant species can inform us more about people&#x02019;s cultural and botanical history in the study area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p id="Par11">The famous open-air market Ver-o-Peso (VOP) is located in Bel&#x000e9;m, near the mouth of the Amazon River in the state of Par&#x000e1;, Brazil. This popular market functions as a source of medicinal plants for nearby smaller markets and is known for its wide variety of herbal medicine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In 1984, Van den Berg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] published the only ethnobotanical survey of the VOP, listing the most common plants encountered in each section of the market (medicinal and ritual plants, handicrafts, vegetables and root crops, fruits, horticultural and ornamentals). This study provided an overview of the most popular species; however, this approach possibly underestimated the total medicinal species composition of the market. Furthermore, it remains unknown to what extent the botanical composition of this major Amazonian market has changed over the past 34&#x02009;years.</p><p id="Par12">The aim of this paper was to compile an up-to-date botanical overview of the VOP medicinal plant market, concentrating on species composition and vernacular names. Specifically, we wanted to know what plant species are sold at the medicinal stalls of VOP today and how these differed from those listed by Van den Berg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. We also compared the vernacular names for species in use today with those reported by Van den Berg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Furthermore, we investigated whether the origin of currently marketed plant species and their attributed vernacular names reflected the cultural backgrounds of the VOP sellers. Our three hypotheses were as follows. First, we expected to find a higher and different medicinal species composition due to our methodological approach, which differed from that of previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], and because the diversity of medicinal plants being offered for sale changes over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Availability of plant species changes from time period to time period, certain plants are conserved, new species are added, and other species are lost over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Second, we hypothesize that vernacular plant names would remain similar over time, as previously found in the Amazonian context [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Thirdly, with their own language backgrounds, religious faiths, and practices, the VOP sellers are of mixed descent: indigenous, African, and European [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. This mix of peoples is found throughout Brazil and influences the Brazilian Portuguese lexicon, including names of flora and fauna [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Afro-Brazilians of the Bahia state in northeastern Brazil, where a considerable number of enslaved Africans were forcefully brought to, sometimes use African-derived names for plants used in a medicinal and ritual context [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Also, many plant names in Surinam, a neighboring country to Brazil with a comparable history in the triangular trade involving the dislocation of western Africans, have African etymologies, influenced by the enslaved peoples that were forced to work there under brutal conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Therefore, following these examples, we hypothesized that the multicultural origins of the current population of north Brazil, including VOP sellers and consumers, would be reflected in the species&#x02019; origin and vernacular names [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. In the end, the outcome of this research contributes to the understanding of the present biocultural diversity of one of the largest and most biodiverse markets in South America.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study area: Ver-o-Peso market</title><p id="Par13">The VOP is situated on the bank of the river Par&#x000e1;, a tributary to the Amazon River, in the city of Bel&#x000e9;m (Figs. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). It is a daily open market that caters to a large and varied public and offers several types of products, from fish to artisanal craftwork, which are offered for sale in separate areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. We collected the medicinal plants at the VOP between the 7th and 25th of August of 2018 during ten mornings between 6:30 and 10:00&#x02009;am. We checked the stalls for the freshest plants and bought a varying number of plants on each visit. Prior to buying the specimens, we introduced ourselves in Portuguese to the vendors, explained the framework of this research project, and highlighted that we were collecting medicinal and ritual plant specimens for the Herbarium of the Museu Paraense Emilio Goeldi (MG). We followed the ISE Code of Ethics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. On the 25th of August, we counted 80 medicinal plant stalls and 50 <italic>erveiras</italic> and <italic>erveiros</italic>, female and male vendors respectively.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Map of the study area. Red square in the upper left map indicates Bel&#x000e9;m&#x02019;s location; larger map shows the location of the VOP market on the banks of the Par&#x000e1; river</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2021_433_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Market stalls at VOP. <bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold> Stalls selling fresh medicinal plants. <bold>c</bold> Stall that sells barks in plastic bags. d Fruit and seed stall. Photos by I. Pombo Geertsma (a and d) and C.A. van der&#x000a0;Hoeven (b and c)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2021_433_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Plant collection and identification</title><p id="Par14">We collected plants at the medicinal stands and at one artisanal stand known for its selection of dry fruits and seeds with medicinal applications. Popular plants that we could accurately identify on the spot, such as <italic>Allium cepa</italic> L. (onion) and <italic>Ruta graveolens</italic> L. (arruda), were not collected. We obtained oral informed consent from the vendors before buying the plants in the units in which they were sold. We documented vernacular names, date, price, and vendor&#x02019;s names in a notebook. We asked for the vernacular names to be repeated several times for the correct notation. Following Albuquerque et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], we made photographs of the specimens and close-up pictures of every plant in several angles, and we pressed the plants in a standard plant press to make herbarium vouchers. We either dried the specimens at home with a hairdryer, blowing hot air into a plastic bag opened at the end, in which the plant press was placed; or in the drying stove of the MG (TE-394/4, at 70&#x02009;&#x000b0;C circulation and air renewal turned on). To disinfect our collections, we stored the dried plants in a freezer provided by the MG. After identification, we deposited all vouchers and specimen labels at the MG to become part of their collection and coded each plant according to the abbreviation of the first author: IPG.</p><p id="Par15">We identified most plants by comparing them to herbarium vouchers at the MG and in the field during informal walks in nearby areas where these plants were presumably collected, such as at Ilha do Combu and the Parque Estadual do Utinga. Photographs of those specimens that we could not identify at the MG were compared to South American collections at the Herbarium of Naturalis Biodiversity Center (L) in Leiden, the Netherlands. We completed our identifications by consulting the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) website [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], the online checklist of the Flora do Brasil 2020 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], the Tropicos database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], and literature on medicinal plants in Brazil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] and Suriname [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. We identified seeds and barks by comparing their vernacular names with those mentioned in literature on Brazilian useful plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], and comparing them with photographs in Google Images. We checked and updated the species scientific plant names by using The Plant List [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par16">We organized the following information for each recorded specimen in an Excel sheet: family, genus, species and collection number, vernacular name, language, plant part sold, status in Brazil (native or introduced). We verified the spelling of the names, first with the help of the vendors in the market, and later by using Corriente [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], Navarro [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], DATAPLAMT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], Dicion&#x000e1;rio ilustrado Tupi Guarani [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], and Michaelis Dicion&#x000e1;rio Brasileiro da L&#x000ed;ngua Portuguesa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The Tupi and Portuguese dictionaries, along with the Online Etymology Dictionary [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], Corriente [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], Sebba and Corbacho [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>], and Fernandes and Soares [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] were used to determine the etymology of the vernacular plant names. Names with Latin, Greek, Phoenician (in the case of Malaga), and Arabic etymologies were listed as Portuguese, as these words were implemented into Portuguese language prior to entering Brazilian Portuguese vocabulary [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p><p id="Par17">To check the phytogeographical distribution, its status in Brazil, and the origin of each plant species, we used the Tropical Plant Database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>], Missouri Botanical Garden Plant Finder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>], GBIF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], PROTA4A [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], PROSEA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], Van Andel et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>], the Flora do Brasil 2020 online checklist [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], the Flora of China [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], Kew Science Plants of the World online [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>], the Catalogue of Life Annual Checklist [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>], Tropicos [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], the Naturalis Bioportal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>], and Herbarium voucher labels at MG. To compare our results to the VOP ethnobotanical inventory in the 1980s, we updated the taxonomy of the plant species found at the medicinal and religious plant stalls by Van den Berg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and checked if they were native or introduced. Comparing detailed medicinal or ritual uses of plants between 1984 and 2018 was not part of our research aims.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Data sharing</title><p id="Par18">This study was based on the participation of local specialist vendors. Although we compensated them financially by buying their plants, we also discussed our research results with them and followed up their request to provide them with a complete list of the common and scientific names of the identified plants, following Del Arco et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. We also included pictures of some pressed and dried vouchers, our contact information, and the MG location. We decided that this was the best option due to time constraints preventing us from organizing workshops or other benefit-sharing activities.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Inventory of medicinal and ritual plants at the VOP in 2018</title><p id="Par19">We recorded 155 plant specimens with in total 165 corresponding vernacular names and collected 146 specimens from the medicinal stalls of the VOP (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Most of the vernacular names had Portuguese roots (59%), followed by Tupi (28%) roots, while three names had unknown origins (2%) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). If a name had a double etymological root, they were classified in separate categories. We found names that had a combination of Tupi and Portuguese roots (9%) and African and Portuguese roots (2%). For example, <italic>uxi-amarelo</italic> (<italic>Endopleura uchi</italic> (Huber) Cuatrec.) is a combination of a Tupi plant (<italic>uxi</italic>) and the Portuguese term for yellow (<italic>amarelo</italic>). Likewise, <italic>Tapete de Oxal&#x000e1;</italic> (<italic>Episcia cupreata</italic> (Hook.) Hanst.) is a combination of an African term (the god Oxal&#x000e1;) and the Portuguese term for rug.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Medicinal plant species documented at VOP</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Family, scientific name/voucher number</th><th>Vernacular name/language</th><th>Part sold</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3">Acanthaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;cf. <italic>Blechum</italic> sp./IPG20</td><td>Amansa/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Justicia pectoralis</italic> Jacq./IPG17, IPG44</td><td>Abre caminho/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Adoxaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Sambucus canadensis</italic> L./IPG24, IPG57</td><td>Sabugueiro/P</td><td>Branches, fresh leaves, flowers</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Amaranthaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Alternanthera brasiliana</italic> (L.) Kuntze/IPG6, IPG78</td><td>Chega at&#x000e9; a mim/P, Meracilina/?</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Pfaffia glomerata</italic> (Spreng.) Pedersen/IPG33</td><td>Corrente/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Amaryllidaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Allium cepa</italic> L./not collected</td><td>Cebola/P</td><td>Bulb&#x02019;s skin</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Anacardiaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Anacardium</italic> cf. <italic>giganteum</italic> Hancock ex Engl./IPG100</td><td>Caju-&#x000ed; do mato/T + P</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Anacardium occidentale</italic> L./IPG99</td><td>Caj&#x000fa;/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Antrocaryon amazonicum</italic> (Ducke) B.L. Burtt &#x00026; A.W. Hill/IPG103</td><td>Cedro/P</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Schinus terebinthifolia</italic> Raddi/IPG14</td><td>Aroeira/P</td><td>Branches, fresh leaves, flowers</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Spondias</italic> sp./IPG130</td><td>Tapereb&#x000e1;/T, Caj&#x000e1;/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Anacardiaceae sp. IPG94</td><td>Anoera/T?</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Anacardiaceae sp. IPG95</td><td>Aroeira/P</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Annonaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Annona montana</italic> Macfad./IPG81</td><td>Graviola/P</td><td>Branches, fresh leaves</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Xylopia frutescens</italic> Aubl./IPG155</td><td>Ibiriba/T</td><td>Dry fruit and seed</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Annonaceae sp./IPG107</td><td>Cip&#x000f3; urira/T</td><td>Woody stem with</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Apocynaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Aspidosperma nitidum</italic> Benth. ex M&#x000fc;ll.Arg./IPG101</td><td>Carapanauba/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Cascabela</italic> cf. <italic>thevetia</italic> (L.) Lippold/IPG148</td><td>Castanha da India/P, Munduruku/T, Chapeu de mato le&#x000e3;o/P</td><td>Dry fruit and seed</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Himatanthus articulatus</italic> (Vahl) Woodson/IPG129</td><td>Sucu&#x000fa;ba/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Araceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Dieffenbachia seguine</italic> (Jacq.) Schott/IPG79</td><td>Comigo-ningu&#x000e9;m-pode/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Araliaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Polyscias scutellaria</italic> (Burm.f.) Fosberg/IPG73</td><td>Cuia mansa/T + P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Arecaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Manicaria saccifera</italic> Gaertn./IPG144</td><td>Bu&#x000e7;u/T</td><td>Fruit and seeds</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Socratea exorrhiza</italic> (Mart.) H.Wendl./IPG124</td><td>Paxi&#x000fa;ba/T</td><td>Root</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Asparagaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Sansevieria cylindrica</italic> Bojer ex Hook./not collected</td><td>Lan&#x000e7;a-de-S&#x000e3;o Jorge/P</td><td>Whole plant</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Sansevieria hyacinthoides</italic> (L.) Druce/not collected</td><td>Espada-de-s&#x000e3;o Jorge/P</td><td>Whole plant</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Sansevieria trifasciata</italic> Prain/not collected</td><td>Espada-de-Joana d&#x02019;Arc/P</td><td>Whole plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Bignoniaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Bignonia</italic> cf. <italic>nocturna</italic> (Barb.Rodr.) L.G.Lohmann/IPG104</td><td>Cip&#x000f3; curimb&#x000f3;/T</td><td>Woody stem with bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Fridericia</italic> cf. <italic>chica</italic> (Bonpl.) L.G.Lohmann/IPG77</td><td>Pariri/T</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Mansoa alliacea</italic> (Lam.) A.H.Gentry/IPG60</td><td>Cip&#x000f3; de Alho/T + P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Newbouldia laevis</italic> (P.Beauv.) Seem./IPG82</td><td>Espinheira santa/P</td><td>Dry leaves</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Bixaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Bixa orellana</italic> L./IPG174</td><td>Uruc&#x000fa;/T</td><td>Fruit and seeds</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Boraginaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Cordia</italic> sp./IPG115</td><td>Louro rosa/P</td><td>Wood with bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Burseraceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Protium</italic> sp./IPG97</td><td>Breu/P</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Clusiaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Calophyllum brasiliense</italic> Cambess./IPG111</td><td>Jacareuba/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Symphonia globulifera</italic> L.f./IPG92</td><td>Anani/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Commelinaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Commelina erecta</italic> L./IPG31</td><td>Vence-demanda/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Tradescantia zebrina</italic> Bosse/IPG85</td><td>Quebra-chiban&#x000e7;a/P, Trapoeraba/T</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Compositae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Acmella oleracea</italic> (L.) R.K.Jansen/IPG1</td><td>Jambu/T</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Ayapana triplinervis</italic> (Vahl) R.M.King &#x00026; H.Rob/IPG55</td><td>Japana branca/T + P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Bidens</italic> sp./IPG18</td><td>Pic&#x000e3;o/P</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Mikania glomerata</italic> Spreng./IPG54, IPG75</td><td>Sicuriju/T</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Pectis elongata</italic> Kunth/IPG9</td><td>Cominho/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Sphagneticola trilobata</italic> (L.) Pruski/IPG16</td><td>Desempata/P</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Tagetes erecta</italic> L./IPG12</td><td>Cravo/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Unxia camphorata</italic> L.f./IPG51</td><td>Trevo s&#x000e3;o Jo&#x000e3;o/P</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Convolvulaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Cuscuta</italic> sp./IPG65</td><td>Desatrapalha/P</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Costaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Costus spicatus</italic> (Jacq.) Sw./IPG59</td><td>Canarana/P + T</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Crassulaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Bryophyllum pinnatum</italic> (Lam.) Oken/IPG56</td><td>Pirarucu/T</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Cucurbitaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Cayaponia</italic> cf. <italic>rigida</italic> (Cogn.) Cogn./IPG63</td><td>Quebra feiti&#x000e7;o/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Luffa operculata</italic> (L.) Cogn./IPG149</td><td>Cabacinha/P</td><td>Dry fruit</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Momordica charantia</italic> L./IPG15</td><td>Mel&#x000e3;o-de-S&#x000e3;o Caetano/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Dilleniaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Doliocarpus dentatus</italic> (Aubl.) Standl./IPG105</td><td>Cip&#x000f3;-de-fogo/P</td><td>Woody stem with bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Dioscoreaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Dioscorea</italic> sp./IPG176</td><td>Batata-de-colar-osso/P</td><td>Rhizome</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Euphorbiaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Croton cajucara</italic> Benth./IPG128</td><td>Sacac&#x000e1;/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Croton sacaquinha</italic> Croizat/IPG5</td><td>Angel-de-guarda/P, Corre atraz/P, Busca longe/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Euphorbia tithymaloides</italic> L./IPG76</td><td>Coramina/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Jatropha curcas</italic> L./IPG47</td><td>Pi&#x000e3;o branco/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Jatropha gossypiifolia</italic> L./IPG19</td><td>Pi&#x000e3;o roxo/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Jatropha podagrica</italic> Hook./IPG38</td><td>Pi&#x000e3;o-paje/P + T</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Geraniaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Pelargonium</italic> cf. <italic>graveolens</italic> L&#x02019;H&#x000e9;r/not collected</td><td>Malva rosa/P</td><td>Living plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Gesneriaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Episcia cupreata</italic> (Hook.) Hanst./IPG40</td><td>Tapete de Oxal&#x000e1;/P + A (Oxal&#x000e1;), La&#x000e7;o de amor/P</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Humiriaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Endopleura uchi</italic> (Huber) Cuatrec./IPG134</td><td>Uxi-amarelo/T + P</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Humiria balsamifera</italic> Aubl./IPG117, IPG132</td><td>Miri/T; Umiri/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Lamiaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Aeollanthus suaveolens</italic> Mart. ex Spreng./IPG11</td><td>Catinga-de-mulata/T + P</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Ocimum americanum</italic> L./IPG7, IPG8</td><td>Estorakue/P, Manjeric&#x000e3;o/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L./IPG62</td><td>Manjeric&#x000e3;o roxo/P</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Ocimum gratissimum</italic> L./IPG52</td><td>Alfavaca/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Plectranthus amboinicus</italic> (Lour.) Spreng./IPG68</td><td>Hortel&#x000e3;-de-Maranj&#x000e3;o/P + T, Hortel&#x000e3;-de-folha-grande/P</td><td>Branch with fresh leaves</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Pogostemon cablin</italic> (Blanco) Benth./IPG86</td><td>Anica/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Pogostemon heyneanus</italic> Bent./IPG58</td><td>Oriza/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Vitex agnus-castus</italic> L./IPG4</td><td>Alecrim-de-Angola/P (alecrim) + A (Angola)</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Lamiaceae sp. IPG61</td><td>Chama/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Lauraceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Cinnamomum verum</italic> J.Presl/IPG120</td><td>Canela/P</td><td>Woody stem with bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Cinnamomum</italic> sp./IPG46</td><td>Canela/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Lecythidaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Couratari guianensis</italic> Aubl./IPG131</td><td>Tauari/T</td><td>Bark, fruits</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Leguminosae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Anadenanthera</italic> cf. <italic>peregrina</italic> (L.) Speg./IPG121</td><td>Paric&#x000e1;/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Bauhinia</italic> cf. <italic>guianensis</italic> Aubl./IPG110</td><td>Escada-de-Jabot&#x000ed;/P + T</td><td>Woody stem with bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Bauhinia monandra</italic> Kurz/IPG72</td><td>Pata-de-vaca/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Bowdichia virgilioides</italic> Kunth/IPG172</td><td>Sucupira/T</td><td>Seeds</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Caesalpinia ferrea</italic> C.Mart./IPG158</td><td>Juc&#x000e1;/T</td><td>Fruit</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Copaifera</italic> sp./IPG108</td><td>Copa&#x000ed;ba/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Dalbergia monetaria</italic> L.f./IPG135</td><td>Ver&#x000f4;nica/P</td><td>Woody stem with bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Dipteryx odorata</italic> (Aubl.) Willd./IPG152</td><td>Cumaru/T</td><td>Seeds</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Hymenaea courbaril</italic> L./IPG112</td><td>Jatob&#x000e1;/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Mimosa tenuiflora</italic> (Willd.) Poir./IPG114</td><td>Jurema preta/T + P</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Mimosa verrucosa</italic> Benth./IPG113</td><td>Jurema branca/T + P</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;cf. <italic>Ormosia</italic> sp./IPG98</td><td>Buiu&#x000e7;&#x000fa;/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Pentaclethra</italic> sp./IPG125</td><td>Pracax&#x000ed;/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Senna hirsuta</italic> (L.) H.S.Irwin &#x00026; Barneby/IPG50</td><td>Sombra-do-mundo/P, Afasta espirito/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Vouacapoua americana</italic> Aubl./IPG89</td><td>Acap&#x000fa;/T</td><td>Wood</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Leguminosae sp./IPG96</td><td>Barbatim&#x000e3;o/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Lythraceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Punica granatum</italic> L./IPG169</td><td>Rom&#x000e3;/P</td><td>Dry exocarp</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Malvaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Gossypium barbadense</italic> L./IPG42</td><td>Algod&#x000e3;o/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Luehea</italic> sp./IPG90</td><td>A&#x000e7;oita-cavalo/P</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Melastomataceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Miconia ciliata</italic> (Rich.) DC./IPG26</td><td>Canela-de-velho/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Meliaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Carapa guianensis</italic> Aubl./IPG93</td><td>Andiroba/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Moraceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Brosimum acutifolium</italic> Huber/IPG118</td><td>Murur&#x000e9;/T</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Dorstenia cayapia</italic> subsp. <italic>asaroides</italic> (Hook.) C.C. Berg/IPG48</td><td>Api&#x000ed;/T</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Morus nigra</italic> L./IPG28</td><td>Amora/P</td><td>Branch with fresh leaves and fruits</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Olacaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Ptychopetalum olacoides</italic> Benth./IPG116</td><td>Marapuama/T</td><td>Wood with bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Phyllanthaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Phyllanthus amarus</italic> Schumach. &#x00026; Thonn./IPG22</td><td>Quebra-pedra/P</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Phyllanthus urinaria</italic> L./IPG21</td><td>Dinheiro-em-penca/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Phytolaccaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Petiveria alliacea</italic> L./IPG25, IPG179</td><td>Mucuraca-&#x000e1;/T, Rinch&#x000e3;o/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts; Dry whole plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Piperaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Peperomia circinnata</italic> Link/IPG64</td><td>Carrapatinha/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Piper callosum</italic> Ruiz &#x00026; Pav./IPG27</td><td>Elixir-pareg&#x000f3;rico/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Piper peltatum</italic> L./IPG70</td><td>Malvarisco-de-folha-grande/P, Capeba/T</td><td>Fresh leaves</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Plantaginaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Bacopa monnierioides</italic> (Cham.) B.L.Rob./IPG84</td><td>Trevo do mar/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Conobea scoparioides</italic> (Cham. &#x00026; Schltdl.) Benth./IPG32</td><td>Pataqueira/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Scoparia dulcis</italic> L./IPG13</td><td>Vassourinha-de-igreja/P</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Poaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Chrysopogon zizanioides</italic> (L.) Roberty/IPG178</td><td>Patichuli/P</td><td>Dry roots</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic> (DC.) Stapf/not collected</td><td>Capim-marinho/T + P</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Zea mays</italic> L./IPG164</td><td>Milho/P</td><td>Stalk</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Polygonaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Antigonon leptopus</italic> Hook. &#x00026; Arn./IPG69</td><td>Agarradinho/P</td><td>Whole plant with tubers</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Polygala spectabilis</italic> DC./IPG36</td><td>Camembeca/T</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Portulacaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Portulaca pilosa</italic> L./IPG23</td><td>Amor crescido/P</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Rhizophoraceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Rhizophora mangle</italic> L./IPG126</td><td>Ra&#x000ed;z-de-mangue/P</td><td>Root</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Rosaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;cf. <italic>Prunus</italic> sp./IPG91</td><td>Ameixa/P</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Rubiaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Uncaria</italic> sp./IPG133</td><td>Unha-de-gato/P</td><td>Woody stem with bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Rutaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Citrus</italic> x <italic>aurantium</italic> L./IPG67</td><td>Laranja-da-terra/P</td><td>Branch with fresh leaves</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Ruta graveolens</italic> L./not collected</td><td>Arruda/P</td><td>Leaves in small plastic bags; Whole plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Sapindaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Paullinia cupana</italic> Kunth/IPG154</td><td>Guaran&#x000e1;/T</td><td>Seeds</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Sapotaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Pradosia lactescens</italic> (Vell.) Radlk./IPG102</td><td>Casca doce/P</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Selaginellaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Selaginella parkeri</italic> (Hook. &#x00026; Grev.) Spring/IPG49</td><td>Samambaia/T</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Simaroubaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Quassia amara</italic> L./IPG41, IPG123</td><td>Folha-da-quina/P; Pau-tenente/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts; Wood with bark</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Siparunaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Siparuna guianensis</italic> Aubl./IPG88</td><td>Capiti&#x000fa;/T, Negra-mina/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Solanaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic> L./IPG29</td><td>Pimenta malagueta/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Physalis angulata</italic> L./IPG37</td><td>Camap&#x000fa;/T</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Urticaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Cecropia obtusa</italic> Tr&#x000e9;cul/IPG87</td><td>Imba&#x000fa;ba branca/T + P</td><td>Dry leaves</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Pellionia repens</italic> (Lour.) Merr./IPG71</td><td>Hei-de-vencer/P, Vence-batalha/P, Maria-fuma&#x000e7;a/P</td><td>Fresh whole plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Verbenaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Aloysia gratissima</italic> (Gillies &#x00026; Hook.) Tronc./IPG39</td><td>Folha-de-alfazema/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Lippia alba</italic> (Mill.) N.E.Br. ex Britton &#x00026; P.Wilson/IPG43, IPG66</td><td>(Erva) cidreira/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Lippia thymoides</italic> Mart. &#x00026; Schauer/IPG30</td><td>Manjerona-de-Angola/P + A</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Vitaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Cissus verticillata</italic> (L.) Nicolson &#x00026; C.E.Jarvis/IPG10, IPG34, IPG80</td><td>Insulina/P, Cip&#x000f3;-de-puca/T, Quebra-barreira/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Xanthorrhoeaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Aloe vera</italic> (L.) Burm.f./not collected</td><td>Babosa/P</td><td>Whole plant</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Zingiberaceae</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Alpinia zerumbet</italic> (Pers.) B.L.Burtt &#x00026; R.M.Sm./IPG45</td><td>Vindic&#x000e1;/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L./not collected</td><td>Mangarataia/T, Safr&#x000e3;o/P, A&#x000e7;afria/P, Gengibre amarela/P</td><td>Rhizome</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Unidentified</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Indet/IPG74</td><td>Chora-nos-meus-p&#x000e9;s/P</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Indet/IPG83</td><td>Cabi/uncertain</td><td>Fresh aerial parts</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Indet/IPG106</td><td>Cip&#x000f3;-ferro/T + P</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Indet/IPG109</td><td>Core/P</td><td>Bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Indet/IPG122</td><td>Pau-de-bota/P</td><td>Woody stem with bark</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Indet/IPG127</td><td>Raiz-do-sol/P</td><td>Root</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Indet/IPG177</td><td>Cauan/T</td><td>Fresh tuber</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Fresh aerial parts include stem, leaves, flowers, and/or fruit</p><p><italic>Indet</italic> species indetermined; languages: <italic>P</italic> Portuguese, <italic>T</italic> Tupi, <italic>A</italic> African</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Linguistic origin of the vernacular plant names of the Ver-o-Peso market, 2018. Languages are Portuguese (P), Tupi (T), and African (A)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2021_433_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">Most of our recorded specimens consisted of fresh plants, followed by woody stems or barks, and a few fruits, seeds, roots/rhizomes, and dried herbs (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Plant parts sold at medicinal and religious stalls at the VOP market</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Plant parts</th><th>Number of medicinal plant species</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Whole plants (fresh)</td><td>82</td></tr><tr><td>Woody stems and/or barks</td><td>44</td></tr><tr><td>Fruits</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td>Whole plants (dried)</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>Seeds</td><td>7</td></tr><tr><td>Roots/rhizomes</td><td>6</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par21">Of these, we identified 116 taxa to species level, 14 taxa to genus level, five to family level, and seven taxa remained unidentified. Species were spread over 59 families, the most diverse family at the market was Leguminosae (12% of the species), followed by Lamiaceae (7%), Compositae (6%), Euphorbiaceae (4%), Anacardiaceae, and Bignoniaceae (3%) (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). We found 77 (66%) species native to Brazil and 39 (34%) previously introduced from Africa, Asia, Europe, and other Latin-American countries (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). We documented 11 species of African origin, 14 species of Asian origin, and three species of European origin. All African and almost all Asian species had a tropical distribution, except <italic>Allium cepa</italic> L. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], <italic>Morus nigra</italic> L. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>], and <italic>Punica granatum</italic> L. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>], which originated in the drier parts of southwestern Asia.
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Number of species per medicinal plant family at the VOP market</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Plant families</th><th>Number of medicinal plant species</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Leguminosae</td><td>16</td></tr><tr><td>Lamiaceae</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td>Compositae</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>Euphorbiaceae</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Anacardiaceae</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>Bignoniaceae</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>Other<sup>a</sup></td><td>88</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>This category contains 53 families with less than four species</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Comparison between current VOP medicinal plants and VOP in the 1980s</title><p id="Par22">We compared our survey to Van den Berg&#x02019;s medicinal and religious plant survey in 1984 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Van den Berg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] listed 39 (75%) native and 13 (25%) introduced species (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). In our survey, we found 30 species (57%) that were also documented in 1984 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). For these overlapping species, we documented three vernacular names not mentioned by Van den Berg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Likewise, she documented four vernacular names that did not come up in our survey (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Overlapping vernacular names were used for the same botanical species or genus.
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of the proportion of native versus introduced species between Van den Berg&#x02019;s (1984) survey and our inventory (2018)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2021_433_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Venn-diagram showing the overlap between 2018 and the period 1965&#x02013;1984 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] of plant species found at VOP&#x02019;s medicinal and ritual stalls</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2021_433_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Differences in vernacular names found in the current study and in Van den Berg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Species</th><th>Current vernacular names</th><th>Vernacular names reported by Van den Berg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>Cissus verticillata</italic></td><td>Cip&#x000f3; de Puca, Insulina, Quebra barreira</td><td>Puc&#x000e1;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Fridericia</italic> cf. <italic>chica</italic></td><td>Pariri</td><td>Pariri; Crajir&#x000fa;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Petiveria alliacea</italic></td><td>Mucuraca-&#x000e1;; Rinch&#x000e3;o</td><td>Mucura-ca&#x000e1;; Guin&#x000e9;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Piper callosum</italic></td><td>Elixir pareg&#x000f3;rico</td><td>Elixir pareg&#x000f3;rico; &#x000d3;leo el&#x000e9;trico</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Bryophyllum pinnatum</italic></td><td>Pirarucu</td><td>Pirarucu; Folha-da-fortuna</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Medicinal plants at the Ver-o-Peso</title><p id="Par23">Our results give an up-to-date botanical inventory of the VOP, one of the largest open markets in South America, which is often quoted in ethnobotanical review studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Likewise, we were able to complement other medicinal plant market surveys in the area that differ in species composition and richness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], providing a more accurate idea of the present diversity of medicinal plants in the area. Although subject of a previous ethnobotanical study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], comparison with our intensive market inventory resulted in differing degrees of overlap in species assembly and nomenclature.</p><p id="Par24">The differences in the species inventory we found compared to Van den Berg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] may be caused by social or medical factors, such as the incidence of certain diseases for which our newly recorded plants are used for healing. For example, the prevalence of diabetes in Brazilian adults has increased since the 1980&#x02019;s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>], and both <italic>Momordica charantia</italic> and <italic>Bauhinia</italic> species are employed to treat it in Brazil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. <italic>Bauhinia</italic> species are also used to treat high cholesterol, kidney diseases, and high blood pressure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Although recovered by our survey, these plants were not documented before at the VOP, most likely due to their absence or lack of popularity during the time frame of the previous survey [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Furthermore, differences in plant inventory, especially the higher proportion of introduced species in our study compared to Van den Berg&#x02019;s 1960&#x02013;1980&#x02019;s study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], may be influenced by environmental factors. Forest degradation and deforestation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>] caused by logging [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], cattle ranching [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>], and fires [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>] prompt a reduction in the availability of medicinal and native hardwood species, pushing a demand for introduced medicinal species to treat human diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. However, the most popular medicinal species in Bel&#x000e9;m listed by Shanley and Luz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] partly overlap with our survey, but also partly with Van den Berg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. This implies that it is yet unknown what the impacts of deforestation are on the availability of medicinal plants at the VOP.</p><p id="Par25">Van den Berg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] initiated her market study in 1965, and it continued for two decades over a time span in which there was more intact rainforest habitat compared to the present [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. However, our shorter study resulted in a more diverse medicinal plant species composition. We attribute this variation to our different methodological approaches due to our differing aims: while her aim was to document the most frequently occurring species, our aim was to find out the overall medicinal species diversity of the market. Because of these different approaches, a direct comparison of the species composition between studies remains problematic. However, this is inherent to studying ethnobotanical inventories over time and space [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. When comparing such historical ethnobotanical data, the only manner to overcome disparities in historical survey quality across studies is to clearly acknowledge differences in methodology. Our study highlights the importance of repeating market surveys, the necessity of establishing standard methodologies, and the exact documentation of the applied methodologies to ensure comparable results in future studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Plant names preserved</title><p id="Par26">Of the species our survey shared with Van den Berg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], the majority of vernacular names overlapped, indicating that there has been little change in names over three decades at the VOP. The small proportion that did not overlap could, again, be related to shifts in health perceptions and the occurrence of diseases over time. For example, in our study <italic>Cissus verticillata</italic> was called, among other names, <italic>insulina</italic>, which could be due to a higher occurrence of diabetes in Bel&#x000e9;m than at the time of Van den Berg&#x02019;s study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. However, such differences in associated names were minor. This is in line with our expectations, as plant names tend to present a remarkable continuity over time, even for centuries, as was previously found in Brazil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] and neighboring Suriname [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. For example, <italic>Acmella oleracea</italic> was named <italic>jambu</italic> in our survey, and we traced back this name to circa 375&#x02009;years ago in the <italic>Historia Naturalis Brasiliae</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], where it was documented for the same species, in a slightly different spelling (<italic>nhamb&#x000ed;</italic> and <italic>nhambu</italic>).</p><p id="Par27">Substantial transformations in social and environmental factors are needed for plant names to change. Migration plays a large role, as migrants usually bring along their own language, plant uses, and cultural elements, including words for plants that may later be included in the dominant language [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. In Tanzania, vernacular plant names at urban markets changed as a result of the migration from rural to urban centers of people with different cultural and lingual backgrounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Apparently, Bel&#x000e9;m&#x02019;s cultural and linguistic context and its natural surroundings have not changed enough in the past decades to stimulate large shifts in vernacular plant names. Even though Bel&#x000e9;m is a large and expanding city, its surroundings are still inhabited by peoples who have valued and traded in these herbal medicines in the past decades. Their ethnobotanical knowledge of medicinal plants, including vernacular names, is an essential element to their survival and a source of income. Thus, as people worked with these medicinal plants consistently over the past decades, and languages remained the same, it resulted in the preservation of these vernacular names.</p><p id="Par28">Regarding presently recorded names of species, of which the species were not recorded previously at VOP, a broader analysis of names, involving ethnobotanical surveys in and around Par&#x000e1;, could further confirm or refute our results on long-term preservation of plant names in the area.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Language origins</title><p id="Par29">The largest part of the vernacular plant names at this Amazonian market bore names of Portuguese origin. For example, the vernacular name <italic>arruda</italic> (<italic>Ruta graveolens</italic>) is of Portuguese origin, and the species is native to the Mediterranean region where it is embedded in the local plant pharmacopeia and also used against the &#x0201c;evil eye&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. We noticed this that several vendors at the VOP wore a sprig of <italic>arruda</italic> to protect against the &#x0201c;evil eye,&#x0201d; an interesting usage also commonly found in Bahia among Candombl&#x000e9; practitioners [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Bussmann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] also found that most plants sold at markets in Colombia, Bolivia, and Peru have mostly Spanish names. However, in northern Peru, Bussmann and Sharon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] found that Spanish names were mainly used for introduced and coastal plant species whereas plants from the montane forests were often referred to by their indigenous name. In our case, there were relatively few plants of European origin at the VOP market and most plants with Portuguese vernacular names were native Brazilian species, such as, <italic>Mansoa alliacea</italic>, called <italic>cip&#x000f3; de alho</italic> (garlic vine).</p><p id="Par30">The second largest group of vernacular names had a Tupi origin. Names like <italic>caj&#x000fa;</italic>, <italic>tapereba</italic>, <italic>bu&#x000e7;u</italic>, <italic>sicuriju</italic>, <italic>jambu</italic>, and <italic>tauari</italic> reflect an acquisition of indigenous words in the Brazilian lexicon for living organisms found in the natural world, also evidenced by the native and especially Amazonian plants that were sold at the market. Portuguese-speaking people have inhabited the Bel&#x000e9;m area since the seventeenth century, and their language gradually became the official language [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Nevertheless, Tupinamb&#x000e1; indigenous people were still present around Bel&#x000e9;m during the turn of the twentieth century [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>], and Tupi, Tupinamb&#x000e1;, and <italic>l&#x000ed;ngua geral</italic> (a mix of Tupi and Portuguese which served as lingua franca in the region) were spoken in Par&#x000e1; up until the nineteenth or twentieth centuries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>], alongside various other spoken languages also belonging to the Tupi-Guarani language family [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. This indicates that while the Portuguese-speaking peoples that inhabited the area mainly used Portuguese words to describe the natural world, they also relied upon indigenous Tupi names to some degree. This indigenous influence is not only reflected in the vernacular plant names at the VOP and the number of native species, but also in medicinal and religious plant uses. For example, the thin papery inner bark of <italic>Couratari guianensis</italic> (<italic>tauari</italic>), whose presence in Bel&#x000e9;m and surroundings was not previously documented, is used during Amazonian indigenous and Afro-Brazilian ceremonies as tobacco paper to roll ritual cigars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]. We also found combinations of Tupi and Portuguese names, such as <italic>pi&#x000e3;o-paje</italic> (<italic>Jatropha podagrica</italic> Hook.) and <italic>jurema preta</italic> (<italic>Mimosa tenuiflora</italic> (Willd.) Poir.). These are prime examples of names shaped by cultural exchange among people from different cultural and linguistic backgrounds in the area.</p><p id="Par31">We found a few vernacular names that had sub-Saharan African origins. Two of these directly refer to Africa: <italic>alecrim-de-Angola</italic> (<italic>Vitex agnus-castus</italic>), native to the Mediterranean region, and <italic>manjerona-de-Angola</italic> (<italic>Lippia thymoides</italic>), native to Brazil. The term Angola comes originally from Kimbundu, a Bantu language spoken in Angola, and it etymologically refers to a country of people from the Bantu linguistic group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. This word was used in the past by European traders to indicate the western coastline of Central Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. Although it is unclear when <italic>alecrim-de-Angola</italic> entered into Portuguese vocabulary, <italic>V. agnus-castus</italic> is used in Afro-Brazilian ceremonies in baths, as in the <italic>Banho de S&#x000e3;o Jo&#x000e3;o</italic> (bath of Saint John), an Afro-Brazilian ritual during the commemoration of St. John in Bel&#x000e9;m [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par32">Further, the vernacular name <italic>manjerona-de-Angola</italic> has been documented before in Bel&#x000e9;m, but associated with <italic>Origanum majorana</italic> L. instead of <italic>Lippia thymoides</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. A closely related plant, <italic>Lippia multiflora</italic> Moldenke, is used as medicine and in rituals along the western coast of Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. We suggest that <italic>L. multiflora</italic> was replaced in use by <italic>L. thymoides</italic> in Bel&#x000e9;m, and it is possibly used in Afro-Brazilian ceremonies.</p><p id="Par33">The last vernacular name with an African etymology, <italic>tapete de Oxal&#x000e1;</italic> (rug of Oxal&#x000e1; in English, <italic>Episcia cupreata</italic>), is also used in other parts of Brazil for other plant species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Oxal&#x000e1; is a Candombl&#x000e9; deity and has a West African etymology, but it is unknown when and how this name was introduced into the Brazilian Portuguese vocabulary [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], and therefore how and by whom <italic>Episcia cupreata</italic> was first associated with this deity.</p><p id="Par34">Thus, contrary to our expectation, we found very few vernacular names of medicinal and ritual plants sold at the Ver-o-Peso with African-derived origins. Yet, many of the plants we documented at the VOP with Portuguese and Tupi vernacular names, including African and non-African species, are used in rituals and ceremonies performed by followers of Afro-Brazilian religions, like Candombl&#x000e9; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. Other areas in Brazil, for instance in the northeast, where the Afro-Brazilian population is larger and may have experienced less difficulty in preserving Yoruba and Kikongo language elements, may exhibit other vernacular plant name patterns, including more African-derived plant names [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. So, while we documented only a few plant names of African origin, several plants sold at the VOP were associated with ritual uses that were influenced by Afro-Brazilians. These findings may give us a glance into history: enslaved Africans who were brought to Brazil and arrived in the area of Bel&#x000e9;m, and later Afro-Brazilians faced more difficulties in retaining their language, possibly because they were in fewer numbers than Portuguese and Tupi-speaking peoples. However, they were clearly able to keep their knowledge on plant uses alive and to adjust their ceremonial and ritualistic customs to the new plants encountered in Brazil.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par35">A great variety of medicinal plant species, mainly of Amazonian origin, is sold at the medicinal plant stalls of the VOP. Just 30 of the 126 plant species we encountered overlapped with Van den Berg&#x02019;s earlier market survey [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], and we reported a larger number of species and vernacular names not previously recorded at VOP. Also, there was a greater number of introduced species than in 1984 (Van den Berg); however, if this is due to changed environmental factors or to differences in methodologies remains unclear. In the case of vernacular names, we found that vernacular names of plants did not change much in the last three decades. Furthermore, the diverse origin of vernacular plant names reflects how the need for words to describe natural phenomena in the colonized and foreign land impelled Portuguese-speaking peoples to use their own reference words to name native Brazilian plants, but not without taking up several Tupi plant names. Although we only found a few plants with African-derived names, African heritage was not that much embedded in terms of language, but in associated ceremonial uses. In summary, the species sold at the VOP and their vernacular names, as well as the uses associated with these species found in literature, attest to the fact that Bel&#x000e9;m harbors an intricate syncretism of ethnobotanical knowledge of indigenous, Afro-Brazilian and European origin.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><sec id="Sec15"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13002_2021_433_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1.</bold> Geographic distribution and current status in Brazil. Description: Additional information on the geographic distribution and current status of medicinal and ritual plants found at the Ver-o-Peso in 2018.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>VOP</term><def><p id="Par5">The Ver-o-Peso market</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MG</term><def><p id="Par6">Herbarium of the Museu Paraense Emilio Goeldi</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>L</term><def><p id="Par7">Herbarium of Naturalis Biodiversity Center</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GBIF</term><def><p id="Par8">Global Biodiversity Information Facility website [24]</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank all the <italic>erveiras</italic> and <italic>erveiros</italic> who participated in this study. We thank M&#x000e1;rlia Coelho-Ferreira for giving us access to the Museu Paraense Emilio Goeldi Herbarium. Also, other staff of the Museu Paraense Emilio Goeldi, especially M&#x000e1;rio Rosa dos Santos, F&#x000e1;tima Lopes Almeida, Paula Oliveira, and Pedro L. Viana for their botanical expertise and caring for our herbarium vouchers. Jason Irving joined us on a couple of market surveys, which we greatly appreciated. Additionally, we would like to thank all the staff at the Naturalis Herbarium in Leiden for their botanical expertise, especially Paul Maas, and Roxali Bijmoer for making the collection available to us. The map was kindly made by Corn&#x000e9; van der Linden&#x000a0;and&#x000a0;Janine Herterich. Lastly, we thank David Barick for his helpful feedback on a previous version of this manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>IPG, MAR, MF, and TvA designed the study; IPG and MAR conducted the fieldwork; IPG analyzed the data and wrote the manuscript. All authors read, corrected, and approved the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was funded by the Alberta Mennega Stichting, Naturalis Biodiversity Center, and by the European Research Council (ERC) Horizon 2020 Research and Innovation Programme Project <italic>BRASILIAE: Indigenous Knowledge in the Making of Science: Historia Naturalis Brasiliae (1648)</italic> (Agreement No. 715423). None of these funds had involvement in the collection, analysis, and interpretation of data, or on the publishing of the results.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets used during the current study are included in this published article and its additional information files. Voucher specimens of plants are stored in the herbarium of Museu Paraense Em&#x000ed;lio Goeldi. Photos of plants are available from the first author on request.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par36">All work conducted was carried out under the stipulations of the ISE Code of Ethics (2006). The individual prior informed consent was obtained from all sellers before buying their specimens. Prior to buying the specimens, we introduced ourselves in Portuguese to the vendors, explained the framework of this research project, and made clear that we were collecting medicinal plants for the Herbarium of the Museu Paraense Emilio Goeldi (MG).</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par37">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par38">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van den Berg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ver-o-peso: the ethnobotany of an Amazonian market</article-title><source>Adv Econ Bot</source><year>1984</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>149</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mac&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidaurre</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants commercialized in the markets of La Paz and El Alto, Bolivia</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2005</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2004.11.022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15707774?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15707774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tinitana</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Romer-Benavides</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>De la Cruz</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo-de-Sanayana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants sold at traditional markets in southern Ecuador</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>29</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-016-0100-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27380631?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27380631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kasper-Pakosz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietras</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00141;uczaj</surname><given-names>&#x00141;</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wild and native plants and mushrooms sold in the open-air markets of south-eastern Poland</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>45</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-016-0117-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27717395?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27717395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bussmann</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Paniagua Zambrana</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Astonishing diversity &#x02013; the medicinal plant markets of Bogot&#x000e1;, Colombia</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>43</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-018-0241-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29925407?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29925407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agra</surname><given-names>MDF</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bas&#x000ed;lio</surname><given-names>IJLD</given-names></name><name><surname>De Freitas</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa-Filho</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survey of medicinal plants used in the region Northeast of Brazil</article-title><source>Rev Bras Farmacogn</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>472</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-695X2008000300023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brand&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>MGL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosenza</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in the trade in native medicinal plants in Brazilian public markets</article-title><source>Environ Monit Assess</source><year>2013</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>7013</fpage><lpage>7023</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10661-013-3081-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23322507?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23322507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furtado Santos</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coelho-Ferreira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>PGC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Etnobot&#x000e2;nica de plantas medicinais em mercados p&#x000fa;blicos da Regi&#x000e3;o Metropolitana de Bel&#x000e9;m do Par&#x000e1;, Brasil</article-title><source>Biota Amaz&#x000f4;nia</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van den Berg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MHL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotany of a traditional ablution in Par&#x000e1;, Brazil</article-title><source>Boletim do Museu Paraense Em&#x000ed;lio Goeldi Bot&#x000e3;nica</source><year>1986</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>218</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Amorim</surname><given-names>ELC</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>LVF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucena</surname><given-names>RFP</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobiological research in public markets</article-title><source>Methods and techniques in ethnobiology and ethnoecology</source><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>378</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Amorim</surname><given-names>ELC</given-names></name><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local markets and medicinal plant commerce: a review with emphasis on Brazil</article-title><source>Econ Bot</source><year>2010</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12231-010-9132-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bussmann</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shadows of the colonial past &#x02013; diverging plant use in Northern Peru and Southern Ecuador</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-5-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19187546?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19187546</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bussmann</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Paniagua Zambrana</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>No consensus in &#x0201c;traditional&#x0201d; medicine &#x02013; medicinal plants ant their uses in the markets of Bogot&#x000e1; (Colombia), La Paz/El Alto (Bolivia) and Trujillo/Chiclayo (Per&#x000fa;)</article-title><source>Indian J Tradit Knowl</source><year>2018</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>498</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alc&#x000e1;ntara Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pombo Geertsma</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Fran&#x000e7;ozo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Andel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Marcgrave and Piso&#x02019;s plants for sale: the presence of plant species and names from the Historia Naturalis Brasiliae (1648) in contemporary Brazilian markets</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2020</year><volume>259</volume><fpage>112911</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2020.112911</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32389855?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32389855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bussmann</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Paniagua Zambrana</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Moya Huanca</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changing markets &#x02013; medicinal plants in the markets of La Paz and El Alto, Bolivia</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2016</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2016.07.074</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27477298?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27477298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>de Amorim</surname><given-names>ELC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal and magic plants from a public market in northeastern Brazil</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2007</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2006.09.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17056216?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17056216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otieno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Abihudi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Veldman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nahashon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Andel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>De Boer</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vernacular dominance in folk taxonomy: a case study of ethnospecies in medicinal plant trade in Tanzania</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-11-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25971902?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25971902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>PGC</given-names></name><name><surname>Coelho-Ferreira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Silva Santos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspectives on medicinal plants in public markets across the Amazon: a review</article-title><source>Econ Bot</source><year>2016</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12231-016-9338-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shanley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Luz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impacts of forest degradation on medicinal plant use and implications for health care in eastern Amazonia</article-title><source>BioScience</source><year>2003</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1641/0006-3568(2003)053[0573:TIOFDO]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bitencourt</surname><given-names>BLG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>PGC</given-names></name><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Com&#x000e9;rcio e uso de plantas e animais de import&#x000e2;ncia m&#x000e1;gico-religiosa e medicinal no mercado p&#x000fa;blico do Guam&#x000e1;, Bel&#x000e9;m do Par&#x000e1;</article-title><source>Rev FSA</source><year>2014</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12819/2014.11.3.5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furtado Santos</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Plantas medicinais em feiras e mercados p&#x000fa;blicos da regi&#x000e3;o metropolitana de Bel&#x000e9;m do Par&#x000e1;, Brasil [MSc Thesis]</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>Bel&#x000e9;m</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Universidade Federal Rural da Amaz&#x000f4;nia and Museu Paraense Em&#x000ed;lio Goeldi</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Andel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobreff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical notes from Daniel Rolander&#x02019;s Diarium Surinamicum (1754-1756): are these plants still used in Suriname today?</article-title><source>Taxon</source><year>2012</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>852</fpage><lpage>863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/tax.614010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Costa Lima</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dantas de Almeida</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Erveiros (os) do Ver-o-Peso, em Bel&#x000e9;m do Par&#x000e1;: um estudo etnogr&#x000e1;fico</article-title><source>Revista &#x000c1;frica e Africanidades</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>22</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stessuk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A implanta&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da l&#x000ed;ngua portuguesa no Brasil, em contato com o tupi antigo e as l&#x000ed;nguas africanas</article-title><source>Todas as Letras</source><year>2006</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>102</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voeks</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Sacred leaves of Candombl&#x000e9;: African magic, medicine, and religion in Brazil</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Austin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Texas Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Andel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Van&#x02019;t Klooster</surname><given-names>CIEA</given-names></name><name><surname>Quiroz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Towns</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruysschaert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Berg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local plant names reveal that enslaved Africans recognized substantial parts of the New World flora</article-title><source>P Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>5346</fpage><lpage>5353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1418836111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Andel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>African names for American plants</article-title><source>Am Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1511/2015.115.268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrreiro</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>African gene flow to North Brazil as revealed by HBB*S gene haplotype analysis</article-title><source>Am J Hum Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajhb.20467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16378338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shanley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Luz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Swingland</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The faint promise of a distant market: a survey of Bel&#x000e9;m&#x02019;s trade in non-timber forest products</article-title><source>Biodivers Conserv</source><year>2002</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1015556508925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>ISE: International Society of Ethnobiology</collab></person-group><source>ISE Code of Ethics (with 2008 additions)</source><year>2006</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Global Biodiversity Information Facility. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gbif.org/">https://www.gbif.org/</ext-link>. Accessed 24 July 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Flora do Brasil 2020 Online Checklist. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://floradobrasil.jbrj.gov.br">http://floradobrasil.jbrj.gov.br</ext-link>. Accessed 24 July 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tropicos Database. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tropicos.org/">http://www.tropicos.org/</ext-link>. Accessed 22 July 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>LHC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genus Ocimum L. (Lamiaceae) in North-East Brazil</article-title><source>An Jardin Bot Madrid</source><year>1998</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>64</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorenzi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>FJA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Plantas medicinais no Brasil: Nativas e ex&#x000f3;ticas</source><year>2008</year><edition>2</edition><publisher-loc>Nova Odessa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Instituto Plantarum de Estudos da Flora</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Andel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruysschaert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Medicinale en rituele planten van Suriname</source><year>2011</year><edition>1</edition><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>KIT Publishers</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maia</surname><given-names>JGS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoghbi</surname><given-names>MGB</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>EHA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Plantas arom&#x000e1;ticas na Amaz&#x000f4;nia e seus &#x000f3;leos essenciais</source><year>2001</year><publisher-loc>Bel&#x000e9;m</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Museu Paraense Em&#x000ed;lio Goeldi</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva Rocha</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gra&#x000e7;as Bichara Zoghbi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazar&#x000e9; de Carmo Basto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Coelho-Ferreira</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves Jantim</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Cat&#x000e1;logo da flora da Reserva Extravista Chocoar&#x000e9; - Mato Grosso: Santar&#x000e9;m Novo-Par&#x000e1;</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Bel&#x000e9;m</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Museu Paraense Em&#x000ed;lio Goeldi</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavalcante</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><source>Frutas comest&#x000ed;veis na Amaz&#x000f4;nia</source><year>2010</year><edition>7</edition><publisher-loc>Bel&#x000e9;m</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Museu Paraense Em&#x000ed;lio Goeldi</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van den Berg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Plantas medicinais na Amazonia: contribui&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o ao seu conhecimento sistem&#x000e1;tico</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Bel&#x000e9;m</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Museu Paraense Em&#x000ee;lio Goeldi</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peckolt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Peckolt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><source>Hist&#x000f3;ria das plantas uteis e medicinais do Brasil</source><year>2016</year><edition>1</edition><publisher-loc>Belo Horizonte</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Fino Tra&#x000e7;o</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Plant List: a working list of all plant species. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.theplantlist.org/">http://www.theplantlist.org/</ext-link>. Accessed 27 Aug 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corriente</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Los arabismos y otras voces medio-orientales del dicion&#x000e1;rio houaiss da l&#x000ed;ngua portuguesa</article-title><source>Filologia e Lingu&#x000ed;stica Portuguesa</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11606/issn.2176-9419.v15ispep69-184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>EDA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Dicion&#x000e1;rio tupi antigo: a l&#x000ed;ngua ind&#x000ed;gena cl&#x000e1;ssica do Brasil: vocabul&#x000e1;rio portugu&#x000ea;s-tupi e dicion&#x000e1;rio tupi-portugu&#x000ea;s, tupinismos no portugu&#x000ea;s do Brasil, etimologias de top&#x000f4;nimos e antrop&#x000f4;nimos de origem tupi</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>S&#x000e3;o Paulo</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Global Editora</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">DATAPLAMT, Banco de dados e amostras de plantas arom&#x000e1;ticas, medicinais e t&#x000f3;xicas/UFMG. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dataplamt.org.br">http://www.dataplamt.org.br</ext-link>. Accessed 29 Nov 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dicion&#x000e1;rio ilustrado Tupi Guarani. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dicionariotupiguarani.com.br">https://www.dicionariotupiguarani.com.br</ext-link>. Accessed 28 Nov 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Michaelis Dicion&#x000e1;rio Brasileiro da L&#x000ed;ngua Portuguesa. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://michaelis.uol.com.br/moderno-portugues/busca/portugues-brasileiro">https://michaelis.uol.com.br/moderno-portugues/busca/portugues-brasileiro</ext-link>. Accessed 28 Nov 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Online Etymology Dictionary. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.etymonline.com">www.etymonline.com</ext-link>. Accessed 31 Aug 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sebba</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbacho</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name></person-group><source>O l&#x000e9;xico &#x000e1;rabe na l&#x000ed;ngua portuguesa</source><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>FCB</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>EPM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vocabul&#x000e1;rio do escritor Ant&#x000f4;nio Juraci Siqueira</article-title><source>RELACult</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>2</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abreu</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilera</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A influ&#x000ea;ncia da l&#x000ed;ngua &#x000e1;rabe no portugu&#x000ea;s brasileiro: a contribui&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o dos escravos africanus e da imigra&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o libanesa</article-title><source>Entretextos, Londrina</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tropical Plant Database. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://tropical.theferns.info">https://tropical.theferns.info</ext-link>. Accessed 22 July 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Missouri Botanical Garden Plant Finder. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.missouribotanicalgarden.org/PlantFinder/">www.missouribotanicalgarden.org/PlantFinder/</ext-link>. Accessed 22 July 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">PROTA4U. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.prota4u.org/database/">www.prota4u.org/database/</ext-link>. Accessed 18 Dec 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">PROSEA. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.prota4u.org/prosea/">www.prota4u.org/prosea/</ext-link>. Accessed 19 Dec 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Andel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Velden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reijers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The &#x02018;Botanical Gardens of the Dispossessed&#x02019; revisited: richness and significance of Old World crops grown by Suriname Maroons</article-title><source>Genet Resour Crop Ev</source><year>2016</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>710</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Flora of China. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.efloras.org/flora_page.aspx?flora_id=2">www.efloras.org/flora_page.aspx?flora_id=2</ext-link>. Accessed 24 July 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kew Science Plants of the World online. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://powo.science.kew.org/">http://powo.science.kew.org/</ext-link>. Accessed 24 July 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Catalogue of Life Annual Checklist. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.catalogueoflife.org/annual-checklist/2019/">www.catalogueoflife.org/annual-checklist/2019/</ext-link>. Accessed 20 Apr 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Naturalis Bioportal. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bioportal.naturalis.nl/">https://bioportal.naturalis.nl/</ext-link>. Accessed 1 Nov 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Del Arco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Arco</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapia-Cortese</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Blancas</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What have we forgotten? Returning data from ethnobiological research to local communities</article-title><source>Bioremediat Biodivers Bioavail</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>27</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiersema</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>World economic plants: a standard reference</source><year>1999</year><publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Babu</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jadhav</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira da Silva</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Origin, history and domestication of pomegranate</article-title><source>Fruit Veg Cereal Sci Biotechnol</source><year>2010</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helo</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cureau</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cop&#x000ea;s</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaan</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of diabetes in Brazil over time: a systematic review with meta-analysis</article-title><source>Diabetol Metab Syndr</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>65</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13098-016-0181-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27610204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>CM</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Siqueira</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Sales</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Numata</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochrane</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ten-year landsat classification of deforestation and forest degradation in the Brazilian Amazon</article-title><source>Remote Sens</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>5493</fpage><lpage>5513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/rs5115493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asner</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Broadbent</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>PJC</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>JNM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Condition and fate of logged forests in the Brazilian Amazon</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>12947</fpage><lpage>12950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0604093103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16901980?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16901980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deforestation and cattle ranching in the Brazilian Amazon: external capital and household processes</article-title><source>World Dev</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0305-750X(99)00149-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arag&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>LEOC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimabukuro</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The incidence of fire in Amazonian forests with implications for REDD</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2010</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>1275</fpage><lpage>1278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1186925</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20522775?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20522775</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ometto</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousa-Neto</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Tejada</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsberg</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Artaxo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Land use, land cover and land use change in the Brazilian Amazon (1960-2013)</article-title><source>Interactions between biosphere, atmosphere and human land use in the Amazon Basin, Ecological Studies 227</source><year>2016</year><publisher-loc>Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>383</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>De Natale</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Appetiti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Aliotta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Touwaide</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Continuity and change in the Mediterranean medical tradition: Ruta spp. (rutaceae) in Hippocratic medicine and present practices</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2008</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2007.12.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18276094?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18276094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>Hist&#x000f3;ria do Par&#x000e1;</source><year>1963</year><publisher-loc>Bel&#x000e9;m</publisher-loc><publisher-name>UFPA</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Instituto do Patrim&#x000f4;nio Hist&#x000f3;rico e Art&#x000ed;stico Nacional (2017). Hist&#x000f3;ria - Arraial do Cabo (RJ). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://portal.iphan.gov.br/pagina/detalhes/1679/">http://portal.iphan.gov.br/pagina/detalhes/1679/</ext-link>. Acessed 28 Sept 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the influence of indigenous languages on Brazilian Portuguese</article-title><source>DELTA</source><year>2014</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0102-445067692919987352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Glottolog 4.2.1. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/awet1245">https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/awet1245</ext-link>. Accessed 2 Apr 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From gift of the deities to scourge among humans</article-title><source>The master plant: tobacco in lowland South America</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>London, New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Bloomsbury</publisher-name><fpage>xv</fpage><lpage>xiv</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nomes de poss&#x000ed;vel origem africana na topon&#x000ed;mia de minas gerais: pressupostos te&#x000f3;ricos e metodol&#x000f3;gicos da pesquisa topon&#x000ed;mica</article-title><source>Cadernos do CNLF, Rio de Janeiro</source><year>2011</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2075</fpage><lpage>2095</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Postma</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Dutch in the Atlantic Slave Trade 1600-1815</source><year>1992</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Andel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Myren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Onselen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ghana&#x02019;s herbal market</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2012</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2012.01.028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22306470?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22306470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Quiroz D. Do not fear the supernatural! The relevance of ritual plant use for traditional culture, nature conservation, and human health in western Africa. PhD thesis/ Wageningen: Wageningen University; 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stalcup M. Plantas de uso medicinal ou ritual numa feira livre no Rio de Janeiro, Brasil [MSc Thesis]. Rio de Janeiro: Universidade Federal de Rio de Janeiro; 2000.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of medicinal plants by the cultural descendants of African people in Brazil</article-title><source>Acta Farmaceutica Bonaerense</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>144</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>