<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Contrary to previous studies, the current research work has MaxEnt to predict the potential global climatic suitability of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>zonata</italic> under current and four RCPs for the year 2050 using occurrence data of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>zonata</italic>, and eight bioclimatic variables. MaxEnt was selected because several studies have recommended its use in predicting potential distribution of invasive species [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The present study took into consideration the recommendations raised by Ni et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] emphasizing the need to incorporate other factors such as host availability and dispersal capacity of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>zonata</italic> in future modeling exercises. These suggestions by Ni et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] have been previously supported by other authors [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], but this has rarely been implemented. In the present study, these factors were considered to gain better understanding of a more precise overall habitat suitability that would allow for the continual survival and proliferation of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>zonata</italic>. In this regard, the Spatial Production Allocation Model (MapSPAM) dataset was used to determine areas where 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>zonata</italic> popular host plants are being grown to understand its potential to invade them [
 <xref rid="pone.0243047.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. These areas where the host plants are being grown were aggregated at global level and merged with the output of MaxEnt using spatial analysis tools. Further, a simple spread model to predict the potential natural dispersal of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>zonata</italic> from source points using the Gaussian dispersal kernel was developed. To improve on the precision of the potential climatic suitability of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>zonata</italic> in MaxEnt, we ensured that our models combined both exotic and native occurrence records of the fruit fly.
</p>
