<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In addition, modification of lignocellulosic fibers is studied to improve hydrophobicity and compatibility of the lignocellulosic fiber-matrix with thermal treatment or ultrasonic. To improve the properties and fiber/matrix adhesion of the bioplastics, wheat straw fibers/PHBV bioplastics were fabricated. Wheat straw fibers were treated by torrefaction treatment to increase their hydrophobicity. SEM observations revealed that an excellent fiber/matrix compatibility was achieved in the resulting biocomposites. The crystallinity and molecular weight of the bioplastics remained constant and the crystallization of PHBV was facilitated by the introduction of torrefied fibers compared to untreated fibers. The mechanical properties of wheat straw fiber/PHBV biocomposites were only affected by the 30 wt % of torrefied fibers, which displayed increased rigidity. A 30% decrease in water vapor permeability was observed with 20 wt % torrefied fiber contents attributed to the hydrophobic nature of fibers and improvement of fiber/matrix adhesion [
 <xref rid="B150-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">150</xref>]. The chemical composition of the fibers does not change significantly in physical treatments. Therefore, as mechanical bonding between the matrix and the fiber increased, the adhesion between them is improved [
 <xref rid="B3-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Water hyacinth fiber with 10% volume fraction was employed to reinforce the biocomposites obtained from tapioca starch-based plastics. During gelatinization, the biocomposites were cast into a glass plate then placed in an ultrasonic bath. After vibrated with ultrasound for 30 min, the biocomposites with optimal properties can be produced. Tensile modulus and tensile strength increased by 108% and 83% after this vibration. At the same time, water resistance of the bioplastics increased by 25% and achieved a maximum [
 <xref rid="B151-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">151</xref>]. The empty fruit bunch fibers and tapioca starch were blended to prepare the bioplastics. After the gelatinization of the biocomposites, the solution was cast into a glass plate and then vibrated in an ultrasonic bath with 250 watts and 40 kHz in different duration for 0, 15, 30, 60 min, respectively. The results demonstrated the characterization of the biocomposites has been influenced by the vibration during gelatinization. The different fracture surface of the tensile sample was revealed by SEM studies. For vibration duration of 60 min, strain was decreased to 35.1%, meanwhile tensile modulus and tensile strength increased to 277.4 and 64.4%, respectively, compared to untreated one. Water uptake of the untreated biocomposites was higher than that of the vibrated one. FT-IR and XRD of the biocomposites have changed due to various vibration duration [
 <xref rid="B152-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">152</xref>].
</p>
