<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To our knowledge, the present study has investigated for the first time the neuroprotective potential of various 
 <italic>Salvia fruticosa</italic> extracts, in relation to A
 <italic>β</italic>-induced neurotoxicity. The 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> AD model employed in this study was SH-SY5Y human bone marrow neuroblastoma cells treated with A
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>25–35</sub> peptides. A
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>25–35</sub> is the shortest fragment generated 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> from the proteolysis of A
 <italic>β</italic>, which at the same time maintains the toxicity of the larger peptides [
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In conjunction with SH-SY5Y cells, A
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>25–35</sub> peptides have been used extensively to assess the neuroprotective effects of various plant extracts and plant-derived substances [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>–
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The solvents used for the SF extracts generation were of increasing polarity: petroleum ether (nonpolar), dichloromethane (moderately polar), and methanol (polar). Since the chemical complexity of plant extracts, polarity, different functional groups, and chemical behaviour may lead to scattered results due to the antioxidant test employed [
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], the evaluation of the antioxidant activity of the extracts was examined with more than one method: the DPPH
 <sup>•</sup> assay [
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] and the FRAP antioxidant power assay [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The FRAP assay appears to be simple, attractive, and potentially useful test, due to inexpensive reagents, highly reproductive results, and fast procedures. On the other hand, the DPPH
 <sup>•</sup> radical scavenging activity assay is capable of the evaluation of the antioxidant potential of both hydrophilic and lipophilic compounds and can afford data on the reduction potential of the sample, even in cases where the structure of the electron donor is not known (e.g., plant extracts) [
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. In addition, the DCFDA assay was employed to assess the antioxidant capacity of the extracts in living cells [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].
</p>
