<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genetic analysis of resistant 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content> isolates showed a striking similarity with those commonly reported in clinical 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content> isolates. A recent analysis of the Dutch national resistance surveillance program, which included 640 azole-resistant 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content> isolates obtained from 508 patients, showed TR
 <sub>34</sub> and TR
 <sub>46</sub> mutations in 86% of resistant isolates (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Interestingly, some of the clinical isolates harbored polymorphisms in the 
 <italic>cyp51A</italic> gene that are similar to those found in the stockpiles, for instance, S297T in isolates harboring TR
 <sub>34</sub>/L98H. This observation supports a link between environmental resistance and human infection. However, it remains unclear how azole-resistant 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content> is transmitted from an environmental source to the patient and which proportion of clinical isolates can be traced to flower bulb hot spots. There are several observations that underscore the need to investigate transmission routes of resistant 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content>. First, the distribution of TR
 <sub>34</sub> and TR
 <sub>46</sub> mutations over the samples shows an opposite pattern in the stockpile and clinical isolates. While we found 83.7% TR
 <sub>46</sub> mutations in isolates obtained from the stockpiles, these mutations were concurrently found in only 17% of azole-resistant clinical 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content> isolates (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). This might suggest that other sources of azole-resistant 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content> play a greater role in transmission to humans or that there is certain selection for entrance to the lung. Conversely, the distribution of 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content> isolates in stockpiles and patients may also be asynchronously correlated. Furthermore, several studies have investigated the risk of bioaerosol exposure from composting facilities on human health, especially respiratory illnesses (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content> is a well-described and common component of bioaerosols and, thus, is considered a good indicator for bioaerosol emissions in epidemiological studies (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Although high 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content> aerial dispersal rates are found when turning compost heaps (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), epidemiologic studies find no evidence for a relation between bioaerosol exposure and hospital admissions for respiratory disease (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). To further understand the significance of azole-resistant 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content> in (flower bulb) compost and human infection, high-resolution genotyping of environmental and clinical 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content> isolates is needed. Such a study is under way, taking into account the geographic proximity to potential hot spots. In addition, the search for other hot spots in the environment needs to be continued.
</p>
