<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Over the preceding decade, more than 100 xanthones from lichen sources were identified [
 <xref rid="B95-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>], but only a limited number have been investigated for their bioactivities [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Particularly, chlorinated lichen xanthones have been found attractive for their antibacterial and antifungal activities [
 <xref rid="B96-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Based on these models, a series of novel chlorinated xanthones with different substitution patterns were prepared and evaluated for its antimicrobial activity potential [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The presence of chlorine at C-3 seems to have some influence on the antibacterial activity since 3-chloro-4,6-dimethoxy-1-methyl-9
 <italic>H</italic>-xanthen-9-one (
 <bold>28</bold>) showed promising antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>E. faecalis</italic> (ATCC 29212) and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC 29,213 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00431-f008">Figure 8</xref>). On the other hand, 2,7-dichloro-3,4,6-trimethoxy-1-methyl-9
 <italic>H</italic>-xanthen-9-one (
 <bold>29</bold>), with chlorine atoms at C-2 and C-7, exhibited potent antifungal activity suggesting that their joint presence may be required for this effect, similarly to the natural xanthone, thiophanic acid. Inspired by these results and in order to further extend the diversity of the library, our group also explored the potential of brominated xanthones as antimicrobial agents [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Although no antifungal activity was observed for the tested compounds, 1-(dibromomethyl)-3,4-dimethoxy-9
 <italic>H</italic>-xanthen-9-one (
 <bold>30</bold>) and 1-(dibromomethyl)-3,4,6-trimethoxy-9
 <italic>H</italic>-xanthen-9-one (
 <bold>31</bold>) exhibited antibacterial activity against all seven bacterial (including two multidrug-resistant) tested strains (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00431-f008">Figure 8</xref>). While the studied xanthones exhibited great potential as antibacterial (
 <bold>28</bold>, 
 <bold>30</bold> and 
 <bold>31</bold>) or antifungal (
 <bold>29</bold>) agents, the low solubility displayed by some derivatives limited further screenings. Nevertheless, these can be used in the future as models to improve drug-like properties. In the scope of the same study, other xanthone derivatives modified at C-1 (CH
 <sub>3</sub>, CHO, COOH, COOCH
 <sub>3</sub>, or NOH) were also synthesized and screened for their antimicrobial activity. However, none of the tested compounds showed relevant activity against the five fungal and seven bacterial (including two multidrug-resistant) strains tested.
</p>
