<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>UNA can be found in several parts of various plants used in traditional herbal medicines. According to previous studies, UNA can be extracted from fruits of 
 <italic>Crataegus Pinnatifida</italic> and 
 <italic>Malus baccata</italic> [
 <xref rid="B28-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In particular, UNA is one of the major compounds present in the ripened fruits of 
 <italic>Ziziphus jujuba</italic>, a main ingredient of traditional Chinese medicinal formula PHY906, which is used for adjuvant therapy of patients with cancer [
 <xref rid="B17-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. It was reported that resins from 
 <italic>Pistacia atlantica, Bursera delpechiana,</italic> and trees of the Dipterocarpaceae family contain triterpenoids, including UNA [
 <xref rid="B32-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. UNA is also found in the roots of 
 <italic>Toona sinensis</italic>, 
 <italic>Piper betle,</italic> and 
 <italic>Ficus microcarpa</italic> [
 <xref rid="B20-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Extraction of aerial parts of 
 <italic>Lantana camara</italic>, which was traditionally used for treatment of eczema, ulcers, rheumatism, and malaria, also resulted in isolation of UNA [
 <xref rid="B37-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. It is known that UNA can be obtained from the leaves of 
 <italic>Lantana tiliaefolia</italic> and 
 <italic>Rauvolfia vomitoria</italic> [
 <xref rid="B38-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Furthermore, UNA was isolated from a whole plant of 
 <italic>Catharanthus Roseus</italic> and 
 <italic>Dracocephalum komarovi,</italic> which are widely used as folk medicines in Asia, Europe, and African countries [
 <xref rid="B40-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. This extensive presence of UNA in medicinal herbs suggests that UNA itself can exert therapeutic potential against diseases such as cancer and infectious protozoa.
</p>
