<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Pomegranate oil (PGO) is primarily composed of triacylglycerol (TAG) molecules with punicic acid (9Z,11E,13Z-octadeca-9,11,13-trienoic acid) in which double bonds are in a conjugated form [
 <xref rid="B1-nutrients-11-00678" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. The non-conjugated form, α-linolenic acid (9Z,12Z,15Z-octadeca-9,12,15-trienoic acid), is usually found in most vegetable oils [
 <xref rid="B2-nutrients-11-00678" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-nutrients-11-00678" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Several studies have proposed that PGO containing high content of conjugated linolenic acid (CLn), such as punicic acid, may offer beneficial effects relating to inflammation and colon cancer [
 <xref rid="B4-nutrients-11-00678" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-nutrients-11-00678" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. However, the chemical nature of TAG in fats and oils can affect lipid bioavailability and digestibility. For example, it is known that both a shorter length and fewer double bonds in fatty acids promote the hydrolysis rate by pancreatic lipase [
 <xref rid="B6-nutrients-11-00678" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-nutrients-11-00678" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Arishima et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-nutrients-11-00678" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] also reported that the presence of behenic acid (C22:0) in TAG molecules slows a significant reduction of lipolysis rate. Further, in an in-vitro pancreatic lipase assay, more hydrolysis of non-conjugated linoleic acids (9Z,12Z-octadeca-9,12-dienoic acid) than that of the conjugated form of linoleic acids from TAG molecules has been observed [
 <xref rid="B9-nutrients-11-00678" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Because pancreatic lipase is known to have 
 <italic class="italic">sn</italic>-1,3 specificity relating to TAG molecules, TAG species that have different positional fatty acid compositions may induce different lipolysis rates. 
</p>
