<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rsbmt</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Revista da Sociedade Brasileira de Medicina Tropical</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0037-8682</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1678-9849</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Medicina Tropical - SBMT</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7747825</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0037-8682-0092-2020</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">00300</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Major Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Larvicidal activity of plants from Myrtaceae against <italic>Aedes
aegypti</italic> L. and <italic>Simulium pertinax</italic> Kollar
(Diptera)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>Vanessa Cristine de Souza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Lucena</surname><given-names>Luana Braz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Figueir&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>Ronaldo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2815-3725</contrib-id><name><surname>Vict&#x000f3;rio</surname><given-names>Cristiane Pimentel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label> Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Centro Universit&#x000e1;rio Estadual da Zona Oeste, Programa de
Mestrado em Ci&#x000ea;ncia e Tecnologia Ambiental, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brasil. </aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label> Universidade Castelo Branco, Centro Universit&#x000e1;rio de Volta Redonda,
Volta Redonda, RJ, Brasil. </aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label> Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Centro Universit&#x000e1;rio Estadual da Zona Oeste, Laborat&#x000f3;rio
de Pesquisa em Biotecnologia Ambiental, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brasil.</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Dra. Cristiane Pimentel Vict&#x000f3;rio.
<bold>e-mail</bold>: <email>cris.pvictor@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn2"><p>
<bold>Conflicts of Interest:</bold> The authors declare that they have no
conflicts of interest.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="fn3"><p>
<bold>Authors&#x02019; Contributions:</bold> VCSC and LBL: conducted literature
survey and performed experiments. They collected the plant materials,
extracted the metabolites, performed larvicidal bioassays, data acquisition,
and analysis; RF: developed the theoretical formalism for Diptera vectors,
collected vectors, performed statistical analysis, interpreted the
biological results, contributed to the final version of the manuscript, and
supervised the project; CPV: developed the theoretical formalism for the
phytochemistry of plants from Myrtaceae, collected plants, interpreted the
biological results, prepared the manuscript, contributed to the final
version of the manuscript, and supervised the project.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>54</volume><elocation-id>e00922020</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec><title>INTRODUCTION:</title><p> Despite their widespread usage, synthetic insecticides and larvicides are
harmful for controlling disease-causing mosquitoes owing to the development
of resistance. The leaves of <italic>Eugenia astringens</italic>,
<italic>Myrrhinium atropurpureum</italic>, and <italic>Neomitranthes
obscura</italic> were collected from Marambaia and Grumari restingas.
The safety and larvicidal efficacy of their extracts were tested against
<italic>Aedes (Stegomyia) aegypti</italic> L. and <italic>Simulium
(Chirostilbia) pertinax</italic> Kollar. </p></sec><sec><title>METHODS:</title><p> The dry leaves were subjected to static maceration extraction using 90%
methanol. <italic>A. aegypti</italic> and <italic>S. pertinax</italic>
larvae were exposed to 7.5, 12.5, and 25.0 &#x000b5;L/mL of the extracts (n= 30).
The larvicidal activity after 24 h and 48 h, and the mortality, were
determined. The median lethal concentration (CL<sub>50</sub>) was estimated
by a Finney's probit model. </p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS:</title><p>
<italic>M. atropurpureum</italic> and <italic>E. astringens</italic>
extracts exhibited the strongest larvicidal effects against <italic>A.
aegypti</italic>. <italic>M. atropurpureum</italic> extracts (25 &#x000b5;L/mL)
caused mortalities of over 50% and 100% after 24 h and 48 h, respectively
(CL<sub>50</sub> = 11.10 and 9.68 ppm, respectively). <italic>E.
astringens</italic> extracts (25 &#x000b5;L/mL) caused mortalities of 50% and
63.33% after 24 h and 48 h, respectively. High concentrations of <italic>N.
obscura</italic> extracts induced a maximum mortality of 46.66% in
<italic>A. aegypti</italic> larvae after 48 h (CL<sub>50</sub>= 25 ppm).
The larvae of <italic>S. pertinax</italic> showed 100% mortality following
exposure to all the plant extracts at all the tested concentrations after 24
h. </p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSIONS:</title><p> The extracts of <italic>M. atropurpuerum</italic> exhibited the strongest
larvicidal activity against <italic>A. aegypti</italic>. The larvae of
<italic>S. pertinax</italic> were sensitive to all the extracts at all
the tested concentrations.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords:</title><kwd>Alternative chemical control</kwd><kwd>Plant extracts</kwd><kwd>Larvicide</kwd><kwd>Mosquitocide</kwd><kwd>Plant natural products</kwd><kwd>Sandy coastal plains</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="35"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Dengue, yellow fever, zika, chikungunya, filariasis, onchocerciasis, and
mansonellosis are some of the diseases transmitted by mosquito vectors.
<italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> L. transmits different viruses that cause
diseases throughout the Americas, Southeast Asia, and Western Europe. These vectors
are also responsible for causing disorders that arise indirectly from viral
infections, including microcephaly and Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome. Globally, a million
people are affected by diseases transmitted by <italic>A. aegypti</italic> on an
annual basis, and this is most pronounced in summer<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>. The hematophagous species, <italic>Simulium pertinax</italic> Kollar, also
known as black flies or &#x0201c;borrachudos&#x0201d; in Brazil, is an pest of considerable concern
for both humans and domestic animals. Only a limited number of studies on Simuliidae
can be found in the literature. However, the simuliids proliferate uncontrollably in
some parts of the world, and cause a profound deterioration in the quality of life
by acting as vectors of pathogenic organisms, and as hematophagous pests of humans
and domestic animals<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>. However, some studies have reported that <italic>S. pertinax</italic> acts
as a bioindicator of moderately impacted streams<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>.</p><p>Mechanical control is the most common means of controlling mosquito vectors, and
comprises the elimination of the vector and its breeding sites, or the reduction of
mosquito-human contact. Another strategy involves biological control, which is based
on the use of predators or pathogens that potentially reduce the vector
population<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>. Apart from these strategies, synthetically-derived chemicals are also used
to kill the larval and adult stages of mosquito vectors<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>. For several decades, the use of synthetic insecticides has been a
widespread strategy for controlling disease-causing mosquitoes. However, the
prolonged and indiscriminate use of synthetic insecticides has resulted in the
development of resistance to these substances<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>. Insecticide resistance is currently a major threat to the control of
insects, including <italic>A. aegypti</italic>
<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref> and <italic>S. pertinax</italic>
<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>. Apart from the development of resistant mosquito populations, the use of
such insecticides increases environmental pollution and the risk of toxicity in
human beings, which are issues of increasing global concern. This necessitates the
development of natural substances that act at different stages of the life cycle of
insects, which comprises the egg, larva, pupa, and adult stages. Natural agents are
less toxic and safer than synthetic insecticides, and offer an alternative strategy
for vector control<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref>. Some studies have demonstrated that various species of plants possess
larvicidal and insecticidal potential. It is estimated that approximately 479
articles were published between 1968 and 2016, which evaluated the activity of
natural plant products against <italic>A. aegypti</italic>
<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref>. Amides, quinones, and terpenoids are active larvicidal compounds, and
represent the major natural substances responsible for controlling <italic>A.
aegypti</italic>
<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">
<sup><italic>10</italic></sup>
</xref>
<sup><italic>,</italic></sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">
<sup><italic>13</italic></sup>
</xref>. Biolarvicides, based on mosquitocidal toxins derived from strains of
<italic>Bacillus thuringiensis</italic> (Bt), are globally used on a large scale
for their pathogenicity and specificity against the larval stages of
<italic>S.</italic> sp.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref>.</p><p>Numerous species of plants from Myrtaceae are found in the slopes of the ombrophilous
forests or Atlantic forests, Amazon rainforest, Restinga, and Cerrado regions of
Brazil<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref>. For instance, the preserved area of Marambaia restinga in Rio de Janeiro
houses a wide diversity of plant species belonging to this family, and are present
in seven of the eleven plant formations defined in the restingas<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>17</sup>
</xref>. Numerous species are also found in Grumari restinga, which, despite being
located in an urban area and being subject to anthropic activity, still houses
remnants of the restinga<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>18</sup>
</xref>. Several species of plants from Myrtaceae are used for medicinal purposes,
including the treatment of gastrointestinal disorders, hemorrhagic conditions, and
infectious diseases, and it is thought that the underlying mechanism of action is
related to the astringent properties of the plants. The most commonly used plant
parts are the leaves, bark, and fruits<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref>. However, there is a scarcity of studies on their use and efficacy against
insect vectors<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>20</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>21</sup>
</xref>.</p><p>In this study, we therefore aimed to investigate the larvicidal activity of different
leaf extracts of plants from the Myrtaceae family as natural alternatives to
chemical insecticides. The use of plants from the Myrtaceae family is further
justified by the diversity of species found in the restinga environments of Rio de
Janeiro.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><sec><title>Restinga areas and collection of plant material</title><p>The study was conducted in the Laboratory of Environmental Biotechnology,
Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Centro Universit&#x000e1;rio Estadual da Zona Oeste (UEZO), Rio de Janeiro,
Brazil. The research was conducted by students pursuing their Masters degree.
The extracts were processed from the leaves of 3 species of plants of the
Myrtaceae family that were collected from the restingas ecosystem in the West
Zone of Rio de Janeiro. These plants included <italic>Eugenia
astringens</italic> Cambess (<italic>syn</italic>. <italic>E.
rotundifolia</italic> Casar., <italic>E. umbelliflora</italic> O.Berg) and
<italic>Myrrhinium atropurpureum</italic> Schott, which were collected from
Grumari restinga (23&#x000ba;02'53.3", 23&#x000ba;03'10"S; 43&#x000ba;31'45.1", 43&#x000ba;32'30"W), and
<italic>Neomitranthes obscura</italic> (DC.) N. Silveira growing in the
preserved area of the Marambaia restinga, &#x0201c;Line 2&#x0201d; (23&#x000b0;04'S, 44&#x000b0;00'W; 23&#x000b0;02'S,
44&#x000b0;34'W) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). The leaves were
collected between the months of February and March of 2017. The plants were
identified by the taxonomist, Marcelo da Costa Souza, and were deposited in the
herbarium collections of the Rio de Janeiro Botanical Garden (RB), Universidade
Federal do Rio de Janeiro (RBR), and Universidade Federal do Estado do Rio de
Janeiro (HUNI). The deposition numbers were: <italic>M. atropurpureum</italic> -
RB415731, <italic>N. obscura</italic> - RBR12592, and <italic>E.
astringens</italic> - HUNI650. The collected materials were dried in an
environment with constant air circulation at 28<sup>o</sup>C&#x000b1;2<sup>o</sup>C for
a period of approximately one month. The permission for sample collection was
obtained from the Ministry of Environment (SISBIO/ICMBio) under approval number
37376-2. </p><p>
<fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1:</label><caption><title>(a) Collection areas in the West Zone of the restingas in Rio de
Janeiro: 1. Marambaia and 2. Grumari. The collection points at
Grumari (b) and Marambaia (c) are indicated in yellow. Program
ArcMap 10.6.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1678-9849-rsbmt-54-e00922020-gf1"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of hydroalcoholic plant extracts</title><p>The dried leaves of <italic>E. astringens</italic> (44 g), <italic>M.
atropurpureum</italic> (58 g), and <italic>N. obscura</italic> (34 g) were
shredded and placed in 500 mL beakers, into which 450 mL of a solution of 90%
methanol:distilled water was added. The extraction was performed by static
maceration for 10 days at 28<sup>o</sup>C&#x000b1;2<sup>o</sup>C, and the setup was
protected from light during this process. The extracts were subsequently
filtered using a paper filter. The solvent was evaporated on a rotary evaporator
at 50&#x000b0;C and the aqueous residues were removed by lyophilization.</p></sec><sec><title> Bioassay for determining larvicidal activity against <italic>A.
aegypti</italic>
</title><p>In order to determine the larvicidal activity of the extracts against <italic>A.
aegypti</italic> by bioassays<italic>,</italic> the eggs of <italic>A.
aegypti</italic> were obtained from <italic>N&#x000fa;cleo Operacional Sentinela de
Mosquitos Vetores</italic> (NOSMOVE/FIOCRUZ) and placed in two tulle-covered
trays containing 750 mL of filtered water. After hatching, which occurred within
24 h, the larvae were fed on a yeast-based diet until they reached the third
instar stage, determined by the head/body size ratio.</p><p>For the biological assays, the extracts were prepared at three concentrations of
25, 12.5, and 7.5 &#x000b5;L/mL, corresponding to 500, 250, and 150 &#x000b5;L/L, respectively.
These extracts were prepared from a stock solution containing 150 mg of each
extract, dissolved in 3 mL dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO). The solutions were
subsequently placed in an ultrasound bath for 1 h. The tests were performed in
200 mL plastic cups containing 20 mL of distilled water. Each treatment was
repeated thrice using ten experimental setups comprising 10 cups with 10 third
instar larvae each (n= 30). Water and DMSO were used as the controls. The
results were recorded after 24 h and 48 h, by counting the dead larvae that did
not react to the mechanical stimuli provided by light and tweezers.</p></sec><sec><title> Larvicidal bioassay against <italic>S. pertinax</italic>
</title><p>In the present study, the samples were collected from the Santo Aleixo River
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>). The Santo Aleixo River is
in the neighborhood of Andorinhas in Santo Aleixo District under the
jurisdiction of Mag&#x000e9; municipality, located in the biogeographic province of
Serra do Mar, Serra dos &#x000d3;rg&#x000e3;os region, in Rio de Janeiro (22&#x000b0;39'10'' S,
43&#x000b0;02'26'' W; S 22<sup>o</sup>32', W 43<sup>o</sup>02'. The Santo Aleixo River
is part of the Para&#x000ed;ba do Sul River Basin that falls within the tropical
Atlantic morphoclimatic region. The climatic conditions of this area ranges from
hot and sub-hot to super humid, and comprise an intermediate sub-drought
period.</p><p>
<fig id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2:</label><caption><title>(a) Map of the Santo Aleixo River, &#x0201c;Andorinhas&#x0201d; (orange)
indicates the collection area for <italic>S. pertinax</italic>. (b)
S. Aleixo River. Program ArcMap 10.6.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1678-9849-rsbmt-54-e00922020-gf2"/></fig>
</p><p>The samples were collected from each site using the transect method in which all
the larvae present within a 5 m stretch of the river were collected. The larvae
were collected from rocky substrates and the shafts of the dams along the
watercourse, and the larvae that adhered to the substrate were removed with
tweezers. The collected materials were stored in covered plastic pots (200 mL)
containing 20 mL distilled water, which were placed in a styrofoam box. The pots
were aerated by flowing air from an air compressor for simulating running water.
Biological ice was used to maintain temperature at
20<sup>o</sup>C&#x000b1;2<sup>o</sup>C and to ensure larval survival for the subsequent
bioassays. The covers on the plastic pots were perforated to allow the insertion
of a plastic tip connected to a silicone hose that permitted the aeration of the
pots. This equipment was used for transporting the samples and for performing
the bioassays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>)<italic>.</italic>
Simuliids are aquatic insects found in flowing watercourses (rheophilic) with
different volumes of water. They live in environments with high dissolved oxygen
content and feed on finely dissolved organic particles suspended in water<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>22</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>23</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>24</sup>
</xref>. The collected larvae were then transported to the laboratory after
approximately two hours of collection, and the last instar larvae were selected
using a stereoscope for performing bioassays for evaluating the larvicidal
potential of the extracts at different concentrations. The same aforedescribed
equipment was used for this bioassay, with the exception that 200 mL cups were
used instead of plastic pots, as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>. Water and DMSO were used as the controls. Three
concentrations of the extract (25, 12.5, and 7.5 &#x000b5;L/mL) were used for the
biological assays. The extracts were prepared from a stock solution containing
150 mg of each of the extracts that were separately dissolved in 3 mL DMSO and
placed in an ultrasound bath for 1 h. The larvicidal activity of the extracts
were evaluated in triplicate using ten cups (n= 30), according to a method
described previously<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>. Each of the cups contained the leaf extracts that were diluted in 20 mL
distilled water. Each of the cups contained 10 simuliid larvae, and the number
of dead larvae were counted at 24 h and 48 h.</p><p>
<fig id="f3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3:</label><caption><title>Equipment used for transporting the simuliid larvae and
performing bioassays with the plant extracts.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1678-9849-rsbmt-54-e00922020-gf3"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>All the data were initially analyzed by Lilliefors normality tests, and
subsequently by the Kruskal-Wallis test if the data distributions were not
normal, for determining the statistical differences between the control group
and the three treatment groups that were administered different plant extracts
at different concentrations, at a significance level of p&#x0003c; 0.05. The
percentage mortality (%) and median mortality were also determined using a
Finney&#x02019;s probit model for estimating the median lethal concentration
(CL<sub>50</sub>)<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>25</sup>
</xref> with 95% confidence limits.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title> Larvicidal activity against <italic>A. aegypti</italic>
</title><p>Only the methanolic extracts of <italic>M. atropurpureum</italic> and <italic>E.
astringens</italic>, at concentrations of 7.5, 12.5, and 25 &#x000b5;L/mL, showed
larvicidal activity after 24 h. It was also evident that DMSO had no impact on
larval mortality, as depicted in <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.
The extracts of <italic>M. atropurpureum</italic> exhibited the strongest
larvicidal activity at a concentration of 25 &#x000b5;L/mL. This resulted in a total
larval mortality of 100% in all the repetitions. At a lower concentration of
12.5 &#x000b5;L/mL, larval mortality was higher than 50%. The extract of <italic>E.
astringens</italic> showed promising results at a concentration of 25 &#x000b5;L/mL,
with 50% larval mortality after 24 h of treatment, as depicted in <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>
<table-wrap id="t1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 1:</label><caption><title>Larvicidal activity of methanolic extracts (90%) of Myrtaceae
plant species against <italic>A. aegypti</italic> after 24 hours
(comparison between treatment and control triplicates).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Samples</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concentration</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mortality</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mortality Median</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL<sub>50</sub> (ppm)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% confidence</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(&#x000b5;L/mL)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Q1, Q3) (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">interval</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Neomitranthes obscura</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6472</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33&#x000b1;4.71</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(5,15)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6472</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33&#x000b1;4.71</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0,0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.e.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.e.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4805</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00&#x000b1;14.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50(40,55)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Myrrhinium atropurpureum</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2014</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0&#x000b1;21.60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20(10,45)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005691*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.66&#x000b1;9.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70(60,75)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.62 - 14.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001357*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0&#x000b1;0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100(100,100)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Eugenia astringens</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.66&#x000b1;4.71</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40(20,50)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04131</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0&#x000b1;14.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40(40,50)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.64 - 37.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01465*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0&#x000b1;21.60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80(55,80)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water (control)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b1;0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0,0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMSO (control)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b1;0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0,0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.541</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.66&#x000b1;9.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0,10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b1;0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0,0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><p> *Significant differences, p&#x0003c; 0.05, according to
Kruskal-Wallis test. CL<sub>50 -</sub> median lethal dose. n.e.
- no effectiveness after 24 h. (-) not calculated.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>The toxicity of the extracts was also evaluated by Finney&#x02019;s probit analysis
method<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>25</sup>
</xref>, and the results are expressed in terms of CL<sub>50</sub>. The
CL<sub>50</sub> values of the methanolic extracts of <italic>M.
atropurpureum</italic> and <italic>E. astringens</italic>, determined using
third instar larvae, were 11.10 ppm and 23.58 ppm, respectively. The
CL<sub>50</sub> values of the extracts of <italic>N. obscura</italic> could
not be calculated owing to insufficient efficacy after 24 h of treatment.</p><p>The larvicidal effects of the methanolic extracts of the leaves of <italic>M.
atropurpureum</italic> and <italic>E. astringens</italic>, at concentrations
of 12.5 and 25 &#x000b5;L/mL, and that of the <italic>N. obscura</italic> extract at a
concentration of 25 &#x000b5;L/mL (46.66% mortality), were verified after 48 h of
treatment (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><p> The larvicidial effect of <italic>N. obscura</italic> was evident at higher
concentrations, and caused a maximum mortality of 46.6% after 48 h of treatment.
However, the other plant species showed no significant differences with respect
to the duration of exposure. The CL<sub>50</sub> values of the leaf extract of
<italic>M. atropurpureum</italic> and methanolic extract of <italic>E.
astringens</italic> after 48 h were 9.68 ppm and 15.32 ppm,
respectively<italic>.</italic> The CL<sub>50</sub> value of the leaf extract
of <italic>N. obscura</italic> was 25 ppm, as depicted in <xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The methanolic extracts of <italic>M.
atropurpureum</italic> showed maximum larvicidal activity, resulting in 100%
mortality.</p><p>
<table-wrap id="t2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 2:</label><caption><title>Larvicidal activity of methanolic extracts (90%) of Myrtaceae
plant species against <italic>A. aegypti</italic> after 48 hours
(comparison between treatment and control triplicates).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Samples</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concentration</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mortality</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mortality Median</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL<sub>50</sub> (ppm)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% confidence</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(&#x000b5;L/mL)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Q1, Q3) (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">interval</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Neomitranthes obscura</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4541</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#x000b1;8.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(5,15)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b1;0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0,0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.54 - 40.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04728*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.66&#x000b1;12.47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50(40,55)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Myrrhinium atropurpureu</italic>m</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1966</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#x000b1;29.47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20(10,45)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01092*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.66&#x000b1;12.47</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70(60,75)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.68</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.42 - 12.62</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001128*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100&#x000b1;0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100(100,100)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Eugenia astringen</italic>s</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1661</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33,33&#x000b1;24,94</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40(20,50)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04728*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.66&#x000b1;9.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40(40,50)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.41 - 31.66</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01422*</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.33&#x000b1;23.57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80(55,80)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water (control)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b1;0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0,0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMSO (control)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b1;0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0,0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6805</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.66&#x000b1;9.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0,10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x000b1;0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0(0,0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN2"><p> *Significant differences, p&#x0003c; 0.05, according to
Kruskal-Wallis test. (-) not calculated.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec><title> Larvicidal activity against <italic>S. pertinax</italic>
</title><p>After the 24 h of treatment, 100% mortality was observed in the larvae of S.
pertinax in all the treatment groups, while DMSO had no impact on larval
mortality. In fact, all the larvae in the control groups remained alive after
the treatment period. This strongly suggested that these plant extracts had
larvicidal activity. However, as the mortality rate was 100%, the
CL<sub>50</sub> value could not be determined.</p><p>This study is the first to elucidate the larvicidal activity of plants of the
Myrtaceae family against simuliid larvae. However, it was not possible to
determine the precise concentration of the extract at which the simuliid larvae
were killed. Nonetheless, this study suggested the high sensitivity of S.
pertinax to the plant extracts studied herein.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The larval stage represents the most delicate stage in the life cycle of insect
vectors. Therefore, efforts to control these vectors are usually directed at the
larval stage for disrupting their biological cycle by different strategies. The most
commonly used forms of vector control include mechanical, biological, and chemical
strategies. Several studies have been performed on plant extracts with the aim of
developing a method for the biological control of vectors, that would have minimal
environmental impact and adverse effects on the local fauna and flora. Myrtaceae,
Lamiaceae, and Rutaceae are the most frequently studied plant families, owing to
their larvicidal and insecticidal properties<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>26</sup>
</xref>. In a previous study, the larvicidal property of <italic>Eugenia
candolleana</italic> was evaluated using the essential oils extracted from
hydrodistilled leaves. The results proved to be highly satisfactory against the
larval stage of <italic>A. aegytpi</italic>, with a mortality of 100% within 24 h of
treatment. This observation is in agreement with that of the present study, in which
the larvicidal activity of the leaf extracts of <italic>M. atropurpureum</italic>
was determined in terms of percentage mortality. The results of our study
demonstrated that the leaf extracts of <italic>M. atropurpureum</italic> caused 100%
mortality after 24 h of treatment. It has been reported that the essential oils
extracted from the leaves of <italic>Pimenta pseudocaryophyllus</italic> have
larvicidal activity against <italic>A. aegypti</italic> (CL<sub>50</sub> = 44.09
ppm)<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>27</sup>
</xref>. Numerous studies have reported the larvicidal activity of essential oils
extracted from various plants. It has been demonstrated that the polar extracts of
the leaves and fruits of <italic>Callistemon citrinus</italic> have larvicidal
activity, and induce various malformations in the fourth instar larvae of <italic>A.
aegypti</italic> following exposure to the extract<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>28</sup>
</xref>.</p><p>The results of our study are interesting as the determinant of larval toxicity of a
substance or phytocomplex is the efficacy, even at low concentrations, among other
properties. Compared to the concentration used in other studies, we treated the
larvae with the extracts at a relatively low concentration of 25 &#x000b5;L/mL<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>28</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>29</sup>
</xref>. Numerous studies have evaluated the toxicity of natural products in terms
of the CL<sub>50</sub> value, concentration of the sample that is responsible for
inducing the concerned effect in 50% of the test organisms. A low CL<sub>50</sub>
value indicates a higher toxicity of the sample. The results of this study are
promising owing to the fact that the CL<sub>50</sub> value of the methanolic
extracts of <italic>M. atropurpureum</italic> after 24 h was 11.10 ppm. The values
obtained herein are comparable to those obtained by Govindarajan and
Karuppannan<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>30</sup>
</xref> who reported that the maximum larvicidal activity of the methanolic extracts
of <italic>Eclipta alba</italic> (Asteraceae) was observed at 127.64 ppm. The
extract prepared herein can be considered to be effective at relatively low
concentrations. Several authors, including Komalamisra and coworkers<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>31</sup>
</xref>, suggest that a natural product with a CL<sub>50</sub> value of 50 mg/L is
active, and if the CL<sub>50</sub> value varies between 50 mg/L and 100 mg/L, the
natural product is said to be moderately active. The CL<sub>50</sub> values obtained
in our study were below 50 mg/L. The leaf extracts of <italic>M.
atropurpureum</italic> and <italic>E. astringens</italic> caused 30 and 33.33%
mortality, respectively, after 24 h, at the lowest concentration of 7.5 &#x000b5;L/mL. These
data had very high values of standard deviation, which were higher than the mean
values in some cases. These results suggested that more bioassays are necessary for
proving the efficiency of the extracts at certain concentrations, although the
sampling performed for the larvicidal assays was satisfactory. However, treatment
with 25 &#x000b5;L/mL methanolic extracts of <italic>M. atropurpureum</italic> caused 100%
mortality in the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> larvae, indicating the larvicidal
efficacy of this extract. In terms of the duration for which the treatments were
conducted, the highest concentrations of <italic>N. obscura</italic> and <italic>E.
astringens</italic> tested herein showed a higher activity compared to that of
the other treatments, after 24 and 48 h. Nonetheless, the extracts of <italic>N.
obscura</italic> were found to be ineffective against the larval stages. These
results suggested that the duration of treatment should be 24 h.</p><p>There are few studies on the larvicidal activity of natural products against simuliid
larvae. Some studies have been conducted in India, using the roots and leaves of
<italic>Ocimum gratissimum</italic>, <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic>
(popularly known as &#x0201c;neem&#x0201d;), <italic>Pterocarpus santalinoides</italic>, and
<italic>Pistia hyptis</italic>
<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>32</sup>
</xref>. The results of our study indicated that all the plant extracts tested
herein had larvicidal activity; however, the CL<sub>50</sub> values could not be
determined owing to a mortality rate of 100%. </p><p>Previous studies have reported the phytochemical data pertaining to the essential
oils present in the leaves of the species growing in Grumari restinga. The studies
demonstrated that sesquiterpenes are the main constituents of the leaves of
<italic>N. obscura</italic>, while pinene monoterpenes are the major volatile
compounds in the leaves of <italic>E. astringens</italic> and <italic>M.
atropurpureum</italic>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>33</sup>
</xref>. Studies on the polar extracts of the leaves demonstrated the presence of
phoroglucinols (eugenial C, eugenial D, and eugenial E) and pentacyclic triterpenes
(&#x003b1;-amirin, &#x0a7b5;-amirin, and betulinic acid) in <italic>E. astringens</italic>
<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>34</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>35</sup>
</xref>. On the other hand, the flavonoid, quercitrin, is the main component of
<italic>N. obsucura</italic> (data not shown).</p><p>The methanolic extract of <italic>M. atroporpureum</italic> was highly lethal to the
larval stage of <italic>A. aegypti</italic> at a concentration of 25 &#x000b5;L/mL,
resulting in 100% mortality after 24 h (CL<sub>50</sub> = 11.10 ppm), and its
larvicidal activity was higher than that of the other extracts tested herein. This
extract showed more promise for the control of mosquito larvae. Our study further
demonstrated that the 24 h treatment period is sufficient for efficacy. The extracts
of <italic>E. astringens</italic> also showed larvicidal activity, with a larval
mortality rate of 50% (CL<sub>50</sub> = 23.58 ppm). After 48 h of treatment, the
CL<sub>50</sub> values of the leaf extracts of <italic>E. astringens</italic>
and <italic>M. atroporpureum</italic> were 15.32 ppm and 9.68 ppm, respectively. The
results of this study demonstrated that the methanolic extracts of <italic>M.
atropurpureum, E. astringens</italic>, and <italic>N. obscura</italic> have
significant larvicidal potential against the larval stages of Simuliidae; however,
further studies are necessary for determining the lethal concentrations
(CL<sub>50</sub>) of each of the leaf extracts.</p><p>This work contributes to the literature on the vegetation growing in the restinga
areas of Rio de Janiero, and increases the probability of finding new natural
compounds with enhanced larvicidal activity that can be used for biological vector
control. Further studies are necessary for isolating and identifying the active
phytochemicals present in the extracts of <italic>E. astringens</italic>, <italic>M.
atropurpureum</italic>, and <italic>N. obscura</italic>. It is also necessary to
perform bioassays for identifying the compounds that are responsible for larval
mortality and for determining whether these compounds act synergistically. These
natural products can be used in the future as a tool for the biological control of
<italic>A. aegypti</italic> and <italic>S. pertinax</italic> larvae.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>The authors express their gratitude to the Brazilian Army, in particular to those
responsible for the administration and care of the Marambaia sandbank area, for
their kind hospitality and access to the materials used in this study. We also thank
Prof. A. P. Esperan&#x000e7;o who constructed the equipments for evaluating the larvicidal
efficacy of the extracts against <italic>Simulium</italic> larvae.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn1"><p>
<bold>Financial Support:</bold> The authors are grateful to the Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Carlos
Chagas Filho de Amparo &#x000e0; Pesquisa do Estado do Rio de Janeiro - FAPERJ (Brazil.
Rio de Janeiro) for providing financial support (Grant numbers: Proj.
E-26/211.013/2016 and E-26/010.001536/2016).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global epidemiology of dengue outbreaks in 1990-2015: A
systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28748176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Figueir&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil-Azevedo</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of neotropical blackflies (Diptera: Simuliidae) as
vectors of the onchocerciasis: a short overview of the ecology behind the
disease</article-title><source>Oecol Aust</source><year>2010</year><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>755</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Docile</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueir&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil-Azevedo</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nessimian</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water pollution and distribution of the black fly (Diptera:
Simuliidae) in the Atlantic Forest</article-title><source>Brazil. Rev Biol Trop</source><year>2015</year><volume>63</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26666125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo-Coutinho</surname><given-names>CJPC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueir&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Becnel</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonality and prevalence rates of microsporidia in Simulium
pertinax (Diptera : Simuliidae) larvae in the region of Serra dos Org&#x000e3;os,
Rio de Janeiro, Brasil</article-title><source>J Invert Path</source><year>2004</year><volume>85</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>191</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa-da-Silva</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Capurro</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two step male release strategy using transgenic mosquito lines to
control transmission of vector-borne diseases</article-title><source>Acta Trop</source><year>2014</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>177</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pates</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mosquito behavior and vector control</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><year>2005</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15355233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gambarra</surname><given-names>WPT</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>WFS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucena</surname><given-names>ML</given-names><suffix>Filho</suffix></name><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>IMC</given-names></name><name><surname>Apolin&#x000e1;rio</surname><given-names>OKS</given-names></name><name><surname>Beserra</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial distribution and sterase activity in populations of Aedes
(Stegomyia) aegypti (Linnaeus) (Diptera: Culicidae) resistant to
temephos</article-title><source>Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</source><year>2013</year><volume>46</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23740072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>CFS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insecticide resistance in Simulium populations (Diptera,
Simuliidae)</article-title><source>Cad Sa&#x000fa;de P&#x000fa;blica</source><year>2002</year><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12048592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zara</surname><given-names>ALSA</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandes-Oliveira</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estrat&#x000e9;gias de controle do Aedes aegypti: uma
revis&#x000e3;o</article-title><source>Epidemiol Serv Sa&#x000fa;de</source><year>2016</year><volume>25</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27869956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant extracts as potential mosquito larvicides</article-title><source>Indian J Med Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>598</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22771587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guilhermino</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrero</surname><given-names>ATG</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Grillo</surname><given-names>ZCFA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ci&#x000ea;ncia no uso de produtos naturais para controle do vetor do
v&#x000ed;rus Zika (ZIKV)</article-title><source>Rev Fitos</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Satoto</surname><given-names>TBT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadianto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Istiyana</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Badriyah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Diptyanusa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mosquitocidal activities of Tagetes erecta L. compared to
prallethrin against Aedes aegypti and Culex quinquefasciatus (Diptera:
Culicidae)</article-title><source>Res J Med Plants</source><year>2018</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>71</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcez</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcez</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>LMGE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarmento</surname><given-names>UC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Naturally occurring plant compounds with larvicidal activity
against Aedes aegypti</article-title><source>Rev Virtual Quim</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>393</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Direito</surname><given-names>ICN</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueir&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological control of black flies (Diptera: Simuliidae): overview
and perspectives</article-title><source>Cad UniFOA</source><year>2014</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>104</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stefanello</surname><given-names>M&#x000c9;A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascoal</surname><given-names>ACRF</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvador</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oils from neotropical Myrtaceae: Chemical diversity and
biological properties</article-title><source>Chem Biodiv</source><year>2011</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>94</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Morim</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subtribos Eugeniinae O. Berg e Myrtinae O. Berg (Myrtaceae) na
Restinga da Marambaia, RJ, Brasil</article-title><source>Acta Bot Bras</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>652</fpage><lpage>683</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vict&#x000f3;rio</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>RCO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Secretory Cavities and Volatiles of Myrrhinium atropurpureum
Schott var. atropurpureum (Myrtaceae): an endemic species collected in the
restingas of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</article-title><source>Nat Prod Commun</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1045</fpage><lpage>1050</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21834254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vict&#x000f3;rio</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Silveira</surname><given-names>EGP</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gama</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Leaf essential oils and volatiles, histochemistry and
micromorphology of Neomitranthes obscura (DC.) N. Silveira (Myrtaceae)
growing in sandy coastal plains of Rio de Janeiro</article-title><source>Biochem Syst Ecol</source><year>2018</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>CFD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergallo</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Sluys</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>MAS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The remnants of restinga habitats in the Brazilian Atlantic
Forest of Rio de Janeiro state, Brazil: Habitat loss and risk of
disappearance</article-title><source>Braz J Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>67</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17876436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>AVM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>MAC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uso medicinal da fam&#x000ed;lia Myrtaceae e Melastomataceae no
Brasil</article-title><source>FLORAM</source><year>2004</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>52</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leyva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>French-Pacheco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Quintana</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Montada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Castex</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Melaleuca quinquenervia (Cav.) S.T. Blake (Myrtales: Myrtaceae):
Natural alternative for mosquito control</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Trop Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>984</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27794392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tisgratog</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanguanpong</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Grieco</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngoen-Kluan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chareonviriyaphap</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants traditionally used as mosquito repellents and the
implication for their use in vector control</article-title><source>Acta Trop</source><year>2016</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26826392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malmqvist</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuusela</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Merrit</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wotton</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Black flies in the boreal biome, key organisms in both
terrestrial and aquatic environments: A review</article-title><source>&#x000c9;coscience</source><year>2004</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>200</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Figueir&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil-Azevedo</surname><given-names>LHG</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Maia-Herzog</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local distribution of blackfly (Diptera, Simuliidae) larvae in
two adjacent streams: the role of water current velocity in the diversity of
blackfly larvae</article-title><source>Rev Bras Entomol</source><year>2008</year><volume>52</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>454</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finney</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Probit analysis</source><edition>3rd ed</edition><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><year>1972</year><size units="pages">333 p</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neves</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezende</surname><given-names>SRF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontes</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Composition and larvicidal activity of essential oil of Eugenia
candolleana DC. (Myrtaceae) against Aedes aegypti</article-title><source>Rev Virtual Quim</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2305</fpage><lpage>2315</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D'angelis</surname><given-names>ASR</given-names></name><name><surname>Negrelle</surname><given-names>RRB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pimenta pseudocaryophyllus (Gomes) Landrum: aspectos bot&#x000e2;nicos,
ecol&#x000f3;gicos, etnobot&#x000e2;nicos e farmacol&#x000f3;gicos</article-title><source>Rev Bras Plantas Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>617</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palanikumar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pravin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Navaneethan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahendren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohanraj</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhanakkod</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Callistemon citrinus (Myrtaceae) methanolic leaf extract: a
potent mosquitocidal agent for controlling dengue vector mosquito Aedes
aegypti (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>J Entomol Zool Stud</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1051</fpage><lpage>1059</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>AAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Paula</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Esp&#x000ed;ndola</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atividade larvicida de extratos vegetais sobre Aedes aegypti (L.)
(Diptera: Culicidae), em condi&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es de laborat&#x000f3;rio</article-title><source>BioAssay</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>SLC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaulberto</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fries</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Avalia&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da atividade larvicida de extratos obtidos do caule de
Croton linearifolius Mull. Arg. (Euphorbiaceae) sobre larvas de Aedes
aegypti (Linnaeus. 1762) (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>Biotemas</source><year>2014</year><volume>27</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>85</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Govindaraian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Karuppannan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mosquito larvicidal and ovicidal properties of Eclipta alba (L.)
Hassk (Asteraceae) against chicungunha vector. Aedes aegypti (Linn.)
(Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Trop Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21771410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komalamisra</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Trongtokit</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rongsriyam</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Apiwathnarson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening for larvicidal activity in some Thai plants against
four mosquitoes vector species</article-title><source>Southeast Asian J Trop Med Public Health</source><year>2005</year><volume>36</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1412</fpage><lpage>1422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16610643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sam-Wobo</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Adeleke</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mafiana</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Surakat</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative Repellent activities of some plant extracts against
Simulium damnosum complex</article-title><source>J Vector Borne Dis</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>1204</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Succar</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Direito</surname><given-names>ICN</given-names></name><name><surname>Assis</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vict&#x000f3;rio</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Atividade antibacteriana de &#x000f3;leos essenciais de plantas de
Myrtaceae contra bact&#x000e9;rias multirresistentes</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>JMB</given-names><suffix>Junior</suffix></name></person-group><source>An&#x000e1;lise Cr&#x000ed;tica das Ci&#x000ea;ncias Biol&#x000f3;gicas e da Natureza 2</source><publisher-loc>Ponta Grossa, PR</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Atena Editora</publisher-name><year>2019</year><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>192</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldoni</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Barretta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Broering</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Faveri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Molleria</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of Eugenia umbelliflora O. Berg (Myrtaceae)-leaf extract
on inflammation and hypersensitivity</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2019</year><volume>244</volume><fpage>112133</fpage><lpage>112133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31377260</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>