<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40" class="p">All mortality data from each treatment group were corrected using Abbott’s formula
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup> and tested for homogeneity of variances using Levene’s tests. To check important factors that influence the susceptibility of the experimental beetles, variables of overall mortality were analyzed (each one separately) using the ordinary least squares regression model with symbiotic status, pesticides and generations as effects. Multivariate tests (using DDVP, EO and DMSO data as dependent variables) and multifactorial analyses (using the symbiotic status and experimental generations as fixed factors) were performed to analyze the variations of mortality within and between all the parameters (symbiotic status, experimental generations and pesticide treatments). The one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to analyze differences in mortality and sequencing data (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). Colony Forming Units of antibiotics treated and untreated samples were analyzed using an independent T-Test. Tukey’s HSD test at P = 0.05 significance, was used for mean separations within and between treatments. Colony Forming Units (CFU) data were log-transformed to narrow down data variations. Statistical analyses were carried out using SPSS 20.0 software (Statsoft Inc, Carey, J, USA). Bray–Curtis and unweighted UniFrac distance matrices were used to calculate the beta diversity and the analysis of similarity (ANOSIM) was performed to evaluate the similarity of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">maculatus</italic> gut bacterial community among treatments using the software PRIMER 7.0. All results (alpha and beta diversity, survival, &amp; sequence data) are presented as mean ± standard deviations (SD) of the three biological replicates. OriginPro 8.5.1 software was used to construct graphs.
</p>
