<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In spite of the importance of controlled synthesis, the synthesis of silver nanoparticles with controllable size is a challenge. Varieties of methods have been reported to prepare size-controlled silver nanostructures. The classical methods can be classified into two categories: seed-mediated synthesis and photochemical synthesis. Wan et al. synthesized quasi-spherical silver nanoparticles with tunable size by following a controlled seed-mediated growth approach via thermal reduction of silver nitrate with citrate [
 <xref rid="B7-micromachines-10-00274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Moreover, Bastús et al. synthesized silver nanoparticles by using a combination of two chemical reducing agents, sodium citrate and tannic acid [
 <xref rid="B8-micromachines-10-00274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. The size of silver nanoparticles was controlled via adjusting reaction temperature, pH, and the concentration of reducing agents and seed. As a result, citrate-coated spherical silver nanoparticles with controllable size from 10 to 200 nm were obtained. However, it is complicated to achieve large-sized silver nanoparticles in most similar methods, because stepwise seeding growth is needed. The size of silver nanocrystals prepared via photochemical pathway was mainly affected by the irradiating time, intensity and wavelength [
 <xref rid="B9-micromachines-10-00274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-micromachines-10-00274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. However, the wavelength of light source available in the laboratory is limited, limiting the synthesis of silver nanocrystals with controlled size in a wide range, and silver nanostructure shape can change during the irradiation process [
 <xref rid="B11-micromachines-10-00274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-micromachines-10-00274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-micromachines-10-00274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. In addition, template-based method is also commonly used to synthesize size-controlled silver nanowires or nanorods by the steric and structure-directing effect. The templates are mesoporous materials, carbon nanotubes, polymer materials, and micelles [
 <xref rid="B14-micromachines-10-00274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. However, the structures of templates, especially for polymer and biological templates, are highly sensitive to the surroundings, and impurities may be introduced during the process of removing templates.
</p>
