<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Dendropanax morbifera,</italic> an ancient medicinal plant native to South Korea, its 100-year-old plant extract is considered for its therapeutic applications to date. Our investigation represents the understandable approach of green synthesis for functional food nanoformulation. A natural coating surface using an ancient DM plant extract mediated with ZnO nanoparticles carrying an antiobese drug tryptophan is formulated. The process of preparation involves the O/W nanoemulsion method using high energy ultrasonication with non-ionic surfactant interactions, to enhance the trapping and efficiency of active ingredients at the targeted site. The synthesized nanoformulation was confirmed by some critical physicochemical characterization using DLS, UV, FT-IR, FE-TEM, and FE-SEM, and its stability was discussed for a longer circulation of over five days. In vitro behavioral changes of the nanoformulation initiate at the targeted site, where it undergoes the process of degrading its outer capping layer to further expose the Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> ion and tryptophan. Due to this exposure of Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> ion, it affects the mitochondrial damages due to its transition permeability and induces oxidative stress to reduce fat depositions and thereby, it increases the bioactivity of tryptophan causing dual effects by reducing the accumulation of lipids at the fat deposited site. This phenomenon is investigated with 3T3-L1 preadipocytes and RAW 264.7 cells at 10 μg/mL concentration. DM-ZnO-Try NE has shown lower toxicity in RAW 264.7 and 3T3-L1 preadipocytes and has shown an excellent efficiency in 3T3-L1 preadipocytes by reducing around 45% of the lipid droplets. This increased activity of the nanoemulsion may be due to its particle size and morphology. Oil Red O staining assay was performed to confirm the lipid reduction, which was then further verified using the OD measurements. This evidence signifies that the DM-ZnO-Try NE substantially reduces more lipid droplets in comparison with its counterpart of DM-ZnO NPs and standard tryptophan. Hence, it could be considered in the treatment of obesity and to study other related metabolic disorders such as heart disease, stroke, and type 2 diabetes by investigating in detail. This study suggests that the enhanced efficacy of the safe formulation can be used as a functional food for commercial applications, due to its low cost and biodegradable natural sources.
</p>
