<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_SPJ1131 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEsi1 svg ?><?FILEsi2 svg ?><?FILEsi3 svg ?><?FILEsi4 svg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saudi Pharm J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Saudi Pharm J</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Saudi Pharmaceutical Journal : SPJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1319-0164</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2213-7475</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7679473</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1319-0164(20)30216-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsps.2020.09.011</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ethnopharmacological study of natural products used for traditional cancer therapy in Algeria</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au005"><name><surname>Ta&#x000ef;bi</surname><given-names>Khaled</given-names></name><email>khaledtaibi@hotmail.com</email><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au010"><name><surname>Abderrahim</surname><given-names>Leila Ait</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au015"><name><surname>Ferhat</surname><given-names>Karima</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au020"><name><surname>Betta</surname><given-names>Soria</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au025"><name><surname>Ta&#x000ef;bi</surname><given-names>Fadhila</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au030"><name><surname>Bouraada</surname><given-names>Fatiha</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au035"><name><surname>Boussaid</surname><given-names>Mohamed</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="af005"><label>a</label>Faculty of Life and Natural Sciences, University of Tiaret, 14000, Algeria</aff><aff id="af010"><label>b</label>Instituto de Biolog&#x000ed;a Molecular y Celular de Plantas (IBMCP), Universitat Polit&#x000e8;cnica de Val&#x000e8;ncia-Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas, Camino de Vera s/n, 46022 Valencia, Spain</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author at: Faculty of Life and Natural Sciences, University of Tiaret, 14000, Algeria. <email>khaledtaibi@hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1451</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ab005"><p>Traditional and complementary medicine constitutes an important, and often underestimated, source of healthcare for multiple diseases including cancer. However, little is known about the ethnomedical knowledge and practices in Northern Africa. The main objective of this study is to identify and analyze the variety of natural products used in Algerian ethnopharmacology for cancer therapy. For this purpose, semi-structured interviews with 225 traditional healers, herbalists and practitioners were realized in twelve locations in Algeria throughout field studies performed from June 2015 to July 2019. Interviews covered popular and vernacular names of the natural product, mode of use and administration, dose, period of treatment, toxicity and side effects among other data. The obtained results reveal the use of 113 medicinal plants (belonging to 53 families and 104 genera), 10 animal species and various products and by-products from different origins such as honey, olive oil, thorns, urine, milk, animal fat and the alkaline water of Zamzam. Basing on the frequency of citation (FC), use reports (UR) and use value (UV), the most used natural products for cancer treatment are honey (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;181, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;194, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.65), <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L. (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;131, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;152, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.54), <italic>Aristolochia longa</italic> L. (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;118, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;144, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.51), <italic>Berberis vulgaris</italic> L. (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;111, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;142, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.51), <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L. (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;107, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;121, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.43), <italic>Trigonella foenum</italic>-<italic>graecum</italic> L. (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;102; UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;119, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.43), <italic>Citrus limon</italic> (L.) Obseck (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;97, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;120, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.43), <italic>Artemisia herba-alba</italic> Asso (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;92, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;115, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.41) and the holy water &#x02018;Zamzam&#x02019; (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;110, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;110, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.43) respectively. Mixtures of two or more ingredients were frequently used. The use of Pelophylax saharicus skin&#x02019; was reported for the first time for the treatment of visible tumors and skin cancer. This is the first study documenting the traditional uses of various natural products for cancer treatment in Algeria. Our findings are relevant to document the traditional uses of numerous natural products and to provide background basis to search for novel compounds for cancer therapy.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kg005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Traditional and complementary medicine</kwd><kwd>Ethnopharmacology</kwd><kwd>Natural products</kwd><kwd>Cancer</kwd><kwd>Algeria</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0005">Cancer constitutes a major public health burden and one of the main causes leading to death in both developing and developed countries (<xref rid="b0565" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2018</xref>). In Algeria, the latest statistics of the Global Cancer Observatory (2018) have accounted 29,453 deaths caused by cancer (around 8% of all deaths). The number of new cancer cases has increased also from 28,736 in 2008 to 53,076 in 2018 (<xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Benarba et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Bray et al., 2018</xref>). The incidence of cancer is increasing in Algeria and the accessibility to health care is difficult due to the insufficient number of oncologists, the serious lack of adapted medical facilities designated for diagnosis and treatment and the incomplete health care framework in the country. Regrettably, the number of cancer centers is insufficient to cover the populations of the whole country (48 departments or wilayas). Therefore, underprivileged families mainly from rural areas and cancer sufferers living away from those cities must travel, in some cases till 1.500&#x0202f;km, via inadequate or even non-existent means of transport to reach these centers. There is also a strong gender bias in cancer treatment as some diseases like breast and cervical cancers are taboo. Besides, the therapeutic efficiency of the conventional treatments is low and often insufficient to eradicate this disease (<xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">Jelonek et al., 2017</xref>). These methods can even carry different side effects on body tissues where healthy cells are destroyed in the same time as cancerous ones (<xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">Durante and Formenti, 2018</xref>).</p><p id="p0010">These circumstances, along with the failure of modern medicine in finding effective treatments for numerous diseases including cancer, have promoted the resurgence of traditional medicine (<xref rid="b0565" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2018</xref>). Traditional medicinal practitioners use a variety of natural products for their health-care needs, the knowledge of such practices was collected and refined over hundreds or even thousands of years (<xref rid="b0575" ref-type="bibr">Yuan et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p id="p0015">Moreover, natural products have received an increasing consideration for their potential use as novel cancer therapeutic agents since they hold a variety of important bioactive compounds acting as inhibitors of various stages of tumorigenesis and associated inflammatory processes (<xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Amaral et al., 2019</xref>). Currently, more than 60% of anticancer drugs are derived from natural products although medicinal plants are considered the most important source by around 75%. Over 3000 plants have been reported at present worldwide to hold potential anticancer molecules and most of those are yet to be discovered (<xref rid="b0445" ref-type="bibr">Rahman et al., 2019</xref>). <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L., <italic>Trigonella foenum-graecum</italic> L., <italic>Aristolochia</italic> spp., <italic>Bryonia dioica</italic> Jacq<italic>.</italic>, <italic>Cassia absus</italic> L., <italic>Aquilaria malaccensis</italic> Lam.<italic>, Marrubium vulgare</italic> L.<italic>, Lavandula maroccana</italic> Murb.<italic>, Ephedra alata</italic> Decne.<italic>,</italic> and <italic>Euphorbia resinifera</italic> O.Berg were the most used medicinal plants by cancer patients in North African countries mainly in Morocco (<xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Alves-Silva et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Bourhia et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr">Kabbaj et al., 2012</xref>). However, <italic>Arum</italic> spp., <italic>Artemisia</italic> spp., <italic>Calotropis procera</italic> (Aiton) Dryand., <italic>Citrullus colocynthis</italic> (L.) Schrad., <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L., <italic>Pulicaria crispa</italic> Sch.Bip., <italic>Urtica</italic> spp., and <italic>Withania somnifera</italic> (L.) Dunal were the most used plants species among cancer patients in the Near East countries (<xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Abu-Darwish and Efferth, 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 2017</xref>). These medicinal plant species can provide a promising strategy for complementary medicine and plant-based drugs discovery.</p><p id="p0020">Furthermore, preparations and uses of natural products differ significantly between regions even for the same country (<xref rid="b0275" ref-type="bibr">Habtamu et al., 2014</xref>). Although Algeria is home of a great plant diversity with 3183 species and numerous endemic and threatened ones due to its climatic and topographic diversity (<xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Ait Abderrahim et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Boussaid et al., 2018</xref>), only few ethnobotanical and ethnomedicinal studies have been carried out dealing with this diversity and only limited preliminary works have been initiated by (<xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">Benarba, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Benarba et al., 2015</xref>) then (<xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">Benarba and Pandiella, 2018</xref>) concerning the exploitation of this diversity for cancer treatment.</p><p id="p0025">With a long history spanning many centuries, wars and colonization which led to the melting of different civilizations (Berber, Greco-Roman, Arab, Ottoman and French), Algeria is characterized as well by its diversified ethnic groups, cultures, languages and beliefs which leads subsequently in turn to diversified traditional medicinal practices. Hence, the traditional uses of natural products in Algeria constitute an important opportunity for focused screening based on their ethnopharmacological and ethnomedicinal utilizations.</p><p id="p0030">Nevertheless, the ancestral knowledge about traditional medicine uses and the associated practices is still not well documented in Algeria. Thus, ethnopharmacological and ethnomedicinal investigations have become more than necessary to disclose locally important natural products and safeguard the traditional medicinal knowledge (<xref rid="b0575" ref-type="bibr">Yuan et al., 2016</xref>). Also, there is an urgent need to develop a national pharmacopoeia besides national standards and guidelines of collect and uses. Moreover, the collected data are being used as basis in research that needs to be tested in clinical and lab trials.</p><p id="p0035">The present study is an ethnopharmacological investigation aiming to identify and analyze the natural products used in traditional medicines for cancer treatment in Algeria. Another objective of this work is to enrich the communities&#x02019; knowledge databases and safeguard the cultural heritage concerning traditional medicines as recognized by the UNESCO (2003). To our knowledge, this is the first ethnopharmacological and ethnomedicinal investigation carried out on cancer in Algeria. Moreover, it will constitute the basis for pharmacological studies on cancer management.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Methodology</title><sec id="s0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Data collection</title><sec id="s0020"><label>2.1.1</label><title>Study area</title><p id="p0040">Ethnopharmacological information was collected throughout field studies performed during four years from June 2015 to July 2019. The study was carried out in twelve different locations in Algeria reflecting both, the traditional and the modern regions encompassing both modern Western-style healthcare and traditional, culture-based healthcare (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). This include the main big cities and the surrounding small villages of each population. The economy of the local populations is based mainly on agricultural activities (animal husbandry, pastoralism, cereal or vegetable farming) and commercial sector, service industries and the other activities are of less importance. The region covered in this study is characterized by a vast ecological and climatic diversity represented by the most characteristically ecosystems of the Algerian territory encompassing the coasts, mountains, forests, arid high plains, steppe and Sahara. These ecosystems shelter a huge faunistic and floristic biodiversity of international importance as defined by the Ramsar Convention. This cross-validation was performed to investigate probable cultural and regional differences within the cancer management used methods by the informants from a part, and in order to obtain representative dataset for the whole West- and Center region of Algeria from another part. Socio-demographic characteristics of the interrogated population are shown in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Socio-demographic characteristics of the informants.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2"><bold>Population</bold></th><th colspan="2"><bold>Gender</bold><hr/></th><th rowspan="2"><bold>Age</bold></th><th colspan="5"><bold>School level</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th><bold>Male</bold></th><th><bold>Female</bold></th><th><bold>Illiterate</bold></th><th><bold>Elementary</bold></th><th><bold>Secondary</bold></th><th><bold>Undergraduate</bold></th><th><bold>Graduate</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Blida</td><td>11</td><td>13</td><td>[21&#x02013;75]</td><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>7</td></tr><tr><td>Chlef</td><td>9</td><td>11</td><td>[24&#x02013;67]</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>8</td><td>4</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Djelfa</td><td>10</td><td>19</td><td>[20&#x02013;77]</td><td>10</td><td>9</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>El Bayadh</td><td>12</td><td>17</td><td>[23&#x02013;81]</td><td>11</td><td>5</td><td>1</td><td>6</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Mascara</td><td>9</td><td>16</td><td>[25&#x02013;70]</td><td>3</td><td>8</td><td>5</td><td>4</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Oran</td><td>12</td><td>18</td><td>[21&#x02013;65]</td><td>2</td><td>6</td><td>5</td><td>4</td><td>13</td></tr><tr><td>Relizane</td><td>10</td><td>14</td><td>[27&#x02013;67]</td><td>2</td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>4</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Saida</td><td>11</td><td>12</td><td>[25&#x02013;71]</td><td>3</td><td>8</td><td>6</td><td>3</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Sidi Belabbes</td><td>9</td><td>13</td><td>[20&#x02013;65]</td><td>2</td><td>6</td><td>4</td><td>6</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>Tiaret</td><td>32</td><td>41</td><td>[18&#x02013;84]</td><td>11</td><td>16</td><td>19</td><td>18</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td>Tissemsilt</td><td>18</td><td>22</td><td>[20&#x02013;82]</td><td>13</td><td>11</td><td>4</td><td>6</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Tlemcen</td><td>11</td><td>14</td><td>[23&#x02013;64]</td><td>5</td><td>7</td><td>3</td><td>4</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Total</bold></td><td>154</td><td>210</td><td>[18&#x02013;84]</td><td>67</td><td>89</td><td>70</td><td>69</td><td>69</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Geographical location of the study area (Locations names are written with red color).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>2.2</label><title>Participants</title><p id="p0045">In total, two hundred twenty-five informants were interviewed (n&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;225). This includes twenty-one traditional healers (n&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;21), seventy-three herbalists (n&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;73) and one hundred thirty-one traditional medicine practitioners and rural dwellers most of them were recommended by other locals when the topic came into question (n&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;131). The study was conducted in accordance with the requirements of the declarations of Helsinki. Therefore, semi-structured interviews based on note-taking while interviewing the informants (known as guided field walk) were conducted as described by <xref rid="b0370" ref-type="bibr">Martin (1995)</xref> in collecting the ethnomedicinal data. The interview was conducted without time limit or pressure to allow the informants to answer questions naturally following the International Society of Ethnobiology (ISE) code of ethics.</p><p id="p0050">It should be noted that cancer diagnosis is made by healthcare professionals and specialists in hospitals whereas traditional medicine is used to support the patients and provide care alongside conventional treatments. The study was approved by the scientific committee of the department of Natural and Life Sciences, Ibn Khaldoun University of Tiaret (Algeria). Interviews were performed through the local dialect of the informants and generally took place in public spaces. Informant consent was obtained prior to the interviews to authorize the collection, use and publication of data, then informants were asked to list natural products used to prevent and/or fight cancers and were requested to provide more detailed information about their uses (<xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Albuquerque et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p id="p0055">The questions covered during the interviews included, in addition to the sociodemographic information, popular and vernacular names of the species, parts used, mode of preparation and administration, dose, duration of treatment and knowledge about toxicity or side effects among other data. Local names were provided generally in Arabic and/or in Amazigh languages. All informants were asked whether they would be willing to provide a sample or to identify it in photographs if the material was not available.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0030"><label>3</label><title>Identification of medicinal species</title><p id="p0060">Collected plant specimens, as pointed out by the informants, were pressed and dried on site then the voucher specimens were identified and conserved in the laboratory at the faculty of Natural and Life Sciences, University of Tiaret (Algeria). The identity of plant and animal species reported by the informants was verified and recognized by specialists from the Department of Natural and Life Sciences and by the available different resources and bibliography (<xref rid="b0435" ref-type="bibr">Qu&#x000e9;zel, 1962-1963</xref>, <xref rid="b0405" ref-type="bibr">Ozenda, 1977</xref>, <xref rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr">Kaddem, 1990</xref>, <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Baba Aissa, 1991</xref>, <xref rid="b0570" ref-type="bibr">Wilson and Reeder, 2005</xref>, <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">Frost, 2020</xref>). The scientific names of plant species were also confirmed in accordance with the <xref rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr">International Index of Plant Name</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipni.org" id="ir005"><underline>http://www.ipni.org</underline></ext-link>) and the <xref rid="b0550" ref-type="bibr">Plant List database</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.theplantlist.org" id="ir010"><underline>http://www.theplantlist.org</underline></ext-link>) while animal species were confirmed in accordance with the <xref rid="b0385" ref-type="bibr">Animal Diversity Web</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.animaldiversity.org" id="ir015"><underline>https://www.animaldiversity.org</underline></ext-link>).</p><sec id="s0035"><label>3.1</label><title>Data analysis</title><p id="p0065">The obtained ethnopharmacological data were assigned into 21 cancer type categories, which have been reported by informants. The use report (UR) was assessed by calculating the total uses for the natural product by all informants within each use-category for that product (<xref rid="b0425" ref-type="bibr">Prance et al., 1987</xref>).<disp-formula id="e0005"><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">UR</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">uNC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">iN</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">UR</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ui</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="p0070">Frequency of Citation (FC) is calculated as the sum of informants that cite a use for the natural product (<xref rid="b0425" ref-type="bibr">Prance et al., 1987</xref>).<disp-formula id="e0010"><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">FC</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">iN</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">UR</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="p0075">The use value (UV) is a quantitative method that can be used in order to prove the relative importance of natural product known locally. It was calculated following the adaptation of <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">da Silva et al. (2014)</xref> using the following formula:<disp-formula id="e0015"><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">UV</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">UR</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ip</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ip</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where UV is&#x02009;the use value of the natural product p mentioned by the informant i; &#x003a3;UR <sub>ip</sub> is&#x02009;the number of uses reports of natural product s mentioned in each event by the informant i; n <sub>ip</sub> is&#x02009;the number of events in which the informant i cited the natural product p.</p><p id="p0080">The homogeneity on the informants&#x02019; knowledge was evaluated by calculating the Informants&#x02019; Consensus Factor (F<sub>IC</sub>) (<xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Andrade-Cetto and Heinrich, 2011</xref>) using the formula:<disp-formula id="e0020"><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">IC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ur</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ur</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Where N<sub>ur</sub> is the number of use reports for a particular cancer type and N<sub>t</sub> is the number of species cited for the same cancer by all informants. The values of the index range between 0 and 1, where values close to &#x02018;1&#x02032; indicate the highest level of consensus.</p><p id="p0085">The Medicinal Importance Index (MI) as a relative importance index of the use of plant species was calculated by dividing the number of use reports cited for a specific cancer by the number of species which have this use (<xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Carri&#x000f3; and Vall&#x000e8;s, 2012</xref>).</p><p id="p0090">All the statistical analyses were performed using the computing environment R (<xref rid="b0440" ref-type="bibr">R Development Core Team, 2013</xref>). Continuous data were represented as mean&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;standard deviation while frequencies and percentages were calculated for categorical variables.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0040"><label>4</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s0045"><label>4.1</label><title>Sociodemographic features</title><p id="p0095">In the current study, female participants accounted for 58% of the total. In general, the age of the informants is comprised between 18 and 84&#x0202f;years old. Around 18% of the total informants were illiterate whereas 24% of them reached just the primary school. In fact, about 38% of the informants were undergraduate or graduate from the university.</p></sec><sec id="s0050"><label>4.2</label><title>Plant taxa diversity</title><p id="p0100">Concerning herbal medicine, the obtained results have revealed the use of 113 medicinal plant species, belonging to 104 genera and 53 families, for cancer treatment (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The reported species were both gymnosperms (4 species, 4%) and angiosperms (109 species, 96%) including both monocotyledonous (12 species, 11%) and dicotyledonous (101 species, 89%) groups. Most of these medicinal plants are herbs (60%) while trees and shrubs represent 20% each.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Medicinal plant species used for cancer management in Algerian traditional medicines.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><bold>Plant family: - <italic>Species</italic></bold></th><th><bold>Voucher n&#x000b0;</bold></th><th><bold>Common name</bold></th><th><bold>Local name</bold></th><th><bold>FC</bold></th><th><bold>UR</bold></th><th><bold>Plant part used</bold></th><th><bold>Application</bold></th><th><bold>Cancer type</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>Amaranthaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Atriplex halimus</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK015</td><td>Sea orache</td><td><italic>Gtaf</italic></td><td>92</td><td>105</td><td>Leaf, flower</td><td>Infusion, powder</td><td>Thyroid, ovarian</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Haloxylon scoparium</italic> Pomel</td><td>EthTK051</td><td>Haloxylon</td><td><italic>Remth</italic></td><td>13</td><td>13</td><td>Aerial parts</td><td>Decoction</td><td>Liver</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Spinacia oleracea</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK017</td><td>Spinach</td><td><italic>Salq</italic></td><td>8</td><td>12</td><td>Root</td><td>raw, decoction</td><td>Breast, pancreatic, lung, prostate, skin</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Anacardiaceae</bold><italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK076</td><td>Mastic</td><td><italic>Dharw</italic></td><td>18</td><td>22</td><td>Leaf, fruit</td><td>Powder, oil, decoction</td><td>Digestive, skin</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Annonaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Annona cherimola</italic> Mill.</td><td>EthTK007</td><td>Cherimoya</td><td><italic>Cherimoya</italic></td><td>12</td><td>14</td><td>Fruit, seed</td><td>Raw, syrup</td><td>Breast, cervical</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Annona muricata</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK008</td><td>Sour Sop</td><td><italic>Qachta</italic></td><td>12</td><td>15</td><td>Fruit, seed</td><td>Raw, syrup</td><td>Breast, bladder, colorectal, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Apiaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Ammi visnaga</italic> (L.) Lam.</td><td>EthTK006</td><td>Visnaga</td><td><italic>Noukha</italic></td><td>14</td><td>14</td><td>Seed</td><td>Infusion</td><td>Breast</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Bunium incrassatum</italic> (Boiss.) Amo</td><td>EthTK021</td><td>Pig Nut</td><td><italic>Talghouda</italic></td><td>67</td><td>73</td><td>Tuber</td><td>Powder</td><td>Colorectal, thyroid</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Carum carvi</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK107</td><td>Caraway</td><td><italic>Karwya</italic></td><td>12</td><td>12</td><td>Seed</td><td>Infusion, powder</td><td>Uterus</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cuminum cyminum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK038</td><td>Cumin</td><td><italic>Kammun</italic></td><td>9</td><td>12</td><td>Seed</td><td>Decoction, infusion</td><td>Lung, neck</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Daucus sahariensis</italic> Murb.</td><td>EthTK040</td><td>Saharian Carrot</td><td><italic>Zrodya</italic></td><td>7</td><td>11</td><td>Root, seed</td><td>Decoction, infusion</td><td>Kidney, digestive, skin</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ferula vesceritensis</italic> Coss. &#x00026; Durieu ex Trab.</td><td>EthTK045</td><td>Foetida</td><td><italic>Hentit</italic></td><td>17</td><td>21</td><td>Resin</td><td>Maceration</td><td>Breast, colorectal</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Foeniculum vulgare</italic> Mill.</td><td>EthTK047</td><td>Fennel</td><td><italic>Besbass</italic></td><td>9</td><td>11</td><td>Leaf, seed</td><td>Infusion, decoction</td><td>Digestive, cervical</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic> (Mill.) Fuss</td><td>EthTK070</td><td>Parsley</td><td><italic>Ma&#x000e2;dnous</italic></td><td>17</td><td>23</td><td>Stem, leaf, fruit</td><td>Decoction</td><td>Bladder, brain, kidney</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Pimpinella anisum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK108</td><td>Anise</td><td><italic>Yansoun</italic></td><td>13</td><td>13</td><td>Fruits, seeds</td><td>Infusion, powder</td><td>Colorectal</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Thapsia garganica</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK098</td><td>Drias Plant</td><td><italic>Derias, Bounafaa</italic></td><td>12</td><td>15</td><td>Root</td><td>Decoction</td><td>Prostate, skin</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Arecaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Chamaerops humilis</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK029</td><td>Fan Palm</td><td><italic>Doum</italic></td><td>12</td><td>15</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Raw, powder</td><td>Breast, brain, blood</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Phoenix dactylifera</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK072</td><td>Date Palm</td><td><italic>Tmar</italic></td><td>16</td><td>20</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Raw</td><td>Breast, brain, lung</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Aristolochiaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Aristolochia longa</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK012</td><td>Snakeroot</td><td><italic>Berrostom</italic></td><td>131</td><td>153</td><td>Root, leaf</td><td>Powder</td><td>Breast, bone, digestive, prostate, ovary, uterus</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Asphodelaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Aloe succotrina</italic> Lam<italic>.</italic></td><td>EthTK005</td><td>Socotrine Aloe</td><td><italic>Mor-w-sbar</italic></td><td>18</td><td>24</td><td>Leaf, gel, juice</td><td>Decoction, oil, infusion</td><td>Breast, colorectal, esophageal, prostate, stomach, skin</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Asteraceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Artemisia campestris</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK013</td><td>Field wormwood</td><td><italic>Tguouffet</italic></td><td>67</td><td>84</td><td>Aerial parts</td><td>Infusion</td><td>Digestive</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Artemisia herba-alba</italic> Asso</td><td>EthTK014</td><td>white wormwood</td><td><italic>Chih</italic></td><td>96</td><td>119</td><td>Aerial parts</td><td>Infusion</td><td>Digestive, lung, kidney</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Carthamus tinctorius</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK025</td><td>Cartham</td><td><italic>Cartam</italic></td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>Leaf, seed</td><td>Oil</td><td>Breast</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Chamaemelum nobile</italic> (L.) All.</td><td>EthTK028</td><td>Roman chamomile</td><td><italic>Babounj Romani</italic></td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>Flower</td><td>Infusion</td><td>Breast</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Echinops spinosus</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK042</td><td>Echinops</td><td><italic>Tassekra</italic></td><td>8</td><td>8</td><td>Root, fruit, seed</td><td>Infusion, decoction</td><td>Breast</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK061</td><td>German Chamomile</td><td><italic>Babounj Berri</italic></td><td>14</td><td>24</td><td>Leaf, flower</td><td>Infusion, inhalation</td><td>Breast, liver, lung, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Matricaria pubescens</italic> (Desf.) Sch.Bip.</td><td>EthTK062</td><td>Chamomile</td><td><italic>Ouezouaza</italic></td><td>9</td><td>12</td><td>Leaf, flower</td><td>Infusion, inhalation</td><td>Breast, liver, lung, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Inula viscosa</italic> (L.) Aiton</td><td>EthTK053</td><td>Yellowhead</td><td><italic>Magramane</italic></td><td>11</td><td>13</td><td>Entire plant</td><td>Decoction, powder</td><td>Breast, bladder, kidney</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Onopordum macracanthum</italic> Schousb.</td><td>EthTK067</td><td>Thistle</td><td><italic>Chouk lahmar</italic></td><td>8</td><td>11</td><td>Flower, seed</td><td>Decoction, infusion</td><td>Colorectal, stomach</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Saussurea costus</italic> (Falc.) Lipsch.</td><td>EthTK090</td><td>Costus</td><td><italic>Qist el Hindi</italic></td><td>13</td><td>16</td><td>Rhizome</td><td>Decoction, powder</td><td>Digestive, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Silybum marianum</italic> (L.) Gaertn.</td><td>EthTK091</td><td>Milk Thistle</td><td><italic>Shouk el Jmal</italic></td><td>12</td><td>18</td><td>Stalk, seed</td><td>Juice, decoction</td><td>Colorectal, liver, prostate, skin</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Berberidaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Berberis vulgaris</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK016</td><td>Barberry</td><td><italic>Oud Ghriss</italic></td><td>119</td><td>142</td><td>Peel, bark</td><td>Decoction, powder</td><td>Breast, blood, bladder, stomach, skin, ovary</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Boraginaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Borago officinalis</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK018</td><td>Borage</td><td><italic>Lessane el ferd</italic></td><td>10</td><td>14</td><td>Stem, leaf, flower</td><td>Decoction</td><td>Colorectal, cervical, liver, lung, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Brassicaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Lepidium sativum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK057</td><td>Cress</td><td><italic>Horf, hab errchad</italic></td><td>11</td><td>15</td><td>Leaf, seed</td><td>Raw, powder</td><td>Breast, digestive, lung, uterus, ovary</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> subsp<italic>. capitata</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK020</td><td>Wild Cabbage</td><td><italic>Krom lahmar</italic></td><td>14</td><td>18</td><td>Leaf</td><td>Raw, juice, decoction</td><td>Breast, cervical, liver</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Burseraceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Boswellia sacra</italic> Flueck<italic>.</italic></td><td>EthTK019</td><td>Frankincense</td><td><italic>Loubane</italic></td><td>21</td><td>24</td><td>Resin</td><td>Oil</td><td>Breast, colorectal, skin</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Commiphora myrrha</italic> (Nees) Engl.</td><td>EthTK034</td><td>Myrrh</td><td><italic>El morr</italic></td><td>11</td><td>16</td><td>Soft sap</td><td>Raw, oil</td><td>Breast, liver, prostate, skin</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Cactaceae</bold><italic>Opuntia ficus-indica</italic> (L.) Mill.</td><td>EthTK109</td><td>Prickly pear</td><td><italic>Sabbar</italic></td><td>10</td><td>10</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Raw</td><td>Bladder</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Capparaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Capparis spinosa</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK023</td><td>Caper bush</td><td><italic>El Kabbar</italic></td><td>12</td><td>15</td><td>Root, fruit, flower</td><td>Powder, decoction</td><td>breast, bone, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Costaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Costus arabicus</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK035</td><td>Spiral Ginger</td><td><italic>Qist Al Bahri</italic></td><td>7</td><td>10</td><td>Rhizome</td><td>Infusion, decoction</td><td>Breast, lung</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Cucurbitaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Citrullus colocynthis</italic> (L.) Schrad.</td><td>EthTK031</td><td>Colocynth</td><td><italic>Handhal</italic></td><td>13</td><td>17</td><td>Stem, leaf, fruit</td><td>Decoction, pomade</td><td>Breast, colorectal, skin</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cucurbita maxima</italic> Duchesne</td><td>EthTK037</td><td>Winter Squash</td><td><italic>Kabouya</italic></td><td>80</td><td>117</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Raw, decoction</td><td>Digestive, prostate, skin</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ecballium elaterium</italic> (L.) A.Rich.</td><td>EthTK041</td><td>Squirting Cucumber</td><td><italic>Fegous el hmir</italic></td><td>14</td><td>17</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Raw, juice, oil</td><td>Breast, digestive, liver</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Cupressaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Juniperus phoenicea</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK054</td><td>Phoenicean juniper</td><td><italic>&#x000c2;r&#x000e2;ar</italic></td><td>12</td><td>15</td><td>Leaf, fruit</td><td>Infusion, decoction</td><td>Colorectal, liver, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tetraclinis articulata</italic> (Vahl) Mast.</td><td>EthTK097</td><td>Juniper gum</td><td><italic>Sandrouss</italic></td><td>13</td><td>17</td><td>Leaf, fruit</td><td>Infusion, decoction</td><td>Breast, cervical, liver, ovarian</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Ephedraceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Ephedra alata</italic> Decne.</td><td>EthTK043</td><td>Ephedra</td><td><italic>Elenda,</italic></td><td>92</td><td>102</td><td>Entire plant</td><td>Infusion, decoction</td><td>Breast, brain, colorectal, liver, lung</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Euphorbiaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Euphorbia guyoniana</italic> Boiss. &#x00026; Reut.</td><td>EthTK044</td><td>Euphorbia</td><td><italic>Lobina</italic></td><td>11</td><td>14</td><td>Aerial parts</td><td>Powder, decoction</td><td>Breast, ovarian, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Phyllanthus emblica</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK073</td><td>Emblica</td><td><italic>El Amlaj</italic></td><td>7</td><td>12</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Raw, juice, powder</td><td>Cervical, lung</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Fabaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Arachis hypogaea</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK010</td><td>Peanut</td><td><italic>Foul Soudani</italic></td><td>18</td><td>18</td><td>Seed</td><td>Raw</td><td>Prostate</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ceratonia siliqua</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK027</td><td>Carob</td><td><italic>Kharroub</italic></td><td>12</td><td>12</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Raw</td><td>Lung</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Glycyrrhiza glabra</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK049</td><td>Liquorice</td><td><italic>Erq-Essous</italic></td><td>21</td><td>23</td><td>Rhizome, root</td><td>Powder</td><td>Blood, lung</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Glycine</italic> max (L.) Merr.</td><td>EthTK048</td><td>Soybean</td><td><italic>Foul el Souya</italic></td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>Seed</td><td>Oil, decoction</td><td>Breast, ovary</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK071</td><td>Bean</td><td><italic>Loubya</italic></td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>Seed</td><td>Raw</td><td>Breast</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Retama raetam</italic> (Forssk.) Webb</td><td>EthTK082</td><td>Retam</td><td><italic>Retem</italic></td><td>12</td><td>16</td><td>Root, leaf</td><td>Powder, decoction</td><td>Breast, cervical</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Senegalia senegal</italic> (L.) Britton</td><td>EthTK110</td><td>Gum arabic tree</td><td><italic>Samgh arabi</italic></td><td>14</td><td>14</td><td>Sap</td><td>Raw</td><td>breast</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Trigonella foenum-graecum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK101</td><td>Fenugreek</td><td><italic>Helba</italic></td><td>108</td><td>132</td><td>Seed</td><td>Raw, infusion</td><td>Breast, brain, digestive, lung</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Gentianaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Centaurium erythraea</italic> Rafn</td><td>EthTK026</td><td>Centaury</td><td><italic>Mararet el hnech</italic></td><td>22</td><td>26</td><td>Aerial parts</td><td>Powder</td><td>Breast, digestive</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Iridaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Crocus sativus</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK036</td><td>Saffron crocus</td><td><italic>Za&#x000e2;frane</italic></td><td>16</td><td>19</td><td>Flower, pistil</td><td>Raw, infusion</td><td>Colorectal, kidney, liver, lung, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Lamiaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Ajuga iva</italic> (L.) Schreb.</td><td>EthTK002</td><td>Herb Ivy</td><td><italic>Chendgoura</italic></td><td>18</td><td>18</td><td>Stem, leaf, flower</td><td>Powder</td><td>Lung</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Lavandula antineae</italic> Maire</td><td>EthTK055</td><td>Lavender</td><td><italic>Khozama</italic></td><td>16</td><td>18</td><td>Leaf, flower</td><td>Infusion, oil</td><td>Neck, urogenital, stomach, skin</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Marrubium deserti</italic> (No&#x000eb;) Coss.</td><td>EthTK060</td><td>Horehound</td><td><italic>Dja&#x000e2;da</italic></td><td>67</td><td>74</td><td>Root, leaf</td><td>Decoction, infusion, ingestion</td><td>Breast, digestive, ovary</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Marrubium vulgare</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK111</td><td>Horehound</td><td><italic>Merriwet</italic></td><td>39</td><td>44</td><td>Stem, leaf</td><td>Decoction, infusion, ingestion</td><td>Breast, digestive, ovary</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Mentha spicata</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK063</td><td>Spearmint</td><td><italic>Na&#x000e2;na&#x000e2;</italic></td><td>16</td><td>20</td><td>Stem, leaf</td><td>Infusion, oil</td><td>Breast, digestive, kidney</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK085</td><td>Rosemary</td><td><italic>Klil, Halhal, Azir</italic></td><td>15</td><td>18</td><td>Stem, leaf, flower</td><td>Raw, infusion, inhalation</td><td>Breast, cervical, digestive, lung</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Salvia verbenaca</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK089</td><td>Wild clary</td><td><italic>Kass&#x000e2;in ra&#x000e2;ie el hmam</italic></td><td>17</td><td>22</td><td>Aerial parts</td><td>Infusion, decoction</td><td>Breast, blood, colorectal, liver, lung, intestine</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK100</td><td>Thyme</td><td><italic>Za&#x000e2;tar</italic></td><td>18</td><td>21</td><td>Entire plant</td><td>Infusion</td><td>Digestive</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Origanum floribundum</italic> Munby</td><td>EthTK068</td><td>Oregano</td><td><italic>Za&#x000e2;tar berri</italic></td><td>24</td><td>27</td><td>Stem, leaf, flower</td><td>Infusion, inhalation</td><td>Breast, digestive, kidney, lung</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Lauraceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Cinnamomum verum</italic> J.Presl</td><td>EthTK030</td><td>Cinnamon</td><td><italic>Qarfa</italic></td><td>15</td><td>17</td><td>Peel, bark</td><td>Decoction</td><td>Breast, lung</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Liliaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Allium cepa</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK003</td><td>Onion</td><td><italic>Bsal</italic></td><td>92</td><td>108</td><td>Bulb</td><td>Juice, decoction,</td><td>Lung, stomach</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Allium sativum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK004</td><td>Garlic</td><td><italic>Thoum</italic></td><td>81</td><td>103</td><td>Bulb</td><td>Juice, decoction</td><td>Breast, blood, lung, esophageal, stomach</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Linaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Linum usitatissimum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK058</td><td>Flax</td><td><italic>Zerri&#x000e2;at el Kettane</italic></td><td>19</td><td>25</td><td>Seed</td><td>Raw, powder</td><td>Breast, blood, digestive, liver, ovary</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Lycopodiaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Lycopodium clavatum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK059</td><td>Clubmoss</td><td><italic>Kebrita</italic></td><td>12</td><td>16</td><td>Leaf, spore</td><td>Powder, oil</td><td>Brain, colorectal, liver, lung, oral, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Lythraceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Lawsonia inermis</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK056</td><td>Henna</td><td><italic>Henna</italic></td><td>11</td><td>13</td><td>Leaf</td><td>Powder, paste</td><td>Breast, skin</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Moraceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus carica</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK046</td><td>Fig</td><td><italic>Karmous</italic></td><td>13</td><td>15</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Raw</td><td>Digestive, lung</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Moringaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Moringa peregrina</italic> (Forssk.) Fiori</td><td>EthTK064</td><td>Moringa</td><td><italic>Hab el Baan</italic></td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>Stem, leaf</td><td>Raw, powder, decoction</td><td>Colorectal, liver</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Myrtaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Syzygium aromaticum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK095</td><td>Clove</td><td><italic>Qronfol</italic></td><td>15</td><td>19</td><td>Flower</td><td>Raw, oil, powder</td><td>Liver, lung, oral, thyroid</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Oleaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Olea europaea</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK066</td><td>Olive</td><td><italic>Zitoune</italic></td><td>35</td><td>44</td><td>Leaf, fruit</td><td>Extraction</td><td>Breast, lung</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Pedaliaceae</bold><italic>Sesamum indicum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK112</td><td>Sesame</td><td><italic>Sanouj</italic></td><td>11</td><td>14</td><td>Seed</td><td>Raw, oil, powder</td><td>Breast, uterus, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Pinaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Pinus halepensis</italic> Mill<italic>.</italic></td><td>EthTK074</td><td>Aleppo Pine</td><td><italic>Snawbar</italic></td><td>7</td><td>11</td><td>Seed</td><td>Extraction</td><td>Esophageal, stomach</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Piperaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Piper nigrum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK075</td><td>Black Pepper</td><td><italic>Felfel k&#x02019;&#x01e25;al</italic></td><td>15</td><td>19</td><td>Fruit, seed</td><td>Powder</td><td>Breast, stomach, pancreas</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Plumbaginaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Plumbago europaea</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK077</td><td>Plumbago</td><td><italic>Siwak er&#x000e2;ayen</italic></td><td>9</td><td>12</td><td>Entire plant</td><td>Powder, decoction</td><td>Lung, skin</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Poaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK052</td><td>Barley</td><td><italic>Zra&#x000e2;, Che&#x000ea;ir</italic></td><td>14</td><td>18</td><td>Seed</td><td>Raw, juice, powder</td><td>Colorectal, liver, stomach, uterus, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Stipa tenacissima</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK094</td><td>Alfa</td><td><italic>Halfa</italic></td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>Leaf</td><td>Powder</td><td>Skin</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK102</td><td>Wheat</td><td><italic>Guemh</italic></td><td>19</td><td>21</td><td>Entire plant, seed</td><td>Raw, juice, powder</td><td>Breast, colorectal</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Polygonaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Rheum palmatum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK084</td><td>Rhubarb</td><td><italic>Rawend</italic></td><td>11</td><td>12</td><td>Rhizome</td><td>Powder</td><td>Digestive, oral</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Punicaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Punica granatum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK081</td><td>Pomegranate</td><td><italic>Rommane</italic></td><td>54</td><td>64</td><td>Root, leaf, fruit, peel</td><td>Raw, syrup, juice, decoction</td><td>Breast, brain, oral, stomach, prostate, colorectal</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Ranunculaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK065</td><td>Devil in the bush</td><td><italic>Habet el Baraka</italic></td><td>140</td><td>160</td><td>Seed</td><td>Raw, decoction</td><td>Breast, blood, colorectal, liver, lung, uterus, skin</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Rhamnaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Rhamnus alaternus</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK083</td><td>Buckthorn</td><td><italic>Meliless</italic></td><td>12</td><td>12</td><td>Leaf</td><td>Infusion</td><td>Breast</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ziziphus lotus</italic> (L.) Lam.</td><td>EthTK106</td><td>Jujube</td><td><italic>Sedra</italic></td><td>12</td><td>18</td><td>Leaf, flower, fruit</td><td>Raw, infusion</td><td>Breast, colorectal, lung</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Rosaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Crataegus azarolus</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK113</td><td>Azarole</td><td><italic>Za&#x000e2;rour</italic></td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>Leaf, fruit</td><td>Infusion, decoction</td><td>Colorectal</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Prunus armeniaca</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK079</td><td>Apricot</td><td><italic>Mechmech</italic></td><td>12</td><td>16</td><td>Root, leaf, flower, seed</td><td>Decoction, powder, oil</td><td>Breast, digestive, liver</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Prunus amygdalus</italic> Batsch</td><td>EthTK078</td><td>Almond</td><td><italic>Louz el mor</italic></td><td>18</td><td>23</td><td>Root, leaf, seed</td><td>Raw, powder, decoction</td><td>Breast, bladder, colorectal, oral, uterus</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Prunus persica</italic> (L.) Batsch</td><td>EthTK080</td><td>Peach</td><td><italic>Khoukh</italic></td><td>80</td><td>90</td><td>Root, leaf, seed</td><td>Raw, powder, decoction</td><td>Breast, digestive</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Rubus fruticosus</italic> G.N.Jones</td><td>EthTK086</td><td>Blackberry</td><td><italic>Alla&#x000ef;ak</italic></td><td>8</td><td>10</td><td>Root, leaf, fruit</td><td>Raw, powder, decoction</td><td>Colorectal, oral</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Rubus idaeus</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK087</td><td>Raspberry</td><td><italic>Toute barri</italic></td><td>12</td><td>14</td><td>Leaf, fruit</td><td>Raw, powder, decoction</td><td>Colorectal, oral, ovary</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Rubiaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Coffea canephora</italic> Pierre ex A.Froehner</td><td>EthTK033</td><td>Robusta coffee</td><td><italic>Qahwa</italic></td><td>9</td><td>11</td><td>Seed</td><td>Raw, infusion</td><td>Colorectal, oral, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Rutaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Citrus limon</italic> (L.) Osbeck</td><td>EthTK032</td><td>Lemon</td><td><italic>Limone</italic></td><td>100</td><td>123</td><td>Fruit, peel</td><td>Juice, infusion</td><td>Breast, digestive, lung, liver, skin</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK088</td><td>Fringed rue</td><td><italic>Fidjel</italic></td><td>11</td><td>14</td><td>Stem, leaf, flower</td><td>Decoction</td><td>Colorectal, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Sapindaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Aesculus hippocastanum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK001</td><td>Horse-chestnut</td><td><italic>Kastal-hindi</italic></td><td>9</td><td>11</td><td>Leaf, bark, seed</td><td>Powder, decoction</td><td>Breast, liver</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Sapotaceae</bold><italic>Argania spinosa</italic> (L.) Skeels</td><td>EthTK011</td><td>Argan</td><td><italic>Argan</italic></td><td>14</td><td>17</td><td>Seed</td><td>Oil</td><td>Breast, ovary, skin</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Solanaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Capsicum annuum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK024</td><td>Pepper</td><td><italic>Sasafinda</italic></td><td>14</td><td>19</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Raw, decoction</td><td>Bladder, digestive, lung, skin</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum nigrum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK092</td><td>Nightshade</td><td><italic>Aneb edhib</italic></td><td>17</td><td>21</td><td>Leaf, fruit</td><td>Raw, decoction</td><td>Breast, colorectal, cervical</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK093</td><td>Potato</td><td><italic>Batata</italic></td><td>8</td><td>12</td><td>Tuber</td><td>Raw, maceration</td><td>Breast, colorectal, cervical, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tamaricaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Tamarix africana</italic> Poir<italic>.</italic></td><td>EthTK096</td><td>African tamarisk</td><td><italic>Tarfa</italic></td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>Stem, leaf, flower</td><td>Decoction, powder</td><td>Cervical</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Theaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> (L.) Kuntze</td><td>EthTK022</td><td>Tea</td><td><italic>Chay</italic></td><td>15</td><td>19</td><td>Leaf</td><td>Infusion</td><td>Breast, lung, ovary, skin</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Thymelaeaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Thymelaea microphylla</italic> Meisn.</td><td>EthTK099</td><td>Thymelaea</td><td><italic>Methnan</italic></td><td>13</td><td>15</td><td>Stem, leaf, flower</td><td>Decoction</td><td>Cervical, uterus</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Aquilaria malaccensis</italic> Lam<italic>.</italic></td><td>EthTK009</td><td>Agar wood</td><td><italic>Oud</italic></td><td>7</td><td>11</td><td>Stem, leaf, flower</td><td>Oil, decoction</td><td>Lung, thyroid</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Tiliaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Grewia tenax</italic> (Forssk.) Fiori</td><td>EthTK050</td><td>White Crossberry</td><td><italic>Godaym</italic></td><td>26</td><td>80</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Raw</td><td>Breast, digestive, liver, lung, prostate, ovary, skin</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Urticaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Urtica dioica</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK103</td><td>Nettle</td><td><italic>Herrig</italic></td><td>22</td><td>25</td><td>Entire plant</td><td>Infusion, decoction</td><td>Breast, bone, stomach, prostate</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Vitaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK104</td><td>Grape vine</td><td><italic>Zbib</italic></td><td>23</td><td>23</td><td>Leaf, fruit</td><td>Raw, powder</td><td>Breast</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Zingiberaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK039</td><td>Turmeric</td><td><italic>Curcum</italic></td><td>112</td><td>133</td><td>Rhizome</td><td>Powder, decoction</td><td>Breast, bone, lung, digestive, uterus</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> Roscoe</td><td>EthTK105</td><td>Ginger</td><td><italic>Zanjabyl</italic></td><td>88</td><td>116</td><td>Rhizome</td><td>Powder, infusion</td><td>Breast, colorectal, liver, lung</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Zygophyllaceae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Peganum harmala</italic> L.</td><td>EthTK069</td><td>Harmel</td><td><italic>Harmel</italic></td><td>66</td><td>87</td><td>Seed</td><td>Raw, powder</td><td>Breast, brain</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0105">The Asteraceae family was represented by the highest number of species (11 species), followed by the Apiaceae (10 species), Lamiaceae (9 species), Fabaceae (8 species) and Rosaceae (6 species) families respectively. Amaranthaceae, Cucurbitaceae, Poaceae and Solanaceae families were represented by three species each while Annonaceae, Arecaceae, Brassicaceae, Burseraceae, Cupressaceae, Euphorbiaceae, Liliaceae, Rutaceae, Thymelaeaceae and Zingiberaceae families were represented by only two species each. The other families were represented by one species each (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).<fig id="f0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Plant families employed for cancer therapy in Algerian traditional medicines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p><p id="p0110">Several reported plant species are cultivated and used either for direct consumption or vended commercially such as <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> subsp<italic>. capitata</italic> L., <italic>Cucurbita maxima</italic> L.<italic>, Hordeum vulgare</italic> L.<italic>, Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.<italic>, Piper nigrum</italic> L., <italic>Prunus sp</italic>. and <italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> L. among others. However, many other species are grown around the homesteads or along rural infrastructures like <italic>Echinops spinosus</italic> L., <italic>Marrubium vulgare</italic> L., <italic>Olea europaea</italic> L., <italic>Onopordum macracanthum</italic> Schousb, <italic>Thapsia garganica</italic> L. and <italic>Urtica dioica</italic> L. Other species are used for their ornamental values, shade or for feeding human or livestock such as <italic>Atriplex halimus</italic> L., <italic>Ficus carica</italic> L. and <italic>Juniperus</italic> sp. Interestingly, several species are belonging to the Algerian steppe region and Sahara namely <italic>Artemisia</italic> sp., <italic>Ajuga iva</italic> (L.) Schreb, <italic>Haloxylon scoparium</italic> Pomel, <italic>Marrubium deserti</italic> (No&#x000eb;) Coss., <italic>Origanum floribundum</italic> Munby, <italic>Retama raetam</italic> (Forssk.) Webb, <italic>Stipa tenacissima</italic> L., <italic>Thymelaea microphylla</italic> Meisn., <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L., <italic>Peganum harmala</italic> L. and <italic>Phoenix dactylifera</italic> L.</p><p id="p0115">Together with non-native plants, many endemic plant species from Algeria, or Algeria, Morocco and Tunisia, have been reported i.e. Ammi visnaga (L.) Lam., <italic>Argania spinosa</italic> (L.) Skeels, <italic>Artemisia campestris</italic> L., <italic>Artemisia herba-alba</italic> Asso, <italic>Atriplex halimus</italic> L., Bunium incrassatum (Boiss.) Amo, <italic>Carthamus tinctorius</italic> L., <italic>Citrullus colocynthis</italic> (L.) Schrad, <italic>Ferula vesceritensis</italic> Coss. &#x00026; Durieu ex Trab., <italic>Lavandula antineae</italic> Maire, <italic>Marrubium deserti</italic> (No&#x000eb;) Coss., <italic>Matricaria pubescens</italic> Schultz, <italic>Origanum floribundum</italic> Munby, Petroselinum crispum (Mill.) Fuss, <italic>Salvia verbenaca</italic> L., <italic>Tetraclinis articulata</italic> (Vahl) Mast. and <italic>Thymelaea microphylla</italic> Meisn. The use of exogenous species like <italic>Annona</italic> sp., <italic>Boswellia sacra</italic> Flueck, <italic>Saussurea costus</italic> (Falc.) Lipsh. and <italic>Syzygium aromaticum</italic> L. was also reported.</p></sec><sec id="s0055"><label>4.3</label><title>Quantitative ethnopharmacology</title><p id="p0120">On the basis of citation frequency, the most cited plant species by the informants to treat any cancer type were respectively <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L. (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;131), <italic>Aristolochia longa</italic> L. (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;118), <italic>Berberis vulgaris</italic> L. (CF&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;111), <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L. (CF&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;107), <italic>Trigonella foenum-graecum</italic> L. (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;102), Citrus limon (L.) Osbeck (CF&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;97), <italic>Artemisia herba-alba</italic> Asso (CF&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;92), <italic>Ephedra alata</italic> Decne (CF&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;91), <italic>Atriplex halimus</italic> L. and <italic>Allium cepa</italic> L. (CF&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;90). Furthermore, on the basis of use reports and use value indices for each species, Nigella sativa L. was the most reported/important plant species (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;152, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.54) followed by <italic>Aristolochia longa</italic> L. (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;144, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.51), <italic>Berberis vulgaris</italic> L. (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;142, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.51), <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;121, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.43), <italic>Trigonella foenum-graecum</italic> L. (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;119, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.43), Citrus limon Decne (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;120, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.43), <italic>Artemisia herba-alba</italic> Asso (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;115, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.41) and Allium cepa L. (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;107, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.38). However, the less cited plant species with the lowest use reports were Stipa tenacissima L. and Phaseolus vulgaris L. (CF&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;3, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;3, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.01) (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0060"><label>4.4</label><title>Plant parts and modes of use</title><p id="p0125">The plants species were used entirely or only the parts supposedly interesting were selected by the informants. Overall, leaves were the most commonly used part by around 26% followed by fruits (15%), flowers (14%) and seeds (14%) as the next most likely plant parts to be used. Stems and roots are used by around 11% and 9% respectively however, the other parts are the least used by the informants (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).<fig id="f0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Frequency of plant parts used for cancer therapy in Algerian traditional medicines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p><p id="p0130">Various methods of use of the medicinal plants&#x02019; parts were reported; about 19% of the plants used by the informants were consumed directly as raw material. However, most often, a decoction was prepared (27%) which involved boiling the crushed plant part in water till the volume will be reduced by around the half to extract the juice to be administered orally. Moreover, 18% of the reported plant parts were crushed or powdered while 16% were used as infusion. Herbal infusions take less time to prepare than decoction, but the herbs should stand for 10&#x0202f;min in hot water to steep thoroughly while tightly covered. In other cases, plant part was dried then administered orally as pills. Besides, seeds, if not administered orally, were used for oil extraction (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>).<fig id="f0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Frequency of methods of use of medicinal plants parts for cancer therapy in Algerian traditional medicines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0065"><label>4.5</label><title>Animal species diversity</title><p id="p0135">Concerning zootherapy, the use of several species belonging to the animal kingdom and their derived products was reported for cancer treatment in Algerian traditional medicines (<xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The consumption of various wild animal species such as <italic>Atelerix algirus</italic> (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;12, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;12, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.04), <italic>Cancer pagurus</italic> (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;28, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;28, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.10), <italic>Corallium rubrum</italic> (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;31, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;31, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.11) and <italic>Varanus griseus</italic> (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;14, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;24, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.05) has been recommended for the treatment of all types of cancer. In addition, the skin of the Sahara frog <italic>Pelophylax saharicus</italic> was reported for the first time for the treatment of visible tumors and skin cancer via external application (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;21, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;36, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.08). Furthermore, some informants have stated even the consumption of the excrement of <italic>Hystrix cristata</italic> (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;12, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;19, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.04) and the use of <italic>Atelerix algirus</italic> thorns as decoction since they believe on their therapeutical virtues.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0015"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Animal species used for cancer management in Algerian traditional medicines.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><bold>Animal family: - <italic>Species</italic></bold></th><th><bold>Common name</bold></th><th><bold>Local name</bold></th><th><bold>FC</bold></th><th><bold>UR</bold></th><th><bold>UV</bold></th><th><bold>Part used</bold></th><th><bold>Application</bold></th><th><bold>Cancer type</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold>Apidae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Apis mellifera</italic></td><td>Honey bee</td><td><italic>Nahl</italic></td><td>181</td><td>194</td><td>0.65</td><td>Honey</td><td>Raw, infusion</td><td>All types</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Bovidae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Bos Taurus</italic></td><td>Cow</td><td>Bakara</td><td>31</td><td>31</td><td>0.11</td><td>Colostrum</td><td>Raw</td><td>All types</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Capra aegagrus hircus</italic></td><td>Goat</td><td><italic>Maaza</italic></td><td>43</td><td>43</td><td>0.15</td><td>Milk</td><td>Beverage</td><td>All types</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td>39</td><td>39</td><td>0.14</td><td>Butter</td><td>Beverage</td><td>All types</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Camelidae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Camelus dromedaries</italic></td><td>Camel</td><td><italic>Naqa</italic></td><td>53</td><td>53</td><td>0.19</td><td>Urine</td><td>Beverage</td><td>All types</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td>53</td><td>53</td><td>0.19</td><td>Milk</td><td>Beverage</td><td>All types</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Cancridae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Cancer pagurus</italic></td><td>Edible crab</td><td><italic>Boujniba</italic></td><td>28</td><td>28</td><td>0.10</td><td>Entire animal</td><td>Eat</td><td>All types</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Coralliidae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Corallium rubrum</italic></td><td>Red coral</td><td><italic>Morjane</italic></td><td>31</td><td>31</td><td>0.11</td><td>Entire animal</td><td>Eat</td><td>All types</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Erinaceidae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Atelerix algirus</italic></td><td>Algerian hedgehog</td><td><italic>Guenfoud</italic></td><td>12</td><td>18</td><td>0.04</td><td>Entire animal</td><td>Eat</td><td>All types</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td>12</td><td>18</td><td>0.04</td><td>Thorns</td><td>Decoction</td><td>All types</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Hystricidae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Hystrix cristata</italic></td><td>Crested porcupine</td><td><italic>Dhorbane</italic></td><td>12</td><td>19</td><td>0.04</td><td>Excrement</td><td>Eat</td><td>All types</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Ranidae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Pelophylax saharicus</italic></td><td>Sahara frog</td><td><italic>Jerana</italic></td><td>21</td><td>36</td><td>0.08</td><td>Skin</td><td>External application</td><td>Visible tumors, skin</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Varanidae</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Varanus griseus</italic></td><td>Desert monitor</td><td><italic>Werl sahraoui</italic></td><td>14</td><td>24</td><td>0.05</td><td>Entire animal</td><td>Eat</td><td>All types</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0070"><label>4.6</label><title>Other natural products</title><p id="p0140">It has been also reported the use and consumption of domestic animal by-products like the fresh cow colostrum (<italic>Bos Taurus</italic>; FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;31, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;31, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.11) and goat milk (<italic>Capra aegagrus hircus</italic>; FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;43, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;43, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.15). The goat butter was used as well for the preparation of mixtures. It should be noted that, in many cases, milk and urine of <italic>Camelus dromedarius</italic> were recommended for beverage in mixture mainly by informants living in the Sahara (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;53, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;53, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.19).</p><p id="p0145">Remarkably, honey bee was the most cited natural product by the informants in the present study (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;181, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;194, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.65). Informants have reported mainly honey produced from <italic>Ziziphus lotus</italic> flowers but most of them have stated that any pure honey could be of interest. Honey was administered fresh or in infusion, alone or in combination with the other natural products from different origins. The religious influence of many practices resulted in the multiple uses of the holy water &#x02018;Zamzam&#x02019; for drink or mixtures as a potential therapeutic agent for the preparation of various (FC&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;110, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;110, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.43).</p></sec><sec id="s0075"><label>4.7</label><title>Monotherapy versus the use of mixtures</title><p id="p0150">Interestingly, many informants have reported the use of mixed plant-based preparations with chemical cancer drugs. It is important to note that the mixture of two or more ingredients was the most common mode of use described among the informants. The storage and consumption of dried medicinal plants was also reported especially for species which are not available throughout the year. The most indicated remedies consisted of mixtures of more than one natural product associated with additives or excipients such as honey, olive oil, milk, butter, vinegar, animal fat or even Zamzam water. These additives are supposed to transport the remedies while diminishing the bitterness and severe taste to make mixtures more palatable.</p></sec><sec id="s0080"><label>4.8</label><title>Cancers&#x02019; category and natural products</title><p id="p0155">In general, the reported animal species and their derived by-products were used for all types of cancers and were not specifically indicated for only a definite type of cancer except for <italic>Pelophylax saharicus</italic> skin&#x02019; which was preconized for external application on cancerous skins and visible tumors. Nevertheless, various aromatic and medicinal plant species were used to manage specific types of cancer. Accordingly, the highest number of plant species was reported to manage breast (65 species), colorectal (60 species), liver (50 species), stomach (45 species), esophageal (41 species) and oral (42 species) cancers while the lowest number of species (11 species) was reported for bone cancer treatment (<xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0020"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Informants' Consensus Factor (F<sub>IC</sub>) and Medicinal Importance Index (MI) of medicinal plants used for cancer management in Algerian traditional medicines.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><bold>Cancer</bold></th><th><bold>Use reports</bold></th><th><bold>Plant species</bold></th><th><bold>F<sub>IC</sub></bold></th><th><bold>IMI</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Breast</td><td>678</td><td>65</td><td>0.91</td><td>10.43</td></tr><tr><td>Colorectal</td><td>565</td><td>60</td><td>0.90</td><td>9.42</td></tr><tr><td>Stomach</td><td>401</td><td>45</td><td>0.89</td><td>8.91</td></tr><tr><td>Liver</td><td>355</td><td>50</td><td>0.86</td><td>7.10</td></tr><tr><td>Esophageal</td><td>133</td><td>41</td><td>0.70</td><td>3.24</td></tr><tr><td>Oral</td><td>116</td><td>42</td><td>0.64</td><td>2.76</td></tr><tr><td>Lung</td><td>356</td><td>39</td><td>0.89</td><td>9.13</td></tr><tr><td>Pancreas</td><td>84</td><td>35</td><td>0.59</td><td>2.40</td></tr><tr><td>Intestine</td><td>114</td><td>40</td><td>0.65</td><td>2.85</td></tr><tr><td>Prostate</td><td>99</td><td>33</td><td>0.67</td><td>3.00</td></tr><tr><td>Skin</td><td>120</td><td>29</td><td>0.76</td><td>4.14</td></tr><tr><td>Blood</td><td>88</td><td>26</td><td>0.71</td><td>3.38</td></tr><tr><td>Brain</td><td>69</td><td>22</td><td>0.69</td><td>3.14</td></tr><tr><td>Ovary</td><td>70</td><td>18</td><td>0.75</td><td>3.89</td></tr><tr><td>Cervical</td><td>73</td><td>22</td><td>0.71</td><td>3.32</td></tr><tr><td>Kidney</td><td>71</td><td>16</td><td>0.79</td><td>4.44</td></tr><tr><td>Thyroid</td><td>99</td><td>16</td><td>0.85</td><td>6.19</td></tr><tr><td>Uterus</td><td>53</td><td>16</td><td>0.71</td><td>3.31</td></tr><tr><td>Bladder</td><td>52</td><td>12</td><td>0.78</td><td>4.33</td></tr><tr><td>Bone</td><td>29</td><td>11</td><td>0.64</td><td>2.64</td></tr><tr><td>Neck</td><td>23</td><td>12</td><td>0.50</td><td>1.92</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0160">The consistency of the use-reports within each cancer category was evaluated numerically using the informants&#x02019; consensus factor (C<sub>IF</sub>). There was a great agreement amongst informants about ethnomedicinal utilizations of plant species for specific cancer with F<sub>IC</sub> values ranging between 0.50 and 0.91 revealing high homogeneity in the reported cancer types (<xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The obtained higher values reflect the important number of use reports for each particular cancer type i.e. breast (F<sub>IC</sub>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.91, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;675), colorectal (F<sub>IC</sub>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.90, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;563), stomach (F<sub>IC</sub>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.89, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;393), liver (F<sub>IC</sub>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.86, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;352), lung (F<sub>IC</sub>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.89, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;346) and esophageal (F<sub>IC</sub>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.70, UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;133). However, the medicinal importance index values ranged from 1.92 to 10.38; the higher values were recorded respectively for breast cancer (IMI&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;10.38), colorectal (IMI&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;9.38), lung (IMI&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;8.87), stomach (IMI&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;8.73), liver (IMI&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;7.04). However, the lower values were recorded for oral (IMI&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;2.76), bone (IMI&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;2.45), pancreas (IMI&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;2.37) and neck cancer (IMI&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;1.92) (<xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0085"><label>4.9</label><title>Dosage</title><p id="p0165">Dosage varied significantly between one informant and another which made difficult establish standards or guidelines of uses. Usually, the prescribed dosages are undertaken by hand palm, tablespoon, little finger index, coffee cup or glass measures or weight. The commonly described dose by informants for decoction and infusion was a glass measure (100 to 150&#x0202f;mL) which could be mixed with honey but not with sugar and administered orally two to three times per day before breakfast or after lunch and dinner. For mixtures and preparations, ingredients are ground and crushed then well mixed with some additives (honey, olive oil, butter, milk, water&#x02026;) in order to obtain a paste. This paste is designed for the formation of tablets and pills or it is stored in hermetically closed glass jars. For certain preparations, informants recommend that the mixture should be combined with additives just before consumption. Patients usually take one to three tablet or tablespoon three times per day.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0090"><label>5</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0170">Algerian populations hold enormous traditional knowledge and practices on natural products that are being used for the treatment and management of various ailments including cancer (<xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Azzi et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">Chermat and Gharzouli, 2015</xref>). This precious knowledge was handed down through apprenticeship from earlier generations to descendants and through the intermingling of diverse ethnicities and civilizations in North Africa (<xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Bouasla and Bouasla, 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">Bouzabata and Mahomoodally, 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0175">In the present study, 128 natural products have been recognized traditionally used for cancer treatment; 113 medicinal plant species were reported along with 10 animal species besides various products and by-products such as honey, olive oil, thorns, urine, milk, animal fat and even the holy water &#x02018;Zamzam&#x02019; (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><p id="p0180">Besides, the use of natural products for cancer treatment might be explained by the failure of the standard cancer therapy, or because of the inaccessibility to a standard treatment (<xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 2017</xref>). In fact, some natural products from various sources are known to have the ability to enhance several physiological and molecular pathways which are required for cancer treatment (<xref rid="b0505" ref-type="bibr">Sharifi-Rad et al., 2019</xref>). In addition, it is well known that drought and temperature changes alter the metabolic composition of plants and increase the metabolites related to abiotic stress tolerance (<xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">Chorfi and Ta&#x000ef;bi, 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0535" ref-type="bibr">Ta&#x000ef;bi et al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0540" ref-type="bibr">Ta&#x000ef;bi et al., 2017</xref>). Consequently, the abiotic stress occurring under arid conditions increase the amount of antioxidant compounds in plants (<xref rid="b0545" ref-type="bibr">Ta&#x000ef;bi et al., 2016</xref>) which might explain partially some of the alleged anticancer properties of the reported medicinal plants belonging to steppe and Sahara.</p><sec id="s0095"><label>5.1</label><title>Plant taxa diversity</title><p id="p0185">The diversity of plant taxa inventoried throughout the present study for cancer management in Algeria, represented by 113 plant species distributed within 104 genera and 53 families, demonstrates the importance of the local populational knowledge in the use of traditional medicines. Previous ethnobotanical studies carried out in Algeria, for not specific ailments, have reported 58 plant species (50 genera and 27 families) in the region of M&#x02019;sila (east Algeria) (<xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Boudjelal et al., 2013</xref>), 41 plant species (37 genera and 24 families) in the region of Hodna (east Algeria) (<xref rid="b0485" ref-type="bibr">Sarri et al., 2015</xref>), 141 plant species (125 genera and 54 families) in the region of Mascara (north west Algeria) (<xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Benarba et al., 2015</xref>), 98 species (90 genera and 48 families) in the region of Tizi-ouzou (north center Algeria) (<xref rid="b0375" ref-type="bibr">Meddour and Meddour-Sahar, 2016</xref>) and 90 species (85 genera and 42 families) in the region of Skikda (north east Algeria) (<xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Bouasla and Bouasla, 2017</xref>).</p><p id="p0190">The most represented families were Asteraceae (11 species, 20%), Lamiaceae (10 species, 19%), Apiaceae (9 species, 17%) and Fabaceae (8 species, 15%) respectively. The predominance of these plant families in the medicinal flora is well established in Algeria (<xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">Benarba, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0375" ref-type="bibr">Meddour and Meddour-Sahar, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="b0485" ref-type="bibr">Sarri et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0490" ref-type="bibr">Sarri et al., 2014</xref>) and in the whole Mediterranean region (<xref rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr">Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Tejero et al., 2008</xref>). Probable reason for the high number of anticancer plant species reported in these families could be due to the presence of special and effective bioactive ingredients holding potential biological activities, e.g. flavonoids, sesquiterpenes lactones, tricyclic sesquiterpenes and germacranolide sesquiterpene lactones in the Asteraceae family (<xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Babaei et al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0510" ref-type="bibr">Shoaib et al., 2017</xref>), and terpenoids, flavonoids, coumarins, polyacetylenes, steroids, sesquiterpenes and flavonols in the Apiaceae family (<xref rid="b0380" ref-type="bibr">Moazzami Farida et al., 2018</xref>). A lot of bioactive compounds with proven therapeutic activity are present in the Lamiaceae family such as arbutin (<xref rid="b0475" ref-type="bibr">Rychlinska and Nowak, 2012</xref>), apigenin and naringenin (<xref rid="b0525" ref-type="bibr">Stacks, 2015</xref>), luteolin (<xref rid="b0355" ref-type="bibr">L&#x000f3;pez-L&#x000e1;zaro, 2009</xref>), hesperidin (<xref rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2010</xref>) and rutin (<xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Chua, 2013</xref>). Some other bioingredients are specific to this family such as clerodendranoic acid (<xref rid="b0590" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al., 2012</xref>) and carnosic acid (<xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Birti&#x00107; et al., 2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0100"><label>5.2</label><title>Quantitative ethnopharmacology</title><p id="p0195">Quantitative ethnopharmacology analysis has demonstrated that <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L. (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;152, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.54), <italic>Aristolochia longa</italic> L. (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;144, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.51), <italic>Berberis vulgaris</italic> L. (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;142, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.51), <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L. (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;121, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.43), <italic>Trigonella foenum</italic>-<italic>graecum</italic> L. (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;119, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.43), <italic>Citrus limon</italic> L. (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;120, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.43), <italic>Artemisia herba</italic>-<italic>alba</italic> Asso (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;115, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.41) and <italic>Allium cepa</italic> L. (UR&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;107, UV&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.38) were the most reported plant species for the management of cancer in Algeria. Interestingly, despite the fact that these species are frequently cited for the treatment of various ailments worldwide including Algeria, they have been reported at topmost species for cancer management in the neighboring countries from North Africa according to the review achieved by <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Alves-Silva et al. (2017)</xref>. Remarkably, even though the inventoried species were frequently reported in previous studies carried out in Algeria for multiple uses, only <italic>Atriplex halimus</italic> L., <italic>Berberis vulgaris</italic> L., <italic>Prunus persica</italic> (L.) Batsch and <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. that have been reported for cancer management by <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Benarba et al. (2015)</xref> in addition to <italic>Allium cepa</italic> L. and <italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic> L. mentioned by <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Bouasla and Bouasla (2017)</xref>. In another study, <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">Benarba (2015)</xref> has stated only <italic>Berberis vulgaris</italic> L., <italic>Aristolochia longa</italic> L., <italic>Atriplex halimus</italic> L., <italic>Glycyrrhiza glabra</italic> L., <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L., <italic>Pimpinella anisum</italic> L., <italic>Allium sativum</italic> L., <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. and <italic>Artemisia herba</italic>-<italic>alba</italic> Asso for the management of breast cancer.</p></sec><sec id="s0105"><label>5.3</label><title>Plant forms, plant parts and modes of use</title><p id="p0200">The medicinal plants reported in this study are not all locally cultivated and most of them grow naturally in the wild. Furthermore, many species pass the borders from other countries without proper inspection and quality control verification. Other species are grown around the homesteads or along roads borders and rural infrastructures which makes them susceptible to pollution and toxicity problems. The most common plants&#x02019; life-forms used by the traditional healers for the preparation of ethnomedicines in treating cancers were herbs (60%), shrubs (20%) and trees (20%). The use of herbs could be due to their higher abundance, easy collection and therapeutic efficacy (<xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 2009</xref>). However, the use of shrub and tree life-forms in herbal medicine may be due to their accessibility throughout the year (<xref rid="b0340" ref-type="bibr">Khan et al., 2013</xref>). In addition, the most common used plant parts among informants were leaves (26% plants, <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Fortunately, the use of these parts does not threaten the life cycle of the plants (<xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Bhat et al., 2013</xref>). However, the subsequent frequent harvested plant parts were fruits (15%), flowers (14%), seeds (14%) and stems (11%). The studies conducted by <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">Panghal et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">Ghasemi Pirbalouti et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">Dolatkhahi et al., 2014</xref> have reported similarly the predominant use of plant leaves followed by flowers, fruits and stems. Moreover, roots harvest was also reported in this study (9%). This is possibly due to their richness with bioactive components (<xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">Adnan et al., 2014</xref>). The unsustainability of roots harvesting is well known by conservationists who labeled those used medicinal plants as highly threatened (<xref rid="b0365" ref-type="bibr">Maroyi, 2013</xref>).</p><p id="p0205">Furthermore, the most common mode of preparation of plants parts was decoction (27%), followed by direct consumption (19%), powdering (18%) and infusion (16%). Similar findings were reported by <xref rid="b0455" ref-type="bibr">Rajaei and Mohamadi (2012)</xref>. The mentioned methods of preparation could be suitable for some plants but not for the others. In fact, the boiling procedure reported by the informants can cause severe degradation of the therapeutic components in some medicinal plants. In addition, the suitable dosage required to have the expected benefits is not clear throughout this study. This concern has been raised also by several researchers indicating that the fixed doses to be administered by patients in traditional medicine is still not yet well-defined (<xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">Jaradat et al., 2016</xref>). Therefore, further studies are needed to determine the concentration of active ingredients with respect to their method of preparation since categorization of finished natural products into dosage forms may aid as well to establish specific procedures for quality control and stability testing.</p></sec><sec id="s0110"><label>5.4</label><title>Animal species diversity</title><p id="p0210">Likewise, zootherapy based on the use of animals or animal derived products has been practiced in traditional medicine of various cultures at the same extent as phytotherapy (<xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Alves et al., 2011</xref>). However, research on animals remains neglected in comparison to medicinal plants that are used in larger quantities with great specific variation (<xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Alves and Rosa, 2007</xref>). Recently, animal products are increasingly used as raw materials in the preparation of modern medicines and herbal preparations (<xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Alves and Rosa, 2005</xref>). In this study 10 animal species have been reported for the treatment of cancer. With regards to their habitat type, 7 animal species are terrestrials, 2 are aquatic species and 1 amphibian. In fact, the use of zootherapy in traditional medicine is related to the faunal composition and the relative abundance of animal species in the given region in which the people live (<xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Alves et al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Alves and Rosa, 2007</xref>). Most animal species used in Algerian traditional medicines are native to arid and semi-arid regions with the exception of <italic>Cancer pagurus</italic> and <italic>Corallium rubrum</italic>. The use of <italic>Pelophylax saharicus</italic> skin&#x02019; in traditional medicine to treat visible tumors is reported for the first time throughout the present study. Interestingly, several natural products secreted from frog skins have been reported as novel and potent antimicrobial and anticancer peptide agents; <xref rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr">Kang et al. (2012)</xref> have described Brevinin as potentially useful new anticancer peptide agent against several tumor cell lines namely skin (SK-MEL-2), lung (A549), stomach (MKN45), colon (HCT116), kidney (A498), prostate (PC-3) and ovary (SK-OV-3). Later, <xref rid="b0285" ref-type="bibr">Hassanvand Jamadi et al. (2019)</xref> have stated the significant anticancer activity of Brevinin in vitro on human breast (MCF-7) and lung (A549) cancer cells with less cytotoxic effects on human red blood cells. By the same, Temporin is another natural frog product characterized by its cytotoxic effect on MCF-7 breast cancer cell line and capable to induce cell death (<xref rid="b0500" ref-type="bibr">Shaheen et al., 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0115"><label>5.5</label><title>Other natural products</title><p id="p0215">In addition, the reported animal derived products consisted mainly in honey, milk, butter, thorns and camel urine. Some of these products have been the subject of several studies which demonstrated their health benefits. For instance, honey holds several compounds with anti-cancer activity such as phenolic acids (caffeic acid and gallic acid) and flavonoids (catechin, kaempferol and quercetin among others) (<xref rid="b0555" ref-type="bibr">Waheed et al., 2019</xref>). It was reported to have antimutagenic (<xref rid="b0495" ref-type="bibr">Saxena et al., 2012</xref>), tumor necrosis factor inhibiting (<xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed and Othman, 2013</xref>, <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Can et al., 2015</xref>), antioxidant (<xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Almasaudi et al., 2016</xref>), apoptotic, immunomodulatory, antiproliferative (<xref rid="b0300" ref-type="bibr">Jaganathan et al., 2015</xref>), anticarcinogenic action (<xref rid="b0530" ref-type="bibr">Subramanian et al., 2016</xref>), anti-inflammatory and estrogenic effects (<xref rid="b0420" ref-type="bibr">Porcza et al., 2016</xref>). Local honey of <italic>Ziziphus lotus</italic> which is the most cited in this study was recently characterized for the first time by <xref rid="b0585" ref-type="bibr">Zerrouk et al. (2018)</xref>. However, despite that <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al. (2019)</xref> have recently recognized the anticancer effect <italic>Ziziphus jujube</italic> honey&#x02019; on hepatocellular carcinoma, there is no published data about the anticancer activity of <italic>Ziziphus lotus</italic> honey to the knowledge of the authors.</p><p id="p0220">Besides, consumption of milk or dairy products (cheese, butter&#x02026;) is correlated with a reduced risk of numerous types of cancer (<xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr">Jeyaraman et al., 2019</xref>). These properties are attributed to the variety of components such as fat compounds, conjugated linoleic acid, and proteins such as casein and vitamins (A, B, C, D) which have been proved to have protective and/or anticarcinogenic properties (<xref rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr">Davoodi et al., 2013</xref>). The use of camel urine by Muslims comes from the fact that prophet of Islam Mohamad &#x02018;Peace Be Upon Him&#x02019; advised its use in the treatment of various ailments (<xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Alebie et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="p0225">In fact, informants have recorded the wide use of the holy water of Zamzam, from Zamzam well in Saudi Arabia, as narrated in holy books of various religions including the Torah, the Bible, and the Quran (<xref rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr">Khalid et al., 2014</xref>). Zamzam water is a naturally hard alkaline type of water (average pH of 8) with unique physicochemical properties that are different from any other water (<xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Al Doghaither et al., 2016</xref>). Analysis revealed that Zamzam water holds high concentrations of minerals such as calcium, magnesium, sodium, potassium and fluoride. It contains also arsenic and nitrate below the level of human consumption danger but above the standard limit of WHO (<xref rid="b0515" ref-type="bibr">Shomar, 2012</xref>). The healing properties of Zamzam water may be attributed in part to its alkaline nature which reduces oxidative stress (<xref rid="b0390" ref-type="bibr">Nassini et al., 2010</xref>) and helps get rid of mercury, acidic wastes and other toxins in the body, as acidic body tends to hold onto (heavy) metals (<xref rid="b0515" ref-type="bibr">Shomar, 2012</xref>). Moreover, numerous researchers have focused on the relationship of pH and cancer who cannot survive in alkaline medium (<xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">Estrella et al., 2013</xref>, <xref rid="b0465" ref-type="bibr">Robey et al., 2009</xref>). However, other studies have demonstrated that the proliferation of cancer cells is inhibited under certain doses of some toxic minerals such as selenium, arsenic, and lithium (<xref rid="b0560" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2011</xref>). <xref rid="b0395" ref-type="bibr">Omar et al. (2017)</xref> reported that Zamzam water has positive effect in cancer therapy and combats blood cancer by targeting specific proteins.</p></sec><sec id="s0120"><label>5.6</label><title>Monotherapy versus the use of mixtures</title><p id="p0230">Otherwise, both monotherapy and concoctions based on the combination of two or more natural products were reported among informants. Interestingly, the informants reported their uses of mixed traditional-based preparations with chemical cancer drugs. The use of multiple medicinal therapies through mixing two or more natural products even combined with chemical drugs may increase the effectiveness of such medicines (<xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">Ait Abderrahim et al., 2019</xref>). Traditional healers may add also different accessory additives in their formulas to enhance the healing efficiency of the mixture, improve the taste and reduce pain and adverse effects (<xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Bayat Mokhtari et al., 2017</xref>). Interestingly, the majority of natural products and accessory additives recorded throughout this study are mentioned in the Holy Quran, such as honey, <italic>Allium cepa</italic> L., <italic>Allium sativum</italic> L., <italic>Ficus carica</italic> L., <italic>Olea europaea</italic> L., <italic>Phoenix dactylifera</italic> L., <italic>Punica granatum</italic> L., <italic>Triticum turgidum</italic> L. and <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L., or by the Prophet Mohamad (PBUH) like Citrullus colocynthis (L.) Schrad, <italic>Cuminum cyminum</italic> L., <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L., <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L., <italic>Trigonella foenum</italic>-<italic>graecum</italic> L., <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> Roscoe and the holy water Zamzam. These natural products have been exploited since long time for food or treatment purposes and their applications have demonstrated considerable benefits in cancer treatment (<xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 2017</xref>). Several active substances with anticancer effects have been purified from these species such as <italic>Quercetin</italic> isolated from <italic>Allium</italic> sp. (<xref rid="b0460" ref-type="bibr">Ranelletti et al., 2000</xref>), <italic>Apigenin</italic> from <italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic>, <italic>Allium sativum</italic>, <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> Subsp<italic>. capitata</italic> L., <italic>Capsicum annuum</italic> L. (<xref rid="b0360" ref-type="bibr">Manach et al., 2004</xref>), <italic>Genistein</italic> from <italic>Glycine</italic> max L. and <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L. (<xref rid="b0470" ref-type="bibr">Rossi et al., 2006</xref>), resveratrol isolated from <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. (<xref rid="b0520" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2013</xref>), alliin and allicin from <italic>Allium sativum</italic> L. (<xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Borlinghaus et al., 2014</xref>), Oleuropein/ omega-3 fatty acids from <italic>Olea europaea</italic> L. (<xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Bulotta et al., 2014</xref>), <italic>Curcumin</italic> from <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L. (<xref rid="b0430" ref-type="bibr">Prasad et al., 2014</xref>), thymoquinone from <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L. (<xref rid="b0345" ref-type="bibr">Kort&#x000fc;m et al., 2015</xref>) and <italic>Kaempferol</italic> from <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> L. (<xref rid="b0270" ref-type="bibr">Guti&#x000e9;rrez-del-R&#x000ed;o et al., 2016</xref>). The increasing interest in traditional Arabic and Islamic medicine is stimulated by the fact that these natural products are safe, cost-effective, and exhibit a wide spectrum of biological activities including stimulation of the immune system, antioxidant, anti-mutagenic, anti-inflammatory, antiviral, and anti-cancer effects (<xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0480" ref-type="bibr">Saad and Said, 2011</xref>). In addition, Islamic medicinal practices generate specific cultural behaviors that aim to preserve health through prevention rather than therapeutic medicine since cancers evolve over a long period of time and biocomponents able to inhibit or delay one or more of its stages may affect the overall development of the disease (<xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0125"><label>5.7</label><title>Cancers&#x02019; category and natural products</title><p id="p0235">The consistency of the use-reports per cancer category was evaluated by the informants&#x02019; consensus factor (C<sub>IF</sub>). F<sub>IC</sub> values ranged from 0.50 to 0.90 revealing high homogeneity in the reported cancer types mainly for breast, colorectal, lung and stomach cancers. These values are higher in comparison to those reported by <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Benarba et al. (2015)</xref> ranging from 0.13 to 0.66 and those of <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Bouasla and Bouasla (2017)</xref> from 0.09 to 0.66. It should be noted here that these cited studies are not designed for specific ailment such as cancer which is the case in our study. <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Andrade-Cetto and Heinrich (2011)</xref> have stated that higher values of the index are obtained when the use of inventoried plant species is reported by a high proportion of informants for the treatment of a particular cancer, whereas low values indicate that informants disagree over which plant to use. As an indicator of the relative medicinal importance of the inventoried plant species (<xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), the Medicinal Importance index ranged from 1.92 for neck cancer to 10.43 for breast cancer. These values are in the same range of those reported by <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Baydoun et al. (2015)</xref> carrying ethnopharmacological in Lebanon (from 2.66 to 16.24) but higher than those of <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Carri&#x000f3; and Vall&#x000e8;s (2012)</xref> in Balearic Islands (Spain). This could be attributed to the high number of informants engaged in this study in comparison to the others mentioned studies from apart, and to the low number of disorders (cancer types) in our study which are healed nearly by the same number of plant species from another part (<xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Baydoun et al., 2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0130"><label>5.8</label><title>Toxicity and side effects</title><p id="p0240">It should be noted that traditional medicines are not always free of side effects due to the presence of various pharmacological substances which may induce problems through inappropriate dosage and method of administration (<xref rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr">Izzo et al., 2016</xref>). Likewise, it is relevant to mention that our informants recognized as toxic some plant species such as <italic>Aristolochia longa</italic> L., <italic>Berberis vulgaris</italic> L. and <italic>Peganum harmala</italic> L. although some had local medicinal uses but not all the toxic plants. It is important to note that among the reported plants, <italic>Aristolochia longa</italic> L.<italic>, Artemisia herba-alba</italic> Asso<italic>, Crocus sativus</italic> L.<italic>, Cuminum cyminum</italic> L.<italic>, Echinops spinosus</italic> L.<italic>, Ephedra alata</italic> L.<italic>, Ferula vesceritensis</italic> L.<italic>, Haloxylon scoparium</italic> Pomel<italic>, Juniperus phoenicea</italic> L.<italic>, Lawsonia inermis</italic> L.<italic>, Lepidium sativum</italic> L.<italic>, Mentha spicata</italic> L.<italic>, Pistacia lentiscus</italic> L.<italic>, Retama raetam</italic> i(Forssk.) Webb<italic>, Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L.<italic>, Tamarix Africana</italic> Poir.<italic>, Thymelaea microphylla</italic> Meisn. are considered all as toxic at higher doses and are not recommended to pregnant women (<xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">Hammiche et al., 2013</xref>). Besides, the harmful use of <italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> L. on spermatozoids motility as well as its embryotoxic effect have been also described (<xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">Gonzales et al., 2007</xref>, <xref rid="b0580" ref-type="bibr">Zeichen de Sa et al., 2000</xref>). As well, human consumption of cyanogenic plants like <italic>Prunus</italic> sp. rich with glycosides, cyanogen and amygdaline at higher doses might cause weakness, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea and spasms followed by terminal coma and death due to cyanide poisoning (<xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Chaouali et al., 2013</xref>). Also, <italic>Thapsia garganica</italic> L. is a poisonous plant rich with histamine-releasing substances such as lactones sesquiterpenes (thapsigargine and thapsigarginine). Exposure to its molecules might induce vomiting, violent diarrhea, digestive mucous inflammation, salivary secretion, nervous disorders and gastroenteritis which leads lastly to death (<xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">Hammiche et al., 2013</xref>). Cucurbitacines and glycosides present in <italic>Citrullus colocynthis</italic> (L.) Schrad. and <italic>Ecballium elaterium</italic> L. might cause severe cutaneous and digestive adverse reactions that should not be ignored (<xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">De Smet, 1997</xref>, <xref rid="b0450" ref-type="bibr">Raikhlin-Eisenkraft and Bentur, 2000</xref>).</p><p id="p0245">In general, in comparison to synthetic drugs, ethnomedicines are also efficient and better tolerant nevertheless, patients must have enough information about their formulation methods, precise dosages, toxicity and side effects. Actually, the use of traditional medicinal knowledge by native populations is not only valuable for conservation of cultural traditions and resources but also useful for the population&#x02019;s healthcare and drug discovery (<xref rid="b0400" ref-type="bibr">Orhan, 2014</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0135"><label>6</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0250">Cancer remains one of the major causes of death worldwide. Ethnopharmacological studies provide significant sources of knowledge since the popular uses of many natural products may be linked to the presence of bioactive compounds and anticancer properties.</p><p id="p0255">This is the first field-study documenting the uses of natural products for traditional cancer therapy in Algeria. The obtained results reveal the use of 113 medicinal plants species (belonging to 53 families and 104 genera), 10 animal species along with various products and by-products such as honey, olive oil, thorns, urine, milk, animal fat and alkaline water of Zamzam for cancer treatment by Algerian local populations.</p><p id="p0260">Quantitative ethnopharmacological analyses have demonstrated that honey, <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L., <italic>Aristolochia longa</italic> L., <italic>Berberis vulgaris</italic> L., <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L., <italic>Trigonella foenum</italic>-<italic>graecum</italic> L., <italic>Citrus limon</italic> L., <italic>Artemisia herba</italic>-<italic>alba</italic> Asso and the holy water &#x02018;Zamzam&#x02019; were the most used natural products.</p><p id="p0265">Interestingly, we report for the first time the use of <italic>Pelophylax saharicus</italic> skin&#x02019; for the treatment of visible tumors and skin cancer. Furthermore, the obtained data describe new therapeutic uses for <italic>Allium cepa</italic> L., <italic>Allium sativum</italic> L., <italic>Aristolochia longa</italic> L., <italic>Artemisia herba</italic>-<italic>alba</italic> Asso, <italic>Atriplex halimus</italic> L., <italic>Berberis vulgaris</italic> L., <italic>Glycyrrhiza glabra</italic> L., <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L., <italic>Pimpinella anisum</italic> L., <italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic> L., <italic>Prunus persica</italic> (L.) Batsch, <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. and <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. However, the remaining 100 medicinal plants, including several endemic species, are documented for the first time for their traditional uses in cancer management in Algeria.</p><p id="p0270">Further <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> studies should be carried out to validate the popular uses of the reported natural products. Besides, associating traditional medicine and conventional treatments could be of great interest as a promising therapeutic approach for cancer treatment. Finally, it is necessary to develop a parallel strategy to preserve biodiversity and to protect it from over exploitation.</p></sec><sec id="s0140"><title>Author contributions</title><p id="p0275">TK designed study, analyzed the data, interpreted the results and wrote manuscript; All authors carried out field studies, identified natural products, collected, prepared and revised data, read and approved the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="p0280">The authors declare that there are no known conflicts of interest associated with this publication and there has been no significant financial support for this work that could have influenced its outcome.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi005"><title>References</title><ref id="b0005"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abu-Darwish</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Efferth</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal Plants from Near East for Cancer Therapy</article-title><source>Front. Pharmacol.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>56</issue><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0010"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adnan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tariq</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murad</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Azizullah</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicine use in the war affected region of northwest Pakistan</article-title><source>J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>16</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24484608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghafoor</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical Study of Upper Siran</article-title><source>J. Herbs Spices Med. Plants</source><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>97</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naqvi</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shehzad</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Ghamdi</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of traditional Islamic and Arabic plants in cancer therapy</article-title><source>J. Tradition. Complement. Med.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>204</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Othman</surname><given-names>N.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Honey as a potential natural anticancer agent: a review of its mechanisms</article-title><source>Evid. Based Complement Alternat. Med.</source><volume>2013</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>829070</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24363771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ait Abderrahim</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ta&#x000ef;bi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ait Abderrahim</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of the Antimicrobial and Antioxidant Activities of Ziziphus lotus and Peganum harmala</article-title><source>Iranian J. Sci. Technol., Trans. A: Sci.</source><volume>43</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>414</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ait Abderrahim</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ta&#x000ef;bi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ait Abderrahim</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boussaid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rios-Navarro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Saur&#x000ed;</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Euphorbia honey and garlic: Biological activity and burn wound recovery</article-title><source>Burns</source><volume>45</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1695</fpage><lpage>1706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31167717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al Doghaither</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Ghafari</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimulddin</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Zahrani</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>U.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the potential anticancer activity of zamzam water in human colon cancer cell line</article-title><source>Cancer Oncol. Res.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>41</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>U.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lucena</surname><given-names>R.F.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alencar</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods and techniques used to collect ethnobiological data, Methods and techniques in Ethnobiology and Ethnoecology</article-title><source>Springer</source><year>2014</year><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>37</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0050"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alebie</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yohannes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Worku</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic applications of camel&#x02019;s milk and urine against cancer: current development efforts and future perspectives</article-title><source>J. Cancer Sci. Therapy</source><volume>9</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>478</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0055"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Almasaudi</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Shitany</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-dayem</surname><given-names>U.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Jaouni</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harakeh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, and antiulcer potential of manuka honey against gastric ulcer in rats</chapter-title><source>Oxidative medicine and cellular longevity 2016</source><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0060"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>R.R.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>J.A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>S.L.D.X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Souto</surname><given-names>W.M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barboza</surname><given-names>R.R.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Animal-based remedies as complementary medicines in the semi-arid region of northeastern Brazil</article-title><source>Evid. Based Complement Alternat. Med.</source><volume>2011</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>179876</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19729490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>R.R.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>I.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why study the use of animal products in traditional medicines?</article-title><source>J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed.</source><volume>1</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16270931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0070"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>R.R.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>I.M.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiversity, traditional medicine and public health: where do they meet?</article-title><source>J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed.</source><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17376227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0075"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves-Silva</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romane</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Efferth</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salgueiro</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>North African Medicinal Plants Traditionally Used in Cancer Therapy</article-title><source>Front. Pharmacol.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>383</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28694778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0080"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Severino</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>A.J.C.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural Products as Treatment against Cancer: A Historical and Current Vision</article-title><source>Clin. Oncol.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1562</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0085"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrade-Cetto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From the field into the lab: useful approaches to selecting species based on local knowledge</article-title><source>Front. Pharmacol.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>20</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21954385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0090"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azzi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Djaziri</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahfa</surname><given-names>F.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekkal</surname><given-names>F.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benmehdi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belkacem</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnopharmacological survey of medicinal plants used in the traditional treatment of diabetes mellitus in the North Western and South Western Algeria</article-title><source>J. Med. Plant Res.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>2041</fpage><lpage>2050</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0095"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0095">Baba Aissa, F., 1991. Medicinal plants in Algeria. Identification, description of active ingredient properties and traditional use of common plants in Algeria. Bouch&#x000e8;ne and Ad. Diwan, Algiers, pp. 1&#x02013;181.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0100"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babaei</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aliarab</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abroon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasmi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>S.G.-G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Application of sesquiterpene lactone: A new promising way for cancer therapy based on anticancer activity</article-title><source>Biomed. Pharmacother.</source><volume>106</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29966966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0105"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bayat Mokhtari</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Homayouni</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baluch</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgatskaya</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeger</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combination therapy in combating cancer</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><volume>8</volume><issue>23</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>38022</fpage><lpage>38043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28410237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0110"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baydoun</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalak</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalleh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnopharmacological survey of medicinal plants used in traditional medicine by the communities of Mount Hermon, Lebanon</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>173</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26165826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0115"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benarba</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of medicinal plants by breast cancer patients in Algeria</article-title><source>EXCLI J.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1164</fpage><lpage>1166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26713086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0120"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0120">Benarba, B., Belabid, L., Righi, K., Bekkar, A.A., Elouissi, M., Khaldi, A., Hamimed, A., 2015. Ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants used by traditional healers in Mascara (North West of Algeria). J. Ethnopharmacol. 175, 626&#x02013;637.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0125"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benarba</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meddah</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamdani</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer incidence in North West Algeria (Mascara) 2000&#x02013;2010: results from a population-based cancer registry</article-title><source>EXCLI J.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26417294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0130"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benarba</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandiella</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colorectal cancer and medicinal plants: Principle findings from recent studies</article-title><source>Biomed. Pharmacother.</source><volume>107</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30099345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0135"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bussmann</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological status and traditional knowledge of medicinal plants in Kedarnath Wildlife Sanctuary of Garhwal Himalaya, India</article-title><source>J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23281594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0140"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birti&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dussort</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierre</surname><given-names>F.-X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bily</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carnosic acid</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><volume>115</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25639596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0145"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borlinghaus</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruhlke</surname><given-names>M.C.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nwachukwu</surname><given-names>I.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slusarenko</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allicin: chemistry and biological properties</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>19</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>12591</fpage><lpage>12618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25153873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0150"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouasla</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouasla</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants in northeastern of Algeria</article-title><source>Phytomedicine</source><volume>36</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29157830</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0155"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boudjelal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henchiri</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarri</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benkhaled</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruberto</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbalists and wild medicinal plants in M'Sila (North Algeria): An ethnopharmacology survey</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>148</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23643544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0160"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0160">Bourhia, M., Abdelaziz Shahat, A., Mohammed Almarfadi, O., Ali Naser, F., Mostafa Abdelmageed, W., Ait Haj Said, A., El Gueddari, F., Naamane, A., Benbacer, L., Khlil, N., 2019. Ethnopharmacological Survey of Herbal Remedies Used for the Treatment of Cancer in the Greater Casablanca-Morocco. Evid.-Based Complement. Alternat. Med. 2019, 1613457.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0165"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boussaid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ta&#x000ef;bi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ait Abderrahim</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ennajah</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity of Ziziphus lotus natural populations from Algeria based on fruit morphological markers</article-title><source>Arid Land Res. Manage.</source><volume>32</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>197</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0170"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouzabata</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahomoodally</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A quantitative documentation of traditionally-used medicinal plants from Northeastern Algeria: Interactions of beliefs among healers and diabetic patients</article-title><source>J. Herbal Med.</source><volume>100318</volume><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0175"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soerjomataram</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torre</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global cancer statistics 2018: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries</article-title><source>CA Cancer J. Clin.</source><volume>68</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30207593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0180"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bulotta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Celano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepore</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montalcini</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pujia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beneficial effects of the olive oil phenolic components oleuropein and hydroxytyrosol: focus on protection against cardiovascular and metabolic diseases</article-title><source>J. Transl. Med.</source><volume>12</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>219</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25086598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0185"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Can</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yildiz</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akyuz Turumtay</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silici</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolayli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An investigation of Turkish honeys: Their physico-chemical properties, antioxidant capacities and phenolic profiles</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><volume>180</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25766810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0190"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carri&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotany of medicinal plants used in Eastern Mallorca (Balearic Islands, Mediterranean Sea)</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>141</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1021</fpage><lpage>1040</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22783553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0195"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaouali</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gana</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khelifi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nouioui</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masri</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belwaer</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghorbel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedhili</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential Toxic Levels of Cyanide in Almonds (Prunus amygdalus), Apricot Kernels (Prunus armeniaca), and Almond Syrup</article-title><source>ISRN Toxicol.</source><volume>2013</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>610648</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24171123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0200"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Jujube honey induces apoptosis in human hepatocellular carcinoma HepG2 cell via DNA damage, p53 expression, and caspase activation</article-title><source>J. Food Biochem.</source><volume>43</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e12998</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0205"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chermat</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gharzouli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical Study of Medicinal Flora in the North East of Algeria - An Empirical Knowledge in Djebel Zdimm (Setif)</article-title><source>J. Mater. Sci. Eng. A</source><volume>1&#x02013;2</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>59</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0210"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chorfi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ta&#x000ef;bi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical Screening for Osmotic Adjustment of Wheat Genotypes under Drought Stress</article-title><source>Tropicultura</source><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>87</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0215"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review on plant-based rutin extraction methods and its pharmacological activities</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>150</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>805</fpage><lpage>817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24184193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0220"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0220">da Silva, V.A., do Nascimento, V.T., Soldati, G.T., Medeiros, M.F.T., Albuquerque, U.P., 2014. Techniques for analysis of quantitative ethnobiological data: use of indices, Methods Tech. Ethnobiol. Ethnoecol. Springer, pp. 379&#x02013;395.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0225"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davoodi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Esmaeili</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortazavian</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of Milk and Milk Products Consumption on Cancer: A Review</article-title><source>Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf.</source><volume>12</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>264</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0230"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0230"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Smet</surname><given-names>P.A.G.M.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Citrullus Colocynthis</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>De Smet</surname><given-names>P.A.G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000e4;nsel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Adverse Effects of Herbal Drugs</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin Heidelberg, Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc><fpage>391</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0235"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0235"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dolatkhahi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolatkhahi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nejad</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants used in Arjan - Parishan protected area in Fars Province of Iran</article-title><source>Avicenna J. Phytomed.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25386404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0240"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0240"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durante</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Formenti</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radiation-Induced Chromosomal Aberrations and Immunotherapy: Micronuclei, Cytosolic DNA, and Interferon-Production Pathway</article-title><source>Front. Oncol.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>192</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29911071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0245"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0245"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Estrella</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wojtkowiak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornnell</surname><given-names>H.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim-Hashim</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balagurunathan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothberg</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sloane</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatenby</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acidity generated by the tumor microenvironment drives local invasion</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><volume>73</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1524</fpage><lpage>1535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23288510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0250"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0250">Frost, D.R., 2020. Amphibian Species of the World: an online reference. Version 6.0 (05/04/2020). Electronic Database accessible at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://amphibiansoftheworld.amnh.org/index.php" id="ir020">https://amphibiansoftheworld.amnh.org/index.php</ext-link> American Museum of Natural History, New York, USA.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0255"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0255"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghasemi Pirbalouti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Momeni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahmani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants used by Kurd tribe in Dehloran and Abdanan Districts, Ilam Province, Iran</article-title><source>Afr. J. Tradit. Complement. Altern. Med.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24146463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0260"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0260"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benavides</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pino</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efecto embriot&#x000f3;xico y teratog&#x000e9;nico de Ruta chalepensis L. &#x000ab;ruda&#x000bb;, en rat&#x000f3;n (Mus musculus) %J</article-title><source>Revista Peruana de Biolog&#x000ed;a.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>226</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0265"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0265"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Tejero</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casares-Porcel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Rojas</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramiro-Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Molero-Mesa</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieroni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giusti</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Censorii</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Pasquale</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Della</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paraskeva-Hadijchambi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadjichambis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houmani</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Demerdash</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Zayat</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hmamouchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>ElJohrig</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants in the Mediterranean area: Synthesis of the results of the project Rubia</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>116</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18242025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0270"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0270"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez-del-R&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villar</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lomb&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic uses of Kampferol: Anticancer and antiinflammatory activity</article-title><source>Biosynthesis, Food Sources Therapeutic Uses</source><year>2016</year><fpage>71</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0275"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0275"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habtamu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulatu</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsdeke</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional medicinal plants utilization, management and threats in Hadiya Zone Ethiopia</article-title><source>J. Med. Plants Stud.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>16</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0280"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0280"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammiche</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merad</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Azzouz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Plantes toxiques &#x000e0; usage m&#x000e9;dicinal du pourtour m&#x000e9;diterran&#x000e9;en</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Spiegler</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Springer</source><year>2013</year><publisher-name>Paris</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0285"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0285"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hassanvand Jamadi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaghoubi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadeghizadeh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brevinin-2R and Derivatives as Potential Anticancer Peptides: Synthesis, Purification, Characterization and Biological Activities</article-title><source>Int. J. Pept. Res. Ther.</source><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>160</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0290"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0290">IPNI (2020). International Plant Names Index. Published on the Internet <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipni.org" id="ir025">http://www.ipni.org</ext-link>, The Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, Harvard University Herbaria &#x00026; Libraries and Australian National Botanic Gardens.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0295"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0295"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Izzo</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoon-Kim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Critical Approach to Evaluating Clinical Efficacy, Adverse Events and Drug Interactions of Herbal Remedies</article-title><source>Phytother. Res.</source><volume>30</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26887532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0300"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0300"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaganathan</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaji</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vellayappan</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asokan</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Supriyanto</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Razak</surname><given-names>S.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marvibaigi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review on antiproliferative and apoptotic activities of natural honey</article-title><source>Anti-Cancer Agents Med. Chem.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>56</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0305"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0305"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaradat</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Ramahi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaid</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayesh</surname><given-names>O.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eid</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnopharmacological survey of herbal remedies used for treatment of various types of cancer and their methods of preparations in the West Bank-Palestine</article-title><source>BMC Complement. Altern. Med.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>93</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26955822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0310"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0310"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jelonek</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietrowska</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Widlak</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systemic effects of ionizing radiation at the proteome and metabolome levels in the blood of cancer patients treated with radiotherapy: the influence of inflammation and radiation toxicity</article-title><source>Int. J. Radiat Biol.</source><volume>93</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28281355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0315"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0315"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeyaraman</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abou-Setta</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farshidfar</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Copstein</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lys</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottschalk</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desautels</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Czaykowski</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarychanski</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dairy product consumption and development of cancer: an overview of reviews</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e023625</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0320"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0320"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabbaj</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meddah</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherrah</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faouzi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnopharmacological profile of traditional plants used in Morocco by cancer patients as herbal therapeutics</article-title><source>Phytopharmacology</source><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>256</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0325"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0325">Kaddem, S.E., 1990. Les plantes m&#x000e9;dicinales en Alg&#x000e9;rie, Ed. Bouch&#x000e8;ne, Oued Zenati, Alg&#x000e9;rie.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0330"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0330"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>H.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>B.-J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anticancer activity of undecapeptide analogues derived from antimicrobial peptide, Brevinin-1EMa</article-title><source>Arch. Pharmacal. Res.</source><volume>35</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>799</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0335"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0335"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Irfan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mineral Composition and Health Functionality of Zamzam Water: A Review</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Prop.</source><volume>17</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>677</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0340"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0340"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaheen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal flora and ethnoecological knowledge in the Naran Valley, Western Himalaya, Pakistan</article-title><source>J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23302393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0345"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0345"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kort&#x000fc;m</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campregher</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khare</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evstatiev</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittlb&#x000f6;ck</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scharl</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kucherlapati</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edelmann</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasche</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mesalazine and thymoquinone attenuate intestinal tumour development in Msh2(loxP/loxP) Villin-Cre mice</article-title><source>Gut</source><volume>64</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1905</fpage><lpage>1912</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25429050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0350"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0350"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>M.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>S.-T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>C.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>C.-C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The inhibitory effect of hesperidin on tumor cell invasiveness occurs via suppression of activator protein 1 and nuclear factor-kappaB in human hepatocellular carcinoma cells</article-title><source>Toxicol. Lett.</source><volume>194</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20138977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0355"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0355"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-L&#x000e1;zaro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution and Biological Activities of the Flavonoid Luteolin</article-title><source>Mini-Rev. Med. Chem.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19149659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0360"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0360"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manach</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scalbert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morand</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000e9;m&#x000e9;sy</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polyphenols: food sources and bioavailability</article-title><source>Am. J. Clin. Nutr.</source><volume>79</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15113710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0365"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0365"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maroyi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional use of medicinal plants in south-central Zimbabwe: review and perspectives</article-title><source>J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>31</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23642285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0370"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0370"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Ethnobotany-A manual of methods</chapter-title><year>1995</year><publisher-name>Chapman et Hall</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0375"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0375"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meddour</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meddour-Sahar</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants and their traditional uses in Kabylia (Tizi Ouzou, Algeria)</article-title><source>Arabian J. Med. Aromatic Plants</source><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>151</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0380"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0380">Moazzami Farida, S.H., Ghorbani*, A., Ajani, Y., Sadr, M., Mozaffarian, V., 2018. Ethnobotanical Applications and Their Correspondence with Phylogeny in Apiaceae-Apioideae. Res. J. Pharmacognosy 5(3), 79&#x02013;97.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0385"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0385">Myers, P., R. Espinosa, C. S. Parr, T. Jones, G. S. Hammond, and T. A. Dewey. 2020. The Animal Diversity Web (online). Accessed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://animaldiversity.org" id="ir030">https://animaldiversity.org</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0390"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0390">Nassini, R., Andr, egrave, Eunice, Gazzieri, D., Siena, G.D., Zanasi, A., Geppetti, P., Materazzi, S., 2010. A Bicarbonate-Alkaline Mineral Water Protects from Ethanol-Induced Hemorrhagic Gastric Lesions in Mice. Biolog. Pharmaceut. Bull. 33, 8, 1319&#x02013;1323.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0395"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0395"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>U.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Doghaither</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimulddin</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Zahrani</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Ghafari</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In Vitro Cytotoxic and Anticancer Effects of Zamzam Water in Human Lung Cancer (A594) Cell Line</article-title><source>Malays. J. Med. Sci</source><volume>24</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28814929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0400"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0400"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orhan</surname><given-names>I.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacognosy: Science of natural products in drug discovery</article-title><source>Bioimpacts</source><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25337461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0405"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0405">Ozenda, P., 1977. Flore du Sahara. Ed CNRS, Paris, p. 622.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0410"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0410">Panghal, M., Arya, V., Yadav, S., Kumar, S., Yadav, J.P., 2010. Indigenous knowledge of medicinal plants used by Saperas community of Khetawas, Jhajjar District, Haryana, India. J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed. 6, 1, 4. Pharmacognosy Research 2, 2, 31&#x02013;35.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0420"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0415"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porcza</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simms</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chopra</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Honey and Cancer: Current Status and Future Directions</article-title><source>Diseases</source><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>30</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0425"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0420"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prance</surname><given-names>G.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bal&#x000e9;e</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boom</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative Ethnobotany and the Case for Conservation in Ammonia*</article-title><source>Conserv. Biol.</source><volume>1</volume><issue>4</issue><year>1987</year><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>310</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0430"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0425"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>B.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent developments in delivery, bioavailability, absorption and metabolism of curcumin: the golden pigment from golden spice</article-title><source>Cancer Res. Treat.</source><volume>46</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24520218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0435"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0430">Qu&#x000e9;zel, P., Santa, S., 1962&#x02013;1963. Nouvelle Flore de l'Alg&#x000e9;rie et des R&#x000e9;gions D&#x000e9;sertiques M&#x000e9;ridionales. Paris, 2 Tomes, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0440"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0435">R Development Core Team, R.T., 2013. R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org" id="ir035">http://www.r-project.org</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0445"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0440"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>A.S.M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mostofa</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosaddik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadik</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>A.H.M.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of anti-ROS and anticancer properties of Tabebuia pallida L. Leaves</article-title><source>Clin. Phytosci.</source><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>17</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0450"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0445"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raikhlin-Eisenkraft</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentur</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecbalium elaterium (squirting cucumber)&#x02013;remedy or poison?</article-title><source>J. Toxicol. Clin. Toxicol.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10866331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0455"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0450"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajaei</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamadi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants of hezar mountain allocated in South East of iran</article-title><source>Iran J. Pharm. Res.</source><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1153</fpage><lpage>1167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24250549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0460"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0455"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranelletti</surname><given-names>F.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maggiano</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>F.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larocca</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanza</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scambia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fattorossi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Capelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piantelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quercetin inhibits p21-RAS expression in human colon cancer cell lines and in primary colorectal tumors</article-title><source>Int. J. Cancer</source><volume>85</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>438</fpage><lpage>445</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10652438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0465"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0460"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robey</surname><given-names>I.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baggett</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dosescu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sloane</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashim</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghunand</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatenby</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bicarbonate increases tumor pH and inhibits spontaneous metastases</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><volume>69</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>2260</fpage><lpage>2268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19276390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0470"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0465"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Negri</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Talamini</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosetti</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parpinel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnagnarella</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franceschi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dal Maso</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montella</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giacosa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>La Vecchia</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flavonoids and Colorectal Cancer in Italy</article-title><source>Cancer Epidemiol. Biomark. Prev.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>1555</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0475"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0470"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rychlinska</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative determination of arbutin and hydroquinone in different plant materials by HPLC</article-title><source>Notulae Botanicae Horti Agrobotanici Cluj-Napoca</source><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>113</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0480"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0475"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Said</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Greco-Arab and Islamic Herbal Medicine : Traditional System, Ethics, Safety, Efficacy, and Regulatory Issues</chapter-title><year>2011</year><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken, N.J.</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0485"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0480"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boudjelal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarri</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benkhaled</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flora and ethnobotany of medicinal plants in the southeast of the capital of Hodna (Algeria)</article-title><source>Arabian J. Med. Aromatic Plants</source><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>2015</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0490"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0485"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mouyet</surname><given-names>F.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benziane</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheriet</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional use of medicinal plants in a city at steppic character (M&#x02019;sila, Algeria)</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Pharmacognosy Res.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0495"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0490"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maru</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Suppression of error prone pathway is responsible for antimutagenic activity of honey</article-title><source>Food Chem. Toxicol.</source><volume>50</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22269905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0500"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0495"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaheen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadeem-ul-Haque</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simjee</surname><given-names>S.U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganesan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jabeen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis of breast cancer targeting conjugate of temporin-SHa analog and its effect on pro- and anti-apoptotic protein expression in MCF-7 cells</article-title><source>Peptides</source><volume>106</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30026168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0505"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0500"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharifi-Rad</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozleyen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyunegmez Tumer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oluwaseun Adetunji</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>El Omari</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balahbib</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taheri</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouyahya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martorell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural Products and Synthetic Analogs as a Source of Antitumor Drugs</article-title><source>Biomolecules</source><volume>9</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>679</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0510"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0505"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shoaib</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tahir</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>S.W.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishtiaq</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Umer</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sesquiterpene lactone! a promising antioxidant, anticancer and moderate antinociceptive agent from Artemisia macrocephala jacquem</article-title><source>BMC Complement. Altern. Med.</source><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>27</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28061778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0515"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0510"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shomar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zamzam water: Concentration of trace elements and other characteristics</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><volume>86</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>600</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22138338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0520"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0515"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resveratrol-based combinatorial strategies for cancer management</article-title><source>Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.</source><volume>1290</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23855473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0525"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0520"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stacks</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Apigenin and Naringenin: Natural Sources, Pharmacology and Role in Cancer Prevention</chapter-title><year>2015</year><publisher-name>Nova Science Publishers</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Incorporated</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0530"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0525"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vellayappan</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaji</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaganathan</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Supriyanto</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Honey and its Phytochemicals: Plausible Agents in Combating Colon Cancer through its Diversified Actions</article-title><source>J. Food Biochem.</source><volume>40</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>629</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0535"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0530"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ta&#x000ef;bi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Campo</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilagrosa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Gresa</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Nicol&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulet</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinctive physiological and molecular responses to cold stress among cold-tolerant and cold-sensitive Pinus halepensis seed sources</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol.</source><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>236</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30326850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0540"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0535"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ta&#x000ef;bi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>del Campo</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilagrosa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Gresa</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pla</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvete</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Nicol&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulet</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drought Tolerance in Pinus halepensis Seed Sources As Identified by Distinctive Physiological and Molecular</article-title><source>Markers.</source><volume>8</volume><issue>1202</issue><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0545"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0540"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ta&#x000ef;bi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ta&#x000ef;bi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ait Abderrahim</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ennajah</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belkhodja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulet</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of salt stress on growth, chlorophyll content, lipid peroxidation and antioxidant defence systems in Phaseolus vulgaris L</article-title><source>S. Afr. J. Bot.</source><volume>105</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>312</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0550"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0545">The Plant List (2013). Version 1.1. Published on the Internet; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.theplantlist.org" id="ir040">http://www.theplantlist.org</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0555"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0550"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waheed</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Javed</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mushtaq</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shariati</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Majeed</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nigam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heydari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Honey and cancer: A mechanistic review</article-title><source>Clin. Nutr.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>2499</fpage><lpage>2503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30639116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0560"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0555"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arsenic trioxide induces the apoptosis of human breast cancer MCF-7 cells through activation of caspase-3 and inhibition of HERG channels</article-title><source>Exp. Ther. Med.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22977528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0565"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0560">WHO, 2018. Global Health Observatory. who.int/gho/database/en/, in: Geneva, S.W.H.O. (Ed.).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0570"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0565"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeder</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Mammal Species of the World. A Taxonomic and Geographic Reference</chapter-title><edition>(3rd Ed),</edition><year>2005</year><publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0575"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0570"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Traditional Medicine and Modern Medicine from Natural Products</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>559</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0580"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0575"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeichen de Sa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arga&#x000f1;araz</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bindstein</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perinatal toxicology of Ruta chalepensis (Rutaceae) in mice</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>69</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10687865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0585"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0580"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zerrouk</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seijo</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Escuredo</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Flores</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of Ziziphus lotus (jujube) honey produced in Algeria</article-title><source>J. Apic. Res.</source><volume>57</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>174</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0590"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0585"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clerodendranoic acid, a new phenolic acid from Clerodendranthus spicatus</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>17</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>13656</fpage><lpage>13661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23165309</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ak005"><sec id="s0145"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0285">Authors would like to acknowledge the local community in general and informants in particular for their valuable information and support.</p></sec><sec id="s0150"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0290">This report was financed solely by the authors own resources, without financial help of any institution.</p></sec></ack><fn-group><fn id="d32e4207"><p id="np005">Peer review under responsibility of King Saud University.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>