<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Materials and Methods </div>
 <sec id="sec3dot1-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Plant Material and Extraction of Essential Oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Leaves of 
   <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span> were collected in Botucatu City, Brazil (22°57′55,90″ N 48°24′16,99″ W), on a morning during December 2014. For the purpose of scientific research of the species under study, an authorization to access samples of components of the genetic patrimony (Nº 010621/2015-6) was obtained from the National Council of Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq). The plant was identified by a specialist, and a voucher specimen was deposited in the Herbarium of the Federal University of Uberlândia, under number HUFU 71037. The essential oil was obtained by steam distillation of fresh leaves for 2 h using a distiller designed for essential oil production (model MA480—Marconi). The essential oil was separated from water by decantation, filtered (membrane filter—0.2 μm), stored at low temperature (−10 °C) and protected from light until analysis. The percentage yield was calculated relative to the dried mass of the initial sample and this analysis was performed in triplicate.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot2-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Gas Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry (GC/MS) Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oils from 
   <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span> leaves were analyzed using a gas chromatograph coupled to a mass spectrometer, model FOCUS ISQ 230ST (Thermo Scientific, Austin, TX, USA), equipped with a TraceGOLD TG-5MS capillary column (Thermo Scientific, 30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm film thickness). The carrier gas was helium, at a flow rate of 1 mL·min
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. Injector and detector temperatures were 220 °C and 240 °C, respectively; the injection volume was 1 μL and split ratio was 1:20. The oven temperature was programmed from 60 °C to 246 °C, at 3 °C/min. The electron impact energy was set at 70 eV and fragments from 40 to 415 
   <span class="italic">m</span>/
   <span class="italic">z</span> were collected [
   <a rid="B37-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijms-19-00033">37</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The identification of the essential oil components was carried out by comparison of the mass spectrum obtained with that stored in the software library (Nist08), and by comparing the calculated arithmetic retention index (AI) according to the equation proposed by Van Den Dool and Kratz (1963) [
   <a rid="B60-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-ijms-19-00033">60</a>] with arithmetic retention index reported in the literature [
   <a rid="B37-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijms-19-00033">37</a>,
   <a rid="B38-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijms-19-00033">38</a>]. AI calculation was based on retention times of linear alkane standards (C8-C40, Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) run under the same operating conditions as previously described. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantitative analysis was carried out in triplicate and the amounts of volatile compounds were calculated using the internal standard method, taking into account the relative response factor (RRF) according to IOFI Working Group on Methods of Analysis [
   <a rid="B61-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-ijms-19-00033">61</a>]. For this purpose, heptanal (Sigma-Aldrich; 0.0092 mg·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) was selected as the internal standard. Phellandrene, linalool, caryophylene and nerolidol (Sigma-Aldrich) were selected to represent the response factors for monoterpene hydrocarbons, oxygenated monoterpenes, sesquiterpene hydrocarbons and oxygenated sesquiterpenes, respectively. Analyses for the RRF calculation were completed five times at four concentrations (0.0104, 0.0146, 0.0187 and 0.0229 mg·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) [
   <a rid="B62-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-ijms-19-00033">62</a>] and the average response factors were obtained.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot3-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Cytotoxic Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A sample of the essential oil was solubilized in methanol (Synth, São Paulo, Brazil) and diluted in supplemented Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM, Sigma-Aldrich) to form a stock solution of 640 μg·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. Cell viability was tested with cell lines from American Type Culture Collection (ATCC, Rockville, MD, USA). MCF-7 (human metastatic adenocarcinoma-estrogen-receptor positive; ATCC HTB-22) and MDA-MB-231 (human metastatic adenocarcinoma-estrogen-receptor negative; ATCC HTB-26) breast cancer cell lines, and the MCF-10A (human mammary epithelial cells; ATCC CRL-10317) normal breast cell line, were selected for cytotoxicity assays. A solution containing 1 × 10
   <span class="sup">4</span> cells in 100 μL of supplemented DMEM was pipetted into each well and the plate was incubated overnight at 37 °C, with a humidified atmosphere and 5% CO
   <sub>2</sub>, allowing cell adhesion in wells. Once attached and after removal of the culture medium, the stock solution of essential oil was added to the microplate and a serial dilution was performed to achieve concentrations ranging from 4 to 512 μg·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. For this analysis, the controls of cell growth, solvent (methanol 3%), samples and negative control (100% lysed cells) were performed. Microplates were incubated for 48 h at 37 °C with a humidified atmosphere and 5% CO
   <sub>2</sub>. Next, a revealing solution of resazurin (3 mM) diluted in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) was added to each well [
   <a rid="B63-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63-ijms-19-00033">63</a>] and the plate was incubated again for 24 h under the same conditions. Readings of absorbance at 595 nm were performed using a Multiskan GO Microplate Spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific). Assays were performed in six replicates and the results of absorbance were calculated according to the growth control. The cytotoxic concentration at which 50% of the cells are viable (CC
   <sub>50</sub>) was calculated by a dose-response graph of nonlinear regression.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to check specificity, a relationship between normal breast and breast cancer cell lines was established by the selectivity index (SI) and calculated according to the Equation (1) adapted from Case et al. (2006) [
   <a rid="B64-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64-ijms-19-00033">64</a>]: 
   <div class="disp-formula">SI = log (CC
    <sub>50</sub> normal cell line/CC
    <sub>50</sub> cancer cell line).
    <span class="label">(1)</span>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot4-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Flow Cytometry Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For this analysis, MDA-MB-231 and MCF-10A cells were selected based on results from cytotoxic activity assays. Cells were seeded (5 × 10
   <span class="sup">6</span>) in 6-well dishes and treated with essential oil for 48 h at 37 °C at the dose of CC
   <sub>50</sub> previously determined by the cytotoxic activity assay. After treatment, the cells were harvested by trypsinisation, washed with PBS and stained with annexin V and propidium iodide (PI) using a FITC Annexin V Apoptosis Detection Kit I (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA), following the manufacturer’s instructions. The fluorescence was measured in a CytoFLEX Flow Cytometer (Beckman Coulter Inc., Miami, FL, USA) and data analyzed in Kaluza Analysis Software (Beckman Coulter Inc., Miami, FL, USA).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot5-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. Antifungal Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tested strains were obtained from ATCC and the Laboratory of Fungi Biology, Department of Microbiology and Immunology, São Paulo State University (UNESP-Botucatu Campus). No ATCC strains were molecularly identified and deposited at GenBank database of the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). The following microorganisms were used in the evaluation of antifungal activity of the essential oil: 
   <span class="italic">Candida krusei</span> (ATCC 6258), 
   <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span> (ATCC 36801), 
   <span class="italic">Candida guilliermondii</span> (ATCC 22017), 
   <span class="italic">Candida parapsilosis</span> (ATCC 90018), 
   <span class="italic">Candida orthopsilosis</span> (ATCC 96141), 
   <span class="italic">Candida metapsilosis</span> (ATCC 96142), 
   <span class="italic">Cryptococcus neoformans</span> (ATCC 90012), 
   <span class="italic">Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</span> (strain TLM17LM2, GenBank accession number KX774393, yeast form), 
   <span class="italic">Microsporum canis</span> (strain RS5, GenBank accession number KT443098) and 
   <span class="italic">Trichophyton mentagrophytes</span> (ATCC 11480). A microdilution broth susceptibility assay for yeasts and filamentous fungi was performed, as recommended by Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute [
   <a rid="B65-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65-ijms-19-00033">65</a>,
   <a rid="B66-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66-ijms-19-00033">66</a>], with some adaptations. Assays were performed on 96-well microplates (Costar, Cambridge, MA, USA) with RPMI-1640 supplemented with glutamine without sodium bicarbonate (Cultilab, Campinas, Brazil). A sample of essential oil was dissolved in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO, Synth, São Paulo) and a serial dilution was performed to achieve concentrations ranging from 2.44 to 5000 μg·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. The final DMSO concentration was 3% (
   <span class="italic">v</span>/
   <span class="italic">v</span>). For inoculums, adjustment of yeast (
   <span class="italic">Candida</span> spp., 
   <span class="italic">C. neoformans</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. brasiliensis</span>) was performed using microscopic enumeration with a cell-counting hematocytometer (Neubauer chamber, Knittel Gläser, Braunschweig, Germany) from the initial growth at RPMI-1640 medium. 
   <span class="italic">Candida</span> spp. was grown at 37 °C for 48 h, 
   <span class="italic">C. neoformans</span> at 37 °C for 72 h and 
   <span class="italic">P. brasiliensis</span> at 35 °C for 10 days. After counting, the inoculums were adjusted to a final concentration of 1.2 × 10
   <span class="sup">3</span> cell mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. Filamentous fungi, 
   <span class="italic">M. canis</span> and 
   <span class="italic">T. mentagrophytes</span>, were grown on potato dextrose agar (PDA; Oxoid, Basingstoke, Hampshire, UK) for 7 days at 25 °C before counting. Cell counting in a Neubauer chamber was also performed, and microplates were inoculated with a final concentration of 2 × 10
   <span class="sup">4</span> cell mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. The tested systems were incubated in a humid atmosphere, with agitation, at 37 °C for 48 h for 
   <span class="italic">Candida</span> spp. and 72 h for 
   <span class="italic">C. neoformans. P. brasiliensis</span> was incubated for 14 days at 35 °C with agitation and 
   <span class="italic">M. canis</span> and 
   <span class="italic">T. mentagrophytes</span> for 10 days at 25 °C without agitation. The experiment was performed in six replicates and the growth inhibition was determined by measuring turbidity of the cultured medium at 530 nm using a spectrophotometer (BioTek, Winooski, VT, USA). Amphotericin B (Sigma-Aldrich) was used as positive control. Controls of sterility of the broth, control culture (inoculum), essential oil and DMSO (3%) were performed.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot6-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.6. Antibacterial Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experiments were performed with standard strains from ATCC and clinical isolates (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 6) obtained from the Laboratory of Microbiology, Department of Microbiology and Immunology, São Paulo State University (UNESP-Botucatu Campus). The study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and the use of isolated microorganisms was approved by the Institutional Committee on Human Research (number 47186415.0.0000.5411-8 March, 2015), according to the ethical principles for medical research involving human subjects, and the strains were submitted to biochemical tests for phenotypic confirmation of the species [
   <a rid="B67-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67-ijms-19-00033">67</a>]. The following microorganisms were used: methicillin-resistant 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> (MRSA) (ATCC 33591), methicillin-sensitive 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> (MSSA) (ATCC 25923), 
   <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span> (ATCC 43895) and 
   <span class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> (ATCC 27853). Susceptibility assays were performed according to the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute [
   <a rid="B68-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68-ijms-19-00033">68</a>] on 96-well microplates (Costar) with Mueller Hinton broth (Difco, Detroit, MI, USA) culture medium. The sample of essential oil was dissolved in DMSO (Synth, 160,000 μg·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) and serial dilution was performed to achieve concentrations ranging from 2.44 to 5000 μg·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. The final DMSO concentration was 3% (
   <span class="italic">v</span>/
   <span class="italic">v</span>). Bacterial strains were grown (37 °C for 18–24 h) in brain heart infusion (BHI; Difco) and, after standardization by 0.5 McFarland scale, were inoculated (around 10
   <span class="sup">5</span> cfu·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) in wells at concentrations previously prepared. After incubation (37 °C for 18–24 h), the minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) of each strain was visually recorded after addition of 50 μL of resazurin (0.01%) in respective wells. Polymyxin B (Latinofarma, Cotia, Brazil) was used as a positive control for Gram-negative bacteria and Cephalothin (Latinofarma) for Gram-positive bacteria. Controls of sterility of the broth, culture control (inoculum), essential oil and DMSO (3%) were performed. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot7-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.7. Statistical Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis of the data was performed by analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey’s test for analysis of cytotoxic activity and the Kruskal–Wallis test followed by the Student–Newman–Keuls test or Dunn’s test for analysis of minimal inhibitory concentration against microorganisms using SigmaPlot 11.0 software (Erkrath, North Rhine-Westphalia, Germany). For flow cytometry analysis, two-way ANOVA followed by Sidak’s test was performed using the software GraphPad Prism 6.01. Probability values 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05 were considered to denote a statistically significant difference.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
