<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The common procedures to fabricate the superhydrophobic surface on Cu substrates include two important steps: One is how to achieve a rough face on the micro- and nano-scales, the other is how to modify a firm film or membrane with a low-surface energy effectively. Cu surfaces were easily achieved by simple acid or base etching, replacement deposition, and electrodeposition [
 <xref rid="B11-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. In general, micro- and nano-scale structures on the hydrophobic surfaces of these copper substrates were usually involved in many types of morphology and different modified compounds with a low surface energy. Shirtcliffe et al. developed a method to construct a nanoribbons’ surface with a size of 1 µm × 100 nm × 6 nm, which was coated with a commercial fabric waterproofing agent sequentially. The uniform superhydrophobic layer on the inside of round copper tubes of a millimetric internal radius could enhance flow rates and reduced drag for both water and 50% 
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">w</italic> water-glycerol mixtures [
 <xref rid="B17-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Chen et al. used a one-step solution-immersion process to prepare a compact and uniform superhydrophobic film, the leaf-like and compact submicroscopic structure was maintained in ethanol solutions of 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-dodecanethiol and tetradecanoic acid. Meanwhile, the results of theoretical calculations showed the bonding style was two Cu atoms combined with one S atom [
 <xref rid="B18-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Chaudhary et al. prepared a superhydrophobic CuO/Cu(OH)
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> coating on the copper sheet surface with microflowers and nanoneedle arrays by a simple solution-immersion in a mixture of 2.0 M sodium hydroxide and 0.15 M ammonium persulfate at room temperature, without using a low surface energy material [
 <xref rid="B19-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. A similar etching method was developed with the H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>/HCl etchants, followed by the modification of stearic acid. The as-prepared surface was composed of many convex polyhedral protrusions with diameters ranging from 0.5 to 2 μm and many cavities included sizes of hundreds of nanometers on these protrusions [
 <xref rid="B20-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Cheng et al. fabricated a mesh film with pine-needle-like structures, followed by the modification of the mixed thiol (containing both alkyl and carboxylic acid groups). The formed Cu(OH)
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> on the surface possessed a diameter of 80−150 nm and a length of about 8 μm [
 <xref rid="B21-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Other typical structures onto the copper substrates also include the non-flaking bicrystalline CuO nanowires [
 <xref rid="B22-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. The pine-cone-like hierarchical micro-nanostructure [
 <xref rid="B23-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>], the surface distributed grooves and ridges in micrometer scale and many nano-wrinkles [
 <xref rid="B24-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>], and the unique nanoworm-like structure [
 <xref rid="B25-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] were mainly modified by fluorosilane previously. Also, some other examples involve rodlike nanostructures of Cu(OH)
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> [
 <xref rid="B26-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>], highly dense ordered Cu
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O nanorods [
 <xref rid="B28-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>], flower-like [
 <xref rid="B29-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>], leaves-like, and wormlike micro-/nano-scale structures [
 <xref rid="B30-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>], and these hydrophobic surfaces were finally modified by 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-alkanethiolates [
 <xref rid="B32-polymers-11-00097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. To some extent, the techniques described above were efficient for separating mixtures of water and oil, however, there are some disadvantages that need to be overcome, such as time-consuming and complicated fabrication, special equipment, and expensive materials. Especially, very few reports have involved the interaction mechanism on the superhydrophobic surface.
</p>
