<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemicals</div>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All chemicals used were of analytical reagent grade. All reagents were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich-Fluka (Saint-Quentin France).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection of plant material</div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The flowers of 
   <span class="italic">Citrus limon</span> were collected by hand in the beginning of Avril 2015 from the Cap Bon of Tunisia, precisely in the surroundings of Nabeul localized in 5 m of altitude and 1044 of longitude. In Mars 2015, Nabeul average rainfall was 31 mm, the average of Temperature was 20.5 °C and humidity was 79% (NIM-National Institute of Meteorology-Tunisia, 2015). Then the botanical identification of 
   <span class="italic">Citrus lemon</span> was conducted by Professor Ferjeni Ben Abduallah, botanist in the Faculty of Science of Sfax, Tunisia.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oil extraction</div>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The oil extraction was obtained from 1 kg fresh plant by steam distillation during 3 h using a Clevenger-type apparatus [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. The aqueous phase was extracted with dichloromethane (3 × 50 ml) and dried with anhydrous sodium sulphate (PubChem CID: 24,243). After filtration the solvent is eliminated by pressure distillation reduced in rotary evaporator and pure oil was stored at 4 °C in obscurity till the beginning of 
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO analysis. The amount of oil obtained from each plant material was calculated as:
  </p>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oil (%
   <span class="italic">v</span>/
   <span class="italic">w</span>) = observed volume of oil (ml)/weight of sample (g) × 100.
  </p>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO was solubilised in 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-Hexane (PubChem CID: 8058) for gas chromatography and mass spectrometry analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antioxidant testing assays</div>
  <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DPPH radical scavenging activity</div>
   <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Radical scavenging activity of the different fractions was determined using DPPH radical as a reagent according to the method of Kirby and Schmidt with some modifications [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. Briefly, 1 ml of a 4% (
    <span class="italic">w</span>/
    <span class="italic">v</span>) solution of DPPH radical in ethanol (PubChem CID: 702) was mixed with 500 μl of sample solutions (different concentrations). The mixture was incubated for 20 min in the dark at room temperature. Scavenging capacity was read spectrophotometrically by monitoring the decrease of the absorbance at 517 nm. Lower absorbance of the reaction mixture indicates higher free radical scavenging activity. Ascorbic acid was used as standard. DPPH radical scavenging activity (%) was calculated according to the formula: DPPH radical scavenging activity (%) = [(OD
    <sub>blank</sub> − OD
    <sub>sample</sub>)/OD
    <sub>blank</sub>] × 100.
   </p>
   <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">OD
    <sub>blank</sub> is the absorbance of the control reaction containing all reagents except the tested compound. OD
    <sub>sample</sub> is the absorbance of the test compound. Extract concentration providing 50% inhibition (IC
    <sub>50</sub>) was calculated from the graph plotting inhibition percentage against extract concentration. Tests were carried out in triplicate.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">β-Carotene bleaching assay</div>
   <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antioxidant activity was determined according to the β-carotene bleaching method described by Pratt [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. A stock solution of β-carotene/linoleic acid mixture was prepared as follows: 0.5 mg of β-carotene (PubChem CID: 5,280,489) was dissolved in 1 ml of chloroform (PubChem CID: 6212) with 25 μl of linoleic acid (PubChem CID: 5,280,450) and 200 mg of Tween-20 (PubChem CID: 443,314). Chloroform was completely evaporated, using a vacuum evaporator. Then, 100 ml of distilled water, saturated with oxygen (30 min), were added and the obtained solution was vigorously shaken. Four ml of this reaction mixture were dispensed into test tubes and 200 μl of each sample, prepared at different concentrations, were added. The emulsion system was incubated for 2 h at 50 °C. The same procedure was repeated with Butylated hydoxytoluene (BHT) as positive control and a blank as a negative control. After this incubation period, the absorbance of each mixture was measured at 490 nm. Antioxidant activity in β-carotene bleaching model in percentage (A %) was calculated with the following equation: A %  = 1 − (A
    <sub>0</sub> – A
    <sub>t</sub>/A
    <span class="sup">’</span>
    <sub>0</sub>−A
    <span class="sup">’</span>
    <sub>t</sub>) × 100, where A
    <sub>0</sub> and A’
    <sub>0</sub> are absorbances of the sample and the blank, respectively, measured at zero time, and A 
    <sub>t</sub> and A’
    <sub>t</sub> are absorbances of the sample and the blank, respectively, measured after 2 h. All tests were carried out in triplicate.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antimicrobial activity</div>
  <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microorganisms and growth conditions</div>
   <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Authentic pure cultures of bacteria and fungi were obtained from international culture collections: American type culture collection (ATCC) and the local culture collection of the Center of Biotechnology of Sfax, Tunisia. They included Gram-positive bacteria: 
    <span class="italic">Bacillus subtilis</span> ATCC 6633
    <span class="italic">, Bacillus cereus</span> ATCC 14579
    <span class="italic">, Staphylococcus aureus</span> ATCC 25923
    <span class="italic">, Staphylococcus epidermidis</span> ATCC 12228
    <span class="italic">, Enterococcus faecalis</span> ATCC 29212 and 
    <span class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</span> ATCC 19117 and Gram-negative bacteria: 
    <span class="italic">Salmonella enterica</span> ATCC 43972
    <span class="italic">, Escherichia coli</span> ATCC 25922 and 
    <span class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> ATCC 9027.
   </p>
   <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The following fungal strains were also tested: 
    <span class="italic">Aspergillus niger</span> CTM 10099
    <span class="italic">, Aspergillus flavus</span> (food isolate)
    <span class="italic">, Aspergillus nidulans</span> (food isolate), 
    <span class="italic">Aspergillus fumigatus</span> (food isolate), 
    <span class="italic">Fusarium graminearum</span> (ISPAVE 271
    <span class="italic">), Fusarium oxysporum</span> (CTM10402)
    <span class="italic">, Fusarium culmorum</span> (ISPAVE 21w) and 
    <span class="italic">Alternaria alternata</span> (CTM 10230)
    <span class="italic">.</span> The bacterial strains were grown on Mueller Hinton broth (Bio-Rad, France) at 37 °C for 12–14 h while potato dextrose agar (PDA) (1.5% agar) at 28 °C for 4 days were used for fungi. Inocula were prepared from an overnight broth culture by their dilution in saline solution to approximately 10
    <span class="sup">7</span> colony-forming units (CFU)/ml for bacteria and 10
    <span class="sup">5</span> spores/ml for fungus.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Agar diffusion method</div>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antibacterial and antifungal tests were performed by agar well diffusion method as described by Tagg and McGiven [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>] and broth microdilution assay using sterile Mueller–Hinton media (Bio-Rad, France) for bacterial strains and potato dextrose agar (Bio-Rad,France) for antifungal tests. Fifteen milliliters of the molten agar (45 °C) were poured into sterile petri dishes (Ø 90 mm). Working cell suspensions were prepared and 100 μl were evenly spread onto the surface of the agar plates of Mueller-Hinton agar (Oxoid Ltd., UK) for bacteria, or potatoes dextrose agar medium (Oxoid Ltd., UK) for fungi. Once the plates had been aseptically dried, 06 mm wells were punched into the agar with a sterile Pasteur pipette. The 
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO were dissolved in dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO)/water (1/1) and sterile water to a final concentration of 50 mg/ml. Thus, 50 μl were placed into the wells and the plates were incubated at 37 °C for 24 h for bacterial strains and 72 h for fungi at 28 °C. Gentamicin (10 μg/wells), Amphotericin B (PubChem CID: 5,280,965) at 20 μg/wells and DMSO served as positive and negative control. Antimicrobial activity was evaluated by measuring the diameter of circular inhibition zones around the well. Tests were performed in triplicate.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Determination of MIC and MFC</div>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) of 
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO were determined according to Gulluce et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>] against a panel of 21 microorganisms representing different species of different ecosystems. The test was performed in sterile 96-well microplates with a final volume in each microplate well of 100 μl. A stock solution of the 
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO (50 mg/ml) was prepared in DMSO/water (1/9). The inhibitory activity of the 
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO was properly prepared and transferred to each well in order to obtain a twofold serial dilution of the original sample and to produce the concentration range of 0.039–10 mg/ml. To each test well 10 μl of cell suspension were added to final inoculums concentrations of 10
   <span class="sup">6</span> CFU/ml for bacteria and 10
   <span class="sup">5</span> spores/ml for fungus. Positive growth control wells consisted of bacteria or fungi only in their adequate medium. DMSO/water (1/9) (PubChem CID: 679) was used as negative control. The plates were then covered with the sterile plate covers and incubated at 37 °C for 24 h for bacterial strains and 72 h for fungi at 28 °C. The MIC was defined as the lowest concentration of the total essential oil at which the microorganism does not demonstrate visible growth after incubation. As an indicator of microorganism growth, 25 μl of Thiazolyl Blue Tetrazolium Bromide (PubChem CID: 64,965) (MTT), indicator solution (0.5 mg/ml) dissolved in sterile water were added to the wells and incubated at 37 °C for 30 min. The colourless tetrazolium salt acts as an electron acceptor and is reduced to a red-coloured formazan product by biologically active organisms. Where microbial growth was inhibited, the solution in the well remained clear after incubation with MTT. The minimum fungicidal concentrations (MFCs) were determined by serial subcultivation of 10 μl in Potatoes Dextrose Agar (PDA) plates and incubated for 72 h at 28 °C. The lowest concentration with no visible growth was defined as the MFC, indicating ≥99.5% killing of the original inoculum. DMSO and ethanol were used as a negative control. The determinations of MIC and MFC values were done in triplicate.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In situ effect of 
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO
  </div>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The in situ efficacy of the 
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO was evaluated against 
   <span class="italic">L. monocytogenes</span> in minced beef meat model according to the procedure described by Ben Hsouna et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>] and Careaga et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>] with slight modifications. Briefly, a fresh working culture of 
   <span class="italic">L. monocytogenes</span> containing about 10
   <span class="sup">6</span> CFU/ml was prepared by suspending 3–5 isolated colonies in 10 ml of Mueller-Hinton broth (MH) and was cultured overnight at 37 °C for 24 h to reach the stationary phase. Freshly post-rigor lean beef muscles were obtained from a slaughterhouse in Sfax-Tunisia and transported to the laboratory in insulated polystyrene boxes on ice within 1 h of the chopping process. A healthy and freshly slaughtered animal has its muscle sterile [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. In order to reduce the number of microorganisms attached to the surface of beef muscle, each piece was immersed in boiling water for 5 min. The cooked surface of the muscle was eliminated with sterile knives under aseptic conditions. The pieces of meat prepared as described above were minced in a sterile grinder, and portions of 25 ± 0.1 g were placed in bags. Half of the meat samples were inoculated with 2 × 10
   <span class="sup">2</span> CFU of 
   <span class="italic">L. monocytogenes</span>/g of meat and mixed homogeneously for 3 min at room temperature to ensure proper distribution of the pathogen. Before inoculation of the second half of meat, the 
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO was dissolved in 10% DMSO, filtered through 0.22 μm pore-size black polycarbonate filters (Millipore) and was then added two concentrations of 2MIC and 3MIC corresponding to 0.06 and 0.312 mg of 
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO/g of meat, respectively; and mixed to evenly distribute the microorganisms. All bags containing the samples of meat were stored at 7 °C and examined at 0, 2, 4, 6, 8 and 10 days of storage for 
   <span class="italic">L. monocytogenes</span> enumeration. After predetermined intervals, the 
   <span class="italic">L. monocytogenes</span> isolation was done by removing the pieces aseptically and blending with 250 ml of MH. The samples were homogenized for 1 min, and incubated at 37 °C for 6 h. From this pre-enrichment (for the resuscitation of possible injured living cells), the remaining 
   <span class="italic">L. monocytogenes</span> was determined by the plate colony count technique. After serial 10-fold dilution technique with physiological saline solution, 100 μl of each sample were spread onto surfaces of the Muller Hinton agar medium followed by incubation at 37 °C for 24 h. Sterile saline water was added in the untreated control instead of 
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO, inoculated with the test bacteria and stored under the same conditions as the other samples. Three individual replicates of each experiment were performed, in all cases.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample preparation</div>
  <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Raw meat beef was provided by a local supplier (slaughterhouse of Sfax, Tunisia). They were placed in insulated polystyrene boxes on ice and transferred to the laboratory within 1 h of slaughtering. Raw meat beef was raw minced by grinding in a sterile grinder. Concerning the conditioning of raw minced beef for storage at 4 °C studies, five equal portions (C, T1- T4): C (Control), T
   <sub>1</sub> (
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO: 0.06%), T
   <sub>2</sub> (
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO: 0.312%), T
   <sub>3</sub> (BHT at 0.01%), T
   <sub>4</sub> (
   <span class="italic">Cl</span>EO 0.312% and BHT at 0.01%). For each experiment, all runs were applied to a single batch of raw minced beef meat. Each formulation produced one mixture homogeneous which was vacuum stuffed into plastic casings to produce three ‘replicates’.
  </p>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Meat samples were stored at 4 °C for 10 days and analyzed for pH and TBARS.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">pH determination</div>
  <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">pH was determined for the homogeneous mixtures of meat with distilled water using a proportion of 1:10, 
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">v</span> [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. A 5 g portion of the sample was homogenized in 50 ml of distilled water (pH 7.00) and the mixture was filtered. The pH of the filtrate was measured using pH-meter (pH 210 Microprocessor pH Meter, HANNA instruments, Germany) at each sampling point.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS) value</div>
  <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">TBARS were determined according to the method of Eymard et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>]. Two grams of sample were mixed with 100 μl of BHT (PubChem CID: 31,404) in ethanol (1 g/l) and 16 ml of trichloroacetic acid (TCA 50 g/l) (PubChem CID: 6421). Samples were homogenized by a kitchen blender for 10 min then filtered. Two ml of filtrate (or 2 ml of TCA for blank) were added to 2 ml of thiobarbituric acid (PubChem CID: 2,723,628) solution (20 mol/l). The tightly closed tubes were heated at 70 °C for 30 min and rapidly cooled in ice. Absorbance was read against the blank at 508 (A508nm), 532 (A532nm) and 600 (A600nm) with a spectrophotometer (T 60UV- visible Spectrophotometer, PG instruments). The absorbance measured at the maximum (A532 nm) was corrected for the baseline drift as follows: A532 nm corrected = A532 nm − [((A508 nm − A600 nm) × (600 – 532))/(600/508)] − A600 nm. Results were expressed as mg of malonaldehyde (MDA) equivalents per kg of sample (mg/kg) using the molar extinction coefficient of the MDA–TBA adduct at 532 nm (1.56 × 105 M − 1 cm − 1) according to Buege and Aust [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. The MDA was determined using the following formula: mgMDAeq/kg = (A corrected × VTCA × 2 × MMDA . 10 – 2)/(1.56 × m).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography–mass spectrometry (GC–MS)</div>
  <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analysis of the essential oil was performed on a GC–MS HP model 6980 inert MSD (Agilent Technologies, J&amp;W Scientific Products, Palo Alto, CA, USA), equipped with an Agilent Technologies capillary HP-5MS column (60 m length; 0.25 mm i.d.; 0.25 mm film thickness), and coupled to a mass selective detector (MSD5973, ionization voltage 70 eV; all Agilent, Santa Clara, CA). The carrier gas was Helium and was used at 1.2 ml/min flow rate. The oven temperature program was as follows: 1 min at 100 °C ramped from 100 to 280 °C at 5 °C min
   <span class="sup">−1</span> and 25 min at 280 °C. The chromatograph was equipped with a split/split less injector used in the split less mode. Relative proportion of each component was expressed as percentage obtained by peak area normalization, all relative response factors being taken as one. Their Kovats indices were calculated using a homologous series of C
   <sub>10</sub>-C
   <sub>22</sub>
   <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes injected at the same conditions. Identification of components was assigned by matching their mass spectra with Wiley Registry of Mass Spectral Data 7th edition (Agilent Technologies, Inc.) and National Institute of Standards and Technology 05 MS (NIST) library data. Identifications were also made by comparison of their Kovats retention indices with private reference libraries and from the literature.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Turkey’s post hoc test were performed to determine significant differences between the treatments using SPSS 19 statistical package (SPSS Ltd., Woking, UK). Microbiological data were transformed into logarithms of the number of colony forming units (CFU/g) and subjected to analysis of variance. Means and standard errors were calculated. Differences among the mean values of the various treatments were determined by the least significant difference test. A probability level of 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05 was used in testing the statistical significance of all experimental data. Mean differences were separated by the least significance difference (LSD) procedure.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
