<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nie et al. summarized the roles of ARSs in various immune diseases, such as autoimmune diseases, infectious diseases, and tumor immunity, and described their role as important regulators and signaling molecules in the development of immune cells [
 <xref rid="B75-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Antisynthetase syndrome (ASSD) is a heterogeneous group of autoimmune diseases, including interstitial lung disease (ILD), myositis, mechanic’s hands, Raynaud’s phenomenon, and arthritis. ASSD is often caused by specific anti-ARS autoantibodies [
 <xref rid="B76-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], and the specificity of anti-ARS autoantibodies is related to the clinical features, disease severity, and survival of ASSD patients [
 <xref rid="B77-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. ARSs are also dysregulated in other autoimmune diseases, including multiple sclerosis, rheumatoid arthritis, immune thrombocytopenia, and systemic lupus erythematosus [
 <xref rid="B79-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. For example, Wang et al. analyzed the interaction of indoleamine-2,3-dioxygenase (IDO)-expressing dendritic cells (DCs) and TrpRS-expressing CD4(+) T cells in Graves’ disease (GD) patients. In general, IDO and tryptophanyl-tRNA synthetase (TrpRS) are responsible for the metabolism and utilization of tryptophan, respectively, and play important roles in immune regulation [
 <xref rid="B83-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. From their analysis, the ratio of serum kynurenine to tryptophan was increased in GD, TrpRS expression from CD4(+) T cells was increased, and there was resistance to IDO-mediated immunosuppression from DCs [
 <xref rid="B84-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. ARSs are also closely related to tumor immunity, that is, tumor cells can regulate the functions of immune cells by secreting ARSs, or tumor-related immune cells can secrete ARSs and affect tumor development. For example, Wellman et al. suggested that the direct correlation of ThrRS levels with disease stage in ovarian cancer patients is derived from ThrRS-regulated angiogenesis and immune cell responses [
 <xref rid="B85-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Additionally, Adam et al. discovered that cancer cells could upregulate TrpRS in two different ways to adapt to the nutritional stress caused by tryptophan degradation. First, tryptophan depletion caused by the high expression of indoleamine-2,3-dioxygenase-1 (IDO1) and tryptophan-2,3-dioxygenase (TDO2) in LN229 glioblastoma cells upregulates TrpRS expression through the activation of the general control nonderepressible-2 (GCN2) kinase and phosphorylation of eukaryotic translation initiation factor 2α (eIF2α), followed by the activation of activating transcription factor 4 (ATF4). Second, tumor-infiltrating T cells jointly induce the expression of IDO1 and TrpRS in breast cancer, colon carcinoma, and B-cell lymphoma by secreting IFN-γ [
 <xref rid="B86-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. As far as we understand, no small molecule directly related to the autoimmune diseases caused by ARSs is known. Given the high limitations of current immuno-oncology therapies in the clinic, ARS-regulating small molecules that are related to tumor immunity can also be an interesting area to explore. The important functions of tRNA synthetases in neurological and neuromuscular disorders have been explored recently as well [
 <xref rid="B87-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. ARSs have been studied as therapeutic targets predominantly for pathogen-derived infectious diseases because of concerns that ARS catalytic site inhibitors would block translation in normal cells. However, their indispensable role in other human diseases has been explored, and some ARS inhibitors are undergoing clinical studies for fibrosis as an example. Given the vast number of studies reported on the role of ARS in tumors, it is reasonable to expect that more clinical studies will emerge for cancer therapeutics in the near future. The role of ARS in central nervous system disorders has recently been revealed. As such, the relatively unexplored area of ARS as a target for human diseases other than infectious diseases is being explored by burgeoning biological investigations. Upon these advancements in the newly found roles of ARSs in human diseases, approaches using small molecules targeting ARSs may drive innovative next-generation therapeutic agents.
</p>
