<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hanahan and Weinberg described various hallmarks of cancer [
 <xref rid="B32-nutrients-12-00609" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], which have enabled us to study the impact of extracts/compounds on these hallmarks (e.g., evasion of programmed cell death) and their related pathways, rather than on cancer directly. Underlying these hallmarks are mechanisms such as inflammation, genome instability and the creation of a tumour microenvironment [
 <xref rid="B32-nutrients-12-00609" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Many of the in vitro studies outlined in 
 <xref rid="nutrients-12-00609-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> showed an increase in anti-oxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B31-nutrients-12-00609" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], increase in apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B19-nutrients-12-00609" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-nutrients-12-00609" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] or an upregulation of pro-apoptotic genes [
 <xref rid="B21-nutrients-12-00609" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-nutrients-12-00609" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and anti-inflammatory activity [
 <xref rid="B23-nutrients-12-00609" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In addition, PARP, which is involved in DNA repair, genomic stability and programmed cell death, increased in response to treatment in a sarcoma cell line [
 <xref rid="B20-nutrients-12-00609" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Cell cycle dysregulation is another hallmark of cancer [
 <xref rid="B32-nutrients-12-00609" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] and may be a target of the mechanism of action of FPKc. This reasoning is supported by in vitro evidence showing the inhibition of cell proliferation; damage to cell membrane in sarcoma but not healthy cells; the triggering of S-phase cell cycle arrest; a decrease in MMP and release of mitochondrial cytochrome C [
 <xref rid="B19-nutrients-12-00609" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Together, these in vitro studies show that 
 <italic>F. pinicola</italic> extracts/compounds have anti-cancer activities which warrant further investigation.
</p>
