<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">When the solvent used is water, the technique is also called superheated water, subcritical water extraction, high temperature water extraction, pressurized hot water extraction or hot water extraction. Water is used in a liquid state under pressure between 100 째C and the critical temperature of 374 째C. Temperature has an important effect on yield and selectivity. The dielectric constant of water decreases with temperature, enabling the extraction of compounds with different polarities at different temperatures. High temperature also enhances diffusivities, making possible the transport of solutes from the solid matrix, and a compromise solution with thermal degradation has to be reached. The major variable during the operation is temperature, at 150 째C or higher, since water properties (especially the polarity) are significantly affected and polymeric substrates can be hydrolyzed because of the enhanced reactivity of water under these conditions. This strategy is attractive for the conversion of aquatic biomass, since the energy-intensive drying steps could be avoided [
 <xref rid="B86-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> hydrothermal liquefaction shows substantial variation in composition, with a bio crude oil yield from 9 to 20% [
 <xref rid="B85-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>]. The hydrothermal liquefaction with subcritical water (300 째C) is very important to extract organic solvents, such as methanol and ethanol [
 <xref rid="B52-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. This technology is also suitable for treating a combination of microalgae and macroalgae for heavy metal bioremediation and bioenergy production [
 <xref rid="B86-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>]. The use of alcoholic solvents increased the bio-oil yield and converted the acids obtained in bio-oil to the corresponding methyl and ethyl esters. High-temperature liquefaction was used to improve the hydrolysis yield of 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> sugars, which is already higher than other agricultural biomass [
 <xref rid="B87-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>]. This process generated less microbial inhibitors (HMF, 5-hydroxymethylfurfural) regarding other pre-treatments. After comparing different pre-treatments (organic solvents, alkaline solvents, liquid hot water and ionic liquids) to obtain an efficiency saccharification of 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic>, it appears that organic solvent and liquid hot water provide the highest glucan yield with 81% and 63%, respectively [
 <xref rid="B88-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>]. The most efficient saccharification before ethanol production is reached with the liquid hot water treatment with a 98% yield.
</p>
