<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Development of new antifungal drugs implies a high level of activity against targeted fungi and acceptable toxicity against host cells. In this aim, we have developed a new family of azole derivatives, indolyl-triazoles
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>25</sup>
 </xref>, that could inhibit yeast growth at low concentrations (MIC
 <sub>90</sub>s &lt; 0.50 µg/mL). The compound 
 <bold>8 g</bold> has a broad-spectrum activity against most clinical relevant 
 <italic>Candida</italic> species. Against all 
 <italic>Candida</italic> spp., MIC range of 
 <bold>8 g</bold> (&lt; 0.016 – 4 µg/mL) was narrower than for fluconazole or voriconazole with MIC ranges of &lt; 0.125 – &gt; 64 µg/mL and &lt; 0.016 – &gt; 8 µg/mL, respectively. Against fluconazole low-susceptible spp. (
 <italic>C. glabrata</italic> and 
 <italic>C. krusei</italic>), 
 <bold>8 g</bold> was more active than fluconazole and voriconazole. Because of their increasing frequency in bloodstream infection and their ability to resist to antifungal drugs, these species are now the real target of new drugs
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref>. 
 <bold>8 g</bold> inhibited their growth at very low concentrations (MIC
 <sub>90</sub>s = 0.25 µg/mL) whereas fluconazole and voriconazole have higher MIC
 <sub>90</sub>s, 64 and 1 µg/mL, respectively. Moreover 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>, being the most frequently isolated species during invasive candidiasis, is highly sensitive to 
 <bold>8 g</bold> (MIC
 <sub>90</sub> &lt; 0.5 µg/mL). Second-generation triazole antifungals (voriconazole, posaconazole, isavuconazole) have a broad anti-infectious spectrum. When tested against 
 <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>, 
 <bold>8 g</bold> showed a moderate activity, since the concentration that inhibited 80% of the growth was 23 µg/mL. Because triazole derivatives (itraconazole, fluconazole and posaconazole) could inhibit ergosterol-like synthesis in Trypanosomatids
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <bold>8 g</bold> was tested against 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic>. Results (data not shown) showed that 
 <bold>8 g</bold> was effective 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 8 ± 2 µg/mL) against 
 <italic>Leishmania mexicana</italic> promastigote stage. Further investigations must be done to evaluate activity against the most relevant amastigote stage encountered in human host.
</p>
