<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effects of oregano essential oil on behavioral tests in the chronic unpredictable stress-treated rats</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Force swimming test</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the end of day 10, all animals which had undergone CUS protocol showed a significant (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001) increase in duration of immobility in FST when compared with the baseline (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>). The OEO administered to the stressed animals produced significant (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05) decrease in the duration of immobility when compared with CUS group. Fluoxetine significantly reduced the duration of immobility (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01) when compared to CUS group. In CUS + saline group the immobility time was significantly higher than the baseline (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Effects of CUS and intraperitoneal treatment with saline, oregano essential oil (0.2 mL/kg), diazepam (3 mg/kg), and fluoxetine (10 mg/kg) on the immobility time in (A), forced swimming test and (B), sucrose preference test. Each point represents mean ± SEM (
    <span class="italic">n</span> = 7). *, **, and *** indicate significant differences (
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05, 
    <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.01, and 
    <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.0001, respectively) from baseline values; # and ## indicate significant differences (
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05 and 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01, respectively) from CUS day 10 in both experiments. (Base), baseline values; (CUS), chronic unpredictable stress; (CUS d10), measurements at the time point 10 days after beginning of stress exposure; (Saline), saline; (OEO): oregano essential oil; (FLX), fluoxetine; (DZ), diazepam.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="RPS-13-130-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sucrose preference test</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1B</a>, the mean of baseline sucrose preference index was 76.2 %. Chronic unpredictable stress procedure caused a significant drop of sucrose preference. During the CUS procedure, significant decrease was observed on day 10 compared to the baseline (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001). After the administration of OEO for two weeks, the sucrose preferences of the CUS + OEO group was significantly higher than those of the CUS group (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05). Meanwhile, treatment with fluoxetine and diazepam also significantly increased the percentage of sucrose consumption as compared to the CUS group (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05). Treatment with saline for two weeks did not affect sucrose preference index. In CUS + saline group the sucrose preference was significantly lower than the baseline (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1B</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
