<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The highly reactive molecules derived from oxygen molecules are known as ROS. Recently, ROS have received increasing interest because they are produced in the body as a result of aerobic metabolism, and their overproduction is related to some diseases initiation and progress. Additionally, a connection between ROS generation and the onset of senescence process in the human body has been well evidenced. Hydroxyl radical (HO
 <sup class="sup">•</sup>), superoxide radical (O
 <sup class="sup">•−</sup>
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>), peroxyl radical (ROO
 <sup class="sup">•</sup>) and hydrogen peroxide (H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) are the main ROS molecules. In recent years, the potent radical scavenging activity of the extracts against ROS can be devalued under in vitro conditions. The obtained extracts from different parts of walnut fruit have been evaluated for their abilities in the scavenging of different types of ROS radicals (
 <xref rid="molecules-24-02133-t007" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 7</xref>). For different parts of walnut fruit, only the hydrogen peroxide radical scavenging of kernel and husk extracts was tested [
 <xref rid="B182-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">182</xref>]. In the case of superoxide radical scavenging, the antiradical activities of extracts derived from different parts of walnut fruit have been comprehensively investigated in several research studies [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B140-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">140</xref>,
 <xref rid="B182-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">182</xref>]. Among different parts of extracts derived from walnut fruit, only the radical scavenging activity for the shell extract was reported [
 <xref rid="B140-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">140</xref>]. There are no reports on the peroxyl radical scavenging activity of walnut fruit.
</p>
