<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par38">The antihypertensive activities of 
 <italic>A. scoparia</italic> (AS) on hypertensive rats (ASHR) showed splendid activity (Cho et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2015</xref>). 
 <italic>A. persia</italic> (AP) is used in folk medicine for antihypertensive potency. The aqueous methanolic extracts of 
 <italic>AP</italic> are used for obtaining cardiovascular effects, for blood pressure (BP), cardiac rate (CR) of normotensive ephedrine induced hypertensive rats. High blood pressure was decreased by a single sip of ephedrine (40 mg/kg/IM) to uplift BP 20–30 mmHg. Aqueous methanolic extracts were given at a dose of (300, 400, and 500 mg/kg) by gavage process excellent results for the systolic blood pressure of normotensive rats observed at 400 mg/kg afterward 20 min consummation while others don’t influence diastolic BP or HR compared with enalapril (30 mg/kg). Oral consummation of AP extracts next 20 min systolic BP in normotensive hypertensive rats, on the contrary, the aqueous extract of AP extenuated the BP of hypertensive rats much faster as that of enalapril (Ghisalberti et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">1998</xref>; Esmaeili et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">2009</xref>; Ahmed et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2017</xref>). Another variety of the genus artemisia that is 
 <italic>A. pallens</italic> has successfully been reported in Ayurveda for the treatment of high blood pressure (Pavithra et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR264">2018</xref>). Moxibustion is a conventional and East Asian medical treatment that contains 
 <italic>A. vulgaris</italic> with acupuncture treatments (Kim et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR176">2010</xref>; Zhou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR382">2018</xref>). One more distinct species of the genus artemisia that is 
 <italic>A. herba-alba</italic> recognized for its therapeutic medicinal characteristics, it was consumable in an easy way and available in both traditional as well as in contemporary medicine. 
 <italic>A. herba-alba was</italic> utilized as a folk remedy for the prevention of arterial hypertension (Mohamed et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR218">2010</xref>; Samaha et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR294">2019</xref>).
</p>
