<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">According to the results of antimicrobial activity testing, GR-EO had a potent effect on both gram-negative and gram-positive bacteria. The mechanisms of the antimicrobial action of essential oils are still not completely understood. Some studies suggested that, the amphiphilic nature of terpenoids due to the presence of hydrophobic skeleton and hydrophilic functional groups enables easy transport of these phytochemicals across biological membranes of microbial cells, thereby allowing them to reach cytosol and interact with key intracellular biomolecules [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-22-01561" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-22-01561" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Generally, the antibacterial properties of essential oils are closely associated with their most abundant components therein [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-22-01561" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Although the previous studies revealed a significant antibacterial activity of β-caryophyllene [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-22-01561" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>], the antibacterial effect of the oil was higher than that of single constituent of β-caryophyllene. Some studies have demonstrated that different terpenoid components of essential oils can interact to either reduce or increase antimicrobial efficacy [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-22-01561" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. However, in many cases the whole oils usually have higher antibacterial capacity than the mixtures of their major components, suggesting that the minor components are critical to the synergistic activity [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-22-01561" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-22-01561" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-22-01561" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. Therefore it was speculated that a synergistic effect between the major and minor components of GR-EO contributed to the antibacterial activity.
</p>
