<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Drug development is a tedious and highly time-consuming process usually takes years to get the newly developed drug for the treatment (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Thus, one of the most preferred method is to find a suitable drug through drug repurposing, as it saves both time and financial resources (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The most common source of drug repurposing is existing drugs or molecules of natural origin, and the scientists across the globe feel that the use of compounds from natural sources is one of the best and sought about way to move forward (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), even to find a drug for COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Computational approaches in identifying potential hits have gained momentum due to their cost effective and time saving efficiencies in drug discovery process (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Moreover, these approaches have been well-utilized for mining potential chemical moieties from diverse phytochemical libraries (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In recent times, studies on traditional medicine have climbed to newer heights across the globe due to its immense potential, easy availability, time-tested safety profile, and wide range of pharmacological actions. The increase in studies is also due to the implementation of technologies to understand the structure and function of phytocompounds from nature (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). With the continuous advancement in the field of computer science, many drugs have been approved from natural sources through computer-aided drug design, like Ponatinib (FDA approval: 2012), Dasatinib (FDA approval: 2006), and Imatinib (FDA approval: 2001). Applications of 
 <italic>in silico</italic> approach helps to calculate and analyze the combinations of compounds and targets as highly accurate, hence gaining more and more importance in the field of drug discovery by saving time and money (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Several studies revealed that ethnomedicinal “phytophores” belonging to different classes, based on their structure activity relationship (SAR), showed effectiveness in curtailing viral replication in diverse viral infections. The antiviral compounds usually interfere in host-virus interaction points like viral entry process from adhesion/attachment to fusion and penetration, inhibit enzymatic activity, and or block one or more steps of the viral life cycle including replication to release. The scientific evidence and the traditional usage of antiviral plant extracts clearly portray the potential of natural compounds in modulating viral infection (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).
</p>
