<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viral infections are increasing across the globe mainly due to increased anthropogenic activities like land-use change, increased human-animal interaction and lack of proper healthcare infrastructure. Hence, the discovery of antivirals from natural sources, mainly traditionally used medicinal plants have gained importance. Since ages, plants have been used as a source of therapeutics in diverse ethnomedicinal practices. Many ethnomedicinal plant extracts and phytocompounds are known to modulate host immune responses (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) and may exert antimicrobial and antiviral effects (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). A variety of plant compounds including alkaloids, coumarins, essential oils, flavonoids, polyphenols, phytosterols, proteins, peptides, saponins, and tannins play diverse roles in the human system. Consistent progress has been made in the development of nature-based antiviral drugs in recent years, as natural products like plant extracts and phytocompounds used in TM are novel and broad-based chemical entity that may serve as a potential sources of antiviral drugs (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). The ever-increasing drug resistance, frequent microbial mutations with increased emerging and re-emerging outbreaks of viruses necessitate the development of easily available cost-effective antimicrobials and antivirals for better treatments. Hence, traditional medicines are the hope and source for novel agents to manage viral diseases (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). A whole range of viral diseases caused by the Dengue, Human herpes viruses, HIV, Rabies, and Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) needs potential therapeutics; while using modern tools the vast knowledge of ethnomedicinal practices can be identified and validated for antiviral applications (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Thus, a surge of research is been observed in research institutes and universities, particularly the countries rich in TM.
</p>
