<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent times, several phytocompounds having antiviral potential have been identified with their molecular mechanism of action. Spiroketalenol, isolated from the rhizome extract of 
 <italic>Tanacetum vulgare</italic> L., was found to inhibit HSV-1 and HSV-2 by blocking the virus entry, and inhibit the activity of viral glycoproteins (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Another compound Samarangenin B from the roots of 
 <italic>Limonium sinense</italic> found to suppress the replication of HSV-1 by inhibiting the expression of HSV-1 immediate early (IE) or α- gene (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Harmaline (HM), a dihydro-pyrido-indole, from the ethnomedicinal herb 
 <italic>Ophiorrhiza nicobarica</italic> is reported to exhibit anti-HSV activity by suppressing the viral IE gene synthesis through epigenetic blocking of LSD-1 with a different mode of action than the gold standard antiviral Acyclovir (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Further, it was reported that the ursolic acid isolated from 
 <italic>Mallotus peltatus</italic> (Geist) Muell. Arg. dose-dependently inhibits the plaque formation of both HSV-1 and HSV-2 at 10 μg/ml within 2–5 h post-infection (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Moreover, 
 <italic>Odina wodier</italic> Roxb, a herb used in folklore medicine confer therapeutic effects on the skin infections caused by HSV (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). 
 <italic>Pterocarya stenoptera</italic> traditionally used in the treatment of viral diseases is another potential plant with antiviral activity and its isolated compound Pterocarnin A was shown to inhibit HSV-2, by blocking the penetration of the virion into the host cells (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Complementarily, many bio-active compounds from plants were shown to have immunomodulatory activities by triggering anti-inflammatory responses, which in turn helps in the control of viral infection (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Earlier studies have revealed that modulation of NF-κB signaling mediated anti-inflammatory response triggered by 
 <italic>Pedilanthus tithymaloides</italic> L. confer a higher level of anti-HSV activity (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Further, ultrasound-induced Gallic acid based gold nanoparticles can inhibit HSV infection with EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 32.3 and 38.6 μM against HSV-1 and HSV-2, respectively (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). While oleo-gum resin-extract and β-Boswellic acid of 
 <italic>Boswellia serrata</italic> inhibit HSV-1 infection through modulation of NF-kβ and p38 MAP kinase signaling (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>).
</p>
