<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We produced two experimental diets: one for a growth test (
 <xref rid="animals-09-00100-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>) and the other for a challenge test (
 <xref rid="animals-09-00100-t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). For the growth test, five experimental diets were formulated. A control diet (65% FM) contained the following protein sources: 65% FM and 8% corn gluten meal. Three experimental diets contained graded levels of DMW-1 to replace 38%, 60%, or 100% of FM in the control diet, corresponding to dietary DMW-1 inclusion levels of 250 (25% MW), 400 (40% MW), and 650 g/kg (65% MW), respectively. Additionally, to assess the effect of the oil fraction from MW (MO), a diet containing 1.84% DHA to be equivalent in n-3 highly unsaturated fatty acid (HUFA) content to the 65% MW diet and 5.16% MO to replace the fish oil in the 65% MW diet was formulated (65% MW + MO). For the challenge test, three experimental diets were formulated. A control diet (50% FM) contained the following protein sources: 65% FM, 16% soybean meal, and 8% corn gluten meal. Two experimental diets contained graded levels of DMW-2 to replace 10% or 20% of the proteins from FM in the control diet, corresponding to dietary DMW-2 inclusion levels of 5% (5% MW) and 10% (10% MW), respectively. The crude protein level in these diets was targeted to be approximately 50% to obtain satisfactory growth of red seabream [
 <xref rid="B18-animals-09-00100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] in the growth test. Supplementation with plant-derived protein sources (soybean meal and corn gluten meal) was used to achieve this protein level. To prepare the diets for use in the feeding trials, powdered forms of all the components were thoroughly mixed and supplemented with fish oil, MW oil, or DHA. These mixtures were then granulated after adding water and air-dried at 60 °C for more than 1 day. The resulting diets were stored at 4 °C until use.
</p>
