<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">Pakistan has diverse genetic resources and a rich floristic wealth of medicinal plants due to favorable climatic conditions. Secondary metabolites are profiled using different techniques, which are then linked with biological activities, before further isolation of the active ingredients in an effort to cure diseases. 
 <italic>Monotheca buxifolia</italic> belongs to the family Sapotaceae that comprises 800 species and 65 genera. Gurguri is the local name of its fresh fruit that is sold in markets due to its ethnobotanical significance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. 
 <italic>M. buxifolia</italic> is found in barren hilly areas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. In Pakistan, it is widely present in Balochistan (i.e., Zhob, Gorakh Hills, and Loralai) and Khyber Pakhtunkhwa (Kohat, Drosh, Chitral, and Attock Districts). Its distribution is also observed in tribal areas along the border of Afghanistan, i.e., Mohmand Agency and Darraadamkhel [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The plant is used as folk medicine in South Asia (Pakistan, India, and Afghanistan) and the Middle East, Iran, and Iraq. According to folk knowledge, 
 <italic>M. buxifolia</italic> has digestive and laxative properties, and the leaves are used to treat liver, kidney, and urinary diseases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The fruit extract has hepatoprotective, urease-inhibitory, and antibacterial activities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], and it is also known for its pain-, inflammation-, and pyrexia-ameliorating properties, mainly due to its oleanolic-acid and isoquercetin contents [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. A previous study showed that the 
 <italic>M. buxifolia</italic> fruit has a high amount of phenolics and flavonoids, and it depicts free-radical-scavenging activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The leaves of 
 <italic>M. buxifolia</italic> are chemically enriched with flavonoids, terpenoids, saponins, anthraquinones, cardiac glycosides, tannins, and reducing sugars depicting high antioxidant activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. The fruit also possesses significant antibacterial and cytotoxic properties, and it is enriched with lupeol and α-amyrin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].
</p>
