<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Proline accumulation in plants can regulate the osmotic potential of cells, stabilize the cell structure, and remove excess reactive oxygen species, thereby improving the resistance of rye to environmental stress [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The current study revealed that proline content in rye shoots increased with an increase in the oil concentration in the soil. Furthermore, these changes were more pronounced in the Krona variety. Despite the fact that the current experiment did not reveal any significant changes in water content in rye shoots grown on the oil-polluted soil, the increase in proline content in plants can be related to its functioning as an indicator of water stress. Data on changes in proline content in plants at different oil concentrations in the soil are rather controversial and are determined by both the pollutant type and plant species. For example, it was previously shown that soil contamination with heavy metals, as a rule, leads to an increase in proline content in plants [
 <xref rid="B49-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Additionally, a number of studies revealed a decrease in proline level in leaves of 
 <italic>Plantago lanceolata</italic> [
 <xref rid="B51-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and 
 <italic>Brassica juncea</italic> [
 <xref rid="B52-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] exposed to heavy metal soil contamination. Rusin et al. [
 <xref rid="B17-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] found that soil contamination with petroleum-derived substances led to a decrease in proline content in leaves of broad bean plants. At the same time, the authors previously showed that soil contamination with diesel and gasoline led to an increase in proline content in wheat plants [
 <xref rid="B5-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].
</p>
