<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> was seeded into separate tubes (10
 <sup class="sup">4</sup> cells per tube) in Sabouraud culture medium supplemented with Mentha × piperita EO (Extral-Bio
 <sup class="sup">®</sup>, Blida, Algeria) at various concentrations (0, 1, 3, 5, and 10 μL/mL). The Mentha × piperita EO we used was solvent free. In the first set of experiments, the EO was added directly to the 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> cell suspension. In the second set of experiments, because this EO could potentially release volatile chemicals with antimicrobial properties, we investigated the effect of EO vapor on 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> growth. To do so, 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> (10
 <sup class="sup">4</sup>) was incubated in the presence of 0, 1, 3, 5, and 10 μL/mL of Mentha × piperita 
 <italic class="italic">EO</italic> placed at a distance of 4 cm from the surface of the culture medium. In this second experimental set-up, only the volatile chemicals (vapor) released from the EO were in contact with the 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic>. Cultures from both the contact and vapor conditions were maintained for 24 h, after which 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> growth was assessed by means of the (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl tetrazolium bromide) (MTT) assay. Absorbance (optical density, OD) was measured at 550 nm using an xMark microplate spectrophotometer (Bio-Rad, Mississauga, ON, Canada). A culture containing cells unexposed to the EO was included as the negative control, while cells exposed to Amphotericin B (5 μg/mL) was included as the positive control. Amphotericin B is an antifungal prescription medicine approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration for the treatment of several types of fungal infections, including candidiasis [
 <xref rid="B35-antibiotics-08-00010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. The results were reported as the means ± SD of four separate experiments.
</p>
