<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_HLY4460 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEgr6 jpg ?><?FILEgr7 jpg ?><?FILEgr8 jpg ?><?FILEgr9 jpg ?><?FILEgr10 jpg ?><?FILEgr11 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 docx ?><?FILEsi1 svg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7393437</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2405-8440(20)31304-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e04460</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e04460</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> activities of crude extracts and triterpenoid constituents of <italic>Dichapetalum crassifolium</italic> Chodat against clinical isolates of <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Chama</surname><given-names>Mary Anti</given-names></name><email>antichama@yahoo.com</email><email>machama@ug.edu.gh</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Onyame</surname><given-names>Henry Akwaffo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Fleischer</surname><given-names>Claudine</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Osei-Safo</surname><given-names>Dorcas</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Waibel</surname><given-names>Reiner</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Otchere</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Addae-Mensah</surname><given-names>Ivan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Chemistry, School of Physical and Mathematical Sciences, P.O Box LG 56, University of Ghana, Legon, Ghana</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Chemistry and Pharmacy, Friederich Alexander University of Erlangen-Nurnberg, Schuhstrasse 19, 91052 Erlangen, Germany</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Parasitology Department, Noguchi Memorial Institute for Medical Research, College of Health Sciences, University of Ghana, Legon, Ghana</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>antichama@yahoo.com</email><email>machama@ug.edu.gh</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e04460</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p><italic>Dichapetalum crassifolium</italic> Chodat (Dichapetalaceae) is widely distributed in Africa, Tropical Asia and Latin America. As part of our quest for potential bioactive lead compounds for various neglected tropical diseases, we report the anti-schistosomal potential of the crude extracts and chemical constituents of the stems and roots of <italic>Dichapetalum crassifolium.</italic> Column chromatography of extracts of the stems and roots led to the isolation and identification of three oleanane-type triterpenoids, friedelan-3&#x003b2;-ol (1), friedelan-3-one (2), and maslinic acid (3); the ursane-type tritepenoid, pomolic acid (4) and the dammarane-type tetracyclic triterpenoids, dichapetalin A (5) and dichapetalin M (6). Dichapetalin A was isolated from only the roots. Isolated compounds were identified by comparison of their physico-chemical and spectral data with published data. The highest <italic>in vitro</italic> anti-schistosomal activity (IC<sub>50</sub>) of the crude extracts against clinical isolates of <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic> (Bilharz 1852) was 248.6 &#x003bc;g/ml for the ethyl acetate extract of the root while dichapetalin A gave the highest activity at 151.1 &#x003bc;g/ml among the compounds compared with the 15.5 &#x003bc;g/ml for the standard drug, praziquantel. The rest of the compounds showed activities in the order 177.9, 191.0, and 378.1 &#x003bc;g/ml respectively for mixture of &#x003b2;-sitosterol/stigmasterol, dichapetalin M and friedelan-3-one. The least active extract was the methanol extract of the stem (893.7 &#x003bc;g/ml). The constituents of <italic>D</italic>. <italic>crassifolium</italic> showed activity against the <italic>S</italic>. <italic>haematobium</italic> that are below praziquantel. It is envisaged that the presence of multiple layers and the minute sizes of pores in the egg shells, may preclude penetration of eggs by the compounds.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0015"><p>Natural product chemistry; Organic chemistry; Pharmaceutical chemistry; <italic>Dichapetalum crassifolium</italic>; <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic>; Dichapetalin a; Dichapetalin M; Maslinic acid; Pomolic acid</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Natural product chemistry</kwd><kwd>Organic chemistry</kwd><kwd>Pharmaceutical chemistry</kwd><kwd><italic>Dichapetalum crassifolium</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic></kwd><kwd>Dichapetalin A</kwd><kwd>Dichapetalin M</kwd><kwd>Maslinic acid</kwd><kwd>Pomolic acid</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Naturally-occurring pentacyclic triterpenoids of the lupane, oleanane and ursane classes are known to possess a variety of biological activities. Quite a number of these triterpenoids have been isolated and identified from some plant species of the Dichapetalaceae family. One of the hitherto uninvestigated species is <italic>Dichapetalum crassifolium</italic> Chodat widely distributed in Africa, Tropical Asia and Latin America (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Breteler, 1978</xref>). It is typically found in the rain or gallery forests, primitive woods, shady places, and among rocks (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Breteler, 1978</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hiern et&#x000a0;al., 1901</xref>). Even though there is no documented ethnobotanical use and phytochemical investigation for <italic>D.&#x000a0;crassifolium,</italic> other species of the genus have indicated the presence of a wide range of secondary metabolites with diverse biological activities. These include the fluorinated carboxylic acids reputed to be responsible for the toxicity of some members of the genus (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Meyer and O'Hagan, 1992</xref>) as well as various types of triterpenoids including the dichapetalins reputed to have cytotoxic and antiproliferative activities (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Fang et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Long et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>). Other non-terpenoidal compounds recently reported from the genus are the bisbenzyl derivatives heudelotol A and B from <italic>D.&#x000a0;heudelotii</italic> (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Additional compound types obtained from the genus are the alkaloid trigonelline, the amino acids N-methylserine and N-methylalanine (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Breteler, 1978</xref>; <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Eloff, 1980</xref>), sugars, various glycosides, esters of (E)-ferulic acid (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Addae-Mensah et&#x000a0;al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Adu-Kumi, 1997</xref>) and pyracrenic acid (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Long et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>).</p><p id="p0015">Apart from the cytotoxic and antiproliferative activities exhibited by the dichapetalins (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Achenbach et&#x000a0;al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Addae-mensah et&#x000a0;al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Jing et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>), this unique class of triterpenoids has also shown anthelmintic (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chama et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Jing et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>), antifungal, feeding deterrent, inhibition of intracellular release of nitric oxide (NO) and acetylcholinesterase (AChE) activities (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Jing et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). As part of our quest for potentially active constituents against parasitic and other causative agents of various neglected tropical diseases, we report the anti-schistosomal activity of the crude extracts and constituents of the stems and roots of the hitherto uninvestigated <italic>D</italic>. <italic>crassifolium</italic> against clinical isolates of <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic> Bilharz 1852, (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Tan and Ahana, 2007</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Materials</title><p id="p0020">The roots and stems of <italic>D.&#x000a0;crassifolium</italic> were obtained from the Bobiri Forest Reserve in the Bosomtwe district of the Ashanti Region in July 2013. Identification was done by John Ntim-Gyakare formerly of the Forestry Commission, Kumasi. Voucher specimen (DCR001) has been deposited in the Ghana Herbarium, Department of Plant and Environmental Biology, University of Ghana.</p><p id="p0025">TLC was performed on aluminium foil slides pre-coated with silica gel (thickness 0.2 mm, type Kieselgel 60 F<sub>254</sub>, Merck, Rogers, AR); detection: I<sub>2</sub> vapour, vanilin stain and anisaldehyde spray reagent. Column chromatography was carried out on silica gel 60 (Fluka Analytical, Bellefonte, PA). Melting points (uncorrected) determined on a Stuart Scientific Melting Point Apparatus (Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO). IR spectra were obtained on an FT IR spectrometer at the Food and Drugs Authority in Ghana. Visualisation of spots under UV light was done with UVGL-58 Handheld UV lamp at 254&#x02013;365 nm. Organic solvents were concentrated using Buchi Rotary Vacuum Evaporator.</p><p id="p0030">NMR were run on a 500 or 600 MHz Br&#x000fc;ker Avance instrument at 90, 125 or 150 MHz for <sup>13</sup>C NMR and 360, 500 or 600 MHz for <sup>1</sup>H NMR. Depending on the solubility of a particular compound, solvents used were CDCl<sub>3</sub>/CD<sub>3</sub>OD, DMSO-d6, acetone-d6 or CD<sub>3</sub>OD with TMS as the internal standard. Schistosomal activity testing was carried out at the parasitology laboratory of the Noguchi Memorial Institute for Medical Research, University of Ghana. Ethical clearance for the anti-schistosomal work was obtained from the Noguchi Memorial Institute for Medical Research (NMIMR-IRB CPN 059/13&#x02013;14). Schistosome egg recovery and concentration from infested urine samples was by the modified Kotze et&#x000a0;al. method (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kotze et&#x000a0;al., 2005</xref>). Urine reagent strips were obtained from URIT Medical Electronic Co, Ltd, China. Different pore sizes of sieves for filtration of suspensions were obtained from Nonaka Rikaki Co. Ltd, Japan.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec2.2.1"><label>2.2.1</label><title>Sample collection of clinical isolates</title><p id="p0035"><italic>S.&#x000a0;haematobium</italic> eggs were obtained from urine samples collected from 120 school children in Tomefa in the Ga South District of Accra and stored in air-tight plastic containers. More than 80% of participants were between ages 8 and 14 years. Samples were first tested with urine reagent strips, URIT 10V to identify cases of haematuria and then kept in a Styrofoam box and transported to the parasitology laboratory at the Noguchi Memorial Institute for Medical Research.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2.2"><label>2.2.2</label><title>Recovery, purification and identification of <italic>S.&#x000a0;haematobium</italic> eggs from urine samples</title><p id="p0040">Portions (10 ml) of collected urine samples were centrifuged and observed using a low power microscope to determine the presence of <italic>S.&#x000a0;haematobium</italic>, whose eggs were identified by the presence of terminal spines (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref>). Urine samples that were positive for schistosome eggs were pooled into 50 ml falcon tubes and centrifuged at 500x<italic>g</italic> for 5 min. The supernatant was discarded and the deposits suspended in 50 ml of normal saline (0.9%, NaCl) and centrifugation repeated. The sediment was suspended in 40 ml of 0.015% Brij-35 and shaken vigorously. It was centrifuged again at 500x<italic>g</italic> for 5 min. The supernatant was discarded and the sediment re-suspended in normal saline into a 200 ml beaker. More saline was added to make up to the 150 ml mark. Due to the different particle sizes of faecal samples which do not usually produce clean egg cells of the parasite, sieves of different pore sizes were used.</p><p id="p0045">For differential separation to obtain cleaner schistosome eggs, the suspension was filtered through a stack of three sieves of pore size 180 &#x003bc;m, 150 &#x003bc;m and 80 &#x003bc;m respectively.</p><p id="p0050">The stack of sieves was thoroughly flushed with a jet of normal saline to wash the eggs. To prevent air lock, the 150 &#x003bc;m and 80 &#x003bc;m sieves were occasionally separated. At the end of washing, the 80 &#x003bc;m sieves were removed and inclined at approximately 45&#x000b0; to the horizontal and a jet of saline applied to it to wash off the eggs into a beaker. The suspension was centrifuged at 200x<italic>g</italic> for 10 min and left for 30 min after which the supernatant was aspirated down to 5 ml. Three 30 &#x003bc;l suspensions of the concentrated schistosome eggs were pipetted and observed under light microscope, the number of eggs per 30 &#x003bc;l was noted and hence the average number of eggs per 30 &#x003bc;l determined. From this result, the approximate number of <italic>S.&#x000a0;haematobium</italic> eggs in the 5 ml concentrated egg solution was calculated.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Extraction, isolation and structure elucidation of compounds</title><p id="p0055">Soxhlet extraction of 5 kg each of pulverized roots and stems in batches of 500 g of <italic>D.&#x000a0;crassifolium</italic> was carried out exhaustively using 5 L of petroleum ether for 24 h to give 54 g root and 34 g of stem extracts after concentration, <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>. Each plant residue was further extracted with EtOAc and MeOH respectively after drying. Concentration of the root extracts gave 77 g (EtOAc extract) and 108 g (MeOH extract) crude material. The stem yielded 65 g (EtOAc extract) and 23 g (MeOH extract) of crude material, <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Flow diagram of the work done on petroleum ether, ethyl acetate and methanol extracts of the stem and root of <italic>D</italic>. <italic>crassifolium</italic>. PE: Petroleum ether.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Figure&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="p0060">Column chromatography of the petroleum ether extract of the stem (20 g) on 230 g silica gel, eluting with petroleum ether/EtOAc (10:1 to 0:10, v/v) gave three main fractions, S1&#x02013;S3, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>. Fraction S2 (12.6 g) was re-chromatographed on silica gel (80 g) with petroleum ether/CHCl<sub>3</sub> (1:3, v/v) to give three fractions (S4&#x02013;S6). Fraction S4 gave compounds 1 (180 mg), while fraction S6 yielded compound 2 (80 mg), both as white crystals, as well as a mixture of the two compounds. Similar separations of the petroleum ether extract of the roots also gave compounds 1 (215 mg), and 2 (82 mg) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>). The EtOAc extract (40 g) of the stem was also column chromatographed on silica gel (450 g) with petroleum ether/EtOAc solvent gradient (10:1 to 0:10, v/v) to give five main fractions S7&#x02013;S11. Fraction S7 yielded compounds 1 and 2 identified respectively as friedelan-3&#x003b2;-ol and friedelan-3-one (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;3</xref> and <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) while S8 gave a mixture of &#x003b2;-sitosterol/stigmasterol (7 and 8, 25 mg), Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. Fraction S9 precipitated solids recrystallized from a mixture of Et<sub>2</sub>O/CHCl<sub>3</sub> (10:3, v/v) to afford a white powdery compound 4 identified as pomolic acid (60 mg, <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>). Fraction S11 was re-chromatographed in similar manner to afford compounds 6 (dichapetalin M, 20 mg) as a white amorphous solid, recrystallized from a mixture of Et<sub>2</sub>O/CHCl<sub>3</sub> (2:5, v/v), and compound 3, maslinic acid (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>) as a creamy powder (32 mg) recrystallized from a mixture of Et<sub>2</sub>O/CHCl<sub>3</sub> (2:5, v/v), <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4</xref>. Similar separation procedures by column chromatography were also carried out on the crude EtOAc extract of the roots to yield compounds 3, 4, 5 and 6. Column chromatography of the EtOAc extract (38 g) on 450 g silica gel, eluting with petroleum ether/EtOAc solvent gradient (10:0 to 0:10, v/v) gave nine main fractions R1-R9. Fractions R1-R2 gave compound 3, while compound 4 was obtained from fraction R3 and compound 6 from fraction R4. Compound 5, 40 mg, was isolated from fraction R7 and recrystallized from Et<sub>2</sub>O/EtOAc (10:1, v/v) as yellowish flakes (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4</xref>). All compounds were characterised by comparison of their physico-chemical properties (melting point, TLC profile in various solvent systems), as well as their spectroscopic data (IR, <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR) with literature data as indicated below.<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Chromatographic separation of the petroleum ether extracts of the stem and root of <italic>D</italic>. <italic>crassifolium.</italic></p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Figure&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Structures of friedelan-3&#x003b2;-ol <bold>1,</bold> friedelan-3-one <bold>2</bold>, maslinic acid <bold>3</bold> and pomolic acid <bold>4</bold>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Figure&#x000a0;3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Chromatographic separation of the ethyl acetate extracts of the stem and root of <italic>D</italic>. <italic>crassifolium</italic>. PE: Petroleum ether.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Figure&#x000a0;4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Structures of &#x003b2;-sitosterol (7) and stigmasterol (8).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Figure&#x000a0;5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p><sec id="sec2.3.1"><label>2.3.1</label><title>Physico-chemical properties and spectral data of isolated compounds</title><p id="p0065">(3S,4R,4aS,6aS,6aS,6bR,8aR,12aR,14aS,14bS)-4,4a,6a,6b,8a,11,11,14a-octamethyl-1,2,3,4,5,6,6a,7,8,9,10,12,12a,13,14,14b-hexadecahydropicen-3-ol (F<italic>riedelan-3&#x003b2;-ol</italic>, <bold>1):</bold> 53 mg as white crystals; mp: 272&#x02013;274 &#x000b0;C (Lit. 274&#x02013;276 &#x000b0;C, (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Utami et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>); Anisaldehyde: purple; IR &#x003bd;<sub>max</sub> (KBr) cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; 3477 (O&#x02013;H), 2932, 2871 (C&#x02013;H), 1448, 1385 [C(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]; Co-TLC with authentic sample in 100% CHCl<sub>3</sub>, R<sub>f</sub> 0.81; petroleum ether/EtOAc (14:0.5), R<sub>f</sub> 0.61; and petroleum ether/Me<sub>2</sub>CO (12:0.5), R<sub>f</sub> 0.5.</p><p id="p0070">4,4<italic>a</italic>,6<italic>a</italic>,6<italic>b</italic>,8<italic>a</italic>,11,11,14<italic>a</italic>-octamethyl-2,4,5,6,6<italic>a</italic>,7,8,9,10,12,12<italic>a</italic>,13,14,14<italic>b</italic>-tetradecahydro-1<italic>H</italic>-picen-3-one (<italic>Friedelan-3-one,</italic>
<bold>2</bold>): 215 mg as white crystals; mp: 249&#x02013;251 &#x000b0;C (Lit. 249&#x02013;251 &#x000b0;C, (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Utami et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>); Anisaldehyde: yellow; IR &#x003bd;<sub>max</sub> (KBr) cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; 2927, 2870 (C&#x02013;H), 1716 (C=O), 1462, 1389 [C(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]; Co-TLC with authentic sample in 100% CHCl<sub>3</sub>, R<sub>f</sub> 0.94; petroleum ether/EtOAc (14:0.5), R<sub>f</sub> 0.87; and petroleum ether/Me<sub>2</sub>CO (12:0.5), R<sub>f</sub> 0.82.</p><p id="p0075">(2&#x003b1;,3&#x003b2;)-2,3-Dihydroxyolean-12-en-28-oic acid (<italic>Maslinic acid,</italic>
<bold>3</bold>), 50 mg as creamy powder: mp: 249&#x02013;251 &#x000b0;C (Lit. 248&#x02013;250 &#x000b0;C, (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Hossain and Ismail, 2013</xref>); Anisaldehyde: purple; IR &#x003bd;<sub>max</sub> (KBr) cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; 3443 (O&#x02013;H), 2941 (C&#x02013;H), 1692 (C=O), 1461, 1385 (C&#x02013;H), 1270 (C&#x02013;O&#x02013;H) and 1051.37 (C&#x02013;O). <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR: see <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref> (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Woo et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>) and Supplementary material Figures&#x000a0;S1 and S2. TLC: petroleum ether/Et<sub>2</sub>O (3:7), R<sub>f</sub> 0.68; petroleum ether/EtOAc (10:3), R<sub>f</sub> 0.53; petroleum ether/Me<sub>2</sub>CO (10:3), R<sub>f</sub> 0.40; petroleum ether/EtOAc (10:6), R<sub>f</sub> 0.88.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p><sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR data of maslinic acid and pomolic acid isolated from <italic>D.&#x000a0;crassifolium</italic>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0070">Table&#x000a0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Position</th><th colspan="2">Maslinic acid <bold>(3)</bold> (CD<sub>3</sub>OD/CDCl<sub>3</sub>)<hr/></th><th colspan="2">Pomolic <bold>(4)</bold> acid (Acetone-D6)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>delta;<sub>C</sub>/ppm</th><th>&#x003b4;<sub>H</sub> (J, Hz) (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Woo et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>)</th><th>&#x003b4;<sub>C</sub>/ppm</th><th>&#x003b4;<sub>H</sub> (J, Hz) (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Lee et&#x000a0;al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>47.7</td><td>-</td><td>39.5</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>68.8</td><td>3.66(1H, ddd, J<sub>1</sub> = 10.3,<break/>J<sub>2</sub> = 8.5, J<sub>3</sub> = 6.5 Hz)</td><td>27.5</td><td>2.63(2H, ddd, J<sub>1</sub> = 8.8,<break/>J<sub>2</sub> = 9.6, J<sub>3</sub> = 6.6 Hz)</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>83.7</td><td>3.45(1H, d, 10.3 Hz)</td><td>78.3</td><td>3.15(1H, dd, J<sub>1</sub> = 4.5,<break/>J<sub>2</sub> = 10 Hz)</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>39.3</td><td>-</td><td>39.5</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>55.4</td><td>-</td><td>53.0</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>18.5</td><td>-</td><td>18.0</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>32.7</td><td>-</td><td>32.4</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>39.4</td><td>-</td><td>38.3</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>49.0</td><td>1.90(1H, dd, J<sub>1</sub> = 4.2,<break/>J<sub>2</sub> = 7.8 Hz)</td><td>48.2</td><td>2.55(1H, s)</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>38.3</td><td>-</td><td>37.2</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>23.6</td><td>1.61(2H, dd, J<sub>1</sub> = 11.3,<break/>J<sub>2</sub> = 11.3 Hz)</td><td>23.8</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>122.2</td><td>5.27(1H, t, J = 3.5 Hz )</td><td>128.5</td><td>5.28(1H, t)</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>144.1</td><td>-</td><td>137.8</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>42.0</td><td>-</td><td>40.9</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>27.8</td><td>-</td><td>29.2</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>23.1</td><td>1.95(2H, ddd, J<sub>1</sub> = 11.6,<break/>J<sub>2</sub> = 9.6, J<sub>3</sub> = 9.6 Hz)</td><td>26.3</td><td>1.95(2H, d, J = 5 Hz)</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>46.5</td><td>-</td><td>47.8</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>41.3</td><td>2.83(1H, dd, J<sub>1</sub> = 7.8,<break/>J<sub>2</sub> = 8.3 Hz)</td><td>54.8</td><td>2.80(1H, s)</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>46.3</td><td>-</td><td>72.5</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td>30.8</td><td>-</td><td>40.8</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>21</td><td>34.0</td><td>-</td><td>26.4</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>22</td><td>33.2</td><td>-</td><td>38.1</td><td>1.94(2H, d, J = 4.6 Hz)</td></tr><tr><td>23</td><td>28.7</td><td>1.02(3H, s)</td><td>27.8</td><td>2.55(3H, s)</td></tr><tr><td>24</td><td>16.6</td><td>0.78(3H, s)</td><td>16.0</td><td>2.25(3H, s)</td></tr><tr><td>25</td><td>16.8</td><td>0.98(3H, s)</td><td>15.1</td><td>1.35(3H, s)</td></tr><tr><td>26</td><td>17.0</td><td>0.81(3H, s)</td><td>18.1</td><td>1.21(3H, s)</td></tr><tr><td>27</td><td>25.7</td><td>1.06(3H, s)</td><td>25.1</td><td>0.99(3H, s)</td></tr><tr><td>28</td><td>180.8</td><td>-</td><td>180.5</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>29</td><td>32.7</td><td>0.90 (3H, s)</td><td>25.6</td><td>0.95 (3H, d, J = 6.5 Hz)</td></tr><tr><td>30</td><td>23.6</td><td>0.93 (3H, s)</td><td>15.5</td><td>0.79 (3H, d, J = 6.5 Hz)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0080">(1<italic>R</italic>,2<italic>R</italic>,4<italic>aS</italic>,6<italic>aR</italic>,6<italic>aS</italic>,6bR,8<italic>aR</italic>,10<italic>S</italic>,12<italic>aR</italic>,14<italic>bS</italic>)-1,10-dihydroxy-1,2,6<italic>a</italic>,6<italic>b</italic>,9,9,12<italic>a</italic>-heptamethyl-2,3,4,5,6,6<italic>a</italic>,7,8,8<italic>a</italic>,10,11,12,13,14<italic>b</italic>-tetradecahydropicene-4<italic>a</italic>-carboxylic acid (<italic>Pomolic acid</italic>, <bold>4</bold>): 71 mg as white powder: mp: 268&#x02013;270 &#x000b0;C (Lit. 276&#x02013;278 &#x000b0;C); Vanillin stain: purple; anisaldehyde: violet; IR &#x003bd;<sub>max</sub> (KBr) cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; 3567, 3419 (O&#x02013;H), 2937, 2874 (C&#x02013;H), 1686, 1618 (C=O); <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR: See <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref> (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chama et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Lee et&#x000a0;al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>) and Supplementary material Figures&#x000a0;S3 and S4; TLC: petroleum ether/Et<sub>2</sub>O (3:7), R<sub>f</sub> 0.81; petroleum ether/EtOAc (10:3), R<sub>f</sub> 0.45; petroleum ether/Me<sub>2</sub>CO (10:3), R<sub>f</sub> 0.29; petroleum ether/EtOAc (10:6), R<sub>f</sub> 0.77; petroleum ether/EtOAc (1:1), R<sub>f</sub> 0.71.</p><p id="p0085">(3<italic>S</italic>,5<italic>R</italic>)-5-[(<italic>E</italic>)-3-hydroxy-2-methylprop-1-enyl]-3-[(1<italic>S</italic>,2<italic>R</italic>,3<italic>R</italic>,5<italic>R</italic>,6<italic>R</italic>,9<italic>S</italic>,14<italic>S</italic>,15<italic>R</italic>,18<italic>S</italic>,19<italic>S</italic>)-3-hydroxy-2,6,14-trimethyl-9-phenyl-8-oxahexacyclo[16.3.1.0<sup>1,18</sup>.0<sup>2,15</sup>.0<sup>5,14</sup>.0<sup>6,11</sup>]docosa-11,16-dien-19-yl]oxolan-2-one (<italic>Dichapetalin A</italic>, <bold>5</bold>): 40 mg as yellow flakes; mp: 210&#x02013;213 &#x000b0;C (from Et<sub>2</sub>O/EtOAc (10:1, v/v)) (Lit.: 212&#x02013;213 &#x000b0;C, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>); Vanilin stain: blue; Anisaldehyde: purple; IR &#x003bd;<sub>max</sub> (KBr) cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>: 3573, 3552, 3369 (O&#x02013;H); 2957, 2932, 2873 (C&#x02013;H); 1746 (C=O), 1655 (C=C), 1096, 1039 (C&#x02013;O&#x02013;O), 767 (aromatic C&#x02013;H); <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR: see <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref> (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chama et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>) and Supplementary material Figures&#x000a0;S5 and S6; Co-TLC with authentic sample in petroleum ether/Me<sub>2</sub>CO (10:3), R<sub>f</sub> 0.40; petroleum ether/EtOAc (10:4), R<sub>f</sub> 0.65; petroleum ether/EtOAc (10:6), R<sub>f</sub> 0.20.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p><sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR data of dichapetalins A and M isolated from <italic>D.&#x000a0;crassifolium</italic>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0075">Table&#x000a0;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Position</th><th colspan="2">Dichapetalin A (5)<hr/></th><th colspan="2">Dichapetalin M (6)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>&#x003b4;<sub>C</sub> (ppm)</th><th>&#x003b4;<sub>H</sub> (<italic>Mult</italic>)</th><th>&#x003b4;<sub>C</sub> (ppm)</th><th>&#x003b4;<sub>H</sub> (<italic>Muit</italic>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1(CH<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>41.3</td><td>2.15, s</td><td>39.9</td><td>2.90,1.65</td></tr><tr><td>2(CH)</td><td>119.3</td><td>5.45, m</td><td>116.6</td><td>5.40</td></tr><tr><td>3(C)</td><td>141.2</td><td>-</td><td>141.3</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>4(C)</td><td>39.5</td><td>-</td><td>39.8</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>5(CH)</td><td>43.5</td><td>2.00<xref rid="tbl2n1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>59.1</td><td>1.60</td></tr><tr><td>6(CH<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>24.2</td><td>1.87,m</td><td>71.3</td><td>4.60,dd,3.80</td></tr><tr><td>7(CH)</td><td>73.2</td><td>3.92 (t, J = 1.5)</td><td>213.7</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>8(C)</td><td>37.4</td><td>-</td><td>47.0</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>9(CH)</td><td>45.1</td><td>1.75 (d, J = 2.5)</td><td>52.1</td><td>2.00</td></tr><tr><td>10(C)</td><td>37.2</td><td>-</td><td>36.9</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>11(CH)</td><td>124.1</td><td>5.43 (dd, J = 10, 2.5Hz)</td><td>120.1</td><td>5.40,dd</td></tr><tr><td>12(CH)</td><td>131.1</td><td>6.25 (dd, J = 10, 3Hz)</td><td>131.6</td><td>6.35,dd</td></tr><tr><td>13(C)</td><td>30.6</td><td>-</td><td>31.6</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>14(C)</td><td>37.5</td><td>-</td><td>36.5</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>15(CH<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>26.2</td><td>2.04<xref rid="tbl2n1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>26.7</td><td>2.00,2.20</td></tr><tr><td>16(CH<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>23.9</td><td>1.13, s</td><td>23.6</td><td>1.30,1.80,m</td></tr><tr><td>17(CH)</td><td>41.8</td><td>2.62, m</td><td>40.5</td><td>2.55</td></tr><tr><td>18(CH<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>18.4</td><td>0.94,s</td><td>17.1</td><td>1.10</td></tr><tr><td>19(CH<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>18.6</td><td>-</td><td>18.2</td><td>1.30,s</td></tr><tr><td>20(CH)</td><td>42.6</td><td>3.30,m</td><td>47.3</td><td>3.00,dd,2.45</td></tr><tr><td>21(C)</td><td>181.3</td><td>-</td><td>174.0</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>22(CH<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>31.4</td><td>2.37,m</td><td>72.1</td><td>4.20,dd</td></tr><tr><td>23(CH)</td><td>77.1</td><td>5.26, m</td><td>111.3</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>24(CH<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>123.1</td><td>5.50, s</td><td>45.7</td><td>2.90,2.50,d</td></tr><tr><td>25(C)</td><td>143.2</td><td>-</td><td>85.1</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>26(CH<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>67.3</td><td>3.98,s</td><td>78.5</td><td>4.35,d,4.10,d</td></tr><tr><td>27(CH<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>14.1</td><td>1.75, s</td><td>22.0</td><td>1.70,s</td></tr><tr><td>28(CH<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>24.7</td><td>1.32, s</td><td>26.5</td><td>1.55,s</td></tr><tr><td>30(CH<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>16.9</td><td>0.85 (d, J = 5Hz)</td><td>14.4</td><td>1.30,d,1.05</td></tr><tr><td>2&#x02032; (CH<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>73.6</td><td>3.56 (d, J = 10.5Hz)</td><td>71.3</td><td>4.35,3.95,d</td></tr><tr><td>5&#x02032; (CH<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>42.6</td><td>2.20 (dd, J = 13.5, 4Hz)</td><td>40.1</td><td>2.70, t<sub>br</sub>,2.25</td></tr><tr><td>6&#x02032; (CH)</td><td>83.6</td><td>4.27 (dd, J = 11.5, 2.5Hz)</td><td>81.3</td><td>4.35,dd</td></tr><tr><td>1&#x02033;(C)</td><td>143.90</td><td>-</td><td>142.5</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>2&#x02033;/6&#x02033; (CH)</td><td>126.97</td><td>7.37, m</td><td>128.4</td><td>7.45,d</td></tr><tr><td>3&#x02033;/5&#x02033; (CH)</td><td>129.5</td><td>7.33, m</td><td>125.7</td><td>7.40,t</td></tr><tr><td>4&#x02033; (CH)</td><td>128.5</td><td>7.26, m</td><td>127.5</td><td>7.30,t</td></tr><tr><td>AcCO(C)</td><td/><td/><td>170.4</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>AcCH<sub>3</sub>(CH<sub>3</sub>)</td><td/><td/><td>21.8</td><td>2.00,s</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2n1"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara7PIpvdMSD3">Overlapping signals.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0090"><italic>(3R,8R,9R)-9-hydroxy-8-((3S,6aR,</italic>6bR<italic>,8aS,9S,11aS,</italic>11bR<italic>,13R,13aR,</italic>13bR<italic>)-13-hydroxy-6a,11b,13b-trimethyl-12-oxo-3-phenyl-1,3,4,6,6a,6b,9,10,11,11b,12,13,13a,13b-tetradecahydro-8a,11a-methanocyclopenta[5,6]naphtho[1,2-h]isochromen-</italic>9-yl<italic>)-3-methyl-7-oxo-1,6-dioxaspiro[4.4]nonan-</italic>3-yl <italic>acetate</italic> (<italic>Dichapetalin M</italic>, <bold>6</bold>), 201 mg as white amorphous solids; mp: 282&#x02013;284 &#x000b0;C (Lit.: 280&#x02013;282 &#x000b0;C, (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chama et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>); Vanilin stain/anisaldehyde: violet; IR &#x003bd;<sub>max</sub> (KBr) cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>: 3432, 1244 (O&#x02013;H); 2976, 2883, 1367 (C&#x02013;H); 1770, 1751, 1700 (C=O), 1618 (C=C), 1191 (C&#x02013;O&#x02013;O), 671 (aromatic C&#x02013;H) cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR: see <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref> (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chama et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>) and Supplementary material Figures&#x000a0;S7 and S8. Co-TLC with authentic sample in Et<sub>2</sub>O/CHCl<sub>3</sub> (2:5), R<sub>f</sub> 0.48; petroleum ether/EtOAc (10:3), R<sub>f</sub> 0.38; petroleum ether/EtOAc (10:6), R<sub>f</sub> 0.67 (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>).</p><p id="p0095">17-(5-Ethyl-6-methylheptan-2-yl)-10,13-dimethyl-2,3,4,7,8,9,11,12,14,15,16,17-dodecahydro-1H-cyclopenta[a]phenanthren-3-ol/(3<italic>S</italic>,8<italic>S</italic>,9<italic>S</italic>,10<italic>R</italic>,13<italic>R</italic>,14<italic>S</italic>,17<italic>R</italic>)-17-[(<italic>E</italic>,2<italic>R</italic>,5<italic>S</italic>)-5-ethyl-6-methylhept-3-en-2-yl]-10,13-dimethyl-2,3,4,7,8,9,11,12,14,15,16,17-dodecahydro-1<italic>H</italic>-cyclopenta[a]phenanthren-3-ol (<italic>&#x003b2;-Sitosterol/stigmasterol</italic>, <bold>7</bold>, <bold>8</bold>); 25 mg as white crystals; mp: 138&#x02013;140 &#x000b0;C (Lit. 142&#x02013;145 &#x000b0;C, (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Chama, 2007</xref>); Anisaldehyde: orange; IR &#x003bd;<sub>max</sub> (KBr): 3434 (O&#x02013;H); 2936, 2882, 1463, 1382, 1062 (C&#x02013;H); 1639, 1618 (C=C) cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Chama, 2007</xref>); Co-TLC with authentic sample in 100% CHCl<sub>3</sub>, R<sub>f</sub> 0.50; petroleum ether/EtOAc (10:4), R<sub>f</sub> 0.82; petroleum ether/Me<sub>2</sub>CO (12:0.5), R<sub>f</sub> 0.21.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>In vitro screening of test samples against schistosome eggs using the 96-well plate-egg hatch assay</title><p id="p0100">For each of the test compounds; namely, friedelan-3-one (2), dichapetalins A (5) and M (6) and mixture of &#x003b2;-sitosterol/stigmasterol (6, 7), 2 mg was dissolved in 1 ml of 5% DMSO to give 2 mg/ml stock solution. For each of petroleum ether, EtOAc, and MeOH crude extracts of the roots and stems, 5 mg was dissolved in 1 ml of 5% DMSO to obtain a stock solution of 5 mg/ml.</p><p id="p0105">For each test sample of the stock solution, 100 &#x003bc;l was pipetted in duplicate into the first wells of 96-well plate. Serial dilutions of the 2 mg/ml solutions produced 1, 0.5, 0.25, 0.125, 0.0625 and 0.03125 mg/ml. Serial dilutions with concentrations 2.5, 1.25, 0.625, 0.3125, 0.15625 and 0.078125 mg/ml of the stock (5 mg/ml) solution of the crude extracts were also prepared. From the suspension of purified eggs, 50 &#x003bc;l was added to each well and the presence of eggs was ascertained under an inverted microscope. The final concentration of DMSO was kept below 0.1%. The choice of DMSO as a solvent and selection of suitable concentration that had no effect on the morphology of the eggs followed the method of <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Treger et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</xref>. Water and praziquantel (2 mg/ml stock solution) were used as negative and positive controls respectively. Praziquantel, because of its partial solubility in cold water, was dissolved in warm water. The assays were incubated for 24 h at ambient temperature and the process of egg hatch was stopped by the addition of 100 ml of formalin to each well. The number (#) of hatched eggs and unhatched eggs (larvae) was counted using inverted light microscopy.</p><p id="p0110">The percent egg hatch inhibition (% EHI) was calculated as:<disp-formula id="ufd1"><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>#</mml:mo><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>#</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mo>#</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="p0115">The %EHI was plotted against log of the concentration. Extrapolation of the 50% EHI on the curve gave the half maximal inhibitory concentration (IC<sub>50</sub>) of each test sample using GraphPad Prism v.7.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results and discussion</title><p id="p0120">Compound <bold>1</bold> was identified as friedelan-3&#x003b2;-ol (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>), mp 272&#x02013;274 &#x000b0;C (Lit. 274&#x02013;276 &#x000b0;C, <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Utami et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>) and stained purple with anisaldehyde spray reagent. Compound <bold>2</bold> was also identified as friedelan-3-one (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>), mp: 249&#x02013;251 &#x000b0;C, (Lit. 249&#x02013;251 &#x000b0;C, <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Utami et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Sousa et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>) and stained yellow on TLC with anisaldehyde spray reagent. Other physico-chemical and spectroscopic properties were consistent with those reported in literature (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Chama, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chama et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). Compound <bold>3</bold> was identified similarly as maslinic acid (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>, <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>), creamy powder which stained purple with anisaldehyde spray reagent, mp 249&#x02013;251 &#x000b0;C (Lit. 248&#x02013;250 &#x000b0;C, (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Hossain and Ismail, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Lozano-Mena et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Tanaka et&#x000a0;al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Woo et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). This is the first report of maslinic acid from the genus <italic>Dichapetalum</italic> aside its isolation from <italic>Crataegus oxyacantha</italic> and <italic>Eriobotrya japonica</italic>. Compound <bold>4</bold> was characterised as pomolic acid (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>, <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). Melting point and spectral data were consistent with literature values (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chama et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>). Compounds <bold>5</bold> and <bold>6</bold> (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref> were each identified as dichapetalin A and M, respectively upon comparison of their physico-chemical and spectral data with literature, <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>. Melting point of dichapetalin A (210&#x02013;213 &#x000b0;C) and spectral data (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>) were consistent with literature (Lit: 212&#x02013;213 &#x000b0;C, <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Achenbach et&#x000a0;al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Addae-mensah et&#x000a0;al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chama et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). Melting point of dichapetalin M, 282&#x02013;284 &#x000b0;C and spectral data were also consistent with that of known values (Lit: 280&#x02013;282 &#x000b0;C, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). This is the first report of the presence of these two dichapetalins in <italic>D</italic>. <italic>crassifolium</italic> and this could be of chemotaxonomic importance. With the exception of compounds 1 and 2 which were isolated from the petroleum ether extracts, the rest of the compounds including 1 and 2 were isolated from the EtOAc extracts. Phytochemical screening indicated the petroleum ether extracts contained only terpenoids in the stem and terpenoids, saponins and cardiac glycosides in the roots. Also, terpenoids and tannins were present in the EtOAc extracts of both the stem and root extracts in addition to saponins and cardiac glycosides which were present only in the roots. The methanol extracts contained terpenoids, tannins, and cardiac glycosides.<fig id="fig6"><label>Figure&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Structures of dichapetalins A (<bold>5</bold>) and M (<bold>6</bold>).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Figure&#x000a0;6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig></p><p id="p0125">Dichapetalin A was first isolated from <italic>D.&#x000a0;madagascariense</italic> (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Achenbach et&#x000a0;al., 1995</xref>) as the major constituent of the roots. Later the compound was isolated from <italic>D</italic>. <italic>gelonioides</italic> (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Fang et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>), <italic>D</italic>. <italic>ruhlandii, D. mombuttense, D</italic>. <italic>zenkeri, D</italic>. <italic>eickii</italic>, <italic>D.&#x000a0;fillicauli</italic> (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chama et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>) and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>pallidum</italic> (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Dichapetalin M has so far been isolated from only two other species, <italic>D</italic>. <italic>Madagascariense</italic> (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>) and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>eickii</italic> (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Long et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). Pomolic acid has also been isolated from <italic>D.&#x000a0;fillicauli</italic> (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chama et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>) and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>pallidum</italic> (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Earlier isolation of friedelan-3&#x003b2;-ol and friedelan-3-one was reported in <italic>D</italic>. <italic>barteri</italic>, <italic>D</italic>. <italic>madagascariense</italic> (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>), <italic>D.&#x000a0;filicaule</italic> (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chama et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>) and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>pallidum</italic> (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Osei-Safo et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). &#x003b2;-Sitosterol and stigmasterol have previously been isolated from <italic>D</italic>. <italic>barteri</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>madagascariense</italic>. &#x003b2;-Sitosterol and stigmasterol commonly occur in most plants and differ structurally only at the C22&#x02013;C23 due to the presence of unsaturation in the latter and as a result both are often isolated together as a mixture.</p><p id="p0130">The most abundant of the tritepenoids were the friedelan-3&#x003b2;-ol and friedelan-3-one. Even though phytochemical screening indicated the presence of terpenoids, tannins and cardiac glycosides in the roots and terpenoids, tannins in the stem of the ethyl acetate extracts, only triterpenoids were isolated suggesting that they constituted the abundant phytochemicals in the plant whiles tannins and cardiac glycosides occurred in least amounts.</p><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Results of <italic>in vitro anti-schistosomal</italic> activity against <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic></title><p id="p0135">The picture of <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic> eggs identified under a low power microscope is presented in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref>. The half maximal inhibitory concentrations, IC<sub>50</sub> (&#x003bc;g/ml, &#x000b1; SEM) of reference standard, compounds and extracts were determined for duplicate experiments (n = 2) as presented in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>.<fig id="fig7"><label>Figure&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Egg of <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic> isolated from school children in Tomefa in the Ga South District of Accra, Ghana under a low power microscope.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Figure&#x000a0;7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Half maximal inhibitory concentrations, IC<sub>50</sub> (&#x003bc;g/ml, &#x000b1; SEM) of isolated compounds and extracts from the root and stem of <italic>D.&#x000a0;crassifolium</italic> compared with praziquantel standard against <italic>S.&#x000a0;haematobium</italic> eggs.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0080">Table&#x000a0;3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Compound/Extract</th><th colspan="2">IC<sub>50</sub> &#x000b1; SEM (&#x003bc;g/ml)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Friedelan-3-one</td><td colspan="2">378.10 &#x000b1; 0.23</td></tr><tr><td>&#x003b2;-Sitosterol/stigmasterol</td><td colspan="2">177.90 &#x000b1; 0.10</td></tr><tr><td>Dichapetalin M</td><td colspan="2">191.00 &#x000b1; 0.12</td></tr><tr><td>Dichapetalin A</td><td colspan="2">151.1 &#x000b1; 0.21</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>Extracts</td><td>Root</td><td>Stem</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>Petroleum ether</td><td>546.40 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td>443.70 &#x000b1; 0.04</td></tr><tr><td>EtOAc</td><td>248.60 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td>638.00 &#x000b1; 0.08</td></tr><tr><td>MeOH</td><td>566.30 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td>893.70 &#x000b1; 0.08</td></tr><tr><td>Praziquantel</td><td>15.47 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0140">Generally, the isolated compounds showed higher ovicidal activity against <italic>S.&#x000a0;haematobium</italic> eggs than the extracts though activities for both samples were low compared to the standard praziquantel (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>). Among the compounds isolated from the stem, the mixture of &#x003b2;-sitosterol/stigmasterol showed the highest potency (IC<sub>50</sub>, 177.90 &#x003bc;g/ml) but this was about 11 times less potent than the standard praziquantel drug (15.47 &#x000b1; 0.06 &#x003bc;g/ml), (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>, <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;8</xref>). The next highest was dichapetalin A (151.10 &#x003bc;g/ml) whiles friedelan-3-one showed the least potency with IC<sub>50</sub>, 378.10 &#x003bc;g/ml (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>, Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref> and <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>). Dichapetalin M from the root extract gave an IC<sub>50</sub> of 191.00 &#x003bc;g/ml, (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>, <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;9</xref>). All the triterpenoids were isolated from the polar EtOAc extracts. This might be the reason why the most active compound, dichapetalin A was isolated from the most active root EtOAc extract. The root crude extracts were generally more active than the stem crude extracts (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>) even though the root EtOAc extract contained additional saponins and cardiac glycosides aside the terpenoids and tannins which were also contained in the stem EtOAc extract. This could be because of the roots containing more of the terpenoids as observed in the greater yield of the root extracts (1.5%) compared with the stem extracts (1.3%).<fig id="fig8"><label>Figure&#x000a0;8</label><caption><p>Concentration-dependent effect of friedelan-3-one, stigmasterol/sitosterol and dichapetalin M with standard praziquantel from the stem of <italic>D.&#x000a0;crassifolium</italic> against hatching of <italic>S.&#x000a0;haematobium</italic> eggs. Each point is &#x000b1;SEM (n = 2).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Figure&#x000a0;8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8"/></fig><fig id="fig9"><label>Figure&#x000a0;9</label><caption><p>Concentration-dependent effect of dichapetalin A with standard praziquantel from the roots of <italic>D.&#x000a0;crassifolium</italic> against hatching of <italic>S.&#x000a0;haematobium</italic> eggs. Each point is &#x000b1;SEM (n = 2).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0055">Figure&#x000a0;9</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr9"/></fig></p><p id="p0145">The IC<sub>50</sub> values for the root extracts were 248.60 (EtOAc), 546.40 (petroleum ether) and 566.30 (MeOH) &#x003bc;g/ml, while the stem crude extracts gave values of 443.70 (petroleum ether), 638.00 (EtOAc) and 893.70 (MeOH) &#x003bc;g/ml (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>, Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref> and <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>).<fig id="fig10"><label>Figure&#x000a0;10</label><caption><p>Concentration-dependent effect of petroleum ether, EtOAc and MeOH root extracts of <italic>D.&#x000a0;crassifolium</italic> against hatchability of <italic>S.&#x000a0;haematobium</italic> eggs. Each point is &#x000b1;SEM (n = 2).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0060">Figure&#x000a0;10</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr10"/></fig><fig id="fig11"><label>Figure&#x000a0;11</label><caption><p>Concentration-dependent effect of petroleum ether, EtOAc and MeOH extracts of the stem of <italic>D.&#x000a0;crassifolium</italic> against hatchability of <italic>S.&#x000a0;haematobium</italic> eggs. Each point is &#x000b1;SEM (n = 2).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0065">Figure&#x000a0;11</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr11"/></fig></p><p id="p0150">Against the beet armyworm (<italic>Spodoptera exigua</italic>), dichapetalin A showed antifeedant activity with an EC<sub>50</sub> of 3.1 &#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup> (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Jing et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). The compound also indicated nematicidal activity of 15.3% rate at 100 &#x003bc;g/ml over 72 h against <italic>Panagrellus redivivus</italic> (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Jing et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>) and anti-hookworm activity against <italic>Necator americanus</italic> eggs with IC<sub>50</sub> of 162.4 &#x003bc;g/ml (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chama et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>). Against parasitic fungi, dichapetalin A was almost as active as nystatin with growth inhibition of 12.8 &#x000b1; 0.8 and 10.5 &#x000b1; 0.02 at 50 &#x003bc;g/disk on <italic>Colletotrichum musae</italic> and <italic>Rhizoctonia solani</italic> respectively (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Jing et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>).</p><p id="p0155">Except for the anti-shistosomal activity, dichapetalin M has not been tested for its antiparasitic activities. Antiplasmodial activity evaluated for friedelan-3-one (2) against W2 strain of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> gave an IC<sub>50</sub> of 7.7 Mm (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Ndjakou Lenta et&#x000a0;al., 2007</xref>). Stigmasterol showed potency on both 3D7 and K1 strains of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> with EC<sub>50</sub> of 3 &#x003bc;M and 5 &#x003bc;M respectively (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Zhai et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). <italic>Beta</italic>-sitosterol indicated IC<sub>50</sub> of 2.28 &#x000b1; 0.01 &#x003bc;g/ml against 3D7 strain of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>falciparum</italic> and against Dd2 strain, it indicated &#x0003e;50 &#x003bc;g/ml (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Langat et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0160">A number of terpene compounds including monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, diterpenes and triterpenes have showed both remarkable <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> antischistosomal activity. The mechanism of action of their schistosomicidal effects are affected by their lipophilicity that allows easy crossing of the plasma membrane and interaction with intracellular molecules of parasites to cause morphological changes (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">de Moraes, 2015</xref>). Monoterpenes with <italic>in vitro</italic> activity against <italic>S</italic>. <italic>mansoni</italic> adult worms include, rotundifolone from <italic>Mentha x villosa</italic> at a concentration of 70 &#x003bc;g/ml (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Matos-Rocha et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). (+)-Limonene epoxide in essential oils also showed activity at a concentration of 25 &#x003bc;g/ml together with the detection of morphological alterations on the schistosome surface at concentrations of 25&#x02013;75 &#x003bc;g/ml (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">de Moraes et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). Among the antischistosomal sesqueterpene compounds active against the immature stages of <italic>S</italic>. <italic>mansoni</italic> are the antimalaria compounds artemisinin from the leaves of <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> L., artemether, artesunate and dihydroartemisinin (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Liu et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Utzinger et&#x000a0;al., 2001</xref>). The essential oil nerolidol was effective <italic>in vitro</italic> against adult worms of <italic>S</italic>. <italic>mansoni</italic> with a reduction in worm motor activity death at 31&#x02013;62 &#x003bc;M (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Silva et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). Budlein-A from <italic>Viguiera spp</italic> (Asteraceae) showed <italic>in vitro</italic> schistosomicidal activity against <italic>S.&#x000a0;mansoni</italic> adult worms at 12.5 &#x003bc;M and its derivatives 4&#x003b1;, 5-dihydrobudlein A and 4&#x003b1;,5-11&#x003b2;,13-tetrahydrobudlein A gave 100% mortality at the respective concentrations of 50 and 200 &#x003bc;M (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Sass et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). The diterpene phytol, from chlorophyll has also indicated promising <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> activity with infected mice against adult <italic>S.&#x000a0;mansoni</italic> (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">de Moraes et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). Aside these, triterpenes such as betulin isolated from <italic>Schefflera vinosa</italic> plant was effective <italic>in vitro</italic> against <italic>S</italic>. <italic>mansoni</italic> adult worms at a concentration of 100&#x02013;200 &#x003bc;M (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Cunha et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>). The triphenylphosphonium derivatives of betulin and betulinic acid showed <italic>in vitro</italic> antischistosomal activity against newly transformed schistosomula and adult worms of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mansoni</italic> at concentrations between 10 &#x003bc;M and 2 &#x003bc;M, respectively (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Spivak et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). Moreover, balsaminol F and karavilagenin C are cucurbitane-type triterpenes from <italic>Momordica balsamina</italic> with effective <italic>in vitro</italic> antischistosomal activity against <italic>S</italic>. <italic>mansoni</italic> adult worms at LC<sub>50</sub> values of 15 and 29 &#x003bc;M respectively (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Ramalhete et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>). Crude extracts and fractions of different families of plants have also indicated antischistosomal activity at varying degrees of potency. The stem bark and roots of <italic>Rauwolfia vomitoria</italic> killed all cercariae stage of <italic>S.&#x000a0;mansoni</italic> within 2 h of exposure at a respective concentration range of 62.5&#x02013;1000 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/ml and 250&#x02013;1000 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/ml. The LC<sub>50</sub> values after 1 and 2 h was 207.4 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/ml (stem) and 61.18 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/ml (root). In addition, both the stem and root of the plant showed 100 mortality of the adult worm within 120 h of incubation at a concentration range of 250&#x02013;1000 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/ml (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Tekwu et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). The MeOH extracts of <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L. (Zingiberaceae) and <italic>Nerium oleander</italic> L. (Apocynaceae) showed 100% <italic>S</italic>. <italic>mansoni</italic> worm mortality after a 24 h incubation period at concentrations up to 100 &#x003bc;g/ml (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abdel-Hameed et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). Also, MeOH extracts of five plants <italic>Dryopteris filixmas</italic> (Dryopteridaceae), <italic>Tanacetum vulgare</italic> (Asteraceae), <italic>Juglans nigra</italic> (Juglandaceae), <italic>Syzygium aromaticum</italic> (Myrtaceae) and <italic>Allium sativum</italic> (Liliaceae) exhibited strong potency at minimum effective concentrations of 50 &#x003bc;g/ml after 24 h against adult <italic>S</italic>. <italic>mansoni</italic> worms (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Metwalley, 2015</xref>). In a study to evaluate the effect of MeOH extracts on <italic>S</italic>. <italic>mansoni</italic> infected Swiss Albino Mice, <italic>Malus domestica</italic> (Rosaceae) showed significant (P &#x0003c; 0.05) antischistosomal activity at concentrations 300 mg/kg and 200 mg/kg with respective worm reduction of 85.93% and 72.22%. <italic>Allium cepa</italic> (Liliaceae), at 500 mg/kg and 300 mg/kg indicated 72.59% and 58.52% worm reductions respectively, whiles <italic>Citrus limon</italic> (Rutaceae) showed the least worm reduction of 42.96% at 200 mg/kg and 26.63% at 100 mg/kg (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Muema et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>). In a similar study, different solvent extracts of <italic>Ocimum americanum</italic> (Lamiaceae) and <italic>Bridelia micrantha</italic> (Phyllanthaceae) gave significant antischistosomal activity against <italic>S</italic>. <italic>mansoni</italic> infected Swiss Albino Mice (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Waiganjo et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0165">This study has established the presence of tetracyclic and pentacyclic triterpenoids from the stems and roots of <italic>D.&#x000a0;crassifolium</italic>. The identification of dichapetalins from the plant is chemotaxonomically significant since other species of the genus have been shown to contain this unique class of triterpenoids. So far, nine species of this genus have been shown to contain the dichapetalin class of compounds. However, only the roots of <italic>D.&#x000a0;crassifolium</italic> contained both dichapetalins A and M, the stem yielded only dichapetalin M. For the first time, maslinic acid and pomolic acid have been isolated from both the stems and roots of the plant. The activity of both extracts and isolated triterpenoids against <italic>S</italic>. <italic>haematobium</italic> was very low to merit consideration as potential lead compounds for development into any <italic>anti-schistosomal</italic> agent. The extracts and compounds might have an effect on other stages of the diseases such as the schistosomulae, miracidiae and the cercariae. Thus, a study of infections from experimental animals might reveal useful information on this. The general low activity of the tested compounds and extracts may be attributed to the facts that eggs of schistosomes have multiple layers between the shell and the larva. Hence, the presence of these layers, together with the minute size of pores in the egg shells, may preclude penetration of eggs by the extracts used.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec5.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0170">Mary Anti Chama: Conceived and designed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0175">Dorcas Osei-Safo: Conceived and designed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data.</p><p id="p0180">Ivan Addae-Mensah: Conceived and designed the experiments.</p><p id="p0185">Michael Wilson: Conceived and designed the experiments; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data.</p><p id="p0190">Henry Akwaffo Onyame, Claudine Fleischer, Reiner Waibel, Joseph Otchere: Performed the experiments.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0195">This work was supported by the <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100005601</institution-id><institution>University of Ghana Research Fund</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> [Grant numbers URF/5/ILG-009/2011-2012].</p></sec><sec id="sec5.3"><title>Competing interest statement</title><p id="p0200">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.4"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0205">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel-Hameed</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Nahas</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abo-Sedera</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antischistosomal and antimicrobial activities of some Egyptian plant species</article-title><source>Pharmaceut. Biol.</source><volume>46</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>626</fpage><lpage>633</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achenbach</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asunka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waibel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addae-Mensah</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppong</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dichapetalin A, a novel plant constituent from Dichapetalum madagascariense with potential antineoplastic activity</article-title><source>Nat. Prod. Lett.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1995</year><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>100</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addae-Mensah</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adu-Kumia</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waibelb</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppong</surname><given-names>I.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;novel D:A-friedooleanane triterpenoid and other constituents of the stem bark of Dichapetalum barteri Engl</article-title><source>ARKIVOC</source><volume>2007</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>79</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addae-mensah</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waibel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asunka</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppong</surname><given-names>I.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Achenbac</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dichapetalins--A new class of triterpenoids</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><issue>3</issue><year>1996</year><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>656</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8768320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adu-Kumi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Phytochemical And Bioactivity Studies On the Chemical Constituents of the Stem Bark Of D. Bateri</chapter-title><year>1997</year><publisher-name>University of Ghana</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Accra-Ghana</publisher-loc><comment>(Chemistry, M.Phil)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breteler</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title><italic>The African Dichapetalaceae IV: a Taxonomical Revision</italic>: Wageningen</chapter-title><year>1978</year><publisher-name>H. Veenman &#x00026; Zonen B.V</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chama</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Chemical Investigation of Two Ghanaian Medicinal Plants-Dichapetalum Madagascariense and Scoparia Dulcis</chapter-title><year>2007</year><publisher-name>University of Ghana</publisher-name><comment>(Chemistry, PhD)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chama</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dziwornu</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waibel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osei-Safo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addae-Mensah</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otchere</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation, characterization, and anthelminthic activities of a novel dichapetalin and other constituents of Dichapetalum filicaule</article-title><source>Pharmaceut. Biol.</source><volume>54</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1179</fpage><lpage>1188</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uch&#x000f4;a</surname><given-names>C.J.d.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cintra</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>H.C.d.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peixoto</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro schistosomicidal activity of some brazilian cerrado species and their isolated compounds</article-title><source>Evid. base Compl. Alternative Med.</source><volume>2012</volume><year>2012</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Moraes</surname></name><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Junior</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Sousa</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytol, a diterpene alcohol from chlorophyll, as a drug against neglected tropical disease Schistosomiasis mansoni</article-title><source>PLoS Neglected Trop. Dis.</source><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Moraes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural products with antischistosomal activity</article-title><source>Future Med. Chem.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25996071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Moraes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Sousa</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anthelmintic activity of the natural compound (+)-limonene epoxide against Schistosoma mansoni</article-title><source>Planta Med.</source><volume>79</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><comment>03/04</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23408270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eloff</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The amino acid metabolism of Dichapetalum cymosum (Gifblaar) II. The microscale synthesis of N-methyl-L-alanine</article-title><source>Z.&#x000a0;Pflanzenphysiol.</source><volume>98</volume><issue>5</issue><year>1980</year><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>417</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>H.-B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>W.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madulid</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farnsworth</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytotoxic constituents from the stem bark of Dichapetalum gelonioides collected in the Philippines</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Nat. Prod.</source><volume>69</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>337</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiern</surname><given-names>W.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rendle</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Welwitsch</surname><given-names>F.M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><series>Catalogue of the African Plants</series><volume>Vol. 1</volume><year>1901</year><publisher-name>Printed by order of the Trustees</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><fpage>1896</fpage><lpage>1901</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of triterpenes from the leaves of Orthosiphon stamineus</article-title><source>Arab. J. Chem.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>298</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>S.-X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>S.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>X.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biologically active dichapetalins from Dichapetalum gelonioides</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Nat. Prod.</source><volume>77</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>882</fpage><lpage>893</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24597894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kotze</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>G.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Field evaluation of anthelmintic drug sensitivity using in vitro egg hatch and larval motility assays with Necator americanus recovered from human clinical isolates</article-title><source>Int. J. Parasitol.</source><volume>35</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15777920</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langat</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoseah</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elizabeth</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheplogoi</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Philip</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of antiplasmodial activity and toxicity of crude extracts and isolated compounds from oncoba spinosa (Flacourtiaceae)</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Adv. Med. Pharm. Sci.</source><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Juang</surname><given-names>S.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>F.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Triterpene acids from the leaves of planchonella duclitan (Blanco) Bakhuizan</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Chin. Chem. Soc.</source><volume>52</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>1275</fpage><lpage>1280</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.-X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jie</surname><given-names>Z.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.-X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New uses for old drugs: the tale of artemisinin derivatives in the elimination of schistosomiasis japonica in China</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>19</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>15058</fpage><lpage>15074</lpage><comment>Retrieved from</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://res.mdpi.com/d_attachment/molecules/molecules-19-15058/article_deploy/molecules-19-15058.pdf" id="intref0015">https://res.mdpi.com/d_attachment/molecules/molecules-19-15058/article_deploy/molecules-19-15058.pdf</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25244286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aussagues</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Molinier</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcourt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vendier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Massiot</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dichapetalins from Dichapetalum species and their cytotoxic properties</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><volume>94</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23618620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lozano-Mena</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Juan</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Planas</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maslinic acid, a natural phytoalexin-type triterpene from olives--a promising nutraceutical?</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>19</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>11538</fpage><lpage>11559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25093990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matos-Rocha</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>dos Santos Cavalcanti</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa-Filho</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fa;cio</surname><given-names>A.S.S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veras</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feitosa</surname><given-names>A.P.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro evaluation of schistosomicidal activity of essential oil of Mentha x villosa and some of its chemical constituents in adult worms of Schistosoma mansoni</article-title><source>Planta Med.</source><volume>79</volume><issue>14</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1307</fpage><lpage>1312</lpage><comment>Retrieved from</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thieme-connect.com/products/ejournals/abstract/10.1055/s-0033-1350732" id="intref0020">https://www.thieme-connect.com/products/ejournals/abstract/10.1055/s-0033-1350732</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23945759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metwalley</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of the antischistosomal activity of some plant extracts against Schistosoma mansoni infection</article-title><source>World J. Med. Sci.</source><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>169</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Hagan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rare fluorinated natural products</article-title><source>Chem. Brit.</source><volume>28</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>785</fpage><lpage>788</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muema</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Obonyo</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Njeru</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mwatha</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antischistosomal effects of selected methanolic plant extracts in swiss albino mice infected with Schistosoma mansoni</article-title><source>Eur. J. Med. Plants</source><year>2015</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ndjakou Lenta</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngouela</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fekam Boyom</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tantangmo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feuya Tchouya</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsamo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Donald Connolly</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-plasmodial activity of some constituents of the root bark of Harungana madagascariensis LAM. (Hypericaceae)</article-title><source>Chem. Pharm. Bull.</source><volume>55</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17329893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osei-Safo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chama</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addae-Mensah</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waibel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>The dichapetalins-unique cytotoxic constituents of the Dichapetalaceae</chapter-title><source>Phytochemicals as Nutraceuticals-Global Approaches to Their Role in Nutrition and Health</source><year>2012</year><publisher-name>IntechOpen</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osei-Safo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chama</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Addae-Mensah</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waibel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asomaning</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppong</surname><given-names>I.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dichapetalin M from Dichapetalum madagascariensis</article-title><source>Phytochem. Lett.</source><volume>1</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>150</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osei-Safo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dziwornu</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salgado</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunassee</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chama</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bi- and bisbibenzyls from the roots of Dichapetalum heudelotii and their antiproliferative activities</article-title><source>Fitoterapia</source><volume>122</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28882670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramalhete</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magalh&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulhovo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Silva Filho</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>M.-J.U.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro schistosomicidal activity of balsaminol F and karavilagenin C</article-title><source>Planta Med.</source><volume>78</volume><issue>18</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>1912</fpage><lpage>1917</lpage><comment>Retrieved from</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thieme-connect.com/products/ejournals/abstract/10.1055/s-0032-1327832" id="intref0025">https://www.thieme-connect.com/products/ejournals/abstract/10.1055/s-0032-1327832</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23096257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sass</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morais</surname><given-names>G.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>R.A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magalhaes</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><x>&#x02026;</x><name><surname>Heleno</surname><given-names>V.C.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structurally modified natural sesquiterpene lactones constitute effective and less toxic schistosomicidal compounds</article-title><source>Org. Biomol. Chem.</source><volume>12</volume><issue>40</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>7957</fpage><lpage>7964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25030079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Carvalho</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Sousa</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moraes</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antischistosomal activity of the terpene nerolidol</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>19</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>3793</fpage><lpage>3803</lpage><comment>Retrieved from</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://res.mdpi.com/d_attachment/molecules/molecules-19-03793/article_deploy/molecules-19-03793.pdf" id="intref0030">https://res.mdpi.com/d_attachment/molecules/molecules-19-03793/article_deploy/molecules-19-03793.pdf</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24662089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>L.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alc&#x000e2;ntara</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieira-Filho</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><x>&#x02026;</x><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New triterpenes from Maytenus robusta: structural elucidation based on NMR experimental data and theoretical calculations</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>17</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>13439</fpage><lpage>13456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23147402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spivak</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keiser</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gubaidullin</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nedopekina</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shakurova</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Odinokov</surname><given-names>V.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and activity of new triphenylphosphonium derivatives of betulin and betulinic acid against Schistosoma mansoni in vitro and in vivo</article-title><source>Bioorg. Med. Chem.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>21</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>6297</fpage><lpage>6304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25245671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahana</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Theodor Bilharz (1825-1862): discoverer of schistosomiasis</article-title><source>Singap. Med. J.</source><volume>48</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>185</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>J.C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidotti</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>C.C.d.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;New tormentic acid derivative from Luehea divaricata Mart. (Tiliaceae)</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Braz. Chem. Soc.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><comment>Retrieved from</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext%26pid=S0103-50532003000300024%26nrm=iso" id="intref0035">http://www.scielo.br/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&#x00026;pid=S0103-50532003000300024&#x00026;nrm=iso</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tekwu</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosompem</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anyan</surname><given-names>W.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Appiah-Opong</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Owusu</surname><given-names>K.B.-A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tettey</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyarko</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro assessment of anthelmintic activities of Rauwolfia vomitoria (Apocynaceae) stem bark and roots against parasitic stages of Schistosoma mansoni and cytotoxic study</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Parasitol. Res.</source><volume>2017</volume><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Treger</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otchere</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keil</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quagraine</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mott</surname><given-names>B.T.</given-names></name><x>&#x02026;</x><name><surname>Vermeire</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro screening of compounds against laboratory and field isolates of human hookworm reveals quantitative differences in anthelmintic susceptibility</article-title><source>Am. Soc. Trop. Med. Hyg.</source><volume>90</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>74</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Utami</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukari</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahmani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdul</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic contents, antioxidant and cytotoxic activities of Elaeocarpus floribundus Blume</article-title><source>Pak. J. Pharm. Sci.</source><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23455191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Utzinger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuhua</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>N'Goran</surname><given-names>E.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergquist</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The potential of artemether for the control of schistosomiasis</article-title><source>Int. J. Parasitol.</source><volume>31</volume><issue>14</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>1549</fpage><lpage>1562</lpage><comment>Retrieved from</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0020751901002971?via%3Dihub" id="intref0040">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0020751901002971?via%3Dihub</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11730781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waiganjo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yole</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochanda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Anti-Schistosomal Activity of Five Plant Extracts on Swiss white Mice Infected with Schistosoma Mansoni</chapter-title><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>K.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S.U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Triterpenes from perilla frutescens var. acuta and their cytotoxic activity</article-title><source>Nat. Prod. Sci.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>75</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina-Bolivar</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimalarial evaluation of the chemical constituents of hairy root culture of Bixa orellana L</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>756</fpage><lpage>766</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24406786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z.-X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C.-Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Triterpenes from <italic>Callicarpa integerrima</italic> champ</article-title><source>Yao xue xue bao = Acta pharmaceutica Sinica</source><volume>47</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22493809</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0220">The following is the supplementary data related to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>Revision2-Supplementary data</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"><alt-text>Revision2-Supplementary data</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors acknowledge the people of Tomefa in the Ga South District of Greater Accra for providing urine samples.</p></ack></back></article>