<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec26" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cell wall and membrane stress</div>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CNB oil treated RSY150 cells in the stationary phase had an irregular chitin distribution found on the lateral wall of budding cells (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>a). Such effects became pronounced in metabolically active cells grown in the presence of 10% serum (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>c, f), with intense chitin staining at the hyphal tip. Similar staining patterns have been reported for cells exposed to high sugar or salt concentrations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>], for which hypo-osmotic pressure induced chitin synthesis or polymerization at the growing hyphal tip. Consistent with this idea is the larger cell volume of RSY150 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>) and sensitivity of the 
  <span class="italic">SSU18</span> mutant (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>c) exposed to CNB oil. Cell wall reinforcement with chitin in response to stress is a well-known phenomenon in yeast [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>]. It is known that most resistant clinical strains have a higher overall chitin content, reinforcing the cell wall and making them more resistant to cell wall targeted antifungals [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>]. As expected, the metabolically active clinical isolate showed more chitin than RSY150 (Additional files 
  <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>, 
  <a rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM4">4</a>: Figures S2, S3) for both control and treated cells, confirming cell wall reinforcement in the clinical strain.
 </p>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chitin plays an important role in defining the cell wall nanomechanical properties [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>], and β-1,3 D-glucan is critical in maintaining cell shape, mechanical rigidity and resistance to osmotic pressure [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>]. Exposure to CNB oil produced osmotically fragile, swollen cells with an uneven chitin distribution and increased elasticity, consistent with prior studies [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>]. The elasticity values reported in this study are high in comparison, reflecting cross linking from fixation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>]. Inhibition of β-1,3-
  <span class="sc">d</span>-glucan synthase by cinnamaldehyde in 
  <span class="italic">S. cerevisiae</span> or by caspofungin in 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> results in reduced cell wall β-1,3-glucan [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>] and increased cell wall chitin content, respectively [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]. Furthermore, mutants defective in chitin and β-glucan cross linking (
  <span class="italic">chr1chr2Δ</span>) have cell wall elasticity that varies with architecture and composition [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to cell wall chitin and glucans, the surface of 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> is decorated with proteins called adhesins that play a pivotal role in cell communication, adhesion and microbial infection [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>]. Many adhesins are mannoproteins that are homogenously dispersed on the cell surface [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>]. Cell wall stress, temperature variation, exposure to antifungal agents, host interaction and biofilm formation have been shown to alter the adhesive properties of cells [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>]. Adhesive forces in this study are based on the interaction between the cell surface and the hydrophilic, negatively charged silicon nitride AFM tip. Exposure to CNB oil gave rise to a moderate increase in cell adhesion, which may be attributed to cell wall remodelling, as evidenced by concomitant changes in roughness. Changes in adhesion may reflect loss or rearrangement of adhesins, or reorganization of surface sugars [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cell wall stress was characterised not only by changes in chitin distribution and expression, but also polarized growth and moderate sensitivity to cell wall perturbing agents, leading to cell cycle arrest and fungal death [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>]. Congo Red and Calcofluor White target chitin and β-1,3-glucan synthases to produce a cytokinetic defect leading to cell cycle arrest [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>]. A delayed or arrested cell cycle results in polarized growth with formation of pseudohyphal cells [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">81</a>], as characterized by depolymerized microtubules [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">82</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>]. Such a morphology was observed in 30% of the cell population exposed to CNB oil, along with defects in microtubule polymerization.
 </p>
</sec>
