<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec27" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spindle defects</div>
 <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microtubules are central to cell division, forming the mitotic spindle and coordinating nuclear movement [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">82</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>]. In 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span>, the pre-mitotic movement of the nuclei through the bud neck and subsequent separation of nuclei are coordinated by microtubules [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>]. In normal cells, nuclear division is complete when the buds are still small, such that larger budding cells are never observed without the nucleus [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>]. In the control cells, two distinct subcellular microtubule structures were observed, one traversing the mother and budding cells and the other only in the mother cells. Anaphase and G2 cell cycle arrest, as well as a more pronounced filamentous growth, were apparent following CNB exposure (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>a, c). Cell cycle defects associated with microtubule perturbation were readily visualized in CNB treated RSY150 in which Htb-RFP and Tub2-GFP highlighted the nucleus and microtubules, respectively. Four hours following treatment with CNB at MIC, log phase cells had ablated mitotic spindles, observed as fluorescent patches or aggregates of tubulin (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>a). Large-budding cells had nuclear staining restricted to the mother cell (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>a, arrow). These results are consistent with previous observations in which tubulin polymerization inhibitors and Δ
  <span class="italic">kar3/Δkar3</span> mutants had similar phenotypes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>]. We observe anaphase arrest in cells exposed to CNB at MIC, with 14% of the cells in anaphase as compared to 10% in the control, an effect which is reduced at 1/2 MIC. Cells treated at MIC cinnamaldehyde had 15% of cells in anaphase, slightly less than the Δ
  <span class="italic">kar3/Δkar3</span> mutant that had 17% of cells in anaphase and exhibited polarized growth [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. Kar3 may mediate microtubule sliding during nuclear fusion and possibly mitosis, interacting with spindle microtubules to produce an inwardly directed force on the poles that antagonizes the CIP8 and KIP1 outward force [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. The Δ
  <span class="italic">kar3/Δkar3</span> mutant (RSY35) is no more resistant to CNB oil than wild type, suggesting that Kar3 is not likely the target of CNB oil.
 </p>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We observed pseudohyphal growth in CNB oil treated RSY150 at MIC, an effect which became less prominent at 1/2 MIC, a common response of yeast experiencing cell wall stress [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>]. For instance, toxins and chemicals that arrest cells in the S phase or mitosis display polarized growth due to activation of the CWI pathway [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">89</a>]. The CWI pathway activates the MAPK cascade to manage stress, and its components are key elements in controlling the cell cycle. There are three MAPK pathways, namely; the pheromone response pathway, the high osmolality glycerol (HOG) pathway and the 
  <span class="italic">PKC1</span>-mediated pathway [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">89</a>]. The increased sensitivity of the 
  <span class="italic">SSU81</span> knock-out mutant (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>c) suggests that the HOG pathway is activated in the presence of CNB oil. Under stress there is cross talk between these pathways and cell cycle checkpoints, resulting in a delayed cell cycle [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>] and a mixture of yeast and pseudohyphal cells (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>: Figure S2a, b).
 </p>
</sec>
