<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ultrastructural and mechanical analysis</div>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cell surface biophysical properties of CNB oil treated 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> RSY150 and a clinical isolate from blood were analyzed by Quantitative Imaging (QI™) using a Nanowizard III AFM (JPK Instruments, Berlin, Germany) as described previously [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>]. Briefly, cell suspensions (2.2 × 10
  <span class="sup">5</span> cells/mL) from both strains treated either with YPD only (control) or YPD with 1/2 MIC CNB oil for 24 h were deposited onto poly-
  <span class="sc">l</span>-Lysine coated cover slips for 1 h, fixed with formalin and air dried prior to AFM imaging. Cells treated with the fungal wall degrading enzyme, glucanase, served as a positive control. Samples were imaged with silicon nitride cantilevers (HYDRA6R-200NG; Nanosensors, Neuchatel, Switzerland) having calibrated spring constants ranging from 0.03 to 0.062 N/m.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">QI force curves (JPK software) obtained at each pixel of a 128 × 128 raster scan were collected using a Z-length of 7 μm and a raster scan of 100 μm/s for QI™. Adhesion and Young’s modulus calculations were made from approximately 16,536 force curves collected from each of five biological replicates. All force curves within a 200 × 200 nm square in the center of the cell were batch processed and histogram data exported from the JPK software using Excel. Adhesion was determined using the distance between the lowest point and baseline of the retract curve and Young’s moduli determined using the Hertz model (JPK software), an estimate of cell envelope elasticity. Surface roughness was measured at the mid-point of the cell using the QI™ height images [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>] and cellular volume was calculated using “Ellipsoid” (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://planetcalc.com/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://planetcalc.com/</span>) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>] for at least 20 different cells from three different samples.
 </p>
</sec>
