<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Recently, a study showed for the first time the antidepressant-like effects of 
 <italic class="italic">Asarum heterotropoides</italic> F. Schmidt essential oil (from the roots) in mice [
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. The chemical composition of this essential oil was analyzed; 78 peaks were detected by gas chromatography. The main compounds are methyl eugenol (22%), pentadecane (6%), and 2,3,5-trimethoxytoluene (5%). Antidepressant-like effects were observed after acute inhalation in behavioral despair assays (e.g., forced swimming and tail suspension tests) in mouse. Considering the prevalence of methyl eugenol in the 
 <italic class="italic">Asarum heterotropoides</italic> F. Schmidt essential oil, and the antidepressant-like actions previously reported about this compound in rats [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>], it might be suggested the methyl eugenol as the main mediator of the antidepressant effects induced by 
 <italic class="italic">Asarum heterotropoides</italic> F. Schmidt. Immunohistochemistry was performed to investigate the mechanisms of action. An increase in the CRF- and tyrosine hidroxylase-positive cells in the paraventricular nucleus and locus coeruleus, respectively, and a significant decrease of 5-HT-positive cells was observed in the mouse dorsal raphe after forced swimming exposure. The inhalation of 
 <italic class="italic">Asarum heterotropoides</italic> F. Schmidt essential oil restored to normal levels the immunoreactivity to 5-HT, CRF and tyrosine hidroxylase. Considering that stress-induced depression-like behaviors are closely linked to increased activity of the endogenous peptidergic system of CRF and reduced availability of monoamines [
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>], the mechanistic findings herein reported could be on the basis of the antidepressant-like effects of 
 <italic class="italic">Asarum heterotropoides</italic> F. Schmidt oil.
</p>
