<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Traditionally, smoketree preparations were as well used in liver disease (
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Shen et al., 1991</xref>). The hepatoprotective effect were demonstrated in rodent models (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">Matić et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">Matić et al., 2013</xref>). Liver damage was induced by pyrogallol, and the protective effect of a relatively high dose of methanolic extract (500 mg/kg) from smoketree stem was administered either 2 or 12 h prior to the administration of pyrogallol. The effects were compared to those of myricetin, found to be the main constituent of the extract. Pretreatment with the extract, but as well with myricetin resulted in a hepatoprotective effect, reducing the elevation of serum AST, ALT, ALP and total bilirubin levels that were induced by pyrogallol. Administration of natural compounds was most efficacious when performed 12 h before pyrogallol. In quest of the mechanism of action for the observed effect, the authors explored the status of Akt or protein kinase B in the liver of rats pretreated with smoketree extract or myricetin by immunoblot analysis. Administration of the natural products, either 2 h or 12 h before the pyrogallol application increased Akt activity and phosphorylation. Moreover, an enhanced STAT3 phosphorylation was reported, enabling the adequate activation of the JAK–STAT signaling pathway, an important cascade involved in signal transduction during hepatic injury (
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">Matić et al., 2013</xref>). Administration of 
 <italic>C. coggygria</italic> extract lead to an augmentation of acute phase reactants haptoglobin and a2-macroglobulin with protective role in hepatic lesions. It improved as well markers of oxidative stress, and inhibited NF-kB (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">Matić et al., 2011</xref>). The hepatoprotective effect of smoketree is currently used clinically as part of a compound formula used orally in Traditional Chinese Medicine, where it is mixed with other plant extracts obtained from 
 <italic>Schisandra chinesis</italic>, Chuipencao (
 <italic>Sedum sarmentosum</italic>), wolfberry (
 <italic>Lycium chinense</italic>), jujube (
 <italic>Ziziphus jujuba</italic>), gardenia (
 <italic>Gardenia jasminoides</italic>) (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Hao et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr">Su et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
