<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par50">Besides chemical-based TCM identification, molecular identification that uses specific fragments of DNA as markers is another effective method for authentication and identification of herbal drugs. In ChP, molecular identification has been used for the identification of Dendrobii Caulis, Fritillariae Cirrhosae Bulbus, Agkistrodon, Bungarus Parvus and Zaocys. Among various molecular identification techniques, molecular DNA barcoding has been increasingly studied recently [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. The core of this advanced technique is to assess the sequence variations of one or several commonly recognized, relatively short DNA sequences in the genome of the samples for the identification and authentication of herbal drugs. The process in general could be divided into three steps: DNA extraction, polymerase chain reaction amplification and DNA sequencing. Then the data are compared, aligned and analyzed to identify and authenticate herbal drugs from adulterants. As DNA barcoding technology is more assessable nowadays, ChP has incorporated a general chapter “9107 Guidelines for molecular DNA barcoding of Chinese materia medica”, which provides information and requirements for using DNA barcoding in TCM identification. In recent years, DNA barcoding has been widely used for the authentication and discrimination of TCM with their adulterants, such as Scutellariae Radix [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>], Astragali Radix [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>], Bupleuri Radix [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>], Uncariae Ramulus cum Uncis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>] and Corydalis Rhizoma [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. Compared to chromatographic methods, DNA barcoding is a more specific technique in herbal drugs identification and is not easily affected by external factors such as climates, age, or plant part. But it may suffer from disadvantages such as false positive or negative results originating from poor DNA quality or wrong choice of DNA markers. Its application is also limited in identifying different medicinal parts, and not suitable for processed TCM because DNA degradation would severely occur in this circumstance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. Therefore, combination of chromatographic methods and DNA barcoding may provide comprehensive identification and quality control of TCM.
</p>
