<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Gout is arthritis caused due to the deposition of a type of uric acid crystals called Monosodium Urate (MSU) crystals, usually deposited around or within the joints secondary to chronic hyperuricemia.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr1-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr2-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
 </sup> It affects 1 to 2% of adult population in developed countries and possibly increased the prevalence. Acute gouty arthritis may be associated with clinical symptoms of inflammation.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr1-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
 </sup> Gouty joint pain is known since ancient times and well known by the Egyptian in 2640 BC. Gouty arthritis indications ordinarily happen in the limits where body temperature is lesser than in the middle, and accordingly the deposition of monosodium urate is lesser than 0.41 mmol/l.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr3-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr4-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr"/>-
  <xref rid="bibr5-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
 </sup> Additionally, monosodium urate crystals deposition in synovial fluid is implicated by different variables, similar to pH, lack of articular hydration, and the closeness of such nucleating operators as non-aggregated proteoglycans, chondroitin sulfate and insoluble collagens.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr6-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr7-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
 </sup> Gout is often associated with eating of high protein diet and alcohol consumption.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr8-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
 </sup> The incidence of gout is about 3 per 1,000 persons, mostly affecting males. The common management of gout is by the use of anti-inflammatory agents and xanthine oxidase (XO) inhibitors to inhibit the synthesis of uric acid.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr9-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 </sup> Allopurinol is the most common inhibitor of xanthine oxidase.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr10-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
 </sup> However, its use is limited due to the adverse effects such as chronic kidney diseases and cardiovascular diseases.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr11-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
 </sup> Therefore, alternative treatment options for gout are required. Some herbal medicines have been used traditionally by the Unani physicians as a uricosuric and depurative for treating the gout.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr12-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
 </sup> Urinile is a polyherbal formulation comprising of 
 <italic>Trachyspermum ammi</italic> (Ajwain), 
 <italic>Berberis vulgeris</italic> (Barbbery), 
 <italic>Colechicum autumnale</italic> (Suranjan shireen) and 
 <italic>Apium graveolens</italic> (Karafs). 
 <italic>Colchicum autumnale</italic> is beneficial in gouty arthritis.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr13-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
 </sup> In the Unani Tibb, it is mainly valuable and famous mediator to treat joint pain, back agony as well as gout. 
 <italic>Trachyspermum ammi</italic> is useful remedy to relief the pain.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr14-1559325820946934" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
 </sup> Based on the pain relieving effects of urinile, we hypothesized that it will limit gouty arthritis. This study was planned to evaluate the therapeutic efficacy of urinile (polyherbal formulation) against gouty arthritis.
</p>
