<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">In terms of haplotype distribution, the predominant COII haplotypes for Beijing (China), Shaanxi (China), Japan and the USA were h1 (67.8%), h3 (75%), h11 (81.1%) and h1 (100%). Xu et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] made a similar conclusion that the major COII haplotypes for Beijing (China) and Shaanxi (China), and Japan and the USA were h1 (50%), h3 (100%), h11 (38%) and h1 (100%). Lee et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] identified COI haplotype H1 as the main COI haplotype for China (68%), Hungary (98.8%), Italy (80%) and the USA (92.5%). Similarly, this current study identified haplotype H1 as the predominant one, accounting for 27.6% of the Chinese samples, 93.4% of the Hungarian samples, 95.8% of the Italian samples, and all samples from the USA. The percentage of each haplotype in those countries varies slightly between the current and previous studies, which is likely due to the differences in the sample size. On the other hand, some divergences were also observed between the current and previous studies. For example, COII haplotype h14 was identified as the predominant haplotype (33%) in the Japanese population in Xu’s study [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] but was not detected in this study (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>). Variations in the haplotype numbers and percentages between the current study and that of Cesari et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] were also observed. Cesari et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] reported a total of 26 COI and COII combined haplotypes for BMSB specimens, mainly from Italy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In contrast, only five haplotypes [H1h1 (TH1), H3h3 (TH4), H33h3 (TH25), H8h11 (TH11) and H45h11 (TH22)] were detected in our study, thus, the total number of known BMSB COI and COII combined haplotypes (both known and novel) has increased to 80 known so far. Cesari et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] included relatively large number of samples from Italy (209 samples from 10 regions) and identified 22 unique COI and COII combined haplotypes. Our study was unable to identify any additional COI and COII combined haplotypes beside the common ones (H1h1, H3h3) in Italy due to the small sample size (24 samples from 3 locations) studied. However, there were five shared haplotypes [H1h1 (TH1), H3h3 (TH4), H33h3 (TH25), H8h11 (TH11) and H45h11 (TH22)] among the samples studied here and by Cesari et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Of these, the first two haplotypes were the two most common haplotypes. Interestingly, the last 3 haplotypes [H33h3 (TH25), H8h11 (TH11) and H45h11 (TH22)] detected in Italy by Cesari et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] were also detected in this study from China, Austria, and Japan. After combining the haplotype data from the two studies, haplotype network (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) revealed that the BMSB populations in Italy had genetic relatedness to Japanese populations, sharing the same haplotype H45h11 (TH22). It has been shown that the predominant haplotypes, such as H1h1 and H3h3, found in Italy were also widespread in China, the USA, and other European countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Therefore, it can be hypothesised that the BMSB populations in Italy possibly have originated from Asia, which can be supported by the extensive, ongoing cross-border travel and trade between Asia and Italy. However, invasion from North America cannot be ruled out as H1h1 was found also in the USA. Furthermore, haplotype H8 was detected in Switzerland [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] in 2012, in France [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] and Northern Italy in 2013 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], suggesting the possible invasion of BMSB to Italy was from Switzerland [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] based on the geographical proximity. The detection of the same haplotype of H8 in Austria in the current study raised the possibility that the invasion in Austria might have originated from the neighbouring countries of Switzerland or Italy as they share borders. However, the widespread distribution of H1 and H3 haplotypes in Austria (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) opens the likelihood of invasion from China as well.
</p>
