<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">The PCoA also revealed that the genetic group A (Chile, Georgia, Hungary, Italy, Romania, Turkey, and the USA) could have become a relatively independent genetic group. The neutrality test supported this, where the Fu’s Fs value of the genetic group A (− 1.174, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.02) was negative as that of the ancestral Chinese (− 7.852, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.02) and Japanese populations (− 29.707, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.02), indicating that the populations belong to genetic group A could have been under population expansion stage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The relatively low differences in F
 <sub>ST</sub> values between the populations within the genetic group A indicate that these populations could have originated from the same ancestral line. The close genetic relatedness among the BMSB populations from Chile, Georgia, Hungary, Italy, Romania and Turkey with the USA populations suggests that the late detection in those European countries might have originated from the USA. This also aligns well with the past invasion history of BMSB, where BMSB was first detected in the USA in mid-90s, and then spread throughout the country. Ten years after establishing in the USA, BMSB was detected in Switzerland in 2007 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], then spread in Europe [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] and Chile [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] recently. This study further suggested the secondary invasion from the USA to the European countries such as Georgia, Hungary, Italy, Romania and Turkey, and to Chile. In contrast, the populations of the genetic group B (Austria, Serbia and Slovenia) were clustered with the Chinese populations, but were genetically distant from the group A, indicating that these populations in group B originated from a different pedigree line or genetic group. The neutrality test’s Fu’s Fs value of genetic group B was positive (1.453, 
 <italic>p</italic> &gt; 10), which is consistent with the more recent detection of BMSB in these locations as the positive Fs indicated that these populations were under a population bottleneck [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. The haplotype diversity (
 <italic>Hd</italic>) and nucleotide diversity (
 <italic>π</italic>) of these three populations in group B were higher than 0.5 and 0.001, respectively, implying that these countries have been invaded multiple times by BMSB from different origins.
</p>
