<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The tick
  <span class="italic"> Rhipicephalus (Boophilus) microplus</span> (Canestrini, 1887) is an ectoparasite of cattle [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>], present in tropical and subtropical areas of America, Africa, Asia, and Australia in latitudes between 32°N and 32°S [
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>, 
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>]. About the damage caused by this parasite, direct losses in the production of milk and meat, leather damage caused by inflammatory reactions at the sites of tick attachment, appearance of myiasis, and the transmission of diseases such as bovine tick fever (caused by protozoa of the genus
  <span class="italic"> Babesia</span> and by bacteria of the genus
  <span class="italic"> Anaplasma</span>) could be mentioned [
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>]. The economic losses of Brazil related to ticks are estimated by 3.24 billion dollars a year, represented by the direct action of the parasite in the animals and by the cost of the control systems [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the strategies to minimize the economic losses caused by this pest involves reducing tick populations to economically acceptable levels [
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>]. But the inherent problems in controlling this parasite are acaricide resistance, and environmental residues resulted in only partial success of tick control [
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>]. The searches for environmentally safe products have accelerated the research on botanical acaricides [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>, 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>]. Plants have been used as food, spices, and medicines for thousands of years. These medicines initially took the form of crude drugs such as a variety of plants formulations. Natural products have been the origin of many important molecules in drug discoveries. Different culinary herbs have been screened for their biological activities. The active ingredients from plants are known to possess insecticidal, growth inhibiting, antimoulting, and repellent activities [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>]. Thus, there is increasing interest in alternative methods for tick control and growing demand for nonchemical products in livestock that are safer to animals and the environment [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>, 
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>]. Botanical alternatives, such as essential oils, are currently receiving particular attention [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Brazil, the Rutaceae family comprises about 38 genera and 22 species [
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>].
  <span class="italic"> Citrus limonum</span> (L.) comprises 3 species and various hybrids. Species of this genus are known to show monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes, such as limonene and 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-pinene [
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>, 
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>]. Essential oils of this kind have been evaluated for presenting biological activities such as insecticide, cytotoxic, and antibacterial activities [
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Piper nigrum</span> (L.), popularly known as black pepper, is a member of family Piperaceae [
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>, 
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>]. The genus
  <span class="italic"> Piper</span> includes more than 1000 species, but the best known are
  <span class="italic"> P. nigrum, Piper longum,</span> and
  <span class="italic"> Piper betle</span> [
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>, 
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>]. The fruits of
  <span class="italic"> P. nigrum</span> contain piperine, a compound that has already shown leishmanicidal activity [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>]. Furthermore, secondary metabolites of this species possess active compounds with insecticidal activity, antibacterial, antifungal, and others [
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>, 
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of this work is to develop natural products, like essential oils, for the combat of the cattle tick.</p>
</sec>
