<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Adult Immersion Test (AIT)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The AIT was performed as described by Drummond et al. [
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>] with minor modifications. The ticks were distributed to groups randomly (20 engorged females per group). The different groups of
  <span class="italic"> R. (B.) microplus</span> were immersed for 1 min in 5 mL of the respective concentrations (2.5%, 5%, and 10%) of
  <span class="italic"> C. limonum </span>and
  <span class="italic"> P. nigrum</span> by placing them directly into a 50 mL Falcon-type tube which was gently agitated at room temperature. In experiments of additive effects we used the ratio 1 : 1 (vol/vol) of each oil, with a final concentration of 2.5%, 5%, and 10%. Ticks were recovered from the solutions and dried and each group was transferred to Petri dish (9 cm diameter, 1,5 cm high), weighed, and kept in BOD incubator at a temperature of 28°C and relative humidity of 70–80% for oviposition. This experiment was performed three times in duplicate. The emulsifying solution (2% DMSO) was used as the negative control, while Amitraz (2 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>L/mL) and Deltamethrin (1 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>L/mL) in water were used as positive control. The mortality was observed during 15 days. The dead ticks were diagnosed based on three specific signs and features: increasing cuticle darkness and stopping Malpighian tube movement and hemorrhagic skin lesions. After 15 days, the eggs laid were placed in glass tube, weighed, and observed separately at the same condition of incubation for the next 30 days for visual estimation of hatching rate.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The percentage inhibition of oviposition was calculated as follows.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reproductive index (RI) = average weight of eggs laid (mg)/average weight of females before treatment (g).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Percentage inhibition of oviposition (IO%) = RI of control group − RI of treated group/RI control group × 100.</p>
</sec>
