<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Effect of Essential Oil of
  <span class="italic"> Citrus limonum</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Piper nigrum,</span> and Their Mixture on
  <span class="italic"> Rhipicephalus</span> (
  <span class="italic">Boophilus</span>)
  <span class="italic"> microplus</span> Female Oviposition and Hatching
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the AIT the efficacy of treatment against engorged females was also evaluated by measuring egg production. The results are presented in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>. Ours results showed that
  <span class="italic"> C. limonum</span> and the oil mixture have the best inhibition of oviposition rate, which is 100% in a dilution of 10%. However, at 5% the group with combined oils exhibited greater inhibition of oviposition with 94%, compared to 81.6% inhibition by individual
  <span class="italic"> C. limonum</span>.
  <span class="italic"> P. nigrum</span> essential oil, at concentrations of 10%, 5%, and 2.5%, inhibited egg-laying by 96%, 83%, and 50%, respectively. Data were significantly different in relation to the control (DMSO 2% and water) group (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001). The few eggs laid by the females treated with 5% of
  <span class="italic"> C. limonum</span> essential oil have not hatched into larvae. This result showed that oviposition is also dose-dependent (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>). Thus, analysis of variance 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05 for treatments confirmed the positive development of inhibition oviposition with increasing concentration. The mixture is effective against
  <span class="italic"> R. (B.) microplus</span> engorged females since its effect is fast and is expressed at a low concentration on reducing the rate of lay. However, the essential oils did not interfere in the hatchability of the larvae.
 </p>
</sec>
