<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-plants-07-00019" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Description</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Conradina</span> represents a group of evergreen, compact, perennial shrubs with virgate branches. Leaves are aromatic and needle-like with narrow, entire, revolute leaf-blades. Flowers are solitary or in a group of few in axillary cymes. The calyx is two-lipped; the lower lip has two long, narrow lobes while the upper lip has three short broad lobes. Corolla is white to purple in color, two-lipped; the lower lip has three lobes and usually dotted while the upper lip is erect and slightly concave.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Conradina canescens</span> A. Gray (false rosemary) is the only species of this genus that is relatively common in its range and the most morphologically variable (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="plants-07-00019-t001" href="#plants-07-00019-t001">Table 1</a>)
  <span class="italic">.</span> It is native to a small area of west Florida and south Alabama and southern parts of Mississippi [
  <a rid="B7-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-plants-07-00019">7</a>]. It occurs on sunny, dry sand soils on coastal dunes, in sand scrubs and in dry longleaf pineland ecosystems. It shows tolerance for the heat and humidity of the Southeast and is considered a drought-tolerant landscape plant that grows best in lean, sandy soils [
  <a rid="B8-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-plants-07-00019">8</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">C. canescens</span> is one of the indicator species for wooded dunes [
  <a rid="B9-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-plants-07-00019">9</a>] and is an excellent candidate for restoration of coastal areas. It can be used for beach projects that require planting on the back side of primary dunes, or any side of secondary dunes. It has also been used in gardens as a groundcover as the branches can reach up to 1 m in spread. False rosemary was easily propagated in the University of Florida Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences Extension using softwood stem cuttings from terminal shoots taken during the growing season.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Morphologically, 
  <span class="italic">C. brevifolia</span> Shinners (short-leaved rosemary) is very similar to 
  <span class="italic">C. canescens</span>, differing by its shorter leaves and greater number of flowers per axil, and it is also similar to the endangered 
  <span class="italic">C. glabra</span> [
  <a rid="B1-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-plants-07-00019">1</a>,
  <a rid="B5-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-plants-07-00019">5</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">C. brevifolia</span> was described as a new species by Shinners [
  <a rid="B4-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-plants-07-00019">4</a>]. Many taxonomic reviews of 
  <span class="italic">Conradina</span> have upheld 
  <span class="italic">C. brevifolia</span> as a distinct species yet it is taxonomically questionable [
  <a rid="B1-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-plants-07-00019">1</a>,
  <a rid="B6-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-plants-07-00019">6</a>,
  <a rid="B10-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-plants-07-00019">10</a>,
  <a rid="B11-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-plants-07-00019">11</a>]. Some taxonomists are still uncertain that 
  <span class="italic">C. brevifolia</span> is a true different species and therefore they treat it as a synonym to 
  <span class="italic">C. canescens. C. brevifolia</span> has a very restricted range in the middle of the Lake Wales Ridge in Central Florida [
  <a rid="B12-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-plants-07-00019">12</a>,
  <a rid="B13-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-plants-07-00019">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-plants-07-00019">14</a>] and has been listed as a federally endangered species in 1993 [
  <a rid="B5-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-plants-07-00019">5</a>]. Habitat destruction for agricultural and residential purposes is the main threat to this species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">C. etonia</span> Kral &amp; McCartney (Etonia rosemary) was discovered in the Etonia Scrub in Putnam County, Florida in September 1990 and described as a new species in 1991 [
  <a rid="B6-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-plants-07-00019">6</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">C. etonia</span> is similar to 
  <span class="italic">C. grandiflora</span> in general appearance and the flowers are large and quite similar but the leaves of 
  <span class="italic">C. etonia</span> are broader than 
  <span class="italic">C. grandiflora</span> and have clearly visible lateral veins on the lower surface [
  <a rid="B1-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-plants-07-00019">1</a>,
  <a rid="B15-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-plants-07-00019">15</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">C. etonia</span> is found in very limited areas of deep white sand scrub dominated by sand pines (
  <span class="italic">Pinus clausa</span>) and scrubby oaks (
  <span class="italic">Quercus</span> spp.) on dry soils. Its entire known range is within a subdivision of Putnam County containing streets and a few residences, which make it the most narrowly distributed species of 
  <span class="italic">Conradina</span> [
  <a rid="B6-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-plants-07-00019">6</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">C. etonia</span> was listed as a federally endangered species in July 1993 [
  <a rid="B5-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-plants-07-00019">5</a>]. The latest survey of Etonia rosemary counted about eight subpopulations on Etonia Creek State Forest containing fewer than 1000 total individuals [
  <a rid="B16-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-plants-07-00019">16</a>]. The major threats facing 
  <span class="italic">C. etonia</span> include habitat loss due to development projects for residential housing, horticultural collection, hurricane damage and invasive species or lack of natural processes, such as fire [
  <a rid="B17-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-plants-07-00019">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-plants-07-00019">18</a>]. Because 
  <span class="italic">C. etonia</span> requires light but can tolerate the light shade of openings the in scrub, fire suppression is one of the major limiting factors as it results in over-shading by overstory scrub vegetation rendering the habitat less favorable for 
  <span class="italic">C. etonia</span> [
  <a rid="B18-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-plants-07-00019">18</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">C. grandiflora</span> Small (large-flowered rosemary) is endemic to the scrub habitat of Florida’s east coast between Daytona Beach and Miami as well as near Orlando and Okeechobee County [
  <a rid="B5-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-plants-07-00019">5</a>]. A regime of frequent fires benefits 
  <span class="italic">C. grandiflora</span> because it cannot tolerate shade and requires an open sunny habitat. 
  <span class="italic">C. grandiflora</span> is a candidate for listing as an endangered species but of a lower priority than other 
  <span class="italic">Conradina</span> species [
  <a rid="B5-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-plants-07-00019">5</a>]. Loss of the Florida scrub habitat is the major threat to this species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">C. glabra</span> Shinners (Apalachicola rosemary) was described in a sand hill community east of the Apalachicola River in Liberty County, Florida in 1962 [
  <a rid="B1-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-plants-07-00019">1</a>,
  <a rid="B4-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-plants-07-00019">4</a>]. This species is very narrowly distributed and restricted to Liberty County, Florida. Out of its seven known locations, six 
  <span class="italic">C. glabra</span> subpopulations (artificially divided by the Florida gas transmission pipeline) are remaining, all of which are located on private silvicultural lands and subject to much disturbance. Its other historical locations were converted to pine plantations, and can no longer support this species. Because of homozygosity and inbreeding, many of flowers of 
  <span class="italic">C. glabra</span> are male sterile, and the stamens are very malformed [
  <a rid="B1-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-plants-07-00019">1</a>]. It was added to the federal list of endangered species in 1993 [
  <a rid="B5-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-plants-07-00019">5</a>,
  <a rid="B19-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-plants-07-00019">19</a>,
  <a rid="B20-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-plants-07-00019">20</a>], primarily due to habitat loss and modification of forestry practices. There is no record of how abundant 
  <span class="italic">C. glabra</span> was before its habitat was altered because the silviculture operations began before its discovery.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">C. verticillata</span> Jennison (Cumberland rosemary) is the only species of this genus that is not found in Florida. The species was established in 1933 [
  <a rid="B21-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-plants-07-00019">21</a>]. It is a rare species, existing only as three small subpopulations in Tennessee and one subpopulation in Kentucky [
  <a rid="B22-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-plants-07-00019">22</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">C. verticillata</span> is found only in boulder bars, cobble bars, sand bars and gravel bars in close proximity to rivers on the Cumberland Plateau of north-central Tennessee and southeastern Kentucky [
  <a rid="B22-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-plants-07-00019">22</a>]. The preferred habitat conditions include open to slightly-shaded area, moderately deep well-drained sandy soil, periodic flooding, and topographic features like narrow channels or depressions on gravel bars. 
  <span class="italic">C. verticillata</span> is the only species that is triploid (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 3) and accordingly has a lower ability to reproduce and disperse sexually and greatly reduced seed germination rates. The fresh seeds of 
  <span class="italic">C. verticillata</span> are physiologically dormant and require cold stratification to germinate [
  <a rid="B23-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-plants-07-00019">23</a>]. It has been on the federal list of threatened species since 1991 [
  <a rid="B24-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-plants-07-00019">24</a>]. The major threats facing 
  <span class="italic">C. verticillata</span> are habitat destruction, general deterioration of water quality, competition and shading by woody plants.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2009, analysis of patterns of genetic structure based on microsatellites in 
  <span class="italic">Conradina</span> led to the identification of 
  <span class="italic">C. cygniflora</span> Edwards, Judd, Ionta &amp; Herring [
  <a rid="B25-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-plants-07-00019">25</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">C. cygniflora</span> can only be found in Dunns Creek state park in south-central Putnam County, Florida. It occupies nine tightly-clustered sites that probably form around two to four self-sustaining subpopulations. 
  <span class="italic">C. cygniflora</span> carries several unique morphological characters that distinguish this species from all other described 
  <span class="italic">Conradina</span> species including thin-walled unicellular hairs, epidermis features, and larger calyces. Due to its exceptionally limited geographic distribution and low number of individuals, 
  <span class="italic">C. cygniflora</span> is considered a candidate for listing as federally endangered [
  <a rid="B25-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-plants-07-00019">25</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is very little information in the literature about 
  <span class="italic">C. montana</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. puberula</span>. 
  <span class="italic">C. montana</span> Small was reported in sandy woods and ravines, Appalachian plateau near Rugby, Tennessee while 
  <span class="italic">C. puberula</span> Small was observed in pine-lands, northern Gulf coast region, Florida [
  <a rid="B26-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-plants-07-00019">26</a>,
  <a rid="B27-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-plants-07-00019">27</a>]. Some taxonomic discrepancies surround 
  <span class="italic">C. montana</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. puberula</span> since some experts treat both species as synonyms of 
  <span class="italic">C. verticillata</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. canescens</span>, respectively.
 </p>
</sec>
