<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec5dot1-plants-07-00019" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.1. Allelopathic Activity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The term allelopathy describes the chemical interactions between plants where one plant interferes with the germination and growth of another plant. Allelopathic compounds are thought to enter the surrounding environment via volatilization, leaching with rain, and decomposition of plant litter, thereby inhibiting the growth of competitors or species that may threaten the plant’s survival. In this manner, the plant may have an ecological role in its ecosystem by affecting plant spacing, succession, and community composition [
  <a rid="B35-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-plants-07-00019">35</a>]. Terpenoids, especially monoterpenoids, are considered one of the 14 allelochemical classes [
  <a rid="B38-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-plants-07-00019">38</a>,
  <a rid="B39-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-plants-07-00019">39</a>] that play an important role in the interactions between plants [
  <a rid="B40-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-plants-07-00019">40</a>,
  <a rid="B41-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-plants-07-00019">41</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">C. canescens</span> is thought to play a significant ecological role in maintaining a healthy scrub ecosystem by inhibiting the germination of native grasses [
  <a rid="B42-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-plants-07-00019">42</a>]. It was suggested that by inhibiting germination of the grasses, the development of the more fire-prone sand hill ecosystem is prevented, and the scrub ecosystem is maintained [
  <a rid="B35-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-plants-07-00019">35</a>]. Because detailed knowledge of allelopathic actions in natural plant communities can provide excellent models for new strategies in developing highly selective herbicides, the allelopathic effect of 
  <span class="italic">C. canescens</span> has been a subject of several studies [
  <a rid="B34-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-plants-07-00019">34</a>,
  <a rid="B35-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-plants-07-00019">35</a>,
  <a rid="B43-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-plants-07-00019">43</a>]. Water washes of fresh 
  <span class="italic">C. canescens</span> leaves were reported to have strong inhibitory effects on germination and growth of 
  <span class="italic">Schizachyrium scoparium</span> [
  <a rid="B34-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-plants-07-00019">34</a>,
  <a rid="B43-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-plants-07-00019">43</a>]. The essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">C. canescens</span> and purified ursolic acid remarkably inhibited the germination of 
  <span class="italic">Lactuca sativa</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Lolium perenne</span> [
  <a rid="B37-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-plants-07-00019">37</a>]. The phytotoxic activity of 
  <span class="italic">C. canescens</span> oil can be attributed to the high concentration of 1,8-cineole which can inhibit the seed germination and seedling growth of lettuce in a dose-dependent manner [
  <a rid="B44-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-plants-07-00019">44</a>,
  <a rid="B45-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-plants-07-00019">45</a>,
  <a rid="B46-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-plants-07-00019">46</a>,
  <a rid="B47-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-plants-07-00019">47</a>,
  <a rid="B48-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-plants-07-00019">48</a>] by strongly inhibiting mitochondrial respiration and all stages of mitosis [
  <a rid="B49-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-plants-07-00019">49</a>]. The presence of significant quantities of ursolic acid suggests that this compound might contribute to the strong allelopathic effect of 
  <span class="italic">C. canescens</span> [
  <a rid="B50-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-plants-07-00019">50</a>,
  <a rid="B51-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-plants-07-00019">51</a>]. Ursolic acid is thought to act as a natural detergent by leading water-insoluble monoterpenes to form micelles, rendering them water-soluble, thereby enhancing their ability to leach into rainwater for delivery into the soil [
  <a rid="B42-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-plants-07-00019">42</a>,
  <a rid="B50-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-plants-07-00019">50</a>]. Ursolic acid helps to co-solubilize the allelopathic monoterpenes in water to be more effective [
  <a rid="B52-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-plants-07-00019">52</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
