<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">DHA, as well as arachidonic acid (20:4 n-6, ARA), are two major PUFAs that undergo enzymatic reactions to produce active lipid mediators [
 <xref rid="B1-metabolites-09-00040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. These fatty acids (FAs) can also undergo non-enzymatic reactions through interaction with oxygen radical species from the environment, as well as other oxidative mechanisms. Lipid peroxidation may target PUFAs in the cell membranes, as well as in the free form, releasing 4-hydroxyhexenal (4-HHE) from DHA and 4-hydroxynonanal (4-HNE) from ARA. These alkenal products are readily detected in biological tissues and plasma [
 <xref rid="B20-metabolites-09-00040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. In fact, the increase in production of 4-HNE has been regarded as a marker for oxidative stress in brain injury and stroke [
 <xref rid="B21-metabolites-09-00040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-metabolites-09-00040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>], as well as in infectious brain diseases, such as spirochete-induced encephalitis [
 <xref rid="B23-metabolites-09-00040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-metabolites-09-00040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Depending on conditions and the amount released, 4-HNE can alter cell signaling pathways and undergo cell metabolism by forming adducts with proteins, DNA and lipids [
 <xref rid="B25-metabolites-09-00040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-metabolites-09-00040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-metabolites-09-00040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. Although less is known about 4-HHE, there is evolving evidence that this alkenal compound also possesses properties similar to 4-HNE [
 <xref rid="B28-metabolites-09-00040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. In a study by Nakagawa et al., dietary fish oil given to adult mice was shown to alter levels of the peroxidation products which were correlated with changes in FA composition [
 <xref rid="B29-metabolites-09-00040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. However, information on lipid peroxidation products and FA composition in the brain of offspring mice nursed by mothers fed a DHA diet has not been examined in detail. In this study, pregnant mice were administered a control or a 1% DHA diet throughout gestation and lactation, and the levels of 4-HHE and 4-HNE in different regions of weaning pup brain were determined by liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS), and the FA composition was determined by gas chromatography (GC). In addition, this study also examined the effects of maternal DHA diet on 4-HHE and 4-HNE levels and FA composition in the heart and plasma. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="metabolites-09-00040-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref> outlines the general protocol used in this study.
</p>
