<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ofloxacin, norfloxacin, gatifloxacin, and gemifloxacin (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00438-f003">Figure 3</xref>) are antibiotics containing a β-amino acid, which are useful for treating many bacterial infections and belong to a class of drugs known as quinolone antibiotics [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. 
 <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> is the main cause of bacterial respiratory tract infections in humans. It causes bronchitis to turn to life-threatening pneumonia, bacteremia and meningitis. Ciprofloxacin and other marketed quinolones exhibit only modest activity against it, limiting their use in the case of patients with serious respiratory tract infections. Ofloxacin is effective against Gram-positive and Gram-negative microorganisms, as well as 
 <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic>. The minimum inhibition concentration (MIC) of ofloxacin, at which 90% of isolates are inhibited for 55 isolates of pneumococci, was 4 μg/mL [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Norfloxacin also has a wide spectrum of action; this drug acts against Gram-positive bacteria, i.e., methicillin-susceptible 
 <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic>, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus saprophyticus</italic>; Gram-negative bacteria: 
 <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic>, 
 <italic>H. influenzae,</italic> other 
 <italic>Hemophilus</italic> spp., 
 <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic>, 
 <italic>N. meningitides</italic>, 
 <italic>M. catarrhalis</italic>, 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. Norfloxacin is used to treat different bacterial infections of the prostate and urinary tract (bladder and kidneys), as well as in eye drops. The new fluoroquinolone derivatives, such as Gatifloxacin and Gemifloxacin, have much to offer in terms of bacterial eradication, including activity against such resistant respiratory pathogens as penicillin-resistant, macrolide-resistant, and multidrug-resistant 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>. Gatifloxacin was found to produce a clinical cure rate of 91% versus 88% for levofloxacin and cefuroxime axetil in the treatment of acute exacerbations of chronic bronchitis (ECB). The use of Gemifloxacin in the treatment of ECB was studied by Ball et al. [
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and Wilson et al. [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Gemifloxacin displayed similar clinical success rates to Trovafloxacin (91% vs. 87.6%) and bacterial success rates of 87% [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].
</p>
