<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An adaptogen increases the resistance power against various stresses such as physical, chemical, or biological stress and has a stabilizing effect on the body functions [
 <xref rid="B161-molecules-25-05555" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. 
 <italic>B. crassifolia</italic> can also be considered as a promising phytoadaptogen [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-25-05555" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-molecules-25-05555" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. In a treadmill test, the running-time of rats fed (for 10 days) on 300 mg/kg 
 <italic>Bergenia</italic> black leaves extract was elevated by 30% more than the control group. The running-time was similar to that of rats administered with 5 mL/kg of extract of 
 <italic>Eleutherococcus senticosus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B162-molecules-25-05555" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>]. Similarly, the swimming capacity of the mice treated with infusions prepared from 
 <italic>B. crassifolia</italic> fermented leaves was observed to significantly increase by 2.2-fold, compared to the control. The swimming capacity was increased with a simultaneous increase in glucose utilization and without changing the body weight [
 <xref rid="B163-molecules-25-05555" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>]. A similar study revealed that the endurance capability of rats exposed to a very low temperature of −15 °C (3 h, for 21 days) was significantly ameliorated after treatment with extracts of 
 <italic>Bergenia</italic> black-leaves. Moreover, the floating-time of the rats supplemented with 100 mg/kg extract was considerably augmented after 21 days of treatment, whereas in the other group treated with liposome-encapsulated-extract the swimming-time was increased after seven days of treatment, under extreme circumstances (e.g., hypoxia) [
 <xref rid="B164-molecules-25-05555" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>], because, under hypoxic conditions, the adaptive response of an organism activates mitoK
 <sub>ATP</sub> channel and increases the ATP-dependent potassium transport in mitochondria. Mironova et al. explored the the activation ability of mitoK
 <sub>ATP</sub> channel through water-soluble flavonoid-containing plant preparations of 
 <italic>Bergenia (Bergenia crassifolia)</italic> in a rat model [
 <xref rid="B165-molecules-25-05555" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>].
</p>
