<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many reports and randomized controlled trials have shed light on the relationship between polyphenol-rich diets and prevention against various disorders such as diabetes, cancer, and cardiovascular and inflammation-related conditions [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The antiradical activities of phenolic compounds, including flavonols, flavonoids, coumarins, and tannins among others, are well documented [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. In the current study, we have addressed phenolic, flavonoidic and tannin levels plus antioxidant activities of three 
 <italic>Apiaceae</italic> species known as coriander, parsley, and celery, harvested from the Tinghir region in the southeast of Morocco. The level of such compounds contained in plants is usually different. Parsley exhibited high amounts of polyphenol, followed by celery and, then, coriander. Tang et al. [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and Jung [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] reported high amounts of phenolic compounds in celery (4.640 g GAE.100 g
 <sup>−1</sup>) and parsley (4.231 g GAE.100 g
 <sup>−1</sup>), respectively. Sriti et al. [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] measured different polyphenol contents in coriander seeds (1.555 g GAE.100 g
 <sup>−1</sup>), whole fruit (1.210 g GAE.100 g
 <sup>−1</sup>), and pericarp (0.292 g GAE.100 g
 <sup>−1</sup>). Regarding other classes of polyphenols, Msaada et al. [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] have found lower flavonoid content in Syrian coriander (0.251 g CE.100 g
 <sup>−1</sup>), Egyptian coriander (0.207 g CE.100 g
 <sup>−1</sup>), and Tunisian coriander (0.203 g CE.100 g
 <sup>−1</sup>). In addition, the same author reported lower condensed tannin content in Egyptian coriander (0.016 g CE/100 g DW), Tunisian coriander (0.009 g CE/100 g DW), and Syrian coriander (0.017 g CE/100 g DW). These variations could be related to the phytochemical profile, plant part, genetic diversity, geographical distribution, conditions of cultivation, amount of fertilizers, and extraction procedure [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Flavonoids are the prevailing class of polyphenols, and they have been mentioned as Nutraceuticals and found to possess a huge number of benefits including antioxidant, antimicrobial, antiulcer, antineoplastic, hepatoprotective, and cardioprotective effects [
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The HPLC analysis revealed that the three 
 <italic>Apiaceae</italic> species have different phenolic and flavonoid profiles. p-Coumaric, chlorogenic, caffeic acids, luteolin, and quercetin were the prevailing compounds retained by these extracts. Our findings are in agreement with those reported by Yao et al. [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and Chaowuttikul et al. [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] who have analyzed eleven Chinese and two Thai celery cultivars and found caffeic, ferulic, and p-coumaric acids, as well as luteolin and chlorogenic acid, respectively. However, Hostetler et al. [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] did not detect quercetin and rutin in the parsley extract while luteolin was found at the same amount. Abu-Serie et al. [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] showed that parsley retained all the tested phenolic acids except syringic acid. Moreover, Bilge Ertekin et al. [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] have confirmed that parsley contained caffeic, ferulic, chlorogenic, gallic, and p-coumaric acids. On the other hand, Msaada et al. [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] have demonstrated that chlorogenic, ferulic, p-coumaric, caffeic, vanilic acids, quercetin, rutin, and luteolin are the prevailing compounds of Tunisian and Syrian celery cultivars, whereas the Egyptian cultivar was shown to retain apiginin, quercetin-3-rhamnoside, rosmarinic acid, gallic acid, and trans-hydroxycinnamic acid as the major compounds. Although the current work exhibited similar phenolic profile, the concentration of each compound was different compared to those reported previously. These discrepancies between plants extracts in terms of aerial parts phenolic composition might be ascribed to numerous factors such as genetic variations, cultivation conditions, degree of ripeness, climatic conditions, water availability, plant diseases, harvesting periods, geographic source, storage state, fertilization, soil category, and climatic conditions, as well as the extraction system and analytical method [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
</p>
