<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Antianxiety effects of
 <italic class="italic"> Citrus aurantium</italic> and
 <italic class="italic"> Citrus sinensis</italic> EOs were previously demonstrated through behavioral experiments carried out on laboratory animals. Complex clinical studies considered for this overview suggest that
 <italic class="italic"> Citrus aurantium</italic> or
 <italic class="italic"> Citrus sinensis</italic> EOs, used for anxiolytic therapy of people prevalently in conditions in which stress is dominating, produce positive effects against anxiety. In particular,
 <italic class="italic"> Citrus aurantium</italic> EO aromatherapy reduced anxiety level in the great part of stress conditions studied (subjects affected by chronic myeloid leukemia and preoperative patients) except for a sample of patients subjected to colonoscopy. Exposition to
 <italic class="italic"> Citrus sinensis</italic> EO in clinical studies is shown to be positive in reducing anxiety level in patients waiting for dental treatment as well as in healthy volunteers submitted to an anxiogenic situation. However, a definitive conclusion needs further studies because of the reduced number of studies and the small number of patients for each study. Regarding data reporting of clinical studies with
 <italic class="italic"> Citrus aurantium</italic>, they appear without description of the characteristics of the herbal product and lack qualitative testing. From the methodological point of view, most of the clinical studies show the lack of important items such as treatment allocation conceal and description of double-blind procedure. On the basis of the present overview, we can conclude that the use of
 <italic class="italic"> Citrus aurantium</italic> and
 <italic class="italic"> Citrus sinensis</italic> EOs could be useful to reduce anxiety caused by clinical stress conditions; however, results are impaired by the poor accuracy and methodology applied in clinical studies.
</p>
