<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antitumor activity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The composition of the human diet can influence the risk of cancer and its components can exert positive or negative influences [
  <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">66</a>]. Chemoprevention is the long-term pharmacological control on the risk of cancer. On this matter, several plants, together with their compounds, have been investigated for their antitumor potential [
  <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">66</a>,
  <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">67</a>]. About 70% of the drugs used in cancer treatment derive from natural products [
  <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">68</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As previously described, rosemary is known to exert antioxidant activity thus inhibiting genotoxicity, and protecting from carcinogens or toxic agents [
  <a rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69">69</a>]. However, the pronounced side effects of the therapeutic methods largely prevent its effectiveness, increasing the demand for new approaches in cancer treatment and prevention [
  <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">70</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Polyphenols are compounds capable of modulating cell growth and differentiation and thus interfere with tumor development and progression [
  <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">71</a>]. Since rosemary is rich in phenolic compounds, many studies have been targeted for antitumor activity (about 20%) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0004" href="#F0004">Figure 4</a>) [
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">62</a>,
  <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">72–75</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carnosic acid and carnosol are diterpenes that represent about 5% of 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> dried leaves weight, and these compounds have greater antitumor relevance (35 in 49 studies use these compounds). There has been a large increase in the number of studies regarding the antitumor activity of carnosic acid, carnosol, rosmarinic acid, ursolic acid over the past 5 years (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">Table 3</a>). Breast cancers, melanoma, colon cancer, liver carcinoma and leukemia have been the most studied. In fact, there has been several 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> studies regarding cytotoxicity of carnosol and carnosic acid to human cancer cells (HepG2, COLO 205 and HL-60), breast cancer cells and colon cancer cells [
  <a rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73">73</a>,
  <a rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" href="#B76">76</a>]. These studies reported a decrease of cell viability using carnosic acid in a dose-dependent manner, including resistant tumor cells, suggesting this compound as a complementary antitumoral approach [
  <a rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" href="#B77">77</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span> experiments, carnosic acid and its ester derivatives were found to be effective in preventing gastric lesions in HCl/EtOH-induced gastric lesions model in mice [
  <a rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78">78</a>]. Also, treatment with rosemary extract of 7,12-dimethylbenz[a]anthracene (DMBA)-induced mammary tumorigenesis in rats, suggested a chemopreventative action for experimental mammary tumorigenesis [
  <a rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" href="#B79">79</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">More detailed information concerning 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> and 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span> experimental studies is displayed in the tables in Supplementary material.
 </p>
</sec>
