<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anti-infectious activity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most plants produce antimicrobial secondary metabolites, either from its normal course of growth and development, or in response to stress or pathogen attack. The use of essential oils represents a new way to reduce the proliferation of microorganisms [
  <a rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" href="#B92">92</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span> L. is widely used today as a food preservative and known for its powerful antibacterial activity [
  <a rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" href="#B93">93</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The increasing use of antibiotics in medicine, agriculture and livestock has largely contributed to the increase of multiple drug resistant microorganisms [
  <a rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" href="#B94">94</a>]. Antimicrobial resistance is a global public health concern, and researchers have been increasingly engaging in this area in demand for new effective antimicrobial bioactives [
  <a rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" href="#B94">94</a>,
  <a rid="B95" ref-type="bibr" href="#B95">95</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Besides the antibacterial properties, essential oils also have insecticidal, antiparasitic and antifungal activities, which are important for the control of human diseases of microbial origin [
  <a rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" href="#B96">96</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since the 1990s until 2014, the essential oil of rosemary has demonstrated the highest antimicrobial activity, with 65% of anti-infectious activity studies. The antimicrobial activity of the essential oil was superior, when compared with the single compounds 1,8-cineole and α-pinene [
  <a rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" href="#B97">97</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> studies, concerning MICs, minimal bactericidal concentration and time-kill dynamic processes, have reported that there is a possible synergistic effect between the antimicrobial compounds in essential oil [
  <a rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" href="#B96">96</a>,
  <a rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" href="#B98">98</a>]. These studies were performed testing carnosic acid, carnosol, rosmarinic acid, oleanolic acid, ursolic acid and essential oil, against Gram-positive bacteria (
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Bacillus subtilis</span>), three Gram-negative bacteria (
  <span class="italic">Proteus vulgaris</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span>) and two fungi (
  <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus niger</span>). All reported pronounced antibacterial and antifungal activity (20; 227; 87; 136; 97; 93). It was also found that carnosic acid showed antiviral activity against human respiratory syncytial virus [
  <a rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" href="#B99">99</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">More detailed information concerning 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> experimental studies is displayed in the tables in Supplementary material.
 </p>
</sec>
