<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="S0014" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In recent years, much effort has been devoted to the development of PBMs [
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>], proposing them as natural drugs in many pathological conditions including anti-inflammatory, analgesic, antioxidant, antitumor, anti-infectious, CNS and endocrine system activities.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phytotherapy is a major contributor to the discovery of new, safer and effective PBMs, as well as new drugs, knowing that what pharmaceutical chemistry has sought desperately, nature has in large quantities [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the development of high-accuracy analytical methods and the advances of molecular biology and genetics, it is now possible to isolate plant compounds that exist in extremely small quantities [
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>]. With these improvements, it is now possible to study their chemical structure and therapeutic potential, and thus, modify the molecule for producing new, more selective therapeutic agents [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>,
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>,
  <a rid="B119" ref-type="bibr" href="#B119">119</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This work performed an updated review on 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> L., allowing us to emphasize the current state of the art, on studies and investigations, pointing out the awareness of the pharmacological activities related to the constituents of this plant. Since 1990s, there has been an increasing therapeutic interest in rosemary, from both 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> and 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span> studies on several biological activities, such as antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, analgesic, etc., previously described in ethnobotanicals studies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the reviewed literature, it can be concluded that the most important constituents of 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> L., which are pharmacologically active and the main target of scientific studies, are carnosic acid, carnosol, rosmarinic acid and the essential oil. Thus, these natural drugs can be proposed for preclinical and clinical studies in different diseases and pathological conditions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> has a promising future in the medical field, especially in the treatment and prevention of various cancers, infectious diseases and increasingly emerging diseases such as depression, Alzheimer's and Parkinson's diseases. In fact, there are 80 clinical studies on 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span>, from which 32 are still open studies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These studies regarding herbal remedies should be taken into more consideration since the safety and efficacy of many herbal medicines are still problematic, with inadequate or inconsistent methods. Considering this, more reliable trials are needed in the future to evaluate the 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> active phytocompounds safety and efficacy, in treating different pathological conditions.
 </p>
</sec>
