<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saudi J Med Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Saudi J Med Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SJMMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Saudi Journal of Medicine &#x00026; Medical Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1658-631X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2321-4856</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer - Medknow</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7485663</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SJMMS-8-201</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/sjmms.sjmms_276_19</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antibacterial Activity of <italic>Ritchiea albersii</italic> Gilg and <italic>Cynoglossum amplifolium</italic> Leaves Extracts against Selected Bacteria</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Engiso</surname><given-names>Hizkel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Worku</surname><given-names>Teshale</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nureye</surname><given-names>Dejen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salahaddin</surname><given-names>Mohammed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Woldeselassie</surname><given-names>Workineh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hambisa</surname><given-names>Solomon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sharief</surname><given-names>Nymathullah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, School of Pharmacy, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, Hawassa University, Hawassa, Ethiopia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Medical Laboratory, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, Mizan-Tepi University (Aman Campus), Mizan-Aman, Ethiopia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Pharmacy, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, Mizan-Tepi University (Aman Campus), Mizan-Aman, Ethiopia</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Biomolecular Sciences, Pharmacology Division, University of Mississippi, Oxford, Mississippi, United States of America</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Biochemistry and Biotechnology, Minerva Degree College, East Godavari District, Andhra Pradesh, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence: </bold> Mr. Dejen Nureye, Department of Pharmacy, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, Mizan-Tepi University (Aman Campus), P.O. Box 260, Mizan-Aman, Ethiopia. E-mail: <email xlink:href="dejenureye@gmail.com">dejenureye@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Sep-Dec</season><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>03</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2020 Saudi Journal of Medicine &#x00026; Medical Sciences</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0"><license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background:</title><p>The increase in antimicrobial resistance worldwide has necessitated the search for alternative therapeutic agents. The leaf extracts of <italic>Ritchiea albersii</italic> and <italic>Cynoglossum amplifolium</italic> have been used as traditional medicine for the management of eye, ear and wound infections in Ethiopia.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Objective:</title><p>The objective of the study was to evaluate the antibacterial activity of <italic>R. albersii</italic> and <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> against three common bacteria.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>In this experimental study, the antimicrobial properties of 80% methanol, chloroform and acetone extracts of <italic>R. albersii</italic> and <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> were evaluated against two Gram-positive bacteria (<italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 25923 and <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> ATCC 49619) and one Gram-negative bacterium (<italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC 25922) using the agar-well diffusion method. Ciprofloxacin 0.05 mg/disc was used as a positive control. Furthermore, a preliminary phytochemical study was carried out.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Results:</title><p>The zones of inhibition shown by all extracts of the two plants against the tested bacteria were significantly lesser (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) than the standard drug. <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic> were the most susceptible strains for most extracts studied. The acetone extract of <italic>R. albersii</italic> exhibited a higher inhibitory effect (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) against <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> (16 mm) and <italic>E. coli</italic> (19 mm) compared with its methanol extract. The chloroform extract of <italic>R. albersii</italic> was more effective than its methanol extract (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) against all tested bacteria. The acetone extract of <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> displayed a higher inhibitory effect (20 mm) against <italic>E. coli</italic> than its methanol and chloroform extracts.</p></sec><sec id="st5"><title>Conclusions:</title><p>The leaf extracts of <italic>R. albersii</italic> and <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> exhibited broad-spectrum antimicrobial activity, highlighting their potential as phytotherapeutic drugs in preventing and treating infections caused by <italic>S. aureus</italic>, <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic>. Further investigations for isolating specific compounds and elucidating mechanisms are required to address the need for novel antibacterial drugs.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Antibacterial activity</kwd><kwd><italic>Cynoglossum amplifolium</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Escherichia coli</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Ritchiea albersii</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Infectious diseases are a leading cause of mortality worldwide, particularly in low-income countries.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] According to the World Health Organization, in 2016, lower respiratory infections, diarrheal diseases and tuberculosis accounted for 3 million, 1.4 million and 1.3 million deaths, respectively, making them three of the top ten causes of deaths worldwide.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</p><p>Antimicrobials remain valuable resources for treating and preventing infectious disease despite the global increase in antimicrobial resistance (AMR).[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] However, AMR is a key issue in public health and has increased the rates of morbidity, mortality and socioeconomic costs.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] The increase in multi-drug resistant (MDR) pathogenic bacteria is limiting the choices of effective antibacterial treatment, as this phenomenon has not been paralleled by the development of new antibiotics.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] Consequently, by the year 2050, an increase in AMR is estimated to annually put 10,000,000 lives at risk.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] Hence, there is an urgent need for newer antibacterial agents with novel mechanisms of action.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] Some areas for discovering such antibacterials are natural products of plant origin and antimicrobial peptides.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</p><p>In Ethiopia, about 90% of the population is reliant on traditional remedies for the management of diseases.[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] Studies conducted on numerous traditionally used ethnomedical plants of Ethiopia have shown antibacterial activities including <italic>Nuxia congesta</italic>,[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] <italic>Zehneria scabra</italic>, <italic>Ricinus communis</italic>,[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] <italic>Rhamnus prinoides</italic>,[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] <italic>Justicia schimpriana</italic>,[<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] <italic>Jasminium abyssinicum</italic>, <italic>Myrsine africana</italic>, <italic>Foeniculum vulgare</italic>,[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] <italic>Verbasicum sinaticum</italic>, <italic>Calpurnia aurea</italic>, <italic>Salvia schimperi</italic>, <italic>Hypericum revolutum</italic>, <italic>Pterolobium stellatum</italic>,[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] <italic>Datura stramonium</italic>, <italic>Croton macrostachyus</italic> and <italic>Acokanthera schimperi</italic>.[<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</p><p><italic>Ritchiea albersii</italic> Gilg (<italic>Capparidaceae</italic>) is a small tree with a short thick trunk (11 m high). In Ethiopia, its various parts are used in traditional medicine for the treatment of meningitis, wound, cataract, respiratory tract problems and tonsillitis. <italic>Cynoglossum amplifolium</italic> (Boraginaceae) is a perennial herb or subshrub that is 0.3&#x02013;1.8 m tall and has a thick tuberous root of up to 45 cm and large leaves and tall stems. In Ethiopia, <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> is prescribed by traditional medicine practitioners to treat ear, eye and wound infections.[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref><xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref><xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] Despite their use as traditional medicines, no antibacterial studies of <italic>R. albersii</italic> and <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> have been conducted to date. Therefore, the aim of this study was to screen the antibacterial activities of 80% methanol, chloroform and acetone crude extracts of <italic>R. albersii</italic> and <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> leaves against <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, which are MDR and common causes of ear and wound infections.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Collection of plant material</title><p>For this experimental study, fresh leaves of <italic>R. albersii</italic> and <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> were collected in December 2017 from its natural habitat in Bench district, namely Temenja Yaxi and Andekel Kebele, Southwest Ethiopia, about 574 km from Addis Ababa. The leaves were covered in plastic sheet during transportation. The collected plants were then identified and authenticated as <italic>R. albersii</italic> and <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> by a taxonomist at the National Herbarium, College of Natural and Computational Sciences, Addis Ababa University, where voucher specimens (no. HE 001 and HE 002, respectively) were deposited for future reference.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Preparation of plant extract</title><p>Fresh leaves of the plants were thoroughly washed by tap water and cleaned with gauze to remove dirt and soil. These samples were then air-dried under the shade and crushed into coarse powder using sterile pestle and mortar. Subsequently, 231 g powder of <italic>R. albersii</italic> and 210 g powder of <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> were divided into three portions and extracted by cold maceration technique with 80% methanol (800 mL), acetone (1000 mL) and chloroform (1000 mL) solution in an Erlenmeyer flask for 3 consecutive days at room temperature to get the crude hydroalcoholic, acetone and chloroform extract, respectively. The same volume of solvent was used for the successive extraction of the residues. The extraction process was facilitated using a mechanical shaker (Bibby Scientific Limited, Stone Staffordshire, UK) at 120 revolutions per minute. The resulting crude extracts were separated from the marc with gauze and then filtered by Whatman filter paper Grade-1 using suction twice by the addition of fresh solvent to acquire the maximum yield. The filtrates were combined and concentrated by Rotary evaporator (Buchi Rotavapor R-200, Flawil, Switzerland) under reduced pressure. All extracts were then dried and further concentrated using a dry oven (Leaders Engineering, Hastings, UK). Finally, the extracts were transferred into an amber glass bottle and kept at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C until use. The respective percentage yield of 80% methanol, acetone and chloroform of <italic>R. albersii</italic> was 15.9%, 16.3% and 14.8% and of <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> was 16%, 14.9% and 14.6%, respectively. All the extracts were reconstituted with dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO) to obtain 100 mg/mL concentrations.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Phytochemical screening</title><p>Each crude extract obtained by different solvent extractions was separately tested using standard procedures for the presence of various phytoconstituents, namely alkaloids, flavonoids, saponins, terpenoids, tannins and phenolic compounds.[<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Test organisms</title><p>Standard bacterial strains of two Gram-positive bacteria (<italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> ATCC 49619 and <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC 25923) and one Gram-negative bacterium (<italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC 25922) were obtained from Ethiopian Public Health Institute and used in this study. They were preserved at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C until the preparation of inoculums. Each bacterial strain was activated by streaking on culture media aseptically. For <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC 25923 and <italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC 25922, nutrient agar was used, and for <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> ATCC 49619, 5% sheep blood agar was used. The culture media inoculated with <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> was enclosed in a candle jar to supply 5%&#x02013;10% of carbon dioxide. All the inoculated strains were incubated for 24 h at 37&#x000b0;C in an incubator. Then, the inoculum of each bacterium was prepared by taking 3&#x02013;5 colonies and transferring them to tubes containing 5 ml of normal saline. The immersed colonies of bacteria were mixed gently to form a homogeneous suspension until the turbidity of the suspension became attuned to 0.5 McFarland standards (1.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mL).[<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Antibacterial activity assay</title><p>A sterile cotton swab was implemented to remove surplus suspension by gentle rotation of the swab against the surface of the tube. It was then used to dispense the bacteria evenly over the whole surface of the Mueller&#x02013;Hinton Agar (MHA). For <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>, MHA supplemented with sheep blood (5%) was used. The agar well diffusion method, which is equivalent to Kirby&#x02013;Bauer disc-diffusion method, was used to assess the antibacterial effects of all extracts extracted from the study plants, as described previously.[<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] Wells of 6-mm diameter were formed on the inoculated agar media with a sterile cork borer. Around 100 &#x003bc;L of each extract solution (100 mg/ml) was added into each well. Ciprofloxacin 0.05 mg/disc was used as a positive control. The solvent (DMSO) used for the reconstitution of each extract was used as a negative control. The plates were then incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 18 h. Antibacterial activity was interpreted by measuring the diameter of clear inhibition zones surrounding the wells according to the standards of Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute, 2015.[<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] Each extract was examined in triplicate to ensure the quality and the mean value was calculated.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data were organized, edited and analyzed using SPSS version 22 for Windows (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA). The results of the antibacterial activity were expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error of mean. Statistical significance was determined by a one-way analysis of variance followed by the Tukey <italic>post hoc</italic> test to compare the inhibition zone against the selected bacteria between control and treatment groups. <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered statistically significant at a 95% confidence interval.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Phytochemical screening</title><p>The qualitative phytochemical screening of the crude methanol and chloroform leave extracts of <italic>R. albersii</italic> revealed the presence of all the tested phytoconstituents except saponins [<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>]. However, only alkaloids and phenols were detected in the acetone extract. Similarly, the methanol extract of <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> comprised all of the tested constituents except terpenoids, while its chloroform extract contained flavonoids, tannins, phenols and terpenoids and the acetone extract comprised flavonoids, tannins and saponins.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Phytochemical constituent of <italic>Ritchiea albersii</italic> and <italic>Cynoglossum amplifolium</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Constituents</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><italic>Ritchiea albersii</italic></th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><italic>Cynoglossum amplifolium</italic></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methanol extract</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroform extract</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetone extract</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methanol extract</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroform extract</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetone extract</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkaloids</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavonoids</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tannins</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saponins</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenols</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpenoids</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>+: Trace amount; &#x02212;: Absent; ++: High amount</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Screening of antibacterial activity</title><p>The antibacterial activities of three solvent extracts from <italic>R. albersii</italic> and <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> against each bacterium are tabulated in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The inhibition zones shown by all extracts of both the plants against each bacterial species were significantly lesser (<italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.001) than the positive control [<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>]. From <italic>R. albersii</italic> test groups, the chloroform extract demonstrated a greater inhibition zone against <italic>E. coli</italic> (21.67 mm) and <italic>S. aureus</italic> (19.67 mm). For the acetone extract, <italic>E. coli</italic> was the most susceptible strain with a growth inhibition of 19 mm followed by <italic>S. aureus</italic> (18 mm). There were no significant differences between the inhibition sizes by chloroform and acetone extracts. Overall, the methanol extract of <italic>R. albersii</italic> exhibited a significantly lower inhibitory effect than acetone against <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic> (<italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.001) and than chloroform against <italic>S. aureus</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.002), <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.014) and <italic>E. coli</italic> (<italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.001).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Inhibition zone diameter of extracts from leaves of <italic>Ritchiea albersii</italic> and <italic>Cynoglossum amplifolium</italic> against three pathogenic bacteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test groups</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (ATCC 25923)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Staphylococcus pneumoniae</italic> (ATCC 49619)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (ATCC 25922)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.33&#x000b1;1.86<sup>a,c</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.33&#x000b1;1.67<sup>a,c,d</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.00&#x000b1;0.58<sup>a,c,d</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.67&#x000b1;0.88<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.00&#x000b1;1.00<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67&#x000b1;1.76<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.00&#x000b1;1.16<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.00&#x000b1;0.00<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.00&#x000b1;0.58<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.33&#x000b1;0.88<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.00&#x000b1;1.00<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.00&#x000b1;0.00<sup>a,g</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.33&#x000b1;0.88<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.67&#x000b1;1.67<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.00&#x000b1;0.58<sup>a,g</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.67&#x000b1;1.33<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.33&#x000b1;0.88<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00&#x000b1;1.00<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.00&#x000b1;0.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.00&#x000b1;0.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.00&#x000b1;0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are expressed as mean&#x000b1;SEM (<italic>n</italic>=3). <sup>a</sup>As compared to PC; <sup>b</sup>As compared to MRA; <sup>c</sup>As compared to CRA; <sup>d</sup>As compared to ARA; <sup>e</sup>As compared to MCA; <sup>f</sup>As compared to CCA; <sup>g</sup>As compared to ACA; <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05. The NC has shown no antibacterial activity. MRA &#x02013; Methanol extract of <italic>Ritichea albersii</italic>; CRA &#x02013; Chloroform extract of <italic>Ritichea albersii</italic>; ARA &#x02013; Acetone extract of <italic>Ritichea</italic>
<italic>Albersii</italic>; MCA &#x02013; Methanolic extract of <italic>Cynoglossum amplifolium</italic>; CCA &#x02013; Chloroform extract of <italic>Cynoglossum amplifolium</italic>; ACA &#x02013; Acetone extract of <italic>Cynoglossum amplifolium</italic>; PC &#x02013; Positive control; NC &#x02013; Negative control; SEM &#x02013; Standard error of mean</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>From <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> extract groups, the largest area of inhibition was attained by the acetone extract against <italic>E. coli</italic> (20 mm) followed by methanol extract against <italic>S. aureus</italic> (19.33 mm). All of its extracts showed an inhibitory effect against <italic>S. aureus</italic> and <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>, with no significant differences between them. However, the methanol and chloroform extracts had a significantly smaller zone of growth inhibition (<italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.001) against <italic>E. coli</italic> as compared with the acetone extract [<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>].</p><p>In terms of comparison across the various extracts, it was found that all the tested extracts were lesser effective against <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> than <italic>S. aureus</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic>, except the chloroform extract of <italic>C. amplifolium</italic>. The methanol extracts of both the plants exhibited the same inhibition diameter (15 mm) against <italic>E. coli</italic>, but the inhibition diameter of <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> methanol extract was greater against <italic>S. aureus</italic> compared with that of <italic>R. albersii</italic> (19.33 mm vs. 16.33 mm, respectively). Against <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>, the chloroform extract of <italic>R. albersii</italic> and the methanol extract of <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> had the same inhibition diameter (14 mm). Of all the extracts, the chloroform extract of <italic>R. albersii</italic> had the highest inhibition diameter (21.67 mm against <italic>E. coli</italic>, followed by 19.67 mm against <italic>S. aureus</italic>). In terms of the acetone extracts, the zones of inhibitions of both the extracts against the Gram-positive bacteria were almost identical but differed by about 1 mm against the Gram-negative bacteria.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>An increase in AMR has resulted in medicinal plants gaining importance for their therapeutic potential in producing bioactive substances that inhibit the growth of microbes. The preliminary results of this study, therefore, justify the use of such plants in the complementary and alternative medicine system against some common microbes of public health importance as well as highlight potential sources for developing effective antimicrobial agents in the future.[<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</p><p>Organic solvents were used in this study for extraction, as these have been reported to result in higher antibacterial activity compared with aqueous extract.[<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] Acetone has been reported to be highly effective for extraction, as it dissolves a wide range of active compounds from plants including both hydrophilic and hydrophobic components.[<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref><xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] In addition, the use of organic solvent as an extractant does not confer any negative effect on the bioactivity against the bacteria tested.[<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</p><p>To the best of the authors' knowledge, this is the first study on the antibacterial activity and phytoconstituents of <italic>R. albersii</italic> and <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> extracts. Here, the qualitative phytochemical analysis of the extracts of both plants verified the existence of different secondary metabolites [<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>], which are well known to produce antimicrobial effects in other plants.[<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref><xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] Thus, the antibacterial activity of both the plants in this study may be associated with the availability of these chemicals that act synergistically or individually.</p><p>Despite showing a zone of inhibition, the extracts of these plants did not produce a significant growth inhibition as compared with the standard control. The use of crude extracts of plants can limit their antibacterial potency.[<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] In the current study, a single dose of the crude extract was used, which may have resulted in a lower concentration of the active components. Therefore, future studies should be conducted with multiple doses of the extracts with increasing concentrations to determine its effectiveness compared with the standard control.</p><p>Among the extracts of <italic>R. albersii</italic> leaves, a maximum zone of inhibition against <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic> was observed with the chloroform extract [<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>]. This may be because the chloroform extract had a greater amount of the active component(s) such as flavonoids and, particularly, tannins than that in the 80% methanol extract; these components were absent or present in an undetectable amount within acetone extract [<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>]. Tannins enhance the therapeutic efficacy, as they are able to (a) bind proteins and thus inhibit cell protein synthesis, (b) form a complex with the microorganism membrane because of its astringent properties and (c) deprive iron through precipitation and/or its effect on bacterial metabolism through inhibition of oxidative phosphorylation.[<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref><xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] Moreover, the presence of terpenoids in chloroform extract, which was absent in the methanol and acetone extracts, may have directly/indirectly enhanced its growth inhibitory effects against the studied bacteria.</p><p>The acetone extract of <italic>R. albersii</italic> had only slightly lower inhibition against <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains as compared with the chloroform extract. In the qualitative test, this acetone extract was found to have high alkaloid contents and phenols, which have antimicrobial properties[<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] and thus may have contributed to the effectiveness against these strains. The comparable antibacterial effects of the acetone and chloroform extracts against all tested bacteria suggest that medium polar and nonpolar compounds of <italic>R. albersii</italic> are likely responsible for its bioactivity, which is similar to the findings of Teka <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] The methanol extract had lesser activity on most tested bacteria compared with that of acetone and chloroform extracts, indicating that the active components that inhibit the growth of the studied bacteria might be dissolved better in acetone and chloroform than in 80% methanol. Nonetheless, the zone of inhibition by the 80% methanol extracts of both plants against <italic>E. coli</italic> is similar to that of the same solvent extract of <italic>P. stellatum</italic>,[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], <italic>Ceterach officinarum</italic> DC and <italic>Echinophora tenuifolia</italic> L. subsp. sibthorpiana (Guss) Tutin.[<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</p><p>In terms of the extracts of <italic>C. amplifolium</italic>, the acetone extract had significantly higher efficacy against <italic>E. coli</italic> than the 80% methanol and chloroform extracts [<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>]. The acetone extract consisted of saponins, which was absent in the chloroform extract and may be the differentiating factor for this higher efficacy. This also justifies the localization of active compounds in acetone extract, as 80% methanol and chloroform extract exhibit lesser effect on this microorganism. Against <italic>S. aureus</italic> and <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>, all crude extracts of <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> showed comparable effects. This may describe the relativity of active phytoconstituent composition among those extracts and/or may be because these are Gram-positive bacteria.</p><p>All the extracts of this study were found to inhibit growth in all three studied bacteria. This indicates that these extracts contain compounds with broad-spectrum antibacterial activity, highlighting their potential as alternatives to antibiotics. In terms of the mechanism, the active ingredients in the extracts may affect the overall impermeability and integrity of the bacterial cell wall.[<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref><xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] Flavonoids, which are a diverse group of secondary metabolites that often present in relatively high concentrations in plants,[<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref><xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] have been shown to have effective antimicrobial phytochemicals against various disease-causing organisms (i.e., have a wide range of bioactivities). This biological activity is because of their ability to form a complex with the bacterial cell wall and with extracellular and soluble proteins. Similarly, alkaloids and phenols, which occurred in most extracts in this study, have been recognized to have a growth suppression tendency against various Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria.[<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref><xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]</p><p>The bioactivity of all extracts against all studied bacteria varied except for the 80% methanol extracts of both the plants against <italic>E. coli</italic> and the chloroform extract of <italic>R. albersii</italic> and 80% methanol extract of <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> against <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> [<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>]. These dissimilarities in activity could be linked to the disparity in solvent used for extraction purpose,[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] in addition to phytochemical variations in composition and/or concentration in the respective plant extracts. The sensitivity of microorganisms to chemotherapeutic compounds can change even in different strains of a single bacterial species. Like this study, the extract of various plants inhibited the growth of selected microorganisms at different ratios in another study. The phytochemicals and their concentrations differ across plants, which explains the difference in antimicrobial effect.[<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] On the other hand, the extract from the same plant species has shown variable activity against different bacterial species, presumably because of the difference in sensitivity of the microorganisms to specific active ingredients in a plant.[<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</p><p>It is interesting to note that <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> is less susceptible than <italic>S. aureus</italic> to different extracts of the respective plants despite both microbes being Gram-positive, thereby suggesting that genetic variations between the two bacteria[<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] could be a factor making <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> more resistant to the extracts. Furthermore, this might be because of the more complex nature of cell wall of <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> compared with that of <italic>S. aureus</italic>.</p><p>Although the <italic>in vitro</italic> finding of this study suggests that the extracts from <italic>R. albersii</italic> and <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> are effective against the selected bacterial species, this may not necessarily be the same in <italic>in vivo</italic> studies, as seen in previous studies.[<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] Therefore, more detailed <italic>in vitro</italic> studies, including determination of minimum inhibitory concentration and minimum bactericidal concentration, and <italic>in vivo</italic> investigation of these medicinal plants should be carried out.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec1-5"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>The preliminary findings of this study revealed that because the extracts of <italic>R. albersii</italic> and <italic>C. amplifolium</italic> have a wide spectrum of activity against selected bacteria, they may have potential beyond their current use in ethnomedicine. However, further detailed investigation and isolation of compounds from the extracts should be done so enable more precise testing for the development of newer and safer antibacterial agents. This work can be a basis for elucidation of the actual mechanism of action of these plants.</p><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Peer review</title><p>This article was peer-reviewed by five independent and anonymous reviewers.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>The research was funded by the Department of Pharmacy, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, Mizan&#x02013;Tepi University, Research Grant no. HSR/079/06.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-11" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The financial support of Mizan&#x02013;Tepi University is gratefully acknowledged.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Bayer College of Medicine</collab><source>Introduction to Infectious Diseases</source><year>2019</year><date-in-citation>Last accessed on 2019 Nov 10</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://wwwbcmedu/departments/molecular-virology-and-microbiology/emerging-infections-and-biodefense/">https://wwwbcmedu/departments/molecular-virology-and-microbiology/emerging-infections-and-biodefense/</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>World Health Organization</collab><source>The top 10 Causes of Death</source><year>2018</year><date-in-citation>Last accessed on 2019 Nov 10</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://wwwwhoint/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/the-top-10-causes-of-deathBacktotop">https://wwwwhoint/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/the-top-10-causes-of-deathBack to top</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of antimicrobial stewardship to the English National Health Service</article-title><source>Infect Drug Resist</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24936131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic review and meta-analysis of the effectiveness and safety of tigecycline for treatment of infectious disease</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2011</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1162</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21173186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cassir</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolain</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brouqui</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new strategy to fight antimicrobial resistance: The revival of old antibiotics</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>551</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25368610</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Neill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Tackling Drug-Resistant Infections Globally: Final Report and Recommendations (Review on Antimicro-bial Resistance)</source><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Alb&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of selected Peruvian medicinal plants</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2003</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12963143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schillaci</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Span&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrino</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Montalbano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barraja</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmaceutical approaches to target antibiotic resistance mechanisms</article-title><source>J Med Chem</source><year>2017</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>8268</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28594170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The traditional medicine and modern medicine from natural products</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>559</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haney</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peptide design for antimicrobial and immunomodulatory applications</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>2013</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>572</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23553602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tailhades</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien-Simpson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Separovic</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Otvos</surname><given-names>L</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proline-rich antimicrobial peptides: Potential therapeutics against antibiotic-resistant bacteria</article-title><source>Amino Acids</source><year>2014</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>2287</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25141976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><source>Traditional Medicines: Global Situation, Issues and Challenges The World Medicines Situation 2011</source><year>2011</year><edition>3rd ed</edition><publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alemu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mengistu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasisa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenubih</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the antibacterial activity and phytochemical screening of nuxia congesta leaf in Gondar, Northern Ethiopia</article-title><source>J Vet Sci Technol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>542</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moges</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Abew</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahile</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> antibacterial activity of leaf extracts of Zehneria scabra and Ricinus communis against <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and methicillin resistance <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Asian Pac J Trop Biomed</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>816</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molla</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nedi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tadesse</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Alemayehu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibeshi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the <italic>in vitro</italic> antibacterial activity of the solvent fractions of the leaves of Rhamnus prinoides L'Herit (Rhamnaceae) against pathogenic bacteria</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>287</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27527076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tesfaye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Evaluation of <italic>In-vitro</italic> Antibacterial and Antifungal Activities of Crude Extract and Solvent Fractions of the Leaves of <italic>Justicia schimperiana</italic> Hochst Ex Nees (Acanthaceae) [MSc dissertation]</source><year>2017</year><publisher-loc>Ethiopia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Addis Ababa University</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habtamu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Eguale</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wubete</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> antimicrobial activity of selected Ethiopian medicinal plants against some bacteria of veterinary importance</article-title><source>Afr J Microbiol Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1230</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adugna</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Terefe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kebede</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Keskes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential <italic>In vitro</italic> anti-bacterial action of selected medicinal plants against <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and three <italic>Salmonella</italic> species</article-title><source>Intl J Microbiol Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Giday</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Animut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Seid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activities of selected medicinal plants in traditional treatment of human wounds in Ethiopia</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Trop Biomed</source><year>2011</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23569795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giday</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Asfaw</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Woldu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Teklehaymanot</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plant knowledge of the Bench ethnic group of Ethiopia: An ethnobotanical investigation</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>34</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19912633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giday</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Asfaw</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Woldu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants of the Meinit ethnic group of Ethiopia: An ethnobotanical study</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2009</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19454310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giday</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Asfaw</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Woldu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal study of plants used by Sheko ethnic group of Ethiopia</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2010</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20674734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sofowora</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Medicinal Plants and Traditional Medicine in Africa Ibadan</source><year>1993</year><publisher-loc>Nigeria</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Spectrum Books Ltd</publisher-name><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>289</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Njoku</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Obi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical constituents of some selected medicinal plants</article-title><source>Afr J Pure Appl Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>33</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trease</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><source>Pharmacognosy</source><year>1989</year><edition>13th ed</edition><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>BailliereTindall</publisher-name><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>80</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>CLSI</collab><source>Methods for Dilution Antimicrobial Susceptibility Tests for Bacteria that Grow Aerobically; Approved Standard</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><edition>9th ed</edition><publisher-loc>USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CLSI</publisher-name><fpage>88</fpage><comment>M07-A10 document</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andualem</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Umar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Getnet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tekewe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alemayehu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kebede</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial and phytochemical screening of methanol extracts of three medicinal plants in Ethiopia</article-title><source>Advan Biol Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghasemzadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawa</surname><given-names>ZE</given-names></name><name><surname>Asmah</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadegh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Secondary metabolites constituents and antioxidant, anticancer and antibacterial activities of Etlingera elatior (Jack) RM Sm grown in different locations of Malaysia</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>335</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26399961</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geyid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Debella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Makonnen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Aberra</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Teka</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Screening of some medicinal plants of Ethiopia for their anti-microbial properties and chemical profiles</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2005</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15740876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parekh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jadeja</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of aqueous and methanol extracts of some medicinal plants for potential antibacterial activity</article-title><source>Turk J Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Downey</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanlin</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of ethanol and acetone mixtures for extraction of condensed tannin from grape skin</article-title><source>S Afr J Enol Vitic</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eloff</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Which extractant should be used for the screening and isolation of antimicrobial components from plants?</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>1998</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9533426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaushik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Laboratory evaluation of crude extracts of Cinnamomum tamala for potential antibacterial activity</article-title><source>Electron J Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nema</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemistry of medicinal plants</article-title><source>J Pharm Phytochem</source><year>2013</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>82</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Khandelwal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chopra</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review on scientific technologies in practice to innovate plant based molecules and to improve herbal drug quality to overcome health problems</article-title><source>J Appl Nat Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>81</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marasini</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Baral</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Aryal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghimire</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Neupane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of antibacterial activity of some traditionally used medicinal plants against human pathogenic bacteria</article-title><source>Biomed Res Int</source><year>2015</year><volume>2015</volume><fpage>265425</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25738151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tannins and human health: A review</article-title><source>Critical Rev Food Sci Nutr</source><year>1998</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9759559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scalbert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial properties of tannins</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>1991</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>38, 75</fpage><lpage>83</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Othman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sleiman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Massih</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial Activity of Polyphenols and Alkaloids in Middle Eastern Plants</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>911</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31156565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rondevaldova</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Asfaw</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Demissew</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Damme</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokoska</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> antimicrobial activity of plants used in traditional medicine in Gurage and Silti Zones, south central Ethiopia</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>286</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26283630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erecevit</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x00131;rba&#x001e7;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of some plant species used for the medical purpose in Turkey</article-title><source>J Phytopharmacol</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermaak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Viljoen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cape aloes-a review of the phytochemistry, pharmacology and commercialisation of Aloe ferox</article-title><source>Phytochem Lett</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rates</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants as source of drugs</article-title><source>Toxicon</source><year>2001</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11072038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ionela</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ion</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant products as antimicrobial agents</article-title><source>Sec&#x00163;unea Genetic&#x00103; Biol Molec</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manandhar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Luitel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahal</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> antimicrobial activity of some medicinal plants against human pathogenic bacteria</article-title><source>J Trop Med</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khameneh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Iranshahy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Soheili</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazly Bazzaz</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review on plant antimicrobials: A mechanistic viewpoint</article-title><source>Antimicrob Resist Infect Control</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>118</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31346459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanage</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bessen</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Feil</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population biology of Gram-positive pathogens: High-risk clones for dissemination of antibiotic resistance</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source><year>2011</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>872</fpage><lpage>900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21658083</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>