<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lipid nanoparticle characterization</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Physical–chemical properties</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Particle size (PS) and polydispersity index (PI) of all developed nanosystems were assessed at 25°C by photon correlation spectroscopy (PCS) at an angle of 90° (Beckman Coulter N5, Instrumentation Laboratory, Milan, Italy) after suitable dilution of samples with bidistilled and filtered water (0.22 µm, HA Millipore, Merck KGaA, Darmstadt, Germany).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Physical stability of nanoparticles was evaluated up to 90 days of storage at 2–8°C.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Zeta potential of the more promising formulation was measured at 25°C (Nano ZSP, Malvern Instruments, Alfatest, Rome, Italy).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These nanosystems were also analyzed by a transmission electron microscope (TEM; Jeol JEM-1200 EX II, Basiglio, Milan, Italy) equipped with a TEM CCD camera (Mega View III, Jeol, Basiglio, Italy), after sample deposition on copper grids (Formavar/Carbon 300 mesh, Agar Scientific, Assing, Rome, Italy).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Eucalyptus EO assay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Loading of eucalyptus EO in lipid carriers was determined by means of head space solid phase microextraction (HSSPME) coupled with gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) (according to eucalyptus oil – 07/2010:0390, Eur Ph. 9.0 Ed monograph). The following HSSPME experimental parameters were used: sample amount, 100 µL; water addition, 10 mL; fiber polydimethylsiloxane (100 µm); extraction temperature, 40°C; extraction time, 30 min; desorption temperature, 280°C; desorption time, 5 min.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One hundred-microliter aliquots of eucalyptus EO extracted from lipid nanoparticles and eucalyptus EO dispersed in an aqueous lecithin solution at the same concentration of lipid nanoparticles were separately injected.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC-MS analysis was effected on a Thermo Scientific DSQII single quadrupole GC-MS system (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Milan, Italy) (Xcalibur MS Software Version 2.1) equipped with a Restek Rtx-5 MS capillary column (30 m, 0.25 mm i.d., 0.25 µm film thickness), according to the following temperature program: 4 min at 60°C, then 10°C/min up to 220°C, held for 10 min; carrier gas helium, 1.0 mL/min; injector temperature, 280°C, splitless mode; transfer line temperature, 250°C; run time, 30 min. All mass spectra were acquired in electron-impact mode with ionization voltage equal to 70 eV; ion source temperature 250°C; acquisition mass range 35–500 Da.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each sample was analyzed in triplicate. The content percentage of each oil component was computed from the corresponding GC-MS peak area without applying any correction factor.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bioadhesion measurements</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bioadhesion measurements were carried out using a texture analyzer apparatus (TA.XT plus, Stable Microsystems, ENCO, Spinea, Italy) equipped with a 1 kg load cell, a cylinder probe having a diameter of 10 mm (P10), and the A/MUC measuring system.
   <a rid="b18-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18-ijn-13-175">18</a>,
   <a rid="b19-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b19-ijn-13-175">19</a> The A/MUC measuring system consists of a support in which a biologic substrate can be fixed. In this case, the biologic substrate chosen to mimic damaged skin was an egg shell membrane,
   <a rid="b18-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18-ijn-13-175">18</a> wetted with 100 µL of isotonic saline (NaCl 0.9% w/v). To recover the membrane, the egg shell was placed in a 0.5 M HCl solution for 1 h. The A/MUC system was thermoset at 32°C. One hundred microliters of each nanosystem containing 5% w/w of pull, as described in the section Lipid nanoparticle preparation, and 5%/w pull solution, as control, were placed onto the cylinder probe covered by filter paper disc and the sample and the biologic substrate were put in contact under a preload of 2.5 N for 3 min.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cylinder probe was then moved upward at a prefixed speed of 2.5 mm/s up to the complete separation of the bioadhesive interface (egg shell membrane–sample).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The force of detachment was recorded as a function of displacement and the bioadhesion parameter work of adhesion (area under the curve [AUC]) (mN mm, AUC) was calculated as the area under the force vs displacement curve.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The normalized adhesion parameter ΔAUC/AUC was subsequently calculated according to the following equation: 
   <div id="fd1-ijn-13-175" class="disp-formula">
    <div id="mm1" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
      <span class="mtext">AUC</span>
      <span class="mo">/</span>
      <span class="mtext">AUC</span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mtext">AUC</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mtext">bs</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">−</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mtext">AUC</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mtext">blank</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
      <span class="mo">/</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mtext">AUC</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mtext">blank</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>where: 
   <div list-type="simple" class="list">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>AUC
      <sub>bs</sub> = work of adhesion obtained in presence of the biologic substrate;
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>AUC
      <sub>blank</sub> = work of adhesion obtained from blank measurements.
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Such a normalization should allow comparison of the bioadhesive properties of samples characterized by different cohesive properties (viscosity).
   <a rid="b20-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b20-ijn-13-175">20</a>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
