<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results and discussion</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Physical–chemical characterization of nanoparticles</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijn-13-175" href="#f1-ijn-13-175">Figure 1A and B</a> reports the PS and PI of all lipid nanoparticles developed as a function of storage time (2°C–8°C). 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijn-13-175" href="#f1-ijn-13-175">Figure 1A</a> shows the results of SLN and NLC loaded with eucalyptus oil (e) or rosemary oil (r) and prepared by using olive oil (o), as liquid lipid, while 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijn-13-175" href="#f1-ijn-13-175">Figure 1B</a> shows the results of analogous nanosystems containing sesame oil (s), as liquid lipid.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Independent of nanoparticle composition, PS ranged from 220 to 300 nm and remained almost constant up to 3 months of storage. Similar results were obtained for PI that was close to 0.5, indicating nanoparticle populations characterized by a quite wide PS distribution, stable up to 3 months.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bioadhesion properties</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ijn-13-175" href="#f2-ijn-13-175">Figure 2</a> shows the normalized bioadhesion parameter (ΔAUC/AUC) of all the nanosystems developed, nanoparticles suspension and nanoparticles suspension containing 5% w/w pull.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pull was characterized by good bioadhesive properties. Although all nanoparticles were stabilized lecithin and it is conceivable that their surface was coated by the same lecithin layers, different bioadhesion properties were observed.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both SLN systems, either loaded with eucalyptus oil or with rosemary oil, were characterized by scarce bioadhesive properties. This result could be attributable to rigid structure of these nanoparticles, which impaired their interaction with the biologic substrates, preventing the formation of the bio-adhesive joint. On the contrary, all NLC formulations were characterized by good bioadhesive properties. The systems containing olive oil showed bioadhesion parameters significantly higher than those of the corresponding systems prepared by using sesame oil (one-way ANOVA, multiple range test 
   <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.05).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Olive oil contains 85% of unsaturated fatty acids, in particular 70% of monounsaturated (mainly oleic and palmitoleic acid) and about 15% of polyunsaturated ones (mainly linoleic and linolenic acid). On the contrary, sesame oil contains about 85% unsaturated acids; mono- and poly-unsaturated acids, which are present in comparable amounts (41% of polyunsaturated – linoleic acid and 39% of monounsatured – oleic acid).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These differences in composition could determine a different lipid packaging in nanoparticle core and a consequent modification of NLC flexibility. This could cause a different degree of interaction with the biologic substrate and consequently a different strength of the bioadhesive joint.
   <a rid="b23-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b23-ijn-13-175">23</a>,
   <a rid="b24-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b24-ijn-13-175">24</a> Bioadhesion is an important property to assure efficacy, because it allows an intimate contact between wounded area and formulation.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In vitro biocompatibility properties</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3-ijn-13-175" href="#f3-ijn-13-175">Figure 3</a>, cytocompatibility (% viability) of all the nanosystems developed, loaded with eucalyptus or rosemary oil, are compared. All the nanosytems (independent of the EO loaded) were characterized by concentration-dependent cytocompatibility. For a given formulation, the higher nanoparticle concentration (corresponding to the lowest dilution, 1/20) was characterized by % viability ranging from 30% to 50%, not significantly different than that of 1/40 dilution. On the contrary, 1/100 dilution determined a % viability ranging from 50% to 95%, significantly higher than those of the other two dilutions (one-way ANOVA, multiple range test 
   <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.05). The presence of pull determined an increase in cyto-compatibility. NLC systems based on olive oil and containing 5% w/w pull were characterized at 1/100 dilution by cyto-compatibility not significantly different than that of GM and significantly higher than those of NLC containing sesame oil (one-way ANOVA, multiple range test 
   <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.05).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Proliferation properties</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Proliferation (% viability) results of all the nanosystems developed, loaded with eucalyptus or rosemary oil, are reported in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ijn-13-175" href="#f4-ijn-13-175">Figure 4</a>. Nanoparticles suspension and nanoparticles suspension containing 5% w/w pull were diluted at 1/100 and their proliferation properties compared. The nanosystems were characterized by proliferation properties not significantly different than those of the control (GM). In comparison with GM, 5% w/w pull solution (dilution 1/100) was able to significantly enhance cell proliferation. All nanosystems containing 5% w/w pull solution were characterized by a relevant improvement of proliferation properties; with the exception of NLC s/e, based on sesame oil and loaded with eucalyptus oil, all nanoparticles determined an enhancement of cell growth significantly higher than that of standard growth conditions (control, GM) (one-way ANOVA, multiple range test 
   <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.05). NLC o/e, based on olive oil and loaded with eucalyptus oil, was characterized by the best performance in terms of proliferation enhancement properties.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The presence of olive oil seems to favor cell proliferation: this result could be due to the high content of oleic acid, a fatty acid previously described for its good proliferation properties:
   <a rid="b25-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b25-ijn-13-175">25</a> in fact the content of oleic acid is almost twofold greater than that of sesame oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cell migration/proliferation properties in an in vitro wound healing test</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f5-ijn-13-175" href="#f5-ijn-13-175">Figure 5</a> reports the microphotographs of cell substrates taken at time 0 (immediately after insert removal) and after 48 h growing, by using an optical microscope or a fluorescence microscope (cell nuclei stained with Hoechst 33258 in blue and proliferating cells stained with anti-BrdU antibody in green).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All the samples were able to promote cell migration/proliferation in the gaps at least as the GM. In particular, cell substrates put in contact with NLC o/e, based on olive oil and loaded with eucalyptus oil, containing 5% w/w pull, showed a complete gap closure within 48 h after insert removal and a cell concentration higher than that of standard growth condition (control, GM). This nanosystem, therefore, demonstrated to be more effective in promoting wound healing in vitro.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The contact with NLC o/e determined a higher concentration of green-stained cells in the gap, that were proliferating cells, with respect to the other nanosystems. It is conceivable that oleic acid determined a synergic effect with eucalyptus oil to enhance cell proliferation. Given these results, NLC o/e was chosen as the most promising nanosystem and subjected to further characterization.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In vitro characterization of NLC o/e</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f6-ijn-13-175" href="#f6-ijn-13-175">Figure 6</a> reports the TEM microphotograph of NLC o/e. Nanoparticles were round shaped and showed a relatively small size dispersion around 50–60 nm, smaller than that expected on the basis of PCS measurements, which were probably affected by the presence of aggregates, responsible for a high PI (close to 0.5).
   <a rid="b26-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b26-ijn-13-175">26</a> NLC o/e was characterized by a highly negative zeta potential equal to −22.07±0.29 mV (mean value ± SD, n=3). These results should conceivably be due to the presence onto nanoparticle surface of lecithin, which was proved to confer a negative zeta potential to nanosystems.
   <a rid="b27-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b27-ijn-13-175">27</a> The presence of lecithin allowed particle stabilization and controlled particle aggregation as evidenced by 3-month stability results (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijn-13-175" href="#f1-ijn-13-175">Figure 1A and B</a>). Eucalyptus EO loaded in NLC o/e was close to 100% (101.74±9.06%, mean value ± SD, n=3), indicating that the preparation procedure did not impair oil stability and loading, although it is a volatile extract.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pure cocoa butter melting starts at 31°C and is completed at 34°C. After cutaneous application, given that skin temperature is 32°C, melting of the lipid core was conceivably the mechanism enabling the release of eucalyptus EO.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The MIC values measured against 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Streptococcus pyogenes</span> for NLC o/e and for eucalyptus EO, at the same EO concentration, are reported in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="t2-ijn-13-175" href="#t2-ijn-13-175">Table 2</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Eucalyptus oil was characterized by the same MIC value (3 mg/mL) against 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span>, either as a free oil or after loading into NLC, indicating that encapsulation did not impair its antimicrobial activity. On the contrary, it showed an enhanced antimicrobial activity against 
   <span class="italic">Streptococcus pyogenes</span> when encapsulated in NLC, because MIC values decreased from 1.5 mg/mL, for free oil, to 0.75 mg/mL, for NLC o/e.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In vivo wound healing efficacy of NLC o/e</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ijn-13-175" href="#f7-ijn-13-175">Figure 7</a> reports the profiles of wound area (cm
   <span class="sup">2</span>) as function of time. All the wounds treated with NLC o/e, as either nanoparticle suspension or nanoparticle suspension containing 5% w/w pull, and with saline solution (control) showed similar lesion area vs time profiles. After 4 days of treatment, NLC o/e suspension showed a significantly lower lesion area (not significantly greater than time 0) with respect to NLC o/e containing pull and saline solution, which were characterized by significantly greater dimensions than time 0 (one-way ANOVA, multiple range test 
   <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.05). At the 7th and 10th day of treatment both the lesions treated with NLC o/e, as either nanoparticle suspension or as nanoparticle suspension containing pull, presented dimensions not significantly different from each other and significantly lower than the lesion treated with saline solution (one-way ANOVA, multiple range test 
   <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.05). At the 15th day of treatment NLC o/e suspension presented the highest lesion reduction (one-way ANOVA, multiple range test 
   <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.05) indicating the capability of these nanoparticles to speed up tissue repairing. Given the high variability of results, such a difference could not be observed at 18th day of treatment.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-13-175" href="#f8-ijn-13-175">Figure 8</a> reports microphotographs of skin sections of the wound area, stained with H&amp;E, taken at the 18th day of treatment with saline solution (A), NLC o/e suspension (B), and NLC o/e suspension containing pull (C). Microphotograph of intact skin (D) is reported for comparison.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In correspondence with the wound treated with saline solution (control) (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-13-175" href="#f8-ijn-13-175">Figure 8A</a>), a large part of epidermis was replaced by an eosinophil necrotic tissue (asterisk), and in the peripheral regions of the lesion, epidermis (bracket) was visible. In the underlying dermal connective tissue, an abundant granulation tissue (arrow) was present; moreover, collagen fibers were dispersed and not yet organized in large bundles, typical of the reticular layer of the dermis. There was no evidence of skin appendages (hair follicles and glands), while there were numerous vacuoles of different size (black star), delimited by a wall consisting of a monolayer of flattened cells (endothelium), probably corresponding to dilated vessels.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In correspondence with the wound treated with NLC o/e suspension (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-13-175" href="#f8-ijn-13-175">Figure 8B</a>), epidermis (bracket) appeared continuous and well organized in multiple cell layers with a fair degree of keratinization. In the underlying connective tissue, skin appendages were vacant, but dermal papillae (white star) began to reform. A mild inflammatory infiltrate was visible (arrow), as well as a number of blood vessels (black star). Some scattered collagen fibers were present at the border with epidermis, while in the reticular layer of the dermis, the typical large bundles of collagen (white arrow) were already formed.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In correspondence with the wound treated with NLC o/e suspension containing 5% w/w pull (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-13-175" href="#f8-ijn-13-175">Figure 8C</a>), skin appeared completely re-epithelized, and epidermis (bracket) was well organized in multiple cell layers, with a fair degree of keratinization, similar to the structures observed in the section obtained from wound treated with NLC o/e (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-13-175" href="#f8-ijn-13-175">Figure 8B</a>). Dermal papillae (white star) were in developing phase; furthermore, granulation tissue (arrows) and dilated vessels (black star) were present in a limited area, while collagen fibers were organized in large bundles, typical of the reticular layer of the dermis (white arrow).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Normal skin (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-13-175" href="#f8-ijn-13-175">Figure 8D</a>) was characterized by epidermis (bracket), well organized in multiple cell layers, with a fair degree of keratinization and showed numerous dermal papillae (white star). Dermal layer was characterized by large bundles of collagen fibers (white arrow) and showed a lot of dermal appendages (white triangle), such as sebaceous glands and hair bulbs.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, NLC e/o suspension containing pull promoted an excellent healing, with a good re-epithelization and stratum corneum formation. Although in the underlying connective tissue, skin appendages were vacant, collagen fibers were organized in large bundles typical of the reticular layer of the dermis. Moreover, dermal papillae began to reform. There was only a mild inflammatory infiltrate, visible in a small portion in the center of the wound.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
