<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wound repair is one of the most complex physiologic processes, involving a multitude of different cell types, the contribution of which is tightly regulated over time. The breakdown of such a complex path could result in wound healing failure, leading to nonhealing wounds. The typical path of wound repair includes overlapping stages of inflammation, new tissue generation, and subsequent remodeling of neoformed tissue. These stages take place over dramatically different timescales, lasting from minutes (initial clotting and coagulation) to several months or even years.
  <a rid="b1-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b1-ijn-13-175">1</a>,
  <a rid="b2-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b2-ijn-13-175">2</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chronic wounds (including venous leg ulcers, diabetic foot ulcers, arterial insufficiency, and pressure ulcers) determine severe morbidity and even mortality especially in older individuals, in particular those affected from diabetes mellitus and vascular diseases. In addition, surgery, more common in older population, presents risk of wound complication. In general, chronic wounds deeply affect quality of life and wound care requires high costs of therapy.
  <a rid="b3-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b3-ijn-13-175">3</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Resident cells are less proliferating in chronic wounds and possess a morphology similar to that of senescent cells. In particular, fibroblasts of chronic wounds (long-lasting vascular leg ulcers) are characterized by a poorer response to platelet-derived growth factor, altered capability of transforming growth factor beta type II receptor expression, and abnormal phosphorylation of critical signal transduction proteins. Such features are typical of cells exposed to low oxygen tension, suggesting that chronic wounds are hypoxic.
  <a rid="b3-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b3-ijn-13-175">3</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effect of microbial burden on healing of chronic wound is not completely understood and it is probably underestimated.
  <a rid="b2-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b2-ijn-13-175">2</a> The presence of a biofilm was indicated as a critical factor and a correlation between depth and duration of the lesion and the presence of 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus</span> strains was demonstrated.
  <a rid="b4-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b4-ijn-13-175">4</a> Moreover, microbial wound colonization (typically due to 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Streptococcus pyogenes</span>, and some 
  <span class="italic">Clostridium</span> strains) was proved responsible for a further delay in wound recovery.
  <a rid="b5-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b5-ijn-13-175">5</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Burns are skin wounds that can affect a significant portion of the body. Prevention of microbial infection and scar formation are key factors for wound healing.
  <a rid="b6-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6-ijn-13-175">6</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many efforts to enhance the effectiveness of wound healing process have been focused on boosting the antimicrobial activity of topically applied devices, preventing infections, promoting tissue regeneration, and minimizing pain, discomfort, and scar formation.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the last decades, the occurrence of multiresistant bacteria poses a serious problem worldwide, making a challenge the choice of appropriate treatment for patients affected with infected lesions.
  <a rid="b7-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b7-ijn-13-175">7</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Natural products including β-glucans, aloe, honey, and especially essential oils (EOs) have been proposed as antibacterial agents.
  <a rid="b8-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b8-ijn-13-175">8</a> In particular, EOs are known to possess antimicrobial effect against multiresistant bacteria, thanks to a broad spectrum of biologic and antimicrobial activity.
  <a rid="b9-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9-ijn-13-175">9</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">EOs are volatile products produced by the secondary metabolism of plants, are extracted from nonwoody part (flowers, seeds, leaves, fruits, and roots), and are mainly composed of terpenes and terpenoids and aromatic and aliphatic constituents.
  <a rid="b10-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b10-ijn-13-175">10</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Eucalyptus leaf extracts (EO from eucalyptus tree, belonging to the family of Myrtaceae) demonstrated various biologic effects, such as antibacterial, antifungal, antiseptic, antihyperglycemic, and antioxidant activities; 1,8-cineole or eucalyptol is the most important component, responsible for bioactive properties.
  <a rid="b11-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b11-ijn-13-175">11</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rosemary EO (from 
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span>, belonging to the family of Lamiaceae), which is mainly composed of camphor, 1,8-cineole, borneol, verbenone, α-pinene, and camphene, has been historically used as an antibacterial, antifungal, and antioxidant agent.
  <a rid="b12-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b12-ijn-13-175">12</a>–
  <a rid="b14-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14-ijn-13-175">14</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All EOs are unstable volatile compounds and are easily degradable (by oxidation, volatilization, heating, and light): encapsulation in nanosystems should, therefore, represent a useful tool to enhance their stability and improve antibacterial activity.
  <a rid="b15-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b15-ijn-13-175">15</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Giving these premises, the aim of this work was the development of lipid nanoparticles, solid lipid nanoparticles (SLN), and nanostructured lipid carriers (NLC), to be loaded with eucalyptus or rosemary EOs and to be used, as medical devices, to enhance healing of skin wounds.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lipid nanoparticles were based on natural lipids: cocoa butter, as solid lipid, and olive oil or sesame oil, as liquid lipids. Lecithin was chosen as surfactant to stabilize nanoparticles and to prevent their aggregation. The systems were prepared by high shear homogenization followed by ultrasound application.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nanoparticles were characterized for physical–chemical properties, bioadhesion, cytocompatibility, in vitro proliferation enhancement, and wound healing properties toward normal human dermal fibroblasts (NHDF). Antimicrobial activity of nanoparticles was evaluated against two reference microbial strains, one of 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span>, the other 
  <span class="italic">of Streptococcus pyogenes</span>. Finally, the capability of nanoparticles to promote wound healing in vivo was evaluated on a rat burn model.
 </p>
</sec>
