<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anti-spasmodic</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antispasmodic drugs are prescribed frequently for numerous gastrointestinal illnesses (N'Guessan et al., 
  <a rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" href="#B93">2015</a>). Most of the antispasmodic drugs contain antimuscarinic compounds and calcium channel blockers (Farhadi et al., 
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">2001</a>; Pasricha, 
  <a rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" href="#B100">2001</a>) and the consumption of these drugs may associate with unwanted side effects. Medicinal plants which are used in folk and traditional medicine for gastrointestinal disorders have been validated through pharmacological studies for antispasmodic activity (Hajhashemi et al., 
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">2000</a>; Sadraei et al., 
  <a rid="B115" ref-type="bibr" href="#B115">2003</a>). The results showed that the investigated medicinal plants recorded significant antispasmodic potential (Cortés et al., 
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">2006</a>; Cechinel-Filho et al., 
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">2007</a>). Similarly, the anti-spasmodic potential of hydroalcoholic extract from the leaves and seeds of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> was studied by Sadraei et al. (
  <a rid="B114" ref-type="bibr" href="#B114">2015</a>) by ileum contractions induced by 80 mM KCl, 250 μM of acetylcholine (ACh) and electrical field stimulation (EFS). Both the extracts have an inhibitory potential on ileum contractions. The seeds extract of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> had more potential inhibitory effect of ileum contraction induced by KCl (IC
  <sub>50</sub> = 87 ± 18 μg/ml); ACh (IC
  <sub>50</sub> = 118 ± 18 μg/ml), and EFS (I IC
  <sub>50</sub> = 230 ± 51 μg/ml). Whereas, the leaf extract also showed inhibitory effect of ileum contraction (KCl—IC
  <sub>50</sub> = 439 ± 108 μg/ml; ACh—IC
  <sub>50</sub> = 365 ± 61 μg/ml; EFS—IC
  <sub>50</sub> = 314 ± 92 μg/ml). Further investigation on bio assay guided isolation is required to identify the active molecule which could be an alternative and safer anti-spasmodic molecule for future use.
 </p>
</sec>
