<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> invasions in South Africa cover an estimated 1.8 million hectares, and are increasing at 8 % per annum (
 <xref rid="PLU027C91" ref-type="bibr">Versfeld 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 1998
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU027C83" ref-type="bibr">Van den Berg 2010</xref>). They have the potential to invade between 5 and 32 million hectares of South Africa based on climatic suitability—about a third of the area of the country (
 <xref rid="PLU027C77" ref-type="bibr">Rouget 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2004
 </xref>). 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> is declared as a category 2 invasive alien species because it provides benefits and causes harm; this status means that it is legal to grow 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> in demarcated areas once a permit has been issued. A combination of mechanical, chemical and biological control methods is used to control 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic>, mainly by the government-managed Working for Water programme. Three seed-feeding beetles (
 <italic>A. prosopis</italic>, 
 <italic>A. bottimeri</italic> and 
 <italic>Neltumius arizonensis</italic>) were introduced as biological control agents to try and reduce spread while maintaining its benefits (
 <xref rid="PLU027C98" ref-type="bibr">Zimmermann 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU027C18" ref-type="bibr">Coetzer and Hoffmann 1997</xref>). 
 <italic>Neltumius arizonensis</italic> failed to establish (
 <xref rid="PLU027C97" ref-type="bibr">Zachariades 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2011
 </xref>). Although biological control is considered the most cost-effective way of managing large-scale invasions of many species, there are many cases where the agents fail to make a significant impact and 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> is one of them (
 <xref rid="PLU027C90" ref-type="bibr">van Wilgen 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2012
 </xref>). The overall return on investment is low compared with biological control programmes for 
 <italic>Opuntia</italic> species and Australian 
 <italic>Acacia</italic> species in South Africa (
 <xref rid="PLU027C90" ref-type="bibr">van Wilgen 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2012
 </xref>). There is potential to release more agents, such as the 
 <italic>Evippe</italic> species which is already successful in Australia (see above), should the contentious issues surrounding the benefits and costs of 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> be resolved (
 <xref rid="PLU027C97" ref-type="bibr">Zachariades 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2011
 </xref>). 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> cover increased by ∼35 % between 1996 and 2008, despite the expenditure of R435.5 million (US$42.7 million) on control over this period. Only 15 100 ha were cleared using mechanical and chemical control with this substantial budget (
 <xref rid="PLU027C90" ref-type="bibr">van Wilgen 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2012
 </xref>), which makes the cost/ha very expensive (US$2828). The limited success to date may be due to lack of a management strategy and of prioritization of management projects (
 <xref rid="PLU027C32" ref-type="bibr">Forsyth 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2012
 </xref>). There is a need for researchers, managers and policy-makers to agree on new strategies for prioritizing areas for interventions to curb the spread of 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> and to ensure that the limited resources are used effectively (
 <xref rid="PLU027C32" ref-type="bibr">Forsyth 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2012
 </xref>). There have been some attempts at controlling 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> through utilization, but they had no noticeable impacts on invasions, and these initiatives failed as input and transport costs were too high and financial returns were low (
 <xref rid="PLU027C99" ref-type="bibr">Zimmermann 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2006
 </xref>). South Africa also has many particularly aggressive hybrids that form dense shrub-dominated stands, which makes the utilization approach difficult (
 <xref rid="PLU027C99" ref-type="bibr">Zimmermann 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2006
 </xref>).
</p>
