<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48" class="p">Here, we have also demonstrated, for the first time, the 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H NMR detection of 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-2-alkenals in thermally-stressed culinary oils (section S1). Such 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>- isomers, including 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-2-butenal, are also known to be secondary LOPs which arise from the peroxidation of PUFA sources (for example 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-2-octenal and -nonenal from linoleate, and 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-2-pentenal and -hexenal from linolenate)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>. However, it is conceivable that they may also arise from the thermally-induced isomerisation of their corresponding 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-2-alkenals, and this may explain their generation at only the later LSSFE time-points. Indeed, 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic> -2-heptenal may arise from 
 <italic class="italic">cis-trans</italic> isomerism of its 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-isomer, which is a β-homolysis product of linoleate-12-hydroperoxide
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>
 </sup>. PCA of our oil dataset confirmed a correlation between 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>- and 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-2-alkenal resonances, i.e. they were both found to load significantly and positively on the second orthogonal PC (Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S1</xref>). Additionally, 2-heptenal isomers are derived from alka-2,4-decadienal decomposition, along with acetaldehyde, hexanal, acrolein, butenal, 2-heptenal, 2-octenal, benzaldehyde, glyoxal, and 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-2-buten-1,4-dial
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup>. A further product, 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-3-hexenal, may arise via keto-enol tautomerism of a radical combination product of the 1,3-hexadienyl radical arising from the fragmentation of the 12-hydroperoxide of linolenate and hydroxyl radical (
 <sup class="sup">•</sup>OH)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>. However, we found no major multivariate statistical evidence for associations between the 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-2-alkenal 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H NMR resonance intensities and those of either 
 <italic class="italic">cis,trans</italic>- or 
 <italic class="italic">trans,trans</italic>-alka-2,4-dienals. Indeed, this possible precursor may also decompose to 2,3- or 4,5-epoxyaldehydes, which are then further degraded to combinations of either isomeric 2-octenals and acetaldehyde, or glyoxal and 2-octene
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup>. Although these mechanistic pathways appear to be consistent with Boskou 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.’s results
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup>, our observations revealed that oil 
 <italic class="italic">trans,trans</italic>-alka-2,4-dienal concentrations continued to increase from the 60 to 90 min. time-points for all products explored, with the exception of those for extra virgin olive oil in which it saturated at 60 min.
</p>
