<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par50" class="p">Although the lipid content of fried products is dependent on the types of food, class of frying episode (e.g., shallow- 
 <italic class="italic">versus</italic> deep-frying), frying time and frying temperature, these values broadly range from 6–38% (w/w)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, Naseri 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>
 </sup> have reported that the deep frying of fish (silver carp) gave rise to a substantial exchange of acylglycerol (predominantly triacylglycerol) FAs between the food and the culinary oils employed for this purpose, and as expected, the frying oil FA composition substantially altered that of these silver carp fillets on completion of these frying episodes. Comparable results have been observed in similar investigations focused on lipid uptake by potato chips during standard frying practices (e.g.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup>, and reviewed in
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>
 </sup>). For example, the total lipid content of different varieties of fresh, unfried potato tubers is only 
 <italic class="italic">ca</italic>. 0.10% (w/w), of which the total PUFA content is 70–76%
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>
 </sup>, but escalates to values exceeding 30% (w/w) in chipped potatoes after frying
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup>. Hence, frying oil acylglycerol-normalised (proportionate) concentrations of LOPs will also be expected to migrate into foods fried in such media, and in 2012 Csallany 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup> found that HNE was readily detectable in French fry samples collected from n = 6 fast-food restaurants at concentrations of 8–32 µg/100 g portion (equivalent to 0.9–4.9 µg/g of extracted lipid).
</p>
