<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par52" class="p">Notwithstanding, our 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H NMR analysis results clearly demonstrate that much greater levels of 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-2-alkenals, 
 <italic class="italic">trans,trans</italic>-alka-2,4-dienals, and arguably somewhat less toxic 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-alkanals, are present in FFRPCSs purchased from fast food retail outlets. Indeed, for peroxidised linoleoylglycerols, the predominant compounds featured within the three major aldehydic LOP classes detectable are 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-2-octenal, 
 <italic class="italic">trans,trans</italic>-deca-2,4-dienal and 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hexanal respectively
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>
 </sup>, and assuming that these represent 100% of the above 3 classes of aldehydes, our estimated mean μmol.kg
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> values would constitute as much as 1.53, 2.44 and 1.25 mg aldehyde/100 g portions of FFRPCSs, equivalent to 1.1, 1.7 and 0.9 mg per small (71 g), and 2.4, 3.8 and 1.9 mg per large (154 g) servings, respectively (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" class="xref">4</xref>), values much larger than those previously reported for HNE
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>, as might be expected from our 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H NMR determinations of the relative quantities of these aldehyde classes detectable in the thermally-stressed oils explored here. These small and large serving portion masses correspond to those provided by a well-known major commercial fast food chain, although it should be noted that ‘large’ FFRPCSs may comprise masses as high as 300–400 g, including those available in the USA or Europe. Similarly, major 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-2-alkenal and 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-alkanal species arising from the fragmentation of oleoylglycerol hydroperoxides are 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-2-decenal and nonanal respectively
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>, and again, if these comprised 100% of these two aldehydic LOP classes, then they would be equivalent to 1.90 and 1.89 mg aldehyde/100 g of FFRPCS, corresponding to 1.4 and 1.3 mg per 71 g, and 2.9 and 2.8 mg per 154 g servings, respectively (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" class="xref">4</xref>). Although propanal has a high volatility, determinations of its concentration as a secondary LOP remaining in used frying oils, and its potential uptake by fried foods could, at least in principle, serve as a marker for the peroxidation of linolenoylglycerols present in frying oils. However, further, more extended studies are required to explore relationships between these fried food LOP contents and the % fatty acid compositions of the corresponding cooking oils employed for deep frying purposes by fast-food retail outlets, or alternative sources of such products.
</p>
