<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Corn germ meal (CGM) is produced during the process of germ extraction to produce corn oil for human consumption [
 <xref rid="b1-ajas-17-0891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. As a by-product of the oil industry, CGM could provide relative abundant protein and energy contents, which was firstly thought to be used in pet food to replace part of the more expensive corn and also a small portion of the soybean meal [
 <xref rid="b2-ajas-17-0891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. However, the high fiber content of CGM limits its utilization primarily to ruminant diets [
 <xref rid="b3-ajas-17-0891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="b4-ajas-17-0891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>] and fish diets [
 <xref rid="b2-ajas-17-0891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Recently, researchers began to put more attention on the application of CGM in swine diets. Soares et al [
 <xref rid="b5-ajas-17-0891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>] reported that the inclusion rate of CGM in diet for growing and finishing pigs could reach 30% without disturbing the economical parameters. Weber et al [
 <xref rid="b6-ajas-17-0891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>] showed that an inclusion level of 38% CGM in diets did not affect the average daily gain and average daily feed intake of pigs, but did reduce the feed efficiency. Nevertheless, few data are available on the energy contents of CGM fed to pigs, except that Anderson et al [
 <xref rid="b7-ajas-17-0891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>] presented a relatively detailed research on the digestible energy (DE) value of CGM in pigs, but with only one sample. The composition and quality of CGM can vary considerably [
 <xref rid="b6-ajas-17-0891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="b8-ajas-17-0891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="b9-ajas-17-0891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>] due to different processing conditions during oil extraction as well as different soil, latitude and environmental conditions during corn growing and harvesting [
 <xref rid="b10-ajas-17-0891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. As a result, it is necessary to evaluate the energy contents of CGM in pigs with more samples.
</p>
