<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Preclinical studies: Celastrus seed extract and oil have been evaluated in different experimental models of cognitive impairment such as scopolamine and sodium nitrite induced amnesia. The aqueous, methanolic, chloroform and petroleum ether extracts of seeds of 
 <italic>C. paniculatus</italic> were investigated for their effect on cognitive function in rats. The aqueous extract showed significant improvement in cognitive performance at the doses of 200 and 300 mg/kg, p.o for 14 days. In another study, methanolic extract reported to have memory-enhancing activity in rats at doses of 100, 200 and 400 mg/kg [
 <xref rid="B177-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>]. The antioxidant activity of 
 <italic>C. paniculatus</italic> may be involved in improving the cognitive function [
 <xref rid="B45-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. The oil of 
 <italic>C. paniculatus</italic> seeds when given for 14 days to Wistar rats at a dose of 400 mg/kg resulted in enhanced learning and memory in radial arm maze and decreased the AChE enzyme activity in hypothalamus, frontal cortex and hippocampus [
 <xref rid="B178-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>]. Karanth et al. [
 <xref rid="B179-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>] also demonstrated a similar effect of 
 <italic>C. paniculatus</italic> at the dose of 400 mg/kg for 3 days. In another study, rats treated with 850 mg/kg of 
 <italic>C. paniculatus</italic> oil for 15 days had significantly improved retention in two passive avoidance tasks [
 <xref rid="B56-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The seed oil treatment for 14 days at the doses of 50, 200 and 400 mg/kg, p.o reversed scopolamine induced spatial memory impairment in the Morris water maze and increased locomotor activity without affecting AChE activity in rats [
 <xref rid="B180-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>]. The aqueous seed extract improved memory performance in elevated plus maze and in sodium nitrite induced amnesia by reducing the AChE activity [
 <xref rid="B181-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>]. Furthermore, 
 <italic>C. paniculatus</italic> seed oil treatment showed memory improvement in scopolamine induced amnesia in mice [
 <xref rid="B182-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>]. 
 <italic>C. paniculatus</italic> has not undergone clinical trials for safety and efficacy. Animal toxicology data is also lacking to date.
</p>
