<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For the future we recommend the following initiatives:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>Well-controlled clinical trials (double-blinded, placebo controlled) and pursuit of EU/North American approval or approval at the national level by manufacturers of cannabis-derived products should be conducted, so that high-quality products of known safety and efficacy can be made available for veterinarians and their patients.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Clinical trial studies should be encouraged to investigate the potential therapeutic value and safety of hemp-derived products for companion animals.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Harmonize the analytical procedure of the determination of the THC level in serum and oral fluids and set up harmonised tolerable limits of cannabinoids in different products.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Use of hemp-derived products for animals should require a veterinary prescription.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Prohibition on producing pet food with cannabis-derived products without known safety and efficacy and without the knowledge of the intended purpose of the included cannabis-derived products as specified by the pet food manufacturers.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The prohibition on producing feed supplements or beddings for food producing animals with CBD/Cannabis without known safety and efficacy and without knowledge of the intended purpose of the included cannabis-derived products as specified by manufacturers, and data on any residue in the food derived from these animals.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>We encourage veterinarians to act cautiously, as there may be risks associated with having such products in their possession if the product(s) were subsequently shown to contain illegal levels of THC. Any suspected breaches should be reported to Competent Authorities in the EU Member State where the event occurred.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
