<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In a world where food safety is a priority, several synthetic food additives such as BHA, BHT and PG have been investigated regarding their safety and possible adverse effects. This review also showed that 
 <italic class="italic">Piper</italic> spp. could be used as food preservatives due to their antioxidant and antimicrobial potentials. In this review we have summarized the antioxidant potential of 
 <italic class="italic">Piper</italic> species as antioxidants, e.g., the antioxidant activities of 
 <italic class="italic">P. nigrum</italic> EO and oleoresins showed strong antioxidant activity in comparison with synthetic antioxidants [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>]. Indeed, 
 <italic class="italic">P. nigrum</italic> has demonstrated antibacterial and antifungal activities against human pathogens such as 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus</italic> spp., 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus</italic> spp., 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas</italic> spp., 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus</italic> spp., and 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> spp. Moreover, several 
 <italic class="italic">Piper</italic> species, in particular 
 <italic class="italic">P. aduncum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">P. betle</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">P. longum</italic>, are used to treat parasitic diseases in Africa, Asia and Latin America. There is an increasing demand for natural food preservatives due to the emergence of antibiotic-resistance microorganisms. Particularly, 
 <italic class="italic">P. nigrum</italic> is the most important species of this genus due to its pungent principle component, piperine, and its worldwide popularity as a flavoring for food. Spices and their EOs are considered to be GRAS which makes that 
 <italic class="italic">Piper</italic> species have a promising future prospective as a food preservative to control various food spoilage and pathogenic microorganisms. However, 
 <italic class="italic">Piper</italic> extract could affect food organoleptic characteristics. Therefore, careful selection of appropriate concentrations of this extract with regard to the sensory and compositional status of the food system to which it is applied is required in order to gain consumers’ acceptability. Consequently, new studies and technologies are needed to be developed to enhance food safety and quality without changing the organoleptic properties of the food itself.
</p>
