<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Template DNA for PCR was extracted as follows. Between 5 and 10 fresh colonies of an overnight culture were transferred into 0.5 ml distilled water and heated to 100°C for 15 min. The suspension was centrifuged at 15000 × 
 <italic class="italic">g</italic> for 2 min and supernatant transferred into a fresh tube. PCR amplification was carried out using a liquid handling robot (TheOnyx, Automated Lab Solutions GmbH). All PCR reagents were maintained at 4°C in the reagent rack. Each PCR was performed in a final volume of 50 μl using a Taq polymerase PCR master mix (ReadyMix, ABgene) with oligonucleotide primers at 0.4 μM and 6 μl of extracted template DNA. Thermal cycling conditions were: initial denaturation at 96°C for 1 min; 30 cycles of denaturation at 96°C for 1 min, primer annealing at 58°C for 1 min, extension at 72°C for 2 min; final extension step of 72°C for 5 min. PCR products were purified using a MultiScreen 384-PCR Filter Plate (Merck Millipore) and eluted twice with a total volume of 70 μl distilled water. Sequencing was carried out on both DNA strands: 6 μl of purified PCR product was mixed with 3 μl of DYEnamic ET terminator sequence premix (Amersham Biosciences) and 10 pmol of each MLST gene primer. Thermal cycling conditions for sequencing reactions were 95°C for 2 min, 30 cycles of 95°C for 20 s, 50°C for 15 s and 60°C for 1 min. Salts and unincorporated dye terminators were removed using a MultiScreen SEQ384 Filter Plate (Merck Millipore). DNA sequencing was performed using an automated MegaBACE 1000 96-capillary sequencer (Amersham Biosciences). DNA sequence data were analyzed and converted into FASTA format using the MegaBACE Sequence Analysis Software with integrated cimaron v1.53 phredify base caller. Sequences were queried against the PubMLST Bcc database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubmlst.org/bcc" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://pubmlst.org/bcc</ext-link>) to obtain a sequence type (ST).
</p>
