<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Researchers found that duck feathers cannot be wetted by water a long time ago (
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>
 </xref>a).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup> The modern study of superhydrophobic surfaces has enjoyed a resurgence in the past two decades with the rise of bionics. Scientists try to detect the mechanism behind the lotus effect with the aid of scanning electron microscopy. In 1997, the microscale papillae of lotus leaves were identified as the key to its water-repellency (
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>
 </xref>b).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup> For further exploration, dual-scale micro-/nanostructures of lotus leaves allowing the achievement of both high apparent contact angles and low adhesion were demonstrated by Jiang et al. in 2002 (
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>
 </xref>c).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup> This was the first work to reveal that the multiscale structure is crucial to superhydrophobicity. In the same year, Jiang et al. also discovered that the rice leaf displayed anisotropic wettability (
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>
 </xref>d).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup> Rice leaf papillae are parallel to the leaf edge and randomly in the other direction. In 2004, Gao and Jiang
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup> found that the special hierarchical structure of superhydrophobic water strider legs (
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>
 </xref>e) is the main reason for water striders’ standing effortlessly and moving quickly on water. Researchers reported the second anisotropic creature surface in 2007, namely, butterfly wings (
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>
 </xref>f).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup> A water droplet easily rolls off the wings along the outward direction of the body but pinned in an inward direction, which resulted from the direction-dependent arrangement of flexible nanotips on nanostripes and microscales overlapped on the wings.
</p>
