<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Another interesting technique for the modification of PLA film surfaces and the improvement of their functionalization is by plasma treatments [
 <xref rid="B256-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">256</xref>,
 <xref rid="B257-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">257</xref>,
 <xref rid="B258-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">258</xref>]. For instance, Hu et al. [
 <xref rid="B257-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">257</xref>] have recently coated a PLA film’s surface with nisin after modifying the film’s surface by means of cold plasma treatment (CPT). They studied the surface antimicrobial activity of the films against 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> bacteria by the inhibition zone method. The authors found that the inhibition zone was only formed in the area where the incubated agar medium was in direct contact with the PLA–nisin-based films due to the poor water solubility of nisin. The antibacterial effectiveness of the PLA–nisin films was then determined quantitatively by means of the viable cell count method, and the total viable counts (TVCs) of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> decreased from 3.01 to 2.25 log
 <sub class="sub">10</sub> (CFU/mL) by increasing the time of functionalization of the PLA’s surface by CPT from 15 to 60 s. These results suggest that increasing the CPT time positively affects the nisin adsorption capacity of the PLA’s surface as well as allowing for nisin to be released from the PLA’s surface when it is in an appropriate medium. Zhang et al. [
 <xref rid="B258-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">258</xref>] treated electrospun materials with oxygen plasma to obtain a material with a hydrophilic surface that can be further functionalized with antimicrobial substances. Catechol possesses an essential role as an adhesive between interfaces; particularly, the synthetic catechol derivative dopamine methacrylamide monomer (DMA) possesses an exceptional adhesive property, which was used by these authors for surface modification in the development of biomedical devices. The electrospun PLA materials were modified with graphene oxide with DMA and the obtained nanocomposite showed excellent biocompatibility and exhibited antimicrobial properties against 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> bacteria.
</p>
