<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Among all sustainable polymers, PLA is currently the most promising one to replace petroleum-derived polymers. Moreover, PLA is biocompatible and biodegradable, and this is why it is widely used in the biomedical field as well as in a wide range of commodity applications in other industrial sectors, such as the agricultural and food packaging sectors [
 <xref rid="B236-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">236</xref>,
 <xref rid="B237-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">237</xref>]. PLA is chemically synthesized starting with simple sugars obtained from agro-resources, such as corn, potatoes, cane, and beet, and fermented to the lactic acid monomer [
 <xref rid="B236-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">236</xref>,
 <xref rid="B237-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">237</xref>]. The most common route to produce PLA at the industrial level is the ring-opening polymerization (ROP) of the cyclic lactide dimer by condensation with metal catalysts (e.g., tin octoate) with the elimination of water at a high temperature (but less than 200 °C) [
 <xref rid="B238-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">238</xref>,
 <xref rid="B239-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">239</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-00641-f009" class="xref">Figure 9</xref>). Another important advantage that has allowed us to rapidly introduce PLA into the market is that PLA can be processed with the same processing technology that is already used at the industrial level for traditional petroleum-based thermoplastics to obtain films, molded pieces, and fibers, including melt blending, extrusion, injection molding, thermoforming, film forming, and electrospinning [
 <xref rid="B236-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">236</xref>,
 <xref rid="B240-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">240</xref>,
 <xref rid="B241-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">241</xref>].
</p>
