<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>By considering surveillance effort and the performance of the detection method used, our method does lend itself well to the capturing of the costs of surveillance itself in isolation from the costs of disease or control, which can be achieved by simply comparing the number of samples that need to be collected in order to achieve a given probability of detection. This is shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.3000863.g005">Fig 5</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.3000863.s007">S6 Fig</xref>, which clearly demonstrate that at least twice as many samples would be required to achieve any given detection probability when conventional site-selection methods are used in contrast to the optimised approach. If we ignore the costs of travelling between sites (which are likely minimal in comparison to the costs of inspection and testing of hosts) and assume a fixed cost of surveillance per site, the use of conventional site-selection strategies would therefore be expected to at least double the costs of surveillance in comparison to the optimised approach. Based on the cost estimates described above, in order to achieve a mean detection probability of 0.95, the optimised strategy would cost US$8,859 per year, in contrast to the US$19,282 per year required to achieve the same mean detection probability using the best-performing conventional strategy. This therefore represents a potential saving of US$10,423 per year. Assuming in our particular case that the first pathogen entry occurred around 1 year after the start of surveillance and took an average of around 7 years to reach the threshold prevalence, this represents a total cost saving of US$83,384 when using the optimised approach. This is a considerable saving, considering the limited funds generally available for plant health monitoring and surveillance. The bulk of this cost is associated with PCR testing, and whilst savings could be made by only testing suspected cases, this would likely require the use of more highly trained surveyors, which would constitute an additional cost in itself. Further exploration of the optimal balance of these costs would be an interesting and valuable area for further exploration.
</p>
