<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent years, traditional plants have emerged as potential sources of antioxidants, antimicrobials, and secondary metabolites for therapeutic interventions, which has opened doors for the development of novel plant-based antibacterial agents [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. At the same time, evolving consumer outlook has created increased importance for the nutritive value of the food [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], skyrocketing the need for finding novel sources of healthy phenols and antioxidants. 
 <italic>Artemisia herba-alba</italic> Asso. is widely known as desert wormwood, that is extensively used in conventional and herbal medicine for the treatment of diabetes, parasitic infection, hypertension and cold [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. 
 <italic>A. Herba-alba</italic> mainly belongs to the genus 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic> which can generally grow in the semi-arid region of the Mediterranean (Middle East), North Africa, Spain, and the northwest region of the Himalayas [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic> genus has approximately 400 species which are mostly diploid and tetraploid. 
 <italic>Artemisia herba-alba</italic> plant is a green perennial shrub that grows 20–50 cm long with small and hairy leaves [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Flowering starts from September to December but the full development begins at the end of the summer with woolly hairs stem [
 <xref rid="B10-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. From ancient times, the plant extract of 
 <italic>A. Herba-alba</italic> has been used as a traditional medicine in many cultures because it has many pharmacological and biological activities especially antidiabetic, antimicrobial, antitumor, antimalarial, antioxidant, insecticidal and neurological activities [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In Morocco, this plant has been used in herbal tea to treat hypertension and stomach disorder [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In Algeria, this plant is used as fodder for lamb and other livestock [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-plants-10-00164" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].
</p>
