<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The other most commonly used viability dyes are the tetrazolium salt solutions. These salt solutions are weakly coloured and change to a strong coloured solution when forming the formazan product
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">1</xref>B). Over the years, several tetrazolium salts have been developed. For antifungal susceptibility testing, 3-(4.5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT),
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> 2,3-bis(2-methoyloxy-4-nitro-5-sulfophenyl)-5-[(phenylamino)carbonyl]-2
 <italic>H</italic>-tetrazolium hydroxide (XTT)
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>27</sup>
 </xref> and 2-(2-methoxy-4-nitrophenyl)-3-(4-nitrophenyl-5-(2.4-disulfophenyl)-2
 <italic>H</italic>-tetrazolium monosodium salt (WST-8)
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> have been used. Of these tetrazolium salts, MTT is the only one able to pass the cell membrane, due to its lipophilic side groups and positive net charge;
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> XTT and WST-8 cannot. Tetrazolium salts are reduced by mitochondrial or cell plasma enzymes like oxidoreductases, dehydrogenases, oxidases and peroxidases using NADH, dihydronicotinamide-adenine dinucleotide phosphate (NADPH), succinate or pyruvate as electron donors.
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> With MTT as substrate, purple needle-like formazan crystals are produced in the cell that will destroy the cell's integrity and eventually lead to cell death because they are unable to pass the cell membrane.
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> To quantify the formazan production, a 30-min cell lysis step with isopropanol containing 5% 1M hydrochloric acid is needed to release the formazan dye.
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> To overcome this lysis step, tetrazolium derivatives that produce water-soluble products such as XTT and WST-8 have been developed.
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> The solubility was achieved by introducing negative-charged sulfone groups to the phenyl rings.
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> Due to this modification, most of the dyes are unable to pass through cell membranes and the reduction of these dyes is therefore mainly performed extracellularly.
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> The electron transfer necessary for reduction of the tetrazolium salts is transduced by electron mediators like menadione and 2-methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone.
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> The only tetrazolium salt used in the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> susceptibility assays for mycetoma causative agents is XTT (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">1</xref>B).
</p>
