<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Oxidative stress is the imbalance between reactive oxygen species (ROS) production and the endogenous capacity to rapidly detoxify reactive by-products. It was suggested to play a significant role in atherosclerosis pathogenesis, profoundly contributing to vascular dysfunction and atherogenesis. According to current understanding, endothelial dysfunction in both coronary and peripheral arteries is a consequence of prolonged and/or repeated exposure to cardiovascular risk factors that induce oxidative stress (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>). In this view, the overproduction of ROS showed a clear link to the oxidative damage of vascular endothelium (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>) by promoting vascular cell proliferation, migration, inflammation, apoptosis, necrosis, and, as a result, thrombosis of atherosclerotic plaques (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>). Several studies indicate that oxidative stress is able to generate various oxidized lipids that cause vascular damage and induce lipid accumulation (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>–
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>). The oxidation of the lipid part of low-density lipoprotein (LDL) results in conformational changes facilitating its uptake by monocytes/macrophages, leading to the formation of foam cells and intracellular lipid retention. The precise mechanisms of lipid oxidation are still poorly understood. Moreover, oxidation can facilitate the disruption of high density lipid (HDL) functions, which ameliorate endothelial dysfunction, including activation of endothelial nitric oxide synthase (eNOS) leading to the increase of nitric oxide availability in the endothelial cells, endothelial repair, apoptosis, endothelial adhesion molecule/chemokine expression, and endothelial pro-thrombotic activation (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>). Also, the association of oxLDL with alterations in homeostasis of endothelial cells that occur via the suppression of the important endothelial microRNAs (miRNAs) was reported (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>). The miRNAs regulate endothelial regeneration at atherosclerosis-susceptible sites, and provide a link between endothelial damage and inflammation mediating an inflammatory response and lipid retention in macrophages during the atherosclerotic process (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>). In addition, the implication of oxidized low-density lipoprotein (oxLDL) in the proinflammatory responses, therefore, contributes to endothelial dysfunction development and atheroma plaque formation, as demonstrated by a number of studies (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>–
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>).
</p>
