<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In a study conducted by Manandhar et al. that evaluated methanolic extracts from various 
 <italic>Oxalis</italic> species against pathogenic bacteria, as well as 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> and 
 <italic>Rhizopus</italic> spp., only 
 <italic>O. corniculata</italic> extract was effective against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, while other bacteria, such as 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, as well as fungi, were not susceptible to this extract. In their analysis, the results of agar well diffusion and microdilution tests were not consistent [
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. In a study by Das et al. the antibacterial activity of 
 <italic>O. corniculata</italic> aqueous extract as biofabricated silver nanoparticles (AgNPs) against UTI-causing bacteria was many times higher than normal extract [
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Rahman et al. found that methanolic extract had more bacteriostatic activity against Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria than ethanolic extract, but the bacteriostatic activity of both extracts was lower than that of the cephachlore antibiotic [
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. In a different experiment, the antibacterial activity of 
 <italic>O. corniculata</italic> leaf methanolic extract was reported to be greater than that of other organic extracts, as well as erythromycin and nalidixic acid, against a variety of bacteria, resulting in the highest rate of inhibition against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. In a study that was almost similar to the previous two, the more potent activity of 
 <italic>O. corniculata</italic> methanolic extract was reported in most cases, while chloroform, petroleum ether, and benzene extracts had no effect on at least eight human pathogenic bacteria. Interestingly, the effect of ethanolic extract on 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> was greater than that of methanolic extract alone, and the sensitivity of bacteria to two antibiotics was higher than that of both extracts when compared to gentamicin and streptomacin. According to phytochemical analysis, the contents of compounds such as phenolic compounds and flavonoids are higher in methanolic and ethanolic extracts [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
