<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Complementary and alternative medicines are used by 60–80% of developing countries because they are one of the most prevalent sources of medicine worldwide [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>–
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>]. Essential oils are also one of the most popular natural products, with one of their main applications being their use in dermatology [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>–
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>]. An overview of the research articles about effectiveness of essential oils in topical application states its use for the treatment of infections caused by bacteria, fungi, or viruses in the most cases [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>]. Natural topical preparations containing thyme essential oil could be a valuable alternative to antifungal and antibacterial drugs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</span> L. (Lamiaceae) is an aromatic and medicinal plant containing essential oil and is widely used all over the world for its expectorant, antibroncholitic, antispasmodic, and other properties. Antimicrobial properties of plant essential oils were revealed a long time ago, but researches are expanded and complements acknowledged findings. Recent articles present the beneficial properties in nature as biofungicide: thyme essential oil is active against
  <span class="italic"> Mycosphaerella graminicola</span>—the pathogen today causes one of the most important diseases of wheat [
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>]. Activity against microorganisms is widely published: against
  <span class="italic"> Staphylococcus aureus</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Salmonella typhimurium</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Escherichia coli</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Klebsiella pneumoniae</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Enterococcus faecalis</span>, and
  <span class="italic"> Candida albicans</span> [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>];
  <span class="italic"> Staphylococcus epidermidis</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Streptococcus </span>sp., and
  <span class="italic"> Pantoea </span>sp. [
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>]; and
  <span class="italic"> Bacillus </span>spp.
  <span class="italic">, Shigella </span>spp.
  <span class="italic">, Trichophyton </span>spp. (nail and scalp isolated),
  <span class="italic"> Microsporum </span>spp.
  <span class="italic">, Aspergillus niger, </span>and
  <span class="italic"> Rhodotorula rubra </span>[
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>]. The essential oils are natural, nontoxic, nonpollutive, and biodegradable compounds with broad spectrum of antimicrobial activity, low risk of side effects after their use, and low risk of resistance development by microorganisms [
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>]. In this investigation, the main goal was focused on activity against
  <span class="italic"> Candida albicans. </span>Yeasts may act as opportunistic pathogens and can cause candidiasis at several different anatomical sites [
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>]. Essential oils demonstrating noteworthy activity against this organism are quite extensively investigated and most oils used in dermatology have been tested against this pathogen [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A typical essential oil may contain 20 to 80 phytochemicals [
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>]. Thyme has numerous chemotypes named according to the major compound, for example, thymol, carvacrol, terpineol, and linalool. Thyme essential oil consisted primarily of thymol (38.1%), p-cymene (29.1%), g-terpinene (5.2%), linalool (3.7%), and carvacrol (2.3%) [
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>]. It has been demonstrated that the biological effects of
  <span class="italic"> Thymus vulgaris</span> are mainly due to the presence of phenolic compounds, especially thymol and carvacrol [
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>]. Thymol content in thyme essential oil is much higher than carvacrol content. This compound shows 30 times higher antiseptic effects and four times lower toxicity than phenol [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thyme essential oil is a clear yellow or very dark reddish-brown liquid with a pungent smell of thyme easily mixed with liquid paraffin and vegetable oils. In view of these properties, the form of oleogel was formulated. The majority of oleogel applications reported in the pharmaceutical area were related to transdermal systems, topical bases, and preparations intended for percutaneous absorption [
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>]. Lipophilic gels are popular in the pharmaceutical industry for simple production technology, long-term stability, and new wide range of gelators. In comparison with emulsions, oleogels have better viscosity and spreadability; the high lipid content of the products causes an optimal reduction of any skin roughness, beneficial for skin protection purposes [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anhydrous colloidal silica is suitable for the formulation of oleogel with desired texture and chemical and physical stability. The clear gel is formed when the material is characterized by a similar refractory index as Aerosil (1.48). Incorporation of the silica into oil leads to an increase in viscosity, which is brought about by hydrogen bonding between the silica particles: 5–10 percent silica imparts a paste-like consistency on a range of oils [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>]. Liquid paraffin and olive oil were chosen for the oleogel formulation with the goal of evaluating the influence of the oil origin on the texture and stability. The composition of oleogel was optimized with response surface central composite design in order to get desirable textural properties.
 </p>
</sec>
