<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7">Two main hypotheses have been proposed to explain the role of mycorrhizal fungi in plant invasions, both of which are based on the invasive plants interacting differently with AM fungi relative to native plants: (i) the ‘
 <italic>degraded mutualism hypothesis</italic>’
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup> and (ii) the ‘
 <italic>enhanced mutualist hypothesis</italic>’
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>. The degraded mutualism hypothesis indicates invasive plants either do not form AM (e.g., Brassicaceae or Proteaceae), or are poorly colonized with low dependency on AM fungi in its new range, thereby suppressing AM fungal abundance. By doing so, invasive plants strongly affect mycorrhizal symbiosis of native mycorrhizal plants, often reducing native plant competitiveness
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. (ii) The ‘
 <italic>enhanced mutualist hypothesis</italic>’
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup> indicates invasive plants receive greater benefit from the symbiosis than native plants, altering native AM fungal communities and increasing invasive species competitiveness
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, invasive plants in their new range may parasitize local CMNs, deriving disproportionally large benefits compared to their symbiotic costs at the expense of competing native plants. CMNs have been shown to preferentially transfer mineral nutrients (
 <sup>15</sup>N and P) to an invasive plant, with less transferred to the native species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup>. CMNs mediation of invasive and native plants may be crucial to the understanding of invasion success or naturalization of an invasive plant and concomitant ‘spread
 <italic>’</italic>: these aspects of invasion have not currently been widely studied.
</p>
