<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0140">Alkaloids are plants secondary metabolites containing nitrogen atoms and are isolated from some plant families, amongst which these families are Solacaneae, Rubiaceae and Fabaceae. Many authors have reported the nematicidal activity of alkaloids (
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Rao et al., 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Chitwood, 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Ntalli and Caboni, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Kahkeshani et al., 2019</xref>). Four isoquinoline were isolated from the crude extracts of the aerial parts of 
 <italic>Macleaya cordata,</italic> this plant has been a source for alkaloids. These compounds i.e. allocryptopine, chelerythrine, protopine and sanguinarine, were evaluated against nematodes i.e. 
 <italic>Bursaphelenchus xylophilus</italic>, 
 <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> and 
 <italic>M. incognita.</italic> Three of these alkaloids (allocryptopine, chelerytherine and sanguinarine) exerts significant nematicidal activity with a median lethal concentration (LC50) values as 37.45, 28.52 and 34.50 μg/ml, respectively against 
 <italic>B. xylophilus</italic>; 38.90, 22.78 and 40.25 μg/ml against 
 <italic>C. elegans</italic> and 76.56, 67.52 and 61.00 μg/ml against 
 <italic>M. incognita (</italic>
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2012</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">Wen et al. (2013)</xref> reported a bioguided assay column chromatography was carried out to identify compounds in 
 <italic>Cephalotaxus fortune</italic> twigs and leaves with nematicidal activity. The isolated compound called drupacine and the crude alkaloid extract suppress the plant-parasitic nematode hatch, activity of mixed life stages, and population numbers on plant roots. The roots of 
 <italic>Waltheria indica</italic> exhibited strong nematocidal activity against 
 <italic>Meloidogyne incognita</italic> hence study was carried out to characterized the constituents responsible for this significant activity (
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Jang et al., 2019</xref>). Three alkaloid compounds, they are 4-quinolone alkaloids i.e. waltherione A, waltherione C and 5′-methoxywaltherione A., were ecofriendly and exhibited good nematicdal activity. Alkaloids contained in plants have been noticed to affect the multiplication of plant-parasitic nematodes and the plants have been confirmed by many authors as nematicidal plants (
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Perrett and Whitfield, 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Kusano et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Srivastava et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Matsuhashi et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Sobkowiak et al., 2011</xref>). A common plant in West Africa countries 
 <italic>Tithonia diversifolia</italic> (Hemsl.) A. Gray is very rich in alkaloids. Authors have assessed its crude alkaloid fraction and they discovered that it suppresses egg hatching of 
 <italic>M. incognita</italic> by 98 % from the second day after the necessary incubation and displayed 100 % inhibitory effect after 9 days. 
 <italic>Tithonia</italic> extracts' treatment at the rate of 30 tons/ha on yam (
 <italic>Discoria rotundata</italic>) in the greenhouse experiments significantly curbed the growth of 
 <italic>M. incognita</italic> (5,000 eggs/plant) reproduction, number of eggs, and juveniles, as well as root gall index (
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Odeyemi and Adewale, 2011</xref>). Hence, 
 <italic>B. verticillata</italic> could display a significant antinemic activity since it is alkaloid containing plant.
</p>
