<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In addition to volatile oils of 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> plants, the volatile oils of other plants (Labiatae, Asteraceae and Lauraceae) are also effective at inhibiting 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> postharvest pathogens fungi (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-08-00026-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>). The most active ones are volatile oils such as laurel, clove, oregano, cinnamon and mint. CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> supercritical fluid extraction of laurel oil [
 <xref rid="B27-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] has a good inhibitory effect on postharvest pathogenic fungi, and good results at a concentration of 200 μg/mL. The chemical components of laurel oil were analyzed by GC-MS, and mainly contains 1.8-cineole, linalool, terpineol acetate, methyl eugenol, linalyl acetate, eugenol (21), sabinene, β-pinene and α-terpineol. Yigit et al. [
 <xref rid="B14-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] studied the inhibitory effect of volatile oils from five plant spices on 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum</italic> and the preservation effect of 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic>. Cumin volatile oil can completely inhibit the growth of mycelium and spore germination. Coriander, rosemary, wild thyme and dill volatile oils also have a certain antifungal effect (mycelial growth inhibition rate is 70–80%). During in vivo experiments, 900 ppm thyme essential oil was found to have a 50% inhibition rate, and other volatile oils had no effect. The results showed that the extracts of essential oil had some differences in fungus inhibition in vitro and in vivo. Hall et al. [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>] studied the inhibitory activity of several essential oils on 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum in vitro</italic>. Results indicated that all essential oils (cinnamon leaf, lemongrass, spearmint, clove leaf and cumin) inhibited the growth (colony and diameter) of both pathogens over untreated PDA plates, but the inhibition was the strongest by clove and cinnamon leaves oil. Tripathi et al. [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>] screened the antifungal activity of twenty plants’ volatile oils against 
 <italic class="italic">P. italicum</italic>. At the concentration of 500 μg/mL, thirteen plants showed the activity of completely inhibition of mycelium growth. Among them, the IC50 of 
 <italic class="italic">Ocimum canum</italic>, wild mint and ginger are 100, 500 and 200 μg/mL, respectively. This is far less than the positive control fungicide benzimidazole (3000 μg/mL). The MIC and MFC concentrations of the peppermint volatile oil [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>] against 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum</italic> were 2.25 mg/mL and 4.5 mg/mL, respectively. Soylu et al. [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>] studied the inhibitory effect of volatile oil of five Turkish plants (oregano, fennel, artemisia, laurel and lavender) on 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum</italic>. Oregano and fennel are most active, the concentrations required to completely inhibit mycelial growth and germ tube elongation was 64 μg/mL and 352 μg/mL, respectively. The other three volatile oils at a concentration 352 μg/mL partially inhibited the elongation of the tube of 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum</italic>. Zhang et al. [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] when testing for antimicrobial activities of 
 <italic class="italic">Melaleuca alternifolia</italic> essential oils showed that mycelial growth and conidial germination were clearly affected by these oils treatments, indicating that these concentrations affected various stages of the development of 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">P. italicum</italic>. 
</p>
