<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">High salinity in the plant environment produces high ratios of reactive oxygen species (ROS) that may damage plant cells. Plants produce non-enzymatic antioxidants such as phenols (e.g., flavonoids) that play a pivotal role in detoxyifying signlet oxygen, hydroxyl radical, hydrogen peroxide, and others (Gupta and Huang, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; Rakhmankulova et al., 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>; AbdElgawad et al., 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Rosemary plants subjected to salinity at 2,000 and 4,000 ppm NaCl showed higher antioxidant activities in their leaves extracts and their essential oils compared to NaCl-untreated plants. Also, SA treated plants with 100–300 ppm and grown under saline irrigation at 2,000–4,000 ppm NaCl showed higher antioxidant activities in leaves extracts and essential oils than SA-untreated plants. The higher antioxidant activities in leaf extracts of plants subjected to high salinity levels and/or SA treatments at 100–300 ppm are associated with higher composition of phenols. Previous reports indicated that SA application may protect the photosynthesis by reducing the oxidative stress (Ananieva et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>; Krantev et al., 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). In addition, SA may enhance stress tolerance by improving their antioxidant activities (Horváth et al., 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>). The higher antioxidant activities in the essential oils of plants treated with high saline (2,000 and 4,000 ppm NaCl) and/or SA sprays compared to control might be explained by the changes in the chemical composition of the essential oil itself as well as the probable higher antioxidant activities of the fluctuating essential oils main components. Elansary et al. (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) reported fluctuations in the main oil constitutes of 
 <italic class="italic">Ocimum basilicm</italic> (Lamiaceae) subjected to water stress. The fluctuation of the main oil constitutes (e.g., phenolic compounds) had been associated with SA application in other plants such as in 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus daenensis</italic> Celak (Lamiaceae) subjected to drought stress (Pribalouti et al., 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) and in 
 <italic class="italic">Melissa officinallis</italic> (Lamiaceae) under normal conditions (da Silva et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
