<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among the antiviral effects of the plant-based bioactive compounds are papain-like protease (PL
 <sup>pro</sup>) and 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> inhibitions. Both proteases are crucial in the viral life cycle. Therefore, inhibition of these proteases observed in many medicinal plants would then curb the viral replication. 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> is a major protease in coronavirus. It is involved in catalytic cleavage of the viral polyproteins at 11 cleave sites, producing 12 individual viral proteins which then form functional complexes essential in viral replication [
 <xref rid="B164-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>]. Biflavonoids like amentoflavone, apigenin, and luteolin, purified from 
 <italic>Torreya nucifera</italic>, inhibit 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> function [
 <xref rid="B165-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>]. Polyphenols purified from the most active chloroform fraction of 
 <italic>Broussonetia papyrifera</italic> roots selectively exhibit higher inhibitory activity against PL
 <sup>pro</sup> than 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>, and papyriflavonol is among the compounds that has the highest inhibitory effects on PL
 <sup>pro</sup> with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 3.7 µM [
 <xref rid="B153-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. Xanthoangelol, an alkylated chalcone isolated from the ethyl acetate soluble fraction of 
 <italic>Angelica keiskei</italic> leaves, is also active against both 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> and PL
 <sup>pro</sup> with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 11.4 and 1.2 µM, respectively [
 <xref rid="B152-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>]. Diarylheptanoid compounds isolated from the ethanol extract of 
 <italic>Alnus japonica</italic> barks also exhibited dose-dependent inhibitory effects against PL
 <sup>pro</sup>. Among the compounds, hirsutenone showed the highest effect with IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 4.1 µM [
 <xref rid="B166-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>]. In another study, sinigrin, indigo emodin, and hesperetin isolated from the water extract of 
 <italic>Istatis indigotica</italic> inhibited 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> of SARS-CoV via cell-based cleavage and cell-free cleavage assays [
 <xref rid="B151-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>]. Cell-free cleavage assay is an enzyme immunoassay to detect anti-3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> effect by the plant extract. In this assay, viral purified recombinant 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> expressed in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> is incubated with a substrate fusion protein (cleavage substrate) and plant extract before the detection of non-cleavage substrate protein using enzyme immunoassay. On the other hand, purification of 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> is not necessary in a cell-based assay. Plasmid that carries 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>, cleavage substrate, and luciferase is co-transfected with a vector like pEGFP-N into cells, and then later the luciferase activity is determined to estimate the cleavage by the viral 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> [
 <xref rid="B151-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>]. Based on these reports, it seems that the isolated polyphenols displayed greater suppression on PL
 <sup>pro</sup> than on 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> to exert their anti-SARS-CoV effects, suggesting that these compounds may be effective in inhibiting coronavirus replication.
</p>
