<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Lophatherum gracile</italic> is distributed in the south region of the Yangtze River in China, as well as in India, Sri Lanka, Myanmar, Malaysia, Indonesia, new guinea island and Japan, and it is wild in the valley, stream, woodland, forest edge and gully edge (Institute of Drug Control &amp; South China Institute of Botany 
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">1963</xref>; Editorial Committee of flora of China 
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). 
 <italic>Lophatherum gracile</italic> belongs to 
 <italic>Gramineae</italic> family and is a perennial herb. Its dried stems and leaves can be used for medicine to clinically clear heat, disinhibit dampness, and treat inflammation (Editorial Committee of flora of China 
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Y. Chen 
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Wang et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Lai et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Its leaves are rich in flavonoids, phenolic acids and polysaccharides (Xue et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Zhang 
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Tang et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>;). Through modern pharmacological analysis, it is found that 
 <italic>Lophatherum gracile</italic> has antibacterial, anticancer, anti-aging and diuretic effects (M. Chen et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Liu 
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Xue et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Huang and Cronk 
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Istiqomah et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). It can protect liver and myocardium (Kim et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Lin et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Fu and Chen 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The ethanol extract of 
 <italic>Lophatherum gracile</italic> has antiviral activity against respiratory syncytial virus infection (L. Chen et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). To identify 
 <italic>Lophatherum gracile</italic> accurately and then guarantee the medicinal quality, herein the complete chloroplast genome of 
 <italic>Lophatherum gracile</italic> was sequenced by using next-generation technology to study the taxonomy for 
 <italic>Lophatherum gracile</italic>.
</p>
