<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The total phenol content in the EOs was determined by the Folin-Ciocalteu spectrometric method. The amount of total content of phenols for both oils was moderate with a value of 63.7 ± 10.7 for EO_LS and significantly higher (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) 163.6 ± 10.7 mg Gallic acid equivalent/g for CA_EO respectively. The FRAP method is based on the reduction of the Fe
 <sup>3+</sup>-TPTZ (iron-tripyridyltriazine) complex, to Fe
 <sup>2+</sup>-TPTZ, that is, it measures the capacity of the EO to reduce Fe
 <sup>3+</sup> to Fe
 <sup>2+</sup>. For this assay the EO of LS was significantly more effective (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the reduction of the complex Fe
 <sup>3+</sup> with a value of 229.8 ± 11.1 mg Trolox equivalent/g EO, while the CA_EO presents values of 166.8 ± 27.9 mg Trolox equivalent/g EO respectively. Two complementary techniques were used to evaluate the potential free radical scavenger of EOs using the DPPH and ABTS radicals. When comparing the IC
 <sub>50</sub> values, it was observed that both EOs exhibit moderate DPPH radical scavenging activity. The values for CA_ EO was 417.8 ± 5.8 µg/mL and 492.7 ± 11.1 µg/mL for LS_EO. Both oils scavenged the DPPH radical in a concentration-dependent manner. Neither of the two oils was as effective as the Trolox antioxidant (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 11.7 ± 2.1 µg/mL). The CA_EO showed a significantly (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) greater ability to inhibit the ABTS radical compared to the LS_EO with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 203.0 ± 12.8 µg/mL and 401.2 ± 8.7 µg/mL respectively (
 <xref rid="molecules-25-05600-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Both EOs showed a significantly (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) lower inhibitory activity than Trolox (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 35.6 ± 1.5 µg/mL). While no phenolic compounds were found and considering that CA_EO has a higher antioxidant potential than EO_LS, this could be attributed to compounds such as α-terpineol, γ-terpinene, β-phellandrene whose activity had been previously described by Amorati [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-05600" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. It could be inferred that the antioxidant activity of the 
 <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> oil is mainly due to the presence of its major compounds, namely 1,8-cineole (63.8%) [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-05600" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Eucalyptol (1,8-cineole) showed various degrees of reducing power, radical scavenging and chelating capacity, in addition to its DNA-protective capacity [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-05600" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Moreover, the high value of the reducing power indicated that the EOs components are able to act as electron donors and reduce the oxidized intermediate of lipid peroxidation so that they can act as primary and secondary antioxidants [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-05600" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].
</p>
