<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Beside the invasibility of the ecosystems, the attributes of IAAPs play a major role for successful invasion. 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2019.01747" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Szabó et al.</ext-link> explored the eco-physiology of two invasive elodeids (
 <italic>Elodea canadensis</italic> and 
 <italic>E. nuttallii</italic>) as a key to understanding their relative invasiveness. Their investigation of the combined effects of nutrient and light environment demonstrated that relative growth rate, chlorophyll concentration, and efficiency of photosystem II provide 
 <italic>E. nuttalli</italic> the ability to replace congeneric species in the invaded sites. Similarly, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2019.00647" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Tóth et al.</ext-link> discussed the roles of physiological and ecological traits in explaining the differentiated performances of invasive macrophytes, obtaining evidence on the existence of key adaptive responses of IAAPs. Importantly, 
 <italic>Ludwigia hexapetala</italic>—one of the most invasive IAAPs globally—showed exceptionally high photosynthetic efficiency, resulting in an elevated tolerance to high light intensities. Both papers reinforce the direct implication of plant traits for the invasiveness of IAAPs, suggesting the importance to gain knowledge on this topic. In this respect, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2020.00422" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Asaeda et al.</ext-link> have investigated habitat preference of 
 <italic>Egeria densa</italic>, focusing on physiological stress proxies. Based on the tissue concentrations of hydrogen peroxide (H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>), it is possible to define critical thresholds for the species survival in terms of flow velocity and light intensity, with relevant implications for designing management solutions to counteract the spread of IAAPs.
</p>
