<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Triterpenoids in apples have various activities such as anti-tumor, anti-oxidation, and immunity enhancement, but it is difficult for traditional edible methods to make full use of triterpenes [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-09-01408" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. At present, the development and utilization of triterpenoids are insufficient, and the beverages with triterpenes have not yet been seen. As apple triterpenes have a particular bitter taste, adding other plant-derived sweeteners can adjust the sugar-acid ratio of the beverage and improve the taste of the beverage [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-09-01408" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Compounding konjac gum and xanthan gum can increase the stability of the beverage. Functional beverages have huge market demand, and the development of an apple triterpene beverage has broad prospects [
 <xref rid="B81-plants-09-01408" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. With the rapid development of the fruit juice processing industry, the discharge of pomace is gradually increasing. Apple pomace is acidic and piled together will quickly ferment and deteriorate, which wastes resources and pollutes the environment. Using biological fermentation technology and suitable combination of microbial composite strains, the nutritional value of the peel and pomace after biological fermentation is greatly improved and has advantages in food products [
 <xref rid="B82-plants-09-01408" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. In addition to the significantly increased crude protein content, the product also contains beneficial micro-ecological factors, which has become an excellent green biological feed with dual characteristics of protein feed and micro-ecological preparation. In some animal studies, Skinner et al. (2018) have shown that apple pomace has the potential to be a safe livestock feed additive and its concentrations within the established safety thresholds for human consumption. When compared to many other commonly consumed fruits and veggies in countries like the United States, apples had the second-highest level of antioxidant activity. Apples are considered second after cranberry for the total concentration of phenolic compounds. However, apples could be considered a classical healthy diet as they contain the highest portion of free phenolics when compared to other fruits such as strawberry, cranberry, red grape, pear, peach, orange, pineapple, banana, lemon, and grapefruit [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-09-01408" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Commercial development of apple pomace for human consumption requires more research focusing on standardized methods of nutrient reporting, mechanistic studies, and human clinical trials in the future [
 <xref rid="B83-plants-09-01408" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Yet, the presence of phytochemicals (flavonoids) in a vast number of apples or its products can be a significant source of these nutrients in average daily diets of a person in Europe [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-09-01408" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].
</p>
