<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Many studies investigate the composition and biosynthesis of essential oils in sweet basil. We observed a significant interaction between the fungi and the heavy metal treatments on the linalool, eucalyptol and methyl chavicol concentrations (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" class="xref">5</xref>). A clear increase in linalool and eucalyptol concentration was visible when the roots were inoculated with 
 <italic class="italic">R. irregularis</italic> irrespective of the heavy metal treatment. Even though, the mechanisms are not very well studied, we suspect that the increase of certain essential oils in sweet basil inoculated with AMF might be due to increased nutrient uptake. However, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Copetta et al. (2006)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Khaosaad et al. (2006)</xref> suggested that an altered P uptake is not be responsible for variations observed in the essential oil production in plants belonging to the 
 <italic class="italic">Lamiaceae</italic> family. A possible explanation might be that methyl chavicol and eugenol belong to the phenylpropenes which have a different biosynthesis pathway than the terpenes linalool and eucalyptol. 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Prasad et al. (2011)</xref> found an increase in linalool content in the presence of lead, but methyl chavicol levels were unaffected in their study. Even though they examined 
 <italic class="italic">O. basilicum</italic> in a pot experiment, differences in their experimental conditions such as soil structure, plant age and heavy metal content prevent direct comparison to our results. Moreover, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hristozkova et al. (2015)</xref> found that different isolates of 
 <italic class="italic">F. mosseae</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. claroideum</italic> have changing effects on the composition of essential oils in 
 <italic class="italic">O. majorana</italic>, supporting our hypothesis that the AM fungus is the active component affecting essential oil biosynthesis. Research on the ability of fungi to produce bioactive fungal metabolites is of high interest for the production of organic crops (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rai et al., 2014</xref>).
</p>
