<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33">Evaluation of the effectiveness of risk minimisation programmes became mandatory with amendments to the EU’s pharmaceutical legislation in 2012, with updated guidelines highlighting the importance of evaluation of effectiveness of aRMMs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Studies have found that effectiveness of aRMMs is evaluated through routine pharmacovigilance for more than half of the products with aRMMs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Recent reviews of studies evaluating the effectiveness of product-specific risk minimisation measures have shown heterogeneous methodology and mixed study outcomes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. In one review of effectiveness evaluation studies, the outcome of effectiveness evaluations led to discontinuation of the aRMMs under investigation in 9% of effectiveness evaluation studies. Further action such as updates to the content or improved distribution or follow-up assessment was required following half of the evaluations, and the evaluation did not lead to any changes in the remaining 40% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. However, these reviews concerned effectiveness evaluations in a subset of medicines (those intended for chronic treatment) or have been conducted using data available in the EU PAS register [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. They may not provide an exhaustive overview of all effectiveness studies performed in the EU, since registration in the EU PAS register is only mandatory for studies imposed on the MA or studies that are a specific obligation to the MA—effectiveness evaluation studies rarely fall in these categories [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. In our study, effectiveness evaluation was the trigger for only one discontinuation (Hirobriz breezhaler). This effectiveness evaluation study was not registered in the EU PAS register.
</p>
