<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The adipose tissues of diabetic and obese people have exhibited a rich expression of numerous TLR family members [
 <xref rid="B75-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Activation of TLR2 and TLR4 receptors by free fatty acids (FFA) ends up as insulin resistance [
 <xref rid="B76-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Naringenin inhibits TLR2 expression in adipocytes through activation of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma (PPARγ) [
 <xref rid="B78-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. It also downregulates TNF-α-induced TLR2 expression by decreasing NF-κB and c-Jun NH2-terminal kinase (JNK) pathways in differentiated adipocytes. Further pathology behind the advancement of insulin resistance and diabetes mellitus is the interaction of adipocytes and macrophages in the adipose tissue, which results in the inflammation of adipose tissue. Naringenin counteracts this inflammation by suppression of monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1) and migration of macrophages into adipose tissue [
 <xref rid="B79-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Of all biomolecules, lipids have an inevitable role in the pathogenesis of diabetes mellitus [
 <xref rid="B80-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. A common metabolic anomaly related to diabetes mellitus is dyslipidemia. Research findings have reported various abnormalities in lipid metabolism attended by the risk of cardiovascular arteriosclerosis in DM patients [
 <xref rid="B81-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Naringenin has been reported to have insulin-like effects, according to in vitro studies, which increase the expression of LDL receptor via PI3K-mediated upregulation of SREBP-1 in the cytosol and nucleus of human HepG2 and rat McA-RH7777 hepatoma cells. Naringenin treatment escalates the PI3K activity and reduces insulin receptor substrate-2 (IRS-2) levels. The plausible mechanism for naringenin’s insulin-like effects is probably the increased activity of PI3K [
 <xref rid="B82-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>].
</p>
