<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To date, a large number of Nigerian medicinal plant extracts has been successfully tested and found to show antiprotozoal activity (Lifongo et al., 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Several studies have reported remarkable 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> activity of extracts and fractions of Nigerian plants against 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> spp. (Adebayo and Krettli, 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), 
 <italic>Trypanosoma</italic> spp. (Abiodun et al., 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Nwodo et al., 
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">2015a</xref>), and 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic> spp. (Bello et al., 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Indeed, promising lead compounds have been identified from some of these plants (Amoa Onguéné et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Ntie-Kang et al., 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Bekono et al., 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). However, due to research and resource limitations, the active principles of too many extracts from Nigerian medicinal plants remain unknown, and further studies that would facilitate the translation of the few identified compounds into drug candidates are limited by a lack of funding for such work (Ebiloma et al., 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2018b</xref>). It should be noted that previous reviews have provided a compilation of evidence of antiprotozoal activity in materials collected from Nigerian flora. Other works have also documented bioactive compounds from plants that grow in Nigeria and the wider African continent, but not necessarily isolated from materials collected in the country or the region (Adebayo and Krettli, 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Nwodo et al., 
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">2015a</xref>). With detailed analytical chemistry and bioactivity screening of plant materials collected specifically from Nigeria increasing, it has become opportune to document the compounds isolated from these plants, and their utility for development as antiprotozoal drugs. This would provide a guide for a focused and evidence-based approach for advancement and development of natural compounds from Nigeria and hence, from Africa in general.
</p>
