<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In addition to the above scientific writings, Fern et al. [
 <xref rid="B127-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">127</xref>] in his website has made an extensive report on the traditional uses of 
 <italic class="italic">P. umbellatum</italic>. The leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">P. umbellatum</italic> are extensively applied in various forms to treat different types of ailments as listed below. The leaves are used as an antseptic, emollient, vermifuge and vulnerary; the leaf juice is taken as a diuretic, emmenagogue and galactagogue, used as ear drops to remedy earache or eye drops to remedy conjunctivitis; a decoction of leaves is consumed to treat hypertension, toothache, jaundice, malaria, urinary and kidney problems, syphilis and gonorrhea, leucorrhea, menstrual problems and stomach-ache, used as a wash for feverish children, or applied on wounds and inflamed tumors; the crushed leaves are utilized in the form of an enema to treat rectal prolapse; an infusion of young ground-up leaves is taken to treat severe colic; the aerial parts are commonly given to women to regulate menses and prevent abortion, and; the leaves are also taken in order to expel tapeworms, while suppositories of the leaves are used to rid the body of pinworms, used in massages for relieving migraine and other forms of headache, and are applied in a friction to relieve rheumatic pain, and applied as a poultice on swellings, boils and burns. In Brazil, the leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">P. umbellatum</italic> are used in baths to subdue edema and uterine complaints. The leaves and fruits are used to treat pain in the kidneys, edema, anemia and colic while the fruits of 
 <italic class="italic">P. umbellatum</italic> are chewed with 
 <italic class="italic">P. betle</italic> leaves to treat coughs. On the other hand, the root of 
 <italic class="italic">P. umbellatum</italic> is considered diuretic, febrifuge and stimulant, and also to promote the flow of bile while a decoction of its root is used to improve digestion and to treat dyspepsia, constipation, jaundice, malaria, urinary and kidney problems, syphilis and gonorrhea, leucorrhea, menstrual problems and stomach-ache or applied externally to treat wounds and inflamed tumors. Moreover, the roots are macerated in alcohol and used to treat rheumatism. Meanwhile, a mixture of pounded twigs and seeds, and salt is taken to treat intestinal worms, a tea made from the flower clusters is used in the treatment of coughs.
</p>
