<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The aim of the present work was to synthesise new 13α-oestrone derivatives as potent antiproliferative agents against human cancer cell lines of reproductive origin. Our strategy included the combination of structural elements of our promising antiproliferative or enzyme inhibitor compounds synthesised recently. Ring A was chosen as the subject for transformations and positions C-2, C-3, and C-4 were aimed to modify. Concerning the feasibility of the planned transformations, the order of the reaction steps seemed to be crucial. The activating behaviour of the phenolic OH group enables fast and effective bromination of the aromatic ring; however, the regio- and chemoselectivity is very low. To enhance the selectivity, first the 3-OH group was etherified. We have recently published that bromination of 3-
 <italic>O</italic>-methyl-13α-oestrone with 1 equiv. of NBS in dichloromethane results in a mixture of 2- and 4-bromo regioisomers in a ratio of 1:3
 <sup>17</sup>. Now we carried out the etherification of the phenolic OH group with a dual purpose: to get the two desired monobromo compounds regioselectively in the next step, and to introduce a terminal alkyne function onto C-3-
 <italic>O</italic>. We chose propargyl bromide as the reagent and performed the reaction under the conditions established earlier. The resulting phenolic ether (
 <bold>10</bold>) was suitable for the next bromination step, but the addition reactions on the terminal alkyne moiety had to be avoided. That is why we continued the sequence with the CuAAC reaction of the propargyl derivative (
 <bold>10</bold>) with two different benzyl azides (R = H or 
 <italic>t</italic>-Bu). Azide reagents were selected based on the cell growth-inhibitory results of 3-
 <italic>N</italic>-benzyltriazolylmethyl-13α-oestrone derivatives synthesised and investigated earlier
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref>. It has been established recently, that compound 
 <bold>4a</bold> displayed outstanding antiproliferative action against certain cancer cell lines; however, its 
 <italic>para</italic>-
 <italic>t</italic>-Bu counterpart 
 <bold>4b</bold> did not influence cell growth markedly
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref>. In this study, CuAAC reactions were performed using CuI as catalyst and PPh
 <sub>3</sub> as an accelerating phosphine ligand. The desired triazoles (
 <bold>4a</bold> and 
 <bold>4b</bold>) were formed in excellent yields. The CuAAC reactions were followed by the bromination of the 3-
 <italic>N</italic>-benzyltriazolylmethyl compounds (
 <bold>4a</bold> and 
 <bold>4b</bold>) with 1 equiv. of NBS in dichloromethane. Electrophilic brominations furnished the two 
 <italic>ortho</italic> regioisomers in a ratio of 
 <bold>8:9 </bold>=
 <bold> </bold>2:1 in high yields. Interestingly, regioselectivity of the bromination depends markedly on the nature and size of the C-3-
 <italic>O</italic> function. The difference in regioisomeric ratios compared to those of 3-
 <italic>O</italic>-Me derivatives might be explained by the steric hindrance of a more bulky 3-
 <italic>O</italic> substituent in 3-
 <italic>N</italic>-benzyltriazolylmethyl compounds 
 <bold>4a</bold> and 
 <bold>4b</bold>. In the last step, the 2- and 4-bromo regioisomers were subjected to Hirao couplings. In our earlier study, microwave-assisted conditions for the transformations of 2- and 4-bromo-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-mehyl and −3-
 <italic>O</italic>-benzyl derivatives involved 10 mol% Pd(PPh
 <sub>3</sub>)
 <sub>4</sub> as a catalyst, 1.3 equiv. of phosphite or phosphine oxide, and 3 equiv. K
 <sub>2</sub>CO
 <sub>3</sub> in toluene
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref>. The reaction time and temperature depended on the nature of the 3-
 <italic>O</italic> substituent. The transformations of 3-
 <italic>O</italic>-benzyl ethers required a more apolar solvent (toluene instead of acetonitrile) and harsher reaction conditions (150 °C, 30 min). Based on these experiences, we performed the present couplings in toluene at 150 °C, under microwave irradiation for 30 min. These conditions proved to be excellent for the effective synthesis of the desired phosphonates (
 <bold>13a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold>; 
 <bold>14a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold>, and 
 <bold>15a</bold>), except for that of a 4-bromo derivative bearing a 4′-
 <italic>t</italic>-Bu substituent (
 <bold>15b</bold>). This coupling required longer irradiation (150 °C, 1 h), which might be attributed to steric factors.
</p>
