<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The International Standard Organization (ISO) defines the essential oils (EO) as volatile products extracted from plants by steam distillation, in most cases. They are usually complex mixtures of volatile, lipophilic, liquid, and odoriferous substances and associated with various functions necessary for the survival of the plant in its ecosystem, playing a key role in the defense against microorganisms and predators and in attracting insects and other fertilizing agents. In traditional medicine, essential oils have a long tradition of use [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>, 
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Lamiaceae family has potential in obtaining EO and it plays and important role in various sectors of the economy, for example, the pharmaceutical industry, perfumery, cosmetics, and food. Several biological functions are associated with species by popular medicine, used for the treatment of burns, headache, colic, fever, reports of antiflu activity, antiemetic, carminative, insecticide, repellent, antibacterial, and combat intestinal parasites [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>–
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The genus
  <span class="italic"> Mentha</span>, popularly known in Brazil as “hortelãs, hortelã-pimenta, menta, menta-inglesa, hortelã-apimentada, hortelã das cozinhas and sândalo,” includes 25–30 species that are known mainly due to the characteristic and refreshing taste. It is native to Europe and was brought by settlers to Brazil, where it is cultivated as medicinal plant in gardens [
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>, 
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The literature logs its spasmolytic activities: antivomitive, carminative, stomachic and anthelmintic, topical antibacterial, antifungal, and antipruritic. In the preliminary phytochemical analysis of the essential oil, there was the presence of the main constituents: the majority were menthol, menthone, and menthofuran compounds which were responsible for pleasant odor [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>–
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Amazon region with its immense biodiversity offers a great potential for the discovery of new flavors and products. However, there is great scarcity of chemical and biological activities information associated with plant species due to deficient support in research work in biotechnology. The aim of this study is to evaluate the chemical composition and
  <span class="italic"> in vitro</span> antioxidant, cytotoxic, antimicrobial, and larvicidal activities of the essential oil of
  <span class="italic"> Mentha piperita</span> L. (Lamiaceae).
 </p>
</sec>
