<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Antioxidant Activity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antioxidant activity (ability or antioxidant potential) is a widely used parameter to characterize different biological materials. This activity is related to compounds capable of protecting a biological system against the harmful effects of processes or reactions that cause excessive oxidation involving reactive oxygen species [
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">39</a>, 
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The vast majority of compounds with antioxidant properties have a molecular structure having at least one aromatic ring and a hydroxyl group, including phenols, flavonoids and isoflavones, esters, lignin, coumarins, flavones, and oligomeric proantocianidinas. In mixtures of these compounds, an antioxidant arrangement is produced that may act by different mechanisms to give an effective defense system against free radicals. Alcohols are the second class of oxygenated monoterpenes, which comprise the essential oil, and more active in oxidizing activities [
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mean values of percentage of antioxidant activity (%AA) of essential oils are shown in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The species
  <span class="italic"> M. piperita</span> has significant antioxidant activity and 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.0001 in the concentration of 100 mg·mL
  <span class="sup">−1</span> with % AA 79.9 ± 1.6. The antioxidant activity is associated with the presence of linalool major compound (51.80%). The inhibitory concentration (IC
  <sub>50</sub>) by linear regression presented a value of 0.54 mg·mL
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, showing the strong coefficient correlation (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>) of 0.9770. On the other hand, if polar compounds, such as ascorbic acid (IC
  <sub>50</sub> 0.12 mg·mL
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) compared to the essential oil, were only tested by it, they would be considered weak antioxidants.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of antioxidant activity are similar to previous studies of Derwich et al. [
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>] % AA values ≥ 81.09 in the concentration of 150 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g·mL
  <span class="sup">−1</span> and IC
  <sub>50</sub> ≥ 53.67 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g·mL
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. However, previous studies of essential oil species showed menthol as the major compound, in which the radical scavenging activity is associated with the presence of compounds menthone and menthol, both compounds with the presence of the hydroxyl radical (-OH). The species
  <span class="italic"> M. piperita</span> is described by several authors as a potential antioxidant, and there are also reports of cytotoxic activity. Some authors describe the possible elimination of monoterpene ketones (menthone and isomenthone) and 1,8-cineole in changing the chemical composition of the species [
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
