<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Larvicidal Activity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several studies demonstrate the activity of essential oils and plant extracts against different species of mosquitoes including
  <span class="italic"> A. aegypti </span>[
  <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">49</a>–
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">51</a>]. The study of potential larvicide, insecticide, and repellent of essential oils is an alternative technology to synthetic products destined to vector control, since, to date, there is no vaccine ready for use against the four serotypes of dengue. Active agents at potential larvicide essential oils and plant extracts at LC
  <sub>50</sub> values of &lt;100 ppm are considereed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The researches for vector control come showing the efficiency of the larvicidal effect of essential oils. Some studies detect the effects of the chemical composition of monoterpenes, as well as, some sesquiterpenes, which serve as repellents at toxicity significant to insects but negligible toxicity to mammals. Mixtures of these volatile low molecular weight compounds provide plants, such as
  <span class="italic"> Mentha piperita</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Citrus limon</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Ocimum basilicum</span>, and
  <span class="italic"> Salvia officinalis,</span> with their distinctive odor, which are commercially available, produced, and important ingredients for fragrance and flavor creation because of their specific sensory characteristics [
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">52</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab6" href="#tab6">Table 6</a> refers to the average mortality readings performed in the period of 48 h of the larvicidal activity of essential oils from
  <span class="italic"> M. piperita</span>. The results are significant and expressed in percentage of mortality (%).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the bioassay, the species
  <span class="italic"> M. piperita</span> has a low potential larvicide at LC
  <sub>50</sub> 367.6 ppm, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> (value) &lt; 0.01, and coefficient of determination (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>) of 0.9980; these results are statistically significant. The study is similar to research by Kumar et al. [
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">52</a>]. Reduction of LC
  <sub>50</sub> in periods of 24 or 48 hours (111.9 and 98.66 ppm) in the potential larvicide of the species was observed. The bioactivity is ineffective for the larvae, because they develop from pupas into adults in the 60–72 h period.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oils extracted from various plants have been reported to have larvicidal and repellent properties against
  <span class="italic"> A. aegypti </span>[
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">53</a>, 
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">54</a>]. Although some of the reports are available in relation to repellent potential of the
  <span class="italic"> M. piperita</span> essential oil against insects, the research is of fundamental importance to respect the larvicidal effect evaluation of the mosquito in the preparation of a bioproduct that does not harm the environment.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The evaluation of larvicidal activity is in agreement with studies made by Pavela et al. [
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">54</a>]. That determined the value LC
  <sub>50</sub> &gt; 100 mg·L
  <span class="sup">−1</span> against larvae of
  <span class="italic"> Culex quinquefasciatus</span>, having as a major component the monoterpene which is L-(−)-menthol, in which the participation in the EO differs depending on the genotype of 20.5% to 57.3%, together with carvone (0.0 to 56.8%) and piperitenone oxide (0.0 to 31.8%).
 </p>
</sec>
