<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Serum proteins are key indicator of vital functions, such as humoral defense, coagulation, metabolite transport, and homeostasis [
 <xref rid="B65-animals-11-00982" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Their levels may be influenced by water quality and seasonal changes or by endogenous factors (e.g., hemodilution and reproductive cycle) [
 <xref rid="B66-animals-11-00982" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-animals-11-00982" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. In the present study, serum proteins increased according to the temperature rise, reaching the highest peak when exposed to 21 °C. Further switching the temperature up to 25 °C, serum protein decreased, in particular in fish fed on CD. Our results for serum protein showed similarity with the study of Islam et al. [
 <xref rid="B26-animals-11-00982" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], which found a decreasing trend in sea bass exposed to thermal stress. In response to the environmental fluctuations, proteins are released into circulation where they are catabolized in order to produce ATP, to support gluconeogenesis and to maintain the physiological homeostasis [
 <xref rid="B68-animals-11-00982" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. The activation of protein catabolism exposes fish to immune dysfunction [
 <xref rid="B69-animals-11-00982" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>], skeletal muscle degradation [
 <xref rid="B70-animals-11-00982" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>], growth restriction, and makes fish susceptible to death [
 <xref rid="B71-animals-11-00982" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. On the other hand, the elevated protein levels observed in fish fed on experimental diets may be attributed to EO supplementation, likely due to activation of regulatory and metabolic pathways to protect proteins from degradation. Many studies reported a high protein level and the consequent immuno-stimulating effect in rainbow trout, carp, or catfish treated with carvacrol [
 <xref rid="B72-animals-11-00982" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-animals-11-00982" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-animals-11-00982" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75-animals-11-00982" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>].
</p>
