<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Malar J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Malar J</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Malaria Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1475-2875</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7777528</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3552</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12936-020-03552-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>In vivo anti-malarial activity of the hydroalcoholic extract of rhizomes of <italic>Kniphofia foliosa</italic> and its constituents</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alebachew</surname><given-names>Yonatan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bisrat</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tadesse</surname><given-names>Solomon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1212-8688</contrib-id><name><surname>Asres</surname><given-names>Kaleab</given-names></name><address><email>kaleab.asres@aau.edu.et</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7123.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1250 5688</institution-id><institution>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry and Pharmacognosy, School of Pharmacy, </institution><institution>College of Health Sciences, Addis Ababa University, </institution></institution-wrap>Addis Ababa, Ethiopia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>3</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1"><italic>Kniphofia foliosa</italic> is a flamboyant robust perennial herb which has dense clumps and tick upright rhizomes with leaves at the base. In Ethiopia, it has several vernacular names including <italic>Abelbila</italic>, <italic>Ashenda</italic>, <italic>Amelmela</italic>, <italic>Yeznjero Ageda</italic>, <italic>Shemetmetie</italic> and <italic>Yezinjero Ageda</italic>. The plant is endemic to Ethiopian highlands, where its rhizomes are traditionally used for the treatment of malaria, abdominal cramps and wound healing. In the present study, the 80% methanol extract of <italic>K. foliosa</italic> rhizomes and its constituents are tested against <italic>Plasmodium berghei </italic>in mice<bold>.</bold></p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Isolation was carried out using column and preparative thin layer chromatography (PTLC). The chemical structures of the compounds were elucidated by spectroscopic methods (ESI&#x02013;MS, 1D and 2D-NMR). Peters&#x02019; 4-day suppressive test against&#x000a0;<italic>P. berghei&#x000a0;</italic>in mice was utilized for in vivo anti-malarial evaluation of the test substances.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Two compounds, namely knipholone and dianellin were isolated from the 80% methanolic extract of <italic>K. foliosa</italic> rhizomes, and characterized. The hydroalcoholic extract (400&#x000a0;mg/kg) and knipholone (200&#x000a0;mg/kg) showed the highest activity with chemosuppression values of 61.52 and 60.16%, respectively. From the dose&#x02013;response plot, the median effective (ED<sub>50</sub>) doses of knipholone and dianellin were determined to be 81.25 and 92.31&#x000a0;mg/kg, respectively. Molecular docking study revealed that knipholone had a strong binding affinity to <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> l-lactate dehydrogenase (pfLDH) target.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Results of the current study support the traditional use of the plant for the treatment of malaria.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Kniphofia foliosa</italic></kwd><kwd>Antimalarial activity</kwd><kwd>In vivo</kwd><kwd>Phenolic fractions</kwd><kwd><italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic></kwd><kwd>Knipholone</kwd><kwd>Dianellin</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec2"><title>Background</title><p id="Par15">Malaria is one of the most serious life-threatening infectious diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. It occurs mostly in poor tropical and subtropical areas of the world, where the Africa region accounted for 93% of all malaria cases and 94% of malaria deaths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]<italic>.</italic> Most often, pregnant women and children under five years old are severely affected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. For instance, from the total deaths due to malaria in 2018, 67% or 272,000 were children under 5&#x000a0;years of age. That is nearly 745 children under age 5 daily or one child under five every two minutes dies of malaria in 2018 alone and most of these deaths occurred in sub-Saharan Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. In addition to funding shortfalls and fragile health systems, the major contributor to malarial morbidity and mortality is almost certainly the increasing resistance of malaria parasites to available drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">In Ethiopia, there has been success in the past recent years to reduce malaria burden. However, it is still prevalent in 75% of the country putting over 45 million people at risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The disease accounts for 7% of outpatient visits to health clinics and represents the third largest cause of morbidity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In addition, 8% of global <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> malaria cases occur in Ethiopia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Hence, the fight against malaria in Ethiopia remains a public health priority.</p><p id="Par17">Natural products from plants have played a huge role throughout history in the fight against malaria. For instance, the aqueous extracts of cinchona bark were an effective anti-malarial preparation for more than 300&#x000a0;years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Later, quinine, the major active alkaloid of cinchona was isolated in the 1820s. Similarly, artemisinin was isolated from the cold ether extracts of the leaves of Chinese traditional medicinal herb, <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> in 1972 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Inspired by these, different classes of anti-malarial compounds were isolated from a variety of plant families. Although hundreds of potent anti-malarial compounds were isolated from African traditional medicine, there has not been any clinically successful molecule [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]<italic>.</italic></p><p id="Par18">The genus <italic>Kniphofia</italic> belongs to the family Asphodelaceae which comprises 70 species mainly confined to Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Fifteen of these species have been recorded in Eastern Africa, of which five including <italic>Kniphofia foliosa</italic> are endemic to Ethiopia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The rhizomes of <italic>K. foliosa</italic> are traditionally used for the treatment of abdominal cramps, malaria and wounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Previously, six in vitro active anti-malarial compounds were isolated from roots of <italic>K. foliosa</italic> by Wube et al<italic>.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] and Abdissa et al<italic>.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. In continuation of search for lead anti-malarial compounds from Ethiopian medicinal plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], the in vivo anti-malarial activity of the rhizomes of&#x000a0;<italic>K. foliosa</italic> and its constituents are investigated.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec4"><title>Chemicals and instruments</title><p id="Par19">Chromatographic separations were performed by analytical TLC on Silica gel 60 F254 (0.2&#x000a0;mm thick), Silica gel 60 (0.063&#x02013;0.200&#x000a0;mm) for column chromatography (70&#x02013;230 mesh) (Merck KGaA, Darmstadt, Germany) and solid phase separation on Isolute C<sub>18</sub> columns (10&#x000a0;g; IST, Hengoed, UK). Trisodium citrate was obtained from BDH Chemicals Ltd, England, Giemsa was purchased from ESJAY Chemicals, Maharashtra 401,504, India, and pure chloroquine phosphate was supplied by Ethiopian Pharmaceutical Manufacturing Factory (EPHARM, Ethiopia).</p><p id="Par20">NMR spectra were recorded at 500&#x000a0;MHz for <sup>1</sup>H and 125&#x000a0;MHz for <sup>13</sup>C on a Bruker Avance DMX400 FT-NMR spectrometer (Bruker, Billerica, Massachusetts, USA) using tetramethylsilane (TMS) as internal standard. All spectra were measured in CDCl<sub>3</sub>, except for compound <bold>1</bold>, which was dissolved in CD<sub>3</sub>OD. HRMS were determined on a Shimadzu LC&#x02010;MS Advanced spectrometer (Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan) in the positive and negative modes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Plant material</title><p id="Par21">The rhizomes of <italic>K. foliosa</italic> were collected in February 2017 from Mount Kundi near the city of Ankober in Shewa region of Central Ethiopia and identified by Professor Sebsibe Demisew at the National Herbarium, Addis Ababa University (AAU), Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, where voucher specimens were deposited (Collection number: YA01/2017).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Experimental animals</title><p id="Par22">Healthy, 5&#x02013;6&#x000a0;weeks old Swiss albino mice weighing 20&#x02013;25&#x000a0;g were employed throughout the experiment. Female mice were used for acute toxicity study as per the OECD Guideline 425 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], and either male or female mice were employed for the anti-malarial activity tests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. All mice used for the experiments were obtained either from the animal house of the School of Pharmacy (SoP), AAU or purchased from the Ethiopian Health Nutrition and Research Institute (EHNRI). The animals were maintained under natural lighting conditions (12&#x000a0;h light and 12&#x000a0;h dark cycle) at room temperature and relative humidity of approximately 50%. They were provided with food and water ad libitum and acclimatized for one week before the commencement of the experiment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Rodent parasite</title><p id="Par23">Chloroquine (CQ) sensitive ANKA strain of <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic> was used. The donor mice infected with the parasite was obtained from the EHNRI. The parasites were maintained by serial blood passage from mouse to mouse at 5&#x000a0;days interval. All procedures followed were in accordance with the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] and were approved by the Institutional Review Board of the SoP, College of Health Sciences, AAU.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Extraction, fractionation and isolation</title><p id="Par24">The air-dried powdered rhizomes of <italic>K. foliosa</italic> were soaked in 80% methanol at room temperature for 4&#x000a0;days with occasional shaking. Removal of the organic solvent using rotary evaporator (BUCHI Rotavapor&#x02122; R-300, Switzerland) followed by freeze drying of the remaining water extract yielded a dark red gummy solid. Portion of the dried extract was dissolved in 5% KOH solution and partitioned with chloroform to remove the nonphenolic components. The aqueous phase was acidified with 2% HCl and then further partitioned with chloroform. The chloroform layer was collected and concentrated in a rotary evaporator to give a dried solid designated crude phenolic fraction I. The reddish solid mass (methanol soluble) formed between the acidified aqueous and chloroform layers was collected as phenolic fraction II. Purification of phenolic fraction I by preparative TLC (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Fig. S1) gave KFP-1 (18&#x000a0;mg, 0.048%). Furthermore, portion of the hydroalcoholic extract was fractionated on silicagel flash column chromatography to yield three fractions. Fraction 1 was eluted with 100% chloroform, fractions 2 and 3 with a mixture of chloroform and methanol (1:1), and fraction 4 with 100% methanol. Fraction 3 was concentrated and freeze dried to give viscous solid, which was further purified by sequential PTLC and solid phase extraction on Isolute C<sub>18</sub> columns to give YKFM-2 (14&#x000a0;mg, 0.04%) (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Fig. S2).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Acute oral toxicity testing</title><p id="Par25">Acute oral toxicity study was conducted as per the internationally accepted protocol of OECD Guideline 425 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Fifteen healthy Swiss female albino mice weighing 20&#x02013;25&#x000a0;g were randomly grouped into 3 each having 5 mice. Following 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;h of fasting (food only), one mouse from each group was orally administered 2000&#x000a0;mg/kg of the hydroalcoholic extract, KFP-1 and YKFM-2, consecutively. This was repeated on the remaining mice for the following four days. The mice were then observed individually for any physical or behavioural changes, such as loss of appetite, ruffled fur, lacrimation, mortality, and other signs of toxicity for 4&#x000a0;h. The same procedure was followed for the remaining mice for the next five consecutive days and the results recorded. The follow-up observations were continued for all mice for 14&#x000a0;days.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>In vivo anti-malarial assay</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Inoculation</title><p id="Par26">Blood smear was prepared on microscope slides from blood films taken from the donor (infected) mouse tail. The smear was fixed with methanol and stained with Giemsa to count the parasitaemia of the donor under a microscope (Primo Star, Carl Zeiss, Germany). The mice were then inoculated on day 0 with parasitized erythrocytes obtained from the donor by cardiac puncture using a sterile syringe when the parasitaemia level was 30&#x02013;40%. Blood from the donor was collected on a Petri dish containing 2% trisodium citrate and was immediately diluted with uninfected mouse blood and normal saline in such a way that the final volume contains 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>7</sup> infected erythrocytes/ml of blood. The diluted blood (0.2&#x000a0;ml) was injected into all the experimental mice intraperitoneally (i.p) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>4-Day suppressive test</title><p id="Par27">The standard 4-day suppressive method was used for anti-malarial evaluation of the test substances [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The test was carried out in two phases. The extract and phenol fractions were evaluated in the first phase followed by KFP-1 and YKFM-2 in the second phase. Doses were selected based on the acute toxicity results whereby the middle dose was taken as one tenth of the limit dose which is 200&#x000a0;mg/kg. The higher dose was twice (400&#x000a0;mg/kg) the middle dose and the lower dose was one half (100&#x000a0;mg/kg) of the middle dose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. During the first phase, 60 inoculated mice were randomly grouped into 12 groups each having five mice. Groups 1 served as a negative control (distilled water, Vehicle1, 0.2&#x000a0;ml) for the extract and phenolic fraction 2 treated groups, while group 2 animals were used as a negative control (1% tween 80, Vehicle2, 0.2&#x000a0;ml) for phenolic fraction 1 treated group. The third group which served as a positive control was treated with standard pure chloroquine (25&#x000a0;mg/kg/day). The remaining nine groups were treatment groups and received 100, 200, and 400&#x000a0;mg/kg/day of the hydroalcoholic extract and the two phenol fractions. The dosage regimen for the pure compounds was chosen from the preliminary test results obtained from experiments carried out on a few mice. Similarly, during evaluation of KPF-1 and YKFM-2, 45 inoculated mice were randomly grouped into 9 groups, each containing five mice. The first two groups were negative controls (distilled water, Vehicle3, 0.2&#x000a0;ml) and positive controls (standard pure chloroquine, 25&#x000a0;mg/kg/day). The rest of the groups were treatment groups and received KFP-1 (25, 50, 100 and 200&#x000a0;mg/kg/day) and YKFM-2 (25, 50, 100&#x000a0;mg/kg/day). All the test substances were administered orally using oral gavage. Treatment was started 3&#x000a0;h post-infection (p.i) on day 0 and continued daily for the next 3&#x000a0;days (i.e. from day 0 to day 3). On the fifth day (or day 4), two Giemsa-stained blood smears were prepared from each mice to count the number of parasites under the microscope (Primo Star, Carl Zeiss, Germany) with an oil immersion objective of 100&#x000d7;&#x02009;magnification power [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p><p id="Par28">Mean percent parasitaemia and percent suppression were calculated using the following formulae.<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{\% Parasitaemia }} = \left( {\frac{{\text{Number of parasitized RBC}}}{{\text{Total number of RBC count}}}} \right) \times 100$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>\% Parasitaemia</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Number of parasitized RBC</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Total number of RBC count</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12936_2020_3552_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{\% Suppression }} = \left( {\frac{{{\text{Mean parasitaemia of negative control }}{-}{\text{ Mean parasitaemia of treated}}}}{{\text{Mean parasitaemia of negative control }}}} \right)\times {100}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>\% Suppression</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Mean parasitaemia of negative control</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/><mml:mtext>Mean parasitaemia of treated</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Mean parasitaemia of negative control</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12936_2020_3552_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Body weight and survival time measurements</title><p id="Par29">Body weight of each mouse was measured on day 0 before infection and on day 4. Survival time was recorded from day 1 to day 28 post inoculation. Then, the mean body weight and mean survival time were calculated for each group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Molecular docking study</title><p id="Par30">Docking study was carried out on two crystal structures of <italic>Plasmodium</italic> enzymes plasmepsin II (Protein Data Bank; PDB: 4CKU) and l-lactate dehydrogenase (pfLDH) [PDB: 1LDG], using SeeSar10.0 software (BioSolveIT, Sankt Augustin, Germany). For plasmepsin II, the selected binding site was the binding pocket of a previously designed inhibitor P2FE-400, 5-(1,1-dioxido-1,2-thiazinan-2-yl)-N1-((2S,3R)-3-hydroxy-4-((2-(3-methoxyphenyl)propan-2-yl)amino)-1-phenylbutan-2-yl)-N3,N3-dipropylisophthalamide; while for pfLDH, the cofactor nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NADH) binding site was selected for docking. The HYDE score was used to estimate the binding affinity of the molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par31">Data analysis was carried out using IBM SPSS (Statistical Package for Social Sciences) Statistics for Windows, Version 20.0. Armonk, NY: IBM Corp. Results were expressed as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error of mean (M&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM). The statistical significance was determined by one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey post hoc test to compare percent suppression (activity), mean survival time and percent changes in body weight of the <italic>P. berghei</italic> infected mice among the treatment and control groups. <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec17"><title>Structural elucidation of the isolated compounds</title><p id="Par32">Phytochemical investigation of the rhizome extract of <italic>K. folosia</italic> over silica gel column and PTLC resulted in the isolation of two compounds. Compound <bold>1</bold> (YKFM-2): R<sub>f</sub>: 0.69 (a mixture of EtOAc and <italic>n</italic>-butanol-acetic acid&#x02013;water, upper phase; 4:1:5 in a ratio of 1:1); compound <bold>2</bold> (KFP-1) R<sub>f</sub>: 0.47 (toluene/EtOAc; 5:1).</p><p id="Par33">Compound <bold>1</bold> was obtained as a light red amorphous solid. The positive high resolution-ESI mass spectrum gave a pseudomolecular ion at <italic>m/z</italic> 547.1619 [M&#x02009;+&#x02009;Na]<sup>+</sup> (calcd. <italic>m/z</italic> 547.1791 [M&#x02009;+&#x02009;Na]<sup>+</sup>, corresponding to a molecular formula C<sub>25</sub>H<sub>32</sub>O<sub>12</sub>. In the <sup>1</sup>H NMR spectrum, four proton signals which resonated at &#x003b4; 7.12 (<italic>s</italic>, H-4), 7.28 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.3, 7.3&#x000a0;Hz, H-7), 7.36 (1H, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.2&#x000a0;Hz, H-6) and 7.40 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.3, 8.2&#x000a0;Hz, H-5) indicated the presence of aromatic ring moiety. Three of these proton signals which are multiplets imply that they are found in close proximity (or are adjacent) and the fourth singlet aromatic proton peak at &#x003b4; 7.12 (<italic>s</italic>, H-4) provides clues for the presence of a fused aromatic ring system. The presence of a disaccharide unit in compound <bold>1</bold> was revealed by the typical anomeric proton signals at &#x003b4; 3.31 (1H, <italic>m</italic>, H-4&#x02032;&#x02032;) and 5.05 (1H, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.9&#x000a0;Hz, H-1&#x02032;). The proton peaks from &#x003b4; 5.05 to 2.91 further justify the presence of a disaccharide moiety. The <sup>13</sup>C spectrum region from &#x003b4; 76.82 to 66.59 also confirmed that the compound contains a disaccharide moiety. In addition, the two elevated <sup>13</sup>C sugar signals at &#x003b4; 102.84 and 100.86 indicate that the sugar units are linked through acetal bond. Furthermore, the absence of one CH signal in the sugar region (&#x003b4; 76.82&#x02013;&#x003b4; 66.59) suggests one of the sugar units to be rhamnose. And this was found to be in good agreement with <sup>13</sup>C NMR reports of similar glycosides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Hence, the disaccharide moiety was confirmed to be rhamnose-glucose 1,6 linkage. In addition, the presence of 10 <sup>13</sup>C signals from &#x003b4; 154.71 to &#x003b4; 110.5 implies that the fused aromatic ring system is naphthalene. Six of these carbon signals are absent from DEPT spectrum indicating they are quaternary aromatic carbons. Besides, two of them are elevated (&#x003b4; 154.71 and &#x003b4; 151.49) suggesting that they are oxygenated quaternary aromatic carbons. On the other hand, the two less elevated (&#x003b4; 136.74 and &#x003b4; 113.54) quaternary aromatic carbons are the bridgehead carbons of the fused aromatic system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The remaining two quaternary aromatic carbon signals resonated at &#x003b4; 124.73 (C-2) and &#x003b4; 133.30 (C-3). Lastly, the <sup>13</sup>C signals at 207.7 and 41.3 are the carbonyl carbon and its acetyl methyl. Therefore, based on the above evidence and in comparison with <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR data of the same and related compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], the structure of compound <bold>1</bold> was determined to be dianellin or 1-(1-hydroxy-3-methyl-8-(((2S,3R,4S,5S,6R)3,4,5-trihydroxy-6-((((2S,3S,4S,5S,6R)3,4,5-trihydroxy-6-methyltetrahydro-2H-pyran-2-yl)oxy)methyl)tetrahydro-2H-pyran-2yl)oxy)naphthalen-2-yl) ethanone (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> summarizes the NMR data of compound <bold>1</bold>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Chemical structures of dianellin (<bold>1</bold>) and knipholone (<bold>2</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12936_2020_3552_Fig1_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR data of compound <bold>1</bold> measured in methanol-<italic>d</italic><sub>4</sub></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="3">Present data</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Reference data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Position</th><th align="left">&#x003b4;<sub>C</sub> (ppm)</th><th align="left">&#x003b4;<sub>H</sub> (ppm)</th><th align="left">&#x003b4;<sub>C</sub> (ppm)</th><th align="left">&#x003b4;<sub>H</sub> (ppm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td char="." align="char">151.49</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char">150.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td char="." align="char">124.73</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char">125.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td char="." align="char">133.30</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char">132.8</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td char="." align="char">119.58</td><td align="left">7.12 (1H, <italic>s</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">119.4</td><td align="left">7.21 (1H, <italic>s</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td char="." align="char">122.58</td><td align="left">7.40 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.3, 8.2&#x000a0;Hz)</td><td char="." align="char">122.3</td><td align="left">7.47 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.0, 8.0&#x000a0;Hz)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td char="." align="char">127.20</td><td align="left">7.36 (1H, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.2&#x000a0;Hz)</td><td char="." align="char">127.3</td><td align="left">7.40 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.0, 8.0&#x000a0;Hz)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td char="." align="char">110.51</td><td align="left">7.28 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.3, 7.3, Hz)</td><td char="." align="char">110.7</td><td align="left">7.30 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.0, 8.0&#x000a0;Hz)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td char="." align="char">154.71</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char">154.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9</td><td char="." align="char">113.54</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char">113.2</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10</td><td char="." align="char">136.74</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char">135.7</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1&#x02032;</td><td char="." align="char">102.84</td><td align="left">5.05 (1H, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.9&#x000a0;Hz)</td><td char="." align="char">102.6</td><td align="left">5.04 (1H, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.5&#x000a0;Hz)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2&#x02032;</td><td char="." align="char">73.57</td><td align="left">3.46 (1H, <italic>t</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.8&#x000a0;Hz)</td><td char="." align="char">73.3</td><td align="left">3.39 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3&#x02032;</td><td char="." align="char">76.82</td><td align="left">3.37 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">76.2</td><td align="left">3.36 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4&#x02032;</td><td char="." align="char">70.13</td><td align="left">2.91 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">70.1</td><td align="left">3.18 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5&#x02032;</td><td char="." align="char">76.10</td><td align="left">3.68 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">76.0</td><td align="left">3.59 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6&#x02032;</td><td char="." align="char">66.59</td><td align="left">4.05 ( 1H, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.9&#x000a0;Hz); 3.63 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">66.6</td><td align="left">3.93 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.5, 11.0&#x000a0;Hz); 3.50 (2H, <italic>m</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1&#x02032;&#x02032;</td><td char="." align="char">100.86</td><td align="left">4.71 (1H, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.4&#x000a0;Hz)</td><td char="." align="char">100.7</td><td align="left">4.62 (1H, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;Hz)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2&#x02032;&#x02032;</td><td char="." align="char">70.84</td><td align="left">3.84 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.6, 3.4&#x000a0;Hz)</td><td char="." align="char">70.4</td><td align="left">3.68 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3&#x02032;&#x02032;</td><td char="." align="char">71.03</td><td align="left">3.63 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">70.7</td><td align="left">3.50 (2H, <italic>m</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4&#x02032;&#x02032;</td><td char="." align="char">72.59</td><td align="left">3.31 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">71.9</td><td align="left">3.20 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5&#x02032;&#x02032;</td><td char="." align="char">68.55</td><td align="left">3.52 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">68.4</td><td align="left">3.49 (1H, <italic>m</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6&#x02032;&#x02032;</td><td char="." align="char">16.55</td><td align="left">1.17 (3H, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.2&#x000a0;Hz)</td><td char="." align="char">17.7</td><td align="left">1.12 (3H, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.0&#x000a0;Hz)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ar<underline>CH</underline><sub><underline>3</underline></sub></td><td char="." align="char">18.49</td><td align="left">2.25 (3H, <italic>s</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">19.0</td><td align="left">2.25 (3H, <italic>s</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CO<underline>CH</underline><sub><underline>3</underline></sub></td><td char="." align="char">41.3</td><td align="left">2.97 (3H, <italic>s</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">31.9</td><td align="left">2.52 (3H, <italic>s</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic><underline>C</underline></italic>OCH<sub>3</sub></td><td char="." align="char">207.07</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char">204.4</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>s</italic>, singlet, <italic>d</italic>, doublet, <italic>dd</italic>, doublet of doublets, <italic>m</italic>, multiplet, <italic>br</italic>, broad, <italic>t</italic>, triplet</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par34">Compound <bold>2</bold> was isolated as an orange colored amorphous solid. The molecular formula was determined to be C<sub>24</sub>H<sub>18</sub>O<sub>8</sub> by the positive-ion ESIMS (<italic>m/z</italic> 458.21 [M&#x02009;+&#x02009;Na]<sup>+</sup>), which was also consistent with <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR spectral data. The chelated hydroxyl protons shown as singlet peaks at &#x003b4; 12.6 (1H<italic>, s</italic>, -OH, H-1) and 11.9 (1H<italic>, s</italic>, -OH, H-8) and the typical ABC pattern of the proton peaks at &#x003b4; 7.57 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8, 7&#x000a0;Hz, H-6), 7.55 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7, 1.5&#x000a0;Hz, H-5), 7.21 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8, 1.5&#x000a0;Hz, H-7) indicate the presence of chrysophanol moiety. Besides, the singlet aromatic proton signal present at &#x003b4; 7.28 suggests that it is found adjacent to a substituted aromatic carbon. The <sup>13</sup>C and DEPT spectra of compound <bold>2</bold> also support the presence of chrysophanol moiety [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Moreover, from the <sup>13</sup>C spectrum, additional aromatic carbon signals at &#x003b4; 152.44, 132.72, 125.75, 125.31, and 120.11 together with the <sup>1</sup>H peaks at 14.3 (<italic>s</italic>, OH), 6.19 (<italic>s</italic>, aromatic H), 5.7 (<italic>s</italic> (<italic>br</italic>), OH) and 3.91 (<italic>s</italic>, OCH<sub>3</sub>) indicate the attachment of a methyl etherified acetylphloroglucinol moiety to chrysophanol. These data in comparison with the reported <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR results identify compound <bold>2</bold> as knipholone&#x000a0;(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> summarizes the NMR data of compounds <bold>2</bold>.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR data of compounds <bold>2</bold> in chloroform-<italic>d</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="4">Present data</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Reference data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Position</th><th align="left">&#x003b4;<sub>C</sub> (ppm)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">&#x003b4;<sub>H</sub> (ppm)</th><th align="left">&#x003b4;<sub>C</sub> (ppm)</th><th align="left">&#x003b4;<sub>H</sub> (ppm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">161.69</td><td align="left" colspan="2">12.6 (1H<italic>, s</italic>, &#x02212;OH)</td><td align="left">161.7</td><td align="left">12.53 (1H, <italic>s</italic>, &#x02212;OH)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1a</td><td align="left">115.22</td><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">114.7</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">125.31</td><td align="left" colspan="2">7.28 (1H, <italic>s</italic>)</td><td align="left">124.6</td><td align="left">7.32 (1H, <italic>q, J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.7&#x000a0;Hz)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">152.44</td><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">151.6</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">125.75</td><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">128.5</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">4a</td><td align="left">132.72</td><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">131.6</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">120.11</td><td align="left" colspan="2">7.55 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.5, 7&#x000a0;Hz)</td><td align="left">119.3</td><td align="left">7.56 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.5, 7&#x000a0;Hz)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5a</td><td align="left">134.27</td><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">134.4</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">137.12</td><td align="left" colspan="2">7.57 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7, 8&#x000a0;Hz)</td><td align="left">137.4</td><td align="left">7.75 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7, 8&#x000a0;Hz)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">123.85</td><td align="left" colspan="2">7.21 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.5, 8&#x000a0;Hz)</td><td align="left">123.3</td><td align="left">7.30 (1H, <italic>dd</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.5, 8&#x000a0;Hz)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">159.51</td><td align="left" colspan="2">11.9 (1H, <italic>s</italic>, -OH)</td><td align="left">161.1</td><td align="left">12.0 (1H, <italic>s</italic>, -OH)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8a</td><td align="left">115.37</td><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">115.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">192.68</td><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">192.5</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">182.66</td><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">181.9</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1&#x02019;</td><td align="left">106.07</td><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">104.7</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2&#x02019;</td><td align="left">163.27</td><td align="left" colspan="2">5.7 (1H, <italic>s</italic> (<italic>br</italic>), -OH)</td><td align="left">163.3</td><td align="left">8.95 (1H, <italic>s</italic> (<italic>br</italic>), -OH)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3&#x02019;</td><td align="left">107.14</td><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">107.3</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4&#x02019;</td><td align="left">163.07</td><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">162.4</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5&#x02019;</td><td align="left">90.61</td><td align="left" colspan="2">6.19 (1H, <italic>s</italic>)</td><td align="left">91.2</td><td align="left">6.24 (1H, <italic>s</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6&#x02019;</td><td align="left">162.85</td><td align="left" colspan="2">14.3 (1H, <italic>s</italic>, -OH)</td><td align="left">161.9</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ArCH<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left">21.02</td><td align="left" colspan="2">2..21 (3H, <italic>s</italic>)</td><td align="left">20.4</td><td align="left">2.17 (3H, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>J</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.7&#x000a0;Hz)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">OCH<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left">55.56</td><td align="left" colspan="2">3.91 (3H, <italic>s</italic>)</td><td align="left">55.6</td><td align="left">3.98 (3H, <italic>s</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CO<underline>CH</underline><sub><underline>3</underline></sub></td><td align="left">33.14</td><td align="left" colspan="2">2.70 (3H, <italic>s</italic>)</td><td align="left">32.6</td><td align="left">2.62 (3H, <italic>s</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><underline>C</underline>OCH<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left">202.3</td><td align="left" colspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">202.3</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>s</italic>, singlet, <italic>d</italic>, doublet, <italic>dd</italic>, doublet of doublets,&#x000a0;<italic>q</italic>, quartet, <italic>m</italic>, multiplet, <italic>br</italic>, broad</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Acute oral toxicity</title><p id="Par35">Acute oral toxicity test results of this study documented that the 80% methanol extract of <italic>K. foliosa,</italic> knipholone and dianellin were safe at a dose of 2000&#x000a0;mg/kg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. After 72&#x000a0;h, the animals tolerated the administered dose although immediate mild toxicity signs such as ruffled fur, loss of appetite and slight sleepiness, which disappeared few hours after administration were observed. Also, there was no mortality within 14&#x000a0;days of observation which entails that the LD<sub>50</sub>s of the extract, knipholone and dianellin are above 2000&#x000a0;mg/kg.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Anti-malarial activity of the hydroalcoholic extract</title><p id="Par36">The 80% methanol extract of <italic>K. folosia</italic> showed chemosuppressive effect against <italic>P. berghei</italic> in mice (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). At all dose levels tested, the extract exhibited a statistically significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) dose dependent effect. The extract showed the highest activity with 61.52 and 51.39% suppression at 400 and 200&#x000a0;mg/kg, respectively. Moreover, at doses of 200 and 400&#x000a0;mg/kg, the extract significantly extended the survival days of treated groups compared to the negative controls, indicating that the extract has the capacity to lower the overall pathologic effect of the parasite in mice. However, there was no significant difference in percent change in weight before and after treatment among groups except with the positive control group. According to Deharo et al<italic>.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], anti-malarial activity of the 80% methanol extract of <italic>K. folosia</italic> can be regarded as good since it showed greater than 50% suppression at a dose of 200&#x000a0;mg/kg. Previous studies demonstrated that medicinal plants rich in anthraquinones such as aloes and senna possess notable in vivo anti-malarial activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Anti-malarial activity of the 80% rhizome extract of <italic>Kniphofia folosia</italic> in mice infected with <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Test substances</th><th align="left">Dose (mg/kg/day)</th><th align="left">Percent parasitaemia</th><th align="left">Percent suppression</th><th align="left">Mean survival time (in days)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Vehicle1</td><td align="left">0.2&#x000a0;ml</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">35.9860&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.22034</td><td char="." align="char">0.0000</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.0000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.31623</td></tr><tr><td align="left">KF100</td><td align="left">100&#x000a0;mg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24.2100&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.18037</td><td char="." align="char">32.7200<sup>a*c**d*e*</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.4000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.50990<sup>a**e*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">KF200</td><td align="left">200&#x000a0;mg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">17.4920&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.67964</td><td char="." align="char">51.3900<sup>a*b**e*</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.6000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.92736<sup>a*e*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">KF400</td><td align="left">400&#x000a0;mg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.8480&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.76024</td><td char="." align="char">61.5200<sup>a*b*e*</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.4000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.24495<sup>e*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chloroquine</td><td align="left">25&#x000a0;mg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.0140&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.00600</td><td char="." align="char">99.8000<sup>a*</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">27.2000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.58310<sup>a*b*c*d*</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM; n&#x02009;=&#x02009;5; <sup>a</sup>compared to vehicle1 (distilled water), <sup>b</sup>compared to KF100, <sup>c</sup>compared to KF200, <sup>d</sup>compared to KF400, <sup>e</sup>compared to chloroquine; * (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001); **(p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01); KF&#x02009;=&#x02009;80% extracts of <italic>K. folosia</italic>, numbers refer to doses in mg/kg/day</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Anti-malarial activity of the phenol fractions and their constituents</title><p id="Par37">The two phenolic fractions of <italic>K. folosia</italic> were also found to have activity against <italic>P. berghei</italic> in mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Compared to their respective negative controls, both factions possessed significant suppressive activity at all dose levels tested. They showed the highest activity at 400&#x000a0;mg/kg with fraction 1 and fraction 2 causing 46.32% and 47.53% suppression, respectively. Both fractions prolonged the mean survival days of the treatment groups by 2&#x000a0;days relative to their negative controls although it was not statistically significant. No significant difference in percent change in weight was noted in the treatment groups when compared with the positive controls. Therefore, it can be deduced that the phenolic fractions of <italic>K. folosia</italic> are moderate in their in vivo anti-malarial activity, congruent with earlier reports that extracts containing phenolic compounds and their glycosides have modest levels of antiplasmodial activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Anti-malarial activity of the 80% extract and phenol fractions of rhizomes of <italic>Kniphofia folosia</italic> in mice infected with <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic> in 4-day suppression test<italic>.</italic> Values are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM; n&#x02009;=&#x02009;5</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12936_2020_3552_Fig2_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par38">Among the isolated compounds, knipholone displayed the strongest anti-malarial activity against <italic>P. berghei</italic> infected mice (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Although knipholone and dianellin showed significant suppression at all dose levels tested, the former displayed superior activity with percent suppression values of 55.14 and 60.16% at doses of 100 and 200&#x000a0;mg/kg, respectively. Moreover, it significantly prolonged the mean survival days of the treatment groups (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The dose&#x02013;response plot (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) disclosed that the ED<sub>50</sub> values of knipholone and dianellin were 81.25 and 92.31&#x000a0;mg/kg, respectively. However, neither of the compounds caused significant difference in percent change of weight among the treated groups.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Anti-malarial activity of knipholone and dianellin in mice infected with <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Test substances</th><th align="left">Dose (mg/kg/day)</th><th align="left">Percent parasitaemia</th><th align="left">Percent suppression</th><th align="left">Mean survival time (in days)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">Vehicle3 Knipholone</td><td align="left">0.2&#x000a0;ml</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">46.3560&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.46925</td><td char="." align="char">0.0000</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">6.4000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.50990</td></tr><tr><td align="left">25&#x000a0;mg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.5440&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.45634</td><td char="." align="char">34.1200<sup>a*d*e*h*i*</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.8000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.37417<sup>i*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">50&#x000a0;mg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.2640&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.80001</td><td char="." align="char">42.6400<sup>a*e**h*i*</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.0000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.54772<sup>i*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">100&#x000a0;mg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.7940&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.91475</td><td char="." align="char">55.1400<sup>a*b*e**f*g*i*</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.2000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.73485<sup>a***i*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">200&#x000a0;mg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.4680&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.97391</td><td char="." align="char">60.1600<sup>a*b*c**f*g*i*</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.4000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.24495<sup>a**i*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Dianellin</td><td align="left">25&#x000a0;mg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">32.5280&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.96771</td><td char="." align="char">29.8300<sup>a*c*d*e*h*h*i*</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.6000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.24495<sup>i*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">50&#x000a0;mg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">25.9408&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.77243</td><td char="." align="char">44.0400<sup>a*d*e*g*h*i*</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.2000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.37417<sup>i*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">100&#x000a0;mg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.4303&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.84156</td><td char="." align="char">53.7700<sup>a*b*c*f*g*i*</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.2000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.37417<sup>i*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chloroquine</td><td align="left">25&#x000a0;mg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.0140&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.00600</td><td char="." align="char">9.8000<sup>a&#x02012;h*</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">27.4000&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.400000<sup>a&#x02012;h*</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM; n&#x02009;=&#x02009;5; <sup>a</sup>compared to vehicle3 (distilled water), <sup>b</sup>compared to knipholone 25&#x000a0;mg, <sup>c</sup>compared to knipholone 50&#x000a0;mg, <sup>d</sup>compared to knipholone 100&#x000a0;mg, <sup>e</sup>compared to knipholone 200&#x000a0;mg, <sup>f</sup>compared to dianellin 25&#x000a0;mg, <sup>g</sup>compared to dianellin 50&#x000a0;mg, <sup>h</sup>compared to dianellin 100&#x000a0;mg, <sup>i</sup>compared to chloroquine; * (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001); **(p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01); ***(p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05); numbers refer to doses in mg/kg/day</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Anti-malarial activity of knipholone and dianellin in mice infected with <italic>Plasmodium berghei.</italic> The ED<sub>50</sub> was estimated from a plot of log dose against parasitaemia (expressed as a percentage of the control). Values are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM; n&#x02009;=&#x02009;5</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12936_2020_3552_Fig3_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par39">Previously, the methanol and dichloromethane extracts of <italic>K. folosia</italic> as well as dimeric anthraquinones, knipholone and dianellin isolated therefrom have been shown to have in vitro activity against chloroquine-resistant (W2) and chloroquine-sensitive (D6 and 3D7) strains of <italic>P. falciparum</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The ED<sub>50</sub> of knipholone (1.49 &#x003bc;g/ml) against 3D7 strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] was much lower than that of dianellin which showed IC<sub>50</sub> values of 3.14 and 5.47&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml against W2 and D6 strains, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. In addition, knipholone isolated from <italic>Bulbine capitata</italic> and <italic>Bulbine frutescens</italic> has been reported to possess in vitro activity against chloroquine-resistant (K1) and chloroquine-sensitive (NF54) strains with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 1.06 and 1.7&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p id="Par40">In this study, the acute toxicity as well as the in vivo antiplasmodial activities of the various extracts of <italic>K. folosia</italic> and its major constituents was evaluated against <italic>P. berghei</italic> in mice. Since members of the genus <italic>Kniphofia</italic> have been documented to produce anthraquinones and related phenols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], the total extract was further fractionated into phenolic and nonphenolic fractions. Results of the current study demonstrated that the hydroalcoholic extract, the fractions as well as the isolated compounds significantly suppressed parasitaemia indicating that they possesses blood schizonticidal activity on early infection of mice with <italic>P. berghei</italic>. The results also revealed that the in vivo ED<sub>50</sub> values of knipholone (81.25&#x000a0;mg/kg) and dianellin (92.31&#x000a0;mg/kg) correlate well with their reported in vitro activities. After 4&#x000a0;days of treatment with different doses of knipholone and dianellin, there were significant differences in percent parasite suppression among the treatment groups. However, there was no significant change in mean survival time among mice administered with different doses of knipholone and dianellin except that the animals which received 100 and 200&#x000a0;mg/kg of knipholone survived longer than those given 25&#x000a0;mg/kg of the compound. This is an indication that the different doses of the test compounds have the same effect on overall pathologic effect of the parasite in mice concurrent with previous results obtained for the crude extract and solvent fractions of <italic>Strychnos mitis</italic> leaves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report on acute toxicity and in vivo anti-malarial evaluation of <italic>K. folosia</italic> and its constituents.</p><p id="Par41">Perusal of literature reveals that a number of promising anthraquinones and preanthraquinones leads such as visimione, rufigallol, uveoside, aloin and phenyl anthraquinones have been isolated and/or synthesized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. These compounds are considered as oxidants like artemisinins and 4-aminoquinolines. More importantly, they are catalytic oxidants that enhance the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) inside parasitized erythrocytes or increase these cells&#x02019; susceptibility to oxygen radicals. The free oxygen radicals formed interact with haem or other biomolecular targets inhibiting its tetramerization to the insoluble haemozoin (malaria pigment) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Knipholone, being an anthraquinone derivative, is anticipated to undergo one-electron oxidation and subsequently interact with haem (or other biomolecular targets) thereby inhibiting its tetramerization (or detoxification of haem). Similarly, because of the structural similarity of dianellin and phlorizin, a monoglucosidechalcone, its anti-malarial mechanism of action could be due to inhibition of the solute transporter of the host cell membrane induced by the parasite invasion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Molecular docking study</title><p id="Par42">To get further insight on the mechanism of action of the isolated compounds and to study their binding interaction and identify hypothetical binding motifs, a docking study of knipholone, dianellin and the standard anti-malarial drugs chloroquine and artemisinin were carried out on two crystal structures of target enzymes. The two <italic>Plasmodium</italic> enzymes were plasmepsin II (PDB code 4cku) involved in haemoglobin metabolism by the parasite, and <italic>P. falciparum</italic> l-lactate dehydrogenase (pfLDH) (PDB code 1ldg) involved in glycolysis (or glucose metabolism of the parasite) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. There is a strong suggestion that haemoglobin digesting enzymes found in the food vacuole of the <italic>Plasmodium</italic> and pfLDH are potential anti-malarial chemotherapeutic targets for chloroquine and related aminoquionlones, anthraquinones and other oxidative phenolic compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Gossypol and other phenolic compounds were also found to be pfLDH inhibitors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Besides, chloroquine has been found to bind to the cofactor (NADH) binding site of pfLDH acting as a competitive inhibitor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>].</p><p id="Par43">The binding modes of P2FE-400, a designed inhibitor of plasmepsin II, knipholone and chloroquine to plasmepsin II are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. P2FE-400 showed the highest and strongest affinity for the aspartic protease, plasmepsin II, with the HYDE score of &#x02212;&#x02009;38.3&#x000a0;kJ/mol. The aspartic protease plasmepsin II has two aspartic acid residues Asp34 and Asp214 (the catalytic dyad) that serve as proton donors and acceptors, respectively, in the amide hydrolysis of peptide bonds in proteins. As shown in the current study and also described by Jaudzems et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>], P2FE-400 forms four hydrogen bonds with the catalytic dyad (Asp34 and Asp214), Val78 and Ser218 amino acid residues. Chloroquine showed a comparable binding affinity with an estimated HYDE score of &#x02212;&#x02009;19.7&#x000a0;kJ/mol. The Cl substituent of chloroquine was found to be unsuitable for binding in the hydrophobic cavity of plasmepsin II. Chloroquine forms hydrogen bonds with Gly36 and Val78 amino acid residues. Knipholone and dianellin showed weak binding interaction with HYDE score of &#x02212;&#x02009;6.0 and &#x02212;&#x02009;4.2&#x000a0;kJ/mol, respectively. Nonetheless, knipholone forms two hydrogen bonds with one of the catalytic dyad (Asp214) and Val78 amino acid residues.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> Superimposition of redocked P2FE-400 (shown as a solid line) with its original position (shown in ball-stick model) as a complex (co-crystal) in the binding site of the crystal structure of plasmepsin II (PDB 4cku). <bold>b</bold> Surface representation showing chloroquine in the binding site of plasmepsin II with lipophilicity coloring, white representing hydrophobic pockets and blue representing hydrophilic pockets. Chloroquine is shown in ball-stick model</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12936_2020_3552_Fig4_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par44">The binding modes of knipholone and chloroquine to pfLDH binding site are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. Knipholone (&#x02212;&#x02009;29.1&#x000a0;kJ/mol) showed stronger binding interaction with pfLDH than chloroquine (&#x02212;&#x02009;24.7&#x000a0;kJ/mol). Knipholone forms hydrogen bonds with Ile54 and Val98 amino acid residues. Its carbonyl oxygen (at C-9) and hydroxyl group in ring A (at C-1) of the anthraquinone moiety, and the carbonyl oxygen (at C-3&#x02032;) of the phloroglucinol moiety together with the <italic>ortho</italic> and <italic>para</italic> hydroxyl groups (at C-1&#x02032; and C-4&#x02032;) are not favourable for binding. From the experimental data, there were seven hydrogen bonds in pfLDH-NADH complex, of which four are observed in this study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. Chloroquine on its part showed two hydrogen bonds with Asp53 and Gly99 amino acid residues. One of the N-ethyl groups of chloroquine is not needed in the hydrophilic binding sites. Moreover, the actual pfLDH-chloroquine complex also showed two hydrogen bonds with Glu122 and Gly99 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. In contrast, dianellin did not show binding interaction with pfLDH.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> Surface representation showing the superimposed compounds in the binding site of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> l-lactate dehydrogenase (pfLDH) (PDB1ldg). <bold>b</bold> Surface representation showing knipholone in the binding site of pfLDH with lipophilicity coloring, white representing hydrophobic pockets and blue representing hydrophilic pockets. Knipholone is shown in ball-stick model. <bold>c</bold> Binding interaction of knipholone with amino acid residues of pfLDH</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12936_2020_3552_Fig5_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par45">In conclusion, the rhizome extracts of <italic>K. folosia</italic> possess in vivo anti-malarial effect against <italic>P. berghei</italic> in mice. This finding in conjunction with the safety profile obtained from the acute oral toxicity results support the traditional claim of the plant for the treatment of malaria. The current molecular docking study also identified the binding motifs of the isolated compounds showing that knipholone interact with important amino acid residues in the binding site of the target enzymes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><sec id="Sec23"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12936_2020_3552_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Fig. S1.</bold> Isolation protocol of knipholone (<bold>2</bold>). <bold>Fig. S2.</bold> Isolation protocol of dianellin (<bold>1</bold>). <bold>Fig. S3.</bold> I: <sup>1</sup>H, <sup>13</sup>C, DEPT and HRMS of YKFM-2 (Dianellin). <bold>Fig. S4.</bold> II: <sup>1</sup>H, <sup>13</sup>C, DEPT and HRMS of KFP-1 (Knipholone). <bold>Table S1.</bold> Antimalarial activity of the phenolic fractions of <italic>Kniphofia folosia</italic> in mice infected with <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic>. <bold>Table S2.</bold> Prediction of partition coefficient Log P, aqueous solubility Log S and partition coefficient for partially dissociated compounds Log D of the compounds. <bold>Table S3.</bold> Docking result of compounds on the crystal structure of plasmepsin II (4cku) and plasmodium falciparum l-lactate dehydrogenase (pfLDH) (PDB 1ldg). <bold>Table S4.</bold> Acute oral toxicity results of dianellin. <bold>Fig. S4.</bold> Microscope slide photos of the negative control groups (A and B), dianellin and knipholone treated groups (C-E) and positive control group (F).</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AAU</term><def><p id="Par5">Addis Ababa University</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EHNRI</term><def><p id="Par6">Ethiopian Health Nutrition and Research Institute</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ED<sub>50</sub></term><def><p id="Par7">Median effective dose</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>i.p</term><def><p id="Par8">Intraperitoneally</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NADH</term><def><p id="Par9">Nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>pfLDH</term><def><p id="Par10"><italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> L-lactate dehydrogenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>p.i</term><def><p id="Par11">Post-infection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PTLC</term><def><p id="Par12">Preparative thin layer chromatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PDB</term><def><p id="Par13">Protein Data Bank</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SoP</term><def><p id="Par14">School of Pharmacy</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12936-020-03552-7.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>YA would like to acknowledge the Office of Graduate Studies and Research of Addis Ababa University for the sponsorship. The authors would like to express their gratitude to Professor Sebsebe Demissew, the National Herbarium, AAU, for identification of the plant material.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>YA conceived the study, collected the plant material, conducted the laboratory experiments and prepared the manuscript. DB and KA were involved in the analysis and interpretation of experimental results, and edited the manuscript. ST run the NMR experiment and edited the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was supported by the School of Graduate Studies of Addis Ababa University, research grant.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The following are given in the supplementary figures or tables: Isolation protocols of compounds <bold>1</bold> and<bold> 2</bold> and their NMR and HRMS spectra; Summaries of anti-malarial activity of the phenolic fractions along with acute toxicity results of one of the isolated compounds; Predicted physicochemical properties of the standard drugs, isolated compounds and P2FE-400; Summaries of the docking results; and Microscope slide photos.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par46">All the animal study procedures followed were reviewed and approved by the Institutional Review Board of the SoP, College of Health Sciences, AAU. The mice were handled in accordance with the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par47">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par48">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cowman</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Healer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marapana</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Malaria: biology and disease</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2016</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>610</fpage><lpage>624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2016.07.055</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27768886?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27768886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO</collab></person-group><source>World malaria report 2019</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sartorius</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyalo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Maina</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Amratia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundia</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> in sub-Saharan Africa since 1900</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2017</year><volume>550</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature24059</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29019978?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29019978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farooq</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahajan</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug resistance in malaria</article-title><source>J Vector Borne Dis</source><year>2004</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15672556?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15672556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO. World malaria report</collab></person-group><source>Country profile: Ethiopia</source><year>2017</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name><fpage>2017</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tadesse</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fogarty</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Deressa</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and associated risk factors of malaria among adults in East Shewa Zone of Oromia Regional State, Ethiopia: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-017-4577-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Talisuna</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Erhart</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tibenderana</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Baliraine</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quinine, an old antimalarial drug in a modern world: role in the treatment of malaria</article-title><source>Malar J</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>144</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-10-144</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21609473?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21609473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hien</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Nosten</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A brief history of Qinghaosu</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol</source><year>2015</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2015.10.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26776328?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26776328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pant</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhakuni</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimalarial agents from plant sources</article-title><source>Curr Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>1314</fpage><lpage>1329</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fr&#x000e9;d&#x000e9;rich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Quetin-Leclercq</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimalarial compounds isolated from plants used in traditional medicine</article-title><source>J Pharm Pharmacol</source><year>2009</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1401</fpage><lpage>1433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1211/jpp.61.11.0001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19903367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19903367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ntie-Kang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ongu&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lifongo</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndom</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sippl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Mbaze</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The potential of antimalarial compounds derived from African medicinal plants, part II: a pharmacological evaluation of non-alkaloids and non-terpenoids</article-title><source>Malar J.</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>81</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-13-81</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24602358?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24602358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahlgren</surname><given-names>RMT</given-names></name><name><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><source>The families of the monocotyledons</source><year>1985</year><publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Whitehouse C. Asphodelaceae. In: Beentje HJ, ed. Flora of Tropical East Africa. Rotterdam: Balkema Publ.; 2002.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demissew</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><source>Aloes and lilies of Ethiopia and Eritrea</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Addis Ababa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Shama Books</publisher-name><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>125</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Abate G. Etse Debdabe: Ethiopian Traditional Medicine. Demissew S, ed. Addis Ababa: Addis Ababa University Press; 1989. p. 99&#x02013;183.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wube</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bucar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Asres</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattray</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimalarial compounds from <italic>Kniphofia foliosa</italic> roots</article-title><source>Phytother Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>472</fpage><lpage>476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ptr.1635</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16114082?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16114082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdissa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Akala</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Heydenreich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Midiwo</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndakala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yenesew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knipholone cyclooxanthrone and an anthraquinone dimer with antiplasmodial activities from the roots of <italic>Kniphofia foliosa</italic></article-title><source>Phytochem Lett</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytol.2013.02.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Endale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisrat</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Animut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bucar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Asres</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> antimalarial activity of a labdane diterpenoid from the leaves of <italic>Otostegia integrifolia</italic> Benth</article-title><source>Phytother Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1805</fpage><lpage>1809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ptr.4948</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23401280?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23401280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Girma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisrat</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Asres</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimalarial evaluation of the leaf latex of <italic>Aloe citrina</italic> and its major constituent</article-title><source>Anc Sci Life</source><year>2015</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0257-7941.157158</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26120228?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26120228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisrat</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeshak</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Asres</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimalarial activity of the chemical constituents of the leaf latex of <italic>Aloe pulcherrima</italic> Gilbert and Sebsebe</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2016</year><volume>2016</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>1415</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules21111415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">OECD. Guidelines for testing of chemicals. Guideline 425: Acute oral toxicity. Paris, France: The Organization of Economic Co-operation and Development; 2008.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vennerstrom</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbe-Barnes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Charman</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>FCK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chollet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of an antimalarial synthetic trioxolane drug development candidate</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>430</volume><fpage>900</fpage><lpage>904</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02779</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15318224?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15318224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fentahun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Makonnen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Awas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Giday</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> antimalarial activity of crude extracts and solvent fractions of leaves of <italic>Strychnos mitis</italic> in <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic> infected mice</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-016-1529-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28056932?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28056932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Institute of Health Guidelines for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals and National Institutes of Health, Office of Science and Health Reports. Guide for care and use of laboratory animals 83&#x02013;23<italic>.</italic> Bethesda, Md, USA: Office of Science and Health Reports, Department of Health and Human Services; 1996.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waako</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gumede</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Folb</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> antimalarial activity of <italic>Cardiospermum halicacabum</italic> L. and <italic>Momordica foetida</italic> Schumch. Et Thonn</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2005.02.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15848033?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15848033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hilou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nacoulma</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiguemde</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vivo antimalarial activities of extracts from <italic>Amaranthus spinosus</italic> L. and <italic>Boerhaavia erecta</italic> L. in mice</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2005.08.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16171960?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16171960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug resistance in <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic> Vincke and Lips, 1948. I Chloroquine resistance</article-title><source>Exp Parasitol</source><year>1965</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-4894(65)90012-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 5843289?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5843289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamiru</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Engidawork</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Asres</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the effects of 80% methanolic leaf extract of <italic>Caylusea abyssinica</italic> (Fresen.) Fisch. &#x00026; Mey on glucose handling in normal, glucose loaded and diabetic rodents</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med.</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>151</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6882-12-151</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22967092?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22967092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ancelin</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Calas</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonhoure</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Herbute</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vial</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> antimalarial activities of mono-and bis quaternary ammonium salts interfering with <italic>Plasmodium</italic> phospholipid metabolism</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2003</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>2598</fpage><lpage>2605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.47.8.2598-2605.2003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12878525?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12878525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hindle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Briem</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Substantial improvements in large-scale redocking and screening using the novel HYDE scoring function</article-title><source>J Comput Aided Mol Des</source><year>2012</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>701</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10822-011-9531-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22203423?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22203423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hindle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rarey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A consistent description of hydrogen bond and dehydration energies in protein&#x02013;ligand complexes: methods behind the HYDE scoring function</article-title><source>J Comput Aided Mol Des</source><year>2013</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10822-012-9626-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23269578?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23269578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cichewicz</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of stelladerol, a new antioxidant naphthalene glycoside, and other antioxidant glycosides from edible daylily (<italic>Hemerocallis</italic>) flowers</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf010914k</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11754548?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11754548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Naphthalene aglycones and glycosides from the Australian medicinal plant,<italic> Dianella callicarpa</italic></article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>1442</fpage><lpage>1447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0029-1185724</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19468975?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19468975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cichewicz</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>K-C</given-names></name><name><surname>McKerrow</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kwanzoquinones A&#x02013;G and other constituents of <italic>Hemerocallis fulva</italic> &#x02018;Kwanzo&#x02019; roots and their activity against the human pathogenic trematode <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic></article-title><source>Tetrahedron</source><year>2002</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>8597</fpage><lpage>8606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0040-4020(02)00802-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bezabih</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abegaz</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>4&#x02032;-Demethyl knipholone from aerial parts of <italic>Bulbine capitata</italic></article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>1998</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1071</fpage><lpage>1073</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(97)01053-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dagne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Steglich</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knipholone: a unique anthraquinone derivative from <italic>Kniphofia foliosa</italic></article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>1984</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1729</fpage><lpage>1731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(00)83479-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geremedhin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisrat</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Asres</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation, characterization and <italic>in vivo</italic> antimalarial evaluation of anthrones from the leaf latex of <italic>Aloe percrassa</italic> Todaro</article-title><source>J Nat Remedies</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>125</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deharo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourdy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Quenevo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauvain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A search for natural bioactive compounds in Bolivia through a multidisciplinary approach. Part V. Evaluation of the antimalarial activity of plants used by the Tacana Indians</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-8741(01)00270-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11483383?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11483383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abosi</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Raseroka</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> antimalarial activity of <italic>Vernonia amygdalina</italic></article-title><source>Br J Biomed Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09674845.2003.11783680</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12866916?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12866916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deressa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekonnen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Animut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> antimalarial activities of <italic>Clerodendrum myricoides, Dodonea angustifolia</italic> and <italic>Aloe debrana</italic> against <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic></article-title><source>Ethiop J Health Dev</source><year>2010</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Abreu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimalarial flavonol glycosides from <italic>Euphorbia hirta</italic></article-title><source>Pharm Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13880200701214748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bankole</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Adekunlel</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sowemimo</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Umebese</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Abiodun</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Gbotosho</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical screening and <italic>in vivo</italic> antimalarial activity of extracts from three medicinal plants used in malaria treatment in Nigeria</article-title><source>Parasitol Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-015-4747-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26391173?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26391173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Cieckiewicz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakotoarimanana</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafatro</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Degotte</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> antimalarial activity of caffeic acid and some of its derivatives</article-title><source>J Pharm Pharmacol</source><year>2018</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>1349</fpage><lpage>1356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jphp.12982</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30033538?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30033538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bringmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Menche</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezabih</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abegaz</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaminsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiplasmodial activity of knipholone and related natural phenylanthraquinones</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2006-960859</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10630123?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10630123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abegaz</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezabih</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Msuta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Menche</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;hlbacher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gaboroquinones A and B and 4'-O-demethylknipholone-4'-O-beta-D-glucopyranoside, phenylanthraquinones from the roots of <italic>Bulbine frutescens</italic></article-title><source>J Nat Prod</source><year>2002</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>1117</fpage><lpage>1121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/np0201218</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12193014?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12193014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Harinantenaina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Fonseca</surname><given-names>IO</given-names></name><name><surname>Brodie</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goetz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isolation of antiplasmodial anthraquinones from <italic>Kniphofia ensifolia</italic>, and synthesis and structure-activity relationships of related compounds</article-title><source>Bioorg Med Chem</source><year>2014</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bmc.2013.11.032</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24326280?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24326280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sema</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lannang</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsimo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yousuf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoufoud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Wansi</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New indane and naphthalene derivatives from the rhizomes of <italic>Kniphofia reflexa</italic> Hutchinson ex Codd</article-title><source>Phytochem Lett</source><year>2018</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytol.2018.05.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornell</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignatushchenko</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinrichs</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Riscoe</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potentiation of the antimalarial agent rufigallol</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>1996</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1408</fpage><lpage>1411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.40.6.1408</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8726010?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8726010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez-Medel</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereda-Miranda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytotoxic anthraquinone derivatives from <italic>Picramnia antidesma</italic></article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>556</fpage><lpage>558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2002-32562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12094306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fran&#x000e7;ois</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenackers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Assi</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Steglich</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamottke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Holenz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vismione H and structurally related anthranoid compounds of natural and synthetic origin as promising drugs against the human malaria parasite <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic>: structure-activity relationships</article-title><source>Parasitol Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>582</fpage><lpage>588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004360050598</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10382608?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10382608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ignatushchenkoa</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;chinger</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinrichs</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Riscoe</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Xanthones as antimalarial agents; studies of a possible mode of action</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1997</year><volume>409</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(97)00405-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9199506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziegler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Linck</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heme aggregation inhibitors: antimalarial drugs targeting an essential biomineralization process</article-title><source>Curr Med Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/0929867013373840</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11172673?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11172673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kutner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Breuer</surname><given-names>WV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginsburg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabantchik</surname><given-names>ZI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the mode of action of phlorizin as an antimalarial agent in <italic>in vitro</italic> cultures of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic></article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>1987</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-2952(87)90389-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3099799?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3099799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehrenkranz</surname><given-names>JRL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phlorizin: a review</article-title><source>Diabetes Metab Res Rev</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dmrr.532</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15624123?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15624123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bazik</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonyer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> lactate dehydrogenase in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>1993</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0166-6851(93)90016-Q</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8515777</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulnik</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Majer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure and inhibition of plasmepsin II, a hemoglobin-degrading enzyme from <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>10034</fpage><lpage>10039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.93.19.10034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8816746?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8816746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>N&#x000f6;teberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamelink</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hult&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahlgren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuelsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Design and synthesis of plasmepsin I and plasmepsin II inhibitors with activity in <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic>-infected cultured human erythrocytes</article-title><source>J Med Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>734</fpage><lpage>746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jm020951i</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12593654?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12593654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chloroquine: mechanism of drug action and resistance in <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic></article-title><source>Pharmacol Ther</source><year>1993</year><volume>1993</volume><issue>57</issue><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0163-7258(93)90056-J</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Skillman</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Habashita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gluzman</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>TJA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Potent, low-molecular-weight non-peptide inhibitors of malarial aspartyl protease plasmepsin II</article-title><source>J Med Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1428</fpage><lpage>1440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jm980641t</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10212129?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10212129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pradhan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chittiboyina</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tekwani</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design, synthesis, and biological evaluation of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> lactate dehydrogenase inhibitors</article-title><source>J Med Chem</source><year>2007</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>3841</fpage><lpage>3850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jm070336k</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17636950?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17636950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D'Alessandro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvestrini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dechering</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbett</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Parapini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmerman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> screening assay for anti-gametocyte drugs based on parasite lactate dehydrogenase detection</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2013</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>2048</fpage><lpage>2058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkt165</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23645588?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23645588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jatana</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> antimalarial evaluation of piperidine- and piperazine-based chalcones: inhibition of falcipain-2 and plasmepsin II hemoglobinases activities from <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic></article-title><source>ChemistrySelect</source><year>2017</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>7684</fpage><lpage>7690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/slct.201701162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheuka</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dziwornu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Okombo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chibale</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasmepsin inhibitors in antimalarial drug discovery: medicinal chemistry and target validation (2000 to present)</article-title><source>J Med Chem</source><year>2010</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>4445</fpage><lpage>4467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jmedchem.9b01622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conners</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schambach</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessions</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mapping the binding site for gossypol-like inhibitors of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> lactate dehydrogenase</article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>2005</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molbiopara.2005.03.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15978953?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15978953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Megnassan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Keita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Esmel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Frecer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Miertus</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design of novel dihydroxynaphthoic acid inhibitors of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> lactate dehydrogenase</article-title><source>Med Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>970</fpage><lpage>984</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/157340612802084324</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22741776?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22741776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tranter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessions</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chloroquine binds in the cofactor binding site of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> lactate dehydrogenase</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>10213</fpage><lpage>10218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.15.10213</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10187806?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10187806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaudzems</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tars</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurops</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivdra</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Otikovs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leitans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plasmepsin inhibitory activity and structure-guided optimization of a potent hydroxyethylamine-based antimalarial hit</article-title><source>ACS Med Chem Lett</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ml4004952</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24900843?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24900843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaikuad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairweather</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Conners</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph-Horne</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Turgut-Balik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of lactate dehydrogenase from <italic>Plasmodium vivax:</italic> complexes with NADH and APADH</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>16221</fpage><lpage>16228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi051416y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16331982?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16331982</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>