<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Traditionally, plants with a high level of salicylates have been used therapeutically throughout the world. Nowadays, salicylates containing plants are used as substitutes for nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs). In the fourth century B.C., the father of medicine Hippocrates reportedly prescribed extracts of willow leaves or barks to reduce fever and pain during childbirth [
 <xref rid="B1-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In 1828, the active ingredient salicin (SA derivative) of the willow tree was isolated which is known to be converted to SA upon ingestion. Another natural salicylate methyl salicylate (MeSA), which is found in wintergreen, birch tree, mango, meadowsweet, guelder-rose, is used as analgesic medicine (for joint and muscular pain) and fragrance [
 <xref rid="B2-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In the middle of the nineteenth century, an intense increase in the medicinal use of SA occurred due to the identification of salicin from willow plants as an anti-inflammatory compound. For growing demand, synthetic SA production was begun commercially in 1874. The most commonly used and recognized salicylate is aspirin (acetyl SA), which was first synthesized by Bayer in 1897. SA had some negative side effects, such as stomach irritation and bleeding, thus it was replaced with aspirin with fewer side effects [
 <xref rid="B7-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Recent studies suggest that Aspirin not only reduces fever, inflammation, and pain but also reduces the risk of stroke, heart attack, and some type of cancers [
 <xref rid="B8-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The mechanism of analgesia occurred by aspirin involves the suppression of prostaglandin synthesis by irreversible inhibition of the cyclooxygenases COX1 and COX2 [
 <xref rid="B11-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Aspirin is also known to target other human proteins, such as nuclear factor-kappaB (NF-κB), cathepsin A (CTSA), ribosomal S6 kinase 2 (RSK2), and cyclin-dependent kinase 2 (CDK2) [
 <xref rid="B12-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Both natural and synthetic salicylates have beneficial effects for the treatments of different diseases as salicylates can target different human proteins (
 <xref rid="ijms-21-09049-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). For example, 5-aminosalicylic acid targets arachidonate 5-lipoxygenase (ALOX5) and glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) protein [
 <xref rid="B15-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]; Sulfasalazine targets ALOX5 and tumor necrosis factor (TNFα) protein [
 <xref rid="B15-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]; Sodium salicylate targets COX2 and NF-κB [
 <xref rid="B18-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]; GAPDH and High mobility group box 1 (HMGB1) both are targeted by acetyl 3-aminoethyl salicylic acid [
 <xref rid="B16-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Thus, salicylates play an important role as a pharmacological agent in human health.
</p>
