<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>A. borbonica</italic>, 
 <italic>A. triplinervis</italic>, 
 <italic>D. viscosa</italic>, and 
 <italic>T. bentzoe</italic> medicinal plants were collected in Réunion Island (France). The botanical identification associated with voucher number of 
 <italic>A. borbonica</italic> (Rubiaceae, RUN052-F), 
 <italic>A. triplinervis</italic> (Asteraceae, TCN-P061), 
 <italic>D. viscosa</italic> (Sapindaceae, TCN-P028), and 
 <italic>T. bentzoe</italic> (Combretaceae, TCN-P009) plants was performed at the University of Réunion Island. After airflow drying at 45 °C, leaves were reduced to powder. A dissolution of each plant powder (2 g) in 10 mL of an aqueous acetonic solution (70%, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>, Sigma–Aldrich, St-Louis, MO, USA) was achieved. Subsequently, the mixture was incubated at 4 °C for 90 min, centrifuged at 1400× 
 <italic>g</italic> at 4 °C for 20 min, and the supernatants containing polyphenols were stored at −80 °C until analysis. Ultra-performance liquid chromatography coupled to electrospray ionization-tandem mass spectrometry analysis (UPLC-ESI-MS-MS, Agilent Technologies, Les Ulis, France) was performed to detect phytochemicals, in accordance with the previously published method [
 <xref rid="B38-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The identification of compounds was based on their retention time, and the 
 <italic>m</italic>/
 <italic>z</italic> ratio of their parent ions and fragments in negative or positive mode at 280 nm. The total polyphenol contents were determined by Folin–Ciocalteu assay, as we previously described [
 <xref rid="B41-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Briefly, 25 μL of each plant extract were added to 125 μL of Folin–Ciolcateu’s reagent (Sigma–Aldrich, St-Louis, MO, USA) and 100 μL of sodium carbonate (Sigma–Aldrich, St-Louis, MO, USA) in a 96-well plate. Absorbance was measured at 760 nm (FLUOstar Optima, Bmg Labtech, Cambridge, UK) after an incubation for 5 min. at 54 °C, and then during 5 min. at 4 °C. A standard solution of gallic acid (Sigma–Aldrich, St-Louis, MO, USA) was used for calibration. The total polyphenol contents were expressed as g gallic acid equivalent (GAE)/100 g medicinal plant powder. 
</p>
