<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The name 
 <italic>Poria cocos</italic> is also commonly applied to a fungal sclerotium, known as “Fuling” in China, which has been used in Chinese traditional medicine for more than 2000 years for relieving coughs, inducing diuresis, aleviating anxiety, relieving fever, antitumor; adjustment of intestinal bacterial flora, antihyperlipidemic activity, antioxidant, anti-hepatitis B virus, anti-inflammation, anti-metastasis, anti-tyrosinase, hypoglycemic activity, improvement of cardiac function, improvement of learning and memory abilities, improvement of liver fibrosis, prevention of diabetic nephropathy, and sedative and hypnotic activities (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Wu et al., 
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Pharmacological studies have confirmed these properties (e.g., Sun, 
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Li et al., 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The edible sclerotia of “Fuling” is widely cultivated in China (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), and the products are exported to more than 40 countries (Chi et al., 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). This prized medicinal mushroom is also known as “Hoelen” (e.g., Xu et al., 
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Li et al., 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Sun et al., 
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), a name erected from a piece of pre-Linnean scientific literature published posthumously by Rumphius (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">1750</xref>). Fries (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">1822</xref>) mentioned “Hoelen” as a little-known medicinal species from China, under the genus 
 <italic>Pachyma</italic>. Merrill (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">1917</xref>) noted that 
 <italic>Pachyma hoelen</italic> Fr. was cultivated on pine trees in various parts of China and that it had been referred to as 
 <italic>Poria cocos</italic>. In order to clarify the identity of 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>hoelen</italic>, he sent a Chinese specimen (received from a drug store) for examination to W. A. Murrill. Murrill stated that the Chinese sclerotia showed similarity to the samples collected from different localities in America, but he thought “
 <italic>that Pachyma hoelen Fries is distinct from P. cocos Fries</italic>” (Merrill, 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">1917</xref>).
</p>
