<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The inhibitory activity of VA-C extracts maybe attributed to the presence of important bioactive compounds (
 <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Abdal Sahib, Al-Shareefi &amp; Hameed, 2019</xref>), which may target different structures of the 
 <italic>Candida</italic> species including the cell wall, cell membrane, and mitochondria enzymes. Some of these compounds may reduce or prevent the virulence factors, including adhesins, enzymes production, germ tubes (Pseudohyphal), biofilm formation, and quorum sensing (
 <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">De Oliveira Santos et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-80" ref-type="bibr">Sardi et al., 2013</xref>). Our results showed the diversity of the compounds extracted from VA-C plant leaves that belong to several effective biochemical compounds with different anticandidal activity, including polyphenols that can destroy the 
 <italic>Candida</italic> cell membrane leading to permeability of the cell contents (
 <xref rid="ref-75" ref-type="bibr">Peralta et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Hwang et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Hwang et al., 2010</xref>), inhibition of mitochondrial enzyme activity in the 
 <italic>Candida</italic> cell (
 <xref rid="ref-98" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2014</xref>) and inhibition of the germ tube formation (
 <xref rid="ref-82" ref-type="bibr">Seleem et al., 2016</xref>). Fatty acids with carbon chains between 10 and 12 carbons had a good inhibitory effect against 
 <italic>Candida</italic> species (
 <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Ababutain, 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Bergsson et al., 2001</xref>). Terpenes have been reported to have inhibitory effects against 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> and may prevent biofilm formation (
 <xref rid="ref-74" ref-type="bibr">Pemmaraju et al., 2013</xref>). Terpenoids inhibit 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> cell growth by affecting the membrane and preventing adhesins, biofilm formation, and germ tube formation (
 <xref rid="ref-91" ref-type="bibr">Touil et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr">Raut et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-100" ref-type="bibr">Zore et al., 2011</xref>).
</p>
