<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The assay for 
 <italic>a</italic>-glucosidase inhibition activity was performed as described by Lee et al. (2014) [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The substrate used was 
 <italic>ρ</italic>-Nitrophenyl-
 <italic>ρ</italic>-D-glucopyranoside (PNPG), prepared by dissolving in 50 mM phosphate buffer (pH 6.5) that is comparable to the conditions of the human intestinal fluid. The seaweed extracts were prepared at a concentration of 5000 ppm and 6 serial dilutions were performed. The extracts were mixed in the 96-well microplate and incubated at room temperature for 5 min. Then, 75 
 <italic>μ</italic>L of PNPG was added to each well containing the sample, blank substrate, and negative or positive controls whereas the remaining wells were loaded with 75 
 <italic>μ</italic>L of 30 mM phosphate buffer. These mixtures in the wells were incubated for 15 min at ambient temperature. The reaction mixtures were stopped by using the stopping agent, 50 
 <italic>μ</italic>L of 2 M glycine (pH 10) for the sample, blank substrate, and negative control. To the remaining wells was added 50 
 <italic>μ</italic>L of deionized water. Subsequently, the absorbance readings for all the wells were measured using a spectrophotometer (Tecan Infinite F200) at a wavelength of 405 nm. The 
 <italic>a</italic>-glucosidase inhibition activity of the test sample was expressed as a percentage (%) of inhibition and calculated using the following:
 <disp-formula id="EEq2">
  <label>(2)</label>
  <math id="M2">
   <mtable>
    <mtr>
     <mtd>
      <mo>%</mo>
      <mtext> inhibition of sample</mtext>
      <mo>=</mo>
      <mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|">
       <mrow>
        <mtext/>
        <mfrac>
         <mrow>
          <mfenced open="(" close=")" separators="|">
           <mrow>
            <mtext>Negative control </mtext>
            <mo>–</mo>
            <mtext> Blank negative control </mtext>
           </mrow>
          </mfenced>
          <mo>–</mo>
          <mtext/>
          <mfenced open="(" close=")" separators="|">
           <mrow>
            <mtext>Sample </mtext>
            <mo>–</mo>
            <mtext> Blank Sample</mtext>
           </mrow>
          </mfenced>
         </mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mtext/>
          <mfenced open="(" close=")" separators="|">
           <mrow>
            <mtext>Negative control </mtext>
            <mo>–</mo>
            <mtext> Blank negative control</mtext>
           </mrow>
          </mfenced>
         </mrow>
        </mfrac>
       </mrow>
      </mfenced>
      <mtext/>
      <mi>x</mi>
      <mtext/>
      <mn>100</mn>
      <mo>%</mo>
      <mo>.</mo>
     </mtd>
    </mtr>
   </mtable>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
