<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par47" class="p">Additionally, we found that dietary inclusion of 8% 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> did not result in beneficial effects on the colonic microbiota in the current trial. To the best of our knowledge, the current study is the first to test partially 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae inclusion in the diets of finishing pigs. Therefore, the available information on the effect of dietary 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae inclusion on gut microbiota of finishing pigs is very limited. As mentioned above, 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae contain chitin, which is not digestible by monogastric animals. A previous study has indicated that low concentrations of chitin might increase the number of 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> and decrease 
 <italic class="italic">E.coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> in the intestine of broilers, while high concentrations of chitin have adverse effects on these bacteria [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>]. In weaning piglets, 8% 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae diet had lower counts of Lactobacilli than the control and 4% 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae diet [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>]. Thus, dietary inclusion of 8% 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae had no positive effects on the microbiota may be due to the higher level of chitin in the diets. Additionally, recent studies have indicated that insects contain non-protein nitrogen, such as chitin, nucleic acids, ammonia, nitrites, etc., could lead to an overestimation of the insect protein content [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>]. In the present study, we used the conventional nitrogen-to-protein conversion factor value of 6.25 to express the protein content of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae, which may result the true protein content in the diet and colonic digesta were lower in the H2 group than in the control group. A previous study has showed that non-protein nitrogen can inhibit the growth of beneficial bacteria, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Bifidobacterium</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Megasphaera</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>] Therefore, additionally potential explanation for had no beneficial effects on the colonic microbiota may be an increasing of non-protein nitrogen content when pigs fed the dietary inclusion of 8% 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae, but further study will be required to elucidate the underlying mechanisms. Nevertheless, our findings suggest that dietary inclusion of 4% 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae altered the microbiota structure of finishing pigs toward a host-friendly gut environment.
</p>
