<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">Previous studies reported that overexpression of 
 <italic>TYDC2</italic> in the opium poppy led to an increase in morphine, codeine, and the baine alkaloids in the transgenic plants compared to the non-transgenic plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The findings of previous research on overexpression of codeinone reductase in 
 <italic>Papaver bracteatum</italic> revealed the production of Codeine (0.04% dry wt) and morphine (0.28% dry wt) in the transgenic hairy root [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. It was demonstrated that overexpression of 
 <italic>SmMYC2</italic> in 
 <italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic> resulted in the production of phenolic acids [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Jiang carried out overexpression of 
 <italic>AaWRKY1</italic> in 
 <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> and showed that 
 <italic>AaWRKY1</italic> increased the content of artemisinin in this plant [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In another major study on 
 <italic>Artemisia annua</italic>, it was found that overexpression of the cytochrome P450 monooxygenase and cytochrome P450 reductase genes can increase artemisinin level [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. In this report, we described the application of an 
 <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation system to a 
 <italic>T. ammi</italic> (Shaheideh Yazd). This method combines the use of the zygotic embryo as an explant and the ability of 
 <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> for transformation cells. Zygotic embryo explant is superior to other regeneration systems due to its independent genotype. The zygotic embryo has been accepted as an adequate explant for tissue culture and genetic transformation in many medicinal plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Since, there have been difficulties with the regeneration of plants from 
 <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-infected zygotic embryo, the 
 <italic>Trachyspermum ammi</italic> transformation system is established. Therefore, this research aimed to provide a fast procedure to increase thymol using zygotic embryos explant for overexpressing 
 <italic>TPS</italic> gene in 
 <italic>T. ammi</italic>. This presented procedure can be beneficial for the genetic transformation of other genes and further biotechnology studies.
</p>
