<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Very recently, Chen and coworkers reported the regulatory efficacy of a novel 
 <italic>G. frondosa</italic> polysaccharide GFP-N on the intestinal microflora of diabetic groups in vivo using single-molecule real-time sequencing technology (SMRT) [
 <xref rid="B31-foods-10-00095" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. There were significant differences exhibited in the composition of microbial populations in gut microbiota between the GFP-N-treated group and the diabetic control group. The relative abundance of some bacterial species such as 
 <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> (
 <italic>L. acidophilus</italic>) and 
 <italic>Bacteroides acidifaciens</italic> (
 <italic>B. acidifaciens</italic>) was increased with GFP-N treatment. 
 <italic>L. acidophilus</italic> has been shown to delay the progression of high fructose-induced diabetes in rats [
 <xref rid="B96-foods-10-00095" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>], and 
 <italic>B. acidifaciens</italic> has shown the potential for treatment of metabolic diseases such as obesity and diabetes [
 <xref rid="B109-foods-10-00095" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Guo et al. obtained similar results, showing that GFP could regulate intestinal microflora by significantly elevating the relative abundance of 
 <italic>Alistipes</italic> and 
 <italic>Bacteroides</italic> and reducing 
 <italic>Enterococcus</italic>, which was associated with the improved hyperlipidemia and hyperglycemia in T2DM induced by streptozotocin and a high-fat diet (HFD) [
 <xref rid="B107-foods-10-00095" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. The same research group also developed 
 <italic>G. frondosa</italic> polysaccharide-chromium (III) (GFP-Cr(III)) through chelation because chromium (III) was the most important trace mineral for T2DM treatment. Compared with inorganic chromium, organic chromium (III) has been found to have much better effects, with lower toxicity and genotoxicity. The researchers found that GFP-Cr(III) not only had the effects of GFP as shown in their previous work but also significantly increased the relative abundance of 
 <italic>Enterorhabdus</italic> and 
 <italic>Coriobacteriaceae</italic> due to the presence of Cr(III) [
 <xref rid="B110-foods-10-00095" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>].
</p>
