<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many medicinal herbs have been reported to improve the nephrotoxicity of AKI via antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Cisplatin produces excessive reactive oxygen species (ROS) and induces mitochondrial dysfunction and macrophage activation, which further increases ROS release and decreases the cellular antioxidant defense system [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Since the process promotes renal neutrophil infiltration and tubular cell apoptosis, the polyherbs of BJ, PJ, and WR showing strong free radical scavenging activities and enhanced levels of SOD and catalase activities might reduce annexin-V-positive cells and activation of caspase 3 that plays a key role in apoptosis. Actually, the deletion of extracellular SOD3 has been shown to lead to functional deterioration in AKI [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. There are concerns that the antioxidant activity of polyherbal formulas might compromise the antitumor activity of cisplatin. However, oxidative stress can increase cisplatin-resistance, and antioxidant reagents can also sensitize tumor cell to cisplatin [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Conversely, even though OR showed no antioxidant properties, it inhibited apoptosis and prevented cisplatin-induced cell death. Furthermore, while BJ, PJ, and WR showed cellular proliferative effects, those of OR were particularly prominent. The fact that OR promoted the cell growth under serum-free conditions for 3 days is interesting because it suggests potential regenerative effects in the kidney. There have been few reports involving the renal signaling pathways; one study has shown that OR has nephroprotective effects by suppressing the activation of the toll-like receptor 4/myeloid differentiation factor 88 signaling and pyrin domain containing 3 inflammasome in hyperuricemic mice [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, the underlying mechanism is completely uncertain in this study, and we are planning the future study to clarify the signaling pathways related to antioxidant and proliferative properties.
</p>
