<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many studies have shown efficacy of individual herbs and their main compounds on AKI models and the relevant mechanisms such as antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, and antiapoptotic effects [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The effective single herbs on AKI include 
 <italic>Astragalus</italic> root, ginseng, and 
 <italic>Glycyrrhiza</italic>, which are constituents of the BJ formula; Hoelen in PJ, OR, and WR; moutan root bark and 
 <italic>Cornus</italic> fruit in PJ; and 
 <italic>Peony</italic> root and 
 <italic>Magnolia</italic> bark in WR. TCM-based polyherbal formulas also showed preventive effects on AKI [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. For instance, the combination of 
 <italic>Angelica gigas</italic> and 
 <italic>Astragalus</italic> roots, as the herbal components of BJ, improves renal blood flow by increasing nitric oxide production [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], and 
 <italic>Zhibai Dihuang Wan</italic>, which included the same four herbal components as PJ, attenuates renal injury and apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Given that the polyherbal formula consists of several medicinal herbs containing hundreds of compounds, the mechanism studies on the multiple targets are difficult to analyze. However, traditional polyherbal formulas can be a useful source of novel herbal combinations for the treatment of AKI from a different perspective. For example, OR is used traditionally as diuretic, and its main herbal component, 
 <italic>Alimatis rhizoma</italic>, has been currently reported to have remarkable diuretic activity [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The systems pharmacology approach has demonstrated the improvement of hypertension by the activation of the RAAS [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. It is expected that multitargeting of the five herbal components of OR may have synergistic effects of diuretic activity coupled with antiapoptotic and proliferating effects in protecting against cisplatin-induced AKI.
</p>
