<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Hydrophobic and hydrophilic fractions of 
 <italic class="italic">Teucrium alopecurus</italic> leaves were characterized by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC/MS). Stock solutions of oily (100 μg/mL) and water soluble fractions (500 μg/mL) were prepared in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) and diluted as needed in a cell culture medium. Penicillin, streptomycin, Iscove's modified Dulbecco's medium (IMDM), Roswell Park Memorial Institute 
 <italic class="italic">medium</italic> (RPMI)-640 medium, Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM)/F12 medium and fetal bovine serum (FBS) were obtained from Mediatech, Inc. (Herndon, VA, USA). Bovine serum albumin (BSA) was purchased from Atlanta Biologicals (Norcross, GA, USA). NaCl, Tris, sodium dodecyl sulphate (SDS), MTT, and glycine, LPS (
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> 055:B5), the β-actin, butyl-hydroxytoluene (BHT), ascorbic acide (1%), 2,2-diphényl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH), ferric reducing antioxidant power (FRAP), potassium ferricyanide (K
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>Fe(CN)
 <sub class="sub">6</sub>) (1%), trichloro acetic acide (TCA) (10%), ferric Chloride (FeCl
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>) (0.1%), CFM (10 μg/μl), and ERTA (10 μg/μl) were purchased from Sigma–Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). Antibodies against c-Myc, CXCR4, MMP-9, cIAP-1/2, Mcl-1, ICAM-1, Bcl-xL, cyclin D1, caspases-3, -8, and -9, PARP, Bcl-2, STAT-3, and pSTAT3 (Tyr705 and Ser727) were obtained from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Santa Cruz, CA, USA); the β-actin antibody was obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA); X-linked IAP and c-FLIP antibodies were obtained from BD Biosciences and Imgenex (San Diego, CA, USA), respectively. Antibodies against survivin were obtained from R&amp;D Systems (Minneapolis, MN, USA); the VEGF antibody was purchased from NeoMarkers (Fremont, CA, USA); 5-FU (purity &gt; 99%) was purchased from Sigma Chemical Co.; Butyl-hydroxytoluene (BHT), Ascorbic acide (1%), 2,2-diphényl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH), ferric reducing antioxidant power (FRAP), Potassium ferricyanide (K
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>Fe(CN)
 <sub class="sub">6</sub>) (1%), Trichloro acetic acide (TCA) (10%), Ferric Chloride (FeCl
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>) (0.1%), CFM (10 μg/μl), and ERTA (10 μg/μl) were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich Chemicals Co. (St. Louis, MO, USA).
</p>
