<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The relationship between chirality and biological activity has been of increasing importance in medicinal chemistry [
 <xref rid="B121-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>], and our group has contributed to this research field with the synthesis of a library of chiral derivatives of xanthones (CDXs). Our inspiration to follow this way was based on Nature, as an unquestionable successful source of chiral bioactive compounds [
 <xref rid="B122-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. Actually, in biological systems, chirality is the rule rather than the exception and the presence of chiral centers in natural products, provides higher affinity and target specificity. Regarding this class of compounds, many naturally occurring xanthones, isolated from terrestrial and marine sources are chiral, and present a wide range of biological and pharmacological activities [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Nevertheless, while biosynthetic pathways frequently give only one enantiomer, the synthetic procedures may allow the preparation of both enantiomers, in addition to the access to structures that otherwise could not be reached [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B123-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. Therefore, our main goals were to synthetize bioactive CDXs inspired in natural molecules and/or introduction of chirality in some interesting molecules, as well as obtaining both enantiomers with very high enantiomeric purity to explore enantioselectivity. We consider that it is of crucial importance to study the biological behaviour of each single enantiomer since the physiological properties, such as pharmacodynamics, pharmacokinetics and toxicity, are often different between enantiomers [
 <xref rid="B124-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. Moreover, enantioselectivity studies must be performed in the early stage of drug discovery and development. Another reason to work with CDXs was to enlarge chemical and biological spaces. In fact, despite the large structural multiplicity of bioactive xanthones, only a handful of synthetic chiral derivatives was reported [
 <xref rid="B125-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>,
 <xref rid="B126-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. Additionally, the CDXs were also obtained to achieve other purposes, such as to be used as analytical tools, as it will be covered at the end of this section.
</p>
