<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4dot4-metabolites-07-00065" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.4. GC/MS Measurements</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Gas Chromatograph (GC-17A and GC-2010), mass spectrometer (QP-5000 and GCMS-QP 2010 Plus), auto injector (AOC-20i) and software (Class 5000 and GCMS solution) used for these measurements were acquired from Shimadzu (Duisburg, Germany). The column used was a silica capillary column Equity TM-5 (30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm film thickness) from Supelco Inc. (Bellefonte, PA, USA).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The measurements were performed as follows: the injector and interface temperature were 230 °C and 250 °C respectively. The temperature settings of the oven were: 70 °C for 2 min, then 70–90 °C with 2 °C/min, then 90–130 °C with 5 °C/min and finally 250 °C for 1 min. The pressure program started at 76.1 kPa with a linear velocity of 40.0 cm/s. The flow control was set to linear velocity. The total flow was 16.1 mL/min while the column flow stayed at 1.19 mL/min. The split ratio was 1:10. The detector volts were approx. 0.8 keV (according to the last tuning result of the MS). The solvent cut was adjusted at 4 min and the sampling rate at 0.15 s. The micro scan width was fixed at 0.1 u.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each sample was analyzed three times in SIM (single ion monitoring) mode. The relative intensities of the standards (camphor and 1,8-cineole) and the samples obtained from GC/MS analysis (peak integration) were processed according to previous publications [
  <a rid="B60-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-metabolites-07-00065">60</a>,
  <a rid="B61-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-metabolites-07-00065">61</a>,
  <a rid="B62-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-metabolites-07-00065">62</a>,
  <a rid="B63-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63-metabolites-07-00065">63</a>]. This evaluation results in the molar excess of carbon isotopologues of the main components camphor and 1,8-cineole only due to the enrichments from the 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C precursor.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC/MS analysis of the essential oil fraction was performed: (i) to determine the composition of all samples; and (ii) to determine the 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C enrichment and isotopologue profiles of the main components in each sample. 
 </p>
</sec>
