<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">Metabolite profiling of PGTs, leaves, stems, and roots showed that the most enriched compounds were terpenoids, flavonoids, phenolic acids, and fatty acids (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM17" ref-type="media">S1</xref>), and the confirmed compounds in PGTs were strikingly similar in leaves. Theoretically, the compounds contained in PGTs should be detected in leaves, whereas the leaf extracts are more abundant than PGT secretions. In addition to PGTs, the leaves contained other types of cells and GTs, and the energy and heat generated in the process of ultrasonic extraction resulted in changes or loss of compounds. The method, which used micropipettes to collect secretions from PGTs, resulted in metabolic profiles closer to those of compounds in vivo. Egomaketone was the precursor of perillaketone and isoegomaketone (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM15" ref-type="media">15</xref>). The contents of perillaketone and isoegomaketone were lower in PGTs than in leaves. In contrast, the egomaketone content was the opposite because the leaves in node 1 (from the tip of the stem to the root) for PGT analysis were younger than leaf extraction (nodes 1 and 2), which may reveal the developmental dynamics of leaf essential oil composition. The relative contents of monoterpenoids and sesquiterpenoids in GC–MS were very low or absent in the roots. In the LC–MS analysis of 
 <italic>P. frutescens</italic>, phenolic acid and flavonoids were generated from flavonoid and phenylpropanoid biosynthesis, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The purple leaves enriched anthocyanin pigments, such as malonylshisonin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. It was detected in PGTs and leaves with the highest intensity in PGTs compared with other tissues. Interestingly, PGTs with higher intensity were gold, while the abaxial surface of the leaves was purple. Anthocyanin is sensitive to light, temperature, and pH [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. These analyses confirmed that PGTs contained the bulk of the bioactive constituents accumulated by 
 <italic>P. frutescens</italic>.
</p>
