<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The optimal hormone concentration [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] for cultured 
 <italic>P. multiflorum</italic> was identified using the results of a previous 
 <italic>P. multiflorum</italic> study for optimizing in vitro culture conditions. The optimum media conditions derived from this previous study led to a large number of cultured 
 <italic>P. multiflorum</italic> seedlings. Differences between the SS samples grown from the currently available products and the CS samples were determined in an experiment that compared the 
 <italic>P. multiflorum</italic> growth characteristics over 1 year under field conditions. The underground 
 <italic>P. multiflorum</italic> organs are the medically important parts. Therefore, a quantitative comparison of the underground and the aboveground biomasses was conducted. Most research on tissue culturing in Korea is related to the medicinal parts of Korean oriental medicine plants, which means that there has been previous research on root hypertrophy because it is mainly the roots that are used in traditional Korean medicine [
 <xref rid="B21-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The results of the comparison between the SS and CS underground parts of 
 <italic>P. multiflorum</italic> plants showed that the underground biomass of the CS samples was higher than that of the SS samples. However, the SS small lateral roots had large fresh weights. Plant roots adapt to changes by adjusting their shape and area according to gravity, light, and soil conditions [
 <xref rid="B23-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Furthermore, plant growth hormones play important roles in root growth and architecture [
 <xref rid="B24-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In particular, the auxin group of plant hormones (phytohormones) is closely involved in root development. In contrast, cytokinin hormones are known to inhibit lateral root development [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. It is thought that 
 <italic>P. multiflorum</italic> CS plants are greatly influenced by phytohormones. The differences in biomass, tuber root, and lateral root development between the CS and SS samples were probably because of the auxin and cytokinin hormones as their levels were higher under the optimal culture conditions than would be expected under field conditions. The plant hormone gibberellic acid, which is associated with the formation of tuber roots, has been extensively studied [
 <xref rid="B27-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Transcriptome based RNA-Seq analyses have been used in hormone studies to investigate the tuber root development process and its relationship to changes in plant hormone biosynthesis. The role of sucrose and glucose in plant physiology is related to seed germination and the control of blooming. In particular, sucrose is closely related to the development of food crop tubers [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Furthermore, the production of medicinal resources is related to the formation of tuber roots in 
 <italic>Rehmannia glutinosa</italic> and 
 <italic>Pinellia ternata</italic> [
 <xref rid="B21-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Therefore, the formation of 
 <italic>P. multiflorum</italic> tubers may also be partly owing to sucrose, and previous research on Korean oriental medicine plants [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] has suggested that this may explain why CS-derived plants have higher fresh weights than SS-derived plants. Multiplication of the tubers can be visually assessed from the shape of the CS tubers (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-09-01280-f003">Figure 3</xref>). This lack of difference in the underground biomasses could be because of a genetic variation in 
 <italic>P. multiflorum</italic>. However, an important point about this study is that the CS-derived plants were developed using an optimized tissue culture system and that this probably led to the underground parts developing more rapidly than those in the conventional SS-derived plants. This results from this study suggested that 
 <italic>P. multiflorum</italic> could be harvested, which would reduce labor and production costs because it takes less time to produce a viable crop. Shortening the growth period or increasing biomass is often considered to be very important aspects of crop cultivation [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].
</p>
