<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is not easy to find the correlation between FTIR spectra and UHPLC-Q-Orbitrap HRMS chromatograms with the contribution of biological activities related to its functional groups and metabolites due to the complexity of metabolomics data. Therefore, chemometrics analysis is needed in order to resolve this issue. The chemometric technique enables measurements of chemical systems through applications between mathematics and statistics, and it is an important method of analyzing much information from chromatographic data and can be used to evaluate the chemical similarities and dissimilarity of fingerprints between chromatographs of the sample [
 <xref rid="B12-metabolites-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Principal component analysis (PCA) and partial least squares (PLS) are the most frequent chemometrics analyses. PCA techniques make it possible to extract analytical information from chromatograms or spectra of samples to identify similarities and differences among highly complex datasets. PLS is one of the most popular calibration methods, which is based on determining the linear relationship between the independent dataset of measurement X (such as peak, absorbance values, fingerprint, spectra, or peak area from the detected metabolites) and the dependent set of variable Y (biological activity) in order to predict the bioactive compounds [
 <xref rid="B13-metabolites-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-metabolites-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-metabolites-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. For the first time, we have performed metabolomics analysis using FTIR and UHPLC-Q-Orbitrap HRMS to identify major functional groups and metabolites in the two 
 <italic>Curculigo</italic> spp. with a focus on substances having antioxidant and α-glucosidase inhibitory activities. We also differentiate the two 
 <italic>Curculigo</italic> species based on their plant parts and their origin of geographical location.
</p>
