<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec id="st1" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Objective:</title>
  <p class="p">Postoperative ileus (POI) is a common complication after surgery that requires a multifactorial therapeutic approach. This study aims to assess the effect of topical chamomile oil on postoperative bowel activity after cesarian section.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st2" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods:</title>
  <p class="p">This randomized controlled trial was carried out in 2015 at Chamran Hospital in Iran. A block randomization list was generated for 142 parturient divided into three groups. In the intervention group (arm A) (
   <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 47), chamomile oil was applied topically on abdominal region after the stability of the patient. Placebo group (arm B) (
   <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 47) received placebo oil and control group (arm C) (
   <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 48) had no intervention. A recovery program was used after surgery for all participants. The primary outcome was time to first flatus. Secondary outcomes were time to bowel sounds, defecation, return of appetite, hospital stay, and rate of nausea and vomiting, abdominal pain.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st3" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Findings:</title>
  <p class="p">Times to first flatus were significantly shorter in Group A (arm A vs. B, 
   <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.001 and arm A vs. C, 
   <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.001). In addition, time to first bowel sounds (arm A vs. B, 
   <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.001 and arm A vs. C, 
   <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and return of appetite (arm A vs. B, 
   <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.001 and arm A vs. C, 
   <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) were significantly shorter in arm A. The times from surgery to first defecation were shorter in Group A versus B and C. However, there were no statistically significant differences between three groups.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st4" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusion:</title>
  <p class="p">These results suggest that topical chamomile oil has a potential therapeutic effect on gastrointestinal motility and can reduce the duration of POI.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
