<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Because of the increasing shortage of wildlife sources, cultivated method starts to be applied on TDG to meet the market demand in consideration of the low survival rate of TDG, so it is of significant to know the growth conditions of TDG, select good varieties, and develop appropriate cultivation techniques. A study discovers that TDG possesses low light acclimation capacity, with the optimal light irradiance condition for TDG cultivation being approximately 67% of the shade. Simultaneously, TDG’s growth and development are limited by ambient temperature (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Dai et al., 2009</xref>). From the transcriptome analysis, 
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al. (2019)</xref> conclude that a total of 114 single genes are assigned to the flavonoid biosynthetic pathway, along with the expression of genes related to flavonol biosynthesis and flavonol content increased in TDG under cold stress. These findings provide valuable information regarding to the transcriptome changes in response to cold stress, and may be useful for creating the novel germplasms with high cold-tolerance 
 <italic>via</italic> molecular breeding. The complete genomic sequence of TDG has been reported to enrich TDG plant information (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2016</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">Song et al. (2017)</xref> isolate 31 endophytic fungi belonging to 10 genera and add fermented broth of endophyte strains (named TH09, TH12, TH14, TH15, TH17, and TH26 respectively) to MS medium to culture axenic seedlings. After 30 days of culture, it is found that endophytic fungi can promote the growth of host plants by measuring net growth, expansion gene expression and flavonoid content, as well as upregulating expansion gene expression and increasing the medicinal ingredient flavonoid synthesis. These findings indicate that new methods for cultivation can be developed from the microbiological aspect to cultivating high-quality varieties. By comparing water extract and alcohol extract, 
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Liu Y. et al. (2019)</xref> evaluate the differences in the various biological activities of the two extracts through different cell models, and eventually get the result that the ethanol extract has good antioxidant activity and decreases with increasing temperature. Whether it is water extract or alcohol extract, research has shown that the temperature should not be too high, otherwise it would destroy its effective ingredients.
</p>
