<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Two other interesting molecules are again carvacrol (12) and thymol (13). The latter was a cardioprotective agent against carotid tissue of hypercholesterolemic rats. The supplementation of thymol (24 mg/kg) in experimental subjects prevents from cardio complications through several mechanisms such as reduction in low density lipoprotein, triglycerides, increment in high-density lipoprotein level, reduction in apoptotic proteins and inflammatory expressions, phosphorylation of p38 (p-p38) and the protein expression of cleaved caspase-3 (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Bayatmakoo et al., 2017</xref>). In another work, thymol (13) administration (7.5 mg/kg) reversed changes produced by isoproterenol in rats. It also enhanced the caspase-8 and 9, as well as Fas genes expression while lowered Bcl-xL gene expression in myocardium (
 <xref rid="B145" ref-type="bibr">Meeran et al., 2016</xref>). Among other effects, previous investigation revealed that multiple pathways are involved in this effect: a lowered serum cardiac troponin-Y, lysosomal thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS), high sensitivity C-reactive protein (hsCRP), and lowered activities of β-glucuronidase, β-galactosidase, cathepsin-B and D activities in lysosomes. Thymol down-regulated the proinflammatory cytokines involving IL-6 and 1β genes expression and TNF-α in myocardium of rats, and lowered heart weight, left ventricular hypertrophy and increased ST segments and tachycardia (
 <xref rid="B152" ref-type="bibr">Nagoor Meeran et al., 2015a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr">Nagoor Meeran et al., 2015b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B154" ref-type="bibr">Nagoor Meeran et al., 2016</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">El-Sayed et al. (2016)</xref> evidenced the protective role of both thymol (13) (20 mg/kg p.o.) and/or carvacrol (12) (25 mg/kg) against doxorubicin induced cardiotoxicity, ameliorating the heart function and oxidative stress parameters.
</p>
