<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to the World Health Organization (WHO), cancer is a group of diseases caused by the malignant growth of cells or tumor resulting from uncontrolled cell division [
 <xref rid="B45-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Cancer was primarily responsible for one in six deaths in among humans in annum of 2018, resulting in an overall estimate of 9.6 million deaths worldwide. Cancer was reported to be the second leading cause of deaths worldwide. Men are often more susceptible to lung, prostate, colorectal, stomach, and liver cancer, while women often suffer from breast, colorectal, lung, cervical, and thyroid cancer [
 <xref rid="B45-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. The majority (70%) of deaths caused by cancer occur in low- and middle-income countries in Africa, Asia, and Central and South America [
 <xref rid="B45-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Currently, therapeutic processes for treating cancer patients present tremendous challenges to both the physician and the patient, resulting from the lack of precision as well as lack of bioavailability, since most anticancer agents are naturally lipophilic and have a high first-pass effect. In addition, these agents are also non-specific towards their targets and, therefore, may interact with non-cancerous tissues. Moreover, cancer patients most often experience adverse effects after therapeutic procedures that are also associated with high toxicity [
 <xref rid="B46-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Due to these complications, cancers and their associated diseases are considered to be a serious healthcare burden to patients globally [
 <xref rid="B49-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. This explains the reasons for continuous focused investigations aimed at discovering new natural bioactive compounds, especially from endophytes, that may serve as alternative agents to combat cancer [
 <xref rid="B47-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].
</p>
