<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Common reed (
 <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> [Cav.] Trin. ex Steud; Poaceae) is a polyploid perennial grass species with clonal architecture [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The species is distributed worldwide and is highly invasive in Kashmir Himalayan aquatic habitats [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In Kashmir, India, this species was earlier reported as a South American native [
 <xref rid="B33-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and European native [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], but substantial molecular evidence for the nativity of this species is lacking. Saltonstall (2002) [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] sampled individuals of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> worldwide and recovered 27 haplotypes of this species on the basis of the sequences of two chloroplast DNA (hereafter, cpDNA) fragments. In North America, both native and exotic haplotypes of the species are found. Introduction of an exotic genotype of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> (Haplotype M) and its rapid spread, aided by anthropogenic disturbance, has contributed significantly to its invasion and range expansion in North America [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Recently, Guo et al. [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] showed that evolutionary mechanisms act differently in the native and introduced ranges of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> and that invasive populations of European origin have evolved to adapt to a different climate and to human-made habitats in North America. In Quebec, Canada, the native haplotype is characterized by a red stem and ligule base (i.e., the junction of the leaf blade with the leaf sheath) with fewer hairs, compared to the green stem of invasive haplotypes, which have more hairs on the ligule. Moreover, the inflorescence of the native haplotype is less dense relative to that of the invasive haplotype, containing fewer seeds [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The invasive haplotype in Quebec tends to grow preferentially along roads and in other human-made habitats, while the native haplotype prefers undisturbed, pristine habitats [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In India, the invasive 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> haplotype is found to occur widely in various aquatic habitats, especially in Kashmir Himalayan wetlands. 
</p>
