<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Cannabis sativa</italic> L. was one of the first cultivated plants, and it was further adapted by humans to a variety of needs: technical (textiles, construction and paper industries), nutritional (food), medicinal and therapeutic, since it contains over 150 bioactive phytocannabinoids [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-24-01138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. It is an annual dioecious plant belonging to the Cannabaceae family and it growths almost in every developed country of the world [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-24-01138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Taxonomic studies have raised a critical issue, owing to the huge variability of specimens within the same genus but, in the scientific community, a monotypic classification is currently preferred [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-24-01138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. According to this agreement, one single species (
 <italic class="italic">C. sativa</italic>) has been supposed, and several chemotypes based on the specific cannabinoid profile have been identified [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-01138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. The two principal phenotypes of interest are the drug-type and the fibre-type 
 <italic class="italic">Cannabis</italic>, also known as “hemp”. The first is rich in psychoactive Δ
 <sup class="sup">9</sup>-tetrahydrocannabinol (Δ
 <sup class="sup">9</sup>-THC), and it is used for medicinal or recreational purposes, while the second has a content of Δ
 <sup class="sup">9</sup>-THC below 0.2–0.3% in dry weight plant material of the upper one-third of the crop; this legal limit was established by the European Industrial Hemp Association (EIHA), in accordance with international regulations [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-24-01138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-24-01138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Discovering the presence of many biologically active metabolites also in fibre-type 
 <italic class="italic">Cannabis</italic> has allowed the valorisation of this latter variety [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-24-01138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-01138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Moreover, the current favourable regulatory framework encourages pharmaceutical and nutraceutical companies to develop and produce dietary supplements containing plant extracts aimed at the maintenance or the recovery of human and animal wellbeing.
</p>
