<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Nanocelluloses, as the principal plant-based source for anisotropic particles, are quasi 1D, high aspect ratio nanofibrils (widths down to the nanometer levels and lengths that can reach several micrometers). Their flexibility is limited to the crystalline domain of the fibrils with sizes in the order of 10
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> nm (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>
 </xref>d).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35" class="xref">35</xref>
 </sup> Taking these features together, it has been postulated that nanocelluloses are ideal choices for oil/water interfacial interactions as long as the radius of curvature of the interface is at least above half the length of the crystalline domains within the nanocellulose.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36" class="xref">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup> For example, interfaces with a radius of curvature in the micrometer scale, onto which CNCs were self-assembled, showed a relatively tight packing (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>
 </xref>d, right). CNC has outstanding axial elastic modulus (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>
 </xref>d, insert), and indirect observations (experimental and computational) reveal the presence of crystal faces that differ in their density of OH groups or hydrophilicity.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup> This expands the possibility for interactions at interfaces but in a manner that is not fully understood; for instance, CNC interacts readily with and stabilizes the oil/water interface, whereas it does not present significant surface (air/water) activity. A plausible explanation is that the surface potential of the air/water interface has an anionic character above pH 4, thus limiting adsorption of negatively charged CNC in conventional conditions.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup> Interestingly, the inherent interparticle electrostatic repulsions do not affect CNC interaction at the air/water interface, for instance, in the assembly of highly packed layers constructed by different deposition techniques, as shown by us,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40" class="xref">40</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup> and even in conditions above the kinetic arrest concentration.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42" class="xref">42</xref>
 </sup> Some clues for the elucidation of the structure of CNC and its potential interaction in an aqueous environment may be given by its polymeric nature that contrasts, for instance, with inorganic particles. For example, polymers such as poly(ethylene glycol) clearly exhibit H-bonding with CNC in the dry state, but the interaction in the wet state is limited.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup> If one takes as an example the surface interactions of polystyrene particles with other multimeric compounds, they are simply explained by the chemical nature of the polymer.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44" class="xref">44</xref>
 </sup> This effect, however, may be limited given the crystalline and highly ordered nature of CNC.
</p>
