<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec20" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anti-biofilm activity</div>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this context, we investigated the ability of ROEO to inhibit biofilm formation or to eradicate preformed biofilm of 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis.</span>
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the anti-adhesion activity, results showed an important attenuated level of 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</span> biofilm formation with different concentration of ROEO ranging from 1.25 to 25 μl ml
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, which presented 4 to 80-fold greater than the MIC. At a concentration of 25 μl ml
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (40–80 × MIC, 10 × MBC), ROEO showed the highest inhibitory effect with a percentage of inhibition value of 57.1%. Moreover, the doses of 12.5, 2.5 and 1.25 μl ml
  <span class="sup">−1</span> exerted also an inhibitory effect with reduction rate of 49.21, 25.43 and 23.24%, respectively (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>).
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Effects of Rosemary essential oil on the inhibition of biofilm formation of 
     <span class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</span> (prevention) expressed as biofilm inhibition (%) (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) and on the reduction of established biofilm of 
     <span class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</span> expressed as biofilm eradication (%) (
     <span class="bold">b</span>). The results are presented as means ± SD of three independent experiments. .* 
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05, ** 
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.01 or ***
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001 versus control values
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12944_2017_580_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ability of the essential oil to destroy established preformed biofilm was also investigated. After an overnight of incubation of established biofilm with essential oil, a concentration of 50 μl ml
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, which presented 20-fold MBC and between 80 and 160 × MIC, was able to reduce the preformed biofilm at only 67.53% (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>). At a concentration of 12.5 μl ml
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, ROEO was able to inhibit 49.21% of cell attachment but only 29.05% of established biofilm was removed. So, the effect of essential oil against the preformed biofilm was lower than that of the inhibition of cell attachment.
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> shows two typical dimensional pictures obtained from the biofilm of strain S61 and the treated biofilm with ROEO using fluorescent microscopy. It could be concluded that ROEO exerted an anti-biofilm activity against S61 with an almost total destruction of biofilm matrix.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Fluorescence microscopy with biofilm coverslips. Biofilms were stained with acridine orange. Bar equals 20 μm 
     <span class="bold">a</span> S61 biofilm, control coverslip; 
     <span class="bold">b</span> S61 biofilm treated with 50 μl/ml of ROEO. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Viability assessment within 
     <span class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</span> biofilm challenged with various ROEO concentrations using resazurin assay. The results are presented as means ± SD of three independent experiments. ** 
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.01 or ***
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001 versus control values
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12944_2017_580_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moreover, Resazurin test showed that ROEO has an effect on the viability of 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</span>. The cell viability is inversely proportional to the concentration of ROEO. In fact, at 50 μl ml
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, the cell viability in 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</span> biofilm did not exceed 50% as assessed by fluorescence measurement (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). The inhibition of cell viability was also found even at a concentration of 1.25 μl ml
  <span class="sup">−1</span>.
 </p>
</sec>
