<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec23" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this research, we determined the chemical composition of the studied ROEO, its antibacterial, antibiofilm and cytotoxic activities. Various studies have been interested in the chemical composition of the ROEO from different countries. The results of ROEO composition are approximately in accordance with those found by Miladi et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]. They reported that the basic compounds were 1,8-cineole (24.10%), camphor (19.87%) and camphene (8.65%), with a remarkably difference in the percentage of α- pinene (13.49%) and β- pinene (3.34%). In another report on ROEO from Brazil, 1,8-cineole (28.5%), followed by camphor (27.7%), α-pinene (21.3%) and camphene (8.7%) were reported as the predominant compounds [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. Kadri et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>] studied the chemical composition of ROEO collected from the mount of Gafsa and reported the main one as 1,8-cineole (35.36%). However, it is different to the studied ROEO composition by the presence of important quantities of trans-caryophyllene (14.7%) and Borneol (9.97%). The quantitative variation of the ROEO chemical composition depends on several factors such as ecological conditions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>], geographic position [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>], period of collection [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>] and oil extraction method [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ROEO is rich in monoterpene compounds (62.28%), which were reported in the literature for their antimicrobial activities [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. More particularly, the richness of the oil in monoterpene hydrocarbons such as 1,8-cineole (23.56%), characterized by its strong antimicrobial activity against several bacteria [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>] may explain the inhibitory and bactericidal effect against both strains 
  <span class="italic">S. epidermidis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus.</span> On the other hand, the effect of minor compounds such as Germacrene-D (0.19%), caryophyllene (2.8%), caryophyllene oxide (5.02%), terpinene-4-ol (1.23%), also known for their antimicrobial effects [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>], could not be denied. In fact, it has been reported that these compounds could act synergistically and consequently be responsible of the founded antibacterial activity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We evaluated the antibiofilm activity against 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</span>, which is affiliated to coagulase-negative staphylococci and known as a commensal microorganism on the human skin [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>]. According to the CDC National Nosocomial Infections Surveillance (NNIS) System Report [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</span> is the most common cause of nosocomial infections in patients with all types of medical devices. In fact, it is often isolated from infected prosthetic joints, central venous catheters, intracardiac devices, artificial heart valves and vascular grafts [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>]. Chu et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>] demonstrated that 
  <span class="italic">S. epidermidis</span> is the cause of 13% of prosthetic valve endocarditis (PVE) infections, with a high rate of intracardiac abscess (38%) and mortality by 24%. Billions of dollars are spent each year for the replacement of infected devices such as intravascular and urinary catheters, mechanical heart valves, pacemakers, contact lenses, prosthetic implants [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two attachment stages are required for biofilm formation; the first is the reversible attachment (low) followed by the second which is the irreversible attachment (strong). Therefore, the high required concentrations to eradicate the already established biofilm compared to those needed to inhibit biofilm formation can deduce that the preformed biofilm may be in the irreversible attachment phase [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>]. On the other hand, this resistance can be attributed to the three-dimensional architecture of the mature biofilm and the presence of an exopolysaccharide polymer matrix acting as a physical barrier against the penetration of antimicrobial agents [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The comparison of the effect of ROEO against biofilm and planktonic cells showed that bacterial cells within biofilm were more resistant than their planktonic forms. These findings correlate with previous studies showing that bacterial resistance to antimicrobial agents within the biofilm can reach 1000 times of the bacterial resistance in suspension [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. Another factor, which can justify the biofilm resistance, is that the majority of antimicrobial agents are active against cells in active division, which is not the case for bacteria in biofilm mode [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>]. In fact, the biofilm is a stack of layers. The deepest are characterized by low growth rates due to the lack of oxygen and nutrients [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>]. It has been previously reported that essential oils could diffuse through polysaccharide matrix of the mature biofilm and destabilize it due to strong intrinsic antimicrobial activities [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. Moreover, the anti-adherent activity is explained by the alteration of bacterial surface proteins due to their interactions with oils. This, will inhibit the initial attachment phase to the abiotic surface [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. These results support the medical application of these oils for the prevention and/or treatment of certain infections and diseases.
 </p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ROEO strongly inhibited the proliferation of Hela followed by MCF-7 cells. The variability of cytotoxicity effect of this oil against Hela and MCF-7 cells could be associated to the polyvalent oil composition, the different types of interaction between compounds and cells [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>] and the difference of cancer cells sensitivities to cytotoxic compounds [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>]. According to the literature, the anticancer activity of ROEO is due to the main components such as 1,8-cineole, camphor, α-pinene [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>] and β-caryophyllene [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>]. The evaluation of cell migration inhibition by ROEO showed that the oil could prevent the rapid cell migration. We can conclude therefore that the ROEO slows the proliferation and the cell migration. Thus, ROEO could be considered as a potential anti-cancer oil.
 </p>
</sec>
