<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Free radicals and reactive oxygen species (ROSs) are byproducts of the basal aerobic metabolism of cells. However, excessive generation of ROSs does result in critical oxidative damage to the cellular components of the cells [
 <xref rid="B133-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>,
 <xref rid="B134-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. Numerous studies suggest that naringenin exhibits profound antioxidant effects against various oxidative insults, which has been reported to improve cardiac functionality even after injuries [
 <xref rid="B135-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. The preclinical and clinical evidence in favor of this has been supported by the findings of various research groups [
 <xref rid="B92-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. One such study conducted by a team of researchers from Cairo University, Egypt, reported that there was a restoration in various antioxidant enzymes including superoxide dismutase (SOD), glutathione-S-transferase (GST), and catalase (CAT) on pre-treatment with naringenin against doxorubicin-induced cardiotoxicity in male Swiss albino rats [
 <xref rid="B136-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>]. In this context, Han et al. (2008) later studied the pathway utilized by naringenin to protect cardiomyocytes from doxorubicin-induced cardiac toxicity [
 <xref rid="B137-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>] and found that the upregulation of several endogenous enzymes possessing antioxidant activities via extracellular regulated kinase 1/2 (ERK1/2) phosphorylation and Nrf2 activation and translocation into the nucleus likely had a key role in the protection of cardiomyocytes. The findings indicated that naringenin protects against cardiomyocyte apoptosis by expressing higher endogenous antioxidants enzyme (SOD, GST, and CAT) via phosphorylation of ERK1/2 and nuclear translocation of Nrf2 [
 <xref rid="B137-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. Subsequently, other researchers opened the horizons of its mechanism and noted that naringenin suppresses the generation of reactive species [
 <xref rid="B45-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], increases the activities of antioxidant enzymes such as superoxide dismutase (SOD) and catalases, and reduces the phosphorylation of ERK1/2 and p38 MAPK. Moreover, it prevents the binding of angiotensin II to angiotensin binding receptors AT1 receptor and AT2 receptor, thereby suppressing the vascular smooth muscle cell proliferation [
 <xref rid="B138-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>].
</p>
