<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2662-7671</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7507638</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3080</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-020-03080-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey on plants used in the treatment of candidiasis in traditional markets of southern Benin</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fanou</surname><given-names>Brice Armand</given-names></name><address><email>fanouabrice@gmail.com</email><email>fanou_bris@yahoo.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5470-9061</contrib-id><name><surname>Klotoe</surname><given-names>Jean Robert</given-names></name><address><email>jrklotoe@yahoo.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fah</surname><given-names>Lauris</given-names></name><address><email>fah_lori@yahoo.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dougnon</surname><given-names>Victorien</given-names></name><address><email>victorien88@hotmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koudokpon</surname><given-names>Charles Hornel</given-names></name><address><email>charleshornel@yahoo.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Toko</surname><given-names>Ghislaine</given-names></name><address><email>ghislainetoko@yahoo.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Loko</surname><given-names>Fr&#x000e9;d&#x000e9;ric</given-names></name><address><email>loko70frederic@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412037.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0382 0205</institution-id><institution>Unit&#x000e9; de Recherche en Microbiologie Appliqu&#x000e9;e et Pharmacologie des substances naturelles (URMAPha), Laboratoire de Recherche en Biologie Appliqu&#x000e9;e (LARBA), Ecole Polytechnique d&#x02019;Abomey-Calavi (EPAC), </institution><institution>Universit&#x000e9; d&#x02019;Abomey-Calavi, </institution></institution-wrap>01BP2009 Cotonou, B&#x000e9;nin </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Ecole Normale Sup&#x000e9;rieure de Natitingou, Universit&#x000e9; Nationale des Sciences, Technologie, Ing&#x000e9;nierie et Math&#x000e9;matiques, BP72 Natitingou, Benin </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Centre de Recherche Enthomologique de Cotonou (CREC), Cotonou, Benin </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>288</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Candidiasis, an opportunistic cosmopolitan disease is nowadays like bacterial infections which is a real public health problem. In view of the emergence of Candida strains resistant to existing antifungal agents, alternative solutions should be considered. This is the purpose of this ethnobotanical survey, which aims to identify the medicinal plant species traditionally used to treat candidiasis in traditional markets of southern Benin.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">The study was performed from October 2015 to January 2018 in the traditional markets of Southern-Benin. Data were collected by two complementary methods: triplet purchase of medicinal recipes (ATRM) from herbalists markets and semi-structured interview (ISS) from traditional healers.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A total of 109 species of medicinal plants belonging to 44 families have been listed and identified. The most frequently cited species were <italic>Pteleopsis suberosa</italic> Engl. &#x00026; Diels, <italic>Lantana camara</italic> L., <italic>Cyanthillium cinereum</italic> (L.) H. Rob, <italic>Ocimum gratissimum</italic> L. and <italic>Lippia multiflora</italic> Moldenke with respectively 43.84, 39.73 and 34.25% citation frequencies for the last three species respectively. Leguminosae (20.18%), Euphorbiaceae (5.50%) and Apocynaceae (5.50%) were the most represented botanical families. Leafy stems were more used than other plant organs. The decoction and the oral route were the most appropriate methods of preparation and administration reported by traditional healers.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Benin&#x02019;s plant cover is made up of a wide variety of medicinal plant species used in the traditionnal treatment of candidiasis and which may constitute new sources of medicines to be developed.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Candidiasis</kwd><kwd>Ethnobotanical survey</kwd><kwd>Medicinal plants</kwd><kwd>Southern Benin</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5">Candidiasis is a cosmopolitan fungal infection associated with yeasts of the genus Candida. It is one of the most common opportunistic infections in tropical areas, with a frequency ranging from 33 to 47% in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In recent decades, their prevalence has been steadily increasing, especially among patients in intensive care and with the advent of HIV/AIDS infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. They affect all types of tissues and mainly mucous membranes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. It is reported that 25% of urinary tract infections were related to Candida spp. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. 50 to 75% of women of childbearing age developed vulvovaginal candidiasis annually and 5 to 8%, or about 75 million women, can be affected at least four times in a year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Oral infections are common but are found in children and immune compromised people [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Ten million cases of oral candidiasis and 2 million esophageal candidiasis are reported annually in people living with HIV. Most seriously, invasive fungal infections are reported to kill more than tuberculosis and malaria and in 90% of fungal deaths, candidiasis ranks second behind cryptococcosis and ahead of aspergillosis and pneumocystis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. They are fatal in 40% of hospital sepsis cases according to letter No. 72 from the Pasteur Institute [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] and are the leading nosocomial fungal disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Their therapeutic management requires the use of antifungals to which <italic>Candida spp.</italic> strains are increasingly resistant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Indeed, high levels of <italic>Candida spp</italic>. resistance to fluconazole have been identified in several countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Candida spp. resistance even extends to amphotericin B [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], one of the last used antifungals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. This emergence of strains resistant to common molecules is, like the emergence of bacterial resistance to antibiotics, of a great public health concern for which sustainable alternative solutions must be found very quickly. In African countries, these alternative solutions involve the use of medicinal plants. Indeed, the use of plants to treat diseases is an old practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] and endogenous to populations. According to several authors, in Africa and Asia, 80% of the population continues to use traditional medicines rather than the so-called modern medicines for primary health care for various reasons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Today, with the support of WHO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], many research focuses on plants to look for active compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In this sense, some research carried out on plants has shown in vitro their antifungal potential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] and could thus constitute new sources of bioactive molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">Unfortunately, plant resources are under significant anthropogenic pressure which dangerously reduces plant biodiversity. According to Dj&#x000e9;go et al., Benin loses 60,000&#x02009;ha of forest per year, an annual rate of deforestation estimated at 1.2%. This deforestation is not without consequences for conservation on medicinal plants. Several medicinal species have thus disappeared or are threatened with extinction. It is therefore important to ensure their conservation for the next generations. This requires their knowledge and compliance with the rules of sustainable use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">In Benin, the plant species indicated for candidiasis treatment is still poorly known, because few studies have been carried out on the antifungal properties of some medicinal plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. This work is therefore the first on aiming to identify the medicinal plants indicated by herbalists and traditional healers in southern Benin for the treatment of candidiasis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Framework</title><p id="Par8">The surveys were conducted in Benin from October 2015 to January 2017, in the geographical area between longitude 03&#x000b0; 40&#x02032; and 04&#x000b0; 11&#x02032; north and the 09&#x000b0; 16&#x02032; - 09&#x000b0; 52&#x02032; east meridians. It is bordered to the north by Bassila and Tchaourou municipalities (departments of Borgou and Donga), to the west by Togo, to the east by Nigeria and to the south by the Atlantic Ocean (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). It covers eight of the twelve departments in the Republic of Benin and corresponds to thirty-six (36) municipalities out of the forty-one in the southern part of Benin.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Location of traditional markets covered by the ethnobotanical survey</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3080_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par9">The localities concerned by study are:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par10">Cotonou (09 traditional markets: Agla, Akpakpa, Dantokpa, Fifadji, Fidjross&#x000e8;, Gb&#x000e8;djrom&#x000e8;d&#x000e9;, Gbogbanou, M&#x000e8;nontin, Wologu&#x000e8;d&#x000e8;)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par11">Abomey-Calavi (04 traditional markets: Atrokpocodji, Godomey, Tokan, Tokpa)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par12">Porto-Novo (02 traditional markets: Ahidahom&#x000e8;, Ouando)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par13">Abomey (01 traditional market: Houndjro)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par14">Adjara (01 traditional market: Adjarra)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par15">Azov&#x000e8; (01 traditional market: Azov&#x000e8;hi)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par16">Bohicon (01 traditional market: Gbohicon)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par17">Cov&#x000e8; (01 traditional market: Cov&#x000e8;hi)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par18">Dassa-Zoum&#x000e8; (01 traditional market: Dassa)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par19">Dogbo-Tota (01 traditional market: Dogbo)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par20">Klou&#x000e9;kanmey (01 traditional market: Klou&#x000e9;kanm&#x000e8;)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par21">Lokossa (01 traditional market: Lokossahim&#x000e8;)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par22">Ouidah (01 traditional market: Kpass&#x000e8;)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par23">Savalou (01 traditional market: Savalouhi)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par24">Sav&#x000e8; (01 traditional market: Sav&#x000e8;)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par25">Tori (01 traditional market: Gbodj&#x000e8;).</p></list-item></list></p><sec id="Sec4"><title>Equipment</title><p id="Par26">Equipment used in this study consists mainly of survey sheets for information collection, a digital camera, a self-recording audio device for interview recording, a position marker (GPRS).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par27">The surveys were conducted with two groups of professionals: market herbalists and traditional healers. Market herbalists sell herbal remedies and also compose recipes for the treatment of illnesses. They don&#x02019;t directly treat patients. This role is reserved for traditional healers. The traditional healers interviewed are recognized by the National Program for the Promotion of Traditional Medicine in Benin. As for herbalists, they are registered with the market management company.</p><p id="Par28">Two (02) methods were used for each group of informants. Thus, among market herbalists, the triplet purchase of medicinal recipes (ATRM) method was used and the semi-structured interview method (ISS) was used among traditional healers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</p><p id="Par29">Interviews were conducted in three local languages (Fon, Goun or Mina) and then in French for those who were literate. An interpreter was recruited from each location where local language spoken was not understand.</p><p id="Par30">Data collected consisted of the socio-demographic characteristics of the respondents (sex, age, professional experience, mode of entry into the profession) and information on the recipes used to treat candidiasis (composition of recipes, local names and parts of plants used, methods of preparation and administration routes of the recipes served, dosage, bans and side effects). The study focused on cutaneous candidiasis &#x0201c;Atita&#x0201d;; oral candidiasis &#x0201c;<italic>Noum&#x000e8; vo</italic>&#x0201d;, genital candidiasis or vulvovaginitis &#x0201c;<italic>Atita do Gnonnnou hou&#x000e9;</italic>&#x0201d;. Pictures of the recipes and plants mentioned were taken and sampled. Herbariums were then created for taxonomic identification (scientific name, family).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Identification of plant species</title><p id="Par31">The species mentioned by the markets herbalist were purchased and those indicated by the traditional healers were harvested. Each time, care was taken to collect or purchase fresh samples for identification. These collected samples were identified at the National Herbarium of Benin of the University of Abomey-Calavi (UAC-Benin) using the analytical flora of Benin by Ako&#x000e8;gninou et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The botanical nomenclature used is that of the &#x0201c;The Plant List&#x0201d; database available on the website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.theplantlist.org">www.theplantlist.org</ext-link>.</p><p id="Par32">Listed plant species were checked against the IUCN Red List Categories (Critically Endangered, Endangered, Vulnerable, Near Threatened) to identify endangered species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par33">The data collected were processed using Microsoft Excel version 2010 software, which was also used to draw graphs (Pie charts, charts and histograms). The variables were presented in percentage.</p><p id="Par34">The phototherapeutic importance of each species was assessed by calculating four parameters, namely:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par35">The informant fidelity index (<bold>FI</bold>)</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par36"><inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ FI=\frac{\mathrm{Nc}}{\mathrm{Nt}}x100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="inline"><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">FI</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>Nc</mml:mi><mml:mi>Nt</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3080_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> (Nc&#x02009;=&#x02009;number of informants in a given category who cited the species; Nt&#x02009;=&#x02009;total number of informants in all categories who cited the same species).</p><p id="Par37">It makes it possible to assess the relationship between a given plant species and its use by herbalists and/or traditional healers in the treatment of candidiasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par38">The Informant Consensus Factor (<bold>ICF</bold>) calculated by the formula (total number of revenues minus total number of informants / total number of revenues minus 1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. This consensus factor of informants here expresses their &#x0201c;approval rate&#x0201d; in related to the plants used to make the recipes for candidiasis treatment. The value of the ICF is less than or equal to 1, so when the value of the ICF is less than 0.5, the consensus is low, when it is between 0.5 and 0.75 the consensus is high and very high when the ICF tends towards 1.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par39">The citation frequency (<bold>Fc</bold>) expressed as a percentage (%) and obtained by the formula: (number of citations of a species / total number of citations of species) &#x000d7;&#x02009;100 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par40">The contribution of each plant species to recipes composition (<bold>Cpr</bold>) expressed as a percentage (%). It is also the frequency with which plants are involved in recipes. It was calculated by the formula (number of recipes using the plant species / total number of recipes) &#x000d7;&#x02009;100 (55).</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Sociodemographic characteristics of responders</title><p id="Par41">The recipes were provided by seventy-three (73) informants, fifty-one (51) market herbalists and twenty-two (22) traditional healers with an average age of 52&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;14.65&#x02009;years. All the traditional healers were men and the market herbalists were women. The average ages of traditional healers and herbalists were 53.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;14.79&#x02009;years and 51.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;14.63&#x02009;years respectively, with 40 to 60&#x02009;years as predominant age group (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The majority (90%) of informants were experienced in this activity for at least ten years. And more than half of them (63%) had more than twenty years&#x02019; experience (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) but traditional healers seem to be less experienced than market herbalists. Two thirds (67%) of the responders were out of school. However, the traditional healers sub-group has more educated people than the market herbalists (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Age distribution of respondents</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Age groups (years)</th><th>Herbalists n (Frequency in %)</th><th>Traditional healers n (Frequency in %)</th><th>Overall n (Frequency in %)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Below 20</td><td>0 (<bold>0%</bold>)</td><td>0 (0%)</td><td>0 (0%)</td></tr><tr><td>[20&#x02013;40[</td><td>9 (<bold>17.65%</bold>)</td><td>3 (<bold>13.64%</bold>)</td><td>12 (<bold>16.44%</bold>)</td></tr><tr><td>[40&#x02013;60[</td><td>26 (<bold>50.98%</bold>)</td><td>12 (<bold>54.54%</bold>)</td><td>38 (<bold>52.05%</bold>)</td></tr><tr><td>60 and more</td><td>16 (<bold>31.37%</bold>)</td><td>7 (<bold>31.82%</bold>)</td><td>23 (<bold>31.51%</bold>)</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>51 (100.00%)</td><td>22 (100.00%)</td><td>73 (100%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Professional experience of informants</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3080_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Educational level of respondents</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3080_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Inventory of recipes and plant species</title><p id="Par42">A total of 124 recipes were provided, 81 (65%) of which were from market herbalists. Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> gives the composition of the recipes served. The recipes are made up of a single plant species (21.77%) or a combination of plants species (78.23%). The number of plants per recipe varied according to the category of informants. It was obvious that the proportion of plants constituting the recipes for market herbalists was in opposite trend compared to that of traditional healers. Indeed, plant associations were much more noticeable among herbalists with 45.68% of recipes composed of more than 6 plant species compared to only 6.98% among traditional healers. It should be noted that in some cases (6.45%) non-plant elements such as mineral compound (kaolin, alum or salt) and sulphur are added to plant organs in the composition of recipes.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Composition of recipes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2"/><th colspan="6">n (Frequency in %)</th></tr><tr><th>Single plants</th><th>Plants + NPE</th><th>1Plant</th><th>2plants</th><th>3 to 5plants</th><th>6plants and more</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Herbalists</td><td>80 (98.77%)</td><td>1 (1.23%)</td><td>10 (12.35%)</td><td>11 (13.58%)</td><td>23 (28.40%)</td><td>37 (45.68%)</td></tr><tr><td>Traditional healers</td><td>36 (83.72%)</td><td>7 (16.28%)</td><td>17 (30.23%)</td><td>16 (37.21%)</td><td>7 (16.28%)</td><td>3 (6.98%)</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Global</bold></td><td>116 (93.55%)</td><td>8 (6.45%)</td><td>23 (21.77%)</td><td>27 (21.77%)</td><td>30 (24.19%)</td><td>40 (32.26%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>NPE</italic> non-plant elements (Kaolin, alum, sulphur)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par43">The high proportion of recipes provided by herbalists could have a pecuniary cause. Indeed, since the recipes were bought from herbalists and the cost of a recipe varies most of the time between 300f CFA for the cheapest and 500f CFA or even 1200f CFA for the most expensive, the herbalists prefer to pay for the same affection all that they know as recipes.</p><p id="Par44">The most used preparation method is decoction (82%). Only traditional healers talked about maceration, corresponding to only 2.45% of recipe preparation methods (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The oral route was the most indicated route (45.16%) by informants for preparation administering (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Recipe preparation methods</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3080_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Administration modes of preparation</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3080_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par45">The floristic inventory of species identified 109 species of 101 genera and divided into 44 botanical families (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>) with an overall ICF consensus index of 0.12.
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>List of plant species used for traditional treatment of candidiasis in traditional markets of southern Benin</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>N&#x000b0;</th><th>Voucher Number</th><th>Scientific names</th><th>Vernacular names</th><th>Botanical families</th><th>Parts of plants used</th><th>Mode of preparation</th><th>administration route</th><th>Fc (%)</th><th>Cpr (%)</th><th>IFh (%)</th><th>IFt (%)</th><th>Previous References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>YH 337 / HNB</td><td><italic>Abutilon mauritianum</italic> (Jacq.) Medik.</td><td>Adansounyi (f,g)</td><td>Malvaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>YH 358 / HNB</td><td><italic>Acacia nilotica</italic> (L.) Delile</td><td>Bani (f, y)</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>4.59</td><td>4.03</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>AA 6752 / HNB</td><td><italic>Acalypha wilkesiana</italic> M&#x000fc;ll. Arg</td><td>&#x0201c;Flowa&#x0201d;</td><td>Euphorbiaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>YH 286 / HNB</td><td><italic>Aframomum melegueta</italic> K. Schum.</td><td>Atakoun (f,g)</td><td>Zingiberaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>R cend</td><td>Oral</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>50</td><td>50</td><td/></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>YH 338 / HNB</td><td><italic>Afzelia africana</italic> Pers.</td><td>Kpakpatin / Kpakpa Jid&#x000e9; / Kpakpa Gid&#x000e9; (f)</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Powder</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>50</td><td>50</td><td/></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>YH 339 / HNB</td><td><italic>Allium cepa</italic> L.</td><td>Ayoma, Ayomasa, vovo, massa (f, g)</td><td>Amaryllidaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>2.75</td><td>2.42</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>YH 287 / HNB</td><td><italic>Allium sativum</italic> L.</td><td>Ayo (f, g)</td><td>Amaryllidaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec; Mac</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>YH 345 / HNB</td><td><italic>Amaranthus spinosus</italic> L.</td><td>Handoukpo (f)</td><td>Amaranthaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec; Mac; Mettre en poudre</td><td>Oral</td><td>2.75</td><td>2.42</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>YH 340 / HNB</td><td><italic>Anacardium occidentale</italic> L.</td><td>Akaju (tin), Lakazu (f,g)</td><td>Anacardiaceae</td><td>B</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>3.67</td><td>3.23</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>YH 341 / HNB</td><td><italic>Annona muricata</italic> L.</td><td>Nyiglwe, anyiglwe (f); Chap-chap (fr)</td><td>Annonaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>2.75</td><td>2.42</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>YH 342 / HNB</td><td><italic>Anogeissus leiocarpa</italic> (DC) Guill. &#x00026; Perr.</td><td>Hlihon, hilihon (f)</td><td>Combretaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>50</td><td>50</td><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">12</td><td rowspan="2">YH 343 / HNB</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Antiaris toxicaria</italic> Lesch.</td><td rowspan="2">Guxotin (t)</td><td rowspan="2">Moraceae</td><td>Le</td><td rowspan="2">Powder</td><td rowspan="2">Topic</td><td rowspan="2">0.92</td><td rowspan="2">0.81</td><td rowspan="2">0</td><td rowspan="2">100</td><td rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td>S</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>YH 395 / HNB</td><td><italic>Bambusa vulgaris</italic> Schrad.</td><td>Bambou (fr)</td><td>Poaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>9.17</td><td>8.06</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>YH 400 / HNB</td><td><italic>Bauhinia reticulata</italic> DC.</td><td>Kpakpa, Klon (f); Kongbo (g)</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>YH 344 / HNB</td><td><italic>Blighia sapida</italic> K. D. K&#x000f6;ening</td><td>Lisetin (f);</td><td>Sapindaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Powder</td><td>Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">16</td><td rowspan="2">YH 293 / HNB</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Bridelia ferruginea</italic> Benth.</td><td rowspan="2">Honsukokwe, Hongla (f, g);</td><td rowspan="2">Phyllanthaceae</td><td>B</td><td rowspan="2">Dec</td><td rowspan="2">Oral + Topic</td><td rowspan="2">15.6</td><td rowspan="2">13.71</td><td rowspan="2">100</td><td rowspan="2">0</td><td rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td>R</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>YH 296 / HNB</td><td><italic>Caesalpinia bonduc</italic> (L.) Roxb.</td><td>Ajikun, ajikwin (f, g)</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec; Pounding</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>3.67</td><td>3.23</td><td>25</td><td>75</td><td/></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>YH 347 / HNB</td><td><italic>Caesalpinia pulcherrima</italic> (L.) Sw.</td><td>Orgeuil de Chine (fr);</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>3.67</td><td>3.23</td><td>50</td><td>50</td><td/></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>YH 348 / HNB</td><td><italic>Cajanus cajan</italic> (L.) Millsp.</td><td>Klwekun (f,g)</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>3.67</td><td>3.23</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>20</td><td>YH 298 / HNB</td><td><italic>Carica papaya</italic> L.</td><td>Kp&#x000e8;n (tin) (l&#x02019;arbre), Jikp&#x000e8;n (le fruit) (f);</td><td>Caricaceae</td><td>R</td><td>Powder</td><td>Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">21</td><td rowspan="2">YH 290 / HNB</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Carissa spinarum</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="2">Ahanzo (f);</td><td rowspan="2">Apocynaceae</td><td>R</td><td rowspan="2">Dec</td><td rowspan="2">Oral + Topic</td><td rowspan="2">6.42</td><td rowspan="2">5.65</td><td rowspan="2">71</td><td rowspan="2">29</td><td rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td>B</td></tr><tr><td>22</td><td>YH 349 / HNB</td><td><italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> (L.) G. Don</td><td>Flawe (f)</td><td>Apocynaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>23</td><td>YH 350 / HNB</td><td><italic>Ceropegia fusiformis</italic>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://n.e.br">N.E.Br</ext-link>.</td><td>Zunkuju wewe (f)</td><td>Apocynaceae</td><td>R</td><td>Mac</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>24</td><td>YH 303 / HNB</td><td><italic>Citrus aurantiifolia</italic> (Christm.) Swingle</td><td>Kl&#x000e9;, (f)</td><td>Rutaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>2.75</td><td>2.42</td><td>33</td><td>67</td><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">25</td><td rowspan="2">YH 353 / HNB</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Clausena anisata</italic> (WilId.) Hook.f. ex Benth.</td><td rowspan="2">Gbozohouin/ Gbosu / Zohw&#x0025b;n/ Gboma Duwa Zohw&#x0025b;n (f)</td><td rowspan="2">Rutaceae</td><td>Le</td><td rowspan="2">Dec</td><td rowspan="2">Oral + Topic</td><td rowspan="2">6.42</td><td rowspan="2">5.65</td><td rowspan="2">86</td><td rowspan="2">14</td><td rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td>R</td></tr><tr><td>26</td><td>YH 354 / HNB</td><td><italic>Clerodendrum capitatum</italic> (WilId.) Schumach. &#x00026; Thonn.</td><td>Zoplotin (f); W&#x000e8;ma (f,g)</td><td>Lamiaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>2.75</td><td>2.42</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>27</td><td>YH 306 / HNB</td><td><italic>Cola nitida</italic> (Vent.) Sebott &#x00026; EndI.</td><td>Gbanja, Goro, Golo</td><td>Malvaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td>28</td><td>YH 356 / HNB</td><td><italic>Combretum micranthum</italic> G.Don</td><td>Vrai Kink&#x000e9;liba (fr); kinikiniba (f)</td><td>Combretaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>29</td><td>YH 383 / HNB</td><td><italic>Combretum paniculatum</italic> Vent.</td><td>Dongbo (Dokpo)</td><td>Combretaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td>30</td><td>YH 357 / HNB</td><td><italic>Commiphora africana</italic> (A.Rich.) Engl.</td><td>Liji (man)(f);</td><td>Burseraceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td>31</td><td>YH 359 / HNB</td><td><italic>Crateva adansonii</italic> DC.</td><td>Onton zunzen; Wonton Zinzwen (f, g); Sharu w&#x000e9;w&#x000e9; (y)</td><td>Capparaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>10.09</td><td>8.87</td><td>64</td><td>36</td><td/></tr><tr><td>32</td><td>YH 360 / HNB</td><td><italic>Croton gratissimus</italic> Burch.</td><td>Jelele, jebele (f,g)</td><td>Euphorbiaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>2.75</td><td>2.42</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>33</td><td>YH 355 / HNB</td><td><italic>Croton lobatus</italic> L.</td><td>Al&#x000f2;vi at&#x000f2;n (f)</td><td>Euphorbiaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>34</td><td>YH 361 / HNB</td><td><italic>Curculigo pilosa</italic> (Schumach. &#x00026; Thonn.) Engl.</td><td>Ayote, ayogl&#x000e8;n, (f)</td><td>Hypoxidaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Mac</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>35</td><td>YH 419 / HNB</td><td><italic>Cyanthillium cinereum</italic> (L.) H.Rob.</td><td>Hunsukus&#x0025b; / Hunsikonu (F)</td><td>Compositae</td><td>Pe</td><td>Dec; Pounding; Grilling</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>22.94</td><td>20.16</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>36</td><td>YH 362 / HNB</td><td><italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic> (DC.) Stapf</td><td>Tcha; Ca / Ti (man) (f)</td><td>Poaceae</td><td>Le</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>2.75</td><td>2.42</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">37</td><td rowspan="2">YH 363 / HNB</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Daniellia oliveri</italic> (Rolfe) Hutch. &#x00026; Dalziel</td><td rowspan="2">Zaxaya (f)</td><td rowspan="2">Leguminosae</td><td>Tf</td><td rowspan="2">Dec</td><td rowspan="2">Oral + Topic</td><td rowspan="2">1.83</td><td rowspan="2">1.61</td><td rowspan="2">100</td><td rowspan="2">0</td><td rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td>R</td></tr><tr><td>38</td><td>YH 310 / HNB</td><td><italic>Desmodium velutinum</italic> (Willd.) DC.</td><td>T&#x000e8;d&#x02019;avowu, Z&#x0025b;n&#x02019;ali (f)</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>39</td><td>YH 365 / HNB</td><td><italic>Detarium microcarpum</italic> Guill. &#x00026; Perr.</td><td>Dakpa, dagpa (f);</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>R</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>40</td><td>YH 366 / HNB</td><td><italic>Dialium guineense</italic> WiIld.</td><td>As&#x000f2;nsw&#x000e8;n, asiswetin, aswenswen (f, g);</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>41</td><td>YH 367 / HNB</td><td><italic>Dichapetalum madagascariense</italic> Poir</td><td>Gbaglo (f)</td><td>Dichapetalaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>42</td><td>YH 368 / HNB</td><td><italic>Dichrostachys cinerea</italic> (L.) Wight &#x00026; Arn.</td><td>abadaw&#x000e8;n, badaw&#x000e8;n (f)</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Le</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td>43</td><td>YH 346 / HNB</td><td><italic>Diodella scandens</italic> (Sw.) Bacigalupo &#x00026; E.L.Cabral</td><td>S&#x000e8;houn (f)</td><td>Rubiaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>44</td><td>YH 351 / HNB</td><td><italic>Dysphania ambrosioides</italic> (L.) Mosyakin &#x00026; Clemants</td><td>Amatluzu, godo (f)</td><td>Amaranthaceae</td><td>Pe</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>4.59</td><td>4.03</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>45</td><td>YH 369 / HNB</td><td><italic>Echinochloa pyramidalis</italic> (Lam.) Hitchc. &#x00026; Chase</td><td>Woko (g);</td><td>Poaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>46</td><td>YH 370 / HNB</td><td><italic>Ehretia cymosa</italic> Thonn.</td><td>Zozoma (f); myoma (g);</td><td>Boraginaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>5.5</td><td>4.84</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>47</td><td>YH 371 / HNB</td><td><italic>Entada gigas</italic> (L.) Fawc &#x00026; Rendle</td><td>Gbagbakwin (f);</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>L</td><td>Powder</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>50</td><td>50</td><td/></tr><tr><td>48</td><td>YH 372 / HNB</td><td><italic>Erythrina senegalensis</italic> DC.</td><td>Kpaklesi, pakl&#x000e9;w&#x000e9;s&#x000e8; (f);</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>B</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>49</td><td>YH 373 / HNB</td><td><italic>Eucalyptus camaldulensis</italic> Dehnh.</td><td>Eucalyptus rouge, eucalyptus rostr&#x000e9;,</td><td>Myrtaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>50</td><td>YH 374 / HNB</td><td><italic>Euphorbia hirta</italic> L.</td><td>Hundi hundi asu (f)</td><td>Euphorbiaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>51</td><td>YH 314 / HNB</td><td><italic>Flacourtia flavescens</italic> Willd</td><td>Gbohunkaje / Gbowunkaj&#x0025b; (f);</td><td>Salicaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>52</td><td>YH 260 / HNB</td><td><italic>Garcinia kola</italic> Heckel</td><td>Ahowetin (l&#x02019;arbre), ahow&#x000e9; (la graine) (f, g); arow&#x000e9; (f);</td><td>Clusiaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>3.67</td><td>3.23</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>53</td><td>YH 352 / HNB</td><td><italic>Gladiolus dalenii</italic> van Geel</td><td>Baka [petit oignon]</td><td>Iridaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>3.67</td><td>3.23</td><td>50</td><td>50</td><td/></tr><tr><td>54</td><td>YH 376 / HNB</td><td><italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L.</td><td>Avokanfoun tin (f)</td><td>Malvaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Topic</td><td>2.75</td><td>2.42</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>55</td><td>YH 418 / HNB</td><td><italic>Gymnanthemum coloratum</italic> (Wild.) H.Rob. &#x00026; B.Kahn</td><td>Alomaklu/ Amavive gb&#x000e9;menton (f)/ Gb&#x000e9;l&#x000e9; man</td><td>Compositae</td><td>Pe</td><td>Dec</td><td>Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>56</td><td>YH 377 / HNB</td><td><italic>Heliotropium indicum</italic> L.</td><td>Koklon son, Kokloden; koklosu denpaja (f)</td><td>Boraginaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>57</td><td>YH 420 / HNB</td><td><italic>Hymenocardia acida</italic> Tul.</td><td>Mlanlanv&#x000ea; man (f); Manlanvi (g)</td><td>Phyllanthaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Pounding</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>58</td><td>YH 378 / HNB</td><td><italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> (L.) Poit.</td><td>Afio, Xweflu, hw&#x000e9;flou (f)</td><td>Lamiaceae</td><td>Pe</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>19.27</td><td>16.94</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">59</td><td rowspan="2">YH 421 / HNB</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Imperata cylindrica</italic> (L.) Raeusch.</td><td rowspan="2">X&#x000e8;, x&#x000e8;tin (f), Ox&#x0025b; tin</td><td rowspan="2">Poaceae</td><td>R</td><td rowspan="2">Dec</td><td rowspan="2">Oral + Topic</td><td rowspan="2">5.5</td><td rowspan="2">4.84</td><td rowspan="2">100</td><td rowspan="2">0</td><td rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td>Tf</td></tr><tr><td>60</td><td>YH 411 / HNB</td><td><italic>Indigofera pulchra</italic> Willd.</td><td>Zounh&#x000f4; (Zuko), adoma (f);</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>61</td><td>YH 379 / HNB</td><td><italic>Jatropha gossypiifolia</italic> L.</td><td>Nyikpotin, gbagidi kpotin (f, g);</td><td>Euphorbiaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>6.42</td><td>5.65</td><td>29</td><td>71</td><td/></tr><tr><td>62</td><td>YH 380 / HNB</td><td><italic>Kedrostis foetidissima</italic> (Jacq.) Cogn.</td><td>Jixo cyoma; Tchioma (f)</td><td>Cucurbitaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Pounding</td><td>Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td>63</td><td>YH 381 / HNB</td><td><italic>Khaya senegalensis</italic> (Desr.) A. Juss.</td><td>Zunzatin (f) / Agawu /Tere (g)</td><td>Meliaceae</td><td>B</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>20.18</td><td>17.74</td><td>91</td><td>9</td><td/></tr><tr><td>64</td><td>YH 382 / HNB</td><td><italic>Kigelia africana</italic> (Lam.) Benth.</td><td>Nyablikpo (f);</td><td>Bignoniaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec; Mac</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>2.75</td><td>2.42</td><td>33</td><td>67</td><td/></tr><tr><td>65</td><td>AA 6749 / HNB</td><td><italic>Lantana camara</italic> L.</td><td>Hla Ciyayo / Hla Coyo (f) /Zansoukp&#x000ea; man/ Hla Ciyamadidwe (G)</td><td>Verbenaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec; Pounding</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>26.61</td><td>23.39</td><td>90</td><td>10</td><td/></tr><tr><td>66</td><td>YH 384 / HNB</td><td><italic>Lawsonia inermis</italic> L.</td><td>Lalitin (f); laritin (g); lali (y, n)</td><td>Lythraceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>67</td><td>AA 6750 / HNB</td><td><italic>Lippia multiflora</italic> Moldenke</td><td>Agala (f)/ Aklala (g)</td><td>Verbenaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec; Pounding</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>22.94</td><td>20.16</td><td>96</td><td>4</td><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">68</td><td rowspan="2">YH 385 / HNB</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="2">Manga, amanga (f)</td><td rowspan="2">Anacardiaceae</td><td>B</td><td rowspan="2">Dec</td><td rowspan="2">Oral</td><td rowspan="2">4.59</td><td rowspan="2">4.03</td><td rowspan="2">80</td><td rowspan="2">20</td><td rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td>R</td></tr><tr><td>69</td><td>YH 386 / HNB</td><td><italic>Melaleuca leucadendra</italic> (L.) L.</td><td>Kpenma s&#x000e8;m&#x000e8;ton (f).</td><td>Myrtaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>70</td><td>YH 388 / HNB</td><td><italic>Mitracarpus hirtus</italic> (L.) DC.</td><td>Godokwe, Godoko (f);</td><td>Rubiaceae</td><td>Pe</td><td>Pounding</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>4.59</td><td>4.03</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>71</td><td>YH 389 / HNB</td><td><italic>Momordica charantia</italic> L.</td><td>Nyensinken (f)</td><td>Cucurbitaceae</td><td>Pe</td><td>Dec; Mac</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>5.5</td><td>4.84</td><td>83</td><td>17</td><td/></tr><tr><td>72</td><td>YH 375 / HNB</td><td><italic>Mondia whitei</italic> (Hook.f.) Skeels</td><td>Cirigun (f)</td><td>Apocynaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Pounding; Mac</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>73</td><td>YH 319 / HNB</td><td><italic>Monodora myristica</italic> (Gaertn.) Dunal</td><td>Sasalikun, sasagbakun (f,g)</td><td>Annonaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec; Mac; Grilling</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>14.68</td><td>12.9</td><td>75</td><td>25</td><td/></tr><tr><td>74</td><td>YH 320 / HNB</td><td><italic>Morinda lucida</italic> Benth.</td><td>Xwensin</td><td>Rubiaceae</td><td>R</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>75</td><td>YH 390 / HNB</td><td><italic>Musa &#x000d7; paradisiaca</italic> L.</td><td>Kokw&#x000e9; azo</td><td>Musaceae</td><td>Le</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>76</td><td>YH 391 / HNB</td><td><italic>Ocimum americanum</italic> L.</td><td>Kesu kesu, xesu xesu, xisi xisi (f); akohun (g)</td><td>Lamiaceae</td><td>Pe</td><td>Dec; Pounding</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>17.43</td><td>15.32</td><td>84</td><td>16</td><td/></tr><tr><td>77</td><td>YH 325 / HNB</td><td><italic>Ocimum gratissimum</italic> L.</td><td>Tchao, Ciyayo (f)</td><td>Lamiaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec; Pounding</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>22.94</td><td>20.16</td><td>68</td><td>32</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>78</td><td>YH 392 / HNB</td><td><italic>Olax subscorpioides</italic> Oliv.</td><td>Mitin, mitun (f);</td><td>Olacaceae</td><td>R</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>2.75</td><td>2.42</td><td>67</td><td>33</td><td/></tr><tr><td>79</td><td>YH 393 / HNB</td><td><italic>Parkia biglobosa</italic> (Jacq.) G Don</td><td>Ahwatin, afiti (f)</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>B</td><td>Pounding</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>80</td><td>YH 394 / HNB</td><td><italic>Paullinia pinnata</italic> L.</td><td>Xedulinifen (f, g);</td><td>Sapindaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>4.59</td><td>4.03</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>81</td><td>YH 397 / HNB</td><td><italic>Persicaria senegalensis</italic> (Meisn.) Soj&#x000e1;k</td><td>Towe (g);</td><td>Polygonaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>4.59</td><td>4.03</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>82</td><td>YH 398 / HNB</td><td><italic>Philenoptera laxiflora</italic> (Guill. &#x00026; Perr.) Roberty,</td><td>Ahoma; Aho ma (f)</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Le</td><td>Pounding</td><td>Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td>83</td><td>YH 387 / HNB</td><td><italic>Phymatosorus scolopendria</italic> (Burm. f.) Pic. Serm.</td><td>Duma (f), Degoma (g).</td><td>Polypodiaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>2.75</td><td>2.42</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>84</td><td>YH 401 / HNB</td><td><italic>Piper nigrum</italic> L.</td><td>L&#x000e8;nkun, (f); l&#x000e8;nl&#x000e8;nkun g)</td><td>Piperaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td>85</td><td>YH 399 / HNB</td><td><italic>Pleiocarpa pycnantha</italic> (K.Schum.) Stapf</td><td>Dany&#x000e8; (f); Vonma (g);</td><td>Apocynaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">86</td><td rowspan="2">YH 402 / HNB</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Pseudocedrela kotschyi</italic> (Schweinf.) Harms</td><td rowspan="2">Atindodokpwe / Atinsudo dokpo (f)</td><td rowspan="2">Meliaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td rowspan="2">Dec</td><td rowspan="2">Oral + Topic</td><td rowspan="2">5.5</td><td rowspan="2">4.84</td><td rowspan="2">100</td><td rowspan="2">0</td><td rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td>R</td></tr><tr><td>87</td><td>AA 6753 / HNB</td><td><italic>Pteleopsis suberosa</italic> Engl. &#x00026; Diels</td><td>Kulu Kuli (f)/ Klwi-Klwi (f)</td><td>Combretaceae</td><td>B</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>29.36</td><td>25.81</td><td>94</td><td>6</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>88</td><td>YH 403 / HNB</td><td><italic>Pterocarpus erinaceus</italic> Poir.</td><td>Gb&#x000e8;gb&#x000e8;tin (f)</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>B</td><td>Dec</td><td>Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td>89</td><td>YH 404 / HNB</td><td><italic>Rhaphiostylis beninensis</italic> (Hook.f. ex Planch.) Planch. ex Benth.</td><td>Kplakplama (f)</td><td>Icacinaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>90</td><td>YH 405 / HNB</td><td><italic>Ricinus communis</italic> L.</td><td>Kasu wayi (a)</td><td>Euphorbiaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>R.cend</td><td>Oral</td><td>1.83</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>91</td><td>YH 261 / HNB</td><td><italic>Rourea coccinea</italic> (Thonn. ex Schumach.) Benth.</td><td>Nociovij&#x000e8;, (f)</td><td>Connaraceae</td><td>R</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">92</td><td rowspan="2">YH 406 / HNB</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Sarcocephalus latifolius</italic> (Sm.) E. A. Bruce</td><td rowspan="2">Ko (ma) (f); kodo (g)</td><td rowspan="2">Rubiaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td rowspan="2">Dec</td><td rowspan="2">Oral + Topic</td><td rowspan="2">4.59</td><td rowspan="2">4.03</td><td rowspan="2">60</td><td rowspan="2">40</td><td rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td>R</td></tr><tr><td>93</td><td>YH 407 / HNB</td><td><italic>Schwenckia americana</italic> L.</td><td>Amakwinkwin, zlon (f)</td><td>Solanaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>8.26</td><td>7.26</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>94</td><td>YH 364 / HNB</td><td><italic>Secamone afzelii</italic> (Roem. &#x00026; Schult.) K.Schum</td><td>Anonsima, zounkoudjou (f);</td><td>Apocynaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>0</td><td>100</td><td/></tr><tr><td>95</td><td>YH 408 / HNB</td><td><italic>Securidaca longipedunculata</italic> Fresen.</td><td>Kpata / Kp&#x0025b;ta (f)</td><td>Polygalaceae</td><td>R</td><td>Dec; Pounding</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>3.67</td><td>3.23</td><td>75</td><td>25</td><td/></tr><tr><td>96</td><td>YH 409 / HNB</td><td><italic>Senna alata</italic> (L.) Roxb.</td><td>Amasu yovot&#x000f2;n (f);</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec; Pounding</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>5.5</td><td>4.84</td><td>67</td><td>33</td><td/></tr><tr><td>97</td><td>YH 413 / HNB</td><td><italic>Senna italica</italic> Mill.</td><td>Ago&#x000e8; ago&#x000e8;, agogw&#x000e8;, adwe agwe (f).</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec; Pounding</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>1.83</td><td>1.61</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>98</td><td>YH 410 / HNB</td><td><italic>Senna occidentalis</italic> (L.) Link</td><td>Kink&#x000e9;liba</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>99</td><td>YH 396 / HNB</td><td><italic>Spondias mombin</italic> L.</td><td>Aklokontin/Ahlihon (f)</td><td>Anacardiaceae</td><td>R</td><td>Dec</td><td>Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>100</td><td>YH 412 / HNB</td><td><italic>Syzygium aromaticum</italic> (L.) Merr. &#x00026; Perr</td><td>Atink&#x0025b;n Gbadota (f)</td><td>Myrtaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec; Poudre</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>7.34</td><td>6.45</td><td>75</td><td>25</td><td/></tr><tr><td>101</td><td>YH 414 / HNB</td><td><italic>Terminalia glaucescens</italic> Planch. ex Benth.</td><td>Alotun; Anagositin (f)</td><td>Combretaceae</td><td>R</td><td>Dec</td><td>Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>102</td><td>YH 415 / HNB</td><td><italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> (Schumach. &#x00026; Thonn.) Taub.</td><td>Lendja (f);</td><td>Leguminosae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>4.59</td><td>4.03</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>103</td><td>YH 416 / HNB</td><td><italic>Thalia geniculata</italic> L.</td><td>Aflema (f).</td><td>Marantaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec; Mac</td><td>Oral</td><td>3.67</td><td>3.23</td><td>75</td><td>25</td><td/></tr><tr><td>104</td><td>YH 417 / HNB</td><td><italic>Tribulus terrestris</italic> L.</td><td>Ahwanglon assou (f)/ Kpononmi (Mi).</td><td>Zygophyllaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec; Pounding</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>105</td><td>AA 6751 / HNB</td><td><italic>Uvaria chamae</italic> P. Beauv.</td><td>Aylaha / Ayadaxa/ Win Nyaxa, zinwokokwe, wianxa (f)/ Avun</td><td>Annonaceae</td><td>R</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>9.17</td><td>8.06</td><td>70</td><td>30</td><td/></tr><tr><td>106</td><td>YH 333 / HNB</td><td><italic>Xylopia aethiopica</italic> (Dunal) A. Rich.</td><td>Kp&#x000e9;j&#x000e9;l&#x000e9;kun (f);</td><td>Annonaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec; Mac; Pounding</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>19.27</td><td>16.94</td><td>71</td><td>29</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>107</td><td>YH 334 / HNB</td><td><italic>Zea mays</italic> L.</td><td>Gbad&#x000e9; (f);</td><td>Poaceae</td><td>Tf</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral + Topic</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td>108</td><td>YH 335 / HNB</td><td><italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> Roscoe</td><td>Dot&#x000e8; (f;g)</td><td>Zingiberaceae</td><td>Fr</td><td>Dec</td><td>Oral</td><td>0.92</td><td>0.81</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">109</td><td rowspan="2">YH 422 / HNB</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Zornia glochidiata</italic> DC.</td><td rowspan="2">L&#x000e8;kun l&#x000e8;kun (f)</td><td rowspan="2">Leguminosae</td><td>R</td><td rowspan="2">Dec</td><td rowspan="2">Oral</td><td rowspan="2">0.92</td><td rowspan="2">0.81</td><td rowspan="2">100</td><td rowspan="2">0</td><td rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td>B</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>f: Fon; g: Goun; fr: french B: Bark; Le: Leaves; Tf: Leaf stem; Fr: Fruit; R: Root; Pe: Whole plant; L: Liana; S: Stem; Dec: Decoction; Mac: Mac: Maceration; IFh: Fidelity index for herborists; IFt: Fidelity index for traditional healers; RCend. To make ashes; Fc: Citation frequency</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par46">The most represented families were Leguminosae (20.18%) followed by Euphorbiaceae (5.50%), Apocynaceae (5.50%), poaceae (4.59%) and Combretaceae (4.59%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Distribution of botanical families</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3080_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par47">The most frequently cited species were <italic>Pteleopsis suberosa</italic> Engl. &#x00026; Diels, <italic>Lantana camara</italic> L., <italic>Cyanthillium cinereum</italic> (L.) H. Rob, <italic>Ocimum gratissimum</italic> L. and <italic>Lippia multiflora</italic> Moldenke with respectively 29.36, 26.61 and 22.94% citation frequencies respectively. The most frequently mentioned species did not necessarily belong in order to the most represented botanical families. Their respective frequencies of involvement in the composition of the recipes (Cpr) were 25.81, 23.39, 20.00, 20.00 and 20.00% respectively and their pairs of relative loyalty indices (herbalists/Traditional healers) were (93.75%; 6.25%), (89.66%; 10.34%), (100.00%; 00.00%), (68.00%; 32.00%) and (96.00%; 4.00%) respectively. Among these species, <italic>Ocimum gratissimum</italic> L. was the only plant strongly cited by both market herbalists (66,67%) and traditional healers (33,33%) and involved in about 20% of the recipes provided (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Also, it should be noted that even if <italic>Cyanthillium cinereum</italic> (L.) H. Rob and <italic>Lippia multiflora</italic> Moldenke seem to be two species widely used by herbalists, traditional healers did not use them so frequently.</p><p id="Par48">In addition, seven (07) species of plants inventoried in this study are on the IUCN Red List as Near Threatened (<italic>Cajanus cajan</italic> (L.) Millsp., <italic>Eucalyptus camaldulensis</italic> Dehnh.); Vulnerable (<italic>Afzelia Africana</italic> Pers.<italic>, Garcinia kola</italic> Heckel<italic>, Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L.<italic>, Khaya senegalensis</italic> (Desr.) A. Juss.); and Endangered (<italic>Pterocarpus erinaceus</italic> Poir.).</p><p id="Par49">Different plant organs are used to treat different candidiasis. At the end of this survey, eight (08) plant organs were involved in the composition of traditional recipes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Leafy stems (44.53%) were the most commonly used, followed by whole plants (15.74%) and bark (15.55%). Roots have only a minor role (7.87%) in recipes against candidiasis. Indeed, leafy stems and/or leaves are very important in medicinal recipes since they would constitute the basis for the synthesis of the majority of phytochemical compounds.
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Plant parts involved in recipes</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3080_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par50">The knowledge of the plants used in the treatment of candidiasis is at the level of the elderly. Indeed, in Benin as elsewhere, endogenous knowledge is often hold by elder or wise people. Thus, properties of medicinal plants are ancestral knowledge that is only transmitted from one generation to another [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Other surveys conducted in practitioners Africa on endogenous care practices yielded some findings comparable to ours. In addition, the high degree of seniority of traditional in this care counsellor has also been reported in surveys dealing with medicinal plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. In this sense, As Zougagh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], others authors argued that deep knowledge on the use of plants for healing purposes could only be acquired after years of practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>].</p><p id="Par51">The female predominance of market herbalists and male predominance of traditional healers observed in this study could be explained by the fact that in Benin, sales at the market is an activity mainly carried out by women. Surveys on the traditional use of plants against infections carried out in Benin in the same geographical area support our results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Similar findings were obtained in research activities carried out in other African area highlighting the female-biased sales from the age group of 40&#x02009;years and over [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. However, in other parts of Africa, such as Morocco, the sale of medicinal plants is an activity exclusively done by men [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. On the other hand, all the traditional healers in the current study were male, unlike the results reported by Kloto&#x000e9; et al. (2013) where both sexes were represented with a male predominance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].</p><p id="Par52">The responders (men/women) in our study were mostly illiterate. Our results concordance with those of other authors working in South Benin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>] with focus on the education rate among traditional healers (68.19%) compared to market herbalists (17.65%). But, unlike our study, Koudokpon et al. (2017) had only illiterate market herbalists [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. Differences observed in our study could be due to the fact that our study dealt with almost the whole southern part of Benin and took into account more traditional healers than theirs, which was limited to two cities.</p><p id="Par53">Regarding plant recipes, Kloto&#x000e9; et al. (2018) in their investigations of anti-hemorrhage plants found as in this study, that recipes based on medicinal plants provided by traditional healers contain mineral compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. The addition of mineral compounds to some compositions especially among traditional healers would have a stabilizing role.</p><p id="Par54">Many studies showed that in practice, decoction was the most common method of preparing herbal recipes often indicated by traditional healers. Indeed, in Benin, the recent work of Koudokpon et al. (2017) on plants used in the treatment of infections and that of Fah et al. had reached the same conclusions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. In other area in Africa, several authors in Togo, Nigeria, Congo and South Africa had also found that decoction was the most common preparation method used by traditional healers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Kinda et al. (2017) reports that this method is the most efficient way to extract bioactive compounds from plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. This may explain why many traditional healers use it most often.</p><p id="Par55">The oral administration of the preparations was the preparation method, the most recommended way of administration. According to many other authors, it is also the route of administration for most herbal preparations both in our study area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>] and in other countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>].</p><p id="Par56">The very low degree of Informant Consensus Factor (ICF) in this study could be justified by the difference in the composition of the recipes served. The diversity of single species cited, often involved in the recipes provided, and could justify this weak consensus. This could also be related to socio-cultural factors. Since the populations of southern Benin are of different ethnic groups and cultures, endogenous practices regarding the use of medicinal plants could be different. Indeed, several ethnic groups were met during the survey. These include: A&#x000ef;zo (Atlantic Department); Fons (Littoral and Zou Departments); Idaasha, If&#x000e8;, Isha (Collines Department); Mahi (Zou and Collines Departments); Goun, Yoruba (Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9; and Plateau Department); Adja (Mono and Couffo Departments). Some authors who have worked in the same geographical area found the inhabitants belonging to different socio-cultural groups [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. This study therefore shows that Benin is home for a wide variety of medicinal plant species used in the treatment of candidiasis.</p><p id="Par57">The botanical families most cited in this work (Leguminosae, Euphorbiaceae, Apocynaceae and Combretaceae) were similar to those obtained by Koudokpon et al. (2017) who, in their studies on plants used in the treatment of infections pointing out that Leguminosae species were predominant in the recorded species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]; candidiasis being infections due to Candida yeasts. However, other researchers in Africa found species belonging the Fabaceae family the most represented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. This could be related first to geographical conditions (nature of soils, climatic and other factors) that did not always favor the growth of the same plant species on different soil types and having then a significant influence on bioactive compounds, but also to socio-cultural factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Since knowledge on the therapeutic use of plants was often transmitted from one generation to another, the plants indicated in the treatment of a disease may also differ from one location to another or from one ethnic group to another.</p><p id="Par58">Since few ethnobotanical surveys on candidiasis were specifically carried out, our results on the plant organs used was similar to those of many recent studies on plants with antimicrobial properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. However, unlike many plant studies, Kinda et al.(2017) found in an ethnobotanical survey of plants used in neuropsychiatric disorders that plant roots were the most commonly used by traditional healers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>].</p><p id="Par59">The frequent involvement of leafy stems in recipes could be explained by the fact that the phytochemical compounds responsible for antifungal effects are more concentrated in these plant organs than others. Chemical groups are reported to be more abundant in this plant organs, where secondary metabolites are synthesized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. Castillo et al. reported that terpenes, tannins, flavonoids, essential oils, alkaloids, lecithin and polypeptides are the chemical compounds with antifungal properties in plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]. These properties observed with coriander essential oil on Candida spp. strains are reported by Freires et al. to be related to monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes present in the leaves of this plant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. In addition, ethnobotanical surveys conducted in Benin on medicinal plants sold in Benin have shown that leaf stems are the most commonly used plant organs by medicinal plant sellers, that decoction is the most recommended method of preparation by traditional practitioners and that the oral route is the most commonly used for the administration of medicinal plant recipes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>].&#x000a0;Among plants identified in this survey, nine are previously cited. These ones are: Allium sativum L. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]; Catharanthus roseus (L.) G.Don [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]; Cymbopogon citratus (DC.) Stapf (79); Garcinia kola Heckel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]; Hyptis suaveolens (L.) Poit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].; Ocimum gratissimum L. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], Parkia biglobosa (Jacq.) G Don [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]; Pteleopsis suberosa Engl. &#x00026; Diels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]; Xylopia aethiopica (Dunal) A. Rich [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p><p id="Par60">Among the 109 medicinal plants species identified in the treatment of candidiasis in southern Benin, 7 species are listed as near threatened plants on the IUCN red list. This confirms the anthropogenic pressure exerted on plant resources and raises the question of plant conservation. Indeed, as shown by Dj&#x000e9;go et al. (2011), in Benin, deforestation leads to the disappearance of several medicinal plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. It is therefore important to sensitize the populations on the conservation of plant biodiversity in order to guarantee access to medicinal plants for future generations.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par61">This current ethnobotanical study showed that South Benin is an overflowing area with many species of medicinal plants indicated the traditional treatment of candidiasis. Market herbalists and traditional healers have indicated 109 medicinal plants in the treatment of candidiasis. The most used species are <italic>P. suberosa</italic>, <italic>L. camara</italic>, <italic>C. cinereum</italic>, <italic>O. gratissimum</italic> and <italic>L. multiflora</italic>.</p><p id="Par62">The various species identified could be new sources of bioactive molecules. However, this requires further pharmacological and toxicological studies.</p><p id="Par63">This study could be very useful to scientists for further research works in order to investigate experimentally the properties of the plant species thus identified to effectively inhibit or even kill <italic>Candida</italic> strains involved in candidiasis. It could also be extended to the whole country in order to have a single database of medicinal plants used in the treatment of candidiasis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec13"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12906_2020_3080_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1.</bold>
</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1186/s12906-020-03080-6.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We certainly could not have carried out this study without the precious collaboration of our informants, it is about the herbalists of the markets and the herbals traditional. We show them our deepest gratitude and here we praise their frank and kind collaboration.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>BAF and JRK participated in all stages of the production of this article. FL and DV provided the scientific direction of the works. LF, CHK and GT participated in the survey. All authors participated in reading and editing the manuscript. The authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>No funding was obtained for this study.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par64">The study is part of a thesis. The committee of the &#x0201c;Ecole Doctorale Science de la Vie et de la Terre (ED-SVT) of the University of Abomey-Calavi (UAC) under the number 10185509 has authorized it and obtaining verbal consent from the participants. This choice is justified by the fact that the study population consists mainly of illiterates. To obtain participant consent, study information&#x02019;s were presented to participants in their local languages. And if necessary, answers were given to all their questions. Then, each participant gave his verbal consent which was recorded and archived.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par65">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par66">No conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciss&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><source>Morbidit&#x000e9; et mortalit&#x000e9; parasitaire et fongique dans les services de m&#x000e9;decine interne et maladies infectieuses et tropicales du CHU Point G</source><year>2011</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ota&#x00161;evi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mom&#x0010d;ilovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Golubovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignjatovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ran&#x0010d;i&#x00107;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00110;or&#x00111;evi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Species distribution and epidemiological characteristics of superficial fungal infections in southeastern Serbia</article-title><source>Mycoses.</source><year>2019</year><volume>62</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/myc.12900</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30687976?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30687976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sardi</surname><given-names>JCO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernardi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Scorzoni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fusco-Almeida</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Giannini</surname><given-names>MMJS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Candida species: current epidemiology, pathogenicity, biofilm formation, natural antifungal products and new therapeutic options</article-title><source>J Med Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>62</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.045054-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23180477?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23180477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Azeredo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vulvovaginal candidiasis: epidemiology, microbiology and risk factors</article-title><source>Crit Rev Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>42</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>905</fpage><lpage>927</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/1040841X.2015.1091805</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26690853?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26690853</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapila</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of Candida species in neonatal septicaemia</article-title><source>Int J Contemp Pediatr</source><year>2006</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>605</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pristov</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghannoum</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resistance of Candida to azoles and echinocandins worldwide</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2019</year><volume>25</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>792</fpage><lpage>798</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2019.03.028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30965100?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30965100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deorukhkar</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why Candida species have emerged as important nosocomial pathogens?</article-title><source>Int J Curr Microbiol App Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20546/ijcmas.2016.501.054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geddes-McAlister</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New pathogens, new tricks: emerging, drug-resistant fungal pathogens and future prospects for antifungal therapeutics: drug-resistant fungal pathogens</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>1435</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nyas.13739</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29762860?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29762860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Frenkel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental in vivo models of candidiasis</article-title><source>J Fungi</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>21</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jof4010021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sacarlal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Denning</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimated burden of serious fungal infections in Mozambique</article-title><source>J Fungi</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>75</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jof4030075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caggiano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Montagna</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>&#x000d6;zdemir</surname><given-names>&#x000d6;</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d6;zdemir</surname><given-names>&#x000d6;</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal Infections in Patients of Paediatric Age</article-title><source>Contemporary Pediatrics</source><year>2012</year><fpage>434</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bongomin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gago</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oladele</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Denning</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global and multi-National Prevalence of fungal diseases&#x02014;estimate precision</article-title><source>J Fungi</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>57</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jof3040057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Denning</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gow</surname><given-names>NAR</given-names></name><name><surname>Levitz</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Netea</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hidden Killers: Human Fungal Infections</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><issue>165</issue><fpage>165rv13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.3004404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>GATTI GAFFFI</collab></person-group><source>Global fungal infection forum III: Essential diagnostics for advanced HIV disease and serious fungal infections</source><year>2018</year><publisher-loc>Kampala</publisher-loc><publisher-name>GATTI</publisher-name><fpage>52</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Institut</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Lettre de l&#x02019;institut Pasteur n&#x000b0;72</source><year>2011</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alangaden</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nosocomial fungal infections: epidemiology, infection control, and prevention</article-title><source>Infect Dis Clin N Am</source><year>2011</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idc.2010.11.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perlroth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Spellberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nosocomial fungal infections: epidemiology, diagnosis, and treatment</article-title><source>Med Mycol</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13693780701218689</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17510856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17510856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cortegiani A, Misseri G, Fasciana T, Giammanco A, Giarratano A, Chowdhary A. Epidemiology, clinical characteristics, resistance, and treatment of infections by Candida auris. J Intensive Care. 2018;6(1) Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jintensivecare.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s40560-018-0342-4">https://jintensivecare.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s40560-018-0342-4</ext-link>. Cited 2019 May 27.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Thomaz DY, de Almeida JN, Lima GME, de Oliveira NM, Camargo CH, de Carvalho GR, et al. An Azole-Resistant <italic>Candida parapsilosis</italic> Outbreak: Clonal Persistence in the Intensive Care Unit of a Brazilian Teaching Hospital. Front Microbiol. 2018;9 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fmicb.2018.02997/full">https://www.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fmicb.2018.02997/full</ext-link>. Cited 2019 May 27.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Delli&#x000e8;re S, Healey K, Gits-Muselli M, Carrara B, Barbaro A, Guigue N, et al. Fluconazole and Echinocandin Resistance of <italic>Candida glabrata</italic> Correlates Better with Antifungal Drug Exposure Rather than with MSH2 Mutator Genotype in a French Cohort of Patients Harboring Low Rates of Resistance. Front Microbiol. 2016;7 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fmicb.2016.02038/full">http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fmicb.2016.02038/full</ext-link>. Cited 2019 May 27.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peron</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichert-Lima</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Busso-Lopes</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagasako</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyra</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moretti</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Resistance Surveillance in <italic>Candida albicans</italic>: A Five-Year Antifungal Susceptibility Evaluation in a Brazilian University Hospital</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>e0158126</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0158126</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27414653?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27414653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Whaley SG, Berkow EL, Rybak JM, Nishimoto AT, Barker KS, Rogers PD. Azole Antifungal Resistance in <italic>Candida albicans</italic> and Emerging Non-albicans Candida Species. Front Microbiol. 2017;7 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fmicb.2016.02173/full">http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fmicb.2016.02173/full</ext-link>. Cited 2019 May 27.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawsud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Puripattanavong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Teanpaisan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening for Anticandidal and Antibiofilm activity of some herbs in Thailand</article-title><source>Trop J Pharm Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1495</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/tjpr.v13i9.16</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armstrong-James</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Meintjes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A neglected epidemic: fungal infections in HIV/AIDS</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2014.01.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24530175?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24530175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bassetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Righi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Montravers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornely</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What has changed in the treatment of invasive candidiasis? A look at the past 10 years and ahead</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2018</year><volume>73</volume><issue>suppl_1</issue><fpage>i14</fpage><lpage>i25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkx445</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29304208?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29304208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gbogbo</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Agban</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Woegan</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Amana</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoekou</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Batawila</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation de l&#x02019;activit&#x000e9; antimicrobienne de Momordica charantia (Curcubitaceae); <italic>Psidium guajava</italic> (Myrtaceae) et Pteleopsis suberosa (Combretaceae)</article-title><source>Eur Sci J</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><issue>36</issue><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>421</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lifongo</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Simoben</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ntie-Kang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Babiaka</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Judson</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A bioactivity versus Ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants from Nigeria</article-title><source>West Africa Nat Prod Bioprospecting</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13659-014-0005-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phumthum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Srithi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Inta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Junsongduang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tangjitman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pongamornkul</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal plant diversity in Thailand</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2018</year><volume>214</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2017.12.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29241674?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29241674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>J-K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Demystifying traditional herbal medicine with modern approach</article-title><source>Nat Plants</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>17109</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nplants.2017.109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28758992?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28758992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agban</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Atchou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tchacondo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoekou</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Batawila</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>De Souza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potentiel antimicrobien des extraits de feuilles d&#x02019;Hyptis suaveolens poit</article-title><source>J Rech Sci L&#x02019;Universit&#x000e9; Lom&#x000e9;</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>44</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akpotu</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Eze</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abba</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Umeokoli</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Nwachukwu</surname><given-names>CU</given-names></name><name><surname>Okoye</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activities of secondary metabolites of endophytic fungi isolated from Catharanthus roseus</article-title><source>J Health Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Soro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kon&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakayoko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamanzi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation de l&#x02019;abondance de plantes m&#x000e9;dicinales utilis&#x000e9;es en m&#x000e9;decine traditionnelle dans le Nord de la C&#x000f4;te d&#x02019;Ivoire</article-title><source>J Anim Plant Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>17</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>2631</fpage><lpage>2646</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sofowora A, Ogunbodede E, Onayade A. The role and place of medicinal plants in the strategies for disease prevention. Afr J Tradit Complement Altern Med. 2013;10(5) Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ajol.info/index.php/ajtcam/article/view/92333">http://www.ajol.info/index.php/ajtcam/article/view/92333</ext-link>. Cited 2019 Jun 10.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jamshidi-Kia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorigooini</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Amini-Khoei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants: past history and future perspective</article-title><source>J Herbmed Pharmacol</source><year>2018</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15171/jhp.2018.01</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tantary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Masood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dar</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zargar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganie</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro antioxidant and RBC membrane stabilization activity of Euphorbia wallichii</article-title><source>Free Radic Antioxid</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5530/fra.2017.1.3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chaitanya Kolluru V, Agrawal P, Kotagir D. Comparative Analysis of Antimicrobial Activity of Herbal Extracts against Pathogenic Microbes. Curr Trends Biomed Eng Biosci. 2018;16(1) Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://juniperpublishers.com/ctbeb/CTBEB.MS.ID.555930.php">https://juniperpublishers.com/ctbeb/CTBEB.MS.ID.555930.php</ext-link>. Cited 2019 Aug 19.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boakye</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name><name><surname>Agyare</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hensel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Anti-infective properties and time-kill kinetics of Phyllanthus muellerianus and its major constituent, geraniin</source><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pawar</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antifungal activity of some stem extracts against seed-borne pathogenic fungi</article-title><source>J Phytol</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>45</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sessou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Soua&#x000ef;bou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jean-Pierre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Brice</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Issaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and in vitro antifungal activity of Zingiber officinale essential oil against foodborne pathogens isolated from a traditional cheese wagashi produced in Benin</article-title><source>Int J Biosci</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yaye</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name><collab>KRA AKM</collab><collab>ACKAH JAAB</collab><name><surname>Djaman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x000c9;VALUATION DE L&#x02019;ACTIVIT&#x000c9; ANTIFONGIQUE ET ESSAI DE PURIFICATION DES PRINCIPES ACTIFS DES EXTRAITS DE Terminalia mantaly (H. Perrier), UNE COMBRETAC&#x000c9;E, SUR LA CROISSANCE in vitro DE <italic>Candida albicans</italic>. ASSESSMENT OF THE ANTIFUNGAL ACTIVITY AND TEST OF ACTIVE PRINCIPLE PURIFICATION OF EXCERPT OF Terminalia mantaly (H. PERRIER), A COMBRETACEAE, ON THE in vitro GROWTH OF <italic>Candida albicans</italic></article-title><source>Bull Soci&#x000e9;t&#x000e9; R Sci Li&#x000e8;ge</source><year>2011</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>953</fpage><lpage>964</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agban</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gbogbo</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Amana</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tegueni</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Batawila</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kossi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation de l&#x02019;activit&#x000e9; antimicrobienne de Tridax procumbens (Asteraceae); <italic>Jatropha multifida</italic> (Euphorbiaceae) et de Chromolaena odorata (Asteraceae)</article-title><source>Eur Sci J</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><issue>36</issue><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>290</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dj&#x000e8;go</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Djego-Djossou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cakpo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinsin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation du potentiel ethnobotanique des populations rurales au Sud et au centre du B&#x000e9;nin</article-title><source>Int J Biol Chem Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1432</fpage><lpage>1447</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lagnika</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Amoussa</surname><given-names>AMO</given-names></name><name><surname>Adjileye</surname><given-names>RAA</given-names></name><name><surname>Laleye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial, antioxidant, toxicity and phytochemical assessment of extracts from Acmella uliginosa, a leafy-vegetable consumed in B&#x000e9;nin, West Africa</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>34</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-016-1014-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26817601?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26817601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kloto&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dougnon</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Koudouvo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>At&#x000e8;gbo</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Loko</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ako&#x000e8;gninou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ethnopharmacological survey on Antihemorrhagic medicinal plants in south of Benin</article-title><source>Eur J Med Plants</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9734/EJMP/2013/2093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koudokpon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dougnon</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bankol&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fah</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hounmanou</surname><given-names>YMG</given-names></name><name><surname>Baba-Moussa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of plants used in the treatment of infections in southern Benin</article-title><source>Health Sci Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>99</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mpondo Mpondo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dibong</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional knowledge on medicinal plants use by ethnic communities in Douala, Cameroon</article-title><source>Eur J Med Plants</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>159</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9734/EJMP/2012/878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Briguiche</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zidane</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants from El-Jadida City (Morocco)/Estudio etnobot&#x000e1;nico de las plantas medicinales de la ciudad de El-Jadida (Marruecos)</article-title><source>Lazaroa.</source><year>2016</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5209/LAZAROA.51578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ako&#x000e8;gninou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Burg</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Maesen</surname><given-names>LJG</given-names></name><name><surname>Adjakidj&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Essou</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinsin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Flore analytique du B&#x000e9;nin</article-title><source>Wageningen University papers</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Pays-Bas</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Backhuys Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>1064</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shalukoma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogaert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Duez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>St&#x000e9;vigny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pongombo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Les plantes m&#x000e9;dicinales de la r&#x000e9;gion montagneuse de Kahuzi-Biega en R&#x000e9;publique D&#x000e9;mocratique du Congo: utilisation, accessibilit&#x000e9; et consensus des tradipraticiens</article-title><source>Bois For Trop</source><year>2014</year><volume>326</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.19182/bft2015.326.a31282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zougagh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Belghiti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rochd</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zerdani</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mouslim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal and aromatic plants used in traditional treatment of the Oral pathology: the Ethnobotanical survey in the economic capital Casablanca, Morocco (North Africa)</article-title><source>Nat Prod Bioprospecting</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13659-018-0194-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alsarhan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadir</surname><given-names>MRA</given-names></name><name><surname>Aburjai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnopharmacological survey of medicinal plants in Malaysia, the Kangkar Pulai region</article-title><source>Int J Pharmacol</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3923/ijp.2012.679.686</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lougbegnon</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Gbesso</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Logbo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tente</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Codjia</surname><given-names>JTC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of plants with therapeutic value in the commune of Glazou&#x000e9; in Benin (West Africa)</article-title><source>Int J Innov Appl Stud</source><year>2018</year><volume>24</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>644</fpage><lpage>655</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambe</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouattara</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiebre</surname><given-names>M-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vroh</surname><given-names>BTA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zirihi</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x02019;guessan</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversit&#x000e9; des plantes m&#x000e9;dicinales utilis&#x000e9;es dans le traitement traditionnel de la diarrh&#x000e9;e sur les march&#x000e9;s d&#x02019;Abidjan (C&#x000f4;te d&#x02019;Ivoire)</article-title><source>J Anim Plant Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>4081</fpage><lpage>4096</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bade</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name><surname>Maliki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Allagbe</surname></name><name><surname>Dah-Nouvlessounon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nabede</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Assogba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical Survey of Three Species of Desmodium genus (Desmodium ramosissimum, Desmodium gangeticumandDesmodium adscendens) Used in Traditional Medicine, Benin</article-title><source>Int J Therm Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>12</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ezeifeka</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name><surname>Mbata</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activities of Cajanus cajan, Garcinia cola and Xylopia aetiopica on pathogenic microorganisms</article-title><source>Biotechnology.</source><year>2004</year><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3923/biotech.2004.41.43</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmo</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><collab>Pereira F de O</collab><name><surname>Cavalcante</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gayoso</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><collab>Lima E de O</collab></person-group><article-title>Treatment of pityriasis versicolor with topical application of essential oil of Cymbopogon citratus (DC) Stapf - therapeutic pilot study</article-title><source>An Bras Dermatol</source><year>2013</year><volume>88</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20131800</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23793205?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23793205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adomou</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yedomonhan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Djossa</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Legba</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Oumorou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Akoegninou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Etude Ethnobotanique des plantes m&#x000e9;dicinales vendues dans le march&#x000e9; d&#x02019;Abomey-Calavi au B&#x000e9;nin</article-title><source>Int J Biol Chem Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>772</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaumont</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activit&#x000e9;s antimicrobiennes in vitro de cinq huiles essentielles de Lamiac&#x000e9;es togolaises vis-&#x000e0;vis de germes repr&#x000e9;sentatifs de la microflore cutan&#x000e9;e</article-title><source>Acta Bot Gallica</source><year>2001</year><volume>148</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/12538078.2001.10515877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mgbeahuruike</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuorela</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Amandikwa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fyhrquist</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnobotanical survey and antifungal activity of Piper guineense used for the treatment of fungal infections in West-African traditional medicine</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2019</year><volume>229</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2018.10.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30336302?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30336302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dassou</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogni</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Y&#x000e9;domonhan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Adomou</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tossou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dougnon</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diversit&#x000e9;, usages v&#x000e9;t&#x000e9;rinaires et vuln&#x000e9;rabilit&#x000e9; des plantes m&#x000e9;dicinales au Nord-B&#x000e9;nin</article-title><source>Int J Biol Chem Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/ijbcs.v8i1.18</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agbankp&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dougnon</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bankol&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Y&#x000e8;hou&#x000e9;nou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Y&#x000e9;domonhan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000e8;gonou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Etude ethnobotanique des l&#x000e9;gumes feuilles th&#x000e9;rapeutiques utilis&#x000e9;s dans le traitement des diarrh&#x000e9;es au sud-B&#x000e9;nin (Afrique de l&#x02019;Ouest)</article-title><source>Int J Biol Chem Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1784</fpage><lpage>1795</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/ijbcs.v8i4.36</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Odoh</surname><given-names>UE</given-names></name><name><surname>Uzor</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Eze</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Akunne</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Onyegbulam</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Osadebe</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants used by the people of Nsukka local government area, South-Eastern Nigeria for the treatment of malaria: an ethnobotanical survey</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2018</year><volume>218</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2018.02.034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29477369?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29477369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laleye</surname><given-names>FOA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mensah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Assogbadjo</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahissou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity, knowledge, and use of plants in traditional treatment of diabetes in the Republic of Benin</article-title><source>Ethnobot Res Appl</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17348/era.14.0.231-257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masevhe</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>McGaw</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eloff</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The traditional use of plants to manage candidiasis and related infections in Venda. South Africa</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2015</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2015.03.046</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25816985?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25816985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dougnon</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Attakpa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bankol&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hounmanou</surname><given-names>YMG</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000e8;hou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Agbankp&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Etude ethnobotanique des plantes m&#x000e9;dicinales utilis&#x000e9;es contre une maladie cutan&#x000e9;e contagieuse: La gale humaine au Sud-B&#x000e9;nin</article-title><source>Pharmacop&#x000e9;e M&#x000e9;decine Tradit Afr</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mugisha</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Asiimwe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Namutebi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Borg-Karlson</surname><given-names>A-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakudidi</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of indigenous knowledge on medicinal and nutritious plants used to manage opportunistic infections associated with HIV/AIDS in western Uganda</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2014</year><volume>155</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2014.05.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24862490?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24862490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fah</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kloto&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dougnon</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Koudokpon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanou</surname><given-names>VBA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dandjesso</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>&#x000c9;tude ethnobotanique des plantes utilis&#x000e9;es dans le traitement du diab&#x000e8;te chez les femmes enceintes &#x000e0; Cotonou et Abomey-Calavi (B&#x000e9;nin)</article-title><source>J Anim Plant Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2647</fpage><lpage>2658</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koudokpon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dougnon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bankol&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fah</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hounmanou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Loko</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enqu&#x000ea;te ethnobotanique sur les plantes utilis&#x000e9;es dans le traitement des infections au sudb&#x000e9;nin</article-title><source>Health Sci Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>99</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klotoe</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Koudouvo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ategbo</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dandjesso</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dougnon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Loko</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants sold as anti-Haemorrhagic in the Cotonou and Abomey-Calavi markets (Benin)</article-title><source>Int J Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>17</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5539/ijb.v10n1p17</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alfa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Anani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Adjrah</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Batawila</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ameyapoh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants used against FungalInfections in prefecture of Sotouboua central Region</article-title><source>Togo Eur Sci J</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>357</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ngbolua</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Inkoto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mongo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashande</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Masens</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mpiana</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x000c9;tude ethnobotanique et floristique de quelques plantes m&#x000e9;dicinales commercialis&#x000e9;es &#x000e0; Kinshasa, R&#x000e9;publique D&#x000e9;mocratique du Congo</article-title><source>Rev Mar Sci Agron V&#x000e9;t</source><year>2019</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>128</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kinda</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zerbo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Guenn&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Compaor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciobica</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiendrebeogo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants used for neuropsychiatric disorders treatment in the Hauts Bassins region of Burkina Faso</article-title><source>Medecines</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><issue>32</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gbadamosi</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Egunyomi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of plants used for the treatment and Management of Sexually Transmitted Infections in Ibadan, Nigeria</article-title><source>Ethnobot Res Appl</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17348/era.12.0.659-669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawin</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lal&#x000e8;y&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>OAF</given-names></name><name><surname>Agbani</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Assogbadjo</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical assessment of the plant species used in the treatment of diabetes in the Sudano-Guinean zone of Benin</article-title><source>J Anim Plant Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>26</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>4108</fpage><lpage>4123</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohemu</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Agunu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Olotu</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ajima</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Dafam</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Azila</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants used in the traditionaltreatment of viral infections in Jos, plateau state, Nigeria</article-title><source>Int J MedArom Plants</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>81</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agoyi</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Assogbadjo</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouwakinnou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Okou</surname><given-names>FAY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinsin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical assessment of Moringa oleifera lam. In southern Benin (West Africa)</article-title><source>Ethnobot Res Appl</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><issue>i</issue><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17348/era.12.0.551-560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Loko LEY, Toffa J, Adjatin A, Akpo AJ, Orobiyi A, Dansi A. Folk taxonomy and traditional uses of common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.) landraces by the sociolinguistic groups in the central region of the Republic of Benin. J Ethnobiol Ethnomed. 2018;14(1) Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ethnobiomed.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13002-018-0251-6">https://ethnobiomed.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13002-018-0251-6</ext-link>. Cited 2019 May 3.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Onzo</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Azokpota</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Akissoe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Agbani</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiversit&#x000e9; des emballages-feuilles v&#x000e9;g&#x000e9;tales utilis&#x000e9;es dans l&#x02019;artisanat agroalimentaire au Sud du B&#x000e9;nin</article-title><source>J Appl Biosci</source><year>2013</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>5810</fpage><lpage>5821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/jab.v72i1.99666</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dougnon</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Attakpa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bankol&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hounmanou</surname><given-names>YMG</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000e8;hou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Agbankp&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Etude ethnobotanique des plantes m&#x000e9;dicinales utilis&#x000e9;es contre une maladie cutan&#x000e9;e contagieuse : La gale humaine au Sud-B&#x000e9;nin</article-title><source>Rev Cames Pharm M&#x000e9;d Trad Afr</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Castillo F, Hern&#x000e1;ndez D, Gallegos G, Rodr&#x000ed;guez R, Aguilar CN. Antifungal Properties of Bioactive Compounds from Plants. In: Fungicides for Plant and Animal Diseases: Dharumadurai Dhanasekaran; 2012. p. 298. (InTech). Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.intechopen.com/books/fungicides-for-plant-and-animal-diseases/antifungal-properties-of-bioactivecompounds-from-plants">www.intechopen.com/books/fungicides-for-plant-and-animal-diseases/antifungal-properties-of-bioactivecompounds-from-plants</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Almeida</surname><given-names>FI</given-names></name><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Furletti</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sartoratto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>de Alencar</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueira</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L. (Coriander) Essential Oil: Antifungal Activity and Mode of Action on Candida spp., and Molecular Targets Affected in Human Whole-Genome Expression</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e99086</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24901768</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>