<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>
  <italic>Teucrium leucocladum</italic> is among the most used traditional medicinal plants in Palestine, which is used for the treatment of hyperglycemia and colon spasms from ancient times. Therefore, the current investigation aimed for the first time to determine the hypoglycemic, hypolipidemic, and oxidative stress inhibitory effects of the aerial parts (stem and leaves) of 
  <italic>T. leucocladum</italic> hydrophilic (water) extract in streptozotocin- (STZ-) induced diabetic rats (65 mg/kg), given intraperitoneally at a dose of 100 mg/kg for 21 days. The rats were divided into four groups as control (C), control + 
  <italic>T. leucocladum</italic> extract (C + TL), diabetes (D), and diabetes + 
  <italic>T. leucocladum</italic> extract (D + TL). The antioxidant activity was analyzed using in vitro 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl and in vivo methods by measuring the plasma and tissue malondialdehyde (MDA) levels using a colorimetric assay. On the other hand, glutathione peroxidase (GSH-Px), erythrocyte superoxide dismutase (SOD) enzyme levels, serum paraoxonase (PON), and arylesterase (ARE) enzyme activities were assessed by utilizing standard biochemical kits. Besides, the blood glucose and serum insulin levels were assessed by a glucometer and Rat ELISA Kit, respectively. However, the autoanalyzer was used to evaluate the lipid profile. The diabetic rat group that administered 
  <italic>T. leucocladum</italic> extract showed the best reduction in the tissue and plasma MDA levels and an increase of insulin-releasing potentials. Besides, the serum PON and ARE activities and erythrocyte superoxide dismutase and whole blood glutathione peroxidase enzyme levels were significantly increased in all animals treated with 
  <italic>T. leucocladum</italic> extract. The current investigation demonstrated that 
  <italic>T. leucocladum</italic> manifests antihyperglycemic and antihyperlipidemic effects and also increased the antioxidative defense system and reduced the lipid peroxidation process in experimental diabetic rats.
 </p>
</abstract>
