<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Novel method: Three-part DI-MS for profiling glycerides, phospholipids and fatty acids separately</italic>—In order to overcome the inherent difficulties of profiling the lipid/glyceride fraction of milk samples, we developed DI-MS (used successfully a number of times on human dried blood spots [
 <xref rid="B5-nutrients-11-01122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-nutrients-11-01122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-nutrients-11-01122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-nutrients-11-01122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>], plasma [
 <xref rid="B4-nutrients-11-01122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-nutrients-11-01122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>] and serum [
 <xref rid="B30-nutrients-11-01122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]) for milk. The abundance of glycerides (98% of signal intensity in positive mode, 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-nutrients-11-01122" class="xref">Figure S1</xref>) led us to the hypothesis that they were suppressing the PLs. As triglycerides ionise much less well in negative mode, we explored this mode for profiling phospholipids (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-nutrients-11-01122" class="xref">Figure S2</xref>). This produced evidence for an array of such species, including all major phospholipids. However, we noted that the spectrum contained a considerable number of intensities for triglycerides. Washing the dried lipid film briefly with hexane reduced the signal intensity of triglycerides, increased the number of 
 <italic class="italic">m</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">z</italic> signals consistent with phospholipids by around a factor of two and narrowed the variance within phospholipids. Hexane was chosen as although fats readily dissolve in it, its low dielectric constant makes it a poor solvent for lipids. The glyceride profile of the residue was the same as the whole sample and thus this washing step does not appear to be selective between isoforms of triglyceride (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-nutrients-11-01122" class="xref">Figure S3</xref>). We tested for reported lipase activity [
 <xref rid="B31-nutrients-11-01122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-nutrients-11-01122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-nutrients-11-01122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>] in fresh milk using this method. However, the glyceride spectra were dominated by signals of diglycerides that had lost one equivalent of water (DG-H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O). These signals consist of both di- and triglycerides that have fragmented under ionisation conditions [
 <xref rid="B4-nutrients-11-01122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>], confounding measurement of the abundance of DGs.
</p>
