<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This infusion contains green tea, lemon verbena, cinnamon, damask rose, chamomile flowers, primrose, and ginger. Cinnamon (
 <italic>Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic>) belongs to the Lauraceaeis family. It is a small evergreen tree with a height of 5–7 m. The plant is charecterized by the aromatic odor and pleasant smell. The biological activities of cinnamon are due to the presence of tannins [
 <xref rid="B89-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. The bark of C. zeylanicum essential oil was analyzed by GC–MS which revealed the presence of (
 <italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde (68.95%), as the major component, in addition to benzaldehyde (9.94%), and (
 <italic>E</italic>)-cinnamyl acetate (7.44%) [
 <xref rid="B90-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Saponins, tannins, phenols, terpenoids, and phytosterols were observed in the cinnamon plant whether dried or fresh [
 <xref rid="B91-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Cinnamon’s essential oil prevents the hepatic 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl CoA reductase activity in rats which leads to lower hepatic cholesterol content and decrease the lipid peroxidation via enhancement of the hepatic antioxidant enzyme activities [
 <xref rid="B92-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Differences in antioxidant activities of cinnamon maybe related to different parts of the plant. For example, cinnamon leaf oils have high antioxidant activities, whereas cinnamon bark oils have low antioxidant activities [
 <xref rid="B93-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. A cinnamon water extract contained the highest amount of phenolics and had the highest antioxidative activity [
 <xref rid="B94-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. Earlier study has investigated the hepatoprotective activity of both aqueous and ethanolic extracts of cinnamon against carbon tetrachloride (CCl
 <sub>4</sub>) that induced lipid peroxidation and hepatic injury in rats. The raised serum AST and ALT enzymatic activities induced by CCl
 <sub>4</sub> were significantly decreased by oral administration of 200 mg/kg of each extract once daily for seven days, as compared to the untreated rats [
 <xref rid="B95-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>].
</p>
