<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Meats and meat products are mainly prone to deterioration as they are rich in nutritional composition 
 <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref> and moisture content 
 <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>. Addition of spices, herbs, and vegetables extract to raw and cooked meat enhance total antioxidant capacity that is considered important criteria for the shelf life of the meat products, decrease lipid oxidation and improve colour stability 
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>. Lipid oxidation decreases food's nutritional quality due to loss of essential fatty acids and vitamins and results in a toxic reaction in the muscles foods such as malonaldehyde (MDA) and COPs, i.e. cholesterol oxidation products 
 <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>. There are various methods for controlling lipid oxidation, among which use of natural antioxidants are the most reliable, effective, convenient and economical. An antioxidant such as herb stabilizes food lipids and thereby inhibits the quality deterioration of the products and also increases the shelf life of the products. Herbs also reduce risk of diseases and promote healthy well being due to their role to protect the body against oxidative damage. Antioxidants are those substances which, when present in food or the body at low concentrations delays or prevent an oxidative process that leads to quality deterioration in food and initiates degenerative diseases in the body. Lipid oxidation may occur via auto-oxidation, photooxidation, thermal oxidation, and enzymatic oxidation and mostly involve free radicals and other reactive species as the intermediate 
 <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>. Auto-oxidation is the reaction between atmospheric oxygen and lipids and is one of the common causes behind the oxidative deterioration of food and biological systems. The thermal oxidation refers to the process that can be accelerated at higher temperatures as experienced during deep fat frying. It leads to elevated levels of free fatty acids and polar matters, foaming, color, and viscosity. The process that involves photo sensitizer excitation and transfer of energy to lipid molecules or oxygen are mainly referred to as photo-oxidation. Enzymes, such as lipoxygenases also catalyze fatty acid oxidation and are usually inactivated in thermal processing of food. Natural antioxidants are derived from plants, animals and microorganisms and synthetic materials from chemicals. Plants and their constituents are natural inhabitants of antioxidants like tocopherols and polyphenols found mainly in spices, herbs, fruits, vegetables, cereals, grains, seeds, teas, and oils. Some antioxidants are also of marine origin, i.e., from algae, shellfish and marine bacteria 
 <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42, 41</xref>. By-products obtained from the food and agricultural industries have been reported for their potential use as antioxidants like hulls; shells and skins of nuts and cereals; citrus peels and seeds; canola meal. Fish viscera extracts have also been found to possess antioxidant activity 
 <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>. Synthetic antioxidants are derived from chemicals namely butylated hydroxyanisole (BHA), butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT), propyl gallate (PG) and tertiary-butyl hydroquinone (TBHQ) has been extensively used as food preservatives because of their low cost and bland flavor. Primary oxidation of lipid in meat products leads to cardboard flavor and with progress results in the development of rancid and oxidized flavor 
 <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>. Antioxidant-rich sources are mainly fruits and vegetables 
 <xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref> and serve as a natural source of antioxidants in meat products. It contains water-soluble vitamin such as ascorbic acid, flavonoids as well as fat-soluble vitamins and precursors like tocopherols and carotenoids. Antioxidants are chemical compounds that donate hydrogen to the free radicals and reduce rancidity and delayed lipid per-oxidation without altering sensory or nutritional properties of meat products 
 <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>. It has been reported that in last few years for meat product preservation butylated hydroxyanisole (BHA), butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) and tertiary butyl hydroquinone (TBHQ) have been used as a synthetic antioxidant 
 <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>. However, synthetic chemicals used as an antioxidant often result in adverse effects on human health. So, the consumers are interested in the natural source of antioxidant for the application in meat products. Many studies reveal the addition of natural antioxidant in meat products improved the antioxidant properties and colour stability, reduced lipid oxidation, which improves the shelf life of the products (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>).
</p>
