<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The virulence of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> relies on highly effective mechanisms of invasion and spread, which ensure its intracellular lifecycle (Vázquez-Boland et al., 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2001</xref>; Freitag et al., 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Radoshevich and Cossart, 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>). Host cell invasion is either via phagocytosis or receptor-mediated endocytosis, facilitated by the bacterial surface proteins internalins InlA (
 <italic class="italic">inlA</italic>) and InlB (
 <italic class="italic">inlB</italic>) (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). Recently, Drolia et al. have demonstrated that 
 <italic class="italic">Listeria</italic> adhesion protein (LAP) induces intestinal epithelial barrier dysfunction contributing to bacterial translocation from the intestinal lumen, across the gut epithelium (Drolia et al., 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> is initially trapped in a phagocytic vacuole and subsequently secretes the cholesterol-dependent pore-forming toxin listeriolysin O (LLO; 
 <italic class="italic">hly</italic>) and two phospholipases C (PlcA and PlcB), resulting in vacuole rupture and escape of bacteria into cytosol (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). In this phase, an actin assembly-inducing protein (ActA; 
 <italic class="italic">actA</italic>) promotes actin-based motility and cell-to-cell spread (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). These processes are closely regulated, mainly by the transcriptional regulator PrfA (
 <italic class="italic">prfA</italic>), which is activated by host infection (de las Heras et al., 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Recent progress highlights that 
 <italic class="italic">L</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">monocytogenes</italic>, which has long been a model for cytosolic pathogens, is also capable of residing in vacuoles, in a slow/non-growing state (Bierne et al., 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>).
</p>
