<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIALS AND METHODS</div>
 <sec id="sec2-1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plants of 
   <span class="italic">S. macrostema</span> (Moc. and Sessé ex Benth.) Briq. were obtained by micropropagation (data not shown). The seeds for 
   <span class="italic">in vitro</span> culture were collected from plantations established in the experimental area of Nuevo San Juan Parangaricutiro, Michoacán, Mexico (19°25’23’’N, 102°07’47’’W), and the species was identified by Miguel Angel Bello-González PhD (Faculty of Agrobiology, Universidad Michoacana de San Nicolás de Hidalgo). Plants were grown in pots of 1.5 kg containing a mix of peat moss and perlite (1:1), under conditions of 50%–60% of relative humidity without light and temperature control, and were irrigated every 5 days. The plants were fertilized in the substrate once per month with 1 g/pot of Nutrigarden Excelso
   <span class="sup">®</span> (N-P-K, 17-17-17).[
   <a rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref23">23</a>
   <a rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref25">25</a>] The aerial parts (leaves and stems) of 
   <span class="italic">S. macrostema</span> plants of 6 months old were collected to obtain the essential oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample preparation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">200 g of washed and fresh aerial part (leaves and stems) of 
   <span class="italic">S. macrostema</span> plants were subjected to hydrodistillation in a Clevenger-type apparatus, mixing together with 1000 mL of distilled water in a round flask. The operating temperature was 100°C and the extraction was done between 2 and 4 h. The essential oil was separated from the hydrolyte by liquid–liquid partitioning in separating fennel and removed with a micropipette. This was suspended in methanol at a final concentration of 1.0 mg/mL and stored at 4°C in the dark until gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) and antioxidant activity analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chemical composition of the essential oil and major terpene quantification were realized using GC and GC/MS data techniques reported by Torres-Martínez 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
   <a rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref23">23</a>] 1 μL of the sample was injected into an Agilent Technologies (7890A) GC equipped with a mass detector (Agilent 5975C), which operated using helium as a carrying gas, with a flow of 1 mL/min, with a split injection (split 50:1) at a temperature of 250°C in HP 5MS nonpolar capillary column (30 m × 0.25 mm internal diameter × 0.25 μm film), under the following conditions: initial temperature of 50°C, followed by a 5°C/min ramp to attain a temperature of 280°C during 1 min; another 25°C/min ramp to raise the temperature to 380°C, during up to 3 min. The runtime was 50 min. The MS operated at a flow speed of 1 mL/min, with an ionization voltage of 70 eV, at an interface temperature of 250°C, in a SCAN mode, and at a mass interval of 50–500 m/z.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The percentage of essential oil constituents was determined by integration of peak areas, the values shown correspond to the average value of three injections. The compounds were identified by comparison of their retention indices, relative to those of n-alkanes C8–C20, and by comparison with a library of mass spectra with the NIST02 mass spectral library (National Institute of Standards and Technology), as well as by comparison of their retention indices with those described by Adams.[
   <a rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref26">26</a>] Quantitative determination was based on the total ion count detected by the GC-MS.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2,2-Diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl free radical-scavenging capacity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurement of the 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) (Sigma-Aldrich, Mexico) radical scavenging capacity was carried out according to Karamać 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
   <a rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref27">27</a>] Briefly, two mL of 0.5 mmol/L DPPH in methanol (Meyer, México) was mixed with 100 μL of different concentrations of essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">S. macrostema</span> and using major pure terpenes in it (limonene, linalool, pulegone, menthone, thymol, and caryophyllene; Sigma-Aldrich, Mexico) (0.001, 0.01, 0.1, and 1.0 mg/mL). After 20 min incubation, the absorbance was measured at 517 nm with ultraviolet–visible (UV/VIS) spectrophotometer (Genesys 10UV, Thermo Scientific). The percentage of free radical-scavenging capacity was calculated by the following equation:
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Radical scavenging capacity (%) = (
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>blank</sub> − 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>sample</sub>)/
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>blank</sub>× 100,
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>sample</sub> is the absorbance of DPPH mixed with essential oil or terpenes and 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>blank</sub> is the absorbance of DPPH in which sample has been replaced with methanol. All measurements were performed in triplicate and reported as the average value. Butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT, 1.0 mg/mL) (Sigma-Aldrich, Mexico) was used as positive control.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2,2’-Azinobis-3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid cation radical-scavenging capacity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The radical scavenging capacity of the essential oil and major terpenes of 
   <span class="italic">S. macrostema</span> were assayed with an 2,2’-azinobis-3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid (ABTS) (Sigma-Aldrich, Mexico) assay according to the protocol of Rufino 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
   <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">28</a>] with some modifications. The ABTS radical solution was prepared mixing 7.4 mmol/L ABTS and 2.6 mmol/L potassium persulfate (Meyer, México). Samples of 100 μL were subsequently mixed with 1900 μL ABTS radical solution, and the absorbance of the resulting mixtures was measured after 7 min at 737 nm with UV/VIS spectrophotometer. The free radical-scavenging capacity was calculated by the following equation:
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Radical scavenging (%) = 100− ([
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>sample</sub> − 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>blank</sub>]/
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>control</sub>× 100),
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>sample</sub> is the absorbance of the ABTS mixed with the sample, 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>control</sub> is the absorbance of the ABTS mixed with deionized water, and 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>blank</sub> is the absorbance of the sample mixed with deionized water. BHT (1.0 mg/mL) (Sigma-Aldrich, Mexico) was used as positive control.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Total antioxidant activity by phosphomolybdenum method</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The total antioxidant capacity (TAC) of the essential oil and terpenes was evaluated according to the method described by Prieto 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
   <a rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref29">29</a>] An aliquot of 100 μL of sample solution was combined with 900 μL of reagent solution (0.6 M sulfuric acid, 28 mM sodium phosphate, and 4 mM ammonium molybdate) (Sigma-Aldrich, Mexico). For the blank, 100 μL of deionized water was used in place of the sample. The tubes were incubated in a boiling water bath at 95°C for 90 min. After the samples were cooled at room temperature, the absorbance of the aqueous solution of each sample was measured at 695 nm in the spectrophotometer (Genesys 10 UV, Thermo Scientific). The total antioxidant activity was calculated by the following equation:
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">TAC (%) = ([
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>sample</sub>− 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>control</sub>]/
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>blank</sub>) × 100,
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>sample</sub> is the absorbance of the sample mixed with the reagent solution, 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>control</sub> is the absorbance of deionized water mixed with the sample, and 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>blank</sub> is the absorbance of the reagent solution mixed with water. Ascorbic acid (0.001, 0.01, and 0.1 mg/mL) (Sigma-Aldrich, Mexico) was used as positive control.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data were expressed as means ± standard deviations. Differences in DPPH and ABTS radical scavenging capacities among the essential oil and major terpenes were analyzed by one-way analysis of variance and Tukey's test (JMP8). Differences were considered statistically significant at 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
