<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par54">The Brazilian investigators Giordani and collaborators demonstrated in a series of studies the potential of extracts of the Amaryllidaceae plant family and their bioactive alkaloids to inhibit the growth of 
 <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> as well as their anti-trichomonad mechanism of action. The following are highlights of some of their findings. The Amaryllidaceae plant family is known for its ornamental value and is also of medicinal interest owing to the occurrence of alkaloids with biological properties. Vieira, Giordani [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] evaluated the anti-
 <italic>T</italic>. 
 <italic>vaginalis</italic> activity of eighteen methylene chloride (dichloromethane) extracts (12.5 to 0.19 mg/mL) and isolated six alkaloids (125 to 1.9 μg/mL) from the Amaryllidaceae species. The alkaloids diminished the viability of the trophozoite stage (from 15 to 40%). The extracts from 
 <italic>Hippeastrum breviflorum</italic> demonstrated the highest anti-
 <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> activity (viability was reduced by 60%). Six fractions from a bioguided study with antiprotozoal activity had lycorine and lycosinine (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) as major anti-parasitic components. The higher activity of the extracts when compared with activities of the isolated compounds suggests a synergistic effect of multiple compounds in the extracts. Vieira, Giordani [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] used the following procedure to obtain the extracts and isolated alkaloids. The crude extracts obtained after maceration of fresh bulbs in 96% ethanol at room temperature for 15 days were acidified with a solution of 10% HCl. The neutral material was then removed with petroleum ether, the solution was adjusted with 25% ammonium hydroxide to pH 9–10, and then extracted with dichloromethane and 
 <italic>n</italic>-butanol. The alkaloids were then isolated by chromatography and their purity and structures confirmed by high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC), nuclear magnetic resonance, and mass spectrometric analyses. The described methods offer a useful guide for future efforts designed to obtain pure bioactive compounds from plant sources. Giordani, Weizenmann [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] reported that the Amaryllidaceae alkaloids candimine and lycorine inhibited 
 <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> nucleoside triphosphate diphosphohydrolase and ecto-5′-nucleotidase activities, possibly enhancing the susceptibility of the pathogen to host immune responses. The mechanisms of alkaloid-induced cell death seems to involve the arrest of the cell cycle by a pathway that does not involve criteria that are associated with apoptosis or apoptosis-like death [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>].
</p>
