<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The cytoprotective effect of several adaptogenic plant extracts on chemotherapeutics‐induced dramatic impact on transcriptome‐wide RNA microarray profiles of neuroglia cells culture have been recently studied.
 <xref rid="med21743-bib-0497" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>497</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="med21743-bib-0498" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>498</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="med21743-bib-0499" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>499</sup>
 </xref> The fixed combination 5‐fluorouracil, epirubicin, and cyclophosphamide (FEC) has been shown to deregulate 67 genes involved in the reduction of neuronal development, 37 genes involved in development of the sensory system, 12 genes involved in axon extension, and 3 genes involved in neuronal migration. Pretreatment of cells with 
 <italic>A. paniculata</italic> prevented the FEC‐induced deregulation of genes involved in regulation of neuronal death, neurogenesis, and other vital functions in the nervous system. Similar cytoprotective effects exhibit a fixed combination of 
 <italic>A. paniculate</italic> with 
 <italic>E. senticosis</italic>, which prevented the FEC‐induced deregulation of gene expression involved in migration of T98G neuroglia cells, axon extension, conduction of nerves, and other neuronal functions associated with cognitive impairments. Adaptogens significantly modify FEC‐induced deregulation of genes involved in the regulation of cell morphology, synaptic, mitochondrial function, and protein‐related functions suggesting their potential neuroprotective and hepatoprotective effects, which are associated with FEC‐induced adverse events in cancer chemotherapy. The authors concluded that adjuvant treatment with adaptogens can prevent mild cognitive impairments and “chemobrain” effect associated with cancer chemotherapy.
 <xref rid="med21743-bib-0497" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>497</sup>
 </xref> It is noteworthy that adaptogens potentiate the cytotoxic effects of chemotherapeutics in human T98G glioblastoma cells.
 <xref rid="med21743-bib-0498" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>498</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
