<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48" class="p">The ginsenosides (
 <bold class="bold">7</bold>–
 <bold class="bold">31</bold>) in ginseng encounter hydrolysis, dehydration, decarboxylation and addition reactions during decocting (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>]. Zhang et al. investigated the chemical transformation of a famous TCM preparation, Danggui Buxue Tang, an herbal decoction containing Astragali Radix and Angelicae Sinensis Radix. They found that two flavonoid glycosides, calycosin-7-
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>-
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-
 <span class="sc" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">d</span>-glucoside (
 <bold class="bold">32</bold>, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>) and ononin (
 <bold class="bold">33</bold>), in Astragali Radix, could be hydrolyzed to form calycosin (
 <bold class="bold">34</bold>) and formononetin (
 <bold class="bold">35</bold>), respectively, during decocting. The hydrolysis efficiency was strongly affected by pH, temperature, and the amount of herbs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>]. Two compounds of TCM, Sanhuang Xiexin Tang (SXT) and Fuzi Xiexin Tang (FXT), have been used in China for the treatment of diseases such as diabetes for thousands of years. SXT is composed of Rhei Radix et Rhizoma, Scutellariae Radix and Coptidis Rhizoma while FXT is produced by adding another TCM, Aconiti Lateralis Radix Preparata, in SXT. Zhang et al. applied an UPLC-ESI/MS method to monitor 17 active constituents in SXT and FXT decoctions and macerations. The decoction process might enhance the dissolution of some bioactive compounds compared with the maceration process. The contents of 11 constituents [benzoylaconine (
 <bold class="bold">36</bold>), benzoylhypaconine (
 <bold class="bold">37</bold>), benzoylmesaconine (
 <bold class="bold">38</bold>), berberine (
 <bold class="bold">39</bold>), coptisine (
 <bold class="bold">40</bold>), palmatine (
 <bold class="bold">41</bold>), jatrorrhizine (
 <bold class="bold">42</bold>), aloe-emodin (
 <bold class="bold">43</bold>) and emodin (
 <bold class="bold">44</bold>), baicalin (
 <bold class="bold">45</bold>), wogonoside (
 <bold class="bold">46</bold>)] in decoctions of SXT and FXT were significantly higher than those in macerations of SXT and FXT. The β-glucuronidase in herbs could catalyze the hydrolysis of the glucuronic acid group from glycosides (baicalin and wogonoside) to transfer into aglycones [baicalein (
 <bold class="bold">47</bold>) and wogonin (
 <bold class="bold">48</bold>)]. The high temperature in the decoction process deactivated the activity of the 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-glucuronidase and prevented the transformation of glycosides to their aglycones, which led to the discovery of the higher contents of baicalin and wogonoside in decoctions as well as the higher contents of baicalein and wogonin in macerations. The interaction between chemicals from different herbs was also observed. The diester-diterpenoid alkaloids were not detected in the decoction and maceration of FXT, but diester-diterpenoid alkaloid hypaconitine (
 <bold class="bold">49</bold>) was found in the decoction of the single herb Aconiti Lateralis Radix Preparata. The constituents of the other three herbs in FXT might promote the transformation from diester-diterpenoid alkaloids in Aconiti Lateralis Radix Preparata to other less toxic monoester-diterpenoid alkaloids, which might explain the mechanism of toxicity reduction and efficacy enhancement of TCM by formulation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>]. 
</p>
