<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent decades, the discovery of new safe and effective plant-derived medicines has been a major concern for researchers [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Many degenerative diseases, such as cardiovascular, cancer, and arthritis, occur due to metabolic by-products such as free radicals—reactive oxygen species. The interaction between antioxidants has been increasingly studied due to its antioxidative potential for increased health benefits as well as food stability [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Most vegetables from the Cucurbitaceae family have a rich chemical composition, which improves food health and stability because of their antioxidant power. The cucurbita–corn–bean complex formed the nutritional basis for pre-Columbian civilizations in the Western Hemisphere. One of the first species to be domesticated in the New World was 
 <italic>Cucurbits pepo</italic> L. cultivation by the inhabitants of Guila Naquitz cave between 10,000 to 8000 before present (BP), preceding corn and beans by more than 4000 years [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The whole Cucurbitaceae familyhas many health benefits but each plant, depending on the cultivating area, has its own “baggage” of properties and influences human health in its own way. The Cucurbitaceae family has made a significant economic contribution and is used not only in many food products such as important dietary fibers sources, but also in other branches of industry such as cosmetics. Cucumber extracts, known for their cooling, healing and soothing properties, are often added to skin care products. Moreover, 
 <italic>Luffa aegyptiaca</italic> Mill. mature fruits have been known from the oldest times as natural sponges [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], which provide a lot of healthy properties and help insulinemic response and changes in the intestinal function. The healthy properties of cucurbits make them helpful for decreasing cholesterol, insulin response and prevention of constipation [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The chemical composition of the Cucurbitaceae family includes phytochemicals with no nutritional value that occur naturally in plants. Some examples of compounds identified in these plants are tannins, carbohydrates, saponins, polyphenols and cardiac glycosides [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. They also contain a high level of other bioactive compounds, such as triterpenes, sterols, alkaloids and carotenoids. Cucurbits display antioxidant effects thanks to their various bioactive compounds with a free radical scavenging ability, such as cucurbitacins B and E, ellagitannins or carotenoids such as α-carotene, β-carotene, lutein and zeaxanthin [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
</p>
