<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Benincasa hispida</italic> (Thunb.) Cogn., commonly known as Kundur (Malay) or under names such as winter melon, ash pumpkin, and white gourd, is a vegetable best suited to the medium of dry areas of the lowland tropics. It has been found that excessive humidity and prolonged overcast have unfavorable effects on the plant’s health and productivity [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Plants belonging to the genus 
 <italic>Benincasa</italic> have been used as therapeutic agents for the treatment of diabetes mellitus, diuresis diseases, urinary infection, chronic inflammatory disorders [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], epilepsy, peptic ulcer and internal hemorrhages [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Studies on the juice of 
 <italic>B. hispida</italic> revealed its stability over time and its high concentration of nutritional compounds, low sugar and low sulfides content [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The in vitro antioxidant activity of 
 <italic>B. hispida</italic> fruit revealed that its seeds could be good sources of antioxidants, due to their high capacity for the inhibition of linoleic acid oxidation [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. This fruit can reduce the gross intake of food and it can therefore be useful as one of the potential anti-obesity agents [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. α- and β-Amyrins and derived acids such as oleanolic acid, ursolic acid, lupeol, betulin, betulinic acid and stigmasterol and its analogues found in 
 <italic>B. hispida</italic> waxy coatings of leaves and fruits have revealed very good therapeutic activities, including antiviral, anti-inflammatory and antitumor activities [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-25-05468" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
