<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">These works indicated the effect of juglone on various processes in plants, but the main mechanism of its action was participation in oxidative stress. The naphthoquinones’ biological role lies in redox cycling, i.e., a cyclic process of reducing the compound followed by (auto)-oxidation of the reaction product under concomitant generation of reactive oxygen species [
 <xref rid="B189-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">189</xref>]. The ability of juglone to generate reactive oxygen species was confirmed in many studies; however, cellular, biochemical and transcriptional changes involved in this plant response are of particular interest. Such studies appeared only during the latest decade. The transcriptional activity of glutathione transferase gene encoding important cytoprotective enzyme was significantly enhanced in maize seedlings reacting to the juglone-induced oxidative [
 <xref rid="B190-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">190</xref>]. Exposure of rice seedlings to juglone induced reactive oxygen species production and calcium accumulation in roots [
 <xref rid="B191-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">191</xref>]. Large-scale analysis of the transcriptome demonstrated changes in transcript levels of genes related to phytohormone metabolism, cell growth, cell wall formation, chemical detoxification, etc. The data obtained suggest that the inhibition of root elongation was passing via abscisic, jasmonic, and gibberellic acids, and antioxidant enzymes were involved in protection against juglone toxicity. Tobacco seedlings cultivated on nutrient medium supplemented with juglone led to inhibiting the roots growth and increasing the reactive oxygen species content there [
 <xref rid="B192-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">192</xref>]. Plants reacted to stress by upregulation of two proline synthesis genes and downregulation of a proline catabolism gene increasing the proline concentration, which ensured juglone-induced changes mitigation. Using the 
 <italic class="italic">Lactuca sativa</italic> L. seedlings, a complex mechanism of phytotoxic effect of juglone was demonstrated, which inhibited mitosis, changed mitotic phase index, induced creation of reactive oxygen species, and changed levels of reactive nitrogen species [
 <xref rid="B176-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">176</xref>]. Ultimately, that led to mitochondrial dysfunction, DNA fragmentation, and programmed cell death in root tips. Studies on maize coleoptile segments showed that juglone increased the H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> generation, which was primarily produced in the cytosolic and cell wall area, and the activity of antioxidative enzymes involved in degradation of H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, where catalase was the key element [
 <xref rid="B193-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">193</xref>]. This was confirmed at the molecular level in Sytykiewicz et al. [
 <xref rid="B194-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">194</xref>], which stated that treatment of maize and wheat seeds with juglone led to upregulation of 
 <italic class="italic">Cat1</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Cat2</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Cat3</italic> genes encoding the catalase isozymes and significant enhancement in CAT activity. A similar effect juglone had on prokaryotic cells, in particular, 
 <italic class="italic">Microcystis aeruginosa</italic>, one of the most toxic cyanobacteria. The suppression of cell proliferation at a concentration of 3.0–9.0 mg/l resulted in a noticeable increase in the activity of the antioxidant enzymes SOD and CAT, which indicates the juglone induction of oxidative stress in the 
 <italic class="italic">M. aeruginosa</italic> cells [
 <xref rid="B195-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">195</xref>].
</p>
