<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Pistacia is a genus of Anacardiaceae family, of about 11 or more species, which are shrubs or trees. Three Pistacia species (
 <italic class="italic">P. vera Linnaeus</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> P. khinjuk Stocks</italic>, and
 <italic class="italic"> P. Atlantica)</italic> naturally occur,
 <italic class="italic"> Pistacia atlantica Kurdica </italic>is the wildest species widely distributed, from southern-west Asia to northern-west Africa [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. A large number of wild
 <italic class="italic"> Pistacia atlantica </italic>subsp.
 <italic class="italic"> Kurdica</italic> trees are widely distributed in the Zagros Mountains; West and North of Iran, East and North of Iraq, South of Turkey, and North of Syria [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. The mastic gum exudates from the plant stem traditionally have been used in Greek medicine for treatment of gastrointestinal disorders like gastralgia, dyspepsia, and peptic ulcer for many years [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]; the gum possess considerable antibacterial and antifungal activity [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Essential oils are fragrant volatile substances biosynthesized by several parts of plants, which is commonly used for many years for combating pathogens such as bacteria, fungi, and viruses [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. The terpenoids and some hydrocarbons that found in essential oils are responsible for their antimicrobial effect [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Studies suggested that terpenoids that diffuse within the cell membrane of bacteria, damaging it irreversibly, lead to bacterial death, because they are lipophilic in nature; these terpenes cause expansion of the membrane, increase fluid flow, and deactivate the enzymes placed within the membrane [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Pistacia species have caught the interest of researchers due to studies on different parts of this plant such as the leaves, kernels, hulls, and gum demonstrating various biological benefits such as antioxidant, antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory potential [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. It has been proven that Pistachio species are a rich source of phenolic compounds and they have also been considered a source of high antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>].
</p>
