<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Identification of the presumptive pathogenic strains was performed by 16S rRNA sequence analysis. Total genomic DNA was extracted from pure cultures of the bacterial strains after they were cultured on TSA and incubated for 24 h at 30°C. Bacteria were lysed by incubation at 55°C for 1 h in 200 μL of STE buffer (10 mM Tris-HCl, 1 mM EDTA and 100 mM NaCl, pH 8), followed by purification, adding an equal volume of phenol-chloroform-isoamylalcohol (25:24:1) and continuing with a chloroform-isoamylalcohol extraction (24:1). DNA was recovered by adding ethanol (100%) followed by centrifugation at 13000 rpm for 10 min. The pellet was washed with 70% ethanol, dried and resuspended in 50 μL of ultrapure water (pH 7.0). DNA was preserved at -20°C for further use. DNA concentration and purity were estimated with a Varioskan LUX multimode microplate reader (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The 16S rRNA complete gene was amplified using primers suggested by [
 <xref rid="pone.0210478.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] (27F: 
 <monospace class="monospace">5'-AGAGTTTGATCMTGGCTCAG-3'</monospace>, 1492R: 
 <monospace class="monospace">5'-TACGGYTACCTTGTTACGACTT-3'</monospace>). PCR was performed in a 30 μL reaction mixture containing 1X Buffer NH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> (Bioline, Sydney, Australia), 2.5 mM MgCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), 2 mM of each dNTP, 0.3 μM of each primer, 0.5 units of Taq DNA polymerase and 2 μL of DNA. PCR cycling conditions were: DNA denatured for 5 min at 94°C, 35 cycles at 94°C for denaturation, 1 min at 52°C for annealing step and 1 min at 72°C for elongation; and a last cycle of 10 min at 72°C to complete the elongation. Amplicons were separated by 1.5% (w/v) agarose gel electrophoresis, stained with SYBR Safe DNA gel stain (Thermo Fisher Scientific), and illuminated under UV light. Images were captured with an E-Gel Imager System (Thermo Fisher Scientific). PCR products were purified and dissolved in 30 μL of ultrapure water for direct sequencing (Macrogen, Korea). BigDye Terminator Cycle sequencing kit (Perkin Elmer) was used for the sequencing. The sequencing products were analyzed with the ABI 3000 sequencer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). A phylogenetic analysis was carried out with the complete 16S rRNA sequences (1465 bp) from the bacterial isolates, together with 16S rRNA sequences (n = 362) of different 
 <italic class="italic">Vibrio</italic> (pathogens and non-pathogens) obtained from GenBank. The amino acid sequence alignments were generated with ClustalW and the specific region of 16S rRNA was identified using Bioedit 7.0.0. [
 <xref rid="pone.0210478.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Phylogenetic trees were built using Maximum Parsimony (MP), Maximum Likelihood (ML), Neighbor Joining (NJ) and Bayesian Inference (BI). The molecular evolution model was selected through a wide range of phylogenetic and evolutionary tools using a dataset composed only of the unique haplotypes and sequences obtained in the present investigation. JModeltest 2.0 was used to test the evolution models based on the hierarchical likelihood ratio test [
 <xref rid="pone.0210478.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Values of amino acid substitutions per site for the gene were calculated with MEGA 6.0 (Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis). The 16S rRNA sequences were deposited in GenBank under accession numbers MH997724 to MH997742.
</p>
