<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Similar to the pulp and the peel, the MSK is also considered a prospective source of polyphenols with potent antioxidant activity. Ahmed et al. [
 <xref rid="B93-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>] estimated that MSK extract contains about 112 mg GAE/100 g of total polyphenols, and the identified constituents were tannins (20.7 mg), gallic acid (6.0 mg), coumarins (12.6 mg), caffeic acid (7.7 mg), vanillin (20.2 mg), mangiferin (4.2 mg), ferulic acid (10.4 mg), cinnamic acid (11.2 mg), and unidentified compounds (7.1 mg/100 g) (
 <xref rid="ijerph-18-00741-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Soong and Barlow [
 <xref rid="B103-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>] found that the antioxidant activity of the MSK is greater than that of other fruit seeds, namely jackfruit, longan, and avocado. These reports suggest that the polyphenolic content of the MSK contributes to its potent antioxidant activity. Approximately 75% of the total tannins are in hydrolyzable form, which need to be processed before using in food and feed preparations to reduce their toxic effect in vivo. A large difference in the quantity of gallic acid (23 to 838 mg/100 g) and ellagic acid (3 to 156 mg/100 g GAE) was reported in the MSK. The high compositional variation was attributed to the differences in extraction methods (
 <xref rid="ijerph-18-00741-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B103-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. Use of ellagitannins from natural sources was found to be more effective than using purified ellagic acid. The total phenolic content (TPC) of mango seed oil ranges from 9–10 TPC mg/g. Kittiphoom and Sutasinee [
 <xref rid="B104-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>] studied the composition of various phenolic compounds in MSK using the HPLC technique. For the first time, they reported hesperidin as the major compound. The MSK was further characterized using the number of functionally important phenolic compounds, phenolic acids, and antioxidant minerals (selenium, zinc, copper, manganese, and potassium). Among them, quercetin, mangiferin, isomangiferin, homomangiferin, kaempferol, and anthocyanins were found to be the phenolic compounds; gallic acid, caffeic, protocatechuic, coumaric, ferulic, and ellagic acids were reported to be the phenolic acids [
 <xref rid="B88-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. 
</p>
