<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The results of this research showed that the biological yield and EO yield of sweet basil intercropped with maize was enhanced as plant density was increased, such that among different intercropping patterns the maximum biological yield and EO yield were found in treatments with higher sweet basil plants density intercropped with maize. Compared to nitrogen chemical fertilizer, an integration of 
 <italic>A. brasilense</italic> and 
 <italic>A. chroococcum</italic> + 50% nitrogen chemical fertilizer showed an acceptable potential in terms of biological yield; and this treatment did not show a remarkable difference with nitrogen chemical fertilizer. The highest yield of EO was attained by applying 
 <italic>A. brasilense</italic> and 
 <italic>A. chroococcum</italic> + 50% nitrogen chemical fertilizer, although N
 <sub>2</sub> fixing bacteria and no-fertilizer treatments gave higher EO content than did nitrogen chemical fertilizer and 
 <italic>A. brasilense</italic> and 
 <italic>A. chroococcum</italic> + 50% nitrogen chemical fertilizer treatments, but nitrogen chemical fertilizer and an integration of 
 <italic>A. brasilense</italic> and 
 <italic>A. chroococcum</italic> + 50% chemical fertilizer treatments gave higher EO yield. This can be justified as EO yield was mainly affected by biological yield rather than EO content. As the lowest concentrations of main constituents of EO, except methyl chavicol, were obtained by a cropping pattern in which nitrogen chemical fertilizer was used, it is recommended to use the cropping pattern in which 
 <italic>A. brasilense</italic> and 
 <italic>A. chroococcum</italic> or an integration of 
 <italic>A. brasilense</italic> and 
 <italic>A. chroococcum</italic> + 50% nitrogen chemical fertilizer to be utilized. These treatments increased the quality and quantity of generated EO. Also, the highest contents of main EO constituents, except methyl chavicol, were obtained by intercropping; and this indicated an increase in content of most main EO constituents under intercropping sweet basil with forage maize, as compared to its sole cropping.
</p>
