<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_HLY5737 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7758371</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2405-8440(20)32580-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e05737</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e05737</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi alter antifungal potential of lemongrass essential oil against <italic>Fusarium solani,</italic> causing root rot in common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris L</italic>.)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Eke</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Adamou</surname><given-names>Souleymanou</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Fokom</surname><given-names>Raymond</given-names></name><email>rfokom@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Dinango Nya</surname><given-names>Vanessa</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Tsouh Fokou</surname><given-names>Patrick Valere</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Nana Wakam</surname><given-names>Louise</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Nwaga</surname><given-names>Dieudonn&#x000e9;</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name><surname>Fekam Boyom</surname><given-names>Fabrice</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Antimicrobial &#x00026; Biocontrol Agents Unit (AmBcAU), Laboratory for Phytobiochemistry and Medicinal Plants Studies, Faculty of Science, University of Yaound&#x000e9; I, Cameroon</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Soil Microbiology Laboratory, Biotechnology Center, University of Yaound&#x000e9; I, Cameroon</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Institute of Fishery and Aquatic Sciences, University of Douala, Cameroon</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Faculty of Agronomy and Agricultural Sciences, University of Dschang, Cameroon</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>College of Technology, Department of Crop Production Technology, University of Bamenda, Cameroon</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>rfokom@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e05737</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>7</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>The variation in chemical composition of essential oils (EOs) as affected by plant phenology and environmental factors is a crucial limitation in standardization of EOs and thus their effective implementation into novel organic farming. The cultivation of medicinal and aromatic plants (MAP) using bio-elicitors has been advocated as genuine tool to sustainably assure higher quantity and quality EOs. Herein, a field trial and laboratory bioassays were undergone to decipher the impact of a local arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) inoculation on agro-morphological yield, EO output and differential suppression of common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.) root rot incited by <italic>Fusarium solani.</italic> The field experiment was laid out following a completely randomized block design (CRBD) with two treatments; non-inoculated control and AMF-inoculation in triplicates. The effects of the EOs were tested against mycelial growth, conidia and common bean seeds germination. Promising concentrations were thereafter assessed for their suppressive effect against <italic>Fusariun solani in planta</italic>. A significantly higher collar diameter, hypocotyl branching and subsequent Mycorrhizal Dependency (MD) in mycorrhizal lemongrass [(+)AMF] compared to non-inoculated counterpart [(-)AMF]. The resulting EOs consistently repressed <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 conidia germination and mycelium deployment in a dose-dependent manner, with minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of 500 ppm for both the EOs, and 125 ppm for the reference fungicide (Ridomil Plus 44 WP). The EO from mycorrhizal lemongrass protected the common bean plantlets from infection by <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 both in laboratory and greenhouse conditions, leading to healthier and vigorous plantlets. The best protection rate was once more obtained with EO from AMF-primed lemongrass at the concentration of 1000 ppm (65.0%) while the lowest disease severity was obtained with Ridomil Plus 44 WP (63.13%). Overall, AMF inoculation shifted the lemongrass biochemical processes with subsequent impact on growth, and an enhanced suppression in Fusarium root rot under greenhouse conditions.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0015"><p>AM fungi; Lemongrass; Essential oil; Fusarium root rot; Protection; Engineering; Chemistry; Agricultural science; Environmental science; Biological sciences.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>AM fungi</kwd><kwd>Lemongrass</kwd><kwd>Essential oil</kwd><kwd>Fusarium root rot</kwd><kwd>Protection</kwd><kwd>Engineering</kwd><kwd>Chemistry</kwd><kwd>Agricultural science</kwd><kwd>Environmental science</kwd><kwd>Biological sciences</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Soil-borne diseases are major crops yield-limiting factors threatening food security worldwide (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Erper et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). Fungal plant pathogens like <italic>Pythium</italic> spp., <italic>Rhizoctonia solani</italic>, <italic>Thielaviopsis basicola</italic>, <italic>Verticillium</italic> spp., <italic>Sclerotinia</italic> spp., <italic>Phytophthora</italic> spp. and <italic>Fusarium</italic> spp., have been cited as causative agents (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abawi and Pastor-Corrales, 1990</xref>). They may each infect independently the host causing characteristic symptoms, or in complexes, resulting in more severe cases (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Erper et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). Among soil borne diseases, Fusarium root rot (FRR), caused by the fungus <italic>Fusarium solani</italic> f. sp. <italic>phaseoli</italic> (Fsp) W.C. Snyder &#x00026; H.N. Hansen has a cosmopolitan distribution. The former prevails wherever common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L) is grown across the world. In fact, <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> causes hypocotyl rot, seeds and seedlings decay at pre and post-emergences (damping-off) and root rot in common bean, with substantial yield decline culminating at as high as 100% in susceptible cultivars (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Mukankusi et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Nzungize et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>).</p><p id="p0015">Soil disinfestation, and the usage of disease-free or fungicide coated planting materials may help in dwarfing the destructive effects of the phytopathogens. Chemically diverse fungicides such as thiram (Thiram 70 S), benomyl (Benlate), Dithane M-45 (Mancozed) and Captafol (Difolatan) have been screened out against FRR under greenhouse and open field with controversial outcomes, given the resurgence of the damages on fibrous roots out of the protection area at certain distance of seed placement (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abawi and Pastor-Corrales, 1990</xref>; <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Eke et al., 2019</xref>). In addition to the questionable efficiency of chemical fungicides, the worldwide trend toward environmentally-friendly approaches for plant disease control calls for steady mitigation of agrochemicals since they present extensive setbacks such as the development of resistances and non-target effects (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Gianinazi et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Eke et al., 2019</xref>). Thus, attention has been paid to the usage of plant derived fungicidal products such as plant extracts and essential oils (EO) in agriculture (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Tak and Isman 2016</xref>). Isolated from medicinal and aromatic plants (MAP) plant-based drugs have occupied key position in traditional health care systems since ancient times. Moreover, the suppressive action of various EOs toward many agriculturally impactful phytopathogens has been evidenced (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Nana et al., 2015a</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Amini et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p id="p0020">However, estimates reveal that 95% of MAP currently used for diverse purposes are harvested in wild, without any remediation measure (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Karki, 2002</xref>), thought a sustainable balance between the rate of harvest and any resource capital is required (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">McChesney et al., 2007</xref>). As such, there is actually strong advocacy in cooperating the cultivation of MAP into traditional agricultural system, to tackle the unsustainable harvest. Besides, it's well established that many component of the environment influence significantly plants growth and metabolic processes with subsequent repercussion on their inherent bioactivity (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Karagiannidis et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Laku&#x00161;ic et al., 2013</xref>). Nonetheless, reports pertaining to the stabilisation and or the optimisation of the performances of cultivated MAP are still fragmentary though the quality assurance across the whole production system would be necessary to sustainably assure the quality of the end products (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Amujoyegbe et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p id="p0025">Elsewhere, the symbiotic association between the roots of more than 90% of higher plants and rhizospheric arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) termed &#x0201c;Mycorrhizae&#x0201d; has been credited with improved fitness and altered host plants metabolic processes (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Smith and Read, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Eke et al., 2015</xref>). A straight relationship has indeed been drawn between Mycorrhizae frequency and the quantitative and qualitative changes in the EOs production of numerous aromatic plants including but not limited to <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Copetta et al., 2006</xref>), <italic>Mentha arvensis</italic> (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Freitas et al., 2004</xref>), <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Mucciarelli et al., 2003</xref>) and <italic>Chrysopogon zizanioides</italic> (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Adams et al., 2003</xref>). Recently, a preliminary field experiment conducted in the framework of this study, aiming to screen out the effects of harvest periods and a local AMF inoculum on <italic>C. citratus</italic> EO's yield and quality as well as biomass production unveiled an accumulated biomass and a deep shift in the chemical composition (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Fokom et al., 2019</xref>). We thus anticipated that EO from mycorrhizal lemongrass plants could bear improved antifungal potential towards <italic>F. solani</italic>, a recently described virulent bean root rot causing fungus in Cameroon.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Description of the experimental farm</title><p id="p0030">The experiment was conducted at the experimental farm of the Faculty of Sciences of the University of Yaound&#x000e9; I, Cameroon between longitude 11&#x000b0;31&#x02032;00&#x02033; E and latitude 3&#x000b0;52&#x02032;00&#x02033; N. The site is located between 500 to 900 m height from the sea level within the 5<sup>th</sup> agro-ecological zone of Cameroon, characterized by a bimodal rainfall (1500 mm) pattern. The cropping was a raining season maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.) and cassava (<italic>Minihot esculenta</italic>) rotation system. The on-site soil is a Sandy-clay-loam complex. The other physiochemical characteristics included; Organic matter (3.62%), C/N ratio (20.5), cation exchange capacity (29 meq/100 g) and pH of 5.2 (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Fokom et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>). Maize straw and weeds were removed and the field was plowed using the conventional manual hoe-ploughing tillage system to approximately 15&#x02013;20 cm depth. Two plots with 0.5 m interval for non-inoculated control and AMF-inoculation were prepared with three replications each.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Symbiotic organism, sowing and growth conditions</title><p id="p0035">An AMF inoculum made up of a mixture of propagule units of <italic>Glomus aggregatum, Gigaspora margarita</italic> and <italic>Glomus intraradices</italic> (1/1/1), provided by the Laboratory of Soil Microbiology of the Biotechnology Centre, University of Yaound&#x000e9; I was utilized in this experiment. Prior to sowing, 200 g of AMF inoculum containing approxymately 5000 spores and mycelium fragments were placed as seed bed in pokets made at 0.5 m interval (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Nwaga et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Tchameni et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>). Afterward, lemongrass seeds, obtained from the seed bank of the Department of Plant Physiology of the University of Yaound&#x000e9; I were washed under running tap water and surface disinfected with 2% Chlorox (NaOCl) for 5 min and blotted dried. One seed was then placed in each poket and covered with a loose layer of soil. The control plots without mycorrhizal inoculum [(-)AMF] were instead provided with 200 g of sterilize inoculum [(121 &#x000b0;C; 1h), two runs]. The plots (experimental blocs) were randomly organised with AMF treatment [(+) AMF] and control without AMF [(-) AMF].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Assessment of total chlorophyll content</title><p id="p0040">Leaves chlorophyll content is an indicator of plants fitness. The impact of AMF on plant vigour could therefore be estimated through the evaluation of leaves photosynthetic pigments content. Briefly, 100 mg leaves of 14 months old plant were excised (fourth abaxial leaves), and extracted upon grinding in a mortar and pestle with 10 ml of ice cold acetone (80%). The mixture was centrifuged at 13 000g (Eppendorf, 5810R) for 2 min and the supernatant collected. The pellets were re-extracted thrice following the same procedure. The supernatants were pooled and the absorbance readout was done at 663 and 645 nm and the total chlorophyll content was calculated using the <xref rid="fd1" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (1)</xref> as follows (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Lichtenthaler, 1987</xref>)<disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label>Total Chlorophyll = (20.2 &#x000d7; A 645&#x02013;8.02 &#x000d7; A 663) &#x000d7; 100 /mg.</disp-formula>Where: 20.2 and 8.02 = Arnon's constances; A645, A663 = Absorbance recorded at 645 and 663 nm respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Assessment of root colonization by AMF</title><p id="p0045">In order to ascertain mycorrhizae formation upon inoculation, fine lemongrass roots from each treatment were carefully collected and washed with tap water to remove farm adhering soil. Further, the roots were acidified (HCl, 5%) and bleached using 10% potassium hydroxide (KOH) and stained (63 ml glycerin, 875 ml lactic acid, 0.1 g acid fuchsine and 63 ml water) for 14 h on laboratory bench. The excess stain was removed with 5% lactic acid. Characteristic mycorrhizal anatomic structures were visualized under a Nikon YS100 microscope (100&#x02013;400 magnification) and the AMF root colonization percentages was calculated as per the gridline intersect method from <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Giovannetti and Mosse (1980)</xref>. Positive counts consisted of arbuscules, vesicles and/or mycelia within the roots.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Essential oil extraction</title><p id="p0050">Fourteen months after sowing, the aerial parts of lemongrass plants from each treatment and replicates were harvested and pooled together to make a composite sample. The samples were immediately transferred to the Laboratory for Phtytobiochemisty and Medicinal Plants Studies and subjected to extraction by hydro-distillation using a Clevenger-type apparatus. The freshly harvested samples were weighed and placed in a heat-proof container. Tap water, representing two to three folds the total weight of the biological samples was then added and the overall was heated up and maintained to boiling point for around 6 h. The essences were collected by decantation and water traces were removed through an anhydrous sodium sulphate and stored in dark glass bottle at 4 &#x000b0;C until usage.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Pathogenic fungal pathogen and inoculum preparation</title><p id="p0055">The root rot causing fungal pathogen, <italic>Fusarium solani</italic> Fs4 (Accession: JN232142.1) was previously isolated from common bean roots exhibiting typical symptoms of root rots as described by <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abawi and Pastor Corrales (1990)</xref>. Isolation material was collected in a commercial farm devastated by the disease, and the fungus was isolated (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Al-Askar and Rashad, 2010</xref>). Information's pertaining to its identity and virulence toward common bean seedlings are extensively documented (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Nana et&#x000a0;al., 2015b</xref>; <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Toghueo et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Eke et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Eke et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0060">Prior to the experiments, the pathogen's inoculum, made up of macroconidia, microconidia and chlamidospores was prepared by scraping off the propagules on 10 days old PDA cultures using glass wire and sterile distilled water. The obtained slurry, was filtered and adjusted to 2&#x000d7;10<sup>5</sup> cell.ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> using Mallassez haemocytometer and saline solution (NaCl, 0.09%).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><label>2.7</label><title><italic>In vitro</italic> antifungal assays</title><sec id="sec2.7.1"><label>2.7.1</label><title>Mycelial growth inhibition assay</title><p id="p0065">The EOs from either mycorrhizal and non- mycorrhizal lemongrass were assessed for their inhibitory action against <italic>Fusarium solani</italic> Fs4 mycelial development using the food poisoning method described by <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Grover and Moore (1962)</xref>. Briefly, EOs and reference fungicide; Ridomil plus 44 WP were foremost dissolved in Tween 80 emulsifier (0.5% v/v) and added aseptically to sterile (121 &#x000b0;C, 15 min) Potato Dextrose Broth (PDB, Himedia, India) medium in 40 ml Eppendorf tubes so as to obtain final concentrations range of 62.5&#x02013;1000 ppm selected from pre-tests where total inhibition of the pathogen's mycelial growth was obtained at the single dose of 1000 ppm. PDB with tween 80 was considered as negative controls. Thereafter, 50 &#x003bc;L of <italic>Fusarium solani</italic> Fs4 conidial suspension (2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> conidia.ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) were inoculated in each tube. Four replications were prepared for each treatment and the overall experiment was repeated twice. The test and controls sets were incubated at 25 &#x000b1; 2 &#x000b0;C for 10 days and the mycelial mats were harvested through filtration using pre-weighed filter paper and oven-dried (60 &#x000b0;C) till constant weight. The growth inhibition (GI) was thereafter calculated with reference to the negative control using the <xref rid="fd2" ref-type="disp-formula">formula (2)</xref>:<disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label>GI (%) = [(Mc - Mt)/Mc] &#x000d7; 100</disp-formula>Where: Mc and Mt are mat mycelia (mg) of <italic>Fusarium solani</italic> Fs4 grown in inhibitor free PDB and inhibitors (EO and Ridomil Plus 44 WP) amended PDB, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7.2"><label>2.7.2</label><title>Assay for inhibition of pathogen's conidial germination</title><p id="p0070">The M38-A2 method (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">CLSI, 2008</xref>) with slight modifications was utilized to test the effects of studied EOs and Ridomil Plus 44 WP on <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 conidial germination. In brief, sterile PDB (Himedia, India) medium (100 &#x003bc;L) were seeded in the wells of a 96-wells microtiter plate. Thereafter, stock solutions (100 &#x003bc;L) of either EOs or Ridomil Plus 44 WP were added in the first line wells so as to obtain the double of the desired inhibitor's concentration. Upon homogenization, a twofold serial dilution was undergone by transferring successively 100 &#x003bc;L of the content of the precedent wells into subsequent ones. Later on, 100 &#x003bc;L <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> conidia suspension, calibrated at 4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells.ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> were pipetted in the wells. Wells with no inhibitors served as negative controls. The conidia germination was monitored after 10, 12, 14, 18, 20, 22 and 24 h of incubation by optical density (OD600 nm) readout (Magelan Infinite pro M200). The germination at each EO concentration was assessed as per the following <xref rid="fd3" ref-type="disp-formula">formula (3)</xref>:<disp-formula id="fd3"><label>(3)</label>Germination rate (&#x00394;OD) = OD<sub>tx</sub>-OD<sub>t0</sub></disp-formula>where OD<sub>t0</sub>: Optical density readout of a given well at time t = 0 (immediately after addition of pathogen's conidia in the mixture) whilst OD<sub>tx</sub> stands for optical density readout at time t = x (x &#x0003c; 0).</p><p id="p0075">The lowest concentration showing no growth of <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> upon subculture on fresh PDA medium (without EOs) was defined as the Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><label>2.8</label><title>Assessment of common bean seeds germination</title><sec id="sec2.8.1"><label>2.8.1</label><title>Allelopathy/bio-priming effect of EOs towards bean seeds</title><p id="p0080">The procedure described by <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Toghueuo et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</xref> was used to evaluate the effects of the tested EOs on common bean seeds germination or germination inhibition (Allelopathy). Bean seeds of the genotype GLP 190c, obtained from the germplasm of the National Institute of Agricultural Research for Development (IRAD) of Foumbot (West-Cameroon) were selected for any visible damage and surface-disinfected with Chlorox (5%, 1 min). The sterilizing solution was then removed by three rounds rinsing with sterile distilled water and blotted dried. The sterilized seeds were thereafter dipped in EOs suspensions for 2 h, and immediately transferred in 9.0cm Petri dishes provided with water-soaked tissue papers. The negative control seeds were soaked in sterile distilled water. Five plates with 10 seeds each were prepared per treatment and the whole experiment was conducted twice. The mean percentage of seeds germination was calculated in function of the total number of seeds per treatment following the <xref rid="fd4" ref-type="disp-formula">formula (4)</xref> below.<disp-formula id="fd4"><label>(4)</label>[(NGc-NGt)/ NGc]&#x02217;100.</disp-formula>Where: NGc and NGt are respectively the number of germinated seeds in the negative controls and treated plates.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8.2"><label>2.8.2</label><title>Effects of EOs on bean seeds germination under <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 assault</title><p id="p0085">To assure whether the EOs can promote bean seed germination while protecting them from <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> attack, sterilized seeds were soaked in EOs suspensions as described above. The reference fungicide (Ridomil Plus 44 WP), prepared in water at the dose recommended by the manufacturer (3.3 g.l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was used to coat the seeds. Both the EOs-treated and fungicide-treated seeds were allow to dry and afterward transferred into 9.0 cm Petri dishes (10 seeds/plate) provided with two layers of tissue paper. Then, 10 ml of <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> conidia suspension (4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells.ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) prepared in PDB were seeded in each plate. The control plate was rather provided with equal volume of sterile PDB medium. 5 replications were prepared for each treatments and the overall experiment was performed twice. Germinated bean seeds were counted upon 10 days incubation and the percentage of germination was calculated with reference to the controls (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><label>2.9</label><title><italic>In planta</italic> Fusarium root rot suppression assay</title><p id="p0090">To ascertain the protective effect of the EOs oils under natural conditions, a pot experiment was conducted in the greenhouse of the Biocontrol agent's sub-unit of the Laboratory for Phytobiochemisty and Medicinal Plants Studies of the University of Yaound&#x000e9; I, Cameroon. The growth substrate (soil) was collected from the A horizon of a common bean farm beneath the University and classified as Rhodic kanduidlut type following the U.S. soil taxonomy. The soil was checked for stones and woods particles from the bush and thereafter air-dried. The dried soil was then sieved with 4-mm mesh sieve and mixed up with river sand (3:1 v/v soil-sand ratio). The thus prepared substrate was autoclaved (121 &#x000b0;C, 1 h) twice, infested with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> conidia (3000 conidia/g of soil) and filled in the pots (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abawi and Pastor Corrales, 1990</xref>). Sterile seeds (GLP 190C) previously soaked in EOs or Ridomil plus 44 WP as described above were sown in the pots (3 seeds/pot). The pots were arranged in a greenhouse in a randomized block designed with 6 replications of 7 treatments as follow: (1) Control (non-inoculated soil and inhibitor-free seeds), (2) <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and inhibitor-free seeds), (3) Fs_(-)AMF<sub>500</sub> [(infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 500 ppm (CMI)], (4) Fs_(-)AMF<sub>1000</sub> [(infested with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 1000 ppm (2CMI)], (5) Fs_(+)AMF<sub>500</sub> [(infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 500 ppm (CMI)], (6) Fs_(+)AMF<sub>1000</sub> [(infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 1000 ppm (2CMI)], (7) Fs_Ridomil plus (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with the reference fungicide; Ridomil plus 44 WP). 28 days after sowing, agro-morphological parameters were recorded, and the plant vigour was calculated (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Toghueuo et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). The FRR incidence and severity were evaluated by visual and microscopic observations of the necrotic lesions on roots and hypocotyl and through the 1 to 9 disease rating scale of the CIAT (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abawi and Pastor Corrales, 1990</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Eke et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). The FRR severity was thereafter expressed in percentage as per the <xref rid="fd5" ref-type="disp-formula">formula (5)</xref> of <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Filion et&#x000a0;al. (2003)</xref> as.<disp-formula id="fd5"><label>(5)</label>FRR severity = &#x02211; 100&#x02217;[(DSi&#x02217; n)/N&#x02217;DS]</disp-formula>Where: DSi = severity (1&#x02013;9 scale) of a given plant, n = number of plants similar severity, N = total number of plants of the treatment, and DS = highest severity recorded (on the 1&#x02013;9 scale).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.10"><label>2.10</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0095">Numeric data collected from the overall experiments were subjected to the analysis of variance (ANOVA) using Statgraphics (version 5.1) statistical software for windows. Distances between the computerized mean values were measured either by the paired <italic>T-test</italic> when comparing the responses of the two EOs, or the Duncan's multiple comparison test when the treatments were greater than 2. The differences between means were significant at <italic>p &#x0003c; 0.05</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Mycorrhizal inoculation improves lemongrass growth and chlorophyll content</title><p id="p0100">Data reporting the effects of mycorrhizal inoculation on the growth and the chlorophyll synthesis of lemongrass are presented (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). The <italic>T-test</italic> revealed a significantly higher collar diameter (p = 0.02), branching (p = 0.015) and total chlorophyll synthesis in mycorrhizal lemongrass [(+)AMF] compared to the non-inoculated counterpart [(-)AMF]. Likewise, the Mycorrhizal efficiency (ME), indicating the increase in growth parameters of AMF-inoculated plants over the uninoculated ones showed a substantial accumulation in biomass production upon mycorrhization.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Changes in lemongrass growth, chlorophyll content and root colonization rate.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Table&#x000a0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Treatment</th><th colspan="5">Parameter<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Collar diameter (cm)</th><th>N<sup>o</sup> of Branches</th><th>Colonization rate (%)</th><th>Total chlorophyll (mg.g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> Fresh weight)</th><th>ME (%)<xref rid="tbl1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">1</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>(-) AMF</td><td>0.57 &#x000b1; 0.05<sup>b</sup></td><td>3.75 &#x000b1; 0.4<sup>a</sup></td><td>7.0 &#x000b1; 4.0<sup>b</sup></td><td>13.5 &#x000b1; 2.6<sup>b</sup></td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>(+) AMF</td><td>1.13 &#x000b1; 0.2<sup>a</sup></td><td>2.5 &#x000b1; 0.5<sup>b</sup></td><td>43 &#x000b1; 6.0<sup>a</sup></td><td>15.82 &#x000b1; 4.8<sup>a</sup></td><td>92.9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>(-) AMF: Essential oil from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass, (+)AMF: Essential oil from mycorrhizal lemongrass</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0010">Mycorrhizal Efficiency, standing for the increase rate expressed in percentage following mycorrhizal inoculation. The results are displayed in terms of Mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (SD). Mean values in each column with different alphabet are significantly different at &#x003b1; = 0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Inhibitory effects of essential oils and reference fungicide on <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 mycelial growth</title><p id="p0105">The inhibitory profiles of EOs from mycorrhizal and non-mycorrhizal lemongrass as well as Ridomil Plus 44 WP are shown (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>). Obviously, and irrespective of EOs, the inhibition percentages increased as the concentration augmented. At the concentration of 500 ppm, for both the EOs, and at 125 ppm for the reference fungicides, no visible growth of the pathogen was recorded, indicating a significant difference between the EOs and the reference fungicide. Taken at concentrations range of 62.5&#x02013;250 ppm, the mycelial growth inhibition exhibited by the (+)AMF] EO was higher compared to the non-inoculated [(-) AMF] plants though non-significant.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p><italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> mycelial growth inhibition by essential oils and Ridomil Plus 44WP at differing concentrations.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Table&#x000a0;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Conc (%)</th><th colspan="3">Growth inhibition (%)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>(-) AMF</th><th>(+) AMF</th><th>Ridomil Plus 44 WP</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>0</td><td>0.0 &#x000b1; 0.0<sup>e</sup></td><td>0.0 &#x000b1; 0.0<sup>d</sup></td><td>68.4 &#x000b1; 3.2<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td>62.5</td><td>16.5 &#x000b1; 2.1<sup>d</sup></td><td>23.5 &#x000b1; 2.1<sup>c</sup></td><td>82.7 &#x000b1; 6.4<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td>125</td><td>38 &#x000b1; 4.2<sup>c</sup></td><td>46 &#x000b1; 12.7<sup>b</sup></td><td>100 &#x000b1; 0.0<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>250</td><td>71 &#x000b1; 4.2<sup>b</sup></td><td>89 &#x000b1; 15.5<sup>a</sup></td><td>100 &#x000b1; 0.0<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>500</td><td>100 &#x000b1; 0.0<sup>a</sup></td><td>100 &#x000b1; 0.0<sup>a</sup></td><td>100 &#x000b1; 0.0<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>1000</td><td>100 &#x000b1; 0.0<sup>a</sup></td><td>100 &#x000b1; 0.0<sup>a</sup></td><td>100 &#x000b1; 0.0<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tspara0025"><p>(-) AMF: Essential oil from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass, (+)AMF: Essential oil from mycorrhizal lemongrass</p></fn><fn id="tspara0030"><p>The results are displayed in terms of Mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (SD). Mean values in each column with different alphabet are significantly different at &#x003b1; = 0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Inhibitory effects of essential oils from mycorrhizal and non- mycorrhizal inoculated lemongrass on <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> conidia germination</title><p id="p0110">The data reveal that the <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> conidia germination rate varied as function of concentration within and between EOs (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>). Irrespective of the essential oil involved, a negative correlation was found between the essential oils concentration and conidia germination in the sense that conidia germination speed dropped steadily as the EOs concentration increased. Between EOs, at lowest doses (62.5, 125 and 250 ppm), the overall inhibition of conidia germination of the EO from mycorrhizal lemongrass [(+)AMF] was significantly (p &#x0003c; 0.05) higher compared to the un-inoculated counterpart (-)AMF]. At higher concentrations (500, 1000 and 2000 ppm) reversely, no growth was recorded upon subculture on solid medium with the EO from mycorrhizal lemongrass [(+)AMF] upon 8 h incubation till the end of the experiment. Whilst at 500 ppm, growth re-occurred with the EO from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass (-)AMF indicating a better performance of the EO from mycorrhizal lemongrass (MIC = 500 ppm; 8 h) over the non-mycorrhizal counterpart (MIC = 1000 ppm; 8 h).<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Inhibitory profiles of EOs from non-inoculated and AMF-inoculated lemongrass plantlets towards <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> spores germination in function of time and concentration. (-) AMF: Essential oil from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass, (+)AMF: Essential oil from mycorrhizal lemongrass. Each curve with a given colour indicates the germination rate of <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic>'s conidia at a given concentration.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Figure&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Essential oils from mycorrhizal and non-mycorrhizal inoculated lemongrass impact common bean seeds germination in presence and absence of <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4</title><p id="p0115">Prior to pot trial, the EOs were screened out at their respective CMI and 2CMI on common bean seeds germination under sterile and <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> infected environments (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>). In the absence of the pathogen, as referred to the mock, both the EOs significantly slowed down the common bean seed germination at the concentration of 1000 ppm, indicating an allelopathic reaction at that concentration. Meanwhile, at 500 ppm the later rather enhanced the germination power by 7% and 19% respectively for EOs from non-inoculated and AMF-primed lemongrass. The ANOVA indicated a significantly higher germination rate at 500 ppm for (+)AMF EO compared to (-)AMF EO. In the presence of <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>)<italic>,</italic> while no germination was recorded in infected bean seeds, a protective effect was obvious upon coating the seeds with the EOs (p &#x0003c; 0.05). Irrespective of the EO, the concentration 500 ppm was the best in both protecting and enhancing seed germination compared to 1000 ppm. The best germination rate being recorded with the EO from (+)AMF lemongrass (p &#x0003c; 0.05).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Effects of essential oils from mycorrhizal and non- mycorrhizal primed lemongrass, on common bean seeds germination in presence and absence of <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Table&#x000a0;3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3">Treatment</th><th colspan="6">Germination percentage<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="3">Without <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic><hr/></th><th colspan="3">Infected With <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic><hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Control</th><th>500 ppm</th><th>1000 ppm</th><th>Control</th><th>500 ppm</th><th>1000 ppm</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>(-) AMF</td><td>81.5 &#x000b1; 4.9<sup>e</sup></td><td>89 &#x000b1; 2.4<sup>e</sup></td><td>64.5 &#x000b1; 0.7<sup>d</sup></td><td>0.0 &#x000b1; 0.0<sup>a</sup></td><td>45 &#x000b1; 7.07<sup>c</sup></td><td>35 &#x000b1; 7.07<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td>(+) AMF</td><td>81.5 &#x000b1; 4.9<sup>e</sup></td><td>100 &#x000b1; 0.0<sup>f</sup></td><td>69.5 &#x000b1; 7.7<sup>d</sup></td><td>0.0 &#x000b1; 0.1<sup>a</sup></td><td>65.0 &#x000b1; 2.4<sup>d</sup></td><td>34.5 &#x000b1; 3.5<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tspara0040"><p>(-) AMF: Essential oil from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass; (+) AMF: Essential oil from mycorrhizal lemongrass.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0045"><p>Mean values in each column with different alphabet are significantly different at &#x003b1; = 0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Germination of common bean seeds coated with either EO from non-primed [(-) AMF] and AMF-primed [(+) AMF] lemongrass, at different concentrations. Mock, stands for non-treated seeds seeded in <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> infected Petri plates. Arrow indicate fungal invasion on bean seeds.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Figure&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>FRR suppressive test</title><sec id="sec3.5.1"><label>3.5.1</label><title>FRR suppression with essential oils from AMF-primed lemongrass or not</title><p id="p0120">The results indicate that, seeds dressing with EOs significantly suppressed both the disease incidence and severity compared to the negative control (inhibitor-free seeds planted in <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> infested soil (p &#x0003c; 0.05) with protection rate ranging from 0 to 65.0% and 0&#x02013;63.13% for root rot incidence and severity, respectively. The best protection was recorded with essential oils from AMF-primed lemongrass at the concentration of 1000 ppm (65.0%) as far as the FRR incidence is concerned while the lowest disease severity was obtained with the reference fungicide, Ridomil Plus 44 WP (63.13%) (see <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;4</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Effects of common bean seeds coating with essential oils from mycorrhizal and non- mycorrhizal primed lemongrass and Ridomil on FRR incidence and severity.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Table&#x000a0;4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Treatment</th><th>DI (%)</th><th>Protection rate (%)</th><th>[DS (%)&#x02217;]</th><th>Protection rate (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Control</td><td>0.0<sup>a</sup></td><td>0.0</td><td>1,0<sup>a</sup></td><td>0.0</td></tr><tr><td><italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> (Fs)</td><td>100.0<sup>e</sup></td><td>0.0</td><td>78.2<sup>e</sup></td><td>0.0</td></tr><tr><td>Fs_(-) AMF<sub>500</sub></td><td>55.0<sup>d</sup></td><td>45.0</td><td>42.2<sup>d</sup></td><td>46.03</td></tr><tr><td>Fs_(-) AMF<sub>1000</sub></td><td>43.0<sup>c</sup></td><td>57.0</td><td>36.7<sup>c</sup></td><td>53.06</td></tr><tr><td>Fs_ (+) AMF<sub>500</sub></td><td>46.5<sup>c</sup></td><td>54.5</td><td>40.6<sup>d</sup></td><td>48.08</td></tr><tr><td>Fs_ (+) AMF<sub>1000</sub></td><td>35.0<sup>b</sup></td><td>65.0</td><td>32.4<sup>c</sup></td><td>58.56</td></tr><tr><td>Fs_Ridomil Plus</td><td>41.7<sup>c</sup></td><td>59.3</td><td>28.8<sup>b</sup></td><td>63.13</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0125">Control (non-inoculated soil and inhibitor-free seeds), <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and inhibitor-free seeds), Fs_(-)AMF<sub>500</sub> (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 500 ppm), Fs_(-)AMF<sub>1000</sub> (infested with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 1000 ppm), Fs_(+)AMF<sub>500</sub> (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 500 ppm), Fs_(+)AMF<sub>1000</sub> (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 1000 ppm), Fs_Ridomil plus (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with the reference fungicide; Ridomil plus 44 WP). DI = Disease Incidence; DS = Disease Severity; Mean values in each column with different alphabet are significantly different at &#x003b1; = 0.05. &#x02217;Disease severity expressed as percentage according to <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Filion et&#x000a0;al. (2003)</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5.2"><label>3.5.2</label><title>Common bean seeds coating with essential oils from either AMF-primed lemongrass or not impact the growth in the presence of <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic></title><p id="p0130">The data displayed in <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;5</xref> unveiled the beneficial effects of bean seeds coating with lemongrass EOs and Ridomil compared to <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> infected and negative controls. While symptoms like leaves chlorosis, stunting and premature defoliation were observed in plantlets emerging from <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> infested pots only (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>), reiterating the aggressiveness of the fungus. A substantial increase could be observed in plantlets whose seeds were previously dressed with either essential oils or the reference fungicide (p &#x0003c; 0.05) compared to the untreated controls. Globally, the root and shoot length and their respective dry masses were magnified by approximately two-folds upon seeds coating with AMF-primed EO at 1000 ppm compared to other treatments. This clearly indicated that AMF-primed lemongrass oils, protected the common bean plantlets from being infected, leading to more biological matter yield.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl5"><label>Table&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Effects of common bean seeds coating with essential oils from mycorrhizal and non- mycorrhizal primed lemongrass and Ridomil on common bean seedlings growth.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Table&#x000a0;5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Treatment</th><th colspan="5">Agro-morphological parameter<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Root length (cm)</th><th>Shoot length (cm)</th><th>Root dry weight (g)</th><th>Shoot dry weight (g)</th><th>Vigour index</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Control</td><td>20.3 &#x000b1; 2.2<sup>b</sup></td><td>48.1 &#x000b1; 5.4b<sup>c</sup></td><td>0.31 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup>b</sup></td><td>3.43 &#x000b1; 1.21<sup>b</sup></td><td>5435</td></tr><tr><td><italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> (Fs)</td><td>12.8 &#x000b1; 2.4<sup>a</sup></td><td>29.4 &#x000b1; 6.6<sup>a</sup></td><td>0.18 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup>a</sup></td><td>1.9 &#x000b1; 0.6<sup>a</sup></td><td>2815</td></tr><tr><td>Fs_ (-) AMF<sub>500</sub></td><td>21.3 &#x000b1; 1.6<sup>b</sup></td><td>45.6 &#x000b1; 3.4<sup>b</sup></td><td>0.32 &#x000b1; 0.1<sup>b</sup></td><td>2.8 &#x000b1; 0.74<sup>b</sup></td><td>4654</td></tr><tr><td>Fs_ (-) AMF<sub>1000</sub></td><td>25.9 &#x000b1; 4.2<sup>c</sup></td><td>52.8 &#x000b1; 6.7<sup>c</sup></td><td>0.57 &#x000b1; 0.1<sup>c</sup></td><td>4.6 &#x000b1; 1.30<sup>c</sup></td><td>5548</td></tr><tr><td>Fs_ (+) AMF<sub>500</sub></td><td>17.5 &#x000b1; 4.8a<sup>b</sup></td><td>42.6 &#x000b1; 5.5<sup>b</sup></td><td>0.33 &#x000b1; 0.02<sup>b</sup></td><td>3.32 &#x000b1; 1.10<sup>b</sup></td><td>4525</td></tr><tr><td>Fs_ (+) AMF<sub>1000</sub></td><td>26.6 &#x000b1; 4.7<sup>c</sup></td><td>54.6 &#x000b1; 2.8<sup>d</sup></td><td>0.74 &#x000b1; 0.2<sup>d</sup></td><td>5.01 &#x000b1; 1.7<sup>c</sup></td><td>7814</td></tr><tr><td>Fs_Ridomil Plus</td><td>23.9 &#x000b1; 7.1b<sup>c</sup></td><td>50.2 &#x000b1; 4.7<sup>c</sup></td><td>0.49 &#x000b1; 0.18<sup>c</sup></td><td>4.50 &#x000b1; 1.9<sup>c</sup></td><td>5812</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Control (non-inoculated soil and inhibitor-free seeds), <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and inhibitor-free seeds), Fs_(-) AMF<sub>500</sub> (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 500 ppm), Fs_(-) AMF<sub>1000</sub> (infested with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 1000 ppm), Fs_(+) AMF<sub>500</sub> (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 500 ppm), Fs_(+) AMF<sub>1000</sub> (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 1000 ppm), Fs_Ridomil plus (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with the reference fungicide; Ridomil plus 44 WP). Mean values in each column with different alphabet are significantly different at &#x003b1; = 0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Effects of common bean seeds coating with essential oils from mycorrhizal and non- mycorrhizal primed lemongrass at different concentrations and Ridomil on FRR and plant growth. Control (pots with un-inoculated soil and non-treated seeds); Control (non-inoculated soil and inhibitor-free seeds), <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and inhibitor-free seeds), Fs_(-) AMF<sub>500</sub> (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 500 ppm), Fs_(-) AMF<sub>1000</sub> (infested with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 1000 ppm), Fs_(+) AMF<sub>500</sub> (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 500 ppm), Fs_(+) AMF<sub>1000</sub> (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with EOs from mycorrhizal lemongrass at the concentration of 1000 ppm), Fs_Ridomil plus (infested soil with <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 and seed coated with the reference fungicide; Ridomil plus 44 WP).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Figure&#x000a0;3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0135">The efforts towards reducing the usage of pesticides in agricultural systems initiated in the second half of the 20th century has led to the investigation of alternative approaches of which botanical pesticides (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Nana et&#x000a0;al., 2015a</xref>). In spite of the broad spectrum activity of EOs against a plethora of agriculturally impactful pests and pathogens, just few manufactured pesticides is commercially availablereason being the instability in EOs composition which runs counter the legislation governing botanical pesticides validation. To address this task earlier findings focus on techniques likegenetic manipulations, the usage of elicitation products and new biotechnological methods to grow MAPs, aiming at both increasing the production and assuring standardized EOs composition (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Mahmoud and Croteau, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Iannicelli, 2016</xref>). Here, we attempted to assess the effects of mycorrhizal inoculation on the growth, essential oil production and the suppressive effects of the resulting EOs towards a local highly virulent common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.) root rot causing pathogen; <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4.</p><p id="p0140">Our data unveiled a significantly higher biological yield and mycorrhizal dependency in mycorrhizal lemongrass compared to uninoculated ones. The obtained data are in agreement with our previous data indicating an accumulated biomass in mycorrhizal lemongrass compared to non-inoculated control (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Fokom et al., 2019</xref>), and further lay emphasis on the impact of AMF in improving the growth of many higher plants on earth (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Ngakou et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Nana et al., 2015b</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Gomoung et al., 2017</xref>). Tentative explanation of such trait has pointed out foremost mycorrhiza (up to 43% colonization rate relative to the normal control) with their subsequent established repercussion on plant fitness. In fact, a set of physical and metabolic shifts occur in the host and its surrounding environment including the exploration of more volume of soil by extra-radical mycelia, leading to an enhanced uptake of water and essential micro and macro nutrients (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Schnepf and Leitner, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Azc&#x000f3;n-Aguilar et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Gosling et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Eke et al., 2019</xref>). The tested EOs displayed significant inhibition in <italic>F. solani</italic> Fs4 mycelial growth and conidia germination in a dose-dependent manner. The MIC were 500 ppm for the EOs, and 125 ppm for the Ridomil Plus 44 WP as far as the mycelial growth is concerned. The mycelial growth inhibition recorded with EO from AMF-inoculated lemongrass was significantly higher compared non-inoculated counterpart though non-significant. Reversely, the EO from (+)AMF was statistically more performant in inhibiting conidia germination compared to EO from non-mycorrhizal lemongrass. Similar inhibitory effects of EOs has been reported against a vast array of phytopathogens including <italic>Alternaria alternata, Ralstonia solanacearum, Penicillium citrinum, Rhyzopius stolonifera, Phytophthora megakarya, Phytophthora nicotians, Phytophthora colocaseae, Phytophthora capsici and Fusarium solani</italic> (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Bowers and Locke, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Helal et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Mahanta et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Paret et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Bi et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Nana et al., 2015a</xref>; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Sameza, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Amini et al., 2016</xref>) threatening world food security. Lemongrass EOs for instance has earlier been credited with hypocholesterolemy, antimutagenic, antiprotozoal, cytoprotection, antioxidation, and antimalarial and anti-inflammatory activities in addition to their antifungal potentials (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Vazquez-Briones et al., 2015</xref>). The overall activities being more often related to their composition in neral, citral and geranial as major components (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Adukwu et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Fokom et al., 2019</xref>). At the moment, clear mechanism of action undergone by any of these phytochemicals are still to be demonstrated but, it is well-known that EOs oftentimes act by disrupting the cell wall and cytoplasmic membrane of fungi and bacteria, leading to leakage of intracellular compounds and probably cell death by lysis. Otherwise, EOs components may disturb membrane channels and pumps, altering the ionic balance between the cells inner and outer compartments causing cell physical alteration and death without releasing the cellular contents (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Tian, 2012</xref>). The increasing emphasis on EOs as genuine tool in the fight against disease and pest is not only related to the individual efficacy of their putative major components, but to the multitude of mechanisms driven by their chemically diverse constituents, which makes then important weapon to fight the resistance phenomenon. Therefore, synergistic relationships are likely the mostly indicated mode underlying the efficiency of complex mixtures like EOs (<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Vidyasagar and Tabassum, 2013</xref>). Many scenarios have been postulated accordingly. While <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Kim and Park (2012)</xref> pointed out additivity and/or synergism between components bearing individual antimicrobial potential, optional mode indicates that non-active minors ingredients may act either as adjuvants by facilitating the influx of active principles having their target in the cytoplasm or nucleus or the optimisation of an active ingredient through the formation of more active chemical complex (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Shiota et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Sibanda and Okoh, 2007</xref>). The recorded discrepancy among both the EOs (from AMF-inoculated or not) could be due to the shift in the biochemical changes perpetrated in the composition of the essences of AMF-inoculated plants. Of note, inorganic phosphorus, which increased provision by AMF through mycorrhiza has been proven, are essential reactant in the biosynthesis of terpenoids; the major components of EOs (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Ashour et al., 2010</xref>). Also it was observed in our previous study that the percentage of myrcene was significantly higher in EO from mycorhizal plant 14 month post planting than control lemongrass plant (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Fokom et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0145">Moreover, the EO extracted from mycorrhizal lemongrass protected the common bean plantlets from infection by <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 both in laboratory and under greenhouse conditions, leading to healthier and vigorous plantlets with reference to plants emerging from <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> infected common bean plantlets alone. The best reduction in root rot incidence protection rate was obtained with EOs from AMF-primed lemongrass at the concentration of 1000 ppm (65.0%) while the lowest disease severity was obtained with the reference fungicide, Ridomil Plus 44 WP (63.13%). Similar reductions have been shown by several EOs towards soil-borne diseases in cucumber, melon, pepper and Cocoa (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Nana et&#x000a0;al., 2015a</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Amini et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). The recorded data are in accordance with the <italic>in vitro</italic> assays where a significant lethal effect of the EOs towards the conidia of <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> was evidenced. It is likely that once in the rhizosphere, the essential oils may have diffused in the soil and killed the infectious propagules providing a sterile environment around the seeds (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abawi and Pastor-Corrales, 1990</xref>). As a consequence of the disease reduction, the common bean plants grew faster but at doses 2000 ppm the growth of the plants were significantly reduced. This could be ascribed to the phenomenon of allelopathy which has long been cited as inherent attributes of EOs. Overall, we obtained prominent effects at 500 and 1000 &#x003bc;L.l<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. This promising output end to somehow resolve the issue of standardization of EOs, and provides a clear insight on the cost-effectiveness of the application of essential oils in open field. Indeed, seeds dressing require less amount of EOs and can address the volatility issue often cited as the most limiting factor associated to the use of EOs in crop protection.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0150">In this study, we recorded lemongrass biomass accumulation, improved essential oils yield upon mycorrhization under field conditions. Likewise, EO from mycorrhizal lemongrass consistently inhibited <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 development, significantly more than the non-inoculated counterpart. At 1000 ppm, both the essential oils enhanced the common bean seeds germination, and protected plantlets from being infected by <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic> Fs4 both in laboratory and greenhouse conditions, leading to more healthy and vigorous plants. Overall, AMF inoculation had reoriented the metabolome of lemongrass plant. Leading to an enhanced growth and antifungal potential of the resulting EO towards <italic>F.&#x000a0;solani</italic>. But the constance in the chemical composition should be demonstrated overtime in order to standardize the product and move ahead in the search of organic alternative to agrochemicals.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec6.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0155">Pierre Eke, Souleymanou Adamou, Raymond Fokom: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0160">Vanessa Dinango Nya: Performed the experiments.</p><p id="p0165">Tsou Fokou Patrick Valer:Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0170">Louise Nana Wakam, Dieudonn&#x000e9; Nwaga, Fabrice Fekam Boyom: Conceived and designed the experiments; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p></sec><sec id="sec6.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0175">This work was supported by <funding-source id="gs1">Notre Dame Institute for Advanced Study</funding-source> and Pierre Eke was supported by <funding-source id="gs2">Wallace Laboratories (US)</funding-source>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec6.3"><title>Data availability statement</title><p id="p0180">No data was used for the research described in the article.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec6.4"><title>Declaration of interests statement</title><p id="p0185">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec6.5"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0190">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abawi</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pastor-Corrales</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Root rots of beans in Latin America and Africa: diagnosis, research methodologies, and management strategies</chapter-title><source>Centro Internacional de Agricultura Tropical (CIAT)</source><edition>first ed./</edition><year>1990</year><publisher-name>Kandrups Bogtrykkeri edition</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cali, Colombia</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dafforn</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vetiver DNA-fingerprinted cultivars: effects of environment on growth, oil yields and composition</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Essent. Oil Res.</source><volume>15</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>371</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adukwu</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowles</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards-Jones</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bone</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity, cytotoxicity and chemical analysis of lemongrass essential oil (<italic>Cymbopogon</italic> fl<italic>exuosus</italic>) and and pure</article-title><source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>100</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>9619</fpage><lpage>9627</lpage><comment>Constraints. Trends in Plant Science, TRPLSC 1484 in press</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27562470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>AL-Askar</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rashad</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi: a biocontrol agent against common bean Fusarium root rot disease</article-title><source>Plant Pathol. J.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amini</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farhang</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Javadi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazemi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antifungal effect of plant essential oils on controlling <italic>Phytophthora</italic> species</article-title><source>Plant Pathol. J.</source><volume>32</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26889111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amujoyegbe</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agbedahunsi</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amujoyegbe</surname><given-names>O.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cultivation of medicinal plants in developing nations: means of conservation and poverty alleviation</article-title><source>Int. J. Med. Aromatic Plants</source><volume>2</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>353</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashour</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wink</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Biochemistry of terpenoids: monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes and diterpenes</chapter-title><edition>second ed.</edition><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Wink</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><series>Annual Plant Reviews: Biochemistry of Plant Secondary Metabolism</series><volume>40</volume><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azc&#x000f3;n-Aguilar</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palenzuela</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roldan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bautista</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallejo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barea</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the mycorrhizal potential in the rhizosphere of representative plant species from desertification threatened Mediterranean shrublands</article-title><source>Appl. Soil Ecol.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>175</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hausbeck</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitory effects of essential oils for controlling <italic>Phytophthora capsici</italic></article-title><source>Plant Dis.</source><volume>96</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30727361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of formulated plant extracts and oils on population density of <italic>Phytophthora nicotianae</italic> in soil and control of Phytophthora blight in the greenhouse</article-title><source>Plant Dis.</source><volume>88</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30812449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI)</collab></person-group><chapter-title>Reference Method for Broth Dilution Antifungal Susceptibility Testing of Filamentous Fungi; Approved Standard-second ed.</chapter-title><comment>CLSI Document M38-A2</comment><year>2008</year><publisher-name>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</publisher-name><publisher-loc>suite 1400, Wayne, Pennsylvania 190871898, USA</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Copetta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lingua</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berta</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of three AM fungi on growth, distribution of glandular hairs and essential oil production in <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L. var. Genovese</article-title><source>Mycorrhiza</source><volume>16</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16896796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatue</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nana</surname><given-names>W.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toghueo</surname><given-names>K.R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsouh</surname><given-names>F.P.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jesus-Marie</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fekam</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mycorrhiza consortia in dual inoculation with <italic>Fusarium solani</italic> f. sp. Phaseoli control the root rot in common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Biol. Contr.</source><volume>103</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>250</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nana</surname><given-names>W.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toghueo</surname><given-names>K.R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsouh</surname><given-names>F.P.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jesus-Marie</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fekam</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrated assessment of phytostimulation and biocontrol potential of endophytic <italic>trichoderma</italic> spp. against common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.) root rot fungi complex in Centre region, Cameroon</article-title><source>Int. J. Pure Appl. Biosc.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nana</surname><given-names>W.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsouh</surname><given-names>F.P.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekounda</surname><given-names>T.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuleshwar</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamdem</surname><given-names>W.T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fekam</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved nutrient status and Fusarium root rot mitigation with an inoculant of two biocontrol fungi in the common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Rhizosphere</source><volume>12</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>100172</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erper</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karaca</surname><given-names>H.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozkoc</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Root rot disease incidence and severity on some legume species grown in Samsun and the fungi isolated from roots and soils Arc</article-title><source>Phytopathol. Plant Prot.</source><volume>41</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>506</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Filion</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>St.-Arnaud</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jabaji-Hare</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantification of <italic>Fusarium solani</italic> f. sp. Phaseoli in mycorrhizal bean plants and surrounding mycorrhizosphere soil using realtime polymerase chain reaction and direct isolations on selective media</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><volume>93</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18943138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fokom</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adamou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Essono</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngwasiri</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teugwa</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tchoumbougnang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fekam</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amvam</surname><given-names>Z.P.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nwaga</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth, essential oil content, chemical composition and antioxidant properties of lemongrass as affected by harvest period and arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi in field conditions</article-title><source>Ind. Crop. Prod.</source><volume>138</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>111477</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crescimento e produ&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de fen&#x000f3;is totais em carqueja [<italic>Baccharis trimera</italic> (Less.)] napresen&#x000e7;ae na aus&#x000ea;ncia de aduba&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o mineral</article-title><source>Rev. Bras. Pl. Botuc Med.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gianinazzi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gollotte</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Binet</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Tuinen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Redecker</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wipf</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Agroecology: the key role of arbuscular mycorrhizas in ecosystem services</article-title><source>Mycorrhiza</source><volume>20</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20697748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giovannetti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosse</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An evaluation of techniques for measuring vesicular-arbuscular mycorrhizal infection in roots</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><volume>84</volume><year>1980</year><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>499</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomoung</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mbailao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toukam</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngakou</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In<italic>fl</italic>uence of cross-inoculation on groundnut and Bambara groundnut Rhizobium symbiosis: contribution to plant growth and yield in the field at Sarh (Chad) and Ngaoundere (Cameroon)</article-title><source>Am. J. Plant Sci.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1953</fpage><lpage>1966</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gosling</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodge</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodlass</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bending</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi and organic farming</article-title><source>Agric. Ecosyst. Environ.</source><volume>113</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toximetric studies of fungicides against brown rot organism: S. fructicola et Slaxa</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><volume>52</volume><year>1962</year><fpage>876</fpage><lpage>880</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helal</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarhan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu Shahla</surname><given-names>A.N.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abou Elkhair</surname><given-names>E.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of some essential oils against microorganism deteriorating fruit juices</article-title><source>MYCOBIOLOGY</source><volume>34</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24039503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iannicelli</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of polyploidization in the production of essential oils in <italic>Lippia integrifolia</italic></article-title><source>Ind. Crop. Prod.</source><volume>81</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karagiannidis</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomidis</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazari</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Panou-Filotheou</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karagiannidou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of three Greek arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi in improving the growth, nutrient concentration, and production of essential oils of oregano and mint plants</article-title><source>Sci. Hortic.-Amsterdam</source><volume>129</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>334</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref59"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karki</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Organic conversion &#x00026; certification: a strategy for improved value addition and marketing of medicinal plants products in the Himalayas</chapter-title><source>Paper presented at the Regional Workshop at Wise Practices and Experimental Learning in the Conservation and Management of Himalayan Medicinal Plant</source><year>December 15&#x02013;20, 2002</year><comment>Kathmandu, Nepal</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fumigant antifungal activity of myrtaceae essential oils and constituents from <italic>Leptospermum petersonii</italic> against three <italic>Aspergillus</italic> species</article-title><source>Mol</source><volume>17</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>10459</fpage><lpage>10469</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukesh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anuradha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonika</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antima</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancing seed germination and vigor of Chickpea by using potential and effective strains of Trichoderma species</article-title><source>Virol. Mycol.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>128</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laku&#x00161;i&#x000b4;c</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Risti&#x000b4;c</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slavkovska</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laku&#x00161;i&#x000b4;c</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal variations in the composition of the essential oils of Rosemary (Rosmarinus officinalis, Lamiaceae)</article-title><source>Nat. Prod. Commun.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23472478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichtenthaler</surname><given-names>H.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chlorophylls and carotenoids: pigments of photosynthetic biomembranes</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol.</source><volume>148</volume><year>1987</year><fpage>350</fpage><lpage>382</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahanta</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chutia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bordoloi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adhikary</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic> L. essential oil as a potential antifungal agent against key weed moulds of <italic>Pleurotus</italic> spp. spawns</article-title><source>Flavour Fragrance J.</source><volume>22</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>525530</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strategies for transgenic manipulation of monoterpene biosynthesis in plants</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12167332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McChesney</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkataraman</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henri</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant natural products: back to the future or into extinction?</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><volume>68</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>2015</fpage><lpage>2022</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17574638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mucciarelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scannerini</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertea</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maffei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> peppermint (<italic>Mentha piperita</italic>) growth promotion by nonmycorrhizal fungal colonization</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><volume>158</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>597</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukankusi</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Melis</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derera</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buruchara</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;screening technique for resistance to Fusarium root rot of common bean</article-title><source>Afr. J. Plant Sci.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>15161</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nana</surname><given-names>W.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fokom</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakanrga</surname><given-names>V.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Begoude</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tchana</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tchameni</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuate</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chantal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fekam</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of <italic>Syzygium aromaticum</italic> and <italic>Zanthoxylum xanthoxyloides</italic> essential oils against <italic>Phytophthora megakarya</italic></article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Phytopathol.</source><volume>163</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>632</fpage><lpage>641</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nana</surname><given-names>W.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atogho</surname><given-names>T.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toghueo</surname><given-names>K.R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatue</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pokaa</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekounda</surname><given-names>T.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Etoa</surname><given-names>F.X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fekam</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In-vitro</italic> fungitoxic effect of cold and&#x000a0;hot water extracts of three <italic>Ocimum</italic> species on fungi causing common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.) root rot in Cameroon</article-title><source>Int. J. Curr. Microbiol. Appl. Sci.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>596</fpage><lpage>606</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ngakou</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nwaga</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ntonifor</surname><given-names>N.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nebane</surname><given-names>C.L.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parh</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution of arbuscular mycorrhizal Fungi (AMF), rhizobia and <italic>metarhizium&#x000a0;anisopliae</italic> to cowpea production in Cameroon</article-title><source>Int. J. Agric. Res.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>754</fpage><lpage>764</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nwaga</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansa</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abossolo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>The potential of soil beneficial microorganisms for slash-and-burn agriculture in the humid forest zone of Sub Saharan Africa</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dion</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Soil Biology and Agriculture in the Tropics</source><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>107</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nzungize</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyumugabe</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busogoro</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baudoin</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pythium root rot of common bean: biology and control methods. A review</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Agron. Soc. Environ.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>413</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paret</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabos</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kratky</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of plant essential oils on <italic>Ralstonia solanacearum</italic> race 4 and bacterial wilt of edible ginger</article-title><source>Plant Dis.</source><volume>94</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30754476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sameza</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of clove essential oil as a mycobiocide against <italic>rhizopus stolonifer</italic> and <italic>fusarium solani</italic>, tuber rot causing fungi in yam (<italic>Dioscorea rotundata</italic> Poir)</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Phytopathol.</source><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnepf</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leitner</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Modelling the Effect of Arbuscular Mycorrhizal Fungi on Plant Phosphate Uptake</chapter-title><year>2011</year><publisher-name>Tagung Der &#x000d6;sterreichischen Gesellschaft F&#x000fc;r Wurzelforschung</publisher-name><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>64</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shiota</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizushima</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of action of corilagin and tellimagrandin I that remarkably potentiate the activity of &#x000df;-lactams against methicillin resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Microbiol. Immunol.</source><volume>48</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14734860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sibanda</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okoh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The challenges of overcoming antibiotic resistance: plant extracts as potential sources of antimicrobial and resistance modifying agents</article-title><source>Afr. J. Biotechnol.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>2886</fpage><lpage>2896</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Mycorrhizal Symbiosis</chapter-title><edition>3 edition</edition><year>2008</year><publisher-name>Acad. Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tak</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isman</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolism of citral, the major constituent of lemongrass oil, in the cabbage looper, <italic>Tricohoplusia ni</italic>, and effects of enzyme inhibitors on toxicity and metabolism</article-title><source>Pestic. Biochem. Physiol.</source><volume>133</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27742357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tchameni</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nwaga</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nana</surname><given-names>W.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngonkeu</surname><given-names>M.E.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fokom</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Etoa</surname><given-names>F.X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth enhancement, amino acid synthesis and reduction in susceptibility towards <italic>Phytophthora megakarya</italic> by Arbuscular Mycorrhizal Fungi inoculation in cocoa plants</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Phytopathol.</source><year>2012</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mechanism of antifungal action of essential oil from dill (<italic>Anethum graveolens</italic> L.) on <italic>Aspergillus</italic> fl<italic>avus</italic></article-title><source>PloS One</source><volume>7</volume><year>2012</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e30147</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toghueo</surname><given-names>R.M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>&#x000cd;.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldana</surname><given-names>B.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nana</surname><given-names>W.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyom</surname><given-names>F.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biocontrol and growth enhancement potential of two endophytic <italic>Trichoderma</italic> spp. from <italic>Terminalia catappa</italic> against the causative agent of Common Bean Root Rot (<italic>Fusarium solani</italic>)</article-title><source>Biol. Contr.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>44</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vazquez-Briones</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrero-Beltran</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physicochemical&#x000a0;and antioxidant properties of <italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic> essential oil</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Food Res.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>45</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vidyasagar</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabassum</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antifungal investigations on plant essential oils. a review</article-title><source>Int. J. Pharm. Pharmaceut. Sci.</source><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The combined effects of Arbuscular Mycorrhizal Fungi (AMF) and Lead (Pb) Stress on Pb accumulation, plant growth parameters, photosynthesis, and antioxidant enzymes in <italic>Robinia pseudoacacia</italic> L</article-title><source>PloS One</source><volume>10</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2015</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0145726</object-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>