<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The EU approval for the use of the insect meals in poultry nutrition is “not so distant in the future”, and the approval by the EU Member States could be possible during the first quarter of 2019 [
 <xref rid="B1-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Thus, it is mandatory to understand all the possible aspects related to the chemical-nutritional characteristics, the effects on the animal health and welfare, the impact of feed and food safety of the different meals deriving from insects. This goal is not easy to reach as some characteristics can be modified according to the species and, within the species, in relation to the harvesting stage, the growth substrate, etc. In recent years, several studies pointed out the attention on the use of insect meals in growing broiler [
 <xref rid="B3-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>], quail [
 <xref rid="B7-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>], and barbary partridge [
 <xref rid="B8-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. In laying hens, the available literature on the effects of insect meals on laying performance, egg quality, metabolic and nutritional effects is limited and very often the results are conflicting due to the different species of insects used, the different strains and age of lay of the hens utilized in the trials [
 <xref rid="B10-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>].
</p>
