<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The shade-dried fruits (8.2 kg) were grinded with the help of a local grinder machine to obtain powder, and then, 8.00 kg powder plant material was soaked in methanol (40 liters) for 13 days to obtain a crude methanolic extract 350 g. The crude extract was suspended in water (500 mL) to prepare the paste and then successively extracted with various organic solvent on polarity, to obtain 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane extract (50.9 g), chloroform extract (93.00 g), and ethyl acetate extract (45.87 g) as per standard methods [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. A small portion of all obtained extracts was subjected to thin-layer chromatography (TLC), by using different solvent systems; the maximum separation was observed in 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane and ethyl acetate. Based on the TLC profile, the chloroform fraction was selected for separation because it contains a maximum number of compounds. Among the chloroform extracts, 25.0 g was chromatographed on silica gel by using normal phase column chromatography. The column was eluted with a mixture of 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane and ethyl acetate (0 : 100) of increasing polarity order. Two hundred fractions were collected, which were combined to 16 major fractions (SB-1-SB16), as per the TLC profile. Based on TLC profile, SB-9 was subjected to repeated pencil column chromatography (CC), eluting with 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane and ethyl acetate (14 : 86), which yielded white crystal. The obtained crystals were washed with 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane which gives daturaolone (
 <bold>1</bold>; 99.89% pure) (2.7 g). The chemical structure of daturaolone (
 <bold>1)</bold> was elucidated by advanced spectroscopic technique (
 <sup>1</sup>H-NMR, 
 <sup>13</sup>C-NMR, HMBC, HMQC, NOESY, COSY, and EI-MS). The structure was confirmed by crystallography technique (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>) and compared the spectral data with the reported one [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].
</p>
