<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">Due to the development of superbugs as a result of unprescribed and frequent use of antibiotics in recent years, an alternate form of medicine had to be introduced. In light of this global threat, researchers all over the world have been gravitating towards herbal medicines. In order to find out new ways of saving the planet using medicinal plants, ethnobotanical studies must be carried out. Concerning this, an ethnobotanical study has been done in this paper to identify potential medicinal plants in Rangamati, Bangladesh.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par2">For the ethnobotanical survey, randomized 104 people were interviewed and 62 different plant species were found to treat 19 different kinds of diseases and 84% of people reported to be completely recovered. Furthermore, among the 19 diseases found, the majority of them were common cold, abdominal pain or gastric, diarrhea, and dysentery. From the 62 different plant species, 
   <italic>Heptapleurum hypoleucum</italic>, used for the treatment of diarrhea, was selected for conducting further studies due to its heavy use as reported by the tribal people. In this study, the aqueous, ethanol, and methanol extracts of 
   <italic>Heptapleurum hypoleucum</italic> were subjected to microbial susceptibility assays using the agar well diffusion method. The test microorganisms were 
   <italic>Salmonella typhi</italic>, 
   <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>, 
   <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
   <italic>Shigella flexneri</italic>, 
   <italic>and Escherichia coli.</italic> Among these, the most susceptible organisms were 
   <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (21 mm) and 
   <italic>Salmonella typhi</italic> (19 mm) in the ethanolic extract. Also, the methanolic extract showed an inhibition zone of 13 mm against 
   <italic>E. coli</italic>, which was more than that of the antibiotic’s (11 mm). Phytochemical screening of the plant revealed that it contains alkaloids, phenols, steroids, and flavonoids, but lacks saponins and tannins.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par3">To combat the rising threat of antibiotic resistance, ethnoscience needs to be consolidated with modern biotechnological techniques to make the most use of the vast amount of natural resources. The findings of this study indicate that 
   <italic>Heptapleurum hypoleucum</italic>, an ethnobotanical medicinal plant, has shown comparable antimicrobial activity with commercial antibiotics against several diarrhea-causing pathogens and also contains several medically important phytochemicals.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
