<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> is the most frequent fungal pathogen present in commensalism with bacteria. Furthermore, there is incremental progress in the dual-species biofilms formation between common bacterial species and 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> that usually interact in human beings to cause infection. These kinds of interaction which lead to diseases are studied and concluded based on observational studies, arising mainly in immunocompromised patients. It is difficult to establish a clinical prognosis of polymicrobial interaction from immunocompromised individuals as they are highly vulnerable to other infections. Hence, it is tough to evaluate the degree of polymicrobial interactions and molecular mechanisms from such studies. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> studies suggest that bacterial species and 
 <italic>Candida spp.</italic> isolated from different parts, like the vagina, oral cavity, etc., interact with each other in different ways. This includes exudation of signaling molecules which influences species behavior toward each other, physical interaction between microbial cells (e.g., hyphal cells provides an attachment site to bacterial cells contained within polymicrobial biofilms), biochemical alterations of the local environment like change in oxygen content and pH. For instance, in the case of the vaginal microbiota, 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> interacts with Lactobacillus species which produces lactic acid that changes local pH, thus hindering C. 
 <italic>albicans</italic> growth on the mucosal surface of the vagina. Some hyphal cell wall proteins (E.g., Hwp1), transcription regulators (Tec1 and Bcr1, Efg1, Cph1, etc.) and adhesive proteins (E.g., Als1, Als2, and Als3) show a pivotal role in enhancing the expression of virulent genes and hence the resistance in bacterial species such as 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Streptococcus gordonii</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Harriott and Noverr, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr">Pammi et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Chinnici et al., 2019</xref>). However, deletion or mutation of these proteins results in a decrease in the number of bacterial cells and weakens their interaction with 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>. Although biofilms are formed in an oxygen-rich environment, some anaerobic bacteria can easily grow under 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilms. These biofilms provide bacteria with a positive anaerobic environment to grow. In return, the bacteria augments the formation of 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> “mini biofilms” which can easily float and grow under the toxic condition (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Douglas, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Finkel and Mitchell, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Gulati and Nobile, 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Alim et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
