<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <sec>
  <title>Context</title>
  <p> Diabetes mellitus increases the risk of bone diseases including osteoporosis and osteoarthritis. We have previously demonstrated that 
   <italic>Ficus deltoidea</italic> Jack (Moraceae) is capable of reducing hyperglycaemia. However, whether 
   <italic>F. deltoidea</italic> could protect against diabetic osteoporosis remains to be determined.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Objective</title>
  <p> The study examines the effect of 
   <italic>F. deltoidea</italic> on bone histomorphometric parameters, oxidative stress, and turnover markers in diabetic rats.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Materials and methods</title>
  <p> Streptozotocin (STZ)-induced diabetic Sprague-Dawley rats (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6 animals per group) received one of the following treatments via gavage for 8 weeks: saline (diabetic control), metformin (1000 mg/kg bwt), and methanol leaves extract of 
   <italic>F. deltoidea</italic> (1000 mg/kg bwt). A group of healthy rats served as normal control. The femoral bones were excised and scanned 
   <italic>ex vivo</italic> using micro-computed tomography (micro-CT) for histomorphometric analysis. The serum levels of insulin, oxidative stress, and bone turnover markers were determined by ELISA assays.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p> Treatment of diabetic rats with 
   <italic>F. deltoidea</italic> could significantly increase bone mineral density (BMD) (from 526.98 ± 11.87 to 637.74 ± 3.90). Higher levels of insulin (2.41 ± 0.08 vs. 1.58 ± 0.16), osteocalcin (155.66 ± 4.11 vs. 14.35 ± 0.97), and total bone n-3 PUFA (2.34 ± 0.47 vs. 1.44 ± 0.18) in parallel with the presence of chondrocyte hypertrophy were also observed following 
   <italic>F. deltoidea</italic> treatment compared to diabetic control.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>
   <italic>F. deltoidea</italic> could prevent diabetic osteoporosis by enhancing osteogenesis and inhibiting bone oxidative stress. These findings support the potential use of 
   <italic>F. deltoidea</italic> for osteoporosis therapy in diabetes.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
