<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Studies have shown that pseudoginsenoside-F11 (PF11) in PQR may be a potential drug candidate for the prevention and treatment of neurologic disorders caused by methamphetamine (MA) abuse. PF11 could significantly shorten the resting time of mice induced by MA, (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) and significantly shorten the incubation period of MA, (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) antagonize the decrease of dopamine (DA), 3,4-dihydroxyphenylacetic acid (DOPAC), homovanillic acid (HVA) and 5-hydroxyindoleacetic acid (5-HIAA) induced by MA (
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2003</xref>). In addition, PF11 can inhibit methamphetamine induced hyperactivity, preference and the increase of extracellular DA by regulating GABA neurons and opioid receptors. It has effective neuroprotection, promotes learning and memory, and antagonizes the pharmacological effects of morphine (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Fu et al., 2016</xref>). Wang et al. showed that PF11 in PQR could significantly improve the motor ability, motor balance and coordination ability of Parkinson rats. PF11 could also increase the expression of tyrosine hydroxylase (TH) in substantia nigra and the content of extracellular DA in striatum, decrease the levels of extracellular hydroxyl radical (∙OH), 2,3 - and 2,5-dihydroxybenzoic acid (2,3 - and 2,5-DHBA), and increase the level of extracellular ascorbic acid (AA) (
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr">Wang J. Y. et al., 2013</xref>). Other studies have shown that PF11 could significantly inhibit the expression of amyloid protein (APP) and Aβ 1-42 in the cortex and hippocampus, restore the activities of superoxide dismutase (SOD) and glutathione peroxidase (GSH-PX), and reduce the generation of malondialdehyde (MDA) in the cortex. And the expressions of JNK2, p53, and cleaved caspase 3 in the hippocampus were down-regulated by PF11. These results suggest that PF11 may be a potential drug for the treatment of AD (
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">Wanget al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
