<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec0020" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Primary cell culture</div>
 <p id="par0025" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All reagents should be used at room temperature (
  <a rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0005">Fig. 1</a>). Vortex the conical vial containing cells for approximately 15 s at the highest speed (speed 10 using a VWR Mini Vortexer VM3000) to assist is disrupting the mucus that was collected with the cells. Centrifuge the cells 5000 rpm for 5 min. Remove the supernatant and discard. Add 10.0 mL fresh supplemented PBS. Repeat the vortex/wash 2X. After the final wash, remove as much PBS as possible without disrupting the pellet of cells in the bottom of the tube.
  <div id="fig0005" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Collection of epithelial cells for primary culture. Fish were removed from home tanks and place in ∼1500 mL of water containing 400 uL of oil of cloves solution (
     <a rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0005">Fig. 1</a>A, B). After a light plane of anethesia was induced, epithelial cells were removed from the fish with a clean scalpel (
     <a rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0005">Fig. 1</a>C) and placed into a 15 mL polypropelene vial containing supplemented PBS (
     <a rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0005">Fig. 1</a>D, E).
    </p>
   </div>
   <span id="at0120" class="alt-text">Fig. 1</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="par0030" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Resuspend the final pellet in 6.0 mL Leibovitz's L-15 culture medium supplemented with 20% fetal bovine serum, 1.5% penicillin/streptavidin and 1.% Fungizone, 1.5% kanamycin and 1.5% tetracycline (this solution will be referred to as supplemented Leibovitz's). Leibovitz's medium was selected for cell culture because it is CO
  <sub>2</sub> independent; thus, cells require no O
  <sub>2</sub> or CO
  <sub>2</sub> supplementation. This media also maintains physiological pH through salts, high concentration of basic amino acids and galactose. and vortex. If scales are evident in the tube, allow the tube to stand vertically for 15 s—the scales will settle to the bottom. Avoiding the scales if present, remove the media/cell solution from the conical vial with a sterile Pasteur pipet and transfer to a sterile T25 flask with a vented cap (Corning).
 </p>
 <p id="par0035" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Culture T25 flasks at room temperature on a clean lab bench. In 24 h, pellet the cell suspensions at 5000 rpm for 5 min. The supernatant (containing culture media and cellular products) should immediately be stored at −20C in a 15.0 mL polypropylene conical vial for use in behavioral assays.</p>
 <p id="par0040" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Add 10.0 mL of supplemented PBS to the pellet and vortex for 10 s at max speed to resuspend. Centrifuge the cells 5000 rpm for 5 min. Remove the supernatant and discard. Add 10.0 mL fresh supplemented PBS. Repeat the vortex/wash 2X. After the final wash, remove as much PBS as possible without disrupting the pellet of cells in the bottom of the tube. After the third wash, resuspend cells in 6.0 mL supplemented Leibovitz's.</p>
 <p id="par0045" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maintain primary cell culture and harvest media every 24 h for a maximum of 5 days.</p>
 <p id="par0050" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For use in behavioral assays, thaw frozen media in conical vials on ice. Warm the vial to room temperature with hands just prior to use.</p>
</sec>
