<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">Aspergillus fumigatus</named-content> is a common plant waste-degrading fungus, of which spores are abundantly present in the air. When inhaled, these spores can cause diseases in animals and humans, ranging from allergic syndromes to acute invasive aspergillosis depending on the host immune system (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). The number of drug classes that are available for the treatment of 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> diseases remains very limited, with the azoles representing the major class. Azole resistance is an emerging concern in 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content>, complicating the treatment of patients. Recent cohort studies indicate a 20% lower survival in patients with culture-positive voriconazole-resistant invasive aspergillosis than in patients with azole-susceptible infection (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Up to 90% of 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content> isolates recovered from patients with azole-resistant invasive aspergillosis exhibit resistance mutations that are associated with resistance selection in the environment (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). These resistance mutations, e.g., TR
 <sub>34</sub>/L98H and TR
 <sub>46</sub>/Y121F/T289A, are believed to be selected through exposure to azole fungicides in the environment (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Cross-resistance is commonly observed, and several azole fungicides have similar chemical structure as medical azoles (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Furthermore, new resistance mutations continue to emerge in the environment (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), indicating that the diversity and frequency of resistance mutations in 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">A. fumigatus</named-content> are currently undersampled and are likely to continue to increase. Thus, exploring the potential and effectiveness of interventions in the environment is critical to reduce the resistance burden and safeguard the use of azoles for treating 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> diseases. However, such interventions have to be informed by a better understanding of the dynamics of resistance selection in the environment (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).
</p>
