<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>From non-native areas, we sampled individuals of P. glandulosa, 
 <italic>P. pallida</italic>, 
 <italic>P. velutina</italic> and putative hybrids from Australia, 
 <italic>P. pallida</italic> from Hawaii and various 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> species and putative hybrids from South Africa that could not be identified to species level (hereafter referred to only as 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> spp.). From Eastern Africa, we included areas where 
 <italic>P. juliflora</italic> and 
 <italic>P. pallida</italic> individuals were first introduced; we sampled 
 <italic>P. juliflora</italic> from the Afar Region, Ethiopia, 
 <italic>P. juliflora</italic> and 
 <italic>P. pallida</italic> from Baringo County, Mombasa and Taveta, Kenya, and 
 <italic>P. juliflora</italic> from Mombo and Tanga arboreta, Tanzania. All sampled species belong to the sections Algarobia and Strombocarpa, and from the section Algarobia, the species belong to the series Chilenses, Pallidae and Ruscifoliae (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). One to 35 sampling sites were included per country for each species and 1–474 adult trees were sampled per species per country (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>; 
 <italic>n</italic>
 <sub>total</sub> = 1107 individuals). This uneven sampling reflects the availability of individuals at each location, i.e. areas where only one tree was located versus areas with dense invasive populations. We sampled trees that were separated by at least 30 m to avoid collecting genetically related material (
 <xref rid="CIT0504" ref-type="bibr">Vilardi 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 1988
 </xref>). In the case of Kenya, Ethiopia and Tanzania, some sampled trees were separated by less than 30 m. Throughout this manuscript we use the term ‘population’ to refer to a group of individuals of the same species that were sampled in a specific native or non-native area in each country. Leaf material was air-dried and stored on silica gel until further use for DNA extraction. Because 
 <italic>P. juliflora</italic> is the only polyploid member of the genus (2
 <italic>n</italic> = 4
 <italic>x</italic>), we performed flow cytometry analysis on a subset of 
 <italic>P. juliflora</italic> individuals (
 <italic>n</italic> = 75). Further details on DNA extraction, morphological classification of individuals and flow cytometry analyses are provided in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">
  <bold>Supporting Information—Appendix S1</bold>
 </xref>.
</p>
