<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par76">UFAs are the main components of plant cell membrane lipids and storage lipids, which play important roles in physiological functions. In most plants, UFAs account for more than 75% of the total fatty acids [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. In this study, there were more than 95% UFAs, especially 70% PUFAs in herbaceous peony seed oil (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). The first double bond is introduced by the soluble enzyme stearoyl-ACP desaturase (SAD), which catalyzes the desaturation of C18:0-ACP to form C18:1-ACP. There are subsequently two pathways of desaturation by fatty acid desaturases (FADs). In one pathway, C18:1-ACP is successively transformed to C18:2-ACP and C18:3-ACP in plastid by FAD6 and FAD7 or FAD8, respectively. In another pathway, C18:1-ACP undergoes a series of enzymatic reactions to produce C18:1-PC, which is desaturated by FAD2 and FAD3 in the endoplasmic reticulum to form C18:2-PC and C-18:3 PC. SAD controls the total amount of UFAs in plant oils and the ratio of saturated fatty acid to UFA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. The content of SA in the 
 <italic>SAD</italic> mutant was found to increase from 0.8 to 14.3% compared with wild-type 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, accompanied by a decrease in OA content [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. In contrast, upon overexpression of 
 <italic>SAD</italic> in 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, the SA content decreased and OA content increased [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. The expression of 
 <italic>SAD</italic> was higher in seeds than in other tissues, and the expression of 
 <italic>SAD</italic> was bell-shaped with seed development [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. FADs are all intact membrane proteins, including FAD2, FAD3, FAD6, FAD7 and FAD8, and they catalyze the desaturation of C18 fatty acids. FAD2/FAD6 catalyze the dehydrogenation of OA at the Δ12 position to form LA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>], and LA to form ALA by Δ15 fatty acid dehydrogenase including FAD3, FAD7 and FAD8 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. In this process, FADs play a key role in the formation of ALA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. FAD2 is a key enzyme that controls the transformation of OA to LA. By inducing the mutation of 
 <italic>FAD2</italic> or inhibiting its expression by antisense methodologies, the content of OA in soybean [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>], sunflower [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>] and peanut [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>] seed oil can be improved, thus improving the quality of edible oil. The 
 <italic>FAD3</italic> gene is semidominant, and its overexpression leads to a decrease in LA and an increase in ALA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. In this study, we identified 6, 9, 5, 2 and 2 DEGs annotated to 
 <italic>SAD</italic>, 
 <italic>FAD2</italic>, 
 <italic>FAD3</italic>, 
 <italic>FAD7</italic> and 
 <italic>FAD8</italic>, respectively. The FPKM values of those DEGs at 90 DAF were mostly less than 1, which indicated that the absolute contents of unsaturated fatty acid in herbaceous peony seed oil showed a downward trend at the later stage. Although most of the FPKM values of 
 <italic>SAD</italic>, 
 <italic>FAD2</italic> and 
 <italic>FAD3</italic> based on the transcriptome sequencing showed a decreasing trend with seed development, their expression levels were highest at 45 DAF by qRT-PCR analysis and exhibited a bell shape with seed development (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>), consistent with the rate of unsaturated fatty acid accumulation (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). Moreover, the FPKM values of 
 <italic>FAD7</italic> and 
 <italic>FAD8</italic> were more lower than that of 
 <italic>FAD3</italic>. Therefore, we inferred that the key genes in herbaceous peony seed oil with high contents of unsaturated fatty acids, such as ALA and LA, are 
 <italic>SAD</italic>, 
 <italic>FAD2</italic> and 
 <italic>FAD3</italic>.
</p>
