<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par77">Most fatty acids in plants are successively transferred to the 
 <italic>sn-1</italic>, 
 <italic>sn-2</italic> and 
 <italic>sn-3</italic> position of glycerol-3-phosphate to form TAG, which is assembled in the endoplasmic reticulum through the Kennedy pathway, and finally formed into an oil body by budding for storage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. TAG assembly mainly involves enzymes including GPAT, LPAAT, PAP and DGAT [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. DGAT catalyzes the final step of TAG assembly in the Kennedy pathway, and it is the only rate-limiting enzyme in this pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. The expression of single 
 <italic>DGAT</italic> can restore the accumulation of TAG and the formation of OBs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Four different types of 
 <italic>DGATs</italic> were found in plants, namely, 
 <italic>DGAT1</italic>, 
 <italic>DGAT2</italic>, 
 <italic>DGAT3</italic> and 
 <italic>WS/DGAT</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. Organ expression of 
 <italic>DGAT</italic> is specific. 
 <italic>DGAT1</italic> is highly expressed in developing seeds, petals, and flower buds of most dicotyledonous plants, but it is poorly expressed in leaves and stems [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]. In this study, there was only 1 DEG annotated to 
 <italic>DGAT</italic>, the FPKM value of which showed a continuous upward trend and expression by qRT-PCR was highest at 75 DAF, which was consistent with the highest oil content at 75 DAF. TAGs are the most abundant neutral lipids, and most TAGs are partitioned in small spherical particles called oil bodies (OBs) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. OBs contain a hydrophobic core of TAG surrounded by a monolayer of phospholipids and unique proteins called oleosin (OLE), caleosin and steroleosin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. Among these proteins, OLE is the main protein and covers almost the whole surface of OBs, accounting for approximately 75–80% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. OLE plays an important role in maintaining the size and stability of the oil body [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. In addition, Siloto et al. found that the expression level of 
 <italic>OLE</italic> in 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seeds with high oil content was higher than that in seeds with low oil content [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. The expression of 
 <italic>OLE</italic> is higher in seeds than in roots, stems, leaves and flowers. Additionally, with the development of seeds, the expression of 
 <italic>OLE</italic> in seeds first increases and then decreases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]. In the present study, we identified 6 DEGs annotated to 
 <italic>OLE</italic>, the FPKM values of which in the transcriptome were very high and increasing; however, the expression of 
 <italic>OLE</italic> by qRT-PCR was highest at 75 DAF, which was consistent with the oil accumulation. Similarly, the trend of 
 <italic>OLE</italic> expression in developmental seeds was consistent with other studies. Therefore, we speculated that high oil accumulation in herbaceous peony seed was related to the high expression levels of 
 <italic>DGAT</italic> and 
 <italic>OLE</italic>.
</p>
