<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Not many authors assessed the positive impacts of 
 <italic>Boswellia</italic> species on elevated BP which is an important component of the metabolic syndrome. Recent studies have introduced some mechanisms of actions concerning 
 <italic>B.</italic>
 <italic>serrata</italic> gum resin on cardiac health. There is enough knowledge of the relationship between oxidative stresses, inflammation, and thrombosis resulting in cardiovascular diseases (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Hence, the anti-oxidant and antithrombotic characteristics of 
 <italic>B.</italic>
 <italic>serrata</italic> gum resin were examined. Enriching 
 <italic>B.</italic>
 <italic>serrata</italic> gum resin with triterpenoids showed their anti-oxidant activities based on the respective chemical compositions (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). The experiments of the anti-oxidant activities of 
 <italic>B.</italic>
 <italic>serrata</italic> gum resin suggested antilipid per-oxidation actions in the liver and heart. Researchers studied the phytochemical ingredients of the crude extract of 
 <italic>B.</italic>
 <italic>serrata</italic> and demonstrated that it consists of essential oils, resin, and gum. Boswellic acid, a pentacyclic triterpene, has been recognized as an active moiety of the resin portion (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Primary phytochemical studies showed the existence of flavonoid and saponin in 
 <italic>B.</italic>
 <italic>serrata</italic> Previous observations showed that several compounds, such as flavonoids, saponins, or organic acids might contribute to the herb diuretic impacts (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). Likewise, some authors revealed that specific flavonoids induce diuretic activities by attaching with adenosine A1 receptors related to the diuretic actions (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Since 
 <italic>B.</italic>
 <italic>serrata</italic> has a lot of saponins and flavonoids, the diuretic activities of the herb understudy might result from these mechanisms. It has been indicated that sodium is a prominent external agent that plays a role in primary HTN (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Several research projects demonstrated the adverse effects of higher uptake of sodium adversely on the arterial BP (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). The higher excretion of urinary sodium in the present experimental animals revealed the antihypertensive activity of the 
 <italic>B.</italic>
 <italic>serrata</italic> (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).
</p>
