<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32" class="p">The method for protein extraction was adopted from Hamilton and colleagues
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" class="xref">88</xref>
 </sup> and detailed in Musundire and colleagues
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" class="xref">89</xref>
 </sup> Briefly, the BSFL samples were separately snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen and crushed into fine powder. The samples (2 g each) were extracted for 1 hour in ice cold 5 v/w 100 mM 4-(2-hydroxyethyl)-1-piperazineethanesulfonic acid (HEPES) pH 7.2, 2 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), 2.5% Polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP), 0.5 mM Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA), 1 mM benzamidine 0.1 mM phenylmethanesulfonylfluoride (PMSF) in a magnetic stirrer. The samples were filtered through KERLIX™ Gauze Bandage Rolls Sterile Soft Pouch 5.7 × 2.7 cm centrifuged at 8,000 rpm for 30 min at 4 °C to remove solid debris. Protein was precipitated between 45% and 80% (NH4)2SO4 and the pellet recovered by centrifugation at 21,000 rpm for 30 min at 4 °C. The protein pellets were desalted in 20 mM HEPES–NaOH pH 8 containing 2mMDTT using Sephadex G-25 gel filtration chromatography (PD-10 columns, GE Healthcare, Chicago, USA) to give 80.2 mg and 77.9 mg of proteins from processed and unprocessed insect samples, respectively. Ten (10) mg from each of the samples were separately transferred into a 5 ml micro-reaction vial into which 2 ml of 6 N HCl were added and closed after careful introduction of nitrogen gas. The samples were hydrolyzed for 24 hours at 110 °C. For tryptophan analysis, 10 mg from each of the samples were separately transferred into a 5 ml micro-reaction vial into which 2 ml of 6 N NaOH were added and then capped after careful introduction of nitrogen gas. The samples were hydrolyzed for 24 hours at 110 °C. After the hydrolysis, the mixtures were evaporated to dryness under vacuum. The hydrolysates were reconstituted in 1 ml 90:10 water: acetonitrile, vortexed for 30 s, sonicated for 30 min, and then centrifuged at 14,000 rpm and the supernatant analyzed using a liquid chromatography quadrupole time-of-flight mass spectrometry (LC-Qtof-MS) (Waters Corporation, Milford, USA). The analysis was replicated three times.
</p>
