<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For AOM, zero-valent sulfur was detected within ANME cells, the methane-oxidizing archaeal partners of sulfate-reducing bacteria (
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Milucka et al., 2012</xref>). The authors of the study hypothesized that the studied ANME, which belong to the ANME-2 cluster, might reduce sulfate to zero-valent sulfur, which is then disproportionated to sulfate and sulfide by bacterial partners, implying that ANME, who lack key enzymes of the classical dissimilatory sulfate reduction pathway (
 <xref rid="B203" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Timmers et al., 2017</xref>) use a different sulfate activation mechanism (
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Milucka et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B139" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). It has been shown that methane oxidation by ANME can be decoupled from sulfate reduction (
 <xref rid="B182" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Scheller et al., 2016</xref>), indicating that ANME are not responsible for sulfate reduction. Nevertheless, the observation that zero-valent sulfur was detected within ANME cells remains valid and is further corroborated by the finding of zero-valent sulfur with AOM biomass in a two stage high-pressure continuous incubation experimental system (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Deusner et al., 2014</xref>). Bacteria that disproportionate native sulfur have been identified in sediment-free, long-term AOM enrichments of cultures that were obtained from coastal hydrocarbon seeps from Elba Island, Italy, from hot vents of the Guaymas Basin, Gulf of California, and methane seeps in the vicinity of the Gullfaks oil field in the North Sea (
 <xref rid="B215" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wegener et al., 2016</xref>). These sulfur-disproportionating bacteria likely persisted because native sulfur was available, either due to oxidation of sulfide by O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> introduced during cultivation, or from the ANME (
 <xref rid="B215" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wegener et al., 2016</xref>). Sulfur-disproportionating bacteria also appear to be present in oxygen-free environments, such as cold seeps, with active AOM (e.g., 
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lloyd et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Niemann et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Orcutt et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B177" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ruff et al., 2015</xref>) with unknown sources of native sulfur. These findings are intriguing since AOM most likely plays a role in the formation of a suite of native sulfur deposits, evidenced by (1) the very light carbon isotope signatures of authigenic carbonates (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" class="xref">4</xref>) and (2) presence of archaeal lipids in native sulfur containing limestones from Sicily that are similar – but not identical – to lipids of ANMEs from marine methane seeps (
 <xref rid="B231" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ziegenbalg et al., 2012</xref>).
</p>
