<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The gastric mucosa maintains its function and structure through a balance between aggressive and protective factors [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Increased levels of aggressive ulcerogens result in the overproduction of ROS, such as superoxide anions, hydroxyl radicals, and hydrogen peroxide, and the depletion of protective factors, such as antioxidants (SOD, CAT, GSH, etc.), causing gastric mucosal erosion and ulcers [
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In rat gastric tissue, SOD and CAT activities and GSH levels decrease by one-third to one-half after HCl/ethanol administration, compared with normal rats, and inhibition of this decrease exerts gastroprotective effects [
 <xref rid="B38-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. SOD converts superoxide radicals into hydrogen peroxide and CAT converts hydrogen peroxide to water and oxygen [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. GSH reacts non-enzymatically with superoxide, nitric oxide, hydroxyl radical, and peroxynitrite and functions as an ROS scavenger and a cofactor for GSH peroxidase in the neutralization of hydrogen peroxide [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. MDA is produced by the peroxidation of cell membrane lipids and is widely utilized as an oxidative stress marker [
 <xref rid="B42-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Herein, IFE significantly increased SOD and CAT activities and GSH levels and decreased MDA levels in ulcerated gastric tissues. In support of our results, 
 <italic>I. britannica</italic> reportedly increases the levels antioxidant enzymes and exhibits free radical scavenging activity, and these effects are related to flavonoid components [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. 
 <italic>I. britannica</italic> extract and its flavonoid fractions enhance SOD and CAT activities and decrease MDA levels in the skin and liver tissues of rats [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In addition, several flavonoid compounds in 
 <italic>I. britannica</italic> reportedly increase CAT activity and GSH levels in rat cortical cells [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Butanol fractions and flavonoid compounds from 
 <italic>I. britannica</italic> show free-radical scavenging activity [
 <xref rid="B43-molecules-25-05623" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Along with these previous studies, our results indicate that IFE exerts gastroprotective effects by reducing oxidative stress.
</p>
