<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The melting behaviour and the crystallization of the composites were studied by differential scanning calorimetry (DSC) on a differential scanning calorimeter (DSC 1 STARe System, Mettler Toledo, Columbus, OH, USA). Samples of the films at the approximate weight of 5 mg each were placed in aluminium pans. Nitrogen flow was set to 50 mL/min., and the following heating program was applied: an initial heating cycle from 25 °C to 200 °C (10 °C/min), maintaining the same for 2 min, and subsequent cooling to −50 °C (20 °C/min); this temperature was maintained for 2 min prior to conducting another heating scan to 200 °C. The melting temperature (T
 <sub>m</sub>) and the exothermal response relating to cold crystallization (T
 <sub>c</sub>) were obtained from the second heating cycle. The degree of crystallinity (
 <italic>X
  <sub>C</sub>
 </italic>) was calculated from the value for specific enthalpy of melting (Δ
 <italic>H
  <sub>f</sub>
 </italic>), as determined from the area under the melting peak in the second scan, applying the theoretical enthalpy of melting for 100% crystalline PP (209 J/g); see Equation (1) below [
 <xref rid="B26-polymers-13-00906" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-polymers-13-00906" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-polymers-13-00906" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. 
 <disp-formula id="FD1-polymers-13-00906">
  <label>(1)</label>
  <math id="mm1">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <msub>
      <mi>X</mi>
      <mi>C</mi>
     </msub>
     <mrow>
      <mo>(</mo>
      <mo>%</mo>
      <mo>)</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mfrac>
      <mrow>
       <mo>Δ</mo>
       <msub>
        <mi>H</mi>
        <mi>f</mi>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mo>Δ</mo>
       <mi>H</mi>
       <msub>
        <mo>°</mo>
        <mi>f</mi>
       </msub>
       <mo>×</mo>
       <mi>W</mi>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
     <mo>×</mo>
     <mn>100</mn>
     <mo>,</mo>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where Δ
 <italic>H°
  <sub>f</sub>
 </italic> is the theoretical enthalpy of melting for 100% crystalline PP, and 
 <italic>W</italic> is the weight fraction of PP in the composite.
</p>
