<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our aims were to determine whether the invasive earthworm 
 <italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic> and leaf litter of 
 <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> might influence native plant abundance, performance and physiology. We focussed on a common herbaceous plant: 
 <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> (Berberidaceae). We selected native species 
 <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> because it is common in the northeastern USA and co-occurs with the two invaders 
 <italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic> and 
 <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>. In addition, 
 <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> associates with AMF (
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Soudzilovskaia 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2020
 </xref>), making it a potential candidate for indirect effects (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). First, we utilized a large-scale observational dataset to determine if native 
 <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> abundance correlates with invader abundance in the field. Because nutrient availability in the soil influences plant physiology, we explored whether soil nutrients and invaders might interact to influence 
 <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> abundance. Second, we conducted a factorial experiment to determine effects of these two invaders on 
 <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> growth and physiology. We predicted that 
 <italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic> might increase the exposure of 
 <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> to allelochemicals produced by 
 <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>, resulting in greater suppression of native plant biomass in the presence of both invaders (super-additive effect). If the interaction between the invasive plant and earthworm is mediated by allelochemicals in the soil, we predict the interaction will be stronger in the absence of activated carbon, which binds allelochemicals (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, arrow 5). An interaction only in the presence of activated carbon would be more consistent with nutrient-mediated effects (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, arrow 4). Alternatively, 
 <italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic> might enhance nutrient availability for 
 <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic>, leading to greater plant resistance to allelochemicals produced by 
 <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (sub-additive effect). If this is the case, we predict that 
 <italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic> might enhance plant access to soil nitrogen, increasing the ability of the native plant to fix carbon (greater Ci and greater Amax in the presence of 
 <italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic>).
</p>
