<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3-1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Chemical composition of the essential oil</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> The results of GC-MS analyses of Tagetes oil is reported in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a> for the first time from Northern Iran. The volatile oil (orange-yellow color) obtained by hydrodistillation method of the aerial parts of 
  <span class="italic">Tagetes minuta</span> showed an average yield of 0.77% (according to dry material weight). The different chemical constituents of the plant were identified and listed in order of their increasing retention times on the HP-5MS column. A total of twenty- four chemical compounds were separated and detected, representing 92.32% of the total oil. Most of the volatile compounds analyzed during this work contain mainly 9 monoterpenes (52.13%) and 15 sesquiterpenes (40.19%).The oil profile exhibits dihydrotagetone (23.44%) as the most abundant compound. The other main compounds were spathulenol (10.56%), caryophyllene oxide (6.35%), alpha-atlantone (4.76%) and isoaromadendrene epoxide (3.11%), respectively. In fact, the essential oil tested was rich in monoterpenoids. The oil of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> L. has been evaluated in some parts of the country by a number of investigators who have recognized α-terpineol (20.8%), β-ocimene (17.6%)
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">6</a>
  </span> and dihydrotageton (45.9%), trans-ocimenone (27.0%), cis-
  <span class="italic">β</span>-ocimene (11.9%)
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">8</a>
  </span> and limonene (13.0%), piperitenone (12.2%), α-terpinolene (11.0%)
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">7</a>
  </span> as the major components in this species. A review and analysis of the literature revealed that no oil of any 
  <span class="italic">Tagetes minuta</span> has been found in which spathulenol and caryophyllene oxide were the main ingredients so its identification of potential significance in Iran. Also according to the Articles, no isoaromadendrene epoxide and neophytadiene were reported of the oil. On the other hand, the main chemical substance essential oil obtained from Tagetes oil in England was dihydrotagetone (54.1%).
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">10</a>
  </span> As high amount of dihydrotagetone found in the oil our plant (23.44%). The main constituents identified in another studies in South Africa and Saudi Arabia were cis-
  <span class="italic">β</span>-ocimene and 5 octyn-4-one 2,7-dimethyl (50.9%, 11.52% respectively).
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">9</a>,
   <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">10</a>
  </span> On comparison to this reports, the findings of our study indicated the diversity of volatile terpenes and their percentage which can be attributed to ecological, climatic and genetically factors. Here it is worth noting that despite this variations, the main constituents of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> oil growing wild in north of Iran are oxygenated monoterpenoids (41.75%) that can be a valuable for further research especially medicinal properties.
 </p>
</sec>
