<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3-4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Determination of total polyphenols and flavonoid contents</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> The Folin–Ciocalteu reagent is widely used for the colorimetric in vitro assay of polyphenolic antioxidants. Plant phenolics constitute a large group of secondary metabolites which act as primary antioxidants.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">29</a>
  </span> As shown in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T4" href="#T4">Table 4</a>, total phenolic contents in the oil of 
  <span class="italic">T.minuta</span> was 153.27±0.9 mg GAE
  <span class="italic">/</span>g dry plant sample. Lower total phenolic contents were found in the methanol extract of the plant (34.17±0.6 mg GAE/g dry extract). In the past years a study performed by Ranilla et al. on selected leaves showed 67±7 0.6 mg GAE/g of phenolic compounds in the dry weight of the extracts (methanolic) of 
  <span class="italic">Tagetes minuta</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">28</a>
  </span> Our results seem to be consistent with other research which found 
  <span class="italic">Tagetes minuta</span> is rich of phenolic acids and can be considered as a invaluable source of natural antioxidants.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> In terms of TFC, the oil of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> (63.79±0.1 mg/g, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05) was richer in flavonoids, than the extract (14.86±0.4 mg/g, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05) (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T4" href="#T4">Table 4</a>). Previously, Kaisoon et al. discovered that the flowers of this genus had 68.9 mg/g of flavonoid content.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">30</a>
  </span> Flavonoids are a large family of plant polyphenolics that act as free-radical scavengers and the biological function is related to their chemical structure (hydroxyl groups).
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">31</a>
  </span>
 </p>
</sec>
