<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0330">Guaiacane sesquiterpenes are isolated and identified earlier from AR, and they belong to azulene derivatives, an aromatic skeleton compound composed of five and seven-membered rings. 
 <xref rid="bib110" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. (2008)</xref> obtained sesquiterpenes (
 <bold>1–5</bold>) from 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic>, and confirmed that the compounds have no cytotoxic activity on P388 and A549 cells through cytotoxic experiments. 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Kitajima et al. (2003b)</xref> isolated various water-soluble guaiacum sesquiterpenoids from the rhizomes of 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> and 
 <italic>A. japonica</italic>, and analyzed the structure of the compounds (
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> , 
 <bold>7–16</bold>). Compounds 
 <bold>13</bold> and 
 <bold>14</bold> were isolated from 
 <italic>A. japonica</italic>, and compounds 
 <bold>18–21</bold> were isolated from 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> for the first time. Pharmacological experiments showed that compounds 
 <bold>18</bold> and 
 <bold>20</bold> have no significant inhibitory effect on protein tyrosine phosphatase-like, member b (PTPLB) and β-glucosidase. 
 <xref rid="bib110" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. (2008)</xref> isolated and identified cineole sesquiterpenes from AR. 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Duan et al. (2008)</xref> analyzed the structure of compound 
 <bold>25</bold>. 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Endo and Hikino (1979)</xref> determined the absolute configuration of compounds 
 <bold>33</bold> and 
 <bold>34</bold> via circular dichroism. 
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Endo et al. (1979)</xref> isolated atractylenolide II (
 <bold>37</bold>) from 
 <italic>A. japonica</italic> for the first time and analyzed its structure. Atractylolide Ⅲ (
 <bold>38</bold>) was isolated from 
 <italic>A. Japonica</italic> for the first time by 
 <xref rid="bib131" ref-type="bibr">Yosioka et al. (1959)</xref>. And both atractylolide Ⅲ and atractylone had acaricidal activity (
 <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Meng et al., 2010</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Kitajima et al. (2003a)</xref> isolated a series of eucalyptosyl sesquiterpene glycosides from AR and analyzed the chemical structure of compounds (
 <bold>42–50</bold>), among which compounds (
 <bold>43</bold>, 
 <bold>44</bold>, 
 <bold>46</bold>) were first isolated from 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> methanol extract, as shown in 
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Compounds 
 <bold>54–64</bold> were isolated from 30% n-butanol fraction of 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> and their structures were analyzed (
 <xref rid="bib121" ref-type="bibr">Xu, 2017</xref>). At present, 14 species of spirosane sesquiterpenes (
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, 
 <bold>65–78</bold>) have been found in 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic>. Compounds 
 <bold>77</bold> and 
 <bold>78</bold> are irimophenol alkane sesquiterpenes. The triterpenoid saponins in AR are mainly tetracyclic triterpenoids, pentacyclic triterpenoids, and tetracyclic triterpenoids. Six triterpenoids (
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, 
 <bold>79–84</bold>) were isolated from 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> by 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Duan et al. (2008)</xref>, and their chemical structures were analyzed. The information of the sesquiterpenoid biosynthesis is largely unknown. 
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed et al. (2016)</xref> investigated the transcriptome of different tissues of 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic>. All the enzymes that took part in the terpenoid biosynthesis and five different known sesquiterpenoids were identified via cytosolic mevalonic acid and plastidal methylerythritol phosphate pathways. Besides, 6864 simple sequence repeats were found to be great potential markers in 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic>. Jia et al. (2016) demonstrated that endophytic bacterium-triggered ROS could directly oxidize oxygen-free sesquiterpenoids and increase the oxygenous sesquiterpenoid content and diversity in 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">Takeda et al. (1996)</xref> transplanted the rhizomes of 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic>, 
 <italic>A. chinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>A. koreana</italic> growing in China from 18 populations in the same experimental field. Main essential oil components: the sesquiterpenes and the polyacetylene of atractylodin were determined. The analytical data of 306 cultivated plants were compared with plants collected in their habitat. 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> varied significantly in the contents of the components after cultivation. Compared to this, 
 <italic>A. chinensis</italic> had constant content values. Three types of 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> and two types of 
 <italic>A. chinensis</italic>, which are distinguished by the characteristics of the components in the wild conditions, were statistically recognized after cultivation. From these results, it was determined that the geographical variation in the components of these species mainly reflects genetic variability.
</p>
