<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">TIC results showed that the five major components of the kaffir lime oil separated very well with the RTX-5 MS column, with the order of retention time, tR, retention time ie by silica gel column filler increases. TR sequences of these compounds were sabinene, L-linalool, β-citronellal, citronellol and β-sitronelyl acetate. Apart from sabinene, the four other major components contained oxygen, so it was possible to form hydrogen bonds that could result in higher boiling point. This sequence illustrated the boiling point of the compounds. The β-citronellal level that was obtained from the kaffir lime plant twigs (46.40%) was lower than the ß-citronellal level that was obtained from lime plant leaves, which reached 70.30% to 80.04% (analysis product of PT. Indesso). It means that the β-citronellal secondary metabolites stored more in leaves than in twigs. Although the quantitative component is varied, but in general the main component of lime oil is relatively the same with kaffir lime oil from other countries, such as from Johor and Selangor, Malaysia by Loh [
  <a rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit0014">14</a>], from Thailand by Srisukh, et al [
  <a rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit0015">15</a>]. Distilled kaffir lime oil fractionation at the optimum conditions showed several things, there are: (1) the highest level of β-citronellal in fraction-7 was at 84.86% (increased by 38.46%). He distilled fraction in kaffir lime oil has higher level of β-citronellal and is relatively high compared to β-citronellal that was obtained from steam distillation of kaffir lime leaves (80.04%) [
  <a rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr" href="#cit0015">15</a>]. Furthermore, L-linalool components in fraction-5 reached 20.13% (increased by 7.02%), (2) β-citronellal and L-linalool components was distributed in every fraction, which means that during the distillation process, the second component composed the majority of the steam product, (3) sabinen in fraction-1 reached the highest level of 19.83% (increased by 13,92%), it indicates that sabinen has the lowest boiling point among the major components on kaffir lime oil, (4) β-pinene, β-micren and trans-β-ocimen was very low, these components appeared to have significant level value in fraction-1 to fractions-3, although these component became weaker after fraction-4,and (5) 4-terpeneol, β-citronellol and citronelyl acetate appeared on the final fraction, i.e. the fraction-9, respectively in level of 7.16% (increased by 5.64%), 12.27% (increased by 1.24%) and 5.22%, which indicates that all of these compounds has the highest boiling point. It is due to the two components that contains the highest amount of oxygen and are able to form hydrogen bonds.
 </p>
</sec>
