<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 3.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Rupture of protein-dsDNA complexes between TRF1 and a single human telomere upon forces. (
   <bold>A</bold>) TRF1-telomere complexes rupture in force–ramp assays. At the protein concentration of [TRF1] = 10 nM, protein–dsDNA complexes repetitively rupture and form when forces oscillate between 0 and 17 pN at a loading rate of ±4 pN/s (cartoon). Force–extension traces (
   <italic>N</italic> = 10) show that rupture events occur as multiple leaps in extension and finish at a stretching force &lt;8 pN in a buffer of 20 mM of HEPES (pH 7.5), 1 mM of EDTA, 100 mM of NaCl and 0.0063% Tween-20 at 23°C. Upon relaxing, the extension of a single telomere smoothly responds to forces without distinguishable refolding steps. (
   <bold>B</bold>) Force–jump assays show the responses of a single human telomere extension to forces in real-time. The applied protocol of forces is 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>rest</sub> = 0 pN, 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>test</sub> = 2–8 pN, 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>high</sub> = 10 pN and 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>max</sub> = 20 pN. Buffer and temperature conditions are the same as those in (A). Sampling rate = 200 Hz. (
   <bold>C</bold>) Measurements of dissociation time and change in extension upon a rupture event of TRF1–telomere complexes. At the concentration of [TRF1] = 10 nM, force–jump assays reveal rupture events of TRF1-telomere complexes at 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>test</sub> after an incubation time of 120 s at 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>rest</sub> = 0 pN (cartoon). The duration between two subsequent changes in extension at 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>test</sub> indicates the dissociation time of a TRF1 from a single human telomere. 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>high</sub> and 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>max</sub> assure the complete extension of a single telomere. Buffer and temperature conditions are the same as those in (A). Sampling rate = 200 Hz. (
   <bold>D</bold>) Dissociation rates of TRF1 from a single telomere as a function of tested forces. The logarithm of the dissociation rate at tested forces (mean ± SD, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 206 from 24 molecules) follows the model of Kramer Bell-Evans (red curve and legend equation). Inset shows the averaged dissociation time 
   <inline-formula>
    <tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$( {\langle \tau \rangle } )$\end{document}</tex-math>
   </inline-formula> at 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>test</sub>. (
   <bold>E</bold>) Distribution of change in extension upon rupture events of TRF1–telomere complexes. Changes in extension (Δ
   <italic>L</italic>) were measured using telomeres with TL = 2.5–3.5 kb at [TRF1] = 10, 20 and 40 nM. Black and red curves represent Gaussian fittings.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="gkaa1222fig3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
