<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Biosurfactants are structurally complex bio-molecules where diverse metabolic pathways are involved in their biosynthesis (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Santos et al., 2016</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shaligram et al., 2016</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sun et al., 2018</xref>). For example, the bio-synthesis of lipopeptide type BS is mediated via nonribosomal peptide synthetases (NRPS). The NRPS are a kind of peptide secondary metabolites is also known in the synthesis of toxins, siderophores, pigments, antibiotics, etc. (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ansari et al., 2004</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Satpute et al., 2010c</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Song et al., 2015</xref>). Involvement of different genes and pathways ensures synthesis of various metabolites in microbes. Considerate knowledge of the genetic mechanisms involved in their biosynthesis would be helpful in expanding their economical scale of production. DNA sequencing technique is routinely used to sequence the whole genome or a region of microbial genome to reveal the pathways involved in their biosynthesis. Whole-genome sequencing (WGS) and transcriptome analysis facilitate molecular level profiling of desirable gene clusters where one can predict their transcriptional activity at any given time in the cell (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Song et al., 2015</xref>). Thus, WGS of microorganisms holds huge promise for clinical diagnosis, public health and also for understanding the production mechanisms of microbial natural products (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kamada et al., 2014</xref>). Presently, microbial genome analysis is being vigorously performed by several researchers to understand their genetics, evolution, outbreak analysis, pathogenicity and antimicrobial resistance mechanisms (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Edwards and Holt, 2013</xref>).
</p>
