<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Cytotoxicity Assay</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cytotoxic effect of essential oils was evaluated against P815 (Murine Mastocytoma, cell line), MCF7 (human breast adenocarcinoma), and VERO (kidney carcinoma cell line of monkey). The used cell lines were obtained as a gift of Professor G. Lemaire, Institute of Biochemistry, University of Paris XI, France. PBMCs were isolated using the standard Ficoll-Hypaque density gradient from samples of healthy volunteers under medical supervision. These cells were maintained and grown in special culture medium (RPMI-1640, Sigma-Aldrich, France) supplemented with 10% heat inactivated fetal calf serum (FCS) and 1% penicillin-streptomycin (Sigma-Aldrich). Cultures were maintained at 37°C in humidified 5% CO
  <sub>2</sub> incubator. The cytotoxicity assays were performed in triplicate on each cell line using the MTT [3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide] assay (Sigma-Aldrich), as described and modified by Mosmann [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>] and Mouse et al. [
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All experiments were performed with twice PBS washed cells at a density of about 1.5 × 10
  <span class="sup">4</span> cells per well (1.5 × 10
  <span class="sup">5</span> cells/ml), in flat-bottomed 96-well microtiter plates (Thermo Fisher Scientific) in 100 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>l complete medium per well. Then 100 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>l of complete culture medium containing different concentrations of the tested essential oils (dissolved in DMSO) was added to each well. After 48 h exposure of cells to these concentrations of tested essential oils at 37°C and 5% CO
  <sub>2</sub>, 100 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>l of medium was carefully aspirated from each well and replaced with 20 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>l of MTT solution (5 mg/ml of PBS). After incubation in the same conditions for 4 hours, the plates were treated with 80 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>l of an HCl/isopropanol (24 : 1) solution to dissolve the blue intracellular formazan produced by living cells. One hour later, the absorbance (optical density OD) of the plates was determined by a Multiskan EX spectrophotometer reader at two wavelengths (540 and 630 nm). DMSO (0.5%) was used as the negative control and methotrexate (MTX) as the positive one.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The viability was evaluated by the following formula:
  <div id="eq1" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">(1)</span>
   <div id="M1" class="math">
    <div style="T1" class="mtable">
     <div class="mtr">
      <div class="mtd">
       <span class="mi">%</span>
       <span class="mo"> </span>
       <span class="mo"> </span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">V</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">i</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">a</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">b</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">i</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">l</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">i</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">t</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">y</span>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div separators="|" class="mfenced">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span height="13.2pt" depth="9.55399pt" class="mspace"/>
         <div class="mfrac">
          <div class="mrow">
           <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">O</span>
           <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">D</span>
          </div>
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="msub">
            <div class="mrow">
             <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">O</span>
             <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">D</span>
            </div>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mn">0</span>
            </div>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span height="13.2pt" depth="9.55399pt" class="mspace"/>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">×</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mn">100</span>
       <span class="mo">.</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>OD is the optical density of the solution in wells containing cells treated with essential oils and OD
  <sub>0</sub> is the optical density of the solution in wells containing DMSO treated cells (negative control). The test was performed in triplicate. The IC
  <sub>50</sub> values were graphically determined using the Microsoft excel 2013 edition.
 </p>
</sec>
