<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0005">From prehistoric times medicinal plants are used for their therapeutic qualities. Plants are the paramount sources for phytochemical and chemical ingredients for treatment of different ailments (
 <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">Petrovska, 2012</xref>). Medicinal herbs are an infinite home of drug compounds with diverse biological and pharmacological activities. At present, raw extracts from these medicinal plants have been shown to pay attention to the production and preparation of alternative conventional medicines. (
 <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Pan et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">Yuan et al., 2016</xref>). Garden cress (GC) biological name 
 <italic>Lepidium sativum</italic> belonging to the 
 <italic>Cruciferae</italic> family, is a fast growing annual herb that is native to western Asia and Egypt but is extensively used for various medicinal and culinary uses worldwide (
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Doke, 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Sharma</xref>). GC has been shown to have remarkable preventive functions in various ailments such as high blood pressure, bronchitis, inflammation, arthritis, cancer, liver disorder and hyperglycemia (
 <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">KM, N, 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Sharma</xref>). The GC mucilage, also recognized as polysaccharides, is a blend of cellulose and uronic acid, (L)-rhamnose, arabinose, (D)-glucose, galactose, and galacturonic acid are the acid hydrolysis products (
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Doke, 2014</xref>). Polysaccharides are classified as carbohydrate polymeric molecules consisting long monosaccharide strings. Polysaccharides are classified as polymeric molecules of carbohydrate consisting long monosaccharides strings. Because of their unique properties they serve as key components in the growth and progress of living things (
 <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Samavati and Manoochehrizade, 2013</xref>). Polysaccharides are also reported to have anti-cancer properties (
 <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Gamal-Eldeen et al., 2009</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Thulasi et al., 2010</xref>). Several reports have suggested that polysaccharides have ability to inhibit the tumor growth via following mechanisms: the inhibition of tumorigenesis by oral active preparations, apoptosis of tumor cells, inhibition of tumor metastasis, and immunopotentiation activity in combination with anticancer therapy (
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Zong et al., 2012</xref>). Polysaccharides are heterogeneous, and depending on the composition they may have different features from their monosaccharide key components. Polysaccharides may be amorphous in liquids, or even insoluble. Their structural spectrum ranges from linear to strongly branched, including starch, cellulose, glycogen and, chitin (
 <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Cumpstey, 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Varki et al., 2009</xref>).
</p>
