<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">In this study, we evaluated antioxidant, antihyperuricemic, and herbicidal activities of essential oils (EOs) from 
  <italic class="italic">Piper cubeba</italic> Bojer and 
  <italic class="italic">Piper nigrum</italic> L.; two pepper species widely distributed in tropics, and examined their chemical compositions. Dried berries of 
  <italic class="italic">P. cubeba</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">P. nigrum</italic> were hydro-distilled to yield essential oil (EO) of 1.23 and 1.11% dry weight, respectively. In the antioxidant assay, the radical scavenging capacities of 
  <italic class="italic">P. cubeba</italic> EO against DPPH and ABTS free radicals were 28.69 and 24.13% greater than 
  <italic class="italic">P. nigrum</italic>, respectively. In the antihyperuricemic activity, 
  <italic class="italic">P. cubeba</italic> EO also exhibited stronger inhibitory effects on xanthine oxidase (IC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> = 54.87 µg/mL) than 
  <italic class="italic">P. nigrum</italic> EO (IC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> = 77.11 µg/mL). In the herbicidal activity, 
  <italic class="italic">P. cubeba</italic> EO showed greater inhibition on germination and growth of 
  <italic class="italic">Bidens pilosa</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">Echinochloa crus-galli</italic> than 
  <italic class="italic">P. nigrum</italic> EO. Besides, 
  <italic class="italic">P. cubeba</italic> EO decreased 15.98–73.00% of photosynthesis pigments of 
  <italic class="italic">B. pilosa</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">E. crus-galli</italic>, while electrolyte leakages, lipid peroxidations, prolines, phenolics, and flavonoids contents were increased 10.82–80.82% at 1.93 mg/mL dose. Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) and liquid chromatography-electrospray ionization-mass spectrometry (LC-ESI-MS) analyses revealed that 
  <italic class="italic">P. nigrum</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">P. cubeba</italic> EOs principally possessed complex mixtures of monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes. Terpinen-4-ol (42.41%), α-copaene (20.04%), and γ-elemene (17.68%) were the major components of 
  <italic class="italic">P. cubeba</italic> EO, whereas β-caryophyllene (51.12%) and β-thujene (20.58%) were the dominant components of 
  <italic class="italic">P. nigrum</italic> EO. Findings of this study suggest both 
  <italic class="italic">P. cubeba</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">P. nigrum</italic> EOs were potential to treat antioxidative stress and antihyperuricemic related diseases. In addition, the EOs of the two plants may be useful to control 
  <italic class="italic">B. pilosa</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">E. crus-galli</italic>, the two invasive and problematic weeds in agriculture practice.
 </p>
</abstract>
