<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The insect community feeding on both 
 <italic>Prunus</italic> species was sampled in Nationaal Park Zuid-Kennemerland (52°25′N, 4°35′E), a partly forested area of coastal sand dunes near Haarlem, the Netherlands. Sampling was done by traversing a 2 × 2 km area in the old, forested dunes, and haphazardly selecting 300 individuals (150 of each species). We took care that on each day, roughly equal numbers of 
 <italic>P. padus</italic> and 
 <italic>P. serotina</italic> were investigated. Where possible, individuals of the two species were sampled in alternation. Sampling was done manually (no tools like nets, beating trays, or exhausters were used) in spring and early summer of 2009 (3 days), 2010 (10 days), and 2012 (8 days), by a single person inspecting, for 5 min., leaves, twigs, flowers, and fruits up to c. 2.5 m above ground level. All insects feeding or ovipositing on the host plant were stored in 96% ethanol. To obtain measurements on the actual amount of foliage searched, we replicated the above sampling method in September 2015 on 10 and 8 trees, respectively, of 
 <italic>P. serotina</italic> and 
 <italic>P. padus</italic>, and counted the numbers of leaves and lengths of twigs searched. We also determined fresh weights of ten leaves of each of the two plant species. Insects were identified morphologically, with help from experts (see ‘Acknowledgements’). The 2009 and 2010 Geometridae and Tortricidae were identified by sequencing of the Cytochrome Oxidase I DNA-barcode region (e.g., 
 <xref rid="ref-74" ref-type="bibr">Van Nieukerken, Mutanen &amp; Doorenweerd, 2011</xref>) and the “animal identification” module in BOLD (
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.boldsystems.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.boldsystems.org</uri>). All 2009 and 2010 specimens were deposited in the collections of Naturalis Biodiversity Center (container codes BE90711–90716). Because of improper curation, the specimens from the 2012 sampling were discarded after identification. We adopted 
 <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Leather</xref>’s (
 <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">1985</xref>) host range indicators of G (generalist, feeding on multiple plant families), R (feeding on Rosaceae only), P (on 
 <italic>Prunus</italic> only), and M (monophagous, feeding on 
 <italic>P. padus</italic> only). In addition, we categorized species that are specialized on non-Rosaceae (e.g., 
 <italic>Quercus</italic>-specialists) as O (“other”). Differences in species richness for each of these categories were compared between both host species and tested for significance with a chi-square test. Natuurmonumenten (Ruud Luntz) permitted us to work in Nationaal Park Zuid-Kennemerland under permit No. 19 of 2008. Dunea (Harrie van der Hagen) permitted us to work in Meijendel by permission 25/2/2013.
</p>
