<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Microstegium vimineum</italic> is a grass species from eastern Asia that invades forest edges and disturbed habitats in the eastern half of the U.S. (Flory, Long, &amp; Clay, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Huebner, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). The species forms dense mats across the forest floor by spreading from stolons, ultimately reducing native tree seedling density, growth, and diversity (Oswalt, Oswalt, &amp; Clatterbuck, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Brewer, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0074" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>), as well as overall native plant species cover (Adams &amp; Engelhardt, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). The forest floor in invaded habitats in Maryland, often in areas with high densities of vertebrate herbivores, is generally simplified in structure, due in part to the growth habit of 
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic> (Civitello, Flory, &amp; Clay, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Landsman pers. obs.). Given its growth habit and stand density, the presence of 
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic> also alters abiotic characteristics of the near‐ground forest environment. The forest floor experiences an increase in solar irradiation within 
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic> stands, which decreases relative humidity and increases microhabitat temperatures (Civitello et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). Such climatic changes subsequently alter the ability of 
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic> patches to host invertebrate populations: 
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic> ground cover has been shown to reduce the overall diversity of soil microarthropods by greatly increasing the abundance of mites and subsequently reducing community evenness (McGrath &amp; Binkley, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). The abundance of cicadellidae planthoppers, as well as acridid and gryllid Orthoptera, was also found to be higher in 
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic> patches (Marshall &amp; Buckley, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Conversely, 
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic> can also reduce the abundance of Blattodea and chrysomelid beetles, as well as the abundance and survival of hard tick species in the Ixodidae (Civitello et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Marshall &amp; Buckley, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>).
</p>
