<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>I found no support for the role of grass competition in the second experiment. A well-supported hypothesis to explain the coexistence of trees and grasses in the same habitat is the two-layer hypothesis [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. Briefly, this hypothesis posits that grasses monopolize the upper soil layers while trees mostly use deeper water sources, even reaching as deep as the aquifer. A global meta-analysis has largely substantiated this hypothesis [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. Many earlier studies have shown that there are significant negative effects for range-expanding trees of growing with grasses, which usually outcompete the woody plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. When rain falls, it is mostly taken up by shallow-rooted grasses. Some water percolates through to reach the deeper roots of trees. When grasses are heavily grazed, most frequently by domestic livestock, this frees up water for the trees to exploit. Heavy grazing might thus facilitate niche expansion by trees such as eastern redcedars because space, nutrients and moisture are provided to woody plants, leading to a rapid increase in abundance [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref127" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. We [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>] have also found that trees may grow their roots very quickly through the root layer occupied by grasses, minimizing the time that there is competition between grasses and trees. Another experiment clearly showed that absence of grazing resulted in low survival of eastern redcedar seedlings in grasslands, indicating that competition with herbaceous plants was important [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. When grasses are removed by grazing animals, such as cattle, space is made available (and nutrients probably too) [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>], and can often be occupied by eastern redcedar. I did not examine the effects of competition for water in either of these experiments, which was provided 
 <italic>ad libitum</italic>. Fire may enhance the ability of the related redberry junipers 
 <italic>Juniperus pinchotii</italic> in the Edwards Plateau of south-central Texas to outcompete grasses if fire and droughts occurred contemporaneously [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].
</p>
