<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A possible reason for the absence of competition by grasses in the second experiment may be that the grasses were not sufficiently established to exert a competitive effect (they were planted one month prior to burning), especially by means of shading which is a common mechanism used by grasses to outcompete trees [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref129" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. The most important negative effect of grasses was through a reduction in photosynthetically active radiation (PAR) and only secondarily by plant-available soil water, as indexed by soil clay content [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. PAR has also been found to be of primary importance in grass-induced competition [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref130" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. Because the grasses used in this experiment were relatively short, they were unlikely to have had a negative effect on eastern redcedars. However, I note that evidence for competitive effects of grasses on trees is mixed. Although there was a significant negative of grass competition [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref126" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>], precipitation has been found to be far more important than grass competition [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Both nutrients and water availability have been found to affect competition by grasses on tree seedlings [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref131" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]. For example, Bermuda grass (
 <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic>) suppressed the growth of the sweet acacia tree (
 <italic>Acacia farnesiana</italic>; syn. 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>smallii</italic>) in nutrient-rich soils but not in nutrient-poor soils [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref132" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. The soils used in the second experiment were nutrient-rich, but no competitive effect of grasses or trees on eastern redcedars was observed. However, there may be little effect of herbaceous plant community diversity or composition on encroachment by eastern redcedars [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Competition for resources (i.e., nutrients) and non-resources (i.e., interference for space) could alter the effects of grasses on trees [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref133" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>]. These authors found that early-successional forest species, such as eastern redcedars, were affected by both resource competition and non-resource competition in the form of non-self competition, while late-successional species, such as the post oak studied in the first experiment, were affected by resource competition only. I found very little effect of life-form competition (i.e., tree competition by post oaks on eastern redcedars or 
 <italic>vice versa</italic>; with the exception of the aforementioned interaction between shade X lime X competition on belowground biomass of eastern redcedars) in the first experiment, even in fertilized soils.
</p>
