<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some researchers have found that niche- and range-expansion by eastern redcedar can be reduced by use of fire [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref134" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>], although it may be necessary to treat individual trees [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref135" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. In the second experiment reported on here, burned eastern redcedars were smaller after one month, were in poorer condition (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0242003.g004">Fig 4</xref>), and had lower nitrogen (but not total nonstructural carbohydrates) than unburned control trees. At least part of the reason for the negative effects of fire may be related to bark thickness. Bark thickness is known to be related to susceptibility to fire [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref136" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref139" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>]. Trees with thin bark, such as eastern redcedars, are more susceptible to fire [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. In general, tree bark gets thicker as trees grow larger [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref136" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref138" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. Thus, small trees such as those examined (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0242003.g004">Fig 4</xref>), are likely to be very susceptible to fire. The impact of the fire regime I applied was high [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. With less intense fires, it is less likely that larger, older, non-resprouting trees (such as the eastern redcedar [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]) would suffer mortality [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref126" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref138" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. Indeed, topkill (complete death of the aerial biomass) may be necessary to kill juvenile trees [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref140" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref141" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>], resulting in the ‘fire trap’ [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref142" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref144" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>] that prevents them from recruiting into the adult size classes. However, in the experiment reported on here, there was a considerable number of young trees that did not die (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0242003.g004">Fig 4</xref>).
</p>
