<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">Antibiotics are widely used as an important means of control and prevention of diseases in people's everyday lives, however, thorough or long term use of antibiotics can help strengthen tolerance against pathogenic organisms (
 <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Fonberg, 1971</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Palanisamy et al., 2019</xref>). Repeated usage of antibiotic medications can induce resistance to the microbes have sparked the search for new antimicrobials or antibiotics (
 <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Fair and Tor, 2014</xref>). Hence, natural compound with antibacterial properties have a strong potential for production as antimicrobials (
 <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Angiolella et al., 2018</xref>). Free radical disruption to the human body primarily has three components: damaging the cell membrane; inactivating the serum anti-protease; and allowing the cell mutations to develop and accumulate (
 <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Kurutas, 2016</xref>). Antioxidant is a chemical capable of slowing certain molecules down or preventing their oxidation (
 <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Kurutas, 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Phaniendra et al., 2015</xref>). Within natural circumstances the antioxidants detoxify the body's reactive oxygen species (ROS) stream. The ROS can quickly target and inflict oxidative harm to various biomolecules like proteins, lipids, lipoproteins, and DNA (
 <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">Birben et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Shahidi and Wanasundara, 1992</xref>). Oxidative disruption is a key etiological element of importance in a number of serious medical diseases such as atherosclerosis, high blood sugar, autoimmune, arthritis, and in the ageing cycle (
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Uttara et al., 2009</xref>). Considering the budding attention in oxygen radical science, and the absence of proper treatment for most chronic conditions, antioxidants are necessary to protect against such illnesses. Several research studies have shown that antioxidant intake such as vitamin C diminishes the incidence of cancer and cardiovascular complications (
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Phaniendra et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">Tan et al., 2018</xref>). The occurrence of chronic diseases may be minimized and the disease stopped either by strengthening the body's natural antioxidant defenses or by incorporating existing nutritional antioxidants (
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Ardelean et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Lobo et al., 2010</xref>). The purpose of this analysis was to investigate the yield of GC polysaccharides and to evaluate possible beneficial effects antibacterial, antioxidant and cytotoxic activity.
</p>
