<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Fat content of animal protein source in this experiment was 9.71% for fish meal, 11.09% for meat meal, 13.00% for poultry meal, and 29.5% for dried mealworm (
 <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic>) larvae. Because experimental diets were formulated with the same energy and dried mealworm (
 <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic>) larvae had the highest fat content and the lowest ash content, 
 <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic> diet had lower ground corn content and higher wheat bran content resulting in higher crude fiber content than the other three diets. This might can have an impact when designing grower feed formula and feeding the diet to grower. Although excessively high fiber content of diet limits feed intake, adequate fiber content can have a beneficial effect on the environment of large intestine. Previously studies have measured CP digestibility of some insect larvae [
 <xref rid="b19-ajas-18-0647" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="b30-ajas-18-0647" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>–
 <xref rid="b32-ajas-18-0647" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. Newton et al [
 <xref rid="b31-ajas-18-0647" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>] have reported that the apparent faecal digestibility of black soldier fly larvae in male growing pigs is 76% similar apparent CP digestibility as soybean meal. Jin et al [
 <xref rid="b19-ajas-18-0647" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] have shown that the total track digestibility of CP is linearly increased with increasing dried mealworm level. The digestibility in their studies was 92.17% (level of dried mealworm larvae included in the diet was 4.5%) or 93.04% (level of dried mealworm larvae included in the diet was 6.0%). That of our experiment is higher than that of Newton et al [
 <xref rid="b31-ajas-18-0647" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>] and lower than that of Jin et al [
 <xref rid="b19-ajas-18-0647" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. In general, the apparent total track protein digestibility is lower than the ileal digestibility due to microorganisms in the large intestine. In addition, the age of the experimental animals [
 <xref rid="b31-ajas-18-0647" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>] was 5 weeks at which the development of protein digestion enzymes was not sufficient. Although the protein digestibility of Jin et al [
 <xref rid="b19-ajas-18-0647" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] was a total track digestibility and the pigs were younger than those of this study, that was higher than that of this experiment due to experimental diet composition (mainly soybean meal was used as vegetable protein by-product) expected to have a higher digestibility than palm kernel meal and wheat bran, and lower feeding amount (2% of body weight) than that of this study (4% of body weight).
</p>
