<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0240">It should be noted that traditional medicines are not always free of side effects due to the presence of various pharmacological substances which may induce problems through inappropriate dosage and method of administration (
 <xref rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr">Izzo et al., 2016</xref>). Likewise, it is relevant to mention that our informants recognized as toxic some plant species such as 
 <italic>Aristolochia longa</italic> L., 
 <italic>Berberis vulgaris</italic> L. and 
 <italic>Peganum harmala</italic> L. although some had local medicinal uses but not all the toxic plants. It is important to note that among the reported plants, 
 <italic>Aristolochia longa</italic> L.
 <italic>, Artemisia herba-alba</italic> Asso
 <italic>, Crocus sativus</italic> L.
 <italic>, Cuminum cyminum</italic> L.
 <italic>, Echinops spinosus</italic> L.
 <italic>, Ephedra alata</italic> L.
 <italic>, Ferula vesceritensis</italic> L.
 <italic>, Haloxylon scoparium</italic> Pomel
 <italic>, Juniperus phoenicea</italic> L.
 <italic>, Lawsonia inermis</italic> L.
 <italic>, Lepidium sativum</italic> L.
 <italic>, Mentha spicata</italic> L.
 <italic>, Pistacia lentiscus</italic> L.
 <italic>, Retama raetam</italic> i(Forssk.) Webb
 <italic>, Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L.
 <italic>, Tamarix Africana</italic> Poir.
 <italic>, Thymelaea microphylla</italic> Meisn. are considered all as toxic at higher doses and are not recommended to pregnant women (
 <xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">Hammiche et al., 2013</xref>). Besides, the harmful use of 
 <italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> L. on spermatozoids motility as well as its embryotoxic effect have been also described (
 <xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">Gonzales et al., 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0580" ref-type="bibr">Zeichen de Sa et al., 2000</xref>). As well, human consumption of cyanogenic plants like 
 <italic>Prunus</italic> sp. rich with glycosides, cyanogen and amygdaline at higher doses might cause weakness, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea and spasms followed by terminal coma and death due to cyanide poisoning (
 <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Chaouali et al., 2013</xref>). Also, 
 <italic>Thapsia garganica</italic> L. is a poisonous plant rich with histamine-releasing substances such as lactones sesquiterpenes (thapsigargine and thapsigarginine). Exposure to its molecules might induce vomiting, violent diarrhea, digestive mucous inflammation, salivary secretion, nervous disorders and gastroenteritis which leads lastly to death (
 <xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">Hammiche et al., 2013</xref>). Cucurbitacines and glycosides present in 
 <italic>Citrullus colocynthis</italic> (L.) Schrad. and 
 <italic>Ecballium elaterium</italic> L. might cause severe cutaneous and digestive adverse reactions that should not be ignored (
 <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">De Smet, 1997</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0450" ref-type="bibr">Raikhlin-Eisenkraft and Bentur, 2000</xref>).
</p>
