<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Methods based on NGS mentioned above and DNA microarrays revolutionized microbial studies with vast quantities of data at a relatively low cost. However, the analysis of enormous amounts of data and interpretation of their biological meaning are still a great challenge. A large number of software tools (ST) and databases (DB) have been produced for bioinformatic analysis, including Greengenes (DB; DeSantis et al., 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>), Ribosomal Database Project (RDP, DB; Cole et al., 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>), SILVA (DB; Quast et al., 
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>), MEGA6 (ST; Tamura et al., 
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>), and QIIME (ST; Caporaso et al., 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>) for 16S rRNA gene data analysis; and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG, DB; Ogata et al., 
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1999</xref>), The Carbohydrate-Active EnZymes (CAZY, DB; Cantarel et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>), Clusters of Orthologous Groups of proteins (COGs, DB; Tatusov et al., 
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2001</xref>), MetaCyc (DB; Caspi et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>), and RefSeq (DB; Pruitt et al., 
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>), Transporter Classification Database (TCDB, DB; Saier et al., 
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>), MetaPathways (ST; Konwar et al., 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>), RAxML version 8 (ST; Stamatakis, 
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>), and Circos (ST; Krzywinski et al., 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>) for analyzing metagenomics, metatranscriptomics, and single genome data. A series of visualization tools have also been developed in recent years, including Tablet (Milne et al., 
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>), Integrative Genomics Viewer (IGV) (Robinson et al., 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>), Sequence Annotation, Visualization, and ANalysis Tool (Savant) Genome Browser (Fiume et al., 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>), MagicViewer (Hou et al., 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>), and Cytoscape (Kohl et al., 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). In the microbiological studies on the DWH oil spill, these ST and databases were broadly used for analyzing DNA- and RNA-based data. Moreover, Mason et al. (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) applied multiple ST and databases to interpret biological meaning from a mass of metagenome, metatranscriptome, and single-cell sequencing data. For instance, the GeoChip database (He et al., 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>) was applied to blast proteins involved in hydrocarbon degradation based on raw metagenomic, metatranscriptomic and single-cell reads, while the database of COGs was used to estimate genome sequence completeness. Reads from single cells were assembled using Velvet (Zerbino and Birney, 
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). Unassembled metatranscriptomic reads were mapped to the single-cell draft genome using the CLC Genomics Workbench (CLC bio). Assembled single-cell data were annotated using CAMERA (v2.0.6.2) (Seshadri et al., 
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>). Clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeat regions were identified in the draft genome using CRISPRFinder (Grissa et al., 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>). Although bioinformatic tools have been vastly applied and greatly stimulated the data analysis, there is urgent need for the establishment of more comprehensive databases or big data sets. Meanwhile, equipment simplification, standardization methods and more user-friendly bioinformatic tools need to be developed (Capobianchi et al., 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
