<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Adenosine-5′-diphosphate (ADP) plays an essential role in platelet aggregation and thrombus formation. Two G-protein coupled P2 purinergic ADP receptors, P2Y
 <sub>1</sub> and P2Y
 <sub>12</sub>, are both required for full ADP-induced platelet aggregation. In recent years, the P2Y
 <sub>1</sub> receptor has emerged as an attractive target for anti-thrombotic therapies from preclinical antithrombotic studies and haemorragic models. P2Y
 <sub>12</sub> receptor antagonists are predicted to blunt platelet activation and they may exert beneficial actions on other cell types affected by COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B91-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Diarylurea BPTU showed good binding affinity with P2Y
 <sub>1</sub> receptor (
 <italic>K</italic>
 <sub>i</sub> = 6 nM) and moderate antiplatelet activity in the ADP-induced platelet aggregation assay in vitro. The pharmacokinetic profile of BPTU revealed that this compound had a moderate half-life (t
 <sub>1/2</sub> = 1.43 h) and bioavailability (F = 18%) when orally dosed at 30 mg/kg in rats [
 <xref rid="B92-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. From the crystal structures of BPTU binding with P2Y
 <sub>1</sub> receptor it emerged that BPTU bound to P2Y
 <sub>1</sub> receptor on the lipid interface of the transmembrane domain, thus indicating BPTU as an allosteric modulator of P2Y
 <sub>1</sub> receptor [
 <xref rid="B93-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. Starting from BPTU as a lead compound, several other analogues were then synthesized. Wang et al. (2013) demonstrated that compounds 
 <bold>43</bold> and 
 <bold>44</bold> (
 <xref rid="antibiotics-10-00092-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>) showed significantly higher aqueous solubility while maintaining antiplatelet activity similar to that of BPTU. Compound 43 was efficacious and showed a dose-dependent reduction of thrombosis weight with an EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 2 µM in the rabbit electrolytic-mediated carotid arterial thrombosis (ECAT) model and had a moderate prolongation of bleeding time in rats similar to that of compound BPTU. However, it showed toxicity in the rabbit [
 <xref rid="B94-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. A novel series of 2-(phenoxyaryl)-3-urea derivatives were designed, synthesized, and biologically evaluated for their anti-thrombotic activity and compared to BPTU. Compound 
 <bold>45</bold> demonstrated a good P2Y
 <sub>1</sub> receptor antagonistic potency in vitro (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.21 µM versus 0.28 µM of BPTU). In a study on antiplatelet aggregation, compounds 
 <bold>46</bold> and 
 <bold>47</bold> exhibited good antiplatelet activity (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 12.52 and 7.19 µM, respectively). The possible binding modes of compounds with P2Y1 receptor were also explored by molecular docking simulation. The docking studies demonstrated that compound 
 <bold>45</bold> interacted well with Phe119 through hydrophobic interaction and modestly improved the P2Y1 receptor antagonistic activity, making it justifiable for further investigation [
 <xref rid="B95-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Qiao et al. (2013) reported new conformationally constrained ortho-anilino diarylureas. Compound 
 <bold>48</bold> acts as P2Y
 <sub>1</sub> antagonist, showing a 
 <italic>K</italic>
 <sub>i</sub> value of 4.3 nM in the primary membrane binding assay and improved in vitro functional potency in the fluorescent imaging plate reader (FLIPR) P2Y
 <sub>1</sub> assay (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 2.5 nM). It showed a strong antithrombotic effect with mild bleeding liability in the rat thrombosis and hemostasis models, showing IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 4.9 µM in the ADP-induced platelet aggregation (PA) assay [
 <xref rid="B96-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. In a successive study, the benzothiazole-containing diarylurea 
 <bold>52</bold> was demonstrated to be a potent P2Y
 <sub>1</sub> antagonist and orally bioavailable with a suitable PK profile in preclinical species. It showed a good binding affinity (
 <italic>K</italic>
 <sub>i</sub> = 7.9 nM) and improved in vitro functional potency in the FLIPR P2Y
 <sub>1</sub> assay (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.12 nM). It also showed a strong antithrombotic effect in the ADP-induced PA assay (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.13 µM), better than the previously described 
 <bold>48</bold> and enhanced haemorragic profile compared to P2Y
 <sub>12</sub> antagonist clopidogrel in rat efficacy/bleeding models [
 <xref rid="B97-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. Then, other diarylureas were studied. Compound 
 <bold>50</bold> was slightly stronger in binding affinity (
 <italic>K</italic>
 <sub>i</sub> = 4.0 nM) but much stronger in FLIPR assay (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.22 nM) and was equiactive in the inhibition of platelet aggregation (PA IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.17 µM). The spiropiperidinyl indoline-containing diarylurea 
 <bold>51</bold>, retained a good in vitro potency (
 <italic>K</italic>
 <sub>i</sub> = 12.9 nM) and was much more active in the in vitro functional assays with FLIPR (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.22 nM) and PA (IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 0.41 µM). Compound 
 <bold>51</bold> also showed the highest metabolic stability and lowest clearance (CL) value (thus, high i.v. exposure), small volume of distribution (V
 <sub>dss</sub>) values, and modest bioavailability [
 <xref rid="B98-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>].
</p>
