<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Here we report on work considering local and regional population dynamics of 
 <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (garlic mustard), a European biennial herb in temperate North America. Range expansion and local abundance increases of 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in the 20th century co‐occurred with native forest understory plant declines. In response, land managers deployed a range of control treatments, but only achieved temporary suppression, prompting research into biological control (Blossey 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Davis 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Gerber 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). We established a regional long‐term monitoring program at 16 sites to establish baseline population dynamics (measuring recruitment as number of rosettes in the first year, survival of rosette cohort to adult plants and fecundity as number of siliques/stem) to enable future assessments in response to a possible introductions of specialised herbivores (Blossey 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). Particularly rosette survival and seed output are crucial parameters in the demography of 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> (Davis 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>), thus our data cover the most important factors in the life cycle of this biennial plant. Based on experience conveyed to us by land managers we predicted sustained local annual 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> populations and vigour (number of stems, height, cover and reproduction) with some annual fluctuations in recruitment driven by local differences in climate but no sustained declines. Several years into this monitoring program, we observed local 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> declines that lacked an obvious cause (such as presence of above ground natural enemies). We used an exploratory assessment of potential underlying mechanisms at a location where the chronosequence of 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> arrival, spread and decline was well established to test for potential negative soil feedback (van der Putten 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0098" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). We show that (1) widespread 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> declines are a function of local residence time; (2) regional differences in patterns of decline may reflect invasion histories and (3) projected population growth rates decline to &lt; 1 (indicating shrinking populations) after 10–20 years. Our exploratory assessment leads to a new hypothesis that changes in population growth rates are a response to negative soil feedback, but this hypothesis needs confirmation at additional sites and across the range of 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in North America.
</p>
