<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Three weeks after transplant, 
 <italic>Cuscuta</italic> stems were collected from a field near the village of Dengshuiling and wound around 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> stems (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35407-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). We used 
 <italic>Cuscuta</italic> raised from stem cuttings instead of seeds because there were no mature seeds in the field at the start of the experiment. To represent low‐ and high‐level parasitism, we wound one and three 
 <italic>Cuscuta</italic> stems (each 15 cm long), respectively, around 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> stems. As a control, we grew 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> without 
 <italic>Cuscuta</italic> infestation. We did not infest 
 <italic>Coix</italic> with 
 <italic>Cuscuta</italic> because in the habitat where we sampled experimental plant materials, 
 <italic>Cuscuta</italic> avoided 
 <italic>Coix</italic> (although 
 <italic>Coix</italic> experienced 
 <italic>c</italic>. 2.5% of parasitism relative to 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> in other habitats). To suppress fungi that were present in the potted soil, we applied benomyl (purchased from Yida Chemical Inc.). Benomyl had been shown to effectively reduce soil fungi including AM fungi with negligible direct effects on plants (Callaway, Mahall, Wicks, Pankey, &amp; Zabinski, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>; Hetrick, Wilson, &amp; Hartnett, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">1989</xref>). The fungicide was applied at a concentration of 50 mg benomyl/kg soil (Callaway et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>; Hetrick et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">1989</xref>). We used streptomycin sulfate (purchased from Linhai Seeds and Vegetation Company) to suppress bacteria in the potted soil. Streptomycin is a commonly used bactericidal antibiotic (El‐Khair &amp; Haggag, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>) that acts by interfering with normal protein synthesis in bacteria (Bailey, Smith, &amp; Bolton, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). We added 40,000 titer units of streptomycin sulfate/kg soil to the soil in the pot every week. The fungicide and bactericide were solubilized in tap water and applied at the rate of 100 ml per pot. As a control against the fungicide and bactericide treatments, we applied 100 ml of tap water. Each of the resulting 12 treatment combinations (i.e., three levels of parasitism on 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> by 
 <italic>Cuscuta</italic> [no parasitism, light parasitism, and heavy parasitism] × 2 levels of fungicide [applied vs. not applied] × 2 levels of bactericide [applied vs. not applied]) was replicated five times, resulting in 60 experimental pots. The pots were arranged randomly within the garden and the experiment ran for 7 weeks.
</p>
