<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0390">Atractylon significantly inhibited NO and prostaglandin E2 production as well as inducible NO synthase and cyclooxygenase-2 expression in LPS-induced RAW 264.7 cells. Atractylon (40 mg/kg) also significantly reduced the acetic-acid-induced writhing response, carrageenan-induced paw edema, and hot-plate latent pain response in mice. The traditional use of 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> for anti-inflammatory effect is demonstrated to be due mainly to interference with the enzymes in the inflammatory pathway, that is, 5- lipoxygenase (5-LOX) and cyclooxygenase-1 (COX-1) (
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">Resch et al., 1998</xref>). The current research showed that atractylodin could inhibit the inflammatory response induced by lipopolysaccharide (LPS). Namely, atractylodin inhibited the wet-to-dry weight ratio of lung, myeloperoxidase (MPO) activity, inflammatory cell infiltration, protein leakage, TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-6, and monocyte chemoattractant protein (MCP-1) secretion. Its mechanism was that atractylodin could down-regulate nucleotide-binding domain-like receptor protein 3 (NLRP3) inflammasome and activate toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4) (
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2018</xref>). Another study reported that atractylodin exhibited anti-inflammatory activity and ameliorated simultaneous dyskinesia in rats with constipation and diarrhea by reducing plasma proinflammatory cytokines (TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL-6) (
 <xref rid="bib133" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib138" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. (2015)</xref> indicated that ATL-I could protect acute lung injury by inhibiting TLR4 expression and NF-κB activation. 
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Ji et al. (2016)</xref> found that ATL-III inhibited the production of NO, PGE2, IL-6, and TNF-α in a dose-dependent manner and had an anti-inflammatory activity on LPS triggered macrophages of RAW264.7 mice. The high concentration of ATL-III (100 μM) could inhibit the expression of cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) by inhibiting the activation of NF-κB and ERK1/2. 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Antwi et al. (2017)</xref> indicated that stigmasterol could inhibit eosinophils, peribronchiolar, lymphocytes, monocytes proliferation, alveolar infiltration of inflammatory cells, perivascular, vascular cell adhesion molecule-1, ovalbumin (OVA)-specific immunoglobulin E expression and thus inhibit OVA-induced airway inflammatory damage in guinea pigs after intraperitoneal injection. Atractylone inhibited allergic inflammation in OVA-induced animal model while decreased rub scores, IL-1, IL-4, IL-5, IL-6, IL-13, COX-2, intercellular adhesion molecule-1 (ICAM-1), and macrophage inflammatory protein (MIP)-2 expression (
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2016</xref>). The results exhibited that atractylone could inhibit histidine decarboxylase activity and expression, tryptase and histamine release in PMACI-induced HMC-1 cells and inhibit filamentous actin formation and morphological alteration in stem cell factor-stimulated peritoneal mast cells (RPMCs) animal model (
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Han et al., 2016</xref>). Stigmasterol and β-sitosterol had inhibitory effects on colitis induced by dextran sodium sulfate in C57BL/6J male mice. They critically suppressed colon shortening, colitis, and distal colon via the inactivation of NF-κB and decreased fecal hemoglobin content (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Feng et al., 2017</xref>). A recent study showed that β-sitosterol had an anti-inflammatory activity based on the rat pleurisy assay and rat paw edema test (
 <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">Paniagua-Pérez et al., 2017</xref>). Polyacetylenes exhibited anti-inflammatory activity with structure-activity relationships: the introduction of an acyl group into a compound increased the inhibitory effect against NO production. Deacylated product of 14-β-methylbutyryltetradeca-2E, 8E, 10E-trien-4, 6-diyn-1-ol, due to boiling extraction with water, results in diminished anti-inflammatory activity (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Kim, 2016</xref>).
</p>
