<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A further explanation for the interaction pattern encountered could be specialized mutualists that increase nutrient availability and therefore the competitive ability of plants when grown with soil biota communities of the same origin. Yang et al. (
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0083" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>) compared plant–soil feedbacks using soil and genotypes from the native and exotic range of 
 <italic>Triadica sebifera</italic> and displayed significant responses for biomass and survival in the native but not in the exotic range. They suggested evolutionary variation in plant–fungi interactions to influence range expansion of exotic plants. In contrast, for 
 <italic>Solidago gigantea</italic>, Maron et al. (
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) found no differentiation among soil genotypes in plant–soil feedbacks. However, we will have to take into account that there is more conditionality behind plant–soil feedbacks, in particular, when addressing biogeographic settings as we did (Maron et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). In natural settings, the strength of plant–soil feedbacks implies associations with the abundance of individuals, variation among plant genotypes, and variation in the effects of soil from geographically disparate sites. Maron et al. (
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) highlight that different plant genotypes vary in their response to pathogenic agents in soil and that the strength of feedback generated in soils from different locations. This emphasizes the need to consider appropriate sample sizes for such tests in order to account for such differences in native–exotic range comparisons. While we were able to implement five populations of origin by status, there is evidence that accounting for genetic heterogeneity within species would require a higher number of populations to be tested as representatives by status groups to avoid effects of nonrandom geographic sampling (Colautti &amp; Lau, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Rosche et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>).
</p>
