<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0065">Numerous papers in the literatures have documented UAE application in relation to the reduced the extraction cycle in natural components that require longer hours or even days using traditional processes. Specific component classes like polyphenols, odorants minerals including organic substances are extracted utilizing varied matrix through ultrasound. The mechanical outcomes show maximum solvent penetration inside cells by enhancing the diffusion and cavitation effect, allowing rupture of cell walls besides releasing the compounds in their medium 
 <xref rid="b0300" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>. Higher yields are therefore obtained with this technology using shorter duration and low operating conditions 
 <xref rid="b0875" ref-type="bibr">[175]</xref>. However, several studies reported such UAE represents another derivative for traditional technique considering food and natural products that are ecologically and economically viable. The main advantages are reductions in the operation and extracted times, the quantity and energy of the solvent utilized during unit operations and CO
 <sub>2</sub> emissions 
 <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. The UAE method has therefore employed towards modifying food items and in development of novel food items which cannot be achieved using conventional extraction techniques 
 <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. In addition, ultrasound eased the detection and quantifiable procedure in organ phosphorus and triazine pesticides of wine samples, through its sensitivity and versatile nature. Particularly pesticides were extracted utilizing liquid–liquid dispersion micro-extraction assisted by ultrasound 
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. A recent observation emphasized on the new methods of extraction implementation for phthalate ester (PAE) and subsequent examination of the GC-MS in the product matrix. Within this field, various literature was documented outlining various methods of sample preparation/extraction 
 <xref rid="b0740" ref-type="bibr">[148]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0745" ref-type="bibr">[149]</xref>. In baby food items, ultrasound-based process vortex-assisted liquid–liquid microextraction joined with GC ion trap MS (GC / IT-MS) enabled to obtain phthalates, that may be an endocrine disruptor.
</p>
