<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Many spectroscopic techniques are used for IONPs characterization. X-ray diffraction allows collecting information about the crystalline structure of the particles (i.e., angle, width), while structure characterization and functional group determination, are commonly performed by Fourier-Transform Infrared (FTIR) spectroscopy [
 <xref rid="B58-materials-12-00465" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-materials-12-00465" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>], thanks to the presence of molecules absorbing light in the region from 2.5 μm to 15 μm (wavenumber from 4000 cm
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> to 660 cm
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>). Alternatively, NMR (Nuclear Magnetic Resonance) techniques can be used to study the structure of a compound. The ability of NMR to provide information regarding the specific bonding structure and stereochemistry of molecules of pharmaceutical interest has made it a powerful analytical instrument for structural determination [
 <xref rid="B60-materials-12-00465" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. Furthermore, the thermal stability of IONPs can be determined by using the thermogravimetry analysis [
 <xref rid="B61-materials-12-00465" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>]. Dynamic Light Scattering (DLS) has several advantages for sizing MNPs and it has been widely used to determine the hydrodynamic diameter of IONPs (typically ranging between 30 to 190 nm) via the Stokes-Einstein equation [
 <xref rid="B62-materials-12-00465" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>]. Moreover, IONPs can be electrostatically characterized by using Zeta potential measurement in order to determine their surface charge (see 
 <xref rid="materials-12-00465-t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). In general, surface charge, and in turn, the Zeta potential can be modified by using polymer coating [
 <xref rid="B63-materials-12-00465" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-materials-12-00465" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. Mass spectroscopy requires a very small amount of sample to determine molecular weight and surface properties with high accuracy and precision. Fluorescence correlation spectroscopy (using the visible and UV radiation) is normally employed for studying concentration effects, molecular diffusion, and chemical kinetics. Surface-enhanced Raman spectroscopy and circular dichroism make it possible to determine IONP structural conformation; Raman spectroscopy in particular offers the unique possibility to record spectra directly in aqueous solution, without the need for any sophisticated sample preparation [
 <xref rid="B14-materials-12-00465" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] (see 
 <xref rid="materials-12-00465-t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>).
</p>
