<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec sec-type="objectives">
  <title>Objectives</title>
  <p>
   <italic>Trachyspermum khasianum</italic> H. Wolff is a rare medicinal plant characteristically used by the traditional healers in traditional medicine for the treatment of throat-pain, toothache, and stomach ache. The study was designed to determine the anthelmintic and analgesic properties of the aerial parts of 
   <italic>Trachyspermum khasianum</italic> H. Wolff (Family Apiaceae). The aqueous and ethanol extract of 
   <italic>T. khasianum</italic> H. Wolff was prepared and subjected for evaluation to determine the possible therapeutic effects.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec sec-type="methods">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>Anthelmintic activities of the extracts were determined by observing the time taken to paralyze and the time taken for the death of earthworms (
   <italic>Eisenia foetida</italic>) as compared to the standard drug–Albendazole (20 mg/ml) and control. Analgesic potential of the extracts was evaluated using Eddy’s hot plate method to understand the analgesic activity in rats (Wistar rats) at 100 mg/kg and 200 mg/kg body weight doses and compared with the standard reference (Diclofenac sodium 10 mg/kg of animals).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec sec-type="results">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>The extracts showed a significant dose-dependent anthelmintic effect at the different concentrations (10, 20, and 40) mg/ml, compared to that of the standard drug (20 mg/ml). Also, the results suggested that the plant extracts possess significantly analgesic activity in rats.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec sec-type="conclusion">
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p>The studies indicate that 
   <italic>Trachyspermum khasianum</italic> shows anthelmintic and potent analgesic activities. Further research should be carried out to identify the specific phytoconstituents responsible for both analgesic and anthelmintic activities and its possible mechanism of action.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
