<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In preceding research, PCA analysis of polyphenols content and composition was used to investigate propolis samples of different origins such as Croatian [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>], Portuguese [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>], Serbian [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>] (one work included also 
 <italic class="italic">P. nigra</italic> sample [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]), Greek [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>], German [
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>], and Turkish [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Statistical analyses based on EOs were less utilized, albeit performed (for example, in Brazil [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>], China [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>] and Estonia [
 <xref rid="B39-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]). Chemometric analyses were also performed for 
 <italic class="italic">Salicaceae</italic> family (including 
 <italic class="italic">Populus</italic> genus) [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. Ristivojević et al. [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>] based PCA analysis of propolis and black poplars buds on quantified amounts of poliphenolic components. In their article, galangin, together with CAPE, chrysin and pinocembrin, were sufficient to classify samples of black poplar and of propolis types, albeit other types were not analyzed. In our opinion, it was possible because the abovementioned work was focused on only one 
 <italic class="italic">Populus</italic> species and propolis that was the product of its exudates. As such, the samples were much more homogenous than the one investigated in our work, which makes their method valid for the particular task. Considering the diversity of chemical compositions of our samples, between black poplars and aspens, between their various chemotypes, and between those and various propolises collected by the bees from those sources, we felt such an approach would have been untenable for our work. Therefore, we tried applying UPLC-DAD chromatogram fingerprints. To avoid complications resulting from the impossibility to obtain standards of some of the compounds commercially, especially phenolic acid glycerides, peaks were calculated as a percentage of the whole chromatogram area, not as content in samples. In analyses of the 70% ethanol in water extract, we obtained a satisfactory discrimination of variables and two principal components model explained more than 70% of variability. Moreover, preliminary reduction analysis eliminated overlapping and unidentified peaks which may have disrupted the analysis. Considering this, we feel our techniques are tenable for our work.
</p>
