<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p id="Par1" class="p">Plant seed oil is an important bioresource for human food and animal feed, as well as industrial bioproducts. Therefore, increasing oil content in seeds has been one of the primary targets in the breeding programs of oilseed crops. 
   <italic class="italic">Thraustochytrium</italic> is a marine protist that can produce a high level of very long-chain polyunsaturated fatty acids (VLCPUFAs) using a PUFA synthase, a polyketide synthase-like fatty acid synthase with multiple catalytic domains. Our previous study showed that a KS domain from the synthase could complement an 
   <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> mutant defective in β-ketoacyl-ACP synthase I (
   <italic class="italic">FabB</italic>) and increase the total fatty acid production. In this study, this KS domain from the PUFA synthase was further functionally analyzed in 
   <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> for the capacity of oil production.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p id="Par2" class="p">The plastidial expression of the KS domain could complement the defective phenotypes of a 
   <italic class="italic">KASI</italic> knockout mutant generated by CRISPR/Cas9. Seed-specific expression of the domain in wild-type 
   <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis</italic> significantly increased seed weight and seed oil, and altered the unsaturation level of fatty acids in seeds, as well as promoted seed germination and early seedling growth.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par3" class="p">The condensation process of fatty acid biosynthesis in plants is a limiting step, and overexpression of the KS domain from a PUFA synthase of microbial origin offers a new strategy to increase oil production in oilseed plants.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Electronic supplementary material</title>
  <p class="p">The online version of this article (10.1186/s13068-019-1514-8) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
