<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">Using legislations and benchmarks similar to pharmaceutical industry standards, biotechnological platforms producing more complex and effective grafts can be achieved. Various human tissue-derived products are required on a daily basis, as in the case of dermal allografts (e.g. human grafts from different persons), in various forms according to the surgical requirements (Calota et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2012</xref>). Likewise, bone allograft processing has resulted in multiple products for orthopaedic (Campana et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2014</xref>; Pierannunzi and Zagra 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2016</xref>), dental (Lobb et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2019</xref>; Kao and Scott 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2007</xref>), maxillofacial (Allegrini et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2008</xref>; Nkenke and Stelzle 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2009</xref>), and neurosurgery (Chau et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2014</xref>; Canzi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2018</xref>) reconstruction fields. The allografts can be free of cellular components and even free of calcium (Drosos et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2015</xref>) to improve its host’s acceptance and tissue repair. They can be dispensed in blocks, sheets and even in the form of an injectable paste (Acarturk and Hollinger 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2006</xref>). Advances in processing techniques and the development of advanced therapies have led to a new generation of processing techniques, such as the “decellularization”, a process that can prevent immune reactions in the recipient (Badylak et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2011</xref>; Crapo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2011</xref>), acting as a “scaffold”, which can be combined with various other cells by the principles of tissue engineering. However, to achieve successful translation of these materials, good manufacturing practices with concepts of quality management, validation and risk management are required in parallel to the clinical transplantation process (European Directorate for the Quality of Medicines &amp; Healthcare (EDQM) 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2019</xref>).
</p>
