<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We developed an innovative modification of the SNAP-
 <italic>tag</italic>
 <sup>®</sup> technology, in order to overcome times and costs relative to the production and the utilisation of commercial or purified customised BG-derivatives. Although they are compatible in terms of catalytic activity as for the SNAP-
 <italic>tag</italic>
 <sup>®</sup>, as well as for the others AGTs
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22–24</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>37</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>46</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>54</sup>
 </xref> the risk of lowering the catalytic activity of these 
 <italic>tags</italic> with customised BG-derivatives should not be underestimated (
 <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). We started by the knowledge that: (i) self-labelling 
 <italic>protein-tags</italic> are still folded and enough stability in their benzylated form after the enzymatic reaction
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref>; (ii) the Huisgen cycloaddition is extremely versatile, fast and specific. Recently, the latter was used for the entrapment of catalytic activities by azide-based pseudo-substrates in a well-known powerful method, the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> activity-based protein profiling (ABPP)
 <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>55</sup>
 </xref>. For these reasons, a 
 <italic>chemo-enzymatic approach</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1(B)</xref>) with an opportunely selected azide-based BG-substrate (
 <bold>BGSN3</bold>) was set up: the efficient exposition of the azide outside the protein surface allows the reaction with a huge number of commercially DBCO-based molecules, more than those BG-derivatives, keeping high the specificity in the presence of 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> “perturbing” proteins (like in cell lysates) and the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> labelling of expressed SNAP-
 <italic>tag</italic>
 <sup>®</sup> in eukaryotic cells. Finally, 
 <bold>BGSN3</bold> proved to be a good substrate for the direct immobilisation of these 
 <italic>tags</italic> on solid surfaces. We demonstrated that splitting the SNAP-
 <italic>tag</italic>
 <sup>®</sup> reaction into two fast steps, as experimentally measured (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2(A,B)</xref>), does not affect the overall rate and efficiency of the protein labelling
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref>, thus opening new perspectives and widening the applications of this powerful biotechnology.
</p>
