<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>BIA pathway engineering efforts have been concomitant with exploration of NCS promiscuity (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>). For example, screening of NCS variants with active site point mutations yielded two variants, A79I and A79F, with increased turnover of methyl-ketone and cyclohexanone 4-HPAA analogs, respectively, was recently reported by 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Lichman et al. (2017)</xref>. This is in keeping with previous work from the same group suggesting that the active site entrance loop is a key determinant of NCS promiscuity toward the aldehyde substrate (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Lichman et al., 2015</xref>). Furthermore, 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2018)</xref> reported 
 <italic>de novo</italic> biosynthesis of noscapine, a BIA with anti-tussive and anticancer properties, in 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, achieving a final titer of 2.2 mg/L. The authors note that halogenated noscapine variants have shown improved bioactivity against cancer cell lines (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">DeBono et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">Tomar et al., 2016</xref>) and hence attempted microbial semi-synthesis noscapine derivatives by supplementing the yeast media with 16 tyrosine analogs, including 3-fluoro-tyrosine, 3-chloro-tyrosine, and 3-iodo-tyrosine (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2018</xref>). Although no noscapine derivatives were detected, peaks matching the exact masses of 8-fluoro-reticuline, 8-chloro-reticuline and 8-iodo substituted (S)-N-methylcoclaurine were observed. The authors present (i) limited promiscuities of the native enzymes, (ii) low reaction efficiencies, and/or (iii) low substrate abundances as possible explanations for missing downstream derivatives. It has been speculated that these short-comings could be addressed by either engineering tailoring enzymes to introduce “late-stage” derivatizations, or by engineering the promiscuity of BIA enzymes such that they turn over the derivatized substrates (
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">Tomar et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr">Srinivasan and Smolke, 2019</xref>). Drawing parallels with the tryptophan halogenases supporting halogenated MIA production, enzymatic halogenation of hydroxyisoquinoline scaffolds is also an option that warrants earnest investigation. For example, direct halogenation of the THIQ scaffold by the fungal halogenase Rdc2 (
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">Zeng et al., 2013</xref>) or of THIQ precursors by the 
 <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> thyroperoxidase (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">Ruf and Carayon, 2006</xref>) are both options for 
 <italic>de novo</italic> production of halogenated BIAs.
</p>
