<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nevertheless, particular attention must be paid to the formulation of EO-based pesticides (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Aćimović et al., 2020</xref>). A well-studied formulation could, on the one hand, counter the high volatility of EOs and ensure the prolonged release of the active substance and, on the other hand, attenuate potential phytotoxic effects (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Moretti et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Maes et al., 2019</xref>). EOs can impact many plant physiological processes (water status alteration, membrane integrity, respiration, and photosynthesis inhibition) through diverse modes of action, such as reactive oxygen species (ROS) induction and enzymatic or phytohormone regulation (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">Werrie et al., 2020</xref>). In this regards, chlorophyll fluorescence has been proven useful to evaluate plant vitality and response to abiotic stress (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Kalaji et al., 2016</xref>). The application of EOs in apple tree may lead to phytotoxicity depending on the application method, concentration, and adaptive duration. For example, 7% of flowers were injured for clove oil in a thinning experiment for concentrations as low as 2% (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Miller and Tworkoski, 2010</xref>). Fruit damages were also reported in postharvest treatment with savory, oregano, and thyme EOs at concentrations of 1–10% for the purpose of controlling 
 <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> and 
 <italic>Penicillium expansum</italic> (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Lopez-Reyes et al., 2010</xref>). Nevertheless, fruit damage was not observed with thermal fogging treatment of lemongrass and citrus EOs at a concentration of 0.125% to control 
 <italic>B. cinerea</italic> (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Mbili et al., 2017</xref>). Therefore, the mode of EO application, the formulation and the selection of the active substance must be adapted for specific purposes and carefully evaluated.
</p>
