<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Trunk injection is a method of applying chemicals directly to the vascular system of the tree after bark piercing, and the chemicals are then distributed systemically through the xylem tissue. This application method directly targets pests whilst reducing environmental exposure to pesticides and input quantities (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Doccola and Wild, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Wise et al., 2014</xref>). It has recently been experimented to fight fungi, such as apple scab, 
 <italic>Venturia inaequalis</italic>, and powdery mildew, 
 <italic>Podosphaera leucotricha</italic>, with disease severity reductions of 22–55 and 41.8–73.5% depending on the season and the product considered (potassium phosphites and synthetic fungicides) (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Percival and Boyle, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Aćimović et al., 2016b</xref>). A similar experiment on insect species [codling moth 
 <italic>Cydia pomonella</italic> (L.), rosy apple aphid 
 <italic>Dysaphis plantaginea</italic> (Passerini) and green apple aphid 
 <italic>Aphis pomi</italic> (Passerini)] reported up to two seasons of control after a single injection of imidacloprid or emamectin benzoate (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Wise et al., 2014</xref>). Spatial and temporal distributions of imidacloprid in leaves have been investigated (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Aćimović et al., 2014</xref>), as well as residues to nectar and pollen, which were below the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) threshold of 25 ng g
 <sup>–1</sup> for imidacloprid (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Coslor et al., 2019</xref>). Although the management of the injection timings may help to keep residue under the toxic limit, systemic resistance inducers have also been explored with the injection of acibenzolar-S-methyl (ASM) to induce systemic acquired resistance (SAR) and to control fire blight (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Aćimović et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
