<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In addition to MS-based approaches, NMR spectroscopy is a potentially valuable technique for analyzing phospholipids in olive oil [
 <xref rid="B22-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Compared to HPLC-MS, NMR and specifically 
 <sup class="sup">31</sup>P-NMR, has higher selectivity, ease of performance and faster analysis. Another advantage of using 
 <sup class="sup">31</sup>P-NMR is that glycerophospholipids give a single signal in the spectrum, while different molecules of these lipids are characterized by specific resonance frequencies derived from their distinct chemical structures. As such, there is no need to separate the components in the sample before analysis [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>], as in HPLC-MS. Even so, 
 <sup class="sup">31</sup>P-NMR high-resolution spectra were hampered by the formation of aggregates and electrostatic complexes with ions in solution [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. The fatty acyl composition of the phospholipids could only be estimated since proton signals are common to the various fatty acyl chains attached to 
 <italic class="italic">sn</italic>-1 and 
 <italic class="italic">sn</italic>-2 positions of glycerol in the phospholipid molecules [
 <xref rid="B23-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Long spectra acquisitions (one hour) were needed to achieve a reasonable signal to noise ratio, due to the low concentration of glycerophospholipids in olive oil [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. The authors needed 100 g of olive oil to carry out the experiments and to obtain the glycerophospholipid profile, while others, using LC-MS/MS approaches, demanded 1 g [
 <xref rid="B12-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] to 50 g [
 <xref rid="B17-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Besides, the 
 <sup class="sup">31</sup>P-NMR approach cannot identify glycolipids in olive oil and these lipids also make up the polar lipid pool of this matrix [
 <xref rid="B12-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>].
</p>
