<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="ab005">
 <p>Antibacterial and cytotoxic activities of 
  <italic>Euphorbia balsamifera</italic>, fractions and pure compounds were evaluated. The cytotoxic assays for HCT116, HePG2 and MCF7 showed a significant IC
  <sub>50</sub>: 54.7 and 76.2 µg/mL of non-polar fraction “
  <italic>n</italic>-hexane” against HCT116 and HePG2, respectively. Antibacterial results revealed that plant fractions exhibited significant potential against the tested pathogens than the total extract where 
  <italic>n</italic>-butanol and ethyl acetate fractions showed significant antibacterial activity (
  <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) against tested bacterial strains. Isolation and structure determination of compounds from 
  <italic>n</italic>-hexane and 
  <italic>n</italic>-butanol fractions were performed. From 
  <italic>n</italic>-hexane fraction, 29-nor-cycloartanol (
  <bold>1),</bold> lanost-8-en-3-ol 
  <bold>(2a</bold>)
  <bold>,</bold> cycloartanol 
  <bold>(2b)</bold> and kampferol-3,4'-dimethyl ether (
  <bold>3</bold>) were isolated and structurally identified, along with 24 compounds were tentatively identified by GC–MS. From the polar 
  <italic>n</italic>-butanol fraction, 4-
  <italic>O</italic>-β-D-glucopyranosyl-2-hydroxy-6-methoxyacetophenone (
  <bold>4),</bold> 4-
  <italic>O</italic>-α-L-rhamnosyl-(1 → 6)-β-D-glucopyranosyl-2-hydroxy-6methoxy-acetophenone (
  <bold>5)</bold>, quercetin-3-
  <italic>O</italic>-glucopyranoside (
  <bold>6)</bold> and isoorientin (
  <bold>7)</bold> were assigned. Structures of the obtained compounds were determined by nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy and mass spectrometry. Except compounds 
  <bold>1</bold> and 
  <bold>5,</bold> all reported compounds announced antibacterial efficiency. Compound 
  <bold>2</bold> showed selectively the highest activity against 
  <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> (22 ± 0.13 mm), meanwhile 4-
  <italic>O</italic>-β-D-glucopyranosyl-2-hydroxy-6-methoxyacetophenone (
  <bold>4)</bold> showed broadly the highest antibacterial activity with MIC of 1.15–1.88 mg/mL against the test Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria. Cytotoxic assays indicated that kampferol-3,4'-dimethyl ether (
  <bold>3)</bold> exhibited the highest activity with matching IC
  <sub>50</sub> values to doxorubicin; 111.46, 42.67 and 44.90 µM against HCT116, HePG2 and MCF7, respectively, however, it is toxic on retina normal cell line RPE1.
 </p>
</abstract>
