<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biosci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biosci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bsr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioscience Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0144-8463</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-4935</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Portland Press Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7791546</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33324970</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR20203022</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">BSR20203022</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Therapeutics &#x00026; Molecular Medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="toc-heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pharmacological insights into <italic>Merremia vitifolia</italic> (Burm.f.) Hallier f. leaf for its antioxidant, thrombolytic, anti-arthritic and anti-nociceptive potential</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Akter</surname><given-names>Sahida</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jahan</surname><given-names>Israt</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khatun</surname><given-names>Mst. Riniara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Mohammad&#x000a0;Forhad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arshad</surname><given-names>Laiba</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8216-1171</contrib-id><name><surname>Jakaria</surname><given-names>Md.</given-names></name><email>md.jakaria@florey.edu.au</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF3"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2935-6345</contrib-id><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>Md. Areeful</given-names></name><email>areeful@gmail.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF4"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><label>1</label>Department of Pharmacy, International Islamic University Chittagong, Chittagong 4318, Bangladesh</aff><aff id="AFF2"><label>2</label>Department of Pharmacy, Forman Christian College (A Chartered University), Lahore, Pakistan</aff><aff id="AFF3"><label>3</label>Melbourne Dementia Research Centre, The Florey Institute of Neuroscience and Mental Health, The University of Melbourne, Parkville, VIC 3052, Australia</aff><aff id="AFF4"><label>4</label>Drug &#x00026; Herbal Research Centre, Faculty of Pharmacy, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, 50300 Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><bold>Correspondences:</bold> Md. Areeful Haque (<email>areeful@gmail.com</email>, <email>areeful@iiuc.ac.bd</email>) or Md. Jakaria (<email>md.jakaria@florey.edu.au</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2021-01-07"><day>07</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>BSR20203022</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted-manuscript"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2021 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article published by Portland Press Limited on behalf of the Biochemical Society and distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CC BY)</ext-link>. Open access for this article was enabled by the participation of University of Melbourne in an all-inclusive <italic>Read and Publish</italic> pilot with Portland Press and the Biochemical Society under a transformative agreement with CAUL.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="bsr-41-bsr20203022.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p><italic>Merremia vitifolia</italic> (Burm.f.) Hallier f., an ethnomedicinally important plant, used in the tribal areas to treat various ailments including fever, headache, eye inflammation, rheumatism, dysentery, jaundice and urinary diseases. The present study explored the biological efficacy of the aqueous fraction of <italic>M. vitifolia</italic> leaves (AFMV) through <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> experimental models. The thrombolytic and anti-arthritic effects of AFMV were evaluated by using the clot lysis technique and inhibition of protein denaturation technique, respectively. The anti-nociceptive activity of AFMV was investigated in Swiss Albino mice by acetic acid-induced writhing test and formalin-induced paw licking test. The antioxidant activities of AFMV, including 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) free radical and total reducing power, were also tested. The qualitative phytochemical assays exhibited AFMV contains secondary metabolites such as alkaloid, carbohydrate, flavonoid, tannin, triterpenoids and phenols. In addition, AFMV showed strong antioxidant effects with the highest scavenging activity (IC<sub>50</sub> 146.61 &#x000b5;g/mL) and reducing power was increased with a dose-dependent manner. AFMV also revealed notable clot lysis effect and substantial anti-arthritic activity at higher doses (500 &#x000b5;g/mL) as compared with the control. The results demonstrated a promising reduction of the number of writhing and duration of paw licking in acetic acid-induced writhing test and formalin-induced paw licking test in a dose-dependent manner, respectively. In conclusion, AFMV provides the scientific basis of its folkloric usage, suggesting it as the vital source of dietary supplement.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Merremia vitifolia</kwd><kwd>anti-arthritic</kwd><kwd>anti-nociceptive activities</kwd><kwd>antioxidant</kwd><kwd>DPPH</kwd><kwd>thrombolytic</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Natural product is known as a healthy source of life for all people, and plants and plant-based dietary supplements have been used due to their wide range of medicinal and nutritional values [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. From prehistoric ages, various natural productsand plant-derived supplement were used by all societies and civilisations for the management of diverse diseases [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. According to the World Health Organization, 80% of the world&#x02019;s population relies on herbal or traditional medications owing to the safety and economic reasons [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Oxidative stress is associated with the pathogenesis of several chronic diseases and disorders such as cardiac diseases, neurodegenerative diseases, diabetes and cancer [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], and plant-based secondary metabolites play protective role against reactive oxygen species (ROS) mediated disorders [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5&#x02013;8</xref>]. However, the identification of natural antioxidants and their source has drawn attention over synthetic drugs owing to their benefits. Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is a chronic inflammatory autoimmune disorder associated with genetic pathophysiology and environmental factors primarily responsible for the destruction of synovial fluids, inflammatory cartilage degeneration, morning stiffness, bone alcoholysis and joint deformities [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Recent research studies revealed that approximately 0.5&#x02013;1% of people are globally suffered from rheumatoid arthritis, where women are affected more than men, women: men (3:1) [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Notably, ROS, lipoxygenase, pro-inflammatory cytokines (such as tumour necrosis factor-&#x003b1;, interleukin (IL)-1&#x003b2;), prostaglandin-endoperoxide synthase, prostaglandins, cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) enzyme and macrophage colony-stimulating factor plays a crucial role in the pathophysiology of rheumatoid arthritis. In the rheumatoid synovium, the activation of polymorphonuclear cells and macrophages enhanced O<sub>2</sub> consumption with the release of toxic free radicals, which can damage joint and cartilage tissue that leads to triggers an inflammatory response and cytolysis [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. This process can reduce antioxidant defence system (glutathione, superoxide dismutase and catalase) or increase in lipid peroxidation marker (such as malondialdehyde).</p><p>Thrombosis is a lethal disease, which causes acute coronary disorders, for example, (ischemia, coronary artery diseases, myocardial infarction and atherosclerosis) that accounts for sudden morbidity or mortality [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Blood clots or thrombus formed in the circulatory system due to homeostatic imbalance between thrombogenic factors and protective mechanisms, causing vascular blockage and depriving tissues normal flow of blood and oxygen, this causes ischemia of the tissues throughout the region and leads to fatal consequences ultimately prompting death [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Numerous thrombolytic agents are used to treat myocardial infarction; among them, streptokinase (SK) is notable but leads to an increased risk of severe hemorrhagic transformation, anaphylactic reaction and hypertension. Treatment with the alternative option of medicines such as traditional and herbal drugs is frequently being searched for their safety profile to overcome current adverse effects of this therapy based on the high importance of the thrombolytic agents.</p><p><italic>Merremia vitifolia</italic> (Burm. f.) Hallier f. is a perennial, climbing plant with twining stems can be 2&#x02013;5 meters long and widely distributed in Bangladesh, India, Srilanka, Myanmar, Thailand and throughout Malaysia. Traditionally, leaf and rhizome of this plant are used in tribal areas to treat numerous illness such as fever, headache, eye inflammation, rheumatism, dysentery, jaundice and urinary diseases [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Considering the enormous ethnomedicinal uses and therapeutic value of <italic>M. vitifolia</italic>, this research was aimed to elucidate the <italic>in vitro</italic> antioxidative potential, thrombolytic effect, anti-arthritic action and <italic>in vivo</italic> anti-nociceptive effect of aqueous extract of <italic>M. vitifolia</italic> leaves (AFMV) to determine its relevance to treating certain disorders.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Chemicals and reagents</title><p>Methanol, acetic acid, <italic>n</italic>-hexane, ethyl acetate, Folin-Ciocalteu reagent, potassium ferricyanide from Sigma Chemical Company, St. Louis, MO, U.S.A.); lyophilised SK vial (1500000 IU) and diclofenac sodium (standard drugs) were procured from the Incepta Pharmaceuticals Ltd., Bangladesh. Normal saline solution (0.9% NaCl) was obtained from the Social Marketing Company (SMC) Ltd, Bangladesh, and Tween-80 was patronised from BDH Chemicals (Leicestershire, U.K.). All other chemicals of analytical grade were purchased from local sources through Taj Scientific Ltd., Bangladesh.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Animals</title><p>Animals were maintained as the published article by Siddiqui et al. (2020) [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Six to 7 week-old Swiss albino mice weighing 22&#x02013;30 g were purchased from the animal research division of the Jahangirnagar University, Dhaka, Bangladesh. The mice were maintained at room temperature (23 &#x000b1; 2&#x000b0;C) and 55&#x02013;65% humidity with a natural 12:12-h light and dark cycle. All the mouse was acclimatised to a new environment for 7 days preceding to the experiment. The mouse was supplied with standard laboratory diet <italic>ad libitum</italic> and freshwater, and mouse fasted overnight before the experiment. The experiment was approved by the Animal Ethical Committee, Department of Pharmacy, protocol number: 2019/65, International Islamic University Chittagong, Bangladesh. All experiments were done at the Department of Pharmacy, International Islamic University Chittagong, Bangladesh. The animal study was observational or behavioural, and no surgery or scarification was implicated for this experiment.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Acute toxicity test</title><p>Mice were healthy at the time of acclimatisation in the laboratory environment before the commencement of the toxicity analysis. The study was conducted according to the OECD guidelines and following the described method with little modification [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Male Swiss albino mice were divided into seven groups, consisting of six animals (n=6) each. Test groups were administered different doses (200, 400, 800, 1600, 3000 and 4000 mg/kg, p.o.) while the control group received 1% tween 80 in saline water. The animals were monitored closely for the next 48 h and up to 14 consecutive days to record any acute toxicological signs (mortality, allergic reaction and behavioural changes).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Plant materials</title><p>Fresh leaves of <italic>M. vitifolia</italic> were collected randomly from hill tract area of Chittagong, Bangladesh. A taxonomist then verified the collected plant samples, and a voucher specimen has been deposited with a number (accession#75488) for future references. The extraneous, objectionable contaminants were removed by hand and then washed the plant materials using freshwater. Washed plant materials were dried in shaded place at low temperature (45&#x02013;50&#x000b0;C) and crushed into coarse powered using a mechanical grinder.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Plant extraction and fraction preparation</title><p>Approximately 500 g coarse powdered leaves were dissolved in 3000 mL of methanol at a ratio of 1:6 (plant sample: solvent) at room temperature (25 &#x000b1; 2&#x000b0;C) for 3 days with occasional shaking and stirring on a shaker machine and then filtered using cotton followed by Whatman #1 filter paper. The filtrate was concentrated by evaporating the solvent using a water bath at a temperature of 40&#x02013;45&#x000b0;C to yield a viscous mass of crude methanol extract. Around 50 g of the crude methanol extract was fractionated, followed by modified Kupchan method [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] (Kupchan et al., 1973). Approximately 8 g of ethyl acetate fraction and 14 g of aqueous fraction were obtained. The fractions were stored at 4&#x000b0;C in airtight containers, and the AFMV was dissolved in saline water with 1% tween 80 before the experiments.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Phytochemical analysis</title><p>The AFMV extracts were subjected to a qualitative phytochemical analysis using standard procedures for assessing the existence of alkaloids, carbohydrates, glycosides, flavonoids, tannins, saponins, phenols and proteins [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Antioxidant activity</title><sec id="sec2-7-1"><title>Determination of DPPH free radical scavenging activity</title><p>The free radical scavenging activity of AFMV was assessed using stable DPPH (1,1-diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazil) according to the procedure mentioned earlier [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. A 3 ml of 0.004% DPPH solution (4 mg DPPH in 100 ml 95% methanol) was dissolved in different concentration of either extract or standard (31.25&#x02013;500 &#x000b5;g/ml). After 30 min incubation at 25&#x000b0;C, the absorbance was taken at 517 nm using UV-visible spectrophotometer (AE-S90, A &#x00026; E Lab, U.K. CO., LTD.). The percentage (%) of inhibition was calculated using following the formula, <disp-formula><mml:math id="um1"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Where, <italic>A</italic><sub>0</sub> = control absorbance and <italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub> = sample/standard absorbance</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7-2"><title>Determination of reducing power capacity</title><p>The reducing power assay was investigated according to the modified method [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. About 1 ml of the test sample or standard at different concentrations level (31.25&#x02013;500 &#x003bc;g/mL) was mixed with 2.5 ml of phosphate buffer (0.2 M, pH 6.6) and potassium ferricyanide (1% w/v), respectively and incubated for 20 min at 50&#x000b0;C to complete the reaction. The mixture was then centrifuged (at 3000 rpm for 10 min) with added 2.5 ml of 10% trichloroacetic acid solution for put an end to the reaction. The supernatant (upper layer) solution was discarded, and 2.5 ml of distilled H<sub>2</sub>0 and 0.5 ml FeCl<sub>3</sub> (1% w/v) were added, a visible Prussian blue colour indicating the endpoint of the reaction. Finally, the absorbance was taken at 700 nm by using UV-visible spectrophotometer (AE-S90, A &#x00026; E Lab, U.K. CO., LTD.) against blank.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Thrombolytic activity</title><p>The thrombolytic activity of AMFV was evaluated following the clot lysis test [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21&#x02013;23</xref>]. About 5 ml of venous blood drawn from ten healthy adult volunteers (Consent approval number: ECPD-IIUC-2019/02) 1:1 (male: female) with no history of an oral contraceptive and anticoagulant treatment. Consent was taken from the participants before collecting the blood sample. Blood from each volunteer distributed in nine pre-weighed sterile Eppendorf tube (0.5 ml/tube) and incubated for 45 min at 37&#x000b0;C to form the clot. After clot formation, serum was removed carefully without disrupting the clot, and each tube was reweighed to define the clot weight. In each tube having the pre-weighed clot, 100 &#x000b5;l of AFMV as the positive control, 100 &#x000b5;l of normal saline as negative control and 100 &#x000b5;l of SK as positive control were separately added. Incubation was done for 90 min at 37&#x000b0;C to notice clot lysis. After incubation, released fluid was separated using micropipette and tubes were reweighed to get the difference in clot weight after clot disruption. The percentage of clot lysis was calculated using the following formula: <disp-formula><mml:math id="um2"><mml:mi>%</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;of&#x02009;clot&#x02009;lysis</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>weight&#x02009;of&#x02009;released&#x02009;clot</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>clot&#x02009;weight</mml:mtext></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Anti-arthritic activity</title><p>The anti-arthritic activity of AFMV was evaluated using the inhibition of protein denaturation technique followed by a method described by Ansari et al. (2017) [<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] with some modifications. Serially diluted concentrations between (31.25&#x02013;500 &#x000b5;g/ml) of AFMV extract and standard diclofenac-Na were obtained. For each concentration 0.5 ml of test/standard solution from prepared dilutions was mixed with aqueous albumin (0.45 ml, 5% w/v) and 1N HCl was then added to adjust the (pH 6.3). The prepared mixtures then incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 20 min after that the temperature was increased to keep the mixtures at 57&#x000b0;C for 30 min, the samples were cooled, and (2.5 ml) of phosphate buffer was added to the solution. All the reagents except extract are contained in the blank solution. The absorbance was measured using UV-Visible spectrophotometer at 416 nm. Each test was done for triplicate for maintaining accuracy. The % of inhibition of protein denaturation was calculated from the following equation: <disp-formula><mml:math id="um3"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Where <italic>A</italic><sub>0</sub> = control absorbance and <italic>A</italic><sub>1</sub> = sample/standard absorbance.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Anti-nociceptive activity</title><sec id="sec2-10-1"><title>Experimental design</title><p>In <italic>in vivo</italic> animal experiment, 24 animals were divided into four groups where each group consists of six animals (n=6). The standard drug diclofenac sodium (10 mg/kg, b.w, i.p.) was used for acetic acid-induced writhing test and formalin-induced paw licking test. The test groups were administrated AFMV at doses of 200 and 400 (mg/kg, b.w, p.o.), respectively, whereas the control group received vehicle (1% Tween 80 in saline water, 10 mL/kg, p.o). The standard drugs (diclofenac sodium) were administrated at 15 min and AFMV (200 and 400 mg/kg, p.o.) or vehicle at 30 min before the experiments.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-10-2"><title>Acetic acid-induced writhing test</title><p>The acetic acid-induced writhing test in swiss albino mice was carried out as described with minor modification [<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25&#x02013;27</xref>]. All the animals received respective doses 30 min before initiating the study as per the experimental design. One hour later, mice in all groups were treated with 0.7% (v/v) acetic acid solution (10 mL/kg body weight, i.p). Five minutes after acetic acid injection (i.p), mice were placed in a glass made cylindrical cage, and the number of writhing and stretching was counted over 20 min. The percent inhibition of writhing was calculated from [<italic>M</italic><sub>c</sub> &#x02212; <italic>M</italic><sub>t</sub>/<italic>M</italic><sub>c</sub>] &#x000d7; 100; where <italic>M</italic><sub>c</sub> = mean control and <italic>M</italic><sub>t</sub> = mean test. The overall study was observational or behavioural, and no surgery or scarification was implicated for this experiment.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-10-3"><title>Formalin-induced paw licking test</title><p>The formalin-induced paw licking test in Swiss albino mice was evaluated as previously described method [<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. All the animals were received with respective treatment 30 min before the commencement of the study as described in the experimental design section. After 30 min of the administration, (2.5%, 20 &#x000b5;L) formalin was injected by a micro-syringe into the sub-plantar region of the right hind paw of mice and placed in a glass made a cage for observation. The licking and biting of the injected paw were pain response and the first 5 min as neurogenic phase and later 15&#x02013;30 min as the inflammatory phase was recorded. The % of inhibition of licking was calculated from [<italic>M</italic><sub>c</sub> &#x02212; <italic>M</italic><sub>t</sub>/<italic>M</italic><sub>c</sub>] &#x000d7; 100, where <italic>M</italic><sub>c</sub> = mean control and <italic>M</italic><sub>t</sub> = mean test. The overall study was observational or behavioural, and no surgery or scarification was implicated for this experiment.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-11"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The data were represented as (MEAN &#x000b1; SEM), and the method was carried out using the GraphPad Prism Version 8.0 (GraphPad Software Inc, San Diego, CA). The statistical variance was dictated by one-way variance of analysis (ANOVA) followed by Dunnett&#x02019;s test, <italic>t</italic>-test (nonparametric test) and two-way variances of analysis (ANOVA). Values of <italic>P</italic> is less than 0.05 and 0.01 considered as statistically significant and 0<italic>.</italic>001 were regarded as highly significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Acute toxicity test</title><p>The oral administration of AFMV doses up to 4000 mg/kg was found tolerable and safe doses in experimental animals during close monitoring. There were no significant changes in the body weight, behavioural changes, stool frequency, water and food intake irregularity of toxicity and mortality were noted during this investigation.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Phytochemical screening</title><p>The qualitative phytochemical screening of AFMV showed alkaloid, carbohydrate, flavonoids, tannins, protein and phenolic compounds (Supplementary Table S1).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>Antioxidant activity</title><sec id="sec3-3-1"><title>DPPH free radical scavenging activity</title><p>The result of DPPH activity of AFMV extract and ascorbic acid are presented in (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). However, a dose-dependent radical scavenging effect was observed in the DPPH assay. Among all concentrations, AFMV showed the highest scavenging (<italic>P&#x0003c;0.001</italic>) activity (76.11 &#x000b1; 1.05%) with IC<sub>50</sub> of 146.61 &#x000b5;g/mL at the concentration of 500 &#x000b5;g/mL, while the ascorbic acid exhibited 84.62 &#x000b1; 0.74% with IC50 30.38 &#x000b5;g/mL. The outcomes suggested that AFMV can decrease OS-induced free radicals.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>DPPH scavenging activity of AFMV and ascorbic acid at different concentrations</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test material</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concentration (&#x000b5;g/mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Scavenging activity (Mean &#x000b1; SEM)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub> (&#x003bc;g mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascorbic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.86 &#x000b1; 0.31<italic><sup>b</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.74 &#x000b1; 0.89<italic><sup>b</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.39 &#x000b1; 0.44<italic><sup>b</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.56 &#x000b1; 0.54<italic><sup>c</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.62 &#x000b1; 0.74<italic><sup>c</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFMV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.30 &#x000b1; 0.71<italic><sup>a</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.29 &#x000b1; 0.77<italic><sup>b</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.31 &#x000b1; 0.42<italic><sup>b</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.61</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.94 &#x000b1; 1.02<italic><sup>b</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.11 &#x000b1; 1.05<italic><sup>c</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>All results are presented as mean &#x000b1; SEM (n=3). Two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Bonferroni post-test was employed where <bold><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></bold><italic>P&#x0003c;</italic>0.05, <bold><italic><sup>b</sup></italic></bold><italic>P&#x0003c;</italic>0.01, <bold><italic><sup>c</sup></italic></bold><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001, were considered as statistically significant compared with the control; AFMV, aqueous fraction of <italic>Merremia vitifolia</italic> leaves.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-3-2"><title>Reducing power activity</title><p>As depicted in the (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) AFMV extract showed substantial reducing activity (<italic>P&#x0003c;0.05</italic>) with the increasing of concentration-dependent manner as compared with ascorbic acid. The extract displayed higher reductive capability 1.113 &#x000b1; 0.010, while the positive control ascorbic acid showed 2.189 &#x000b1; 0.020 at the concentration of 500 &#x000b5;g/mL.</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Reducing power assay of AFMV at different concentration</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test material</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concentration (&#x000b5;g/mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absorbance (Mean &#x000b1; SEM)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascorbic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.943 &#x000b1; 0.030<italic><sup>a</sup></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.278 &#x000b1; 0.010<italic><sup>a</sup></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.621 &#x000b1; 0.030<italic><sup>a</sup></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.828 &#x000b1; 0.030<italic><sup>a</sup></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.189 &#x000b1; 0.020<italic><sup>b</sup></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFMV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.520 &#x000b1; 0.010<italic><sup>a</sup></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.673 &#x000b1; 0.020<italic><sup>a</sup></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.867 &#x000b1; 0.010<italic><sup>a</sup></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.979 &#x000b1; 0.010<italic><sup>a</sup></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.113 &#x000b1; 0.010<italic><sup>b</sup></italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values are represented in Mean &#x000b1; SEM (n=3). <italic>t</italic>-test (nonparametric test) was employed where <bold><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></bold><italic>P&#x0003c;</italic>0.05, <bold><italic><sup>b</sup></italic></bold><italic>P&#x0003c;</italic>0.01, <bold><italic><sup>c</sup></italic></bold><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001 were considered as statistically significant compared to the reference drug; AFMV, aqueous fraction of <italic>Merremia vitifolia</italic> leaves.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>Thrombolytic activity</title><p>The clot lysis activity of the AFMV is presented in (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The AFMV revealed 42.48 &#x000b1; 1.44% Clot lysis, while positive control (SK) showed 72.16 &#x000b1; 1.85% of clot lysis. The AFMV demonstrated statistically significant (<italic>P&#x0003c;0.001</italic>) as compared with the negative control.</p><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>The clot lysis activity of AFMV and streptokinase</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of clot lysis (Mean &#x000b1; SEM)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (normal saline)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80 &#x000b1; 2.45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard drug (streptokinase)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.16 &#x000b1; 1.85<italic><sup>c</sup></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFMV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.48 &#x000b1; 1.44<italic><sup>c</sup></italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>All results are mean &#x000b1; SEM (<italic>n</italic>=3). One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Dunnett's test was employed where <bold><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></bold><italic>P&#x0003c;</italic>0.05, <bold><italic><sup>b</sup></italic></bold><italic>P&#x0003c;</italic>0.01, <bold><italic><sup>c</sup></italic></bold><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001, were considered as statistically significant compared to the control; AFMV, aqueous fraction of <italic>Merremia vitifolia</italic> leaves.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title>Anti-arthritic activity</title><p>In the present investigation, AFMV and diclofenac sodium (standard) exhibited significant (<italic>P&#x0003c;0.05</italic>) inhibition of protein denaturation in a dose-dependent manner, as shown in (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The extract showed the highest % of inhibition (63.87 &#x000b1; 1.74%) at 500 &#x000b5;g/mL, wherein the standard drug (diclofenac sodium) showed 86.78 &#x000b1; 1.92% at the same concentration.</p><table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Effects of AFMV on protein denaturation compared to the standard drug diclofenac sodium</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Diclofenac sodium</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">AFMV</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concentration (&#x000b5;g/mL)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of Inhibition (Mean &#x000b1; SEM)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concentration (&#x000b5;g/mL)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of inhibition (Mean &#x000b1; SEM)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.29<italic><sup>a</sup></italic> &#x000b1; 1.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.56<italic><sup>a</sup></italic> &#x000b1; 1.57</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.95<italic><sup>a</sup></italic> &#x000b1; 2.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.46<italic><sup>a</sup></italic> &#x000b1; 1.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.57<italic><sup>b</sup></italic> &#x000b1; 1.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.93<italic><sup>a</sup></italic> &#x000b1; 2.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.19<italic><sup>b</sup></italic> &#x000b1; 2.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.28<italic><sup>a</sup></italic> &#x000b1; 2.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.78<italic><sup>c</sup></italic> &#x000b1; 1.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.87<italic><sup>b</sup></italic> &#x000b1; 1.74</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Results are represented in mean &#x000b1; SEM (n=3). Significance variance was followed by <italic>t</italic>-test, <bold><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></bold><italic>P&#x0003c;</italic>0.05, <bold><italic><sup>b</sup></italic></bold><italic>P&#x0003c;</italic>0.01, <bold><italic><sup>c</sup></italic></bold><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001, were considered as statistically significant compared to the reference drug; AFMV, aqueous fraction of <italic>Merremia vitifolia</italic> leaves.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-6"><title>Anti-nociceptive activity</title><sec id="sec3-6-1"><title>Acetic acid-induced writhing test</title><p>The effects of the oral administration of the AFMV solution in the number of writhing on the acetic acid-induced test were shown in (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). In the present study, AFMV (200 and 400 mg/kg, p.o.) and diclofenac sodium (10 mg/kg, i.p.) dose significantly (<italic>P&#x0003c;0.001</italic>) decreased the number of abdominal contortions by increasing the test doses (43.64 &#x000b1; 0.60% and 29.92 &#x000b1; 0.98%) and (21 &#x000b1; 0.57%), respectively compared to the control group. However, the present outcomes indicating a dose-dependent effect.</p><table-wrap id="T5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Effect of AFMV extract in acetic acid-writhing response in Swiss albino mice</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dose</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of writhes (Mean &#x000b1; SEM)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (1% tween 80 in DW)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 ml/kg, p.o.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.45 &#x000b1; 2.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard (Diclofenac sodium)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 mg/kg, i.p.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 &#x000b1; 0.57<italic><sup>c</sup></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFMV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200 mg/kg, p.o.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.64 &#x000b1; 0.60<italic><sup>b</sup></italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFMV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">400 mg/kg, p.o.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.92 &#x000b1; 0.98<italic><sup>c</sup></italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values are represented in Mean &#x000b1; SEM (n=6) and <sup>a</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, <sup>b</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01, <sup>c</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001 were considered as statistically significant compared to the control; AFMV, aqueous fraction of <italic>Merremia vitifolia</italic> leaves.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-6-2"><title>Formalin-induced paw licking assay</title><p>The effect of AFMV on formalin-induced nociception is presented in (<xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). In the formalin-induced licking test, pain responses were evaluated individually in both early and late phases through analysing the duration of licking in animal models. The AFMV at 200 and 400 (mg/kg, p.o.) extract showed significant (<italic>P&#x0003c;0.01</italic>) and dose-dependent anti-nociceptive effect in both phases (early and late) of the test (44.19 &#x000b1; 1.00% and 26.45 &#x000b1; 1.05%) and (30.43 &#x000b1; 1.02% and 19.89 &#x000b1; 1.10%) though reducing paw licking duration in a meaningful manner when compared with the vehicle group. The reference drug diclofenac sodium significantly exerted 20.43 &#x000b1; 0.73 and 15.16 &#x000b1; 0.87% inhibition, at the same concentrations.</p><table-wrap id="T6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 6</label><caption><title>Effect of AFMV extract in formalin induced-licking response in Swiss albino mice</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dose</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Duration of paw licking (S) (Mean &#x000b1; SEM)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early phase</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Late phase</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (1% tween 80 in DW)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 ml/kg, p.o.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.16 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.54 &#x000b1; 1.30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard (Diclofenac sodium)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 mg/kg, i.p.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.43 &#x000b1; 0.73<italic><sup>c</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.16 &#x000b1; 0.87<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFMV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200 mg/kg, p.o.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.19 &#x000b1; 1.0<italic><sup>a</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.45 &#x000b1; 1.05<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFMV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">400 mg/kg, p.o.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.43 &#x000b1; 1.02<italic><sup>c</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.89 &#x000b1; 0.1.10<sup>c</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values are represented in Mean &#x000b1; SEM (n=6). One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Dunnett&#x02019;s test was employed where <bold><italic><sup>a</sup></italic></bold><italic>P&#x0003c;</italic>0.05, <bold><italic><sup>b</sup></italic></bold><italic>P&#x0003c;</italic>0.01, <bold><italic><sup>c</sup></italic></bold><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001, were considered as statistically significant compared to the reference drug; AFMV, aqueous fraction of <italic>Merremia vitifolia</italic> leaves.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The modern discovery of natural products based on ethnomedicinal uses of the medicinal herb has been used for their therapeutic values since ancient times. Plant-derived bioactive compounds are commonly used in the pharmaceutical, nutritional and food supplement industries to prepare different herbal products, vitamins, food supplements and drugs for treating different disease [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The importance of medicinal plants in managing a wide range of diseases is progressively increasing because of their rich source of bioactive secondary metabolites [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28&#x02013;32</xref>]. Alkaloids, flavonoids, phenols, terpenoids and glycosides are important metabolites exhibit multiple biological effects [<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Several well-validated experimental protocols and animal models are necessary for developing a pharmacologically complex lead compound derived from a medicinal plant to achieve a clear preclinical and clinical decision. Phytochemical analysis of the plant extract reveals several compounds considered responsible for numerous biological effects [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. AFMV extracts demonstrated that the plant contains several secondary metabolites including alkaloid, carbohydrate, flavonoids, tannins, protein and phenolic. Alkaloids, common secondary nitrogenous compounds, used to treat various human and animal disorders since middle age and flavonoids are used to treat anti-inflammatory, cancer and cardiovascular diseases [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</p><p>The homeostatic balance between free radicals and antioxidants play a central role in the expression of genes and receptor activation. However, a negative shift in the levels of free radicals can become harmful for the biological system, resulting in several diseases like inflammation, neurodegenerative disorders, aging and cancer [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Antioxidants counteract abnormal effects in the body associated with free radical damage and oxidative stress. Therefore, natural products have gained more attention of researchers in identifying, screening and characterising antioxidants to replace the synthetic ones. Numerous studies have reported that polyphenols and their rich extract can reduce oxidative stress associated with the chronic inflammatory diseases [<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38&#x02013;40</xref>]. In the present study, <italic>in vitro</italic> antioxidant activity was analysed by DPPH free radical scavenging assay and reducing power capacity assay. AFMV exhibited a significant (<italic>P&#x0003c;0.01</italic>) correlation between extract and ascorbic acid for the percentage of inhibition in scavenging abilities. The IC<sub>50</sub> values of AFMV indicated that it has promising protein donating ability and might serve as a free radical inhibitor. The reducing power capacity of AFMV extract was evaluated by using Fe<sup>3+</sup> to Fe<sup>2+</sup> reduction assay. The results of the mentioned assay reveal significant reduction (<italic>P&#x0003c;0.05</italic>), where the yellow colour of test solution shifts to different shades of blue and green colour, based on the reduction capabilities of sample [<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The results depicted that AFMV can donate electrons which can react with free radical and energetically impede radical chain reaction.</p><p>The thrombolytic activity of the AFMV was evaluated and compared with positive and negative control, respectively. Available marketed thrombolytic agents demonstrate their action by blocking thrombus formation in the blood vessel, thereby plasminogen converts into plasmin, resulting in clear tracery of cross-linked fibrin. However, these agents also show severe adverse effects are major clinical drawback also linked to many limitations [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Phytochemicals from several ethnomedicinal sources likely, vegetables and fruits are reported to have anticoagulant, antiplatelet and fibrinolytic potential and hence able to mitigate instance of coronary complications and stroke. AFMV was also found to provide significant thrombolytic activity in this study. This inhibition of clot formation could be attributed to various phytochemicals in it.</p><p>Denaturation of intra-cellular protein is a well-known reason for rheumatoid arthritis and other inflammatory diseases. The inhibitory activity against protein denaturation is one of the most common methods to investigate the anti-arthritic activity of the plant extracts. Protein denaturation is associated with heat, superficial anxiety and chemical vulnerability which helps to generate auto antigens-associated type-III hypersensitivity reaction in certain arthritic diseases [<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The denaturation process possibly involves modifying the electrostatic, hydrogen, hydrophobic and disulphide linkages [<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The ability of an agent to prevent protein denaturation suggests the potential of being an anti-arthritic agent. The present experimental findings showed that AFMV exhibited a significant and dose-dependent inhibitory percentage that was parallel to the reference drug. Secondary metabolites include triterpenoids, phenols, tannins and flavonoids might be responsible for this anti-arthritic activity. Research also suggests that flavonoids have the specific potential to inhibit protein denaturation [<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].</p><p>Pain is one of the most pervasive problems and results due to multiple nociceptive and inflammatory mediators activation such as prostaglandin, bradykinin, histamine, tumour necrosis factor-&#x003b1;, IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-8, which ultimately helps to form edema, inflammation and invasion of leukocytes [<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Various available marketed anti-inflammatory and anti-nociceptive drugs include non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, opioids and glucocorticoids are widely used for their significant action at peripheral sites, but these drugs show adverse effect and inefficient sometimes; therefore, investigation of new drugs is needed to overcome those limitations. AFMV extract in the current was investigated against the central and peripheral acting analgesia model by acetic acid-inclined writhing test and formalin-inclined paw licking assay, respectively. Although the acetic acid-induced test showed good sensitivity, sometimes this test showed poor specificity. Research has been suggested that the intraperitoneal administration of acetic acid injection into the peritoneal cavity leads to an elevated level of COX-2 and lipoxygenase. In the present study, AFMV extract significantly decreased acetic acid-induced writhing in a dose&#x02013;response manner, and these results were found parallel with the reference drug. Therefore, present outcomes in acetic acid-induced mice model suggested that the anti-inflammatory activity of AFMV might be linked partly with the reluctance of COX-2, lipoxygenase and other inflammatory mediators in peripheral tissue hence hindering with the signal transduction pathways in main afferent nociceptors. The formalin-induced paw licking test was also employed in the present study to confirm the action of AFMV against central and peripheral anti-nociceptive pain. This is a biphasic model characterised by two distinct phases, neurogenic pain (0&#x02013;5 min) and inflammatory pain (15&#x02013;30 min), respectively [<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. After administration of formalin, early phase indicates acute response caused by the direct effect of formalin on the sensory C-fibers, while the late phase reveals delayed response by the release of inflammatory mediators [<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In this present study, oral administration of AFMV significantly (<italic>P&#x0003c;0.001</italic>) suppressed pain sensation in both phases as confirmed by reduced licking behaviour, but the impact in the late phase was more prominent. Phytochemicals in AFMV such as alkaloids and flavonoids might be responsible for its inhibitory activity against pain in the experimental model.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The study evaluated antioxidant and anti-arthritic effects of AFMV through <italic>in vitro</italic> models. The study also examined associated biological effects such as thrombolytic action and <italic>in vivo</italic> anti-nociceptive activity. Based on the data, AFMV could be a potential source of antioxidant, anti-arthritic, thrombolytic and anti-nociceptive effects. These effects possibly attributed to secondary metabolites (e.g. alkaloids, flavonoids, tannins and triterpenoids) present in the plant. However, AFMV needs to be further analysed by various techniques such as high-performance liquid chromatography, nuclear magnetic resonance and mass spectrometry for the identification of its major isolates to elucidate the underlying mechanism responsible for the activities.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="suppl1"><caption><title>Supplementary Table S1</title></caption><media xlink:href="BSR-2020-3022_supp.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="ack1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by the Department of Pharmacy, International Islamic University Chittagong, Chittagong 4318, Bangladesh.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec6"><title>Data Availability</title><p>All data are included in the manuscript</p></sec><sec id="sec7" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that there are no competing interests associated with the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec8" sec-type="funding"><title>Funding</title><p>The authors declare that there are no sources of funding to be acknowledged.</p></sec><sec id="sec9" sec-type="Open-access"><title>Open Access</title><p>Open access for this article was enabled by the participation of University of Melbourne in an all-inclusive <italic>Read and Publish</italic> pilot with Portland Press and the Biochemical Society under a transformative agreement with CAUL.</p></sec><sec id="sec10" sec-type="author-contrib"><title>Author Contribution</title><p>S.A. investigated, and I.J., M.R.K., M.F.K, L.A., M.A.H. and M.J. contributed to the analysis and interpretation of data and drafting the manuscript. I.J., M.F.K., L.A., M.J. and M.A.H. contributed in the conceptualisation, visualisation and editing of the draft. M.R.K., M.J. and M.A.H. coordinated the research, revised the manuscript and approved the final version for publication. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec11"><title>Ethical Approval</title><p>Experiments about the animals were investigated in the Department of Pharmacy, International Islamic University Chittagong, Bangladesh. &#x02018;Principles of the Laboratory Animal Care&#x02019; (NIH publication no. 85-23, revised 1985) and &#x02018;National Animal Care Laws&#x02019; have been followed strictly during handling of the experimental animals. The study design was accepted by the Department of Pharmacy, International Islamic University Chittagong, Bangladesh (Ref.: IIUC/PHARM-AEC-64/10-19).</p></sec><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list list-content="abbreviations"><def-item><term id="G1">AFMV</term><def><p>aqueous fraction of <italic>Merremia vitifolia</italic> leaves</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">COX-2</term><def><p>cyclooxygenase-2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3">DPPH</term><def><p>2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G4">RA</term><def><p>rheumatoid arthritis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G5">ROS</term><def><p>reactive oxygen species</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G6">SK</term><def><p>streptokinase</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kader</surname><given-names>F.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Pharmacological insights and prediction of lead bioactive isolates of Dita bark through experimental and computer-aided mechanism</article-title>. <source>Biomed. Pharmacother.</source>
<volume>131</volume>, <fpage>110774</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2020.110774</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33152933?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33152933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jantan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arshad</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Bukhari</surname><given-names>S.N.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Exploring the immunomodulatory and anticancer properties of zerumbone</article-title>. <source>Food function</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>3410</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28714500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agbor</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Naidoo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>A review of the role of African traditional medicine in the management of oral diseases</article-title>. <source>African J. Traditional Complementary Alternative Med.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>142</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/ajtcam.v13i2.16</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharifi-Rad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anil Kumar</surname><given-names>N.V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zucca</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Lifestyle, Oxidative Stress, and Antioxidants: Back and Forth in the Pathophysiology of Chronic Diseases</article-title>. <source>Front. Physiol.</source><fpage>11</fpage><?supplied-pmid 32116739?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32116739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakaria</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>D.-Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Neuropharmacological potential and delivery prospects of thymoquinone for neurological disorders</article-title>. <source>Oxid. Med. Cell Longev.</source>
<volume>2018</volume>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/1209801</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29743967?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29743967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al Mamun</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jakaria</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Emerging promise of sulforaphane-mediated Nrf2 signaling cascade against neurological disorders</article-title>. <source>Sci. Total Environ.</source>
<volume>707</volume>, <fpage>135624</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.135624</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31784171?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31784171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakaria</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Taurine and its analogs in neurological disorders: Focus on therapeutic potential and molecular mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Redox. Biol.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>101223</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.redox.2019.101223</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31141786?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31141786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakaria</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Go</surname><given-names>E.-A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>S.-H.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>D.-K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Biological evidence of gintonin efficacy in memory disorders</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol. Res.</source><fpage>105221</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phrs.2020.105221</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33007419?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33007419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smolen</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aletaha</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Rheumatoid arthritis</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Dis. Primers</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>18001</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrdp.2018.1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29417936?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29417936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nossent</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlos</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Rheumatoid arthritis: pathological mechanisms and modern pharmacologic therapies</article-title>. <source>Bone Res.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>15</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41413-018-0016-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29736302?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29736302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>da Fonseca</surname><given-names>L.J.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nunes-Souza</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goulart</surname><given-names>M.O.F.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Rabelo</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Oxidative Stress in Rheumatoid Arthritis: What the Future Might Hold regarding Novel Biomarkers and Add-On Therapies</article-title>. <source>Oxid. Med. Cell Longev.</source>
<volume>2019</volume>, <fpage>7536805</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/7536805</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31934269?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31934269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>A panel of microRNAs as a new biomarkers for the detection of deep vein thrombosis</article-title>. <source>J. Thromb. Thrombolysis</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>221</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11239-014-1131-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25244974?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25244974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mannan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawser</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>A.M.A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Assessment of antibacterial, thrombolytic and cytotoxic potential of Cassia alata seed oil</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Pharmaceutical Sci.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>56</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Medicinal plants used by Chakma tribe in Hill Tracts districts of Bangladesh</article-title>. <source>Indian J. Tradit. Knowl.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>508</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>517</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Or Rashid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Biological efficacy of zinc oxide nanoparticles against diabetes: a preliminary study conducted in mice</article-title>. <source>Biosci. Rep.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR20193972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Araby</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Padina tenuis (marine alga) attenuates oxidative stress and streptozotocin-induced type 2 diabetic indices in Wistar albino rats</article-title>. <source>S. Afr. J. Bot.</source>
<volume>128</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2019.09.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of carbon tetrachloride fraction of Actinodaphne angustifolia Nees (Lauraceae) leaf extract for antioxidant, cytotoxic, thrombolytic and antidiarrheal properties</article-title>. <source>Biosci. Rep.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BSR20201110</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kupchan</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsou</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Sigel</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Datiscacin, a novel cytotoxic cucurbitacin 20-acetate from Datisca glomerata</article-title>. <source>J. Org. Chem.</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>1420</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1421</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jo00947a041</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 4694234?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4694234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Raqmi</surname><given-names>K.A.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Mijizy</surname><given-names>Z.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weli</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Riyami</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Study of total phenol, flavonoids contents and phytochemical screening of various leaves crude extracts of locally grown Thymus vulgaris</article-title>. <source>Asian Pacific J. Tropical Biomed.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>705</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>710</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2221-1691(13)60142-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Auwal</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mairiga</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanda</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shuaibu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Preliminary phytochemical and elemental analysis of aqueous and fractionated pod extracts of Acacia nilotica (Thorn mimosa)</article-title>. <source>Vet. Res. Forum.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 25568701?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25568701</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin Mohammad</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Islam Muhammad</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of carbon tetrachloride fraction of Actinodaphne angustifolia Nees (Lauraceae) leaf extract for antioxidant, cytotoxic, thrombolytic and antidiarrheal properties</article-title>. <source>Biosci. Rep.</source><fpage>40</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parvez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jakaria</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sayeed</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>In vitro clot lysis activity of different extracts of mangifera sylvatica roxb. Leaves</article-title>. <source>Res. J. Med. Plant</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakaria</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Talukder</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clinton</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Thrombolysis potential of methanol extracts from the five medicinal plants leaf, available in Bangladesh</article-title>. <source>Pharmacologia</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>78</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5567/pharmacologia.2017.78.82</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Anti-inflammatory, anti-diarrheal, thrombolytic and cytotoxic activities of an ornamental medicinal plant: Persicaria orientalis</article-title>. <source>J. Basic Clin. Physiol. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/jbcpp-2016-0023</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27487493?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27487493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boonyarikpunchai</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sukrong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Towiwat</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Antinociceptive and anti-inflammatory effects of rosmarinic acid isolated from Thunbergia laurifolia Lindl</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol. Biochem. Behav.</source>
<volume>124</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbb.2014.05.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24836183?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24836183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nasrin</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reza</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Curculigo recurvata WT Aiton exhibits anti-nociceptive and anti-diarrheal effects in Albino mice and an in silico model</article-title>. <source>Animal Models Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>181</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ame2.12119</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayeed</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Investigations of analgesic activity of the methanol extract of Haldina cordifolia (Roxb.) bark by using in vivo animal model studies</article-title>. <source>Res. J. Botany</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>98</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>103</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Azam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jakaria</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>I.-S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>D-K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Regulation of toll-like receptor (TLR) signaling pathway by polyphenols in the treatment of age-linked neurodegenerative diseases: focus on TLR4 signaling</article-title>. <source>Front. Immunol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1000</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.01000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31134076?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31134076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakaria</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clinton</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>In vivo sedative and hypnotic activities of methanol extract from the leaves of Jacquemontia paniculata (Burm. f.) Hallier f. in Swiss Albino mice</article-title>. <source>J. Basic Clin. Physiol. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/jbcpp-2016-0073</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28076314?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28076314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakaria</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>D.-Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>I.-S.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>D-K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Active ginseng components in cognitive impairment: Therapeutic potential and prospects for delivery and clinical study</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>33601</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33620</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.26035</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30323902?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30323902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakaria</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karthivashan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S.-Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ganesan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>D-K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Emerging signals modulating potential of ginseng and its active compounds focusing on neurodegenerative diseases</article-title>. <source>J. Ginseng Res.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>171</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jgr.2018.01.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30976157?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30976157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Al Mamun</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Nootropic and anti-Alzheimer's actions of medicinal plants: molecular insight into therapeutic potential to alleviate Alzheimer's neuropathology</article-title>. <source>Mol. Neurobiol.</source>
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>4925</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4944</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12035-018-1420-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30414087?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30414087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yusuf</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lawal</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Pharmacologicaly activities of Azanza garckeana (Goron Tula) grown in Nigeria</article-title>. <source>Clin. Phytosci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40816-020-00173-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>S.I.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jantan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Naturally occurring immunomodulators with antitumor activity: an insight on their mechanisms of action</article-title>. <source>Int. Immunopharmacol.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>304</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2017.07.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28734166?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28734166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Majid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Studies on phytochemical, antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and analgesic activities of Euphorbia dracunculoides</article-title>. <source>BMC Complement. Altern. Med.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>349</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-015-0868-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26445953?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26445953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Herbal neurotoxicity: an introduction to its occurrence and causes</article-title>. <source>Toxicology of herbal products</source>, pp. <fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>362</lpage>, <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almoulah</surname><given-names>N.F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voynikov</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gevrenova</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Antibacterial, antiproliferative and antioxidant activity of leaf extracts of selected Solanaceae species</article-title>. <source>S. Afr. J. Bot.</source>
<volume>112</volume>, <fpage>368</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>374</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2017.06.016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Trichosanthes dioica Roxb. prevents hepatic inflammation and fibrosis in CCl4-induced ovariectomized rats</article-title>. <source>Clin. Nutr. Exp.</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yclnex.2020.07.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferdous</surname><given-names>K.U.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Polyphenolic compounds of amla prevent oxidative stress and fibrosis in the kidney and heart of 2K1C rats</article-title>. <source>Food Sci. Nutr.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>3578</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3589</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.1640</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32724620?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32724620</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakaria</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>S.-H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>I.-S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dash</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>D.-K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Potential Therapeutic Targets of Quercetin and Its Derivatives: Its Role in the Therapy of Cognitive Impairment</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Med.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1789</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm8111789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Antioxidant activity of whole grain Qingke (Tibetan Hordeum vulgare L.) toward oxidative stress in d-galactose induced mouse model</article-title>. <source>J. Funct. Foods</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>362</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jff.2018.04.036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>) <article-title>Antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and antiarthritic potential of Moringa oleifera Lam: An ethnomedicinal plant of Moringaceae family</article-title>. <source>S. Afr. J. Bot.</source>
<volume>128</volume>, <fpage>246</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>256</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2019.11.023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Itu</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Repon</surname><given-names>A.U.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2019</year>) <article-title>Investigation of phytochemicals and in vitro anti-arthritic activity of methanol extract of Maesa indica (Roxb.) leaves</article-title>. <source>J. Pharmacognosy Phytochem.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>323</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rauf</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Tokuda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Cytotoxic, antitumour-promoting and inhibition of protein denaturation effects of flavonoids, isolated from Potentilla evestita Th. Wolf</article-title>. <source>Nat. Prod. Res.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1775</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1778</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14786419.2014.999336</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25588733?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25588733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Ruiz</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matus-Basto</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Acereto-Escoffi&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Segura-Campos</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activities of phenolic compounds isolated from Melipona beecheii honey</article-title>. <source>Food Agricultural Immunol.</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1424</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1437</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09540105.2017.1347148</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jantan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Harikrishnan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Zerumbone suppresses the activation of inflammatory mediators in LPS-stimulated U937 macrophages through MyD88-dependent NF-&#x003ba;B/MAPK/PI3K-Akt signaling pathways</article-title>. <source>Int. Immunopharmacol.</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>312</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>322</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2018.01.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29310107?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29310107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ali Reza</surname><given-names>A.S.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdullah-Al-Mamun</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Antinociceptive and Anxiolytic and Sedative Effects of Methanol Extract of Anisomeles indica: An Experimental Assessment in Mice and Computer Aided Models</article-title>. <source>Front. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>246</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2018.00246</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29706888?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29706888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zihad</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhowmick</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group> (<year>2018</year>) <article-title>Analgesic activity, chemical profiling and computational study on Chrysopogon aciculatus</article-title>. <source>Front. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1164</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2018.01164</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30374304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30374304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleh</surname><given-names>D.O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kassem</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Melek</surname><given-names>F.R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>) <article-title>Analgesic activity of Gleditsia triacanthos methanolic fruit extract and its saponin-containing fraction</article-title>. <source>Pharm. Biol.</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>576</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>580</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 26154522?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26154522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>