<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There is a high correlation between the content and chemical composition of EOs and phenolic compounds and the antioxidant capacity of some medicinal plants with seasonal variations. For instance, the evaluation of the quantity and quality of EOs extracted from different species of 
 <italic class="italic">Ocimum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus</italic> genus, 
 <italic class="italic">Origanum syriacum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha pulegium</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Thymbra spicata</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Satureja thymbra</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia trilobal</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Lanata camara</italic> has shown a wide range of variations during the different months and seasons [
 <xref rid="B9-foods-08-00052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-foods-08-00052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-foods-08-00052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-foods-08-00052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-foods-08-00052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-foods-08-00052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-foods-08-00052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. The same correlation was reported for total phenolic and flavonoid contents as well as the antioxidant capacity of the 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus</italic> genus and 
 <italic class="italic">Vaccinium myrtillus</italic> with the seasonal variations in environmental conditions [
 <xref rid="B9-foods-08-00052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-foods-08-00052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-foods-08-00052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. However, to the best of our knowledge, to date, no information has been reported on the effect of seasonal variations on the quality and quality of secondary metabolites of 
 <italic class="italic">Vitex</italic> genus. Hence, the present study focused, for the first time, on the variability of the chemical profile of Arabian lilac in different months of a year, to determine the best period of harvesting and achieve the highest level of desirable bioactive compounds for uses in pharmaceutical and food industries.
</p>
