<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Supplying plant-derived therapeutics for human illnesses using microbial synthesis could create cheaper, greener and more reliable sources of these compounds as microbes (i) grow faster (hours for yeast as compared to months/years for plants), (ii) can be engineered to produce less complex mixtures of plant natural product, and (iii) can be cultivated using more standardized and easily scalable fermentation and downstream processing methods (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Junker, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Jungbauer, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Buyel et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr">Zydney, 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B121" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2019a</xref>). Budding yeast (
 <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) presents an attractive chassis for refactoring complex biosynthetic pathways of bioactive natural products, thanks to its eukaryotic cell architecture capable of supporting biosynthetic pathways that require significant endomembrane systems (e.g., P450 enzymes) or compartmentalization (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Avalos et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2016</xref>). Indeed, the seminal demonstration of artemisinic acid production in yeast (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">Ro et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">Paddon and Keasling, 2014</xref>) has inspired research into microbial biosynthesis of many more bioactive plant natural products. This is exemplified by the recent engineering of the native yeast mevalonate pathway to enable high flux toward geranyl pyrophosphate (GPP), and introduction of a heterologous hexanoyl-CoA biosynthetic pathway for the complete biosynthesis of cannabinoids (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Luo et al., 2019</xref>). From tyrosine derivatives, biosynthesis of the common benzylisoquinoline alkaloid (BIA) precursor (S)-reticuline was a landmark achievement toward 
 <italic>de novo</italic> biosynthesis of medicinal alkaloids, including hydrocodone, thebaine, stylopine, and noscapine (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Galanie and Smolke, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Hori et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2018</xref>). Likewise, morphinan BIAs codeine and morphine have also been synthesized in yeast based on feeding substrates (R)-reticuline, salutaridine, and codeine (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Fossati et al., 2015</xref>). In addition to BIAs, another major class of alkaloids are the monoterpene indole alkaloids (MIAs) derived from GPP and tryptophan (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">De Luca et al., 2014</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Brown et al. (2015)</xref> demonstrated the 
 <italic>de novo</italic> synthesis of strictosidine, the common precursor of all MIAs, in yeast through the successful refactoring of 12 heterologous enzymatic steps. 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Ehrenworth et al. (2015)</xref> engineered yeast to produce tetrahydrobiopterin for a mono-oxidation of tryptophan to 5-hydroxytryptophan and further onto 5-hydroxytryptamine (serotonin), which when coupled to exogenously fed secologanin enabled production of 10-hydroxystrictosidine. Further downstream of the MIA building blocks, 
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">Qu et al. (2015)</xref> demonstrated the seven-step conversion of tabersonine to the marketed anticancer precursor vindoline. In addition to BIAs and MIAs, the ergot alkaloid precursor chanoclavine-1 and the complex ergot alkaloid cycloclavine derived from tryptophan and the C5 isoprenoid unit dimethylallyl diphosphate (DMAPP) also exemplifies successful hijacking of native yeast metabolites for microbial alkaloid synthesis (
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">Nielsen et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Jakubczyk et al., 2015</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">Milne et al. (2020)</xref> recently reported the refactoring of the hallucinogenic alkaloid psilocybin biosynthetic pathway extending from an engineered shikimate pathway and coupled via tryptophan decarboxylase to yield the starting block tryptamine for four-step psilocybin biosynthesis. Beyond the refactoring of complete alkaloid biosynthetic pathways derived from natural mevalonate pathway C10 and C15 precursor units, GPP and FPP, respectively, 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Ignea et al. (2018)</xref> also refactored biosynthesis of 40 different C11 non-canonical terpene scaffolds, based on 2-methyl GPP production and engineered C11-specific monoterpene synthases. Lastly, tropane alkaloids derived from the arginine and polyamine metabolism biosynthesis, also should be mentioned to emphasize the versatility of yeast metabolism and cell architecture for microbial synthesis of bioactive alkaloids (
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">Ping et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr">Srinivasan and Smolke, 2019</xref>). While this review will focus on two major classes of alkaloids, BIAs and MIAs, it deserves to be mentioned that other branches of yeast’s native metabolism have been harnessed for microbial biosynthesis of non-alkaloid bioactive natural products. This includes the production of methylxanthines from the S-adenosyl methionine (SAM) 
 <italic>de novo</italic> purine synthesis pathways, and adenine nucleotide pools (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">McKeague et al., 2016</xref>), as well as phenylpropanoids resveratrol and breviscapin produced from the shikimate pathway (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Becker et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2018</xref>). Together with an elaborate review of yeast metabolism for the production of broader classes of plant natural products, this has recently been excellently covered by 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. (2020)</xref>.
</p>
