<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0042">The scientific picturespeculates that different stressors, sleep dispossession and sparkling beverages subdue the immune systemby the release of ACTH (Adrenocorticotrophic Hormones) namely, adrenaline, non-adrenaline and glucocorticoids. This in turn makes a person susceptible to pathogenic infections by weakening the immune system of the body. For instance, immune system mediators like NK (Natural Killer) cells, Helper-T-cells, lymphocytes, antibodies, interleukins (IL4, 5, 10, 13), cytokines are impaired that leads to increased chances of infection along with the reactivation of the latent viruses (
 <xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">Calder et al., 2020</xref>). In addition, scarcity of sleep may also hinder the immune pathways within the individual through ACTH-curbed persistent activation of NF-κB that elevates the threat of infections due to plummeted microbial gene expression levels. Meanwhile, the proper sleep balances the hormonal responses within the body to ensure the reorganisation of T-cells towards lymph nodes to boost their immunogenic memory response (
 <xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">Calder et al., 2020</xref>). Moreover, consumption of fizzy drinks or alcohol based beverages causes high glucose or CO
 <sub>2</sub> within blood that in turn causes hypercapnia so as to inhibit macrophage activity and pathogen clearance. It also hampers the immuno-modulators, thereby loss of control on invading pathogens. Whilst, proper sleep, active daily routine, exercise etc. augments the immune-surveillance in the form of NK cells, monocytes, neutrophils, T-cells, Immunoglobulin's etc. to counteract adverse health components (
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">Nieman and Wentz, 2019</xref>). Apart from this, muti-vitamins intake within human body can wash away the sickness forces through recruiting the immune soldiers (
 <xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">Combs and McClung, 2016</xref>). Diet comprising of multi-vitamins wield immune-modulatory possessions on numerous immune cells such as monocytes, neutrophils, lymphocytes, NK cells, dendritic cells that bump up the immunity against pathogens (
 <xref rid="bib0114" ref-type="bibr">Lewis et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0181" ref-type="bibr">Petric, 2020</xref>). Perhaps, these immune cells would trigger the anti-pathogenic responses against coronaviruses via exasperating the levels of Cathelicidin, Defensin β, antimicrobial peptides, phagocytosis, neutrophil migration and chemotaxis, oxidant generation, NK-activation (CD69, CD25), IF-γ, antibodies synthesis, cytokine synthesis and T-cell proliferation respectively.
</p>
