<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The antibacterial and antifungal activity of the essential oils was determined by the agar diffusion method [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>]. This method was preferred over the dilution method because of low solubility of essential oils in water and in meat peptone broth. The following concentrations of essential oils were used: 150; 100; 50; 25; 12.5; 6.25 μL/mL; dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) was used as the solvent. The 100 μL of each oil solution was introduced to the wells in the agar with test microorganisms. Different Gram-positive (
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus subtilis</italic> WT-A, isolated from metal polluted soils of Kajaran, Armenia; 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> MDC 5233 (Microbial Depository Center, Armbiotechnology Scientific and Production Center, Armenia; laboratory control strain) and Gram-negative (
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> VKPM-M17 (Russian National Collection of Industrial Microorganisms at the Institute of Genetics and Selection of Industrial Microorganisms, Russia; laboratory control strain), 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> GRP3 (Soil and Water Research Institute, Iran) bacteria and ampicillin-resistant 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> dhpα-pUC18 were used. Bacterial cultures were grown on Mueller-Hinton agar. Ampicillin (25 μg/mL) as a positive control and DMSO as a negative control were used. The yeasts (
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic> WT-174 isolated from infected vaginal microbiota of hospitalized patients (clinical strain) and 
 <italic class="italic">Debariomyces hansenii</italic> WT (French National Institute for Agricultural Research, France; laboratory control strain) were grown and maintained on Sabouraud-dextrose agar for 24 h at room temperature. As the positive control fluconazole (25 μg/mL) was used. Data were expressed in minimal inhibitory concentrations (MIC) values.
</p>
