<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <p id="Par1">
  <italic>Sphagneticola trilobata</italic> (L.) Pruski is one of the fast-growing malignant weeds in South China. It has severely influenced local biodiversity and native plant habitat. Photosynthesis is the material basis of plant growth and development. However, there are few reports on the photosynthetic transcriptome of 
  <italic>S. trilobata</italic>. In this study, 
  <italic>S. trilobata</italic> had a relatively large leaf area and biomass. The gas exchange parameters per unit area of leaves, including net photosynthetic capacity (P
  <sub>n</sub>), intercellular CO
  <sub>2</sub> (C
  <sub>i</sub>), stomatal conductance (G
  <sub>s</sub>), transpiration rate (T
  <sub>r</sub>), water use efficiency (WUE), photosynthetic pigment and Rubisco protein content were higher than those of the native plant 
  <italic>Sphagneticola calendulacea</italic> (L.) Pruski. On this basis, the differences in photosynthesis pathways between the two 
  <italic>Sphagneticola</italic> species were analyzed by using the Illumina HiSeq platform. The sequencing results for 
  <italic>S. trilobata</italic> and 
  <italic>S. calendulacea</italic> revealed 159,366 and 177,069 unigenes, respectively. Functional annotation revealed 119,350 and 150,846 non-redundant protein database annotations (Nr), 96,637 and 115,711 Swiss-Prot annotations, 49,159 and 60,116 Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes annotations (KEGG), and 83,712 and 97,957 Gene Ontology annotations (GO) in 
  <italic>S. trilobata</italic> and 
  <italic>S. calendulacea</italic>, respectively. Additionally, our analysis showed that the expression of key protease genes involved in the photosynthesis pathway, particularly 
  <italic>CP43</italic>, 
  <italic>CP47</italic>, 
  <italic>PsbA</italic> and 
  <italic>PetC</italic>, had high expression levels in leaves of 
  <italic>S. trilobata</italic> in comparison to native species. Physiological and transcriptomic analyses suggest the high expression of photosynthetic genes ensures the high photosynthetic capacity of leaves, which is one of the inherent advantages underlying the successful invasion by 
  <italic>S. trilobata</italic>.
 </p>
</abstract>
