<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <bold class="bold">Overview:</bold> Propolis is a resinous substance of natural origin, gathered by bees from different parts of plants, shoots, and exudates [
 <xref rid="B179-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">179</xref>,
 <xref rid="B180-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">180</xref>]. Bees utilize it as a sealant for their hives and to avoid the decomposition of creatures killed by the bees after hive invasions [
 <xref rid="B180-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">180</xref>,
 <xref rid="B181-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">181</xref>,
 <xref rid="B182-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">182</xref>]. Chemically, propolis is a lipophilic material that is hard and fragile when cold, but soft, flexible, and very sticky when hot, hence the name bee glue. It has an agreeable aromatic odor, and it varies in color depending on its origin and maturation. The compounds identified in propolis derive from three sources: Plant exudate collected by bees; substances secreted by the metabolism of the bees; and materials that are introduced during the creation of the resin [
 <xref rid="B180-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">180</xref>,
 <xref rid="B183-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">183</xref>,
 <xref rid="B184-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">184</xref>]. The ethanolic extract of propolis (known as propolis balsam) is the most common, but there are other solvents used to separate and identify many of its components. Among the types of chemical substances found in propolis are waxes, resins, balsams/balms, aromatic oils, pollen, flavonoids, terpenoids, and other organic materials (
 <xref rid="nutrients-10-01954-t008" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 8</xref>). The proportions of these substances are variable and depend on the place and time propolis is obtained [
 <xref rid="B183-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">183</xref>]. Propolis has a long history of being utilized in popular medicine dating from at least 300 BC [
 <xref rid="B180-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">180</xref>,
 <xref rid="B183-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">183</xref>,
 <xref rid="B184-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">184</xref>,
 <xref rid="B185-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">185</xref>]; however, over the last decade, it has been found to possess diverse biological activities, and among the most prominent is its antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, antibiotic, and antifungal potential. Recently, propolis has gained popularity as a health beverage; thus, it has been widely utilized in foods and drinks, with the aim of preventing alterations of the heart and chronic degenerative diseases, such as diabetes and cancer [
 <xref rid="B180-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">180</xref>,
 <xref rid="B185-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">185</xref>,
 <xref rid="B186-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">186</xref>,
 <xref rid="B187-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">187</xref>].
</p>
