<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In vitro pepsin digestibility was analyzed according to the AOAC method 971.09 (AOAC International, 
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) with some modifications. Briefly, 2 parallels of 0.5 g were incubated in a 2 mg pepsin/mL solution for 16 h at 40°C in 2 M hydrochloric acid (
 <bold class="bold">HCl</bold>). After digestion, samples were centrifuged (3,230 × g for 20 min) and separated. Both fractions (solubilized and residual) were then dried at 55°C overnight. The remaining moisture content in the samples was determined gravimetrically after drying at 105°C until constant weight of samples was achieved (typically 24 h). Ash content was determined after heating dry samples at 590°C for 12 h. Total N and C were determined by CHNS-O elemental combustion system (ECS 4010, Costech Analytical Technologies Inc., Valencia, CA) in 4 parallels (experiment 1 only). Concentrations of Na were analyzed by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrophotometry after dry ashing according to the AOAC method 999.11, and S by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrophotometry after microwave oven digestion under pressure according to the AOAC method 991.10 (AOAC International, 
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). Fat content was analyzed by acid hydrolysis (Soxtec System, Foss Analytical, Denmark). The AA concentrations in freeze-dried ground samples were analyzed by a high-performance liquid chromatography system (Agilent Infinity 1260, Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA) coupled to an online post-column derivatization module (Pinnacle PCX, Pickering laboratories, Mountain View, CA), using nynhydrin (Trione) as a derivatizing reagent and a Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> exchange column (4.6 × 110 mm, 5 μm). Amounts of AA, taurine, and ammonium (NH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>) were quantified from standard curves. Prior to the analysis, the samples were hydrolyzed in 6 M hydrochloric acid containing 0.4% merkaptoethanol for 24 h at 110°C. Glutamine and asparagine were converted to glutamic and aspartic acid. Cysteine was quantified in its dipeptide form, cystine, but cysteine and its oxidation products could not be detected. The samples were filtered by microfilter, the pH was adjusted to 2.2, and the samples were further diluted with a citrate buffer (pH 2.2) for the high-performance liquid chromatography analysis. Tryptophan was analyzed, but the method was not optimized for that AA.
</p>
