<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">Methane (CH
 <sub>4</sub>) is a greenhouse gas produced by ruminal microorganisms as a consequence of enteric fermentation. Although CH
 <sub>4</sub> is an inevitable product of fermentation, its emission can be decreased by supplementing ruminant diets with specific additives and ingredients. Plants produce a wide variety of secondary metabolites to prevent disease, pest, and predator attacks (
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Jouany and Morgavi, 2007</xref>). Among secondary metabolites, essential oils have been widely evaluated as feed additives for improving microbial metabolism in the rumen and inhibiting methanogenesis (
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Calsamiglia et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Patra and Yu, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Pirondini et al., 2015</xref>). Essential oils are obtained from the steam distillation of plants and include a variable mixture of different compounds, like terpenes and phenylpropanoid derivatives (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Aziz et al., 2018</xref>), characterized by different properties (
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Bakkali et al., 2008</xref>). Many of the active compounds in essential oils have antimicrobial activity. Antimicrobial activity should be evaluated for the selection of additives that can decrease CH
 <sub>4</sub> production without compromising overall fermentation in the rumen. Only a few individual active compounds of essential oils have been tested for their effects on rumen fermentation and CH
 <sub>4</sub> production (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Joch et al., 2018</xref>). In recent studies (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Joch et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), compounds such as bornyl acetate (BOR) and camphor (CAM) decreased CH
 <sub>4</sub> production without adverse effects on short chain fatty acid (SCFA) production during short-term in vitro incubations. Together with eucalyptol (EUCA), CAM and BOR represent the main components of 
 <italic>Achillea moschata</italic> essential oil (
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Vitalini et al., 2016</xref>). 
 <italic>A. moschata</italic> is a plant that has antimicrobial properties (
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Vitalini et al., 2016</xref>), and which has traditionally been used to treat human digestive disorders as well as animal ones (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Vitalini et al., 2015</xref>). The antibacterial properties of the essential oil from 
 <italic>Achillea</italic> spp. are likely to be due to its high concentration of CAM (about 27% of the oil) and EUCA (about 11% of the oil) (
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Si et al., 2006</xref>). Furthermore, in recent studies (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Fidan et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Zerkani et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Baali et al., 2019</xref>), essential oils having BOR among their main constituents also showed antimicrobial activity.
</p>
