<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mango is the main fruit produced in India, accounting for almost 55% of the global production [
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Mango is one of the best sources of nutrient, such as carbohydrates, proteins, and fatty acids. Various parts of mango contain several bioactive phytochemical compounds, namely polyphenols, carotenoids, flavonoids, tannins, and vitamins. The amounts of bioactive and phytochemicals are different in the epicarp, pericarp, and mesocarp. In the recent years, mango cultivation and research has gained popularity due to their potent antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties. Mango pulp is processed into a number of high-value products, like juice, puree, and jam, with the peel and kernel as byproducts. Mango peel is known to contain pectin, dietary fiber, vitamins, carotenoids, and phenolic compounds, having health-promoting effects. Mango seed contains notable amounts of starch, essential amino acids, and oil. Mango seed oil is rich in oleic and stearic acids, and contains different phytochemicals. Mango seed has been used in the production of mango butter and seed flour, which are used in functional foods. The proper use of mango peel and seed (raw materials) in food and feed preparation not only improves the economy, but also reduces the environmental impacts. The bioactive compounds found in the three parts (pulp, peel and seed) of 
 <italic>M. indica</italic>, such as mangiferin, gallic acid, catechin, quercetin, β-carotene, shikimic acid, and kaempferol, have been reported to have antioxidant effects. These compounds are also well-known for their anticancer, anti-diabetic, anti-inflammatory, skin-protecting, neuron-protecting, antimicrobial, and anti-aging effects. However, more pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, and clinical trials are required to assess the toxicity or the safe dose of these molecules. Nevertheless, mango is considered safe and even beneficial for cellular functioning, and regular consumption of fresh mango fruit and/or use of its byproducts could promote overall health. 
</p>
