<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">Diarrhea is one of the water-borne diseases, endemic in various regions of the world and well-recognized as the significant prosperity threats to the world people, both in tropical and subtropical poor countries [
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The major causative agents of diarrhea in human beings include are mainly various enteropathogens including 
 <italic>Shigella flexneri, Escherichia coli, Staphylococcus aureus, Salmonella typhi and Candida albican</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Diarrheal illnesses are a potential explanation behind morbidity and mortality especially in children and young people in developing countries. It will be very acute in infants and elderly people because of severe, conceivabely fatality as a result of dehydration [
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. It ranges from the mild and socially inconvenient sickness to a noteworthy reason for death likely because of the extra impacts of unhealthiness among the children in less developed nations. As of now, the treatment for diarrhea is non-speciﬁc and is typically planned for diminishing the discomfort and burden of frequent bowel movements [
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Pharmaceutical drugs are regularly used to treat diarrhea, but adverse effects can be actuated by these drugs [
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. A few antimicrobial and antidiarrheal agents have been utilized against the improvement of microbial infection and diarrhea. The response of conventional medication as an elective type of healthcare and the advancement of microbial resistant from the available antibiotics have driven specialists to investigate the antimicrobial effects of herbal preparations. Various research work has been suggested that medicinal plants can be a promising source of antidiarrheal medication. Plants containing flavonoids, terpenoids, steroids, phenolic compounds, and alkaloids have been accounted for having antimicrobial action as well as antidiarrheal action [
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].
</p>
