<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Diabetes is a chronic disease that occurs either when the pancreas does not produce enough insulin or when the body cannot effectively use the insulin it produces. Several medicinal plants have demonstrated hypoglycemic and hyperglycemic activities; these activities seem to be mediated through increased insulin secretion via stimulation of pancreatic cells, interfering with dietary glucose absorption or through insulin-sensitizing action [
 <xref rid="B69-plants-10-00032" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Kamel et al. [
 <xref rid="B38-plants-10-00032" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] demonstrated the antidiabetic effect of an aqueous extract of fruit in streptozotocin (STZ)-induced diabetic mice after oral administration. They also identified steroidal saponins, 26-O-ß-D-glucopyranosyl-(25R)-furost-5-ene-3ß,22,26-triol-3-O-[α-L-rhamnophyranosyl-(1→1)]-[ß-D-xylopyranosyl-(1→3)]-[α-L-rhamnopyronosyl-(1→4)]-ß-D-glucopyranoside and its 22-methyl ether in the extract and recognized two additional saponins, 26-O-ß-D-glycopyranosyl-(25R)-furost-5-ene-3ß,22,26,-triol-3-O-[2,4-di-O-α-L-rhamnopyranosyl)-ß-D-glucopyranoside and its methyl ether. A combination of saponins exhibited greater antidiabetic activity than individual saponins. Gad et al. [
 <xref rid="B70-plants-10-00032" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] administered fruit extracts (1.5 g/kg body weight) to STZ-induced diabetic rats and studied the glycogen content of liver and kidney and on some key enzymes of liver involved in carbohydrate metabolism. STZ (50 mg/kg body weight) caused a five-fold increase in blood glucose level, an 80% reduction in serum insulin level, a 58% decrease in liver glycogen and a seven-fold increase in kidney glycogen content. A marked increment in the activity of glucose-6-phosphatase activity and decreased activity of glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase and phosphofructokinase were recorded. Treatment of rats with fruit extract reduced blood glucose levels by 24% and significantly decreased liver glucose-6-phosphatase activity. The authors also demonstrated that the extract inhibited α-amylase activity in vitro. The major component in the extract was diosgenin, based on high-performance thin-layer chromatography. Additionally, Al-Malki et al. [
 <xref rid="B71-plants-10-00032" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] showed that ethyl acetate extract containing β-sitosterol modulated oxidative stress induced by streptozotocin.
</p>
