<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Along with reduced biomass and delayed flowering, another major factor reducing reproductive output in 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> observed in our study was the negative impact of sweet potato on pollinator visitation. 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> depends on insects for sexual reproduction as it is self-incompatible [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. For insect-pollinated plant species, competition for pollinators may lead to changes in visitation frequency or pollinator composition [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] and consequently, a lowered reproductive output [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. In this study, species of Apidae (bee species), Calliphoridae (flies), and Syrphidae (flies) were the most abundant visitors to 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> flowers and were observed to have the longest foraging time of all floral visitors, which is consistent with the results of other studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Overall flower visits of Apidae, Calliphoridae and Syrphidae per inflorescence were reduced significantly with increasing proportions of sweet potato. From October to February in the study area, the temperature gradually became lower and the delayed flowering phenology of 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> corresponded with reduced insect activity. Moreover, in mixed culture, 70–90 % of 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> stems and leaves were covered by sweet potato [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], thus reducing insect visitation via diminished visibility of 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> flowers. Because flowering in both sweet potato and 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> occurs at virtually the same time, pollinators visited both species during the monitoring period; however, because the number of flowers per shoot was at least 15 times greater for 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> than sweet potato [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], the main influence on pollinator visitation was 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> flower number. 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> can produce a large number of flowers and small, light, and wind-dispersed seeds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The negative correlation we observed between seed set and pollinator visitation in 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> is consistent with the commonly observed link between pollinator visitation rate and seed set [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].
</p>
