<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CT-ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid and PVA were selected for the preparation of nanofibrous mats to be employed as carriers of extracts gained by maceration (acetone/water 70/30 
 <italic>v/v</italic>) of 
 <italic>Garcinia mangostana</italic> fruit hull [
 <xref rid="B126-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>], known to exert important antimicrobial properties due to the presence of the α-mangostin (13.20% 
 <italic>w/w</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B170-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>]. α-Mangostin release experiments from the nanofiber mats loaded with the extracts revealed that active molecules were rapidly released, reaching 80% within 1 h. Additionally, the fiber mats loaded with the natural extracts exhibited antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>. More recently, CT and PVA were successfully used to fabricate electrospun nanofibers containing 
 <italic>Bidens pilosa</italic> extract. Composite nanofibers were effective against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> (growth inhibition 91% and MIC 10 mg/mL) and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> (growth inhibition 86% and MIC 10 mg/mL) bacteria due to the combined effect of CT and natural extract [
 <xref rid="B127-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. Polymeric devices with multi-antibacterial activity were prepared by electrospinning of CT and honey, a carbohydrate-rich syrup, showing a relevant wound healing activity and remarkable antibacterial performances [
 <xref rid="B171-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>]. The synthesis of honey-based nanofibers was frequently hard due to the viscosity of the honey that permits its use in the electrospinning process only at small concentrations (&lt;10%) [
 <xref rid="B172-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>]. Electrospinning of CT and honey at high concentration, with PVA and using eco-friendly solvents, was performed, and the antimicrobial activity of the fiber mats was evaluated against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B128-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B129-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. In addition, two aqueous extracts (
 <italic>Cleome droserifolia</italic> and 
 <italic>Allium sativum</italic>) were loaded within honey, PVA, and CT nanofibers; in vitro antimicrobial experiments revealed a complete inhibition of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B130-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. However, only the fibers simultaneously loaded with both the extracts exhibited some antimicrobial activity against methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>. In addition, preliminary in vivo study (wound closure rates in mice and histological examination of the wounds) revealed the beneficial effects of the extract-loaded device on the wound healing process in comparison with the untreated control.
</p>
