<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p id="Par1" class="p">It is well known that aromatic essential oils extracted from the heartwood of 
   <italic class="italic">Santalum album</italic> L. have wide economic value. However, little is known about the role of terpenoids in response to various adverse environmental stresses as other plants do in the form of signals during plant-environment interactions.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p id="Par2" class="p">In this study, trace amounts of volatiles consisting of α-santalene, 
   <italic class="italic">epi</italic>-β-santalene, β-santalene, α-santalol, β-santalol, (
   <italic class="italic">E</italic>)-α-bergamotene, (
   <italic class="italic">E</italic>)-β-farnesene and β-bisabolene were found in the leaves of mature 
   <italic class="italic">S. album</italic> trees. We identified more than 40 candidate terpene synthase (TPS) unigenes by mining publicly-available RNA-seq data and characterized the enzymes encoded by three cDNAs: one mono-TPS catalyzes the formation of mostly α-terpineol, and two multifunctional sesqui-TPSs, one of which produces (
   <italic class="italic">E</italic>)-α-bergamotene and sesquisabinene as major products and another which catalyzes the formation of (
   <italic class="italic">E</italic>)-β-farnesene, (
   <italic class="italic">E</italic>)-nerolidol and (
   <italic class="italic">E,E</italic>)-farnesol as main products. Metabolite signatures and gene expression studies confirmed that santalol content is closely related with santalene synthase (SaSSY) transcripts in heartwood, which is key enzyme responsible for santalol biosynthesis. However, the expression of three new SaTPS genes differed significantly from 
   <italic class="italic">SaSSY</italic> in the essential oil-producing heartwood. Increased activities of antioxidant enzymes, superoxide dismutase, catalase, peroxidase and ascorbate peroxidase, were detected in different tissues of 
   <italic class="italic">S. album</italic> plants after applying 1 mM methyl jasmonate (MeJA) and 1 mM salicylic acid (SA), or exposure to 4°C, 38°C and high light intensity. MeJA and SA dramatically induced the expression of 
   <italic class="italic">SaTPS1</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">SaTPS2</italic> in leaves. 
   <italic class="italic">SaTPS1</italic> to 
   <italic class="italic">3</italic> transcripts were differentially activated among different tissues under adverse temperature and light stresses. In contrast, almost all 
   <italic class="italic">SaSSY</italic> transcripts decreased in response to these environmental stresses, unlike 
   <italic class="italic">SaTPS1</italic> to 
   <italic class="italic">3</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par3" class="p">Multifunctional enzymes were biochemically characterized, including one chloroplastic mono-TPS and two cytosolic sesqui-TPSs in sandalwood. Our results suggest the ecological importance of these three new SaTPS genes in defensive response to biotic attack and abiotic stresses in 
   <italic class="italic">S. album</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Electronic supplementary material</title>
  <p class="p">The online version of this article (10.1186/s12870-019-1720-3) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
