<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Blood levels of vitamin E and selenium were increased in children who consumed milk from cows fed the COANT and OANT diets; the values increased at 28 and 84 days. This increase was associated with a decrease in white blood cell concentrations (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> = 0.001) and an increase in eosinophils (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> = 0.001). Selenium has numerous functions in the body as a component of approximately 25 selenoproteins already identified in the human body that are important in the regulation of various physiological functions. Selenium has been shown to be an important factor in the immunomodulatory response, and its supplementation has already demonstrated a protective effect against certain cancers, especially in populations where dietary selenium deficiency is present [
 <xref rid="B23-nutrients-11-01218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-nutrients-11-01218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Changes in lymphocyte concentrations caused by vitamin E concentrations may be explained by the fact that lymphocytes are cells that are an integral part of the immune defense system. Therefore, any pathological processes in the body, or processes otherwise affected by the number of blood cells, indicate a reaction of the immune system. Vitamin E acts as a free radical scavenger [
 <xref rid="B25-nutrients-11-01218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] and can react with superoxide anions, singlet oxygen, and carboxylic compounds [
 <xref rid="B26-nutrients-11-01218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-nutrients-11-01218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. In addition, vitamin E concentrates inside the membranes and acts synergistically with ascorbate, as it can sequester radicals by the donation of a hydrogen ion, with the radical formation of tocoferoxil, which is regenerated to its reduced form by vitamin C [
 <xref rid="B28-nutrients-11-01218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Platelets are blood cells formed in the bone marrow from megakaryocytes that fragment, so they are anucleate, that is, devoid of a nucleus. Increased eosinophil concentrations (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> = 0.001) at 28 and 84 days of milk supplementation may be associated with an increase in activity of the children’s immune system [
 <xref rid="B24-nutrients-11-01218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>].
</p>
