<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par54">
 <italic>P. cablin</italic> Benth. (patchouli) is an important aromatic plant that is native to southeast Asia and now cultivated widely in many tropical and subtropical regions, including China, Indonesia, the Philippines, and Thailand [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. At present, the analysis and research on the chemical composition of patchouli mainly focus on the volatile oil, which is also known as patchouli oil (PO). Various ingredients have been reported in PO, such as PA, pogostone, α-guaiene, δ-guaiene, β-caryophyllene, trans-caryophyllene, α-patchoulene, β-patchoulene, and β-elemene [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Sesquiterpenes account for a large proportion of PO, and the content of PA is the highest among all the ingredients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. PA, a tricyclic sesquiterpene, can be isolated from the whole herb, stems, and leaves of patchouli by GC, GCMS, NMR, and other analytical methods [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. It possesses multiple bioactivities and is usually remarked as one of the indicators to distinguish the quality of PO. Besides, β-patchoulene and patchoulene epoxide are also the significant sesquiterpenes in PO, and the physicochemical properties as well as biological activities of these two substances have been reported in many researches [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Furthermore, pogostone is also abundant in patchouli, which is the effective ingredient of patchouli oil for insecticidal and antibacterial effects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The detail information of some major and important volatile chemical components of patchouli oil are presented in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. In addition to volatile oil, patchouli also contains a variety of non-volatile components with significant biological activity. So far, more than 50 non-volatile compounds have been discovered in patchouli and their chemical structures have been determined by various analytical methods [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. These compounds can be roughly divided into terpenoids, flavonoids, glycosides, aldehydes, organic acids, and lignins according to their chemical structures. Some major and important compounds such as pachypodol, retusine, ombuin, apigenin, β-Sitosterol, stigmasterol, isocrenatoside, tilianin, 3ʺ-O-Methylcrenatoside, dibutyl phthalate, and tschimganical A have been reported in a number of researches [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. And among them, Pachypodol has attracted extensive attention due to its multiple biological activities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The information of the non-volatile compounds mentioned above are shown in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.
</p>
