<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In 2016 Okuyama and coworkers investigated the ability of 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin to abolish the microglial activation and dopaminergic neuronal cell death in a lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-induced model of Parkinson’s disease [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. This oxyprenylated coumarin, applied at a concentration of 100 μM in every experiment, was able to decrease (80.9%) the LPS-promoted hyperactivation of microglia in the central nervous system, while exhibited only a weak effect on the so called “reactive gliosis”, namely the activation of astrocytes by LPS. Furthermore, 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin showed a marked preventive effect against neuronal death of dopaminergic cells induced by the inflammatory process evoked by the administration of LPS (2.3-fold decrease in respect to controls), confirming what was observed in vitro and in vivo in 2008 and 2009 by Epifano and coworkers [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In 2010, Karimi and coworkers investigated the extent of inhibition of 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin on acetylcholinesterase [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Quite a low value to this respect was recorded (11.7% at a concentration of 100 μM). This was confirmed in 2019 by Erdogan Orhan and coworkers (12.5% inhibition at the same concentration value) [
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. However, in the latter investigation, it was found that 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin exerted a potent inhibitory activity on butyrylcholinesterase (86.9%, IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 11.77 μM), about 3.5-fold higher than galanthamine, which was used as the reference drug (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 46.6 μM). The interaction of the coumarin with this enzyme has been also detailed by in silico experiments showing how 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin is able to tightly interact in its active site with π–π stacking interactions from its aromatic rings with Trp82, and also shows a water-mediated hydrogen bond interaction between the polar site of the ligand and Gly197.
</p>
