<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Blueberries have been cultivated in commercial plantations in Lower Saxony since the early 1930’s [
 <xref rid="B14-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Since then, the area under cultivation has steadily increased. In 2005, the area with blueberry cultivation in Lower Saxony was approximately 1400 hectares [
 <xref rid="B13-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In nature, blueberries are mainly distributed by birds and small mammals, who spread the seeds. Once established, plants can spread in a vicinity by clonal growth and the high regeneration potential of blueberries favours a strong spread [
 <xref rid="B10-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The species prefers acidic locations, such as pine forests or wetlands. Especially, raised bogs in their degeneration stage provide ideal habitat conditions for invasive blueberries [
 <xref rid="B14-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Thus, blueberries are growing increasingly wild in neighbouring areas. References [
 <xref rid="B9-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] found a correlation between the density of blueberries and the distance to blueberry plantations; a maximum distance of 1700 m was recorded. Near cultivated areas, the feral blueberries form dense shrub stands with height of up to 2–3 m and have a ground coverage of up to &gt;60%. With increasing distance, the degree of coverage decreases rapidly [
 <xref rid="B8-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Since these studies were already conducted in the last millennium, a larger distribution must be expected today. Reference [
 <xref rid="B10-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] describes a distribution of blueberry bushes over 4 ha in the “Krähenmoor”, where the maximum distance to the plantation was identified at 100 m. Blueberry bushes are low and can reach a height of 60 cm, but, occasionally, tall species can be found with a height of 3 m [
 <xref rid="B10-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In the course of the increasing growth and dense shrub structures, other ground vegetation is displaced, since it cannot exist under the shade of blueberries. Other presumed effects of blueberry cultivation are reduced evaporation rates and the influence on nutrient cycles in wetlands, which, in turn, can have an impact on existing plant species. Therefore, human interventions are necessary to protect the sensitive rare structures and characteristic plants of wetlands [
 <xref rid="B10-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
</p>
