<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Jujube is not only consumed as daily food, but also prescribed as a tonic TCM for blood nourishment in a formulated decoction. Among these jujube-containing mixtures, Guizhi Tang (GZT), written by Zhang Zhongjing, a great Chinese medicine practitioner in Han Dynasty (∼200 AD), composed of jujube and other four medicinal herbs is still popularly used today to deal with common cold, fever and headaches in Asian countries, including China, Japan and Korea (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Yoo et al., 2016</xref>). GZT belongs to exterior-releasing formula that is able to dispel pathogenic factors from superficies of body, and the effect of jujube within this formula is believed to tonify “Qi” and to replenish “Blood” of the body resulting from corresponding pathological changes. 
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Yoo et al. (2016)</xref> reported that application of GZT extract in cultured RAW264.7 macrophages showed anti-inflammatory activity, which involved in blocking ERK and NF-κB signaling pathways. The cells were pre-treated with GZT (31.25–1,000 μg/ml) for 4 h prior to application of LPS for an additional 20 h. The treatment with GZT extract enhanced the expression of HO-1 and significantly inhibited pro-inflammatory cytokines, e.g., TNF-α and IL-6, in LPS-induced macrophages. Besides, GZT extract prevented ERK phosphorylation and NF-κB translocation in LPS-treated macrophages (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Yoo et al., 2016</xref>). In another experiment, 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al. (2016)</xref> investigated the inductive roles of GZT on EPO expression in cultures. Cultured Hep3B cells were treated with GZT extracts (0.5–4.0 mg/ml) for 24 h. Applied GZT was able to stimulate the mRNA and protein expressions of EPO. In addition, GZT stimulated the transcriptional activity of HRE in a dose-dependent manner (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2016</xref>). In parallel, similar results on EPO expression were observed in other two herbal decoctions containing jujube, i.e., Neibu Dangguijianzhong written by Sun Simiao in Tang Dynasty (652 AD) and Zao Tang recorded in Official Bureau of Physicans in Sung Dynasty (1,078–1,085 AD) (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2016</xref>). In Zhigancao Tang, jujube combining with ginseng was used to tonify the “Qi.” Besides, jujube was proposed to regulate the relationship between protective and nutritive “Qi.” Nevertheless, jujube showed similar function with other herbal formulae in treating “Qi” and “Blood” deficiency, e.g., Renshen Yangying Tang, Bazhen Tang and Xiangbei Yangying Tang.
</p>
