<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several essential oils show antibacterial and antioxidant activity, together with antiviral function [
 <xref rid="B140-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>]. For instance, oregano, thyme, cinnamon, and allspice (a berry from 
 <italic>Pimenta dioica</italic> used commonly in the food industry) extracts, amongst others, can reduce the growth of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> O157 [
 <xref rid="B141-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>,
 <xref rid="B142-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. A 4% 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic> solution of cinnamon oil, whose main component is cinnamaldehyde, inhibited the growth of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> O157 in vitro, but sub-inhibitory doses reduced the expression of 
 <italic>Stx2</italic> and the release of viral progeny [
 <xref rid="B72-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B94-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. As in the case of EGCG, the interference over phage induction was accompanied by down-regulation of the effector of the stress pathway 
 <italic>recA</italic>, but also of the quorum sensing (QS) (
 <italic>qseB</italic>, 
 <italic>qseC,</italic> and 
 <italic>luxS</italic>) and oxydative stress (
 <italic>oxyR</italic>, 
 <italic>soxR</italic>, and 
 <italic>rpoS</italic>) pathways, as well as the polynucleotide phosphorylase PAP I [
 <xref rid="B94-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>], which is also an inducer of 933 W [
 <xref rid="B143-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. These results suggest that cinnamon oil could interfere with 933 W induction as several overlapping levels. Furthermore, cinnamon oil disrupted 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> O156 and 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> biofilms by interfering with the formation of the fimbriae, which are required to make inter-bacterial connections [
 <xref rid="B72-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B94-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. Oregano had a general suppressive action upon prophages, but the effect was stronger in 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> than in 
 <italic>E. faecalis</italic> or 
 <italic>B. thetaiotamicron</italic> [
 <xref rid="B68-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Eugenol, which is rich in allspice and clove, reduced the induction of both Stx1 and Stx2, and inhibit the growth of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> O157 in vitro [
 <xref rid="B144-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>].
</p>
