<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2-ijms-18-01212" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Antioxidant Activities</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reactive oxygen species are involved in the pathological development of many important human diseases, thus antioxidants play a crucial role in human health due to their unquestionable beneficial effects on living organisms that enable them to overcome oxidative injuries, and modulate biological pathways and membrane functionality [
  <a rid="B23-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijms-18-01212">23</a>]. In this article, the authors conducted the analysis of antioxidant and free radical scavenging properties of HEO by using several antioxidant assays (hydrogen atom transfer and electron transfer-based methods) in order to check their behaviour under different reaction environments and mechanism typologies. This aspect is often overlooked but is critical in order to establish the structure-scavenging activity relationship of the major components of the phytocomplex investigated [
  <a rid="B24-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijms-18-01212">24</a>]. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-18-01212-f001" href="#ijms-18-01212-f001">Figure 1</a> shows the antioxidant and free radical-scavenging potential of HEO towards Fe
  <span class="sup">3+</span>-TPTZ (A), ABTS
  <span class="sup">•+</span> (B), and 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH)
  <span class="sup">•</span> (C) as well as its iron chelating capacity (D). Moreover, the antiradical properties of HEO against two of the most common and dangerous reactive oxygen species produced in the organisms, superoxide anion (O
  <sub>2</sub>
  <span class="sup">•−</span>) and hydroxyl radical (
  <span class="sup">•</span>OH), was investigated and reported in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-18-01212-f002" href="#ijms-18-01212-f002">Figure 2</a>A,B. As can be seen in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-18-01212-f001" href="#ijms-18-01212-f001">Figure 1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-18-01212-f002" href="#ijms-18-01212-f002">Figure 2</a>, the HEO showed a remarkable dose-dependent antioxidant and free-radical scavenging activity towards all assays performed, with the following order of potency, expressed as the half maximal inhibitory concentration (IC
  <sub>50</sub>), 
  <span class="sup">•</span>OH (IC
  <sub>50</sub> 0.003 mg/mL) &gt; Ferric Reducing Antioxidant Power (FRAP; IC
  <sub>50</sub> 0.063 mg/mL) &gt; Trolox Equivalent Antioxidant Capacity (TEAC; IC
  <sub>50</sub> 0.128 mg/mL) &gt; DPPH (IC
  <sub>50</sub> 0.878 mg/mL) as well as having showed a strong iron chelating capacity (IC
  <sub>50</sub> 0.017 mg/mL). The strong antioxidant activity was also confirmed by Folin-Ciocalteu assay results (1278.44 ± 41.79 mg gallic acid equivalents (GAE)/100 g of HEO).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ability to scavenge different reactive species makes the HEO an important source of antioxidants that are potentially useful in the detoxification mechanisms of living organism. Primary and relative weak antioxidants (such as O
  <sub>2</sub>
  <span class="sup">•−</span>), in fact, can be the precursor or be combined with others (e.g., nitric oxide) to give rise to very dangerous reactive species (hydrogen peroxide, hydroxyl radical, singlet oxygen, peroxynitric radical, and so on). Furthermore, HEO, acting as a strong chelating agent, may reduce the availability of transition metals and inhibit the radical-mediated oxidative chain reactions in biological systems preserving the integrity and consequently the functionality of membranes. As showed in β-carotene bleaching assay (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-18-01212-f003" href="#ijms-18-01212-f003">Figure 3</a>), in fact, the presence of these antioxidant compounds in HEO, mainly 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-Cymene, Borneol, and β-Myrcene, are able to form radical adduct with peroxyl radical [
  <a rid="B30-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijms-18-01212">30</a>]; the compounds exhibit antioxidant properties and are capable of preventing oxidative damage from free radical-mediated oxidation in a dose-dependent manner.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These activities are predominantly attributable to the high amount of monoterpenes hydrocarbons found in HEO. In fact, it has widely been demonstrated that monoterpene hydrocarbons are better antioxidant compounds in respect to sesquiterpenes and particularly those with strongly activated methylene groups in their structure, such as 4-Carene, α-Terpinene, and γ-Terpinene, were the most active. So, in agreement with the data reported in literature [
  <a rid="B31-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijms-18-01212">31</a>], among oxygenated monoterpenes, the following order of effectiveness in antioxidant assays can be also hypothesised in our work: monoterpene phenols &gt; allylic alcohols &gt; monoterpenes aldehydes and ketones.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concerning the sesquiterpene group, the radical scavenging properties of the hydrocarbons-type were quite low and lower than that of the monoterpene hydrocarbons group, whereas among the oxygenated type, mainly allylic alcohols showed good scavenging properties, similar to those of oxygenated monoterpenes [
  <a rid="B31-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijms-18-01212">31</a>], but they are completely lacking in this essential oil.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, being a very complex matrix, the antioxidant properties of the essential oil do not always depend on the antioxidant activity of its main components and can be modulated by several mechanisms, so concepts of synergism and antagonism can be very relevant [
  <a rid="B30-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijms-18-01212">30</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
