<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-ijms-18-01212" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-ijms-18-01212" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Essential Oil Composition</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The yield of hull essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">Pistacia vera</span> L. variety Bronte (HEO) was 0.25% (
   <span class="italic">v</span>/
   <span class="italic">w</span> fresh material), well above others reported in literature (&gt;3.50 times) [
   <a rid="B20-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijms-18-01212">20</a>], demonstrating how the Bronte variety possesses a much higher content of essential oil, probably due to characteristic pedoclimatic conditions of growth and probably to the extraction carried out immediately after harvest, which allowed for an increase in the extraction efficiency. This practice also led to a reduced formation of peroxidation, isomerization, or rearrangement of products due to temperature, light, and oxygen availability [
   <a rid="B29-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijms-18-01212">29</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil composition, with retention indices and percentages, was reported in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="ijms-18-01212-t001" href="#ijms-18-01212-t001">Table 1</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 40 volatile constituents were identified, fully characterized, and grouped in four classes: monoterpene hydrocarbons, oxygenated monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, and others (non-terpenoidic compounds). The major components of HEO were 4-Carene (31.743%), α-Pinene (23.584%), 
   <span class="sc">d</span>-Limonene (8.002%), and 3-Carene (7.731%), all monoterpenes hydrocarbons that represented 86.591% of the HEO, followed by oxygenated monoterpenes, which presented an average value of 8.235% with α-Terpineol (4.036%), Borneol (0.831%), and α-Pinene oxide (0.787%) as the main compounds.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the monoterpenes hydrocarbons remained the most abundant family, followed by oxygenated monoterpenes (reflecting the results reported in the literature [
   <a rid="B20-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijms-18-01212">20</a>]), the characteristic absence of oxygenated sesquiterpenes and the very low presence of non-oxygenated sesquiterpenes, makes the essential oil of Bronte pistachio hulls easily recognized and distinguishable from essential oils derived from other pistachio hull varieties.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-ijms-18-01212" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Antioxidant Activities</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reactive oxygen species are involved in the pathological development of many important human diseases, thus antioxidants play a crucial role in human health due to their unquestionable beneficial effects on living organisms that enable them to overcome oxidative injuries, and modulate biological pathways and membrane functionality [
   <a rid="B23-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijms-18-01212">23</a>]. In this article, the authors conducted the analysis of antioxidant and free radical scavenging properties of HEO by using several antioxidant assays (hydrogen atom transfer and electron transfer-based methods) in order to check their behaviour under different reaction environments and mechanism typologies. This aspect is often overlooked but is critical in order to establish the structure-scavenging activity relationship of the major components of the phytocomplex investigated [
   <a rid="B24-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijms-18-01212">24</a>]. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-18-01212-f001" href="#ijms-18-01212-f001">Figure 1</a> shows the antioxidant and free radical-scavenging potential of HEO towards Fe
   <span class="sup">3+</span>-TPTZ (A), ABTS
   <span class="sup">•+</span> (B), and 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH)
   <span class="sup">•</span> (C) as well as its iron chelating capacity (D). Moreover, the antiradical properties of HEO against two of the most common and dangerous reactive oxygen species produced in the organisms, superoxide anion (O
   <sub>2</sub>
   <span class="sup">•−</span>) and hydroxyl radical (
   <span class="sup">•</span>OH), was investigated and reported in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-18-01212-f002" href="#ijms-18-01212-f002">Figure 2</a>A,B. As can be seen in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-18-01212-f001" href="#ijms-18-01212-f001">Figure 1</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-18-01212-f002" href="#ijms-18-01212-f002">Figure 2</a>, the HEO showed a remarkable dose-dependent antioxidant and free-radical scavenging activity towards all assays performed, with the following order of potency, expressed as the half maximal inhibitory concentration (IC
   <sub>50</sub>), 
   <span class="sup">•</span>OH (IC
   <sub>50</sub> 0.003 mg/mL) &gt; Ferric Reducing Antioxidant Power (FRAP; IC
   <sub>50</sub> 0.063 mg/mL) &gt; Trolox Equivalent Antioxidant Capacity (TEAC; IC
   <sub>50</sub> 0.128 mg/mL) &gt; DPPH (IC
   <sub>50</sub> 0.878 mg/mL) as well as having showed a strong iron chelating capacity (IC
   <sub>50</sub> 0.017 mg/mL). The strong antioxidant activity was also confirmed by Folin-Ciocalteu assay results (1278.44 ± 41.79 mg gallic acid equivalents (GAE)/100 g of HEO).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ability to scavenge different reactive species makes the HEO an important source of antioxidants that are potentially useful in the detoxification mechanisms of living organism. Primary and relative weak antioxidants (such as O
   <sub>2</sub>
   <span class="sup">•−</span>), in fact, can be the precursor or be combined with others (e.g., nitric oxide) to give rise to very dangerous reactive species (hydrogen peroxide, hydroxyl radical, singlet oxygen, peroxynitric radical, and so on). Furthermore, HEO, acting as a strong chelating agent, may reduce the availability of transition metals and inhibit the radical-mediated oxidative chain reactions in biological systems preserving the integrity and consequently the functionality of membranes. As showed in β-carotene bleaching assay (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-18-01212-f003" href="#ijms-18-01212-f003">Figure 3</a>), in fact, the presence of these antioxidant compounds in HEO, mainly 
   <span class="italic">p</span>-Cymene, Borneol, and β-Myrcene, are able to form radical adduct with peroxyl radical [
   <a rid="B30-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijms-18-01212">30</a>]; the compounds exhibit antioxidant properties and are capable of preventing oxidative damage from free radical-mediated oxidation in a dose-dependent manner.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These activities are predominantly attributable to the high amount of monoterpenes hydrocarbons found in HEO. In fact, it has widely been demonstrated that monoterpene hydrocarbons are better antioxidant compounds in respect to sesquiterpenes and particularly those with strongly activated methylene groups in their structure, such as 4-Carene, α-Terpinene, and γ-Terpinene, were the most active. So, in agreement with the data reported in literature [
   <a rid="B31-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijms-18-01212">31</a>], among oxygenated monoterpenes, the following order of effectiveness in antioxidant assays can be also hypothesised in our work: monoterpene phenols &gt; allylic alcohols &gt; monoterpenes aldehydes and ketones.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concerning the sesquiterpene group, the radical scavenging properties of the hydrocarbons-type were quite low and lower than that of the monoterpene hydrocarbons group, whereas among the oxygenated type, mainly allylic alcohols showed good scavenging properties, similar to those of oxygenated monoterpenes [
   <a rid="B31-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijms-18-01212">31</a>], but they are completely lacking in this essential oil.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, being a very complex matrix, the antioxidant properties of the essential oil do not always depend on the antioxidant activity of its main components and can be modulated by several mechanisms, so concepts of synergism and antagonism can be very relevant [
   <a rid="B30-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijms-18-01212">30</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-ijms-18-01212" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Cytoprotective Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The potential protective influences of the compounds present in HEO were analysed on lymphocytes treated with tert-butyl hydroperoxide (
   <span class="italic">t</span>-BOOH). A preliminary evaluation, obtained by incubating the cells with the essential oil at the concentration utilized in our work, shows no cytotoxicity effects of lymphocytes (data not shown). As can be seen in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-18-01212-f004" href="#ijms-18-01212-f004">Figure 4</a>, the treatment of lymphocytes with 
   <span class="italic">t</span>-BOOH resulted in a net increase of cell mortality (~41% fall in cell viability vs. controls). The presence of 20, 17.5, 15, and 12.5 µg/mL of essential oil significantly increased cell viability by ~1.50, 1.40, 1.20, and 1.12-fold, respectively, compared cells treated only with 
   <span class="italic">t</span>-BOOH (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-18-01212-f004" href="#ijms-18-01212-f004">Figure 4</a>A). Below this concentration, the effects were almost completely absent, with results superimposable with the ones obtained with lymphocytes treated with 
   <span class="italic">t</span>-BOOH. The protective influences of the compounds present in the essential oil were also evident by monitoring lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) release in cell culture medium. In fact, this enzyme is commonly utilized as a marker of cell integrity and cytotoxicity, following oxidative burden, membrane damages, activation of apoptotic, and/or necrotic events. As we expected (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-18-01212-f004" href="#ijms-18-01212-f004">Figure 4</a>B), the incubation of lymphocytes with 
   <span class="italic">t</span>-BOOH resulted in a remarkable increase of LDH release into the media (~4.2-fold higher than the control). The presence of 20 µg/mL of essential oil resulted in the complete absence of LDH release, confirming the data obtained with trypan blue coloration. The presence of 17.5, 15, 12, and 10 µg/mL of essential oil decreased enzyme release by ~66%, 52%, 31%, and 6%, respectively, in comparison to the sample treated with only 
   <span class="italic">t</span>-BOOH, while concentrations below 10 µg/mL did not show a significant decrease of LDH release. Overall, the compounds present in the hull essential oil showed dose-response activity whereby they increased cell survival and prevented damages due to the presence of the strong antioxidant.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot4-ijms-18-01212" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Antimicrobial Activities</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The minimal inhibitory concentrations (MICs) and minimal bactericidal concentrations (MBCs) values of HEO against the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC) and clinical isolates tested bacteria are reported in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="ijms-18-01212-t002" href="#ijms-18-01212-t002">Table 2</a>. Results of negative controls indicated the complete absence of inhibition of all the strains tested (data not shown). A concentration of 7.11 mg/mL inhibited the growth of all the tested strains with the exception of 
   <span class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> ATCC 9027. The same concentration was found to be bactericidal against all strains. Several studies have previously demonstrated the antimicrobial activity of plant essential oils [
   <a rid="B32-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijms-18-01212">32</a>,
   <a rid="B33-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijms-18-01212">33</a>,
   <a rid="B34-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijms-18-01212">34</a>]. The compound 4-carene, also identified amongst the main constituents of the Iranian Cymbobogon Olivieri essential oil, has been implicated in the antimicrobial activity against Gram-positive bacteria, Gram-negative bacteria, and the yeast 
   <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span> [
   <a rid="B35-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijms-18-01212">35</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The seed oil from the Tunisian endemic 
   <span class="italic">Ferula tunetana</span> Pomel ex Batt. containing α-pinene (39.8%) was also found active against 
   <span class="italic">Salmonella typhimurium</span> LT2 DT104 and 
   <span class="italic">Bacillus cereus</span> ATCC 14,579, with inhibition zones of 16.2 ± 1.0 mm and 15.8 ± 1.0 mm, respectively [
   <a rid="B36-ijms-18-01212" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijms-18-01212">36</a>]. Although we have not performed any mechanistic investigation in the present study, we believe the polyphenols present in HEO damaged the cell wall or cell membrane.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
