<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the search for novel drugs before turning to potentially hazardous laboratory experiments, one should exploit the swiftly developing computer technology. Computers not only improve laboratory work plans but also predict several properties of single molecules or entire molecular systems under various conditions and even carry our simulations of chemical reactions and of more and more biological cellular processes. Cancer really represents plague of the modern era and investigating cancerogenic substances without physically exposing oneself to them certainly poses a significant advantage. For that, it is reasonable to investigate the antigenotoxic potential of natural compounds found in hops also through quantum chemistry-based reaction simulations. Such simulations enable uncovering the mechanisms of action of known antigenotoxic agents and even reveal new potential antigenotoxic agents. In silico quantum–chemical methods used by our laboratory carry a great potential as they are safe, effective, relatively fast, cost-effective and more importantly exhibit a good correlation with the laboratory experiments [
 <xref rid="B166-nutrients-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">166</xref>,
 <xref rid="B167-nutrients-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">167</xref>,
 <xref rid="B168-nutrients-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">168</xref>]. In order to explore the antigenotoxic potential of a specific substance, we first obtain geometrically optimized structures of the species of interest like carcinogenic substance, DNA bases, or potential antigenotoxic agent. Next, we locate, with several quantum–chemical methods and basis sets, reactant, and transition state structures for the reaction of our interest in order to determine the energetic barrier—activation energy. In order to find potential antigenotoxic agents, it is necessary to perform such calculations for the reaction of a carcinogenic substance with DNA and with potential antigenotoxic substances so as to get comparison which of the reactions is energetically more favorable and therefore plausible. The reaction of scavenging (antigenotoxic) compound with the carcinogenic substance must be faster/energetically more favorable than the reaction between carcinogen and the DNA in order to prevent the genotoxicity caused by the carcinogen. 
</p>
