<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f1-dddt-12-2731" position="float" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Figure 1</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">DCEO inhibited the production of NO and PGE2 and the expression of iNOS and COX-2 in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 cells.</p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Notes:</bold> Cells were incubated with indicated concentrations of DCEO for 24 h with or without LPS. Cell viability was determined by the MTT assay. Results were expressed as percentages of respective controls (
   <bold class="bold">A</bold>). Cells were incubated with indicated concentrations of DCEO for 1 h and then stimulated with LPS for 24 h. The production of NO was indicated by the level of nitrite formed in the supernatant detected using the Griess reagent. PGE2 production was measured by ELISA (
   <bold class="bold">B</bold> and 
   <bold class="bold">C</bold>). The protein levels of iNOS and COX-2 were determined by immunoblotting. Representative blots of iNOS and COX-2 are shown (
   <bold class="bold">D</bold>). Bar graphs show the relative levels of iNOS and COX-2 in RAW264.7 cells (
   <bold class="bold">E</bold> and 
   <bold class="bold">F</bold>). Cells were incubated with indicated concentrations of DCEO for 1 h and then stimulated with LPS for 6 h. The mRNA levels of iNOS and COX-2 were determined by qRT-PCR (
   <bold class="bold">G</bold> and 
   <bold class="bold">H</bold>). Data presented in bar charts are mean±SEM values from three independent experiments. 
   <sup class="sup">**</sup>
   <italic class="italic">P</italic>&lt;0.01 vs unstimulated cells. 
   <sup class="sup">***</sup>
   <italic class="italic">P</italic>&lt;0.05 and 
   <sup class="sup">****</sup>
   <italic class="italic">P</italic>&lt;0.01 vs LPS-stimulated cells determined by Dunnett’s multiple comparisons test.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Abbreviations:</bold> DCEO, Dingchuan tang essential oil; NO, nitric oxide; PGE2, prostaglandin E2; iNOS, inducible nitric oxide synthase; COX-2, cyclooxygenase-2; LPS, lipopolysaccharide; MTT, 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenylthiazolium bromide; ELISA, enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; qRT-PCR, quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction; SEM, standard error of the mean.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="dddt-12-2731Fig1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
