<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To improve the utility of promiscuous enzymes, studies have implemented rational enzyme engineering, directed evolution and synthetic biology to assess and improve substrate scope (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Glenn et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Payne et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr">Shepherd et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Neubauer et al., 2020</xref>), regio-specificity (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Lang et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Andorfer et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr">Shepherd et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">Moritzer et al., 2019</xref>), stability (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Payne et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Poor et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">Minges et al., 2020</xref>) and activity (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Andorfer et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Kong et al., 2020</xref>) of FDH halogenases (
 <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Of particular interest are a study deploying directed evolution to yield RebH variants targeting positions 5, 6, and 7 of tryptamine (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Andorfer et al., 2016</xref>), which could help to avoid the tryptophan decarboxylase bottleneck, and a study in which the substrate specificity of RebH was evolved to target, albeit with lower activities, “late-stage” MIAs such as the yohimbines (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Payne et al., 2015</xref>), which may allow promiscuity requirements to be eschewed entirely. These studies have relied on HPLC as a detection method, often limiting the size of the library that can be screened (
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">Schnepel and Sewald, 2017</xref>). The recent development of novel, transcription factor-based biosensors returning a fluorescent output in response to 5- or 6-bromotryptophan (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Ellefson et al., 2018</xref>) may, in combination with multiplex screening (e.g., fluorescence-activated cell sorting), underpin the screening of larger mutant libraries for optimization of the aforementioned parameters in the intracellular environment of yeast strains.
</p>
