<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With the recent refactoring of the 
 <italic>de novo</italic> strictosidine production in yeast (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Brown et al., 2015</xref>), it is expected that there will soon exist a microbial platform in which the combinatorial effects of the above-mentioned learnings can be more systematically tested. Such strains will be invaluable tools for further study because understanding of enzyme promiscuity remains patchy for the pathway leading up to strictosidine and extremely sparse for enzymes beyond this branch point. This is principally because it is only very recently that some of these modules have been fully elucidated and enzymes are still being identified (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Caputi et al., 2018</xref>). The situation is further complicated by the fact that downstream substrates become increasingly complex, making derivatives difficult and expensive to chemically synthesis, leaving enzymatic synthesis as the only alternative (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). This creates a catch-22 in which it is difficult to study 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> enzyme promiscuity without the substrate analogs, yet we cannot effectively produce the substrate analogs without understanding the enzyme promiscuity. If the promiscuity of these downstream modules is to be systematically assessed and engineered 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> or 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, biological platforms producing substrate analogs will have to be developed first. At first glance, source plants may look like attractive targets for these platforms. However, MIA-producing plants often possess multiple competing branches downstream of strictosidine, meaning that a small drop in turnover could cause another branch to outcompete and completely remove flux from the target branch, making it appear that there is no promiscuity. This effect was neatly demonstrated by 
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">Runguphan et al. (2010)</xref>, who observed that substrate halogenation altered the major MIA products in 
 <italic>C. roseus</italic>. The development of dependable, strictosidine analog-producing yeast strains, into which individual downstream MIA branches can be modularly expressed and systematically studied and engineered, will greatly accelerate our progress toward probing the derivative space surrounding MIA scaffolds.
</p>
