<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Olive oil has been shown to possess several classes of glycerophospholipids (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="foods-07-00109-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>), but the presence and amount of each class vary considerably among studies (
 <xref rid="foods-07-00109-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Authors found that the main glycerophospholipid class is PG [
 <xref rid="B16-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], PE [
 <xref rid="B17-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], PA [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>], or lyso-PA [
 <xref rid="B19-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. In Greek VOOs, glycerophospholipids were identified and quantified by 
 <sup class="sup">31</sup>P-NMR [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. PA, PI, and lyso-PA were the major classes identified, but PC, PE, and lyso-PI were also found. PG was only detected in one olive pomace oil that showed higher diversity and concentration in the glycerophospholipid classes: PA, lyso-PA, PI and lyso-PI [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. The MS-based approaches used by other researchers also led to different results. The glycerophospholipid profile of a commercial Tunisian olive oil was composed by PG, PA, PI, PE, and PC (by descending order of abundance) [
 <xref rid="B16-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. In a monovarietal commercial olive oil from the Spanish cultivar Arbequina, the glycerophospholipid classes identified were, by descending order, PE, PG, PC, lyso-PE and lyso-PA [
 <xref rid="B17-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. The glycerophospholipid classes from an Italian VOO blend with Leccino, Frantoio, and Picholine cultivars were PG, PA, lyso-PA, PI, PC and lyso-PC [
 <xref rid="B19-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Calvano et al. (2012) identified different molecular species of PC in one commercial olive oil [
 <xref rid="B13-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Molecular species of PA, PE, PG, PC, and PI were identified in Portuguese commercial olive oils, as well as other lipid molecules not identified previously in this matrix [
 <xref rid="B12-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Glycolipids as DGDG(18:3/18:3) and DGDG(18:3/18:1) were identified in one Italian olive oil [
 <xref rid="B20-foods-07-00109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. 
 <xref rid="foods-07-00109-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref> summarizes the main results of each of these works. All the molecular species of glycerophospholipids and glycolipids identified by the MS-based lipidomic approaches, both in olives and olive oil, are listed in 
 <xref rid="foods-07-00109-t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="foods-07-00109-t003" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>, respectively.
</p>
