<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48" class="p">A change in intestinal microbiota is often accompanied by changes in microbial metabolism [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>]. Undigested carbohydrates in stomach and small intestine can be fermented by microbes with the production of SCFAs in the large intestine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>]. SCFAs, including acetate, propionate, and butyrate, play an important role in the metabolic functions of the gut. In the present study, the 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae induced an increase in the concentration of total SCFAs and butyrate. Previous studies also observed that 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae as a soybean meal substitute increase the concentration of SCFAs in the cecum of laying hens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>]. This increase may have been the result of an increased abundance or the number of microbes capable of producing butyrate in the colon. The correlation analysis indicated the trophic linkage between the abundance of 
 <italic class="italic">Roseburia</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudobutyrivibrio</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Faecalibacterium</italic>, the number of 
 <italic class="italic">Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa and butyrate concentration in the colonic digesta, suggesting that the increase in 
 <italic class="italic">Roseburia</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudobutyrivibrio</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Faecalibacterium</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa may have resulted in the increase in colonic butyrate concentration. Additionally, 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae are rich in chitin, which can not be degraded or absorbed by the small intestine but can flow into the large intestine, and subsequently be fermented by bacteria in large intestine. Thus, another potential explanation for the increase in butyrate concentration may be attributed to the alteration of substrate for microbial fermentation after administering 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae. Butyrate is the major energy source for colonic epithelial cells and exerts an anti-inflammatory function [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>]. Therefore, the increase in butyrate concentration in the current study suggests a host-friendly gut environment after administering 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae.
</p>
