<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Fatty acid methyl ester (FAME) called as biodiesel is produced by transesterification or esterification; a chemical reaction between alcohol and triacylglycerides without or with catalysts such as alkaline catalyst (sodium hydroxide or potassium hydroxide) or acid catalyst (sulphuric, sulphonic, phosphoric, and hydrochloric acids) [
 <xref rid="B190-molecules-26-00943" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>,
 <xref rid="B191-molecules-26-00943" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>]. Many species of microalgae such as 
 <italic>Scenedesmus obliquus, Neochloris oleabundans, Nannochloropsis</italic> sp. and 
 <italic>C. vulgaris</italic> contain a high content of lipids including triacylglycerides that are needed for the biodiesel production [
 <xref rid="B192-molecules-26-00943" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>,
 <xref rid="B193-molecules-26-00943" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>]. The production of biodiesel involves several stages including lipid extraction using solvents; methyl or ethyl alcohol (unrefined lipid), followed by lipid recovery with centrifugation-solvent evaporation (purified lipid and free fatty acids), transesterification or esterification (biodiesel production). The final step of this process is the removal of the solvent for the biodiesel recovery [
 <xref rid="B193-molecules-26-00943" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>]. Biodiesel from renewable resources such as microalgae has several advantages compared to petroleum diesel; non-toxic, biodegradable, renewable and contains low levels of carbon monoxide, soot, hydrocarbons and particulates. It also discharges a low level of CO
 <sub>2</sub> of up to 78% lower [
 <xref rid="B194-molecules-26-00943" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>]. Many researchers have look into the possibility of producing biodiesel alongside with bioethanol from algae biomass. A study by Wang et al. [
 <xref rid="B195-molecules-26-00943" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>] had shown encouraging results of 
 <italic>Tribonema</italic> sp. with enriched lipid and carbohydrate content for biodiesel and bioethanol production. The conversion rate of lipid extracted with hexane-ethanol to biodiesel was 98.4% and the maximum yield of ethanol using yeast 
 <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> was 56.1%.
</p>
