<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Field surveys were conducted between December 2019 and January 2021, to document ethnobotanical information through oral interviews and designed semi-structured questionnaire. Thirty-five villages and 59 districts were visited for field research; 235 people were contacted and 151 of those with ethno-botanical experience agreed to become our informants, including 35 local herbalists (Tabib Arabi) and 10 physicians (who hold a general medicine specialty). The queries were repeatedly made to increase the reliability of the data; interviews with the men were usually carried out in the ‘Mukhtar’ house where they come together, and with women in their homes, bazaars and gardens. The Syria Trust for Development (which is a national development organization, and has a program called ‘Mashrouie’ that runs innovative microcredit programs that encourage economic growth in disadvantaged areas) helped us in data collecting. The information gathered during the present study included socio-demographic characteristics of the interviewed informants (age, gender) and ethnopharmacological information, including the local and scientific name of the species, local names, plant parts used, modes of use, conservation method, administration mode and toxicity, all documented data were then translated into English and Latin. Information that had been carried to the region from the outside and that was not used or confirmed was not included and recorded (Weckerle et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). During the interviews, questions about the following were asked to the participants:
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>Name and surname</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Age and sex</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Educational level</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Are plants collected in your region?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Do you have any contact with plants?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Can you show the plants you use in your region?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Can you tell the names of local plants you use in your region?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>In which season do you collect the plants you use in your region?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>When collecting plant, which parts of the plant do you collect and how do you collect them?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Which parts of the plants do you use? (flowers, fruits, leaves, roots, tubers, young shoots, branches, stems, aerial parts, etc.).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>How do you prepare and administrate the plants’ parts?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>How did you diagnose the disease (by physician, by traditional healers, self-treating)?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>How did you check the effectiveness of the treatment (disappearance of symptoms, by laboratory analysis, other methods)?</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
