<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Both epidemiological and clinical studies have indicated that almond consumption is associated with reduced cardiovascular risk and favorable plasma lipid profiles [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. More interestingly, whole almond kernels and almond oil do not differ significantly in their beneficial effects, which indicates that the favorable effects of almond nut consumption are mediated through the components of their oil fraction [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. As well as providing beneficial nutritional value, the lipid content and composition of almonds are also important for oil stability, as the fatty acid components differ in their vulnerability to oxidation. Polyunsaturated fatty acids are more susceptible to oxidation than monounsaturated fatty acids, thus, Kester et al. [
 <xref rid="B10-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>] proposed an index of resistance to oil rancidity based on the ratio of the oleic to linoleic acid contents. The resistance to oil rancidity also depends on the presence of natural antioxidants, such as the tocopherols [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Such natural antioxidants can allow longer kernel storage times, as they protect against fat oxidation [
 <xref rid="B13-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. The tocopherols are also important for human health; indeed, 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="mm3" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mi class="mi">α</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>-tocopherol is also known as vitamin E, and almonds have the highest tocopherol content seen for nuts [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>].
</p>
