<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We searched for metabarcoding studies that evaluated the effect of biological invasions on environmental microbiomes, and compared invaded and non-invaded habitats. Our literature search for this study was conducted using Web of Science Core Collection (accessed on March 6
 <sup>th</sup>, 2020) using the keywords “Invasive speci*” and “microbio*” published between 2010–2020, and found 1,471 studies. Two additional studies were added by searching the same keywords on Google Scholar (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0240996.s001">S1 Fig</xref>). Records were manually filtered based on the study design appropriate for our research question. This step yielded 22 studies, and we further filtered these studies based on data availability in public repositories. When data was not available, we attempted to contact the corresponding author. Finally we selected only studies that used the 16S rRNA marker gene, primer pair 515F/806R [
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] or 341F/785R [
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], and Illumina MiSeq sequencing platform. After discarding studies that failed quality checks (see below), we were able to include a total of five studies (
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), summing up to a total of 356 samples. The study by Gibbons et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] tested the impact of five invasive plant species (
 <italic>Agropyron cristatum</italic>, 
 <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic>, 
 <italic>Sisymbrium altissimum</italic>, 
 <italic>Erodium cicutarium</italic> and 
 <italic>Poa bulbosa</italic>) on soil microbiome using microcosms, comparing monocultures of each one of them towards a mixture of eight native plant species. A similar question was tested in Rodrigues et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] in field condition. They identified three locations invaded by three different exotic plant species (
 <italic>Microstegium vimineum</italic>, 
 <italic>Rhamnus davurica</italic> and 
 <italic>Ailanthus altissima</italic>) and, within each location, they sampled soil form an invaded area and a non-invaded area for comparisons. Similarly, Collins et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] compared the soil microbial community of field sites invaded by 
 <italic>Artemisia rothrockii</italic> to non-invaded sites. The study by Wehr et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] focused on the effects of feral pig (
 <italic>Sus scrofa</italic>) invasion on soil microbiome comparing invaded areas to those where pigs were removed over a ~25 year chronosequence. Finally, the only study performed in an aquatic environment [
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] compared water samples collected in lake areas invaded by the exotic mussel 
 <italic>Dreissena bugensis</italic> to non-invaded sites. Three studies focused on invasive plants, and the remaining studies focused on a mammal and a mussel (
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).
</p>
