<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The enzyme inhibition potency of individual phenolic compounds through mixed, uncompetitive, and competitive type is highly correlated with their structures (Di Stefano et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Kim et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>; Malunga et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Tadera et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>). Hydroxycinnamic acids are reported to be more potent on inhibition of α‐glucosidase compared with their corresponding hydroxybenzoic acid derivatives. The structure–activity relationship suggests that the number of hydroxyl and methoxy groups present in the aromatic ring phenolic acids decides the inhibitory activity (Malunga et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Furthermore, flavonoids appeared to have a better α‐glucosidase inhibitory activity than phenolic acids due to the additional hydroxyl groups in flavone skeleton, which is most likely responsible for the more pronounced inhibitory activity (Di Stefano et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Tadera et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>). Additionally, proper glucoside substitutions may boost the enzyme inhibition activities and types due to increased number of total aromatic hydroxyl groups (Şöhretoğlu et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). For example, the hydroxy (–OH) groups at C‐3 position of ring C, C‐3’ and C‐4’ position of ring B, and the glucoside substitutions at the C‐3 position of ring C were crucial for the enzyme inhibition activities of flavonols. Molecular docking studies revealed that phenolic compounds bind at both the active sites and allosteric sites, resulting in structural changes and activity inhibitors (Kim et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>; Martinez‐Gonzalez et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Hydrogen bonds, hydrophobic interactions, and van der Waals interactions are the predominant force involved in the complexation of the phenolic compounds with enzymes (Di Stefano et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Martinez‐Gonzalez et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>).
</p>
