<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Polyphenols with higher polymerization also have inhibition effects on the enzymes. Pigmented cereals always gained attentions due to their health benefits associated with anthocyanins (Pei‐Ni et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>). Premakumara et al. (
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>) screened the most resistant varieties of α‐amylase in 70% ethanol extracts from 35 varieties of rice (red and white) in Sri Lankan. The results showed that the anti‐amylase activity of the red wheat bran extract was significantly higher than the white wheat bran extract. The traditional red rice varieties Masuran, Sudu Heenati, etc., all showed significant anti‐amylase activity in a dose‐dependent manner. Yao et al. (
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0073" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>) studied Chinese colored cereals, including red, purple, black rice, purple corn, black barley, and black soybeans. Among the Chinese colored cereals studied, black rice (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 13.56 ± 1.2 mg/ml) has the highest total anthocyanin content, total phenolic content, and α‐glucosidase inhibitory activity. Anthocyanin in purple rice (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 475.14 ± 25.46 mg/ml) has stronger inhibitory activity against α‐glucosidase than proanthocyanidins in red rice (IC
 <sub>50</sub> &gt; 1,000 mg/ml). On the other hand, Hargrove et al. (
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>) compared the inhibition of α‐amylase by monoflavonoids and proanthocyanidins in Sorghum bicolor bran extract. The results showed that the extract of sumac sorghum bran rich in proanthocyanidins (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 1.4 μg/ml) had a stronger inhibitory effect on α‐amylase than the extract of sorghum bran (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 11.4 μg/ml) without procyanidins. In addition, flavonoids have higher IC
 <sub>50</sub> values than proanthocyanidins. Links et al. (
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) prepared a highly efficient sorghum‐condensed tannins (SCT) from sorghum. The results showed that SCT was a better α‐glucosidase inhibitor (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.4 μg/ml) compared with acarbose (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 8,464.0 μg/ml). SCT also had a certain inhibitory effect on α‐amylase. The effect of kafirin microparticles (KEMS) as an oral administration system for SCT has potential hypoglycemic effect. Lignin can also be used as novel α‐amylase inhibitor. The molecular docking studies indicated that the major binding sites are –OH in G units and β‐O‐4 structure of lignin on α‐amylase molecule (Fan et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>).
</p>
