<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Different processing methods significantly affected the total phenolics, individual phenolic compounds, and enzyme inhibitory properties of cereals (Donkor et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Pradeep &amp; Sreerama, 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Germinated millets with higher phenolic compound levels showed highest inhibitory activities toward both the enzymes that their untreated, steamed, and microwaved treated cereal counterparts (Pradeep &amp; Sreerama, 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Similar results were also obtained in germinated wheat, brown rice, barley, sorghum, oat, rye, and buckwheat cereals (Donkor et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). In the recent study of Gong et al. (
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), germination combined with extrusion on free and bound phenolic compound extracts of whole cereal corn increased the anti‐α‐glucosidase activity by 221 and 40%, and increased the anti‐α‐amylase activity by 105 and 108%. In the study of Qin et al. (
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), soaked tartary buckwheat had increased quercetin, kaempferol, total flavonoid, and total phenolic compound contents which were responsible for the highest α‐glucosidase inhibitory activity as compared with raw, steamed, and dried tartary buckwheat. The findings of Irondi et al. (
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>) demonstrated that both the α‐glucosidase and α‐amylase inhibitory activities of sorghum decreased due to roasting, in contradictory with the report of Kunyanga et al. (
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>) that indicated an increase in enzyme inhibitory activities of pearl millet. The parallel changes in phenolic compound levels and enzyme inhibitory activity with different processing methods suggest that phenolic compounds might be the major enzyme inhibitors in the cereals. Additionally, phenolic compounds are mainly concentrated in the pericarp, hull bran, and aleurone layers of whole cereals which may promote their contribution to the enzyme inhibitory activities. The phenolic extracts of these fractions usually displayed strong inhibition toward α‐glucosidase and α‐amylase compared with other fractions of whole cereals (Hemalatha et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Pradeep &amp; Sreerama, 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Moreover, the digestibility of phenolic compounds plays a key role in their enzyme inhibitory activity in the small intestine. Unencapsulated sorghum‐condensed tannins had minimal α‐amylase inhibition and no α‐glucosidase inhibition after pepsin and trypsin–chymotrypsin digestion (Links et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Hence, technologies that ensure bioaccessibility of phenolic compounds in the target site (small intestine) are needed in improving anti‐enzyme activities of whole cereals.
</p>
