<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Llorens et al. went further and developed a drug delivery scaffold constituted by electrospun poly(ethylene glycol) (PEG) and PBS blends. By coaxial electrospinning, different core–shell distributions were obtained, having either PEG or PBS in the outer or inner part (PEG-PBS and PBS-PEG core–shell distributions) in order to be compared with scaffolds obtained using a conventional setup (fibers obtained from a mixed solution of PEG and PBS). PEG and PBS solutions were loaded, respectively, with triclosan (polychlorophenoxy phenol at 1 w/v%), which is an antimicrobial and antifungal agent [
 <xref rid="B307-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">307</xref>], and curcumin (0.5 w/v%), which is a natural phenol that seems to have beneficial effects on the treatment of several diseases [
 <xref rid="B308-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">308</xref>,
 <xref rid="B309-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">309</xref>]. The release profiles were studied for all of the scaffolds and revealed a high dependence on the media’s hydrophobicity and the structure of the fibers. The authors achieved a different release of curcumin and triclosan and claimed that the solubility of PEG in aqueous media led to a fast release of the antibacterial compound, while the non-aqueous solubility of the curcumin-loaded-PBS component will permit a sustained anticancer effect with time [
 <xref rid="B310-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">310</xref>]. Additionally, antibacterial tests were performed against 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">M. luteus</italic>, determining the bacterial adhesion and growth onto triclosan-loaded scaffolds. All drug-loaded scaffolds prevented bacterial colonization effectively, while coaxial samples were found to be more susceptible to bacteria colonization (growth inhibition measurements) than their uniaxial electrospun counterparts. Thus, 60–40% of inhibition was obtained from the coaxial samples, without a significant influence on the core–shell structure, while 90–75% of inhibition resulted from the uniaxial electrospun scaffolds.
</p>
