<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Poly(butylene succinate) is one of the most popular poly(alkylene dicarboxylate) polymers as it combines good properties with biodegradability, and can be produced by polycondensation of succinic acid and 1,4-butanediol (BDO) monomers, which are completely bio-based and obtained from refined biomass feedstock (from sugar-based feedstock by bacterial fermentation) [
 <xref rid="B276-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">276</xref>,
 <xref rid="B277-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">277</xref>,
 <xref rid="B278-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">278</xref>]. In fact, many sources support the view that PBS is a material with the potential to replace polyolefins in the near future [
 <xref rid="B279-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">279</xref>]. Nowadays, the easiest way and most-employed strategy to obtain succinic acid is from micro-organisms, such as fungi or bacteria, being the most intensively studied 
 <italic class="italic">Anaerobiospirillum succiniciproducens</italic> [
 <xref rid="B280-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">280</xref>] and 
 <italic class="italic">Actinobacillus succinogenes</italic> [
 <xref rid="B281-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">281</xref>] due to their ability to produce a relatively large amount of succinic acid. Interestingly, the use of glycerol as a carbon source substrate had been reported to lead to the best yields of succinic acid compared to other carbohydrates [
 <xref rid="B280-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">280</xref>]. BDO can also be directly produced from biomass [
 <xref rid="B277-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">277</xref>,
 <xref rid="B282-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">282</xref>] or indirectly from bio-based succinic acid through its catalytic hydrogenation [
 <xref rid="B283-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">283</xref>,
 <xref rid="B284-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">284</xref>,
 <xref rid="B285-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">285</xref>], being this latest route the most common. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-00641-f013" class="xref">Figure 13</xref> shows an innovative and promising pathway to obtain BDO in a one-step microbial fermentation process. Although, in most of the literature, PBS is produced using petroleum-based monomers, it is within the scope of the present work to include them, as nowadays both monomers that constitute PBS are bio-based, becoming more and more accessible, and slowly replacing the petroleum-based polymer. Therefore, PBS is expected to be completely included in the family of bio-based polymers in the near future as it is already produced by an industrial company [
 <xref rid="B286-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">286</xref>,
 <xref rid="B287-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">287</xref>].
</p>
