<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Generally, for the production of antimicrobial packaging, a common strategy is to use a bio-based EO and biopolymer (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-00641-f015" class="xref">Figure 15</xref>). Therefore, to produce antimicrobial PBS, Petchwattana et al. [
 <xref rid="B290-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">290</xref>] incorporated thymol as an essential oil, which can be extracted from thyme (
 <italic class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</italic>), garlic (
 <italic class="italic">Allium sativum</italic>), and onions (
 <italic class="italic">Allium cepa</italic>) among other plants. As mentioned above, thymol possesses demonstrated antimicrobial efficiency for avoiding food spoilage and extending shelf-life [
 <xref rid="B291-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">291</xref>]. Pure thymol has been demonstrated to possess antimicrobial efficacy against a broad range of micro-organisms, including Gram-positive 
 <italic class="italic">Listeria innocua</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> bacteria and 
 <italic class="italic">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. niger</italic> fungi, with an MIC of 250 ppm for bacteria and mold and 125 ppm for yeast, retaining significant inhibition even under a microencapsulated condition [
 <xref rid="B292-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">292</xref>]. In the same work, these authors also prepared PBS/thymol blown films, with antimicrobial food packaging applications as the target, containing 2, 4, 6, 8, and 10 wt% of thymol, and tested their antibacterial activity against 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli.</italic> The release kinetic of the antimicrobial agent and its activity were evaluated. The MIC value was 10 and 6 wt% of thymol for 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus,</italic> respectively. By incorporation of 10 wt% of thymol in PBS films, the antimicrobial agent release was effective over 15 days in all of the food simulants tested, while the maximum diffusivity was obtained in isooctane due to its identical polarity with thymol. In all of the tested systems, thymol migrated rapidly from the PBS matrix towards the food simulants, requiring 50–60 h to reach an equilibrium plateau in each case. Therefore, the authors claim that these materials are suitable for short-cycle food packaging applications, such as meat, vegetable, and fruit products.
</p>
