<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although EOs are considered to be potential antimicrobial agents for PBS matrices, some authors claim that their strong odors might affect their acceptance on the market, and hence have tested alternative fillers as inorganic particles. The antimicrobial activity of ZnO-modified PBS films was tested against representative food spoilage bacteria (
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic>), and it was observed that a minimum content of 6 wt% was required for their growth inhibition with a slight increase in the inhibition zone diameter with the ZnO content. Release of Zn
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> ions from PBS was measured in distilled water, 3% acetic acid, and 10% ethanol food simulants and was found to have a strong dependence on ZnO concentration. During the tested 15 days, in distilled water and ethanol, Zn
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> released slowly, reaching a maximum at values lower than 10 ppm, while a fast release (similar to the PBS/EO systems discussed above) was observed on samples immersed in acetic acid, reaching a plateau value of 15 ppm after 50 h [
 <xref rid="B296-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">296</xref>]. An applied study of a PBS film filled with ZnO NPs (10–30 nm in size), used as packaging to preserve and prolong the shelf-life of fresh-cut apples, was reported by Naknaen [
 <xref rid="B297-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">297</xref>]. The author, packed, sealed, and stored freshly cut apple slices in PBS plastic bags with different contents of ZnO NPs (0, 2, 4, and 6 wt%) at 10 °C. After a three-day period (over a total of 18 days), quality parameters, such as color, weight loss, total acidity, and concentration of sugar, were determined. Additionally, a microbiological analysis was conducted at the end of the study over homogenized, filtered, and diluted samples in peptone water. Samples were plated onto agar, incubated, and then plate counted, showing a lower total amount of bacteria for samples containing ZnO NPs. By increasing the content of antimicrobial agent, a decrease in the bacteria population was achieved, reaching equal values for the samples containing 4 and 6 wt% ZnO NPs. Taking into account the most common regulation that limits the maximum count of aerobic micro-organisms to 6 log CFU/g at the expiration date [
 <xref rid="B298-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">298</xref>,
 <xref rid="B299-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">299</xref>], the shelf-life of the fresh-cut apple slices was enhanced by 8 days when packed in PBS containing 4–6 wt% of ZnO NPs (from 9 to 18 days).
</p>
