<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In a nutrigenomic observational study of 435 Italian volunteers, of whom 25 % were vegetarian, lipid profiles in plasma were reported to be better for individuals with specific genotypes consuming high polyphenol diets. 
 <xref rid="CIT0077" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rizzi 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> (2016)
 </xref> reported significant associations between specific 
 <italic class="italic">PON1</italic> alleles, anthocyanin consumption and elevated HDL levels. The 
 <italic class="italic">PON1</italic> gene is associated with several human diseases, including CVD (
 <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kim 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2013
 </xref>), and is inversely associated with the risk of CVD, particularly with atherosclerosis (
 <xref rid="CIT0078" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rosenblat 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2005
 </xref>). The PON1 enzyme is tightly associated with HDL particles and protects both LDL and HDL from oxidation, a major step in the progression of atherosclerosis (
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brophy 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2001
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0078" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rosenblat 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2005
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0080" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sahebkar 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>). HDL is a key player in reverse cholesterol transport, which shuttles cholesterol from peripheral cells (e.g. macrophages) to the liver or other tissues. Elevated HDL levels offer a marker for protection against atherosclerosis and CVD. Reverse cholesterol transport that clears cholesterol from the arteries has been reported to respond significantly to dietary anthocyanins in both preclinical and clinical studies (
 <xref rid="CIT0103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhu 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>). While these studies suggest strongly that not all individuals respond in the same way to high polyphenol diets, 
 <italic class="italic">PON1</italic> variants could represent useful biomarkers to stratify individuals who might benefit most from targeted dietary recommendations to promote their health.
</p>
