<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Recognition that diets may impact differentially the health of individuals has given rise to promotion of the concept of personalized nutrition. In its purest form this would involve the alignment of genomic and lifestyle information for an individual with a diet optimized for their risk factors defined genetically and environmentally. While many see this as an excellent opportunity to make money while tackling the challenges of chronic disease and declining diets, there are considerable logistical barriers towards full implementation, including concerns about data protection, the ‘eating context’ and social acceptance. Indeed, the popularity of the term ‘personalized nutrition’ and its presentation as ‘the way forward’ for dietary improvement has been accompanied by a lack of clarity about what personalized nutrition actually involves (
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gibney and Walsh, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stewart-Knox 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>). This is reflected in the outcomes of the Food4Me project (
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Celis-Morales 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>), which suggested that providing personalized dietary advice could lead to greater improvements in eating patterns and health outcomes compared to conventional population-based advice. However, the outputs of this survey of personalized advice on nutrition, which claimed to show a genuine impact of personalized nutrition advice on eating patterns, were assessed after only 6 months and showed no added value (in terms of individual adherence to improved diets) between groups that were given generic dietary advice but in a personalized manner and groups that were given personalized dietary advice linked to their phenotype or to their phenotype plus genotype (
 <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Livingstone 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>). The conclusion of the Food4Me study was that the clinical relevance of this approach was likely to be modest, suggesting that personalized nutrition alone is unlikely to solve the global problems of unhealthy eating, obesity and chronic disease.
</p>
