<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">The Argentine ant, 
 <italic>Linepithema humile</italic> Mayr, is a suitable invasive species for the exploration of intraspecific differences in traits between more- and less-successful haplotypes. 
 <italic>Linepithema humile</italic>, native to South America, is one of the 100 most hazardous invasive species in the world
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup> and has been unintentionally introduced into almost all countries but not in Antarctica and oceanic islands
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. In general, most ant species are multicolonial, with ant individuals being frequently hostile against non-nestmate conspecifics
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup>. However, 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> forms unique social structures called “supercolonies”, in which workers and reproductive castes (queens) move freely among interconnected nests within the same supercolony
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>, but show hostile behaviours towards individuals from different supercolonies, similar to the aggressive behaviour that occurs between colonies of multicolonial ants
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, recent studies based on a 1700-bp sequence of the mitochondrial COI-COII gene and a 524-bp sequence of Cyt b gene
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup> have shown that each 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> supercolony has a single unique mitochondrial haplotype and functions as an independent reproductive unit
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. As a result, the lack of hostility between 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> workers within the same supercolony is maintained even at the transcontinental scale
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. Importantly, the invasion success of 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> is known to differ among supercolonies with different haplotypes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. In Europe, the United States (e.g., California), New Zealand, and Japan, a single 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> supercolony having the same haplotype, “LH1”, extends its distribution range from tens to thousands of kilometres
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup> (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In contrast, invasions by other supercolonies with different haplotypes tend to be much less successful than LH1 in each introduced range
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup> (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). However, the mechanisms and processes underlying the high invasion success of the LH1 supercolony have not been adequately explained. Although some hypotheses have been proposed to explain why the LH1 supercolony has been most successful (e.g., genetic drift resulting from bottlenecks
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup> and new selection pressures
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>), they do not consider trait variations among supercolonies (i.e., haplotypes). Previous studies have shown that the aggressiveness and insecticidal susceptibility of 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> are significantly different among supercolonies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. Such trait variations of 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> supercolonies can be expected to result in supercolony differences in invasion success; if the LH1 supercolony is superior with respect to some traits to other supercolonies, it may promote the dominance of LH1 in its introduced ranges.
</p>
