<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Alkaloids have heterocyclic ring containing nitrogen constituent and are synthesized in the plants during amino acid pathway. They can be classified based on their chemical structure. For example, those that contain an indole structure are known as indole alkaloids. Hence, alkaloids can be grouped into different classes, alkaloids with tropane or indole nucleus can be had as well as terpenoid and steroid structures. Additionally included in this classification are the quinolinic and isoquinolinic structures, and again the pyridines, pyrrolidines and finally the pyrrolizidines. [
 <xref rid="B260-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">260</xref>]. These compounds are generally produced by many plant species, mainly flowering plants. Many testimonies of their use as a natural remedy have been reported for millennia in folk medicine. Since the twentieth century, however, single alkaloids with pharmacological properties extracted and purified mainly from plant sources have been produced on an industrial scale. Many alkaloid substances are part of the human diet, being present in both food and drinks. The plants in the human diet in which alkaloids are present are not only coffee, cocoa or tea but also some Solanaceae such as tomatoes and potatoes [
 <xref rid="B261-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">261</xref>]. About 36 alkaloids isolated from 
 <italic>Catharanthus lanceus</italic> or 
 <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> were evaluated for antiviral activity against polio type III virus, and the most effective amongst all was pericalline. The piperidine ring and free hydroxyl groups present in the heterocyclic structure of this alkaloid were responsible for antiviral activity against HIV infection [
 <xref rid="B262-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">262</xref>,
 <xref rid="B263-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">263</xref>]. Berberine is a natural alkaloid with an isoquinoline structure present in various medicinal plants, such as 
 <italic>Berberis vulgaris</italic>. A documented antiviral activity has been ascribed to this alkaloid. Of interest, this alkaloid is active against herpesvirus, influenza virus and respiratory syncytial virus as widely reported in the literature. Its antiviral activity, described against SARS-CoV and other coronaviruses, could represent a good way to verify its effectiveness against the new pandemic SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus. Specifically, it has been reported that this compound may represent a remedy for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) infection, the causative agent of SARS respiratory disease belonging to the 
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic> family. As we know, the SARS-CoV proteins nsp1, nsp2, nsp7, spike and nucleocapsid are responsible for the activation of NF-κB, a protein involved in the control of cellular processes such as inflammatory and immune responses. When the SARS-CoV virus causes disease (SARS-CoV), it happens that this infecting agent is able to regulate the expression of pro-inflammatory mediators such as TNF, CCL2 and CXCL2, at this level berberine is able to inhibit the NF-κB signaling pathway for which it is plausible to imagine its antiviral action against coronavirus infection [
 <xref rid="B264-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">264</xref>,
 <xref rid="B265-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">265</xref>]. Yan and co-workers (2018) reported an antiviral effect of berberine against influenza H1N1 virus [
 <xref rid="B266-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">266</xref>]. The same authors demonstrated that berberine promotes the inhibition of influenza virus replication in A549 human lung adenocarcinoma cells and in mouse lungs by suppressing infection, in particular by inhibiting the expression of TLR7 and NF-κB. Some scientific evidence has reported that low micromolar concentrations of berberine are capable of inhibiting the replication of different HCMV strains. In particular, in the work carried out by Luganini and co-workers [
 <xref rid="B98-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>] it was shown that this alkaloid interferes with the transactivating function of the HCMV Immediate-Early 2 (IE2) protein. This protein is the most important regulator of HCMV and represents a transcriptional activator of viral and cellular gene expression. Other alkaloids widely studied for their antiviral activities are leurocristine, periformyline, perivine, vincaleucoblastine, michellamines D/F, homonojirimycin, deoxymanojirimycin, castanospermine, australine, sesquiterpene, 5-hydroxynoracronycine, acrimarine F, columbamine, and palmitine. Detailed information regarding their targets are fully explained by [
 <xref rid="B267-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">267</xref>]. Tomatidine is an aglycone metabolite of tomatine, a natural steroidal alkaloid derived mainly from green tomatoes, with marked biological activities such as anti-cancer, anti-inflammatory and capable of stimulating muscle hypertrophy against atrophy and weakness in aged skeletal muscles [
 <xref rid="B268-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">268</xref>,
 <xref rid="B269-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">269</xref>,
 <xref rid="B270-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">270</xref>]. Diosa-Toro et al. [
 <xref rid="B271-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">271</xref>] studied the antiviral properties of tomatidine against DENV, Zika virus (ZIKV) and WNV [
 <xref rid="B271-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">271</xref>]. In this study, these authors highlighted potent anti-DENV activity in Huh7 cells of human hepatocarcinoma. Furthermore, the antiviral activity of this alkaloid towards DENV was confirmed in A549 cells of the alveolar epithelium of adenocarcinoma while less potent antiviral activity towards ZIKV was observed and no antiviral effect was towards WNV. Of interest, it was the confirmation of anti-DENV activity even when tomatidine was added 12 h after infection. Recently, [
 <xref rid="B272-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">272</xref>] reported that tomatidine, can be considered a potential anti-viral against chikungunya virus (CHIKV). Besides, other two compounds, namely solasodine and sarsasapogenin (i.e., two structural derivatives of tomatidine) showed also antiviral activity towards CHIKV, although lower when compared with tomatidine.
</p>
