<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Insects possess economic, ecological, and scientific value because their bodies (e.g., as food, medicine, or ornaments), products (e.g., secretions, excrement), behaviors (e.g., pollination, parasitism, preying on other organisms), cells and intracellular activities, and structures and functions (e.g., bionomics) can be used directly or indirectly by humans as resources. 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> is a resource insect with respect to its proteins, fats, and ability to convert organic waste. Current, research on 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> is primarily focused on its resource value and ecological value. The salivary glands and intestines of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> can secrete digestive enzymes, and their digestive activities are significantly higher those of the enzymes secreted by houseflies [
 <xref rid="B74-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>]. Among these digestive enzymes, trypsin plays decisive roles in the digestion and transformation of organic wastes [
 <xref rid="B81-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>]. The gut microbiome in the larvae plays an important role in the conversion of organic waste [
 <xref rid="B69-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>]. The gut microbial communities (bacterial and fungal communities) in 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> are diverse and abundant, and they vary significantly with substrate [
 <xref rid="B83-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>], 
 <italic class="italic">Bacteroidetes</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Proteobacteria</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Firmicutes</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Fusobacteria</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Actinobacteria</italic> are the predominant bacterial taxa [
 <xref rid="B63-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>], and 
 <italic class="italic">Pichia</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Geotrichum</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Trichosporon</italic> are the predominant fungal taxa [
 <xref rid="B67-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>]. The functional and biological characteristics of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> vary with variation in the compositions of the gut microbial communities [
 <xref rid="B84-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>]. These characteristics include oviposition, hatchability, longevity, conversion, and utilization efficiency of organic waste, and nutritional value [
 <xref rid="B85-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>,
 <xref rid="B86-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>].
</p>
