<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Packaging in medical and biomedical engineering is defined as a technique that enables the closure of a pharmaceutical product from its production to its end use [
 <xref rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. The role of pharmaceutical packaging is to provide life-saving drugs, surgical devices, nutraceuticals, pills, powders and liquids, to name a few [
 <xref rid="B7-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Pharmaceutical packaging influences the isolation and ensures the safety, identity and convenience of using the drug. The packaging must communicate well with the patient so that there are no adverse effects on the health of the patient. The key issue in packaging is also the issue of ecological safety [
 <xref rid="B26-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. Drug companies that pack drugs are among the industry leaders due to their technological advances. Current trends in industrial research on such new materials are the result of a continuous series of challenges being faced by the industry. The packaging industry is constantly evolving and is an important factor in the development of the pharmaceutical industry and biomedical sciences. Electrospinning of polymers/nanomaterials [
 <xref rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>] is one of the potential methods in the packaging process that allows for the use of biopolymers [
 <xref rid="B30-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]/natural substances for the production of medical packaging, dressings, biosensors, medical implants, and is a growing trend in biomedical sciences [
 <xref rid="B10-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00404-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref> illustrates the schematic of a coaxial electrospinning setup. The inset shows an illustration of a coaxial jet under applied voltage [
 <xref rid="B39-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Mercante et al in their excellent review articles have also shown the number of publications that’s involved the use of electrospinning in sensor applications and the number of these publications is increasing day by day [
 <xref rid="B10-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. 
</p>
