<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Different types of electrospun fibers are being produced for biomedical applications [
 <xref rid="B32-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. However, the electrospinning of biopolymers is a very challenging process. For example, in the case of chitosan, its neutralization lead to the loss of chitosan traits by using unsuitable substances. In the production of continuous filaments, suitable solvents should be used so that there is no interruption. In addition, during chitosan nanofiber synthesis, the value of the electric field generated is also crucial. Too high of an electric field causes repulsion between ionic groups of the polymer backbone, which disturbs the formation of continuous filaments. The use of chitin and chitosan nanofibers in biomedical and other applications has been recently reviewed [
 <xref rid="B32-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. Jayakumar et al, in their article, had primarily focused on the properties, preparation and biomedical applications [
 <xref rid="B32-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. Electrospinning of silk has also been reported [
 <xref rid="B35-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. It is used because of beneficial properties such as non-toxicity and biocompatibility. Due to its positive mechanical properties, it can be used in various temperature and humidity ranges. However, in the case of silk, one of the protein components, sericin, should be removed before biological application because it can cause allergic reactions, for example, in the case of medical dressings [
 <xref rid="B36-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>].
</p>
