<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">Pompia is a Sardinian citrus ecotype whose botanical classification is still being debated. In the present study, the composition of Pompia peel essential oil (EO) is reported for the first time, along with that of the leaf EO, as a phytochemical contribution to the classification of this ecotype. The peel EO was tested for its antioxidant ability (with both the 2,2-diphenyl-1-picarylhydrazyl (DPPH) and ferric reducing antioxidant power (FRAP) assays). Moreover, its antimicrobial activities were tested for the first time on dermatophytes (
  <italic class="italic">Microsporum canis</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Microsporum gypseum</italic>, and 
  <italic class="italic">Trichophyton mentagrophytes</italic>), on potentially toxigenic fungi (
  <italic class="italic">Fusarium solani</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Aspergillus flavus</italic>, and 
  <italic class="italic">Aspergillus niger</italic>) as well on bacteria (
  <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and 
  <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus pseudointermedius</italic>). The dominant abundance of limonene in the peel EO seems to distinguish Pompia from the 
  <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> spp. to which it had previously been associated. It lacks γ-terpinene, relevant in 
  <italic class="italic">Citrus medica</italic> EO. Its relative content of α- and β-pinene is lower than 0.5%, in contrast to 
  <italic class="italic">Citrus limon</italic> peel EO. Pompia peel and leaf EOs did not show significant amounts of linalool and linalyl acetate, which are typically found in 
  <italic class="italic">Citrus aurantium</italic>. Pompia peel EO antioxidant activity was weak, possibly because of its lack of γ-terpinene. Moreover, it did not exert any antimicrobial effects either towards the tested bacteria strains, or to dermatophytes and environmental fungi.
 </p>
</abstract>
