<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Oreganum vulgare</italic> L. is known for its essential oil, called oregano essential oil (OEO), a popular compound with proven anticancer, antioxidant and antimicrobial activity. These activities are mainly attributed to two phenols: carvacrol and thymol. Carvacrol, a significant compound, was found to be potentially helpful in tackling free-radical-mediated injuries and saved DNA damage due to its ability to increase the antioxidant level along with the anti-lipid peroxidative activity. Rehman Khan et al. developed OEO-loaded electrospun nanofibers of poly (l-lactic acid-co-e-caprolactone)/silk fibroin (PLCL/SF) to prevent tumor recurrence after surgical removal [
 <xref rid="B213-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>]. The inclusion of OEO increased the mean pore diameter and porosity [
 <xref rid="B214-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>]. This high-porosity nanofiber helps in transporting nutrients and oxygen to the inner surface, absorbing wound exudates from the wound surface and hence lowering the risk of infection [
 <xref rid="B215-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">215</xref>,
 <xref rid="B216-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">216</xref>]. The nanofibers, which provide tensile strength and flexibility in all conditions, were an ideal scaffold for wound healing. The developed nanofibers had an excellent tensile strength (1–32 Mpa) and elongation at break (17–207%), appropriate for skin-tissue applications [
 <xref rid="B217-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>]. A DPPH assay revealed that OEO worked through oxidation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) [
 <xref rid="B218-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">218</xref>]. Cell counting kit-8 and calcein assays on the mouse 4T1 breast tumor cell line revealed potent antiproliferative activity attributed to the carvacrol and thymol present in OEO. The results obtained from this work confirmed that this fiber is beneficial in preventing tumor recurrence after surgical removal.
</p>
