<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">
 <italic>Houttuynia cordata</italic> Thunb. is a perennial herbaceous medicinal plant distributed in Japan, China, Korea, and Southeast Asia and the Himalayas. In India, it is mainly distributed in North-Eastern states including Assam, Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura, Mozoram, Arunachal Pradesh and Sikkim (Bhattacharyya and Sharma 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2010</xref>). The plant prefers to grow in moist and shady habitat (Alves et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2013</xref>; Wei and Wu 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2012</xref>). A study conducted in North-East India has indicated that the plant requires a special moist habitat having clay loam soil with higher organic carbon (0.85 ± 0.05%), average soil pH 5.9 and 78% soil moisture (Bhattacharyya and Sharma 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2010</xref>). It is the only member of the genus 
 <italic>Houttuynia</italic> under the family Saururaceae (Fang 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1981</xref>; Tseng 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">1982</xref>). The plant is popularly known by different common names like Chameleon plant, fish wort or heart leaf, and Chinese lizard tail. It is widely used for ornamental (Frank and Dana 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2012</xref>), culinary and medicinal purposes (Wu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2002</xref>). Mature plants of 
 <italic>H. cordata</italic> Thunb. are 30–60 cm tall, with horizontal rhizomes or stolons that connect the erect aerial stems. The terminal inflorescences consist of dense spikes (1.5–2.5 cm long) of very small flowers without petals, but each inflorescence has four bracts at the base which resembles a single flower. The leaves are heart-shaped, cordate with a sheathing base, measuring up to 10 cm long and 6 cm wide, usually green but can turn into purplish colour when exposed to sunlight. The fruits are tiny (2–3 mm long) with 9 to 18 apomictic seeds in each (Alves et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2013</xref>). Sexual reproduction has not been reported for this plant (Wei and Wu 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2012</xref>). It mainly reproduces through vegetative propagation by producing abundant rhizomes or stolons and by parthenogenesis (Mihara 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1960</xref>; Shibata and Miyake 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1908</xref>).
</p>
