<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Comparative analysis also revealed that plant extracts/essential oils were more effective 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> than 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> against various stages of the parasite. Similar differences between 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> results with plant treatments have been previously reported (
 <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr">Peneluc et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B146" ref-type="bibr">Nogueira et al., 2012</xref>) and might be related with bioavailability of plant chemical constituents in different parts of the ruminant gastrointestinal tract (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Athanasiadou et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Eguale et al., 2007b</xref>). Furthermore, adult nematodes may also be more resistant to the active components, or rumen microbiota may reduce the activity of metabolites (
 <xref rid="B146" ref-type="bibr">Nogueira et al., 2012</xref>), and other aspects, such as ruminal pH. Mostly, in gerbils the efficacy of plant extracts was reported to be comparatively low than the activity observed in sheep. Using rodents for evaluation of plants anthelmintic activity has some drawbacks, firstly the habitat for nematodes is quite different in rodents and small ruminants, hence, association between habitat and drug site absorption define the higher or lower drug activity (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Hennessy, 1997</xref>). Secondly, different efficacy obtained in rodents and sheep can be described by mechanism of distribution and biotransformation of the drug in a monogastric and polygastric animal species. However, efficacy test on rodent nematodes can help researchers deduce the prescriptions to be used on sheep and goats (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Camurça-Vasconcelos et al., 2007</xref>). The studies concerning isolation and purification of plant compounds responsible for antiparasitic acitivities are few and insufficient. Most of the studies reported the presence of key components of the plants which do not provide any information about the effective antiparasitic compounds and their mechanism of action. Therefore, pure comounds isolated from plants should be given focus for 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> evaluation, toxicology, and pharmacology studies in future research, this will provide base-line information for developing new ecofriendly and cost effective drugs with lesser side effects.
</p>
