<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0050">Black pepper (
 <italic>Piper nigrum</italic> L.) is considered as “king of spices” in every cuisine throughout the world. From ancient times, as a medicinal agent it is playing a potential role in nutraceutical and pharmaceutical applications. Moreover, 
 <italic>P. nigrum</italic> contains enormous bioactive compounds, which have been shown to be health beneficiary and these compounds have disease preventing properties such as antiviral, anti-inflammatory, antipyretic, immune, and bioavailability enhancing qualities. Alkaloids, flavonoids, terpenes, steroids, phenolic, unique amino acid, and polyose are the major phytochemicals in peppers. Studies revealed that piperine, an alkaloid, has medicinal properties and effective against pungency (
 <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Vasavirama and Upender, 2014</xref>). Black pepper is the wealthy source of healing agent for treating many diseases, including infectious diseases. As a strong antimicrobial agent, black pepper showed potential antiviral activity against coxsackie virus type B3 (CVB3), vesicular stomatitis indiana virus (an enteric virus), and human parainfluenza virus (a respiratory infection causing virus) (
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Priya and Kumari, 2017</xref>). However, black pepper has been recognized as an immune-modulator reservoir for treating many infectious diseases where piperine possessed promising potential as an immune-modulator (Tables 
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). It has the capability to boost and support the number and efficiency of white cells and helps the body to raise a powerful defense against invading microbes. 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Bezerra et al. (2008)</xref> reported that piperine showed improved immune-competence that was hampered by 5-FU treatment. In other findings, piperine led to inhibition of proliferative responses caused by lipopolysaccharide (LPS) and immunoglobulin α-IgM antibody in B cell functioning and humoral immune response to T-un/dependent antigens (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Bernardo et al., 2015</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al. (2018)</xref> documented that piperine up-regulated IL-10 and NF-κB by combining effect with gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA), which activated p38, JNK, and MAPK pathway to increase the release of EPO and EPO-R expression.
</p>
