<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The methanolic extracts of the three species of seaweed evaluated, 
 <italic>U. intestinalis, H. macroloba</italic>, and 
 <italic>S. ilicifolium,</italic> were tested further for their cytotoxicity levels. The extracts were tested on MCF-7 cells (human breast adenocarcinoma cell line, estrogen receptor positive), MDA-MB-231 cells (human breast adenocarcinoma cell line, estrogen receptor negative), HT-29 cells (human colorectal adenocarcinoma cell line), Hep G2 cells (human liver hepatocellular carcinoma cell line), and 3T3 cells (mouse embryonic fibroblast cells). All cells were maintained in RPMI medium supplemented with 10% fetal calf serum (FCS), 100 unit/ml penicillin, and 0.1 mg/ml streptomycin. Cytotoxicity of the extracts was determined via MTT assay according to the protocol utilized by Mohan et al. 2008 [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], using 3-[4, 5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl]-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide. Initially, cell culture at a concentration of 1 × 10
 <sup>5</sup> cells/mL was prepared and plated (100 
 <italic>μ</italic>L/well) into 96-well plates. The cell was incubated for 24 h at 37°C, 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub>. Diluted ranges of extract samples (1.56, 3.125, 6.25, 12.5, 25, 50, and 100 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL) were dissolved in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO), and the final concentration of DMSO was 0.1% (v/v). Thereafter, various concentrations of the extract samples were plated out in triplicate. Each plate included untreated cell controls and blank cell-free control. 5-Fluorouracil, a drug with antineoplastic activity, was used as a positive control in this study. After 68 h of incubation (to allow for the cancer cells to grow properly or to be inhibited based on extract cytotoxicity), 20 
 <italic>μ</italic>L of MTT (5 mg/mL) was added to each well to form formazan crystals, and the plates were incubated for further 4 h and the media was removed. DMSO was later added to each well to solubilize the formazan crystals. The absorbance was read at a wavelength of 570 nm using a microplate reader (Tecan Sunrise Basic, Groedig, Austria). The percentage of cellular viability was calculated with the appropriate controls taken into account. The concentration which inhibited 50% of the cellular growth (IC
 <sub>50</sub> value) was determined. The inhibitory rate of cell proliferation was calculated by the following formula: growth inhibition = (OD control−OD treated)/OD control×100. The cytotoxicity of the sample on cancer cells was expressed as IC
 <sub>50</sub> values (the sample concentration reducing the absorbance of treated cells by 50% with respect to untreated cells). All cultures were tested for mycoplasma contamination and were found to be negative.
</p>
