<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>TGF-
 <italic>β</italic> pathway is considered as an essential process of signal cascade response to the transforming growth to mediate cell proliferation, apoptosis, and differentiation [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. It exerts a variety of pathological and physiological function in the tumor progression, wound healing, immune response, and so on [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Recently, several emerging shreds of evidences have shown that TGF-
 <italic>β</italic> could serve as a tissue repair mediator to benefit or exacerbate the tissue damage in the brain, liver, and other tissues via mitochondrial apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Jin et al. reported that TGF-
 <italic>β</italic> contributed to LRG1-induced ischemia/reperfusion injury via apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Another study by Wang et al. also indicated that TGF-
 <italic>β</italic> participated in the miRNA-590-5p-regulated chondrocyte apoptosis in response to the mechanical pressure injury [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Mitochondrial apoptosis is exceptionally essential to maintain the stabilization of homeostasis in the body, which could clean up the unwanted and abnormal cells according to a serious of programmed signal instruction of apoptosis factors. However, the disorder and despitefully employed apoptosis would result in normal cell death and tissue injury [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In the treatment of cancer by CPT, enormous shreds of evidence confirmed that CPT induced the cell apoptosis and tissue injury in the normal kidney, liver, lung, and other tissues and eventually caused the severe toxicity effect [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. This information implies that CPT-evoked kidney toxicity during the treatment of oral cancer may be associated to the TGF-
 <italic>β</italic>-induced mitochondrial apoptosis.
</p>
