<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As the pharmacological activities of different plant extracts are closely associated to their bioactive compounds, the chemical compositions of the aqueous extract and essential oil of 
 <italic>T. serrulatus</italic> were determined. The aqueous extract of 
 <italic>T. serrulatus</italic> was shown to be rich in caffeic acid derivatives (e.g., rosmarinic acid) and salvianolic acids, the latter formed by danshensu linked to caffeic acid moieties (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2019</xref>). This finding is in agreement with aqueous decoction of 
 <italic>T. carnosus</italic> in which salvianolic acid K (19.7 mg/g from 42.92 mg/g total phenolics) and salvanolic acid A isomers (16.91 mg/g) constituted the major phenolic content (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Martins-Gomes et al., 2018</xref>). Even though it is known that 
 <italic>Thymus</italic> species are rich in rosmarinic acid (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Pereira and Cardoso, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Afonso et al., 2017</xref>), this was clearly less representative (15%) in 
 <italic>T. serrulatus</italic> aqueous extract. These differences in phytochemical contents can depend considerably on extrinsic and intrinsic factors including plant growth, harvest phases, storage, soil, and climatic conditions (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Shekarchi et al., 2012</xref>). Additionally, isoscutellarein-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucuronide (16%) and luteolin-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucuronide (10%) were the most prevalent among the other flavone glycosides. These findings are in agreement with previous reported data that showed 
 <italic>O</italic>-glucuronide derivatives of luteolin and other flavone glycosides have also been detected in different 
 <italic>Thymus</italic> specie
 <italic>s</italic> in significant amounts (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Pereira et al., 2013a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Pereira and Cardoso, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Afonso et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Afonso et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
