<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coccidiosis remains a severe challenge for the broiler industry owing to the ubiquity of 
 <italic>Eimeria</italic> species parasites and the widespread occurrence of anticoccidial resistance. Today, resistance to anticoccidial drugs and a broad spectrum of other products is easily acquired. Further, consumer opinion is now commonly demanding reduced use of drugs in livestock production, including ionophores or chemical coccidiostats, as well as antibiotic growth promoters (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). As restrictions on the use of anticoccidial drugs increase, and in the absence of affordable or scalable anticoccidial vaccines for broilers, research exploring safe and effective alternatives to control coccidiosis has increased leading to the exploitation of herbal extracts such as essential oils of aromatic or medicinal plants (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). One example has been phenolic compounds, a large group of bioactive constituents found in a wide variety of plants that include thousands of compounds with different chemical structures (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Because of interest in their medicinal and sensorial properties (color and astringency), their analysis in foods, beverages, and feed has been developing in recent years. Similarly, multiple sources of compounds have been investigated because total phenolic content (expressed in mg/g) can be highly variable, for example, between 0.24 mg/g can be detected in grape seed extracts compared with 147 mg/g in basil extracts (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). In our work, oregano and garlic essential oils were examined. Based on the GC-MS results, the main bioactive compounds of oregano essential oil were carvacrol, γ-terpinene, and 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene, whereas the major compounds of garlic essential oil were diallyl sulfides (diallyl trisulfide and diallyl disulfide). We evaluated the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> anticoccidial activity of both oregano and garlic essential oils with the inhibition of coccidial (
 <italic>E. tenella</italic>) invasion in MDBK cells. Moreover, in our 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> trial, we examined the impact of diet supplementation with oregano and garlic essential oils on broiler growth performance, oocyst excretion after natural environmental challenge, and components of the intestinal microbiota.
</p>
