<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plants of the genus 
 <italic>Petasites</italic> contain large amounts of active compounds such as sesquiterpene esters, sesquiterpene lactones and pyrrolizidine alkaloids [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-09-00700" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Pyrrolizidine alkaloids are toxic [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-09-00700" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-plants-09-00700" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], while some of the sesquiterpene esters and sesquiterpene lactones have medicinal properties. Primarily petasin and isopetasin sesquiterpene esters are considered as the most valuable pharmaceutical components in 
 <italic>Petasites</italic> plants [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-09-00700" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Therefore, 
 <italic>P. hybridus</italic> plants used for pharmaceutical purposes, and especially the preparations made from these plants, should ideally contain high amounts of petasin/isopetasin, and, most importantly, low amounts of pyrrolizidine alkaloids [
 <xref rid="B17-plants-09-00700" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-plants-09-00700" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The chemical analysis of the essential oils of 
 <italic>P. hybridus</italic> ssp. ochroleucus from the Balkans revealed low concentrations of isopetasin, no petasin and no pyrrolizidine alkaloids. Concentrations of sesquiterpene lactones were, however, high. Isopetasin was present only in the rhizome essential oil (3.9%) and absent from the essential oil of the leaves. This concentration is below the average petasin/isopetasin concentration found in other preparations of 
 <italic>Petasites</italic> plants [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-09-00700" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The distribution and the concentration of petasin/isopetasin is often higher in rhizomes than in leaves [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-09-00700" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], which is in accordance with the present results. Lower concentrations of sesquiterpenes (for example, farnesene, bisabolene, cyperene, santalene and germacrene, as well as many others) were detected in the rhizome essential oil, compared to the leaves. All the well-known pyrrolizidine alkaloids commonly present in 
 <italic>Petasites</italic> (senecionine, integerrimine, seneciphylline or senkirkine) [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-09-00700" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], as well as other pyrrolizidine alkaloids common in other genera [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-09-00700" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], were below the detection limit in the essential oils. This is in accord with pyrrolizidine alkaloids being non-volatiles, which was the drive for the selection of essential oils (that are produced by distillation) as the medium of study. Therefore, essential oils of 
 <italic>P. hybridus</italic> subsp. ochroleucus from the Balkans are of low toxicity, and satisfy the pharmaceutical requirement for low pyrrolizidine alkaloids content. However, as discussed above, they contain only moderate concentrations of the pharmaceutically active petasin/isopetasin, and their medicinal properties are therefore based on the activity of other compounds. 
</p>
