<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The anti-inflammatory activity of the essential oils of 
 <italic>P. hybridus</italic>, and the role of petasin/isopetasin, have already been described [
 <xref rid="B24-plants-09-00700" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In this paper, we examined the anti-inflammatory activity of essential oils obtained from rhizomes and leaves on the Carrageenan-induced paw edema model in rats. Anti-inflammatory activity of oil obtained from rhizome, starting from the concentration of 10%, is high and immediate, while concentration of 20% leads to significant inhibition of edema only after 4 h and repeated applications (
 <xref rid="plants-09-00700-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), probably due to the slower dermal absorption of higher concentrations and the accompanying slower effects. Although low, the concentration of the sesquiterpene ester, isopetasine, in the essential oil obtained from the rhizome (3.93%) showed an anti-inflammatory effect after local treatment. The local application mode to the inflammation site probably contributed to the anti-inflammatory activity, because it has been shown that presence of petasin/isopetasin below 15% is inefficient for medical use. Rhizome essential oil at the concentration of 40% did not show significant reduction in paw thickness, which can be associated with problem of dermal absorption of high concentrations of this oil, or an inadequately effective dose. Unlike the essential oil from the rhizome, essential oil from the leaves was effective in suppressing paw edema only at the higher concentrations (statistical significance was obtained at the concentration of 40%). The differences in the effects of the essential oils obtained from rhizomes and leaves are due to different groups of active compounds present in those two plant organs. Sesquiterpenes lactones, which are present at high concentration in leaves’ essential oils (fukinanolide, 33.42%), have some medical properties as well [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-00700" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], so the absence of petasin/isopetasin in leaves’ essential oils may be offset by high concentrations of sesquiterpenes lactones. This explains the anti-inflammatory effect of the essential oil from the leaves, as well as the higher concentration required to obtain the corresponding response. The efficiency of high concentrations may also indicate better dermal absorption of the essential oil obtained from the leaves.
</p>
