<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Black locust is an important species in historical parks, gardens, alleys and fortifications in Poland. Old 
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>pseudoacacia</italic> trees might also be desirable because they provide shade and habitat for rare saprophytic fungi and saprophagous beetles [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. 
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>pseudoacacia</italic> trees growing in Europe prefer high insolation, but there are no specific requirements concerning soil pH or fertility [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. It is widely believed that black locust trees can adapt to drought [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], air pollution [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] and strongly acidic soils [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. For the above reasons, it seems to be an interesting species from the point of climate change and the functioning of trees in urban environments, and why we chose it as a model species. However, our research indicates that the health of this species in Poland was visibly worse in the street sites than in the park sites. It can be assumed that this was related to adverse abiotic and biotic factors occurring in street locations as well as indirectly to global warming. In Poland, a gradual increase in temperature has been observed since 1987. According to Kożuchowski and Żmudzka [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], warming of 0.9°C in 50 years has manifested in particular as an increase in temperature at the turn of winter and spring, especially February and March. Winter and summer have shortened, and the transitional seasons have extended, which also has contributed to the gradual lengthening of the growing season [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. This has resulted in extension of the period of plant colonization by pests and pathogens and increases in the range of invasive species as well as the number of generations for insects [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. In the last 20 years of the 20th century and in the present decade, significant warming has also been observed in the winter and spring seasons, as well as in the summer [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Further climate warming is predicted. According to Kundzewicz et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], the mean annual temperature in Poland is expected to increase by about 1°C until 2021–2050 and by about 2°C until 2071–2100. The warming is projected to be stronger in winter than in other seasons.
</p>
