<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As the climate is changing, there is a wider spectrum of insects and pathogenic fungi colonising black locust trees, which have been considered as resistant to diseases and pests according to the “enemy release hypothesis” for introduced species so far. Time and changing environmental conditions can break resistance to an invader [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. After over 200 years presence in Poland and climate change, black locust is damaged by a broader spectrum of pests and diseases than before. Many pests new to Poland (4 species versus 7 noted) have appeared on 
 <italic>Robinia pseudoacacia</italic> in the last 20 years, which coincides with climate warming. Most of the pest species found on black locust trees are alien to the fauna of Poland. They are native to North America. The deformations of black locust leaves and the negative effects on their decorative values were mainly caused by aphids, flies and butterfly larvae. 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>robiniae</italic> and 
 <italic>O</italic>. 
 <italic>robiniae</italic> were first found in Poland in 2007 [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], whereas 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>robiniella</italic> and 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>robiniella</italic> were found in the last decade of the 20
 <sup>th</sup> century [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Although these species appeared in Poland a relatively short time ago, they acclimatised and are expanding northwards. This phenomenon may have been caused by global warming [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. In many European countries, including Poland, monophages from America are listed as the most important pests of 
 <italic>Robinia</italic>: false acacia gall midge 
 <italic>O</italic>. 
 <italic>robiniae</italic>, mining butterflies 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>robiniella</italic> and 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>robiniella</italic>, and 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>robinie</italic> aphid [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Therefore, the question arises whether we can expect other North American species associated with this plant to appear in Poland along with global warming. It seems that 
 <italic>Metcalfa priunosa</italic> (Say) may migrate to Poland. This is a polyphagous insect that feeds not only on fruit plants but also on shrubs and woody plants, including 
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>pseudoacacia</italic>. It is an invasive alien species that is widely distributed in Europe. It was first found in Italy in 1979 and rapidly invaded other countries: France, Spain, Switzerland, Austria, Bulgaria, Greece, and Serbia [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. So far this insect has not been found in Poland, but it has appeared in neighbouring countries such as Germany, the Czech Republic, Ukraine, and Slovakia [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Due to the rapid adaptation and expansion of this species, its population is expected to increase and it may invade a wider range of host plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Important 
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>pseudoacacia</italic> pests in North America are wood-damaging insects: 
 <italic>Megacyllene robiniae</italic> (Forster) (belonging to the Cerambycidae family) and the butterfly of the Cossidae family—
 <italic>Prionoxystus robiniae</italic> (Peck). These species have not been recorded in Europe so far [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Black locust wood can be damaged also by beetles of the Cerambycidae family: 
 <italic>Plagionotus arcuatus</italic> (L.), 
 <italic>Clytus arietis</italic> (L.) or 
 <italic>Chlorophorus figuratus</italic> (Scopoli). They are polyphages found in central and southern Europe [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>], but no damage caused by these insects was noted at the examined sites.Due to global warming, species previously found in southern Europe are migrating north and appearing in Poland, where they often winter and reproduce. Also, native species that occurred locally, especially in warm places, are quickly spreading throughout the country. Migration is facilitated by human activities, especially those related to the transport of plants, and by the lack of natural predators. In recent years new pests and diseases have also emerged on other tree and shrub species introduced in Poland, such as the horse chestnut and boxwood. Horse chestnut trees (
 <italic>Aesculus hippocastanum</italic> L.) are invaded by the horse chestnut leaf miner (
 <italic>Cameraria ohridella</italic> Deschka &amp; Dimić) and 
 <italic>Erysiphe flexuosa</italic> fungus (Peck) U. Braun &amp; S. Takamatsu, which causes powdery mildew and serious health problems. 
 <italic>Aesculus hippocastanum</italic> is an important ornamental tree species, which has been planted in parks and gardens in Poland since the 17
 <sup>th</sup> century. 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>ohridella</italic> was first found in Poland in 1998, whereas 
 <italic>E</italic>. 
 <italic>flexuosa</italic> in 2002. Before these dates they were listed in other European countries [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. The expansion of 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>ohridella</italic> to new areas may have been caused not only by its importation but also by the shift of the northern and eastern limits of its range as a result of global warming [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. As the climate change progresses, its range is forecast to increase further [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Currently, 
 <italic>Cydalima perspectalis</italic> (Walker), which was brought to Europe with boxwood seedlings, is a big problem. The species is native to humid subtropical regions of Southeastern Asia. In Europe it was first found in Germany in 2006. Then it spread rapidly to become an invasive species found in most Western and Southern European countries [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. In Poland it was first observed in 2012 [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. In view of the adaptability of this butterfly and the global rise of temperatures, the range of this pest is forecast to extend to the northern borders of Europe [
 <xref rid="pone.0245398.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Thus, the expansion 
 <italic>of C</italic>. 
 <italic>perspectalis</italic> is determined by temperature rather than humidity, because this pest has perfectly adapted to a much drier climate in Europe.
</p>
