<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study reporting a deoxyribonuclease-like protein in mushrooms, specifically Tiger Milk mushroom. This 230NA deoxyribonuclease-like protein encoded by GME1230_g contains a conserved domain of DNase_NucA_NucB is highly abundance in Ligno TG-K HMWp. The current knowledge on the function of this protein is scarce but the presence of the DNase_NucA_NucB domain suggests that it might act as a deoxyribonuclease. This is also supported by recent studies where fungal antitumor proteins with deoxyribonuclease activity were reported. Antitumor proteins from 
 <italic>Agrocybe aegerita, Pholiota nameko</italic> and 
 <italic>Ramaria botrytis</italic> mushrooms which possessed deoxyribonuclease activity have been reported to exhibit potent antiproliferative activity and apoptosis-inducing effect on several human cancer cells such as neuroblastoma (SH-SY5Y), HeLa, breast adenocarcinoma (MCF7) and lung adenocarcinoma (A549) cells (
 <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2014a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2014b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2017</xref>). Therefore, it is likely that the 230NA protein may have similar cytotoxic properties as with the other reported deoxyribonucleases which may also play a role in cytotoxicity of HMWp. Our data suggests that the lectins, serine proteases, RNase Gf29 and the novel 230NA deoxyribonuclease that constituting 55.93% of the HMWp, may contribute to the cytotoxicity of HMWp. Furthermore, 
 <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Trejo-Becerril et al. (2016)</xref> has demonstrated a combination of proteases and DNaseI inhibited the growth of tumors in colon tumor-bearing mice. Thus, the high content of serine protease and deoxyribonuclease in HMWp could have contributed to the major antitumor activity in this study. Though other proteins which were found in low amounts in HMWp such as agmatinase, thioredoxin reductase, alpha-galactosidase and chain A of a novel pore-forming lectin have not been reported to exhibit antiproliferative activity, these proteins remain as bioactive proteins of interest for future investigations of this species.
</p>
