<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Different extracts (
 <italic class="italic">viz</italic>. acetone, methanol, ethanol, and aqueous) of both 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> plantlets and field grown samples were studied for their antibacterial activity against 
 <italic class="italic">K. oxytoca, Salmonella typhimurium</italic>, Methicillin resistant 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus, K. pneumonia, Proteus vulgaris, Proteus mirabilis, Enterobacter aerogenes, P. aeruginosa, E. coli</italic> O157:H7, 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus, Salmonella paratyphi</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> ATCC 29522. The results revealed that 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> plantlets of 
 <italic class="italic">M. peregrina</italic> showed significant antibacterial potential when compared to field grown samples. At a concentration of 40 mg/100 μl, the ethanol extract of 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> plantlets of 
 <italic class="italic">M. peregrina</italic> showed the highest zone of inhibition against 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> (Alrayes et al., 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Aqueous extract of 
 <italic class="italic">M. peregrina</italic> seeds was investigated for antibacterial activity against clinically isolated multidrug resistant 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> species (Saleh et al., 
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). The results showed that the extracts exhibited good antibacterial activity against the multidrug resistant 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> isolates. The minimum inhibitory concentration of the extract ranged between 109.37 and 437.5 mg/mL. These results support the use of 
 <italic class="italic">M. peregrina</italic> as disinfectant in the folk medicine and further studies can be focused on the isolation of novel antimicrobial molecules to treat the infections caused by microbes.
</p>
