<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app4-pharmaceutics-13-00387">Appendix D</xref> (
 <xref rid="pharmaceutics-13-00387-t0A3" ref-type="table">Table A3</xref>) lists marketed liquid formulations suitable for the paediatric population. Liquid formulations are the most common in paediatrics because of their easy administration. The need for at least one liquid formulation of any drug indicated in the paediatric population is becoming increasingly noticeable. Not all active principles are soluble or stable in water. Therefore, excipients are used in liquid formulations to improve the solubility of certain active principles and/or increase their stability. The problem is that most excipients found in adult formulations should not be used in paediatrics. However, as shown in 
 <xref rid="pharmaceutics-13-00387-t0A3" ref-type="table">Table A3</xref>, there are a wide variety of marketed formulations indicated in paediatrics that contain these non-recommended excipients:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>Ethanol, sorbitol and propylene glycol, despite being contraindicated in paediatrics, especially ethanol, are still included in some paediatric formulations.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The addition of non-recommended sweeteners, such as sucrose, sucralose or sodium saccharine, is also seen in these paediatric formulations.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The addition of preservatives in paediatric formulations should be avoided as much as possible, and if necessary, in the least amount. Parabens are among the safest preservatives in paediatrics, yet others that are not recommended are still used (e.g., 
    <xref rid="pharmaceutics-13-00387-t0A3" ref-type="table">Table A3</xref>: sodium benzoate, benzoic acid and benzyl alcohol). Benzalkonium chloride, despite not being recommended for asthmatic patients, is used for the formulation of most eye drops, nasal drops and gothic drops.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
