<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To the best of our knowledge, to date there has been no animal studies for anticancer activity of any compounds isolated from North American mushroom. There are numerous animal studies reporting the anti-cancer activity of extracts, small molecules and large molecules isolated from mushrooms collected in different parts of the world. Several excellent reviews have already dealt with this topic [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Here, we only highlight some of the key findings from popular medicinal mushrooms. A mushroom mixture named as Micotherapy U-care consisted of 
 <italic>G. lucidum, Lentinula edodes, Agaricus blazei, Ophiocordyceps sinensis,</italic> and 
 <italic>Grifola frondosa</italic> was orally administered in mice implanted with triple-negative breast cancer. The results showed reduced pulmonary metastases density as well as decreased expression of interleukin-6, NOS, and COX-2 [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. In another study, the anticancer effect of β-glucans along with radiation therapy was evaluated against lung cancer. The β-glucan isolated from 
 <italic>G. lucidum</italic> caused inhibition of primary lung cancer metastasis in C57BL/6 mice [
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. In another study, the antitumor effects of a β-glucan isolated from 
 <italic>G. frondosa</italic> combined with cisplatin were evaluated in a BALB/cA mouse model. The β-glucan was able to enhance the antitumor and antimetastatic effects of cisplatin as well as reduced the side effects; myelosuppression and nephrotoxicity, associated with cisplatin treatment [
 <xref rid="B55-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. The ethanol extracts from 
 <italic>F. pinicola</italic> has been shown to significantly inhibit xenograft sarcoma-derived tumor growth in mice and prolong their survival time when administered as a food supplement [
 <xref rid="B56-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>].
</p>
