<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">Population differentiation of endangered species is variable. For example, low differentiation was found between populations of 
 <italic>Platanthera leucophaea</italic> (F
 <sub>ST</sub> &lt; 0.02 over distances &lt; 2 km
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>
 </sup>) while in 
 <italic>H. drasticus</italic> the differentiation levels were high (F
 <sub>ST</sub> from 0.036 to 0.077 over short distances)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. In contrast, the endangered 
 <italic>Paeoma rockii</italic> revealed a high differentiation between populations (F
 <sub>ST</sub> varied from 0.780 to 0.982)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>
 </sup>. Despite the narrow distributional area of 
 <italic>W. salutaris</italic> in Mozambique, this study revealed a high genetic differentiation between the northern populations located in LM and TR and the southern populations located in FC (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Pairwise F
 <sub>ST</sub> comparisons showed lower genetic differentiation between LM and TR (0.049), which are separated by only 28 km, than either between LM and FC areas (0.084, separated by 81 km) or between TR and FC (0.114, separated by 49 km). STRUCTURE analyses also found a distinct genetic cluster in the FC area, which was also supported by PCoA analyses and the NJ tree. Contrary to LM and TR areas, where 
 <italic>W. salutaris</italic> occurs in slopes and forest patches, in the FC area this species occurs near seasonal pans in thicket vegetation associated with termitaria on clay soils
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>
 </sup>. This might imply differences in reproductive ecology, particularly regarding flowering phenology and the activity of pollinators, which would affect gene flow with the other sites, explaining the genetic structure and population differentiation found between the studied sites. Thus, the differentiated FC genetic clusters could be harbouring novel and important alleles and should be given priority in in situ and ex situ conservation strategies in Mozambique
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
