<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Twenty-four female Beagle dogs sourced from Marshall Bioresources (NY, USA) were assigned to the study. At the time of randomization, they were between 1.5 and 2.9 years of age with body weights ranging from 9.3 to 11.6 kg. Each animal was identified with a unique ear tattoo and was implanted with a microchip. Bitches were in at least their second heat period when they were mated. Animals were mated 2 or 3 times, with one day interval between matings. Breeding occurred over 12 days; a different male was used for each female; for a total of 24 different males. Successful mating was defined as an observation of a tie. Males used for mating were proven breeders at least 12 months of age and confirmed healthy. Six females per group were mated to have minimum five pregnancies per group. Animals were tested for pregnancy 29 to 35 days after mating. When all six dams within a group were confirmed pregnant, one dam was randomly selected to be released from the study, so that five pregnant females per group continued on the study. Animals were assigned to cages/pens in order of ascending animal mating number for blinding purposes. Dams were housed individually in European cages (approximately 5 by 6 feet, i.e. 1.5 m by 1.8 m) equipped with an automatic watering system. About two weeks prior to parturition, a nesting box was offered to each dam. Parturition occurred over 11 days. After parturition, on post-partum day 1 (PPD 1), the size of litters with more than six puppies was adjusted by removing extra puppies by random selection to yield six puppies; the removed puppies were cross fostered on segregate dams. Similarly, on PPD 4, the size of each litter was further adjusted to 4 puppies/litter, with at least one male and one female per litter. Starting on PPD 49, a daily period of separation of the puppies from their mother was introduced. The duration was gradually increased until complete separation on PPD 56. While separated from their mother during the weaning process, the puppies had access to a bowl of electrolyte solution. At weaning on PPD 56, one puppy per sex per litter was randomly retained for the 26 weeks growth phase of the study. Dams and puppies not selected to continue on the growth phase of the study were transferred to the Citoxlab animal colony. After weaning, puppies selected for the study were pair housed in stainless steel dog cages (approximately 3 by 3 feet, i.e. 0.9 m by 0.9 m) equipped with an automatic watering system. They were separated for 6–8 hours daily to acquire individual food consumption data starting two weeks after weaning. All cages were clearly labeled with cage cards, indicating a study number, animal tattoo number, blinded animal assignment number, sex and replicate. All animals were transferred to the Citoxlab animal colony upon completion of the study.</p>
