<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Medicinal plants have potential to be used as appetizer [
 <xref rid="B37-animals-11-00048" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] (pp. 220–227), growth promoter [
 <xref rid="B38-animals-11-00048" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] (pp. 217–222), hepatic-nephric protector [
 <xref rid="B39-animals-11-00048" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] (504–514), immunomodulator [
 <xref rid="B40-animals-11-00048" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] (pp. 346–354) antistress [
 <xref rid="B41-animals-11-00048" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] (pp. 19–25) and antioxidants [
 <xref rid="B42-animals-11-00048" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] (pp. 277–284) in aquaculture practices. The results of the present study reinforce this view. In the present study, rohu fed with black seed supplemented diets showed higher growth rate when compared with fish fed an un-supplemented diet. Similar to present study results, the growth rate of 
 <italic>Oreochromis niloticus</italic> fed on 2% black seed supplemented diet improved [
 <xref rid="B43-animals-11-00048" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The growth performance of 
 <italic>Cyprinus carpio</italic> fingerlings fed on 1% black seed supplemented diet enhanced [
 <xref rid="B44-animals-11-00048" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. 
 <italic>Anabas testudineus</italic> fingerlings growth rate was increased when fed on 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> oil supplemented diets for 30 days [
 <xref rid="B27-animals-11-00048" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. 
 <italic>Onocorhynchus mykiss</italic> juveniles fed on 1% and 1.3% black seed oil supplemented diets (0.1%, 0.4%, 0.7%, 1% and 1.3%) improved their growth rate [
 <xref rid="B45-animals-11-00048" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. The growth rate of 
 <italic>O. mykiss</italic> was significantly increased when fed on 2.5 g Kg
 <sup>−1</sup> black seed powder supplemented diet for 25 days [
 <xref rid="B33-animals-11-00048" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. All these aforementioned reports support our results. Black seeds are reported to contain a variety of alkaloids, saponins, minerals (copper, iron, phosphorous and zinc) and vitamins such as folic acid, pyridoxine, riboflavin, vitamin-E and thiamin [
 <xref rid="B46-animals-11-00048" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] (239–242); the cumulative effects of all these components might have increased the growth performance of rohu.
</p>
