<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The fabrication of tapered optical fibres is generally achieved by heating a short section of the fibre while simultaneously pulling the two ends of the fibre, as illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-02294-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>. The heat source could be the flame of a gas burner [
 <xref rid="B8-sensors-19-02294" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>], high power laser radiation [
 <xref rid="B15-sensors-19-02294" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-sensors-19-02294" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], or an arc discharge [
 <xref rid="B17-sensors-19-02294" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. In single mode optical fibre, the one of the functions of the cladding is to reduce the penetration of the electric field of the propagating mode into surrounding medium. In the tapering process, the core and cladding diameters are reduced by the same proportion. This process leads to coupling of light from the fundamental mode of the untapered fibre to modes of the tapered section that can interact with the surrounding medium. The other way to facilitate the interaction of the light propagating within the optical fibre with the surrounding medium is to thin the cladding of the optical fibre, leaving the dimensions of the core unchanged. This can be achieved by chemical etching, polishing and focused ion beam etching [
 <xref rid="B18-sensors-19-02294" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. The thinning of the cladding increases the interaction of the EW of the propagating mode with the surrounding medium. In contrast to tapered fibres, there is no mode coupling between fundamental and higher order modes. The key difference between two configurations is explained in 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot3-sensors-19-02294" class="xref">Section 2.3</xref> and presents the mechanism for coupling of the fundamental core mode to higher order cladding modes in tapered fibres, while no such phenomenon is observed in thinned cladding optical fibres. This difference results in the different sensitivities, with tapered optical fibre more sensitive enabling more information to be extracted about the surrounding medium, as explained later in this review. In this review, we will focus on tapered optical fibres, i.e., optical fibres in which the core and cladding diameters are reduced by the same proportion, rather than on optical fibres with thinned claddings.
</p>
