<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1-2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">BOTANY</div>
 <sec id="sec2-1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The botany of 
   <span class="italic">Umbelliferae</span> or 
   <span class="italic">Apiaceae</span> family
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Umbelliferae</span> or 
   <span class="italic">Apiaceae</span> species have a very uniform morphology characteristics and traits that are very privileged and exclusive.[
   <a rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref8">8</a>] In recognition of genus and species of this family, the structure of fruit and base leaves of the plant, inflorescence, as well as the type of simple or compound umbel is important. All parts of the plants of this family have secretory apparatus. This family which has 275 genera and 2850 species generally grow in temperate regions of both Northern and Southern hemispheres.[
   <a rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref9">9</a>] 
   <span class="italic">Umbelliferae</span> herbs are generally herbaceous of life of a year or several years and have almost right or creeping stems and are usually striate.[
   <a rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref10">10</a>] The central part of the stem is hollow due to loss of brain cells and changes to empty-pipe or overall ducts.[
   <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">11</a>] 
   <span class="italic">Umbelliferae</span> name has been gotten from the arrangement of the flowers held in umbrella-like (
   <span class="italic">Umbelle</span>) bunches. The flowers are single, usually small, sepals are usually white, rarely pink and have five petals.[
   <a rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref12">12</a>] The fruits of the members of this family are dry consisting of one or two bayonets to back and side as a nonflourished cylinder separated by a wide or narrow screen and have no fluff or covered with them filled with scales or thorns.[
   <a rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref13">13</a>] Among 
   <span class="italic">Umbelliferae</span> species, there are various species often recognized by people and used in medicine.[
   <a rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref10">10</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Botany of 
   <span class="italic">Echinophora</span> genus
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Echinophora</span> genus has four species in Iran. Two species 
   <span class="italic">E. platyloba</span> and 
   <span class="italic">E. cinerea</span> are specific to Iran and two other species, namely 
   <span class="italic">E. sibthorpiana</span> and 
   <span class="italic">E. orientalis</span>, grow in Anatolia, Armenia, Russia, Turkmenistan, Afghanistan, Peninsula Balkans, Crete, Cyprus, and Syria, in addition to Iran.[
   <a rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref14">14</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Botany of 
   <span class="italic">Echinophora</span> platyloba
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This plant has the following characteristics: a steady base, slightly covered with pollen and downy, matte green or yellowish opaque, tough and thorny with single stems, branched from bottom, with grooved branches, yellowish or bluish-green, thick, sturdy and stiff, highly branched, with tentacles distorted, radical broad leaves with long with shoulder division with 3–5 pairs of wide-angle divisions, cornered, ovate more or less with 3–4 depth parts with 2–3 divisions thorn at the end, with separated tops, and reduced linear leaflets thorn at the end fully or triangular with yellowish flowers with collected yellow in small circles with 2–5 small rays very short or equal, bracts of triangular faces-bayonets, approximately the same, sharp, in collars almost returned, the bowl has five sharp teeth and male flowers with different heights, triangular and long folding petals slightly downy, almost not equal in height, broad elongated pear-shaped fruit with no blades or sideways, creamy cone, and complete base, with membrane, take away; flowering time is May and June.[
   <a rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref15">15</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Botany of 
   <span class="italic">Echinophora</span> sibthorpiana
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is a perennial or biennial plant, with a height of 20–50 cm, fluffy short shaggy slept together, having relatively thick, hard, single, and grooved stems. It has often large ramifications, corymb-shaped, leaves with bases of the dimensions 3.5–22 cm × 12–40 cm with the broad triangular or oval area, with three times shoulders deep divisions, with triangular-wide long-term parts and also from base to middle divided twice to 5–7 linear narrow passage, with white tips at the end, stem leaves with deep shoulder divisions, with nondivided parts or with 2–3 teeth and pale yellow flowers, with downy petals, nonradial, integrated in multiple umbrellas with 2–3[
   <a rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref5">5</a>] short beam, with 2–10 mm length, not equal height, bracts of short collar, bayonet, the triangular bayonet of the bracts, hard, long and wide pyramidal fruit, no rag or blade, umbelet of fruit-bearing 8 mm diameter, more or less ovate; flowering time is June to July.[
   <a rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref16">16</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Botany of 
   <span class="italic">Echinophora</span> orientalis
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is a perennial plant, dense and bushy, slightly downy, green, standing, highly branched, with height of 30–100 cm, with numerous stems, standing or crouching-wide, with thin branches, almost point-guard and leading up to the inflorescence umbrellas, lower leaves being large, with dimensions of 8–15 cm × 25–40 cm wide, ovate to long-term, 2–3 times deep shoulder divisions with 2–5 pairs of linear segments and cotton, with a length of 1–14 cm, very small and often simple stems, with white, small, radial flowers, integrated with the umbrella inflorescence peduncle length 3 (5.1)–10 (22) cm, bracts of 5–8 number of extents, a linear-bayonet, returned down, with the length of 5–30 mm, of the same heights or not, rays of 7 (5)–15, with a length of 5–30 mm wide at the base widened upward, a subsidiary of bract of the neck six triangular-bayonet shaped, with a length of 4–6 mm, unequal height, returned down, hard and thorns and stinging, minor pedicle 15, outer ones longer than from the bowl and the outer umbrella petals with the length of 2.5–3.5 mm, umbrella fruit as big as 5–10 mm × 8–15 mm, almost flat stretch, nut fruit leading to the creamy of 3–5 mm and the flowering period June to July.[
   <a rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref17">17</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Botany of 
   <span class="italic">Echinophora</span> cinerea
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is a perennial plant, with a height of 12–40 cm, slightly downy, with standing, thick, grooved stems, connected to panicle of short branches, base leaves with the size of 1.5–15 cm × 9–40 cm triangular to wide long, with 3–4 times deeper shoulder ramifications, covered with shaggy, long, wide divisions and subdivisions with solid, linear, narrow, short, studs, at the length of 5 mm, stem smaller and eroded, yellow flowers, inflorescence including lots of umbrella with 5–7 nonequal rays in height a length of 5–10 mm, bracteole of oval face, returned and with different heights, with dimensions of 1–2 cm × 3–4 mm, bracteole of umbelet of five, ovate and nonequal height at dimensions 1.5–3 mm × 1.5–4 mm, 10–13 peduncle of umbelet at the length of 0–4 mm, outer flowers with highlighted foot cream umbelet, with bowel ovate divisions, petals are small and shaggy rag or hairy, downy fruits, with a length of 3–3.5 mm, and flowering time is July to August[
   <a rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref18">18</a>] [
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>].
  </p>
  <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(a) 
     <span class="italic">E. cinerea</span> (Boiss.) Hedge and Lamond (picture of author), (b) 
     <span class="italic">E. platyloba</span> DC (picture of author), (c) 
     <span class="italic">E. orientalis</span> Hedge and Lamond (35), (d) 
     <span class="italic">E. sibthorpiana</span> Guss (36)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="PR-9-305-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
</sec>
