<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In these species studied, the majority of the secondary metabolites belong to flavonoids, and in particular, glycosides of the flavonols quercetin, rutine and myricetin [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. In this study, and despite differences between the different parts of the plant, the leaves appear as the organ with the highest level of total flavonoids for all species studied. Leaves are always more exposed to sunlight than other plant organs. In fact, flavonoids protect plant tissues against the harmful effects of solar radiation [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The presence of flavonoids in the four organs of the plant could suggest that the plant has anti-inflammatory properties, and could thus play a positive role in the treatment of cardiovascular and neurodegenerative diseases, also perhaps having antitumor properties [
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. On the other hand, following our results, ethanolic solvents would be able to extract the highest amounts of total flavonoids from 
 <italic>Passiflora</italic>, 
 <italic>Physalis</italic> and 
 <italic>Solanum</italic>. Mulinacci et al. [
 <xref rid="B55-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] showed that an ethanol:water solution (7:3) increases the amount of flavonoids in the extraction. In this sense, when the aerial parts of 
 <italic>Passiflora caerulea</italic> were evaluated using methanol, more flavonoid structures were detected (isoorientin, orientin, vitexin, saponarin and rutin) than when ethanol was used (isoorientin, orientin, vitexin, isovitexin) [
 <xref rid="B56-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. These findings could explain the higher level of total polyphenols and flavonoid content, which we found in our manuscript with methanol as an extractant agent in 
 <italic>Passiflora</italic> showing the highest extractant polyphenol yield, followed by ethanol. However, ethanol and water are preferable because they have the advantage of being non-polluting, less expensive and non-toxic compared to other solvents, such as methanol [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. The literature is scarce with respect to the plant parts of 
 <italic>Physalis peruviana.</italic> However, in leaves, flavonoids such as quercetin, kaempferol and rutin were the most important secondary metabolites, while the main hydroxycinnamic acids detected were p-coumaric and caffeoyl-quinic acids [
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Regarding 
 <italic>Solanum muricatum</italic>, quercetin was the most important flavonoid, while ferulic and cinnamic acids were the most abundant phenolic acids detected [
 <xref rid="B59-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].
</p>
