<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">We maintain multiple populations of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic>, whose lineages have been confirmed by RFLP analysis according to the methods of Saltonstall
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>, in a laboratory at the University of Rhode Island. For this experiment, we selected 15 different source populations that had been growing in the Rhode Island common garden for at least 3 years. Three source populations were from the Native lineage, two were from the Gulf lineage, and ten were from the Introduced lineage. The original plants were collected from across Eastern North America, spanning a latitudinal gradient from Quebec to Louisiana. Multiple individuals of each plant were propagated in water in the greenhouse from same length stem cuttings so replicates of each population were genetically identical and of standard size. When the aerial shoots of the propagules were sufficiently large (&gt;2.5 cm in length) they were separated from the larger stem on which they were growing by cutting the stem 2.5 cm on either side of the node from which the stem emerged. The surfaces of the plants and roots were dipped in a 10% bleach solution to remove any surface associated microbes and each propagule was individually planted in a clean, bleached cone-shaped “deepot” container (2.5” × 10”, D40L, Stuewe and Sons, Inc.) filled with sifted and homogenized Metromix potting soil. Individual deepots were randomly positioned in racks and racks were rotated regularly to avoid location-specific effects on plant growth. Plants were grown in the greenhouse under identical conditions of water and light for 4 months, at which point individual plants were harvested. To harvest, we gently removed the entire plant from the cone. After allowing loose soil to shake free, we then collected remaining root associated soil into individual cryovials that were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen. Remaining roots were cleaned of any residual soil and roots, shoots, and residual soils were separately bagged and dried for later analysis.
</p>
