<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">At transplanting, plants were treated either with 
 <italic class="italic">R. irregularis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">S. indica</italic> or both simultaneously. AM plants received viable propagules of 
 <italic class="italic">R. irregularis</italic> (INOQ GmbH, Schnega, Germany) inoculum (sand contained about 220 mycorrhizal units/cm3) at 10% v/v mixed throughout the soil. One mycorrhizal unit is a spore, a hyphae or a mycorrhizal root fragment. Control plants were treated with the same amount of sand without any microorganisms in order to create the same soil conditions. 
 <italic class="italic">S. indica</italic> was grown on PDA plates for 2 weeks (Carl Roth, Karlsruhe, Germany). A small hyphal plug was transferred in 500 mL conical flasks with liquid complete media (CM: 50 mL 20x salt solution (120 g NaNO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>, 10.4 g KCl, 10.4 g MgSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> × 7 H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O, and 30 g KH
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>PO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> in 1 L), 20 g glucose, 2 g peptone, 1 g yeast extract, 1 g casamine acids and 1 mL microelements (6 g MnCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, 1.5 g H
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>BO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>, 2.65 g ZnSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> × 7 H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O, 750 mg KI, 2.4 mg NaMO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> × 2 H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O, 130 mg CuSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> × 5 H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O dissolved in 1 L) and incubated for 3 weeks in the dark at 24°C. This liquid fungal culture was blended in a kitchen blender to obtain a mixture as homogeneous as possible. Afterward, this liquid suspension of 
 <italic class="italic">S. indica</italic> hyphae and spores was used to soak plant roots of sweet basil. Control sweet basil seedling received the same amount of autoclaved (121°C for 20 min) 
 <italic class="italic">S. indica</italic> suspension (mock treatment). The application of lead nitrate [Pb(NO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>)
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> × 7 H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O, Carl Roth, Karlsruhe, Germany] solution and/or copper sulfate (CuSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> × 5 H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O, Carl Roth, Karlsruhe, Germany) solution to the potting substrate was conducted either separately for the single heavy metal treatment (400 mg/L) or in combination (200 mg/L each). An amount of 400 mg/L was chosen because higher amounts induced plant toxicity. Plants in the control group remained untreated. One week after transferring the seedlings to the pots and inoculating them with the fungi, the plants were irrigated every day with 100 ml of the stock solution (400 mg/L) containing the appropriate metal ions over a period of 10 days, to avoid a shock for the plants and to gradually achieve 400 mg total heavy metal amount in the soil. Thereafter plants were irrigated with tap water. The factorial design of the experiment resulted in total in 16 treatments (see Table 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>), each with 9 replicates.
</p>
