<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Tested strains were obtained from ATCC and the Laboratory of Fungi Biology, Department of Microbiology and Immunology, São Paulo State University (UNESP-Botucatu Campus). No ATCC strains were molecularly identified and deposited at GenBank database of the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). The following microorganisms were used in the evaluation of antifungal activity of the essential oil: 
 <italic>Candida krusei</italic> (ATCC 6258), 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> (ATCC 36801), 
 <italic>Candida guilliermondii</italic> (ATCC 22017), 
 <italic>Candida parapsilosis</italic> (ATCC 90018), 
 <italic>Candida orthopsilosis</italic> (ATCC 96141), 
 <italic>Candida metapsilosis</italic> (ATCC 96142), 
 <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> (ATCC 90012), 
 <italic>Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</italic> (strain TLM17LM2, GenBank accession number KX774393, yeast form), 
 <italic>Microsporum canis</italic> (strain RS5, GenBank accession number KT443098) and 
 <italic>Trichophyton mentagrophytes</italic> (ATCC 11480). A microdilution broth susceptibility assay for yeasts and filamentous fungi was performed, as recommended by Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute [
 <xref rid="B65-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], with some adaptations. Assays were performed on 96-well microplates (Costar, Cambridge, MA, USA) with RPMI-1640 supplemented with glutamine without sodium bicarbonate (Cultilab, Campinas, Brazil). A sample of essential oil was dissolved in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO, Synth, São Paulo) and a serial dilution was performed to achieve concentrations ranging from 2.44 to 5000 μg·mL
 <sup>−1</sup>. The final DMSO concentration was 3% (
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>). For inoculums, adjustment of yeast (
 <italic>Candida</italic> spp., 
 <italic>C. neoformans</italic>, 
 <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic>) was performed using microscopic enumeration with a cell-counting hematocytometer (Neubauer chamber, Knittel Gläser, Braunschweig, Germany) from the initial growth at RPMI-1640 medium. 
 <italic>Candida</italic> spp. was grown at 37 °C for 48 h, 
 <italic>C. neoformans</italic> at 37 °C for 72 h and 
 <italic>P. brasiliensis</italic> at 35 °C for 10 days. After counting, the inoculums were adjusted to a final concentration of 1.2 × 10
 <sup>3</sup> cell mL
 <sup>−1</sup>. Filamentous fungi, 
 <italic>M. canis</italic> and 
 <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic>, were grown on potato dextrose agar (PDA; Oxoid, Basingstoke, Hampshire, UK) for 7 days at 25 °C before counting. Cell counting in a Neubauer chamber was also performed, and microplates were inoculated with a final concentration of 2 × 10
 <sup>4</sup> cell mL
 <sup>−1</sup>. The tested systems were incubated in a humid atmosphere, with agitation, at 37 °C for 48 h for 
 <italic>Candida</italic> spp. and 72 h for 
 <italic>C. neoformans. P. brasiliensis</italic> was incubated for 14 days at 35 °C with agitation and 
 <italic>M. canis</italic> and 
 <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> for 10 days at 25 °C without agitation. The experiment was performed in six replicates and the growth inhibition was determined by measuring turbidity of the cultured medium at 530 nm using a spectrophotometer (BioTek, Winooski, VT, USA). Amphotericin B (Sigma-Aldrich) was used as positive control. Controls of sterility of the broth, control culture (inoculum), essential oil and DMSO (3%) were performed.
</p>
