<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The simultaneous inhibition of ChEs and indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase 1 (IDO1) resulted in another target combination endowed with beneficial effects in AD. IDO is an intracellular cytosolic heme-containing enzyme that regulates the degradation of Tryptophan (Trp) to N-formylkynurenine in the kynurenine pathway (KP), acting as a first-step rate controller [
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. KP is unbalanced in some neurodegenerative disorders and, as a result, Trp catabolism leads to neurotoxic metabolites such as 3-hydroxykunurenine. IDO1 is essential for this pathway, and its activation has been linked with A
 <italic>β</italic>-related inflammation in AD [
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], making it the focus of various researches on neurodegenerative diseases treatment [
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>–
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Lu et al. have identified a novel structure endowed with double activity on BuChE and IDO1 [
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. The selective activity on BuChE is of particular interest, as its levels rise up in the advanced stages of AD, replacing AChE deficiency in the hydrolysis of Ch, thus becoming an even more important target. Compounds with general structure 
 <bold>22</bold> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref>) are prototypes based on the antifungal drug Miconazole, which had already shown activity as an IDO1 inhibitor [
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and was tested in vivo as a reference compound. The 3-OMe or 4-OMe-substituted analogues showed the weakest activity on AChE and the best inhibitory IC
 <sub>50</sub> values on BuChE and IDO1 (8.3 and 2.8 
 <italic>μ</italic>M for the 3-OMe and 16.5 and 1.0 
 <italic>μ</italic>M for the 4-OMe, respectively), being more potent than Miconazole. Their effect on spatial memory was assessed in the scopolamine-induced impairment in mice, where they displayed better performances than the control group treated with THA. Moreover, no acute hepatotoxic damage was observed. Taken together, all these characteristics highlight the favorable potential for these structures to combine interesting activities on innovative AD-related targets.
</p>
