<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another interesting approach in the search for MTDLs comes from Gao et al., who presented dual ChE and Poly(ADP-ribose) Polymerase-1 (PARP-1) inhibitors [
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. PARP-1 inhibitors have been extensively studied for their anticancer activity [
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], but they may also serve as potential therapeutics for neurodegenerative diseases, with particular attention to AD and PD [
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The role of PARP-1 has not yet been fully elucidated, but there are emerging evidences for the neuroprotective effect of its inhibitors. To merge the PARP-1 inhibition with that on ChEs, the structure of the known PARP-1 inhibitor Olaparib has been selected and modified with the introduction of substituted aryl vinyl groups in the place of the cyclopropane one (
 <bold>23</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref>). This combination should guarantee the dual activity on PARP-1 and ChEs, since it led to the formation of 3-aromatic-
 <italic>α</italic>,
 <italic>β</italic>-unsaturated carbonyl moieties, which are recurring groups in several natural ChE inhibitors and bioactive/neuroprotective compounds. The 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> test revealed that all the analogues of the series were low micromolar inhibitors of PARP-1, even though none of them was more potent than the parent compound Olaparib. However, they showed moderate micromolar activity against AChE and BuChE, being more potent inhibitors of this latter enzyme. When Ar was a 3- or 4-nitrosubstituted phenyl ring, the highest inhibitory potency against BuChE was achieved, with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 9.2 and 5.9 
 <italic>μ</italic>M, respectively, even greater than Neostigmine as the reference. The abovementioned analysis confirmed the dual activity of these analogues and, although they may not be potent enough for 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> analysis, molecular docking studies have already helped find a way to improve their activity. Thus, another interesting class of MTDLs may arise from the combination of these pharmacophoric elements leading to dual ChE and PARP-1 inhibition.
</p>
