<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Because of brittleness and the absence of defensive tissue, nutritionally rich edible fungi are at greater risk of mechanical damage and microbial spoilage. This leads to losses due to concurrent discoloration, quality deterioration, or even decay of the fruiting body of fungi [
 <xref rid="B134-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. In this regard, Pan et al. fabricated an electrospun crosslinked polyvinyl alcohol CPVA/CEO/β-CD nanofibrous film loaded with CEO [
 <xref rid="B135-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. Chemical crosslinking and physical welding were achieved by atomizing and fumigating PVA with the aid of glutaraldehyde to reduce its high water solubility [
 <xref rid="B136-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>]. This otherwise limits its application in food preservation despite many advantages such as low price, harmlessness, high chemical stability, excellent film-forming performance, and biological compatibility [
 <xref rid="B137-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. CEO was encapsulated into β-CD to reduce its high volatility, water infusibility, and pungent odor [
 <xref rid="B138-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. The precise scanning electron microscope images in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-04017-f009">Figure 9</xref> indicated that the CEO increased the nanofiber diameter when β-CD was available in the structure. The CPVA/CEO (1.5 mL)/β-CD nanofibrous films had a water-contact angle of ≈90°, thus increasing their hydrophilicity, as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-04017-f010">Figure 10</xref> [
 <xref rid="B139-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>,
 <xref rid="B140-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>,
 <xref rid="B141-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>]. Moreover, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-04017-f011">Figure 11</xref> shows that when β-CD was added to the PVA/CEO solution, the fibers showed the zone of inhibition against 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>. This effect was enhanced further as the CEO concentration was increased [
 <xref rid="B142-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>,
 <xref rid="B143-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. Thus, CPVA/β-CD/CEO nanofibrous films can slow down mushrooms’ spoilage rate during their storage, demonstrating their potential application in active food packaging.
</p>
