<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="order" class="list">
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Load the sample into a Hassler-type core holder
   <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref> (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>) by following the steps below.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Dismantle the core holder assembly by removing the sealing screw and the M4 bolts of the flowhead. Remove the sealing ring from its groove in the flowhead and clean the sealing surfaces using a clean cloth with a cleaning liquid such as acetone. Place the core holder assembly components on a clear bench in good order (see 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>
   <bold class="bold">A</bold> for the sealing screw, 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>
   <bold class="bold">B</bold> for the flowhead, 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>
   <bold class="bold">C</bold> for the 1/16 PEEK tubing, 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>
   <bold class="bold">D</bold> for the stainless steel end fitting, 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>
   <bold class="bold">E</bold> for the rock sample, 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>
   <bold class="bold">F</bold> for the rubber tubing, 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>
   <bold class="bold">G</bold> for the thermocouple, 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>
   <bold class="bold">I</bold> for the carbon fiber sleeve, and 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>
   <bold class="bold">J</bold> for the flexible heating jacket).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Wrap the flexible heating jacket around the carbon fiber sleeve.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Insert a thermocouple to the annulus via the base of the core holder.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Use a proportional-integral-derivative (PID) controller (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>) that is custom built to control the temperature within ± 1 °C
   <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>. NOTE: Maintaining a stable temperature within ± 1 °C is important to avoid changing the interfacial tension of oil and brine that could affect the contact angle measurement
   <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>
   <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Thread polyether ether ketone (PEEK) tubing through the top and base of the core holder. Then, connect the PEEK tubing to the custom-made end pieces.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Cut a rubber tubing to a length approximately equal to the rock sample length plus the end pieces. Slide the sample gently into a rubber tubing and connect it to the end pieces. Ensure that the rubber tubing gives a tight fit over the end pieces to avoid having a leak of the confining fluid into the sample.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Place the thermocouple tip next to the sample to measure the temperature of the fluids within the pores.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Carefully assemble both ends of the core holder. Ensure that the sample is positioned at the center of the core holder to be in the scanning field of view.</p>
 </list-item>
</list>
