<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Fragrances play a particularly important role in increasing the attractiveness of cosmetics. Pleasant smells influence the comfortability and the effect of the products and also impact significantly on the overall evaluation of cosmetics. Therefore, along with the shape and design of the container, the smell is also one of the characteristics of cosmetics that the consumer experiences [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-26-00666" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and look forward to in the selection of those items. Among natural fragrances, essential oils, which are complex mixtures of terpenes and other aromatic or aliphatic compounds, produced as secondary metabolites in specialized secretory tissues of aromatic plants [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-00666" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], are the most popular. In nature, essential oils play very important roles in plant defense and signaling processes. For instance, they are involved in plant defense against insects, herbivores, and microorganisms, including attraction of pollinating insects and fruit-dispersing animals, water regulation and allelopathic interactions [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-00666" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-00666" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-00666" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Once the plants have been harvested, the essential oil is extracted by means of steam distillation, expression (physical crushing of essential oil glands situated in fruit rinds or outermost waxy layer of fruit’s peel) [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-00666" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], microwave-assisted extraction, solvent extraction, or enfleurage (transfer of the essential oil from flower petals to fat). Of these methods, steam distillation is the most common overall, while expression is most commonly used to obtain essential oils from the peels of citrus fruits such as orange, lemon, bergamot, etc.) [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-00666" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].
</p>
