<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our interpretation and translation of old Persian names into scientific names was based on a book by 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Ghahreman and Okhovvat (2009)</xref>, which provides accounts of the most relevant scientific names according to morphological descriptions. The list of plants retrieved during this process was then searched in electronic databases including PubMed, Scopus, Cochrane Library, and Web of Science. Data were collected from inception until March 2020. Only published articles were included in this review and unpublished works were not considered. Language restriction was performed, and English language articles were included. The search terms were the scientific names and common names of each plant combined with “antiviral”, “influenza”, “lung”, “pulmonary”, “alveolar infiltration”, “cardiac”, “heart”, “cardiomyopathy”, “renal”, “kidney”, or “immunomodulatory”. The inclusion criteria were any 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, or clinical evidence on the antiviral activity of the selected plants against human pathogenic RNA viruses. Additionally, any study about the beneficial effects of these plants or their isolated phytochemicals on the heart, lungs, and kidneys was included. Studies on animal/plant viral pathogens were excluded. This review does not include 
 <italic>in silico</italic> antiviral analyses, however, they are referred to in the discussion of the mechanisms and pharmacological effects reported in experiments and studies. The references of the included articles were also searched in order to find additional relevant studies. The plants discussed in the TPM sources and their protective mechanisms are listed in 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">
  <bold>Table 1</bold>
 </xref> and the pharmacological evidence obtained from published papers are summarized in 
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">
  <bold>Table 2</bold>
 </xref>. 
 <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">
  <bold>Table 3</bold>
 </xref> shows a quality assessment of animal studies based on the Animal Research: Reporting of In vivo Experiments (ARRIVE) guidelines (
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">McGrath and Lilley, 2015</xref>).
</p>
