<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Future climate scenarios for most drylands predict an increased severity and frequency of drought, greater variability in precipitation, and warmer temperatures (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Cayan et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">IPCC, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Reidmiller et al., 2018</xref>). Additionally, warmer temperatures will likely change the form of precipitation, as cooler months will experience more rain instead of snow (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Barnett et al., 2005</xref>). Such changes to climate could alter species ranges, create new temporal niches in plant communities, and differentially affect multiple plant species. For example, winter annuals that grow early in the season are often limited by cold winter temperatures and may be more likely to germinate in response to winter rains resulting from increased temperatures. This earlier germination could infer a competitive advantage over plants that initiate growth later in the season, provided the temperatures are sufficiently high to meet germination requirements, but not too low to induce mortality of the seedlings (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Beatley, 1974</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Kimball et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Wolkovich and Cleland, 2011</xref>). Additionally, invasive annual plants often employ more flexible resource acquisition strategies that can facilitate rapid phenological responses (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Funk, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">Wolkovich and Cleland, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">Winkler et al., 2018</xref>). Given this, invasive plants may be better adapted to tolerate climate change than co-occurring native annuals and perennials, especially those existing at range edges or experiencing novel climate regimes (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">Seastedt et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">Willis et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">Wolkovich and Cleland, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Ashbacher and Cleland, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Phillips, 2019</xref>). Further, invasive annual plants may germinate rapidly, increase growth rates, or advance flower and seed production in response to earlier spring temperatures, unseasonably early rains, and nutrient pulses (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Esque et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">Willis et al., 2010</xref>). Often, invasive plants are better suited to exploit temporal niches than native plants and this can allow invasives to exploit resources at times when natives are inactive, which can lead to subsequent shifts in community composition, vegetation cover, nutrient cycling, and fire regimes (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">D’Antonio and Vitousek, 1992</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Bradley et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">Willis et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Dickens and Allen, 2014</xref>). Together, these traits that allow rapid concerted responses to changing climate have led to predictions of increased invasive species’ ranges and abundance under future climate scenarios (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Bradley et al., 2010</xref>), however, data assessing climate change effects on the timing and success of exotic plants are relatively rare.
</p>
