<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic> (cheatgrass) is one of the most destructive invasive annual plants in North American dryland ecosystems (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Knapp, 1996</xref>). Areas where 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> has naturalized have seen subsequent alterations to fire regimes, native plant composition and survival, and hydrological and nutrient cycles (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">D’Antonio and Vitousek, 1992</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">Rimer and Evans, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Keeley and Brennan, 2012</xref>). 
 <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic> is a native of central Eurasia and was introduced to the western United States in the late 1800s: the exotic grass is highly invasive, and it spread rapidly across the West. This species now covers an estimated 22.7 million hectares in the United States (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Duncan et al., 2004</xref>) and an estimated one-third of the Great Basin Desert (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Bradley et al., 2018</xref>). Invaded areas include at least 20 million hectares where 
 <italic>B. tectoru</italic>m is dominant, or nearly so (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Novak and Mack, 2001</xref>). Additionally, 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> is continuing to spread at an estimated rate of 14% (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Duncan et al., 2004</xref>), moving into high elevation areas after disturbance (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Mealor et al., 2012</xref>), with millions of hectares considered highly likely to experience future invasion (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Pellant and Hall, 1994</xref>). It has been suggested that 
 <italic>B. tectoru</italic>m is able to successfully invade and establish because it has more competitive life history traits than native plants, traits that include high specific leaf area, high nitrogen-use efficiency, faster relative growth rates, and higher and faster rates of seed production (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Hulbert, 1955</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Harris, 1967</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">Wainwright et al., 2012</xref>). Using these traits, 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> has been shown to respond to disturbances including fire, nutrient deposition, and climate change via an increased capacity to tune growth strategies (including phenology) to extant conditions, thereby increasing invasiveness (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Peeler and Smithwick, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Mesa and Dlugosch, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">Williamson et al., 2020</xref>). Once established, 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> can limit water availability and the species’ relatively early phenology can further exacerbate negative impacts on native plants (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Harris, 1967</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Melgoza et al., 1990</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Eliason and Allen, 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Booth et al., 2003</xref>). 
 <italic>Bromus tectorum’s</italic> early and flexible phenology may synergize with future climate conditions and increase its competitive advantage over native plants, as 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> may be able to take advantage of earlier growing seasons and early season rain events that native plants cannot utilize (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abatzoglou and Kolden, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Bradley et al., 2016</xref>).
</p>
