<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Different extracts of 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> have been investigated upon administration in study models (
 <xref rid="plants-10-00063-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In one case, collagen-induced arthritic rats were treated with a 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> extract that arrested the degenerative changes in the bone and joints [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-10-00063" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Potent action was shown to occur using aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> and 
 <italic>B. aristata</italic> against endotoxin-induced uveitis in rabbits when administered topically [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-10-00063" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. An oil-free aqueous extract (COFAE) of 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> and curcuminoids showed significant anti-inflammatory effects against acute and chronic inflammation [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-10-00063" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. A recent study investigated the aerial parts of this species, where its extracts were applied on RAW264.7 macrophage cells. An 
 <italic>n</italic>-butanol fraction significantly curbed the lipopolysaccharide-mediated induction of several mediators, such as nitric oxide, prostaglandin E
 <sub>2</sub>, and pro-inflammatory cytokines, by reducing the levels of nitric oxide synthase and cyclooxygenase-2 in a dose-dependent manner [
 <xref rid="B36-plants-10-00063" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. A polysaccharide fraction (F1) of a 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> aqueous-based extract (NR-INF-02) was also investigated in classical rodent models of inflammation. F1 has been considered for its potential in acute (carrageenan-induced paw edema and xylene-induced ear edema) and chronic (cotton-pellet-induced granuloma) models of inflammation [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-10-00063" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) extracts and curcumin was investigated on human intervertebral disc cells and it was suggested that the intra-distal injection of curcumin could be an alternative approach to treating inflammation [
 <xref rid="B38-plants-10-00063" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].
</p>
