<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the many advantages of cold pressing, the low-cost and sustainable oil extraction technique suffers from low oil yield due to a significant amount of oil that remains trapped in the pressed meal, which has hindered its development and commercial viability [
 <xref rid="B15-foods-10-00712" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Nonetheless, this may be improved by blanching or microwave heating the oil-bearing seeds before pressing. According to Kaseke et al. [
 <xref rid="B9-foods-10-00712" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], blanching seeds improved the pomegranate seed oil yield and bioactive compounds recovery with ethanol. Moreover, seed blanching is a novel technique that presents a sustainable strategy capable of improving seed oil quality whilst significantly reducing the oil extraction time and energy consumption during cold pressing [
 <xref rid="B16-foods-10-00712" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Blanching significantly changes the seed matrix’s structural integrity by disintegrating the cell walls and membranes, which may enhance the extractability of the intracellular material by cold pressing [
 <xref rid="B17-foods-10-00712" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Nevertheless, microwave pretreatment is the commonly used technique to improve oil yield and bioactive compounds recovery in cold-pressed oils [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-10-00712" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-foods-10-00712" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-foods-10-00712" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-foods-10-00712" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], due to its uniform energy delivery, high thermal conductivity to the interior of the material, energy saving, and precise process control [
 <xref rid="B22-foods-10-00712" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Although the influence of seed pretreatment on the oil recovery efficiency of mechanical pressing has been studied, comparative studies on seed pretreatment techniques’ potential to improve the quality of cold-pressed oil are limited.
</p>
