<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Thyme leaves are used to sweeten and flavor variety of foods in Ethiopia.
 <xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> A phytochemical analysis of the essential oil from 
 <italic>Thymus Schimperi</italic> has demonstrated that terpinoids such as β-myrcene, α-terpinene, γ-terpinene, α-terpineol, limonene, carvacrol, α-humulene, p-cymene are the major constituents.
 <xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> In addition, the Ethiopian 
 <italic>T. Schimperi</italic> has many traditional medicinal applications.
 <xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
 <italic>T. schimperi</italic> is suggested for many uses based upon its antimicrobial (against bacteria, virus, fungus and others), spasmolytic and antitussive and scavenging free radical activity.
 <xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> The dried leaves of 
 <italic>T. schimperi</italic> are also used in TM for management of gonorrhea, relief of pain due to headache, toothache, stomachache, and earache, reduce inflammation, as antispasmolytic, blood clotting, overcome urinary retention problems, mental illness like psychosis, eye disease, liver disease, respiratory disorder (leprosy and lung tuberculosis), skin disorder (acne and ascaris).
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Some of pharmacological research on crude and fractional extracts of different parts of 
 <italic>T. schimperi</italic> includes, the antioxidant activity and preservative effect,
 <xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> antimicrobial,
 <xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> diuretic and antihypertensive activity of leaf extracts
 <xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> and antioxidant and α-amylase inhibition activities.
 <xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> In particular in the Ethiopian Oromia region, North Shoa Zone, 
 <italic>T</italic>. schimperi leaves have been used for the management of DM.
 <xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Therefore, based on this TD value claim the current work is initiated to assess the antidiabetic activity of crude leaf extract of 
 <italic>T. schimperi</italic> in chemically induced diabetic mice (acute study and subacute).
</p>
