<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, the studied extracts demonstrated a relatively low cytotoxic activity against all cell lines used. This activity did not differ significantly from one line to another treated by the same extract, which means that these extracts reacted in the same way regardless of the cell used. These findings agree with the literature [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Among the extracts, 
 <italic>P. furfuracea</italic> extract was found to induce the largest effect against all cancer cell lines tested, especially on human prostate cancer (22RV1) cell lines at exposure time 72 h. This result agrees with those reported in the previous study which showed that the extracts of 
 <italic>E. prunastri</italic> and 
 <italic>P. furfuracea</italic> possess cytotoxic effects against human melanoma (FemX) and human colon carcinoma (LS174) with similar IC
 <sub>50</sub> values to ours (55.09–120.89 
 <italic>µ</italic>g/mL). Moreover, the strongest cytotoxic activity was presented by 
 <italic>P. furfuracea</italic>. It was also determined that these extracts induced cell death caused by a strong arrest of the sub-G1 phase in the cell cycle of LS174 and FemX cells [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The literature also pointed out that either raw lichen extracts or their purified components were effective against different cancer cell lines even at low concentrations [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. However, according to the American National Cancer Institute guidelines, the IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of the three lichen extracts found in this study did not indicate strong cytotoxic activity IC
 <sub>50</sub> &gt; 30 
 <italic>µ</italic>g/mL [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], while the strong cytotoxic effect of physodic acid isolated from 
 <italic>P. furfuracea</italic> vs. FemX and LS174 cancer cells with IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 19.52 and 17.89 
 <italic>µ</italic>g/mL, respectively, was already reported [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p>
