<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To evaluate the effects of herbivory on the populations of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>, an herbivore exclosure experiment was conducted on Qingshan Island in 2015. On 8 May 2015, 9 communities without 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> were selected that were spaced more than 50 m apart in four habitats (two communities under trees, two communities on roadsides, four communities in grasses, and one community in a lake littoral zone). Two 1-m × 1-m plots were established in each community. To maintain the homogeneity of the soil and vegetation, the distances between the two plots in each community were kept within a range of 0.2 m to 1 m. In the centre of each plot, the vegetation was removed from a 0.3-m × 0.3-m area, and six 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> of similar height and weight (mean height and fresh weight of 40 cm and 3.802 g, respectively) that had been collected from a field population and cultivated for three weeks were planted in each bare area. Each of the plots was randomly assigned to one of two treatments: (1) herbivore-excluded or (2) natural-control. The herbivore-excluded treatment was caged with a screen (1-m × 1-m × 1-m nylon net with 120 mesh and light transmittance of ≥95%), and all of the plants were sprayed with cyfluthrin and DDVP insecticides twice a month to exclude herbivores. The natural-control treatment was in an open natural area where all of the plants were exposed to natural enemies. Two weeks later, we thinned each plot to four similar-sized plants to minimize the plant-size variation among the plots. In the last week of June/July/August, the defoliation of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> in both the herbivore-excluded and the natural-control treatments was determined by the previously described method. The experiment lasted five months, and the 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> was harvested on 8 October 2015. The number and total lengths of the shoots were measured, and the shoot biomass and root biomass were determined after drying at 70 °C for 72 h. The total biomass was the sum of the shoot biomass and the root biomass.
</p>
