<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060">S protein is cleaved by proteases into two domain S1 and S2, of which S2 domain is responsible for entering fusion protein inside the membrane of host cell and ultimately facilitating the entry of virus into the cell [
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Unlike SARS-CoV-2, some coronaviruses like MHV-2 and SARS-CoV do not need cleavage of spike protein for entering purpose, they can directly enter inside the cell with the presence of exogenous proteases and this process is 100–1000 fold efficient than the endosomal pathway. Proteases like transmembrane protease/serine family (TMPRSS) and human airway trypsin like protease (HAT) both induce the fusion of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Once the fusion occurs and fusion protein enters the host cell, ACE-2 gets cleaved and it is covered by ADAM17 in extra membranal space which convert angiotensin I to angiotensin II, a negative regulator of renin angiotensin pathway and this reduced ACE-2 is responsible for respiratory injury and illness [
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Once viral protein gets translated into the cell, various pathways gets activated and are associated with spreading of infection. An ORF3a protein code for Ca
 <sup>+2</sup> ion channel and activates transcription of NF-kB pathway by interacting TRAF3. The ORF8b protein activates the inflammasome pathway through NLRP3. All these pathways result in overproduction of cytokines and thus cause respiratory problems. JNK pathway is also activated by ORF3a, ORF3b and ORF7a which is responsible for lung disorders [
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. The viral infection can be minimized if the virions do not bind to the cell and this can be done by inactivating the virus. SARS-CoV-2 binds more strongly to the receptor ACE-2 than the SARS-CoV and therefore infection transmission rate and virulence is much higher than the SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. TMPRSS2 associated with ACE-2 is responsible for spreading the infection at initial stages and thus could be another therapeutic target for the new drug discovery [
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].
</p>
