<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">Antioxidants afford a cellular protective mechanism against oxidative stress within the human body. They pertain to the potential to extinguish reactive oxygen species by furnishing hydrogen atoms or electrons, chelating transitional metal ions, invigoration of enzymes, namely superoxide dismutase (SOD), catalase (CAT) glutathione peroxidase (GPx) as well as preventing the oxidizing entities. However, these protective techniques are sometimes inadequate due to the large pathological condition; hence, antioxidant additives play an essential role in encountering oxidative detriment (Gul et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">2013</xref>). Medicinal plants have rescued association in contemporary times due to their elevating abundant biological characteristics appearing apperception of their provenance, functioning structural variations (Sen and Samanta 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR300">2014</xref>). Medicinal plants are attaining significant consideration because of their remarkable antioxidant potential with lesser side effects (Auddy et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2003</xref>). They accommodate a vast range of chemical compositions, which may impart their effect specifically or corroboratory to cure the diseases integrated with oxidative stress, ameliorate health (Bhatt et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2007</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>). The polyphenolic preparation of extract from leaves of 
 <italic>A. annua,</italic> and 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> L. was estimated as a modality of natural antioxidants (Skowyra et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR317">2014</xref>). Leaves of 
 <italic>A. annua</italic>, extract for antioxidant activity have been performed by interpolating different solvents, i.e., chloroform, hexane, ethyl acetate, methanol–water. The antioxidant potential is evaluated by estimating total phenolic and flavonoid content (TPC and TFC), ferric reducing antioxidant power (FRAP), Trolox equivalent antioxidant capacity (TEAC), 2,2-Diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl Hydrate (DPPH) radical scavenging activity, and lipid peroxidation. The extreme TPC, TFC, TEAC, DPPH radical scavenging, and little lipid peroxidation effects were carried out in methanol (CH
 <sub>3</sub>OH) extracts, although aqueous extract evinces exorbitant ferric reducing antioxidant strength demonstrating CH
 <sub>3</sub>OH to be the highly suited suitable extract (Temraz and El-tantawy 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR342">2008</xref>; Iqbal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR146">2012</xref>; Katiyar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR169">2012</xref>; Qadir et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR275">2014</xref>; Pereira et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR267">2018</xref>; Sembiring et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR298">2018</xref>). The aqueous ethanolic extracts of 
 <italic>A. nilagirica</italic> asserted for estimation of in-vitro antioxidant activity, superoxide scavenging activity, total flavanol content, total phenolic content, hydrogen donating activity and reducing power assay, etc. (Devmurari et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2010</xref>; Khezrilu and Heidari 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR174">2014</xref>; Pal and Ghosh 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR256">2018</xref>).
</p>
