<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Appendino et al. investigated the antibacterial activity of five major cannabinoids and their analogs against a range of MDR 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> isolates [
 <xref rid="B60-antibiotics-09-00406" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. It was found that cannabidiolic acid (CBDA) possesses good antimicrobial activity (MIC = 2 μg/mL, 
 <bold>8</bold>), which was further improved with omission of the carboxylate moiety (
 <bold>9</bold>). This has recently been verified by Martinenghi and co-workers, who observed that against several Gram-positive pathogens, CBD had MIC values in range of 1–2 μg/mL, compared with CBDA (2–4 μg/mL) [
 <xref rid="B61-antibiotics-09-00406" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The methyl and phenethyl esters of CBDA were inactive (
 <bold>13</bold>, 
 <bold>14</bold>), which could be caused by the added hydrophobicity and/or steric bulk. Acetylation or methylation of the hydroxyl groups (
 <bold>10</bold>–
 <bold>12</bold>) was also detrimental for activity and indicates the importance of the resorcinol moiety. The MIC for cannabichromene (
 <bold>15</bold>) was 1–2 μg/mL, which is consistent with the findings of Turner et al. [
 <xref rid="B59-antibiotics-09-00406" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. CBGA (
 <bold>16</bold>) possessed moderate activity, which was again improved with removal of the carboxylate (CBG, 
 <bold>17</bold>). Acetylation (
 <bold>18</bold>) and methylation (
 <bold>19</bold>, 
 <bold>20</bold>) of the hydroxyls was again detrimental for activity, as was esterification of CBGA (
 <bold>21</bold>, 
 <bold>22</bold>). ∆
 <sup>9</sup>-THC acid (
 <bold>23</bold>) possessed only a moderate bactericidal effect compared to ∆
 <sup>9</sup>-THC and CBN (
 <bold>24, 25</bold>). Interestingly, swapping the hydroxyl at position 1 and the 
 <italic>n</italic>-pentyl group at position 3 in both CBD and CBG (
 <bold>26</bold>, 
 <bold>27</bold>) did not significantly affect activity. Di-hydroxylation of the prenyl tail in CBG (
 <bold>28</bold>) attenuated potency; prenylation at position 2 abolished activity. Resorcinol was also evaluated with and without an 
 <italic>n</italic>-pentyl group (
 <bold>30</bold>, 
 <bold>31</bold>); although the overall antimicrobial effect was poor, it still demonstrated the importance of the hydrocarbon chain.
</p>
