<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Farha and co-workers evaluated several cannabinoid analogs against MRSA USA300 and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> [
 <xref rid="B65-antibiotics-09-00406" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Several common cannabinoids (
 <bold>35</bold>–
 <bold>43</bold>, 
 <bold>45</bold>, 
 <bold>47</bold>) demonstrated moderate to good activity; these results mostly align with previous studies (vide supra). Δ
 <sup>9</sup>-Tetrahydrocannabivarin (
 <bold>44</bold>) and related analogs (
 <bold>46</bold>, 
 <bold>48</bold>, 
 <bold>49</bold>), which bear a common 
 <italic>n</italic>-propyl chain at position 3, experienced up to a four-fold increase in MIC values, thus further highlighting the importance of the 
 <italic>n</italic>-pentyl chain, which could play a role in membrane insertion. Carboxylation (
 <bold>50</bold>) and hydroxylation (
 <bold>51</bold>) at position 11 of Δ
 <sup>9</sup>-THC resulted in a loss of activity which indicates that lipophilicity may be important in the prenyl tail. Polycyclic cannabicyclol had low activity (
 <bold>52</bold>). CBG showed promising levels of efficacy in a murine systemic infection model of MRSA whereby the bacterial burden in the spleen was reduced by a factor of 2.8 log
 <sub>10</sub> in CFU. None of these analogs displayed a bactericidal effect against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> however, with consistent MIC values of &gt;128 μg/mL recorded. Interestingly, CBG was found to be effective against Gram-negative organisms in combination with polymyxin B or the less nephrotoxic polymyxin B nonapeptide. It is proposed that polymyxins permeabilize the outer membrane of Gram-negative pathogens to enable CBG to act on the inner membrane. Similarly, Kosgodage et al. found that CBD can act as a sensitizing agent in combination with various antibiotics [
 <xref rid="B66-antibiotics-09-00406" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. For Gram-negative pathogens, CBD strongly inhibited the release of membrane vesicles, which play a role in inter-bacterial communication and the transfer of cargo molecules. When 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> VCS257 was treated with CBD in combination with erythromycin, vancomycin, rifampicin, kanamycin or colistin, an enhanced antimicrobial effect was observed. These results are significant as they highlight the potential of cannabinoids as potentiators to improve the efficacy and broad-spectrum activity of existing antibiotic drugs.
</p>
