<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) is a feature of advanced carcinomas, essential for many developmental processes, wound healing, organ fibrosis and also is one of the causes of cancer cell invasion and metastasis [
 <xref rid="B184-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>]. EMT involves loss of epithelial markers including E-cadherin, weakening of cell-cell adhesion, and the expression of some fibroblast markers including vimentin, α-smooth muscle actin (α-SMA), and desmin [
 <xref rid="B185-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>,
 <xref rid="B186-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>]. Moreover, it is well known that adding TGF-β to epithelial cells in culture results in EMT induction in different epithelial cells [
 <xref rid="B187-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">187</xref>]. Treatment of CCl
 <sub>4</sub>-induced liver fibrosis rats with MPEO produced a significant reduction in ALT, AST, MDA and NO (nitric oxide) that are triggered by CCl
 <sub>4</sub> [
 <xref rid="B188-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">188</xref>]. In addition, MPEO administration resulted in inhibition of the TGF-β1/SMAD signaling pathway, downregulation of desmin and α-SMA, which are mesenchymal markers, and p53 and upregulation of 
 <italic>CYP2E1</italic> in rats treated with CCl
 <sub>4</sub>. Nakamura et al. reported that piperitenone oxide, a component of the 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane fraction of the spearmint extract, induced duct formation in RCM-1 human colon cancer cells, a process that is a considered a differentiation marker, i.e., with potential anticarcinogenic activity [
 <xref rid="B189-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">189</xref>]. In vitro anticancer potential of methanolic and aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>Mentha arvensis</italic>, 
 <italic>M. longifolia</italic>, 
 <italic>M. spicata</italic> and 
 <italic>M. viridis</italic> at concentration of 100 µg/mL was evaluated against eight human cancer cell lines—A-549, COLO-205, HCT-116, MCF-7, NCI-H322, PC-3, THP-1 and U-87MG from six different origins (breast, colon, glioblastoma, lung, leukemia and prostate) using sulphorhodamine blue (SRB) assay. Methanolic extracts of 
 <italic>Mentha</italic> spp. displayed anti-proliferative effect in the range of 70–97% against four human cancer cell lines, namely COLO-205, MCF-7, NCI-H322 and THP-1; however, aqueous extracts were found to be active against HCT-116 and PC-3. However, essential oil from 
 <italic>M. pulegium</italic> was found to be a cytotoxic agent against human ovary adenocarcinoma SK-OV-3, human malignant cervical adenocarcinoma HeLa and human lung carcinoma A-549 cell lines [
 <xref rid="B157-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>].
</p>
