<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Preclinical studies: The extract of 
 <italic>B. monniera</italic> has been reported to contain several beneficial bioactive components such as alkaloids, flavonoids, glycoside, triterpenoids saponins and alcohols. The alcoholic extract of 
 <italic>B. monniera</italic> improved acquisition, consolidation and retention of memory in the foot shock motivated brightness discrimination test, active conditioned avoidance test and Sidman continuous avoidance responses in rats [
 <xref rid="B73-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Bacosides A and B (a mixture of 2 saponins) may be responsible for its facilitatory effect on learning and memory. Besides, bacosides has been proven for its antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects [
 <xref rid="B75-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] bacosides also attenuated the retrograde amnesia produced by immobilization induced stress, electroconvulsive shock and scopolamine [
 <xref rid="B76-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. They enhanced protein kinase activity and increased the protein content in the hippocampus, which may also contribute to their memory enhancing effect [
 <xref rid="B74-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Administration of bacosides (200 mg/kg) for 3 months in middle-aged and aged rats exerted a protective effect against age associated alterations in the neurotransmission system, behavioral paradigms, hippocampal neuronal loss and oxidative stress markers [
 <xref rid="B79-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. The involvement of the microRNA 124-CREB pathway and serotonergic receptor in the memory enhancing mechanism of standardized extract of 
 <italic>B. monniera</italic> (BESEB CDRI-08) has also been reported [
 <xref rid="B80-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>].
</p>
