<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are also several studies in which different EOs have been investigated and compared for their antioxidant activity (
 <xref rid="molecules-25-04711-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). In 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-04711-f001">Figure 1</xref>, the chemical structures of some of the main constituents of EOs mentioned in 
 <xref rid="molecules-25-04711-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> are shown. In the study of Purkait et al. [
 <xref rid="B169-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>], the antioxidant activities of EOs from 
 <italic>Piper nigrum</italic> (black pepper), 
 <italic>Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic> (cinnamon), and 
 <italic>Syzygium aromaticum</italic> (clove) were compared, which also show high antimicrobial activity. DPPH, β-carotene-linoleic acid bleaching, and Fe
 <sup>2+</sup> ion chelating methods were carried out to evaluate their antioxidant activities, and the highest activity was observed in 
 <italic>Syzgium aromaticum</italic> EO. Moreover, eugenol (72.46%), cinnamaldehyde (63.82%), and β-caryophyllene (43.47%), which are the main constituents with remarkable amounts in clove, cinnamon, and black pepper EO, respectively were associated with their antioxidant activities. Teixeira et al. [
 <xref rid="B170-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>] examined the antioxidant activity of seventeen different EOs by DPPH and FRAP methods. According to the results of DPPH analysis, only seven of them (
 <italic>Apium graveolens</italic> (celery seed), 
 <italic>Cymbopogon nardus</italic> (citronella), 
 <italic>Eugenia</italic> spp. (clove), 
 <italic>Thymus capitatus</italic> (origanum), 
 <italic>Petroselinum sativum</italic> (parsley), 
 <italic>Petroselinum sativum</italic> (tarragon), and 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> (thyme) EOs) showed observable activity in the range of EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.04–10.04 mg/mL. Among these, 
 <italic>Eugenia</italic> spp. (clove) and 
 <italic>Thymus capitatus</italic> (origanum) EOs showed 50% inhibition at a lower concentration, which indicated their high antioxidant effect. On the other hand, Stanojevic et al. [
 <xref rid="B171-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>] reported the antioxidant activity of 
 <italic>Aetheroleum basilici</italic> (basil) to be higher than 
 <italic>Aetheroleum menthae piperitae</italic> (peppermint) according to the DPPH assay. In another study, 
 <italic>Mentha viridis</italic> EO was subjected to DPPH, ABTS, and FRAP assays in order to evaluate its antioxidant activity, and the researchers demonstrated the significant biological activities of 
 <italic>Mentha viridis</italic> EO, including antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B172-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>].
</p>
