<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this review, we focus on some natural salicylates, amorfrutin, ginkgolic acid, grifolic acid, tetrahydrocannabinolic acid, and cannabidiolic acid and discuss their multitarget inhibitory activities and pharmacological role in human disease (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-09049-f001">Figure 1</xref>). Amorfrutins are natural salicylates isolated from 
 <italic>Amorpha fruticosa</italic> [
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] and 
 <italic>Glycyrrhiza foetida</italic> [
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Different types of amorfrutins (A-D) are identified [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. These amorfrutins are involved in many biological activities thus increasing the interest on it. The phenolic compound ginkgolic acids are found in leaves and fruits of 
 <italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic> [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. These are chemically 2-hydroxy-6-alkylbenzoic acids. Different ginkgolic acids structure such as C13:0, C15:1, and C17:1 have been designated according to their alkyl chain carbon number [
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Recent studies suggest that ginkgolic acids have an anticancer property and some other pharmacological role so this compound may be a good target for drug development in human disease. The natural salicylate grifolic acid is isolated from the fruiting bodies of 
 <italic>Albatrellus confluens</italic> fungus and this compound is a derivative of grifolin [
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Grifolin shows anticancer activity in different types of cancer by inducing apoptosis and arrest of cell growth [
 <xref rid="B31-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Some research suggests that grifolic acid also has anticancer activity [
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. 
 <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> L. is a medicinal plant that is rich in cannabinoids [
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Δ
 <sup>9</sup>-tetrahydrocannabinolic acid (Δ
 <sup>9</sup>-THCA) and cannabidiolic acid (CBDA) are the most abundant cannabinoids in 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic> L. and these are the acidic form of Δ
 <sup>9</sup>-THC and CBD respectively [
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-21-09049" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Besides the popular cannabinoids (THC and CBD), recently the other cannabinoids like Δ
 <sup>9</sup>-THCA and CBDA are gaining attention and interest from researchers due to their biological activities.
</p>
