<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Currently used anti-inflammatory drugs, such as non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), may cause serious side effects. Therefore, numerous researchers have focused on the development of anti-inflammatory drugs from plant sources that are considered to be safe, effective, biocompatible and cost-effective alternatives (
 <xref rid="b2-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Berries are fruits rich in nutritive compounds, such as minerals, vitamins and dietary fiber. They also contain polyphenolic compounds that have strong anti-inflammatory properties (
 <xref rid="b5-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Honeyberry (
 <italic>Lonicera caerulea</italic>) has long been used as a traditional medicine in China, Japan and northern Russia (
 <xref rid="b6-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Honeyberry fruits have been reported to have strong antioxidant effects due to their ascorbic acid content and the presence of phenolic compounds, including anthocyanins, flavonoids and low-molecular-weight phenolic acids (
 <xref rid="b7-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). In addition, a study found that honeyberry fruits had the strongest antioxidant property among 12 types of colored berries from northern China (
 <xref rid="b8-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). A number of studies have shown the various effects of honeyberry fruits, which include anti-inflammatory (
 <xref rid="b9-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="b10-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), hepatoprotective (
 <xref rid="b11-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), lipid and glucose metabolism-enhancing (
 <xref rid="b12-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), anti-hyperthyroidism (
 <xref rid="b13-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), anti-obesity (
 <xref rid="b14-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) and anticancer effects (
 <xref rid="b15-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="b16-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). These fruits contain a variety of polyphenolic compounds, including protocatechuic acid, caffeic acid, chlorogenic acid, coumaric acid and ferulic acid, which have a close association with anti-inflammatory effects (
 <xref rid="b17-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="b18-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). In addition, the anti-inflammatory activity of honeyberry cultivars has been shown to depend on the levels of polyphenolic compounds they contain (
 <xref rid="b19-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Much research has been carried out into the pharmacological activity of honeyberry; however, these studies have mainly focused on honeyberry fruits, and reports of the pharmacological activities of its leaves and branches are limited. The leaves and branches of plants are important for the development of natural medicines due to the presence of high levels of functional substances with various biological activities; therefore, pharmacological studies on the leaves and branches of honeyberry are recommended. Notably, the leaves of chokeberry and mulberry have higher contents of functional substances and higher levels of antioxidant activity than the fruits (
 <xref rid="b20-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="b21-mmr-22-06-5219" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Thus, in the present study, the anti-inflammatory activity of honeyberry leaves and branches was evaluated, and their mechanisms of action were investigated.
</p>
