<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Tundis et al. (2014) reviewed all of the available data on the biologically active substances in 
 <italic class="italic">Stachys</italic> taxa, and found the following diterpenes to be present in the taxa that are included in this review: annuanone, stachylone, and stachone (
 <italic class="italic">S. palustris</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">S. sylvatica</italic>); abietal, abietatriene, stachysic acid, scareol, 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-Phytol, 6β-hydroxy-ent-kaur-16-ene, 6b,18-dihydroxy-
 <italic class="italic">ent</italic>-kaur-16-ene, kaur-16-ene,13-epi-manoyl oxide, and betolide (
 <italic class="italic">S. sylvatica</italic>); betonicoside A-D and 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-Phytol (
 <italic class="italic">S. officinalis</italic>); abietatriene, abieta-8, 11, 13-trien-7-one, 13-epi-manoyl oxide, 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-Phytol, and Labd-13-en-8,15-ol and kaur-16-ene (
 <italic class="italic">S.menthifolia</italic>); abietatriene and epi-Laurenene (
 <italic class="italic">S. germanica</italic>); and 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-Phytol, 11α,18-dihydroxy-
 <italic class="italic">ent</italic>-kaur-16-ene, kaur-16-ene, diacetyl derivatives, and monoacetyl derivatives of stachysolone (
 <italic class="italic">S. recta</italic>). Furthermore, in their overview of data on iridoids isolated in 
 <italic class="italic">Stachys</italic> taxa, the following compounds were determined for the taxa presented: 
 <italic class="italic">S. recta</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. alpina</italic> contained harpagide, ajugoside, aucubin, acetylharpagide, and harpagoside; 
 <italic class="italic">S. germanica</italic> contained harpagide, aucubin, acetylharpagide, and harpagoside, 
 <italic class="italic">S. palustris</italic> contained harpagide and aucubin; while 
 <italic class="italic">S. alpina</italic> contained harpagide, ajugoside, aucubin, and harpagoside [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-08-00032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Furthermore, recent research studies of the active substances in 
 <italic class="italic">S. palustis</italic> identified not only iridoids harpagide and 8-O-acetyl-harpagide, but also monomelittoside, which was the first identification of this compound in 
 <italic class="italic">S. palustris</italic> species [
 <xref rid="B36-plants-08-00032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>].
</p>
