<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Human AML cell lines KG1, HL60, and K562 were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich. All cell lines were grown in complete culture medium containing 90% RMPI-1640 culture medium supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum, 2 mM 
 <sc>l</sc>-glutamine, and 50 U of antibiotic (penicillin and streptomycin). Cells lines were incubated at 37 °C with 100% humidity and 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub>. The cells were permanently maintained in the exponential phase of cell growth; cells were plated at an adequate density and checked every 2 days. Blood samples are collected from voluntary donors. Volunteer informed consent was approved by the Ethical Committee of Institut Jules Bordet. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) were purified by Ficoll gradient separation using Histopaque-1077 from Sigma. In brief, blood samples were collected in sterile tubes containing ACDA; then, samples were diluted in HBSS containing 10% ACDA. Two parts sample were carefully added to one-part Ficoll, and cell separation was performed by centrifugation at 2000× 
 <italic>g</italic> for 20 min. After the centrifugation steps, mononuclear cells were identified as the opaque cellular layer, while erythrocytes and granulocytes were pelleted to the bottom. Then, the cellular layer of PBMCs was carefully transferred to new sterile tubes. Finally, PBMCs were washed twice with PBS-EDTA containing 2% SSPP (stable pasteurized solution of plasma proteins), and the cell pellets were resuspended in complete culture medium. Cell viability for the isolated peripheral blood mononuclear cell (PBMC) was assessed using trypan blue dye exclusion and was always &gt;95%. Essential oil, thymol, and carvacrol were dissolved in ethanol or DMSO to obtain a stock solution of 0.1% for EO, 1 mM for thymol, and 10 mM for carvacrol. The final DMSO concentration for cell treatments was &lt; 0.1%. Unless otherwise mentioned, cells were seeded (0.8 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> cells/mL) and treated at 50% confluency with EO, thymol, and carvacrol at the desired concentration for 24 or 48 h. For most studies, AML cells and PBMCs were treated with different concentrations of carvacrol (100, 200, 300, and 400 µM) and thymol (25, 50, 75, and 100 µM).
</p>
