<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Due to the fact that eucalypts are of great economic importance and occupy very large areas, field experiments with eucalypts are carried out more often than with other allelopathic trees. In allelopathic studies, the main object of study is leaves or litter. Meanwhile, it is widely known that the continuous planting of eucalypts in monoculture can cause the accumulation of phytotoxins in soil, which leads to its degradation and loss of productivity [
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. The allelopathic effect of leaf litter and living roots of 
 <italic class="italic">E. urophylla</italic> on seed germination and seedling survivorship of three common native tree species—
 <italic class="italic">Delonix regia</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Tsoongiodendron odorum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Elaeocarpus sylvestris</italic>—were studied in [
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. These field experiments showed that the presence of the 
 <italic class="italic">E. urophylla</italic> roots significantly inhibited the growth of seedlings of all three species, unlike the litter which did not affect them. Later, this experiment was extended to 12 native broad-leaved tree species. All of them were endemic for South China and had high economic value. The experiment lasted for more than two years [
 <xref rid="B59-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. The results showed that poor establishment of native trees in the 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus</italic> plantations were mainly due to the 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus</italic> roots rather than its litter. On the opposite, the litter stimulated the germination and growth of seedlings of the most tested species. However, an experiment with crops gave another result. Zhang et al. [
 <xref rid="B60-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>] evaluated the effect of three eucalypt species (
 <italic class="italic">E. urophylla</italic> Blake, 
 <italic class="italic">E. citriodora</italic> Hook., and 
 <italic class="italic">E. camaldulensis</italic> Dehnh) on 
 <italic class="italic">Raphanus raphanistrum</italic> var. 
 <italic class="italic">sativus</italic> L. G. Beck, 
 <italic class="italic">Cucumis sativus</italic> L., and 
 <italic class="italic">Brassica rapa</italic> var. 
 <italic class="italic">glabra</italic> Regel, but instead of living roots, live root exudates were used. It was found that the allelopathic effects of the leaf litter extracts were stronger than the root exudates. According to the results, it was concluded that radish is unsuitable for cultivation with these species of eucalypts, while cucumber and Chinese cabbage can be cultivated provided that the leaf litter is removed. Although, Chinese cabbage could be grown only with 
 <italic class="italic">E. urophylla</italic>. The effect of leaf litter of 
 <italic class="italic">E. camaldulensis</italic> depended on the species [
 <xref rid="B61-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>], when a leaf litter was added to the soil in doses of 100 to 2000 kg/ha with an average accumulation of 1028 kg/ha/year litterfall in a plantation. The litter had no effect on growth of crops 
 <italic class="italic">Vigna unguiculata, Cicer arietinum</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Cajanus cajan</italic>, but significantly reduced it in woody plants 
 <italic class="italic">Leucaena leucochephala</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Albizia procera</italic>. The litter inhibited root growth to a greater extent than shoot growth. There was an inhibitory effect on nodulation of 
 <italic class="italic">Vigna unguiculata</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Albizia procera</italic>. This study confirmed the allelopathic effects of 
 <italic class="italic">E. camaldulensis</italic> in field conditions, where the influence of numerous biotic and abiotic factors have been taken into account along with a careful selection of crops for agroforestry systems [
 <xref rid="B61-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>]. The results of this experiment are somewhat different from the studies in the greenhouse, where it showed that for mixed plantations with 
 <italic class="italic">E. camaldulensis</italic> presence it is better to use 
 <italic class="italic">Leucaena leucochephala</italic> than 
 <italic class="italic">Albizia procera</italic> [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>].
</p>
