<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Field tests with four common broad-leaved tree species, three native subtropical evergreen forest species 
 <italic class="italic">Acmena acuminatissima, Pterospermum lanceaefolium</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Cryptocarya concinna</italic>, and one introduced nitrogen-fixing species 
 <italic class="italic">Albizia lebbeck</italic>, showed significant differences between plantations of 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus urophylla</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Pinus elliottii</italic> [
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. The root growth of the three forest species sown in the soil where the eucalypt plantation was located was significantly reduced in comparison to the pine plantation, but no difference was found for 
 <italic class="italic">Albizia lebbeck</italic>. The authors believed that these differences were not necessarily related to the status of plants (native or introduced), but most likely with responses of N-fixing and non N-fixing trees to allelopathy [
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. The experimental results suggested that the N-fixing trees can be used in the mixed with eucalypt plantations. However, these results were not consistent with another extensive study, where in order to evaluate allelopathy in the field conditions, 
 <italic class="italic">E. urophylla</italic> was planted among the seedlings of 20 broad-leaved woody species, and their survival and growth rate were evaluated during the 10-year period [
 <xref rid="B64-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. Based on the results of this experiment 20 species could be divided into two types: inhibited and stimulated/unaffected by aqueous extracts of 
 <italic class="italic">E. urophylla</italic>. Compared to the inhibited species, the uninhibited species grew faster and survived better. In this study, the three N-fixing species did not show better survival and growth than non-N-fixing species, while 
 <italic class="italic">A. lebbeck</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">L. leucocephala</italic> demonstrated the lowest survival rate and growth rate. This study allowed to select woody species that are good candidates for the mixed with 
 <italic class="italic">E. urophylla</italic> plantations [
 <xref rid="B64-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. In addition, this 10-year field experiment led to the conclusion that the reduction in plant biodiversity in 
 <italic class="italic">E. urophylla</italic> plantations was more associated with allelopathy than with competition for resources.
</p>
