<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The results of investigation of the anticancer properties of the 
 <italic>Allium ursinum</italic> extracts are in accordance with data of 
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al. (2013)</xref> who demonstrated that watery extracts of 
 <italic>A. ursinum</italic> caused apoptosis through activation of caspase-3, caspase-8 and caspase-9, and G2/M arrest in human gastric adenocarcinoma AGS cells. Our study is the first to report the influence of 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> gastrointestinal digestion on the cytotoxic activity of extracts obtained from 
 <italic>A. ursinum</italic> against human malignant cell lines. The extracts prepared from medicinal plant 
 <italic>A. ursinum</italic> were reported to exert various pharmacological activities, such as antioxidant, antihypertensive, antidiabetic, antimicrobial, antifungal and anti-inflammatory activities in addition to anticancer activity (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Trio et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Sobolewska et al., 2015</xref>, and references cited therein). Use in European traditional medicine and diverse biological activities exhibited by 
 <italic>A. ursinum</italic> may be attributed to various sulfur-containing compounds, including thiosulfinates which are the most abundant chemical constituents of 
 <italic>A. ursinum</italic> and phenolic compounds (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Sobolewska et al., 2015</xref>). Only seven sulfur compounds, which represent the degradation products of thiosulfinates, were detected by 2D gas chromatography analysis in the examined extracts. The allyl sulfur compounds, including diallyl disulfide identified in the tested extracts, have been shown to inhibit proliferation of malignant cells by inducing accumulation within G2/M phase as well as to induce apoptosis (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Knowles and Milner, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Herman-Antosiewicz and Singh, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Yi and Su, 2013</xref>). In addition, it was demonstrated that diallyl disulfide triggered apoptosis in cancer cells through activation of caspase-3 and mitochondrial signaling pathway (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Nagaraj et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Yi and Su, 2013</xref>).
</p>
