<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We developed a linear, deterministic stage‐structured matrix population model: 
 <bold>n</bold>
 <sub>t +1</sub> = 
 <bold>An</bold>
 <sub>t</sub>, where 
 <bold>n</bold>
 <sub>t</sub> is a vector that quantifies number of individuals in each stage class at time t, and 
 <bold>A</bold> is a transition matrix (Caswell, 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). We constructed annual transition matrices 
 <bold>A</bold> based on three life stages (Fig 
 <xref rid="ele13649-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>: seed (s), rosette (r) and adults (p) (Davis 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Kalisz 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). We estimated parameter values for matrix 
 <math id="nlm-math-1">
  <mi mathvariant="bold-italic">A</mi>
 </math> from permanent marked quadrats at each site. We estimated seedling survival (s
 <sub>g</sub>) and rosette survival (s
 <sub>r</sub>) by counting or estimating number of emergent seedlings per quadrat in June and number of surviving rosettes in September. We then counted number of surviving adults the following summer. We counted number of siliques produced per stem in each quadrat and estimated seed production based on average number of seeds per silique (12 seeds/silique, Nuzzo unpublished data). The monitoring protocol did not include measures of seed survival (s
 <sub>s</sub>) or seed germination (g
 <sub>1</sub> and g
 <sub>2</sub>), therefore we obtained estimates from an experimental seed basket study (Kalisz 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) and applied those estimates to all sites and years. We averaged data across all quadrats per site to populate one matrix per year and site; therefore, sites were treated as replicates. We eliminated two sites (Fermi and Hall Woods) because of incomplete time series.
</p>
