<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another remarkable step forward for the discovery of new MTDLs took into account the possibility of creating structures that could merge the ChE inhibitory activity with the calcium channel blockade ability, thus limiting the entrance of Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> through voltage-gated channels (VGC) and preventing neuronal damage [
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. To this aim, a series of tacripyrimidines have been proposed (
 <bold>28</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>], whose structures arise from the hybridization of THA with 3,4-dihydropyrimidin-2(1H)-thiones, known to be efficient calcium channel blockers. The 3-Br substituted analogue resulted as the most potent and selective 
 <italic>h</italic>AChE inhibitor with IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.037 
 <italic>μ</italic>M, although the 3-methoxyphenyl derivative also showed good 
 <italic>μ</italic>M activity. The selectivity over BuChE was generally high, with the 4-(halo)-substituted compounds being slightly more potent against this enzyme. The 4-Cl derivative showed a reverted trend and was more potent on BuChE, while the 3-OMe-substituted compound was equipotent on the two enzymes. Further analysis revealed a noncompetitive type of inhibition, and molecular docking studies helped establish the key interactions of these compounds in the enzyme's CAS and PAS, pointing out the halogens as important substitutions for the activity and selectivity over the ChEs. The Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>-channel blockade was investigated in SH-SY5Y cells by measuring the Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> influx induced by K
 <sup>+</sup> depolarization. All the tacripyrimidines inhibited Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> influx, with the most promising and potent inhibitors of AChE showing blockade activity similar to the reference Nomodipine. The compounds were relatively safe on HepG2 cells up to 100 
 <italic>μ</italic>M, even if some derivatives showed higher hepatotoxicity than THA at higher concentrations. There was no significant effect on self-induced A
 <italic>β</italic> aggregation, as expected, but predicted ADMET properties showed a favorable potential for this candidate to be evaluated 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. The best performing tacripyrimidine of the series had a balanced activity over the selected targets and good ADME properties coupled with a lower toxicity than THA, thus making it an attractive structure deserving further investigation and development as an MTDL in AD.
</p>
