<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Quercetin is a naturally occurring flavonoid found in onions, shallots, broccoli, peppers, caper fruits, apples, berries, grapes, herbs, tea, and wine (
 <xref rid="ijms-22-04180-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B56-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Quercetin has been shown to have anti-inflammatory and antidiabetic activity. Quercetin has been reported to generate anticancer effect by inhibiting tyrosine kinase enzyme in vivo. It produces antidiabetic effect in patients with type 2 diabetes by ROS scavenging, thus, improving the antioxidant status in type 2 diabetic patients. Quercetin is used to treat chronic oral inflammation (oral lichen planus because it can restrict cytokines such as IL12, IL8, INFγ, INFα, cyclooxygenase 2 (COX-2), and prostaglandin E (PGE) [
 <xref rid="B53-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. A recent mass spectrometry (MS) study has identified the activating effect of SIRT6 at a high concentration of quercetin [
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Quercetin has also been shown to increase the activity of SIRT6 at high concentrations in another study conducted by high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC)-employed SIRT6 assay [
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Quercetin was reported to activate SIRT6 in the deacetylating genes H3K18ac and H3K9ac in nucleosome and on free full-length histone, respectively [
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. The H3K18ac gene is a potential target for anticancer therapy since this gene is a marker of cancer progression [
 <xref rid="B59-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Recently, to discover the mechanism of SIRT6 activity modulation, analysis of binding and activity efforts of quercetin-based compounds on SIRT6 and other sirtuin isoforms were studied by You et al. They found that quercetin activates SIRT6 induced deacetylation by binding to the SIRT6-selective acyl binding channel [
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Furthermore, the mechanism of quercetin-induced modulation of SIRT6 can be explained by its binding with of a large Rossmann fold domain and a small zinc-binding domain [
 <xref rid="B60-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. It was also reported that the specific small Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> binding domain and cofactor binding loop provide SIRT6′s substrate acyl binding channel [
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Ravichandran et al. studied the pharmacophore model of the binding site of SIRT6 protein for quercetin and their study generated a preliminary pharmacophore of the quercetin binding site on the SIRT6 protein that contained three hydrogen bond donors and one hydrogen bond acceptor [
 <xref rid="B61-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].
</p>
