<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>These studies suggest (
 <xref rid="insects-11-00738-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) that the sensitivity of molluscs differs and depends on plant and mollusc species, individual age, and environmental conditions. For example, one of the most effective plants extracts for the control of freshwater snails 
 <italic>Oncomelania hupensis</italic> is an aqueous extract from 
 <italic>Camelia sasanqua</italic>. Meanwhile, for land molluscs, a more effective methanol extract comes from 
 <italic>Cestrum parqui</italic> [
 <xref rid="B31-insects-11-00738" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-insects-11-00738" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Moreover, it seems that freshwater snails are more sensitive to the toxicity of saponins than land snails (
 <xref rid="insects-11-00738-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The LC
 <sub>50</sub> of saponin extracts on freshwater snails was less than on land snails and ranged from 0.001 g/L (aqueous extract) on 
 <italic>O. hupensis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B33-insects-11-00738" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] to ≈0.02 g/L (methanol extract) on 
 <italic>Pomacea canaliculata</italic> [
 <xref rid="B30-insects-11-00738" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. For land snails, it ranged from 0.04 g/L (methanol extract) on 
 <italic>T. pisana</italic> [
 <xref rid="B31-insects-11-00738" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] to 96.94 g/L (aqueous extract) on 
 <italic>A. vulgaris</italic> (our data). This can easily be explained by absorption through the mouth and the whole body surface; the water snail is dipped in water, while the terrestrial snail or slug absorbs through the sole or mouth. On the other hand, different herbal extracts were used. In the first case, extracts from 
 <italic>C. sasanqua</italic> and 
 <italic>S. mucorossi</italic> were tested, and in the second case, the extracts were from 
 <italic>C. parqui</italic> and 
 <italic>Q. saponaria</italic>. Methanol extracts of saponins have stronger molluscicidal effects. Moreover, it is possible that LC
 <sub>50</sub> may vary according to the different observation time (
 <xref rid="insects-11-00738-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).
</p>
