<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The soil-dwelling enchytraeid, 
 <italic>E. albidus</italic>, is a basic component of the soil ecosystem and more sensitive to compounds with amphiphilic characteristics (e.g., soaps, such as saponins) than other soil organisms, such as Collembola or predaceous mites [
 <xref rid="B43-insects-11-00738" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Hence, enchytraeids are often used in eco-toxicological tests as sentinel species [
 <xref rid="B21-insects-11-00738" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-insects-11-00738" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. In this research experimental conditions for slugs and enchytraeids were not equal. There was a large difference between the average body volumes of the examined species, therefore enchytraeids got relatively bigger doses of saponins. In addition, whereas the slugs were exposed to saponins by lower body contact, the worms had it mixed to the soil where they were grown, likely affording a larger surface area of contact (and possibly uptake) with the saponins compared to the slug exposure method. It is also possible that the worm food supply could have been affected by the saponin, leading to an additional intake path besides body contact. Moreover, exposure time of slugs to saponins was two days, whereas that of worms was two weeks. The chosen methods were based on the possible usage of molluscicide: a solution of QE could be sprayed in areas with slugs which would come in contact with saponins through ground and plant surfaces. The solution could get deeper into the ground and affect soil animals (for example, worms). The LC
 <sub>50</sub> at 15 °C on slugs was 68.5 g/L (adults) and 96.9 g/L (juveniles). The LC
 <sub>50</sub> (at 6 ℃) on 
 <italic>E. albidus</italic> was 2.72 g/L, far below those on 
 <italic>A. vulgaris</italic>. Bearing in mind that the median effective doses for sub-lethal parameters (e.g., growth and reproduction) may well be one order of magnitude lower [
 <xref rid="B43-insects-11-00738" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], it is evident that controlling slugs using saponins is likely to adversely affect enchytraeids, lumbricids, and possibly other soft-bodied invertebrates in treated sites.
</p>
