<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0018">The herbalists in Morocco are male and female, and older than 20 years of age. The training to become an herbalist is usually either through an inherited traditional knowledge from parents, or acquired through formal training. Among the herbalists, some followed old popular lifestyle, while others, notably the young, were more associated with a modern western lifestyle. These herbalists fall under a legal framework called the "Union of Moroccan Herbalists (UMH)". Unfortunately, there are no official statistics on their total number. From a legislative point of view, the profession of herbalists in Morocco is regulated by three legal chapters all dated before 1960:
 <list list-type="simple" id="celist0001">
  <list-item id="celistitem0001">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="para0019">
    <bold>The Dahir of February 27, 1923 (corresponding to Rajab 11, 1341 AH),</bold> subjecting the practice of herbalist to the provisions of the Dahir of April 12, 1916, whose second article is: "it is especially forbidden for herbalists to sell any poisonous or toxic plants" 
    <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="celistitem0002">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="para0020">
    <bold>The Dahir of August 20, 1926 (corresponding to Safar 11, 1345 AH),</bold> where “any person who has the herbalist certificate and authorized under the conditions provided for in the article, may hold and sell all plants or parts of medicinal plants, fresh or dried, mixed or not, except poisonous plants listed in Codex” 
    <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="celistitem0003">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="para0021">
    <bold>The Dahir of February 19, 1960 (corresponding to Chaabane 22, 1379 AH),</bold> with article 17: "Anyone with the herbalist certificate and authorized under the conditions of Article 2 will be able to hold and sell all plants or parts of medicinal plants, fresh or dry, except plants classified in the various tables of poisonous substances provided by the Dahir of December 2, 1922 
    <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
