<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 5.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Sequential ruptures of TRF1–telomere complexes using strand-separation assays. (
   <bold>A</bold>) Telomeric hairpin construct with 23 repeats of TTAGGG. The telomeric hairpin construct contains a stem of 169 bp and two flanking handles (&gt;700 bp) with either biotin or digoxigenin modifications (bottom). The G-rich strand sequence of the hairpin stem has 23 repeats of TTAGGG (red) with two spacers of non-telomeric DNA sequences (Black) and flanking sequences (gray) at both ends (top). (
   <bold>B</bold>) Individual strand-separation assays. Manipulation of forces at 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>low</sub> = 6 pN, 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>test</sub> = 17 pN and 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>high</sub> = 22 pN determines the double strands of a telomeric hairpin stem to be either paired together or separated (left, cartoon). At the presence of TRF1 of 25 nM, bound proteins can interrupt the strand separation at 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>test</sub> (right, cartoon). Pauses of extension reveal sequential rupture events with measurable dwell time (magenta). Buffer and temperature conditions are the same as those in Figure 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>. Sampling rate = 100 Hz. (
   <bold>C</bold>) Repetitive strand-separation assays. Incubation time at 
   <italic>F</italic>
   <sub>low</sub> is 60 s between two subsequent assays. (
   <bold>D</bold>) Site-specific time distribution of TRF1 dissociation based on a single trace of strand-separation assays. The red dashed line indicates the position where the hairpin is fully opened (cartoon). Bin size = 1 bp. (
   <bold>E</bold>) The averaged time distribution of TRF1 dissociation upon strand separation. The red dashed line indicates the position where the hairpins are fully open. Inset shows that two major valleys are distinguishable, as indicated by black dashed lines (mean ± SE, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 173 from 10 molecules). The black dashed lines are corresponding to the positions of two non-telomeric sequences of the hairpin stem.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="gkaa1222fig5" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
