<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The safety of 
 <bold>1,8‐cineole</bold> has been previously assessed (EFSA FEEDAP Panel, 
 <xref rid="efs26548-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2012b</xref>). Meanwhile new toxicological data have been published which are reviewed below. In a 50‐day repeated‐dose toxicity and reproductive study, 1,8‐cineole was administered to Wistar rats by gavage at doses of 100, 500 or 1,000 mg 1,8‐cineole/kg bw per day (Caldas et al., 
 <xref rid="efs26548-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Examination included daily observation; weekly body weight, food and water intakes; and haematology,
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="efs26548-note-1033">31</xref> clinical chemistry,
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="efs26548-note-1034">32</xref> organ weights and gross and microscopic pathology at the end of the study. Results showed an effect on body weight at the highest two doses (mainly a result of an initial reduced growth and a failure to restore that) accompanied by some effects on food and water intake. Differences were seen in haematological parameters in male rats, i.e. higher mean corpuscular volume (at 1,000 mg/kg bw per day), higher platelet count (at 500 and 1,000 mg/kg bw per day), lower mean corpuscular haemoglobin concentration (at 500 and 1,000 mg/kg per day) and lower mean platelet volume at all doses as compared to controls. None of these differences showed significant dose‐related trends. Similar differences were not seen in females. No consistent differences were seen in serum chemistry. Treatment‐related changes in organ weights were a decrease in the absolute weight of the spleen and lungs in males at doses of 500 and 1,000 mg/kg bw, and an increase in the absolute and relative weight of the liver in females at 1,000 mg/kg bw. Histopathological examination showed eosinophilic and/or lymphocytic infiltrates in the lungs and liver of males and females and in the uterus of female rats at all doses; however, these infiltrations were minimal and were not considered treatment‐related. Overall, based on the effects on body weight observed at 500 and 1,000 mg/kg bw per day, the FEEDAP Panel identifies the lowest dose tested at 100 mg/kg bw per day as the no observed adverse effect level (NOAEL).
</p>
