<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While the implications of lipid metabolism in the regulation of plant height remain unclarified, a few genes involved in lipid transport [
 <xref rid="B20-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and hydrolysis [
 <xref rid="B21-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] have been shown to influence this phenotype. Glycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase (GPAT) is an important enzyme in lipid biosynthesis that transfers an acyl group to the sn-1 or sn-2 position of sn-glycerol-3-phosphate (Gro3P) to produce lysophosphatidic acid (lysoPtdOH). This is necessary for the production of intracellular lipids such as membrane lipids and storage triacylglycerol (TAG), as well as extracellular lipids such as suberin-associated waxes, cutin, and suberin [
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The multifaceted functions of GPAT were revealed through a series of biochemical and mutational analyses. Ten GPATs have been reported in Arabidopsis thaliana, which are categorized into sn-1-GPAT (ATS1 and GPAT9) and sn-2-GPAT (GPAT1-8) [
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The plastidial ATS1 and endoplasmic reticulum (ER)-localized GPAT9 contribute to the biosynthesis of glycerolipids but not extracellular lipids [
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. For the mitochondria-localized GPATs, GPAT1 is involved in glycerolipid biosynthesis, which is essential for tapetum differentiation and male fertility, while the functions of GPAT2 and GPAT3 are still unknown [
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. ER-bound GPAT4, 6, and 8, which have both sn-2 acyltransferase and phosphatase activities, are required for cutin biosynthesis [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. GPAT4 and GPAT8 are functionally redundant and contribute to proper lateral root outgrowth [
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], as well as prevent water loss and pathogen infection [
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. GPAT6 plays multiple roles in stamen development and fertility [
 <xref rid="B36-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and promotes salt tolerance [
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. ER-bound suberin-associated GPAT5 and GPAT7 only possess sn-2 acyltransferase activity [
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. 
 <italic>GPAT5</italic> plays a role in the production of suberin and suberin-associated root waxes, which contribute to the tolerance of plants to salt stress [
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Lastly, 
 <italic>GPAT7</italic> may only contribute to suberin biosynthesis under stress, such as wounding [
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-22-00785" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Studies on plant GPATs have revealed that they are required for the synthesis of intracellular and extracellular lipids and have important physiological functions, yet their roles in hormone metabolism and hormone-mediated plant development are still unknown.
</p>
