<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite increasing efforts to develop novel drugs effective against HCV, patients are mainly being treated with a virus-unspecific combination therapy of pegylated interferon alpha (PEG-IFN) and ribavirin
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref>. This treatment is expensive and can be associated with severe side effects; in addition, it is effective in only 50–60% of patients infected with HCV genotype 1
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref>. Since early 2011, two direct acting antivirals (DAAs) targeting the viral NS3 protease have been approved by the United States Food and Drug Administration. Unfortunately, both drugs induce severe side effects and have a low resistance barrier as well as an inconvenient administration regime
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref>. Viral resistance may eventually become an issue; due to potential HCV genotype specificity, it is unclear whether all seven HCV genotypes and their subtypes are covered
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>. Therefore, it is a primary goal to identify targets with a significantly higher genetic barrier of resistance that cover all HCV genotypes. Other challenges include appearance of escape mutants, high costs of current therapy regimens, and negative side effects. The mechanisms of resistance to interferon (IFN)-based therapy through immune system interception
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> and also to DAAs like telaprevir and boceprevir through resistance-conferring mutations could be avoided by combinatorial treatment. Although drugs that target the virus are currently in clinical trials, a medical need remains for new HCV therapeutic agents. There is a particular need for HCV therapeutic agents that have broad activity against the majority of HCV genotypes and their subtypes (e.g. 1a/b, 2a/b 3a/b, 4a/b, etc.).
</p>
