<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Natural products are considered powerful inhibitors of microbial activity when the MIC is equal to or lower than 500 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>g/mL [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. Consistently, the results of the present study show that
 <italic class="italic"> C. zeylanicum</italic> Blume EO had powerful antifungal activity on all the tested strains. The only exception was
 <italic class="italic"> C. krusei </italic>ATCC 3413, for which the effect might be rated as moderate, which is also the case with the available antifungals [
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. The MFC/MIC ratio suggests that the tested EO had a fungicidal effect [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] on both the reference (ATCC and CBS) and clinical strains. Reports in the literature corroborate the effect of
 <italic class="italic"> C. zeylanicum</italic> EO on
 <italic class="italic"> Candida</italic> spp. [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>–
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. However, these studies exhibit significant variability as to the
 <italic class="italic"> Cinnamomum</italic> species and plant material used and the methods used to investigate fungal sensitivity, whereas some of them do not indicate from which plant part the EO was extracted. These differences make comparison difficult, as one plant might produce oils with different main components as a function of the plant part used, and different species of the same genus produce EOs with variable chemical composition, resulting in different biological effects [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. In addition, clinical
 <italic class="italic"> Candida</italic> strains that are multiresistant to the drugs that are widely employed in clinical practice demonstrated susceptibility to
 <italic class="italic"> C. zeylanicum </italic>in other studies [
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>].
</p>
