<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chloroplasts, mitochondria, archaea and without Phylum identification ASVs were removed from the ASV table using the phyloseq package [
 <xref rid="B41-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. For the metrics of α-diversity of bulk soil, rhizosphere soil and root endosphere we applied rarefaction to an even sampling depth of 3168 reads to all the samples, except for an endosphere sample from a plot of site H2 which had low number of reads. Richness (observed ASVs) and Shannon Diversity index were calculated using the function “plot_richness” in phyloseq and Faith phylogenetic diversity (PD) using Phylomeasures package. To test whether the ASV richness and diversity differed due to the type of bacterial community, we applied aligned rank transform for non-parametric factorial data with site as random factor using the ARTool package [
 <xref rid="B42-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. We applied this test because the data were not normally distributed and to consider that sample replicates are nested in the site. To test the effect of elevation, we applied the same analysis with the stage of succession and site as random effects. When the fixed effect was significant, a pairwise comparison of means was carried out using contrasts in emmeans package [
 <xref rid="B43-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. To analyze the effects of inundation on the three types of bacterial communities, we separated the endosphere samples from the rhizosphere soil and bulk soil samples. The endosphere samples were rarefied to 3168 sequences, whereas bulk soil and rhizosphere soil samples were rarified to 4520 sequence library depth to increase sequence sampling in more diverse samples. For all β-diversity analyses among different types of samples and elevations, the ASV tables were normalized calculating the relative abundances by dividing the raw abundances by the total number of counts per sample to prior to calculate the Bray–Curtis and UniFrac weighted and unweighted distance matrix using a vegan package [
 <xref rid="B44-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. The pattern of clustering of bacterial communities from bulk soil, rhizosphere soil and root endosphere was visualized in PCoA plots. Type of bacterial community, elevation and stage of succession effect on bacterial community composition was tested on all distance matrices by permutational analysis of variance (PERMANOVA) using the “Adonis” function, and dispersion of variance tests were performed with the function “betadisper” with the R vegan package [
 <xref rid="B44-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].
</p>
