<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="abs0010">
 <sec>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <p>
   <italic>Tragia involucrata</italic> L. have been utilized as traditional medicine in Indian subcontinent for the treatment of numerous illnesses such as inflammation, pain and skin infection. In this current study we sought to assess the anxiolytic, sedative and analgesic activity of 
   <italic>Tragia involucrata</italic> L. leaves extract.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Materials and methods</title>
  <p>We first performed a phytochemical screening test of the leaves extracts following standard phytochemical screening protocols. We next examined the anxiolytic and sedative activity of crude methanol (TIME), ethyl acetate (TIEAE) and n-Hexane (TIHE) extract of 
   <italic>Tragia involucrata</italic> L. leaves using mouse behavioral models such as elevated plus-maze test and pentobarbital-induced sleeping time test, respectively. Likewise, we evaluated the analgesic activity using acetic acid induced writhing test and formalin induced paw licking test. Additionally, we performed a quantitative analysis of heavy metals content of 
   <italic>Tragia involucrata</italic> L. leaves by overnight digestion in concentrated nitric acid (HNO
   <sub>3</sub>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>Phytochemical screening demonstrated that TIME, TIEAE and TIHE contain flavonoids, alkaloids, tannins, phenols, terpenoids and sterols. Administration of these extracts resulted in higher number of open arm entry, lower number of close arm entry and higher time spent in open arm compared to control treatment (p &lt; 0.05). Moreover, these treatments decreased the onset of sleep time and increased the duration of sleep compared to control treated mice (all p &lt; 0.05). Likewise, extracts treated mice exhibited decreased number of writhing as well as lower acute phase and late phase duration compared to control treatment (all p &lt; 0.05). The average level of As and Fe in 
   <italic>Tragia involucrata</italic> L. leaves was 5.16 ± 0.012 ppm and 2.76 ± 0.015 ppm, respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p>Results from this study support that 
   <italic>Tragia involucrata</italic> L. leaves extracts exhibit an anxiolytic, sedative and analgesic activity in mice.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
