<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A large proportion of the total carbon in the World Ocean is in the form of dissolved organic matter (DOM), which is comparable in mass to the carbon in atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (Hansell and Carlson, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1998</xref>). A major source of this material derives from the synthesis and release of exopolymers, or extracellular polymeric substances (EPS), mainly by bacteria and eukaryotic phytoplankton (Verdugo, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1994</xref>; Aluwihare et al., 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1997</xref>). An initial understanding on the secretion of EPS by microorganisms, and their potential stabilizing effects for microbial cells, emerged during the last century with the first report by ZoBell and Allen (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1935</xref>). We now know that most bacteria, and other microorganisms, occur associated with biofilms, either attached to surfaces or as suspended-aggregates in the water column. Exopolymer secretions thus serve important functions in marine environments, where they may be involved in microbial adhesion to solid surfaces and biofilm formation (Thavasi and Banat, 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). They have also been shown to be involved in emulsification of hydrocarbon oils to enhance biodegradation (Gutierrez et al., 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>), mediating the fate and mobility of heavy metals and trace metal nutrients (Bhaskar and Bhosle, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>; Gutierrez et al., 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>), or interacting with dissolved and/or particulate organic matter (Long and Azam, 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2001</xref>). This wide spectrum of functional activity is reflected not merely in the complex chemistry of these biopolymers, but also in the diversity of bacterial and phytoplankton genera found producing them.
</p>
