<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">An important role of exopolymers is in forming marine snow—floating or suspended particles that harbor a community of microorganisms and drive the biological pump. They also play an essential role in marine oil snow (MOS) that forms as a consequence of oil spillage. The article by 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2017.00065" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Sperling et al.</ext-link> reveals a correlation between the concentration of high-molecular-weight organic matter (HMW-OM) and the diversity of particle-associated bacteria during the development of a spring bloom in the southern North Sea, suggesting that the availability of carbohydrates contributes to the multifactorial control of marine bacterioplankton communities. The article by 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2017.00676" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Suja et al.</ext-link> reports, for the first time, the use of Illumina MiSeq sequencing to analyse the bacterial communities associated with MOS. This study was conducted in subarctic waters of the northeast Atlantic, revealing the enrichment of oil-degrading and EPS-producing bacteria on MOS, and providing supporting evidence that MOS particles are “hotspots” of these organisms with potentially profound consequences to the oil biodegradation process in the water column. Since the seafloor is the final endpoint for MOS, the article by 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2016.01384" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Yang et al.</ext-link> reports the distinct occurrence and patterns of oil-associated family- and genus-level bacterial groups over time in surficial sediments in the Gulf of Mexico following MOS sedimentation after the Deepwater Horizon oil spill, and suggest petrocarbon sedimentation and changing biogeochemical niches as factors that shape these bacterial communities in near-surface seafloor sediments.
</p>
