<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The term “handling time” has been defined differently by different studies. For example, one study defined it as “the time lapsed between an attack of the prey by the copepod and its resumption of movement after ingestion,” and found that 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>thermocyclopoides</italic> copepods displayed an average handling time of 83 s for first instar 
 <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic> larvae and 185 s for first instar 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>quinquefasciatus</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. These times are consistent with directly-observed ingestion times reported by another study, which states that a mosquito larva is usually consumed by a cyclopoid copepod within a few minutes [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, the original methods designed for fitting functional response curves assume that the predator only has “two time-consuming behaviours–searching and handling of prey” [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In this context, the “handling time” has been defined as “the time lost from searching per resource consumed,” not as the ingestion time per resource consumed [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Our handling time estimates (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0246178.g002">Fig 2C</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0246178.s008">S4 Table</xref>) are based on the original framework of functional response analysis, and therefore represent average predator search times per larva consumed. The prey-searching techniques of 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>albidus</italic> and 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>viridis</italic> have previously been described as “[relying] on bumping into … prey during the course of … meanderings” [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. This description of rather inefficient prey searching is consistent with our handling time estimates of approximately 30 min to 1 h (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0246178.g002">Fig 2C</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0246178.s008">S4 Table</xref>).
</p>
