<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Life history characteristics other than fecundity, particularly lifespan and resistance to starvation, also impact the efficiency of biocontrol agents, and these characteristics have been shown to positively correlate with cyclopoid copepod body size [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. The relationship between lifespan and body size is recognized as a general rule in ecology and has been exemplified by comparing the lifespan of an elephant to that of a mouse [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>viridis</italic> females from English Lake District cultures have previously been observed to spend approximately 120 days (at 15°C) and 80 days (at 20°C) in the adult life stage [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The fecundity and long-term stability of field copepod populations can be difficult to predict. A year-round field study conducted in Florida, USA of cyclopoid copepod populations in tire piles found that the number of copepods observed was influenced by the age and amount of leaf litter in each tire [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. In addition, cyclopoid copepod populations survive longer in tires near shade or vegetation because the water in the tire is less likely to evaporate [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. In the UK, where 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> adults are only expected to be active from May to September [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], the stability of year-round copepod populations in tires may not be a priority. The use of copepods as biocontrol agents in UK field sites might benefit from bi-monthly re-applications of well-maintained laboratory cultures, and perhaps more frequent reinforcements in case of long droughts followed by substantial precipitation. A control strategy that is based on precipitation patterns and the estimated survival time of adult copepods in the field would be less risky than a strategy that relies on the viability of subsequent copepod generations.
</p>
