<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Polyherbal combination provides treatment of diseases in a holistic approach. Drug combination in Ayurveda is based on two principles, i.e., use as a single drug and use of more than one medicine, the latter known as a mixture of polyherbal formula. This important traditional therapeutic herbal approach deploys the use of a combination of several medicinal herbs to accomplish desired therapeutic efficacy and it is usually known as polyherbalism or polypharmacy (Parasuraman et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The Ayurvedic literature Sarangdhar Samhita highlighted the concept of polyherbalism to achieve greater therapeutic efficacy (Srivastava et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). To obtain the desired therapeutic impact, the active phytochemical constituents of individual plants are inadequate. Although the active phytochemical components of individual plants have been well identified, they generally occur in a lower amount and are always insufficient to attain the desirable therapeutic impact. Scientific studies have disclosed that when mixed, these drugs of variable potency can theoretically generate a higher outcome compared to the plant’s actual use as well as the sum of its impact. In our study, a combination with the combination of four extracts (Combination: ABCD) showed better nephroprotective activity as compared to a combination containing three plant extracts (Combination: ABD). For both the combinations, a higher dose showed better activity as compared to a lower dose. The reversal of kidney function markers, oxidative stress marker and histological changes produced upon methotrexate treatment was also higher in combination ABCD as compared to combination ABD. The pharmacological activity of a combination of four plants was significantly higher as compared to the combination of these plant extracts. This beneficial herbal interaction phenomenon is known as synergism of pharmacodynamics effect (Spinella 
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Some pharmacological activities of bioactive components of medicinal plants are only valuable when potentiated by those of other plants, but not apparent when used alone.
</p>
