<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cardiovascular disease (CVD) is the leading cause of death worldwide. CVD is a result of longstanding risk factors, such as high blood pressure, an atherogenic diet, and dyslipidemia [
 <xref rid="B136-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>,
 <xref rid="B137-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. Herbal drugs and alternative medicine have been taken into consideration in managing cardiovascular risk factors. 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> is known to be rich in bioactive compounds that can improve cardiovascular health. Indeed, in patients with dyslipidemia, a triple-blind randomized placebo-controlled crossover trial reported improvement in endothelial vasodilator function, including flow-mediated dilation (FMD), after consumption of a daily dose of 500 mg of 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> fruits for 4 weeks [
 <xref rid="B103-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. Furthermore, significant reduction in the systolic and diastolic blood pressure, total serum cholesterol and low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C), non-high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (non-HDL-C), and body mass index (BMI) was observed in the 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> treated group compared to the placebo one [
 <xref rid="B103-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. A meta-analysis study revealed that 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> exerts a positive effect on different indices of the lipid profile including increasing Apo A-I and HDL, decreasing Apo B, Apo B/ Apo A1 ratio, total cholesterol, LDL, and triglyceride [
 <xref rid="B105-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Another study showed that methanolic extract of 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> leaves (RCLE) exerts a cardiovascular protective effect in isolated rabbit heart, which when perfused with various concentrations of RCLE for 20 min prior to ischemia, was dose-dependently protected against myocardial injury caused by ischemia–reperfusion [
 <xref rid="B107-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Indeed, RCLE significantly reduced the activity of two markers of myocardial damage, creatinine kinase, and lactate dehydrogenase. Mechanistically, RCLE seems to exert its cardioprotective effect through inhibiting TNF-α, activating endothelial nitric oxide synthase (eNOS) and cyclooxygenases (COX), and scavenging free radicals and ROS [
 <xref rid="B107-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Our group recently reported that the ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> fruit, dose-dependently relaxes rat isolated aorta. This effect is mediated through stimulation of multiple signaling cascades which include PI3-K/Akt, eNOS, nitric oxide (NO), soluble guanylate cycle (sGC), cGMP, protein kinase G (PKG), COX, adenylyl cyclase/cAMP and ATP- gated potassium channels [
 <xref rid="B102-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. In addition to our previous finding as an antihypertensive, ongoing experiments in our lab are also deciphering the potential effect of vasorelaxant activity of sumac on other blood vessel type and not only on the aorta. It appears from our preliminary results that Sumac fruit extract is cardiovascular protective as well (RI and AHE, personal communication). Altogether, these findings strongly support the favorable potential cardio- and vasculo-protective action of 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> and opens the doors toward the advantageous use of folk medicine for amelioration of cardiovascular diseases such as atherosclerosis, aortic aneurysms, and hypertension.
</p>
