<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Long-term feeding of specific diets may cause alterations in the BAT composition and activity. Our work has shown that a high fat, low carbohydrate ketogenic (KG) diet (
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Srivastava et al., 2013</xref>) increased BAT volume and the expression of mitochondrial proteins in BAT in mice. A novel dietary additive, which can be given along with a normal carbohydrate-level diet and yet can increase blood ketone levels, was developed in the lab of R.L. Veech. This ketone ester, when given to mice in liquid diets, produced blood ketone (β-hydroxybutyrate) levels much greater than that achieved with the KG diets without the need to restrict carbohydrate intake (
 <xref rid="B150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Srivastava et al., 2012</xref>). The increased ketone levels were associated with several positive metabolic effects. These include a significant activation of BAT and mitochondrial biogenesis in this tissue, increased UCP1 levels in WAT. Dietary administration of medium chain triglycerides (MCTs) (
 <xref rid="B187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhang et al., 2015</xref>) as well as MCT-enriched diacylglycerol oil (MCE-DAG) (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kim et al., 2017</xref>), which also increase blood ketone levels, was shown to activate BAT. Azelaic acid, a pharmacological activator of Olfr544, was shown to induce ketogenesis in the liver and increased UCP1 expression in the BAT (
 <xref rid="B175" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wu et al., 2017</xref>). All these results indicate that increased blood ketone levels can modulate brown fat activity. Other diet-derived small molecule BAT activators have also been identified. These include butyrate (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Li Z. et al., 2018</xref>), acetate (
 <xref rid="B135" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sahuri-Arisoylu et al., 2016</xref>) and succinate (
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mills et al., 2018</xref>). These studies suggest that elevation of TCA cycle metabolites can trigger changes in BAT activity. 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref> lists some of the diet-derived small molecules shown to increase BAT activity and browning of WAT.
</p>
