<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">Sterilization procedure refers to any process that eliminates or deactivates transmissible infectious agents that contain nucleic acids (Calvo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2011</xref>), either vegetative forms or spores of bacteria and fungi, parasites and viruses. The level of sterility assurance (SAL) is the likelihood of viable microorganisms in a unit of product after sterilization and is described by SAL 10
 <sup>−6</sup> that would ensure that less than one in every million contaminants would survive in the sterilized graft.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn3">3</xref> The most common methodology for terminal allograft sterilization is gamma irradiation (Hamer et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1999</xref>; Akkus et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2005</xref>; Dziedzic-Goclawska et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2005</xref>) using 25 kilograys (kGy) and can be applied after any processing, allowing sealing in its final packaging. In Chile, as well as many other developing countries, under the technical assistance program of the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) (Morales-Pedraza and Phillips 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2009</xref>), this service can be requested from any local procurement unit through the national centralized coordination managed by the CNPT with the “National Tissue Bank”. Here the tissue is processed for later irradiation in an agreement with the “Chilean Nuclear Energy Commission” (Ministerio de Salud 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2018</xref>; Tallentire 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">1990</xref>), which has been a successful partnership after Chile joined the Latin American Association of Tissue Banks (ALABAT) around the year 2002 (Morales Pedraza et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2011</xref>). However, this sterilization technique cannot be applied to all tissues, e.g. cardiovascular tissue, due to direct damage to the biological structure (Yusof 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2001</xref>), it is not recommended for bone grafts (Fawzi-Grancher et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2009</xref>; Kluger et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2003</xref>; Moreau et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2000</xref>; Nguyen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2007</xref>; Ijiri et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">1994</xref>) due to collagen degradation at 25 kGy that may cause lower remodelling and angiogenesis capacity, among others, and gamma-irradiation it is not capable of removing prions, which can be the cause of Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (Lomas et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2013</xref>). To solve the ultrastructure disruption drawback, tissue banks have implemented several other techniques, such as electron beam irradiation (Keshlaf and Schmidt 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2011</xref>), and peracetic acid treatment for bone sterilization that has demonstrated to be a reliable method for sterilization of tissues grafts (Mahirogullari et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2007</xref>; Pruss et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2003</xref>).
</p>
