<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The results of this study revealed that the tested EOs exhibit potent contact toxicity against the green peach aphid and the bird cherry-oat aphid. The values analyzed from LC
 <sub>50</sub> spraying bioassays showed that the EO from 
 <italic>S. chamaecyparissus</italic> was more toxic than that from 
 <italic>T. patula</italic> in both aphid species. This finding could be related to the structural and biological activity of the constituents of the EOs. The bioactivity of EOs and other extracts from different 
 <italic>Tagetes</italic> species have been previously reported with reference to several insect pests, including aphids [
 <xref rid="B35-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Dardouri el al. [
 <xref rid="B38-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] demonstrated that volatiles from 
 <italic>T. patula</italic> significantly reduced performance of the green peach aphid on pepper. Essential oil and extracts from 
 <italic>Tagetes minuta</italic> were also toxic to 
 <italic>M. persicae</italic> and two other aphid species—
 <italic>Acyrthosiphon pisum</italic> (Harris) and 
 <italic>Aulacorthum solani</italic> (Kaltenbach) [
 <xref rid="B36-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. There is less data available on the insecticidal properties of santolina oil; however, with regard to aphids, some studies revealed the oil had strong antifeedant activity against 
 <italic>R. padi</italic> [
 <xref rid="B39-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Moreover, in contact toxicity tests it was shown that essential oil from santolina exhibited potent contact toxicity towards 
 <italic>Reticulitermes speratus</italic> and 
 <italic>Blattella germanica</italic> [
 <xref rid="B40-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. These studies revealed that the toxicity of the oil was strongly connected with its main components, such as 
 <italic>β</italic>-phellandrene and artemisia ketone. In addition, it was shown that the insecticidal activity of 
 <italic>β</italic>-phellandrene correlated with its ability to inhibit the activity of acetylcholinesterase. In general, the most abundant constituents of EOs determine their biological activity [
 <xref rid="B42-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Previous studies have demonstrated that the main components of 
 <italic>T. patula</italic> oil also possess insecticidal properties. Tomova et al. [
 <xref rid="B36-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] reported relatively high toxicity of limonene to the pea aphid. Moreover, in studies on fumigant toxicity of nine monoterpenes against 
 <italic>M. persicae</italic>, it was shown that terpinolene was one of the most toxic, next to carvacrol and bornyl acetate [
 <xref rid="B44-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].
</p>
