<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The present results revealed that treatment with EOs causes significant increases in levels of O
 <sub>2</sub>
 <sup>•−</sup> and H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> within aphid tissues. The formation of superoxide anion may initiate a cascade of free radical reactions that generate other ROS including highly reactive hydroxyl radical (HO
 <sup>•</sup>). Excessive accumulation of ROS leads to disordered redox balance in an organism, inflicting serious damage to biological macromolecules, such as DNA, RNA, proteins and lipids. Hydroxyl radical is the main factor in free-radical toxicity because it is able to initiate lipid peroxidation. Lipid hydroperoxides may undergo secondary reactions producing highly reactive aldehydes and ketones called TBARS [
 <xref rid="B4-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Our results showed an increased level of TBARS in both aphid species after treatment with the tested EOs, indicating that lipid peroxidation occurred within their tissues. Interestingly, the oil of santolina had both a higher aphicidal activity and evoked a higher level of lipid peroxidation. The effect was especially pronounced at 48 and 72 h post-exposure. These findings suggest that oxidative damage may be an important factor contributing to the insecticidal activity of the tested EOs, and therefore may be one of the mechanisms responsible for their toxic effects. Similar observations have been reported in earlier studies on the toxicity mechanisms of 
 <italic>Psidium guajava</italic> (Myrtaceae) EO towards 
 <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> [
 <xref rid="B52-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. The studies presented evidence of oxidative stress, including ROS and TBARS formation, as well as changes in an important antioxidant response system. Shahriari et al. [
 <xref rid="B19-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] also demonstrated a significant increase in lipid peroxidation products in 
 <italic>Ephestia kuehniella</italic> (Lepidoptera) larvae after 24 and 48 h of feeding on a diet containing EO constituents such as α-pinene, trans-anethole and thymol. For phytophagous insects, lipid peroxidation is especially harmful because it leads to disruption of cell membrane permeability and many other physiological functions such as development and reproduction [
 <xref rid="B53-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].
</p>
