<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Aphids and other herbivorous insects possess an antioxidant enzyme system that scavenges excessive ROS. The SOD-CAT system provides the first defense against oxygen toxicity by catalyzing the dismutation of superoxide anion to hydrogen peroxide and decomposition of hydrogen peroxide to water and molecular oxygen [
 <xref rid="B20-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Our results demonstrate that treatment with EOs leads to a significant upregulation of SOD and CAT activity in both aphid species. This upregulation of antioxidant enzymes could be an adaptive response in insects, aimed at minimalizing potentially deleterious effects of the EO-induced oxidative stress. The enzyme activity increased markedly after 24 or 48 h of exposure to EOs and in most cases returned to the control level after 72 h. Significant induction of SOD and CAT activity at 24 and 48 h was also reported by Shahriari et al. [
 <xref rid="B19-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] in 
 <italic>E. kuehniella</italic> after feeding on a diet containing several EO components. On the other hand, comparative studies of antioxidant enzyme activity in two stored product pests exposed to 
 <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> EO showed that, in 
 <italic>Sitophilus oryzae,</italic> SOD and CAT activity increased after 48 h, while in 
 <italic>Oryzaephilus surinamensis</italic> it increased after only 6 h [
 <xref rid="B15-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In studies on the mechanism of toxicity of 
 <italic>Eugenia uniflora</italic> EO towards fruit flies, Cunha et al. [
 <xref rid="B21-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] described a two-phased adaptive response to oxidative stress. This consisted of an early phase triggered by ROS induction, resulting in activation of the master regulator of the cellular antioxidant response (the transcription factor Nrf2), and a late phase, characterized by oxidative damage and increased levels of ROS and xenobiotic detoxifying enzymes. However, it should be noted that differences in the antioxidant response of insects to oxidative stress may depend on factors such as the applied compound and its concentration, type of treatment, insect genus and time of exposure [
 <xref rid="B55-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].
</p>
