<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Foodborne outbreaks associated with the consumption of fruits are not frequent; however, their numbers have been increasing worldwide [
 <xref rid="B1-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. A listeriosis outbreak linked to the consumption of caramel apples (produced with ‘Granny Smith’ and ‘Gala’ apples) was reported in 12 states of USA with a total of 35 people infected, 34 hospitalizations, and seven deaths) [
 <xref rid="B3-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Changes in diet including higher consumption of fruits and vegetables is highly recommended to decrease the risk of several diseases, such as coronary heart disease, cardiovascular disease, stroke, total cancer, and hypertension [
 <xref rid="B4-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. The elderly, pregnant women, and immunocompromised patients are at risk of listeriosis [
 <xref rid="B7-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]; for this risk group the provision of safe fruit and vegetables is critical. In minimally processed produce microbial contamination may occur at several production steps, for example, at orchards, harvest, storage, processing, and distribution [
 <xref rid="B8-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Such contamination may be reinforced by abusive storage temperature, humidity, injured location, nutrients richness (as sugars), and pH value. The consumption of apple cider contaminated with 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7 and 
 <italic class="italic">Cryptosporidium</italic> resulted in outbreaks [
 <xref rid="B10-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>] and several product recalls were noticed due to possible 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> O157:H7 contamination [
 <xref rid="B12-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Besides apples and their food derivatives being characterized by a low pH value (3–4) that can inhibit the bacterial growth, many foodborne pathogens are able to overcome such low pH by displaying stress tolerance responses, challenging food control measures [
 <xref rid="B13-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Fresh-cut fruit is consumed without further microbial control procedures, so effective measures that ensure product safety are necessary, especially because in these products cross-contamination during the peeling and cutting operations may occur. The processing of the fresh-cut fruits includes key preservation techniques, namely the use of packaging with modified atmosphere (modified atmosphere packing) that can be improved with the addition of antimicrobial and antioxidant agents allowing, in combination with low storage temperature, an extended shelf life, at the same time preserving their nutritional and organoleptic proprieties [
 <xref rid="B14-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. The use of edible coatings supplemented with essential oils can constitute a promising approach to improve both preservation and safety of fresh-cut fruits maintaining the use of the conventional packing technologies [
 <xref rid="B14-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. The survival of foodborne pathogenic bacteria, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> spp. and 
 <italic class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, in fresh-cut apples has been reported, representing a public health problem [
 <xref rid="B16-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. The incorporation of essential oils into edible coatings used in fresh-cut apples to control 
 <italic class="italic">L. innocua</italic> was reported [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. However, the composition of the essential oils may significantly vary over the years, so the use of essential oil components into edible coatings will ensure steady properties, meeting the market needs [
 <xref rid="B14-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Eugenol and citral are two essential oil components that are used as flavoring agents in food products. The European Commission approved their use in the food industry (Regulation EU 872/2012). The incorporation of these components into chitosan edible coatings not only reduced the microbial decay, but also conserved the nutritional and sensory quality of 
 <italic class="italic">Arbutus unedo</italic> fruits [
 <xref rid="B20-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. In another study, the use of alginate edible coating supplemented with eugenol or a combination of eugenol and citral achieved similar results on the preservation of fresh-cut ‘Bravo de Esmolfe’ apple, a Portuguese apple cultivar [
 <xref rid="B21-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. The consumption of ‘Bravo de Esmolfe’ apple is increasing due to its agreeable characteristics (flavor, sweetness, and a particular aroma); however, during storage these proprieties significantly decline, becoming more susceptible to cross-contamination [
 <xref rid="B21-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. The use of edible coatings can not only assure the preservation of the nutritional quality and avoid the microbial spoilage, but also limit the colonization of the fruit by foodborne pathogens.
</p>
