<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Headspace SPME that is a clean‐up of procedure was used to extract headspace volatiles from the samples. The 
 <italic>Perilla frutescens</italic> sample was ground in a mortar with a pestle to obtain a paste, and then, 100 mg of paste was placed in a 20 ml headspace vial fitted with a silicone septum. Cyclohexanone (10 µl, 1,000 μg/ml in methanol) as an internal standard was added. After equilibration for at least 10 min, SPME sampling was performed by exposing the fiber for 30 min in the headspace of the sampling vial at 40°C. The SPME device was placed into a GC system equipped with a mass spectrometer (GC: Nexis GC‐2030, MS: TQ8050NX, Shimadzu Corporation) equipped with a capillary column (IntertCap Pure‐WAX, 30 m × 0.25 mm ID, 0.25 μm film, GL Sciences Ltd.). The column temperature was programmed to hold at 40°C for 5 min, subsequently raised to 250°C at 5°C/min, and held for 15 min. The injector temperature was set to 250°C. The flow rate of the carrier gas (helium) was 1.0 ml/min. The MS detector was operated in electron impact ionization mode at 70 eV. The analysis was performed in the SCAN mode in the 30–550 m
 <italic>/z</italic> range. Tentative identification of constituents was based on comparison of the retention time and mass fragmentation with pure standards, and on computer matching with commercial mass spectra libraries (NIST &amp; WILEY) and a home‐made library based on pure compounds, which were analyzed under identical conditions. Furthermore, the volatile compounds in raw 
 <italic>Perilla frutescens</italic> samples with intact oil glands were analyzed. Briefly, raw 
 <italic>Perilla frutescens</italic> sample (100 mg) was placed in a 20 ml headspace vial fitted with a silicone septum. After the addition of an internal standard, the headspace gas was analyzed by HS‐SPME/GC‐MS under the same analytical conditions as described above. Perillaldehyde content in the 
 <italic>Perilla frutescens</italic> sample was determined by preparing calibration curves of perillaldehyde, with cyclohexanone as an internal standard.
</p>
