<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nutrition is considered as a fundamental pillar of human beings for maintaining health or in development across the entire life span. Moreover, it is very important to have a proper diet and enough nutrition for survival, physical growth, mental development, performance and productivity, health and well-being [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. One often quoted phrase, “medicines and foods have a common origin” and based upon this idea, 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> could be considered as one of the most significant mushrooms, enriched with various nutrients with possible nutraceutical value [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Abundant amounts of bioactive components are present in 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> such as proteins, fats, essential amino acids, volatile oils, carotenoids, phenolic compounds, flavonoids, minerals (Fe, Ca, Mg, Ni, Sr, Na, Ti, Pi, Se, Mn, Zn, Al, Si, K, Cr, Ga, V and Zr), vitamins (B1, B2, B12, E and K) as well as various types carbohydrates like monosaccharides, oligosaccharides, polysaccharides, sterols, nucleosides, etc. [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Proximate analysis of some of the 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> species have reported that moisture, total ash, crude protein, fat, crude fibre and carbohydrate content are 7.18%, 7.48%, 21.46%, 1.80%, 6.40% and 55.68%, respectively [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Many authors have also reported proximate analyses of 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> fruiting bodies and mycelial biomass. The protein, moisture, ash, fat, and carbohydrate compositions of 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> fruiting bodies were reported as 59.8%, 5.7%, 5.1%, 8.8% and 29.1%, whereas, mycelial biomass contains 39.5%, 13.1%, 5.7%, 2.2% and 39.6% of protein, moisture, ash, fat and carbohydrates, respectively [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. On the other hand, the amino acid contents of the corpus as well as fruiting bodies of 
 <italic>Cordyceps militaris (C. militaris)</italic> were reported to be 14.03 mg/g and 69.32, respectively. Additional amino acid analysis indicates that the fruiting bodies contains abundant amounts of proline, lysine, threonine and glutamic acid. Moreover, fatty acid profiling indicates almost 70% of unsaturated fatty acids out of the total fat percentage. Importantly, the amount of cordycepin and adenosine in both corpus and fruit bodies was reported to be (0.97 and 0.36%) and (0.18 and 0.06%), respectively [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. With the increasing interest in 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> in recent times for pharmaceutical, nutraceutical or food biotechnological purposes, further research is necessary to obtain an overview of the potential of this medicinal mushroom [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].
</p>
