<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Splat Organic, without the addition of essential oil, had a similar effect to Colgate Total. Splat Organic contains 
 <italic class="italic">Aloe barbadensis</italic> Mill. (
 <italic class="italic">Aloe vera</italic> Mill) gel and papain and 
 <italic class="italic">Melaleuca alternifolia</italic> (Maiden et Betche) Cheel 
 <italic class="italic">(M. alternifolia)</italic> leaf extract. 
 <italic class="italic">Aloe vera</italic> is a well-known medicinal plant of the Liliaceae family. The pharmacological actions of 
 <italic class="italic">Aloe vera</italic> gel, including anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, antioxidant, immune-boosting, and hypoglycaemic properties, have been studied in vitro and in vivo [
 <xref rid="B80-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>,
 <xref rid="B83-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>,
 <xref rid="B84-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>]. An in vitro study showed that an 
 <italic class="italic">Aloe vera</italic> gel was as effective as commercially popular dentifrices in controlling 
 <italic class="italic">S. mutans</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">S. sanguis</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">A. Viscosus</italic> growth. The 
 <italic class="italic">Aloe vera</italic> gel showed an antibacterial effect, especially against 
 <italic class="italic">S. mitis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B85-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>] and 
 <italic class="italic">S. mutans</italic> [
 <xref rid="B86-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>]. In a randomized controlled clinical trial for 6 months, toothpaste containing an aloe vera gel was used, and measurements were recorded at 6 weeks, 12 weeks, and 24 weeks. During this time, the gingival and plaque index scores decreased and there was a significant improvement in the microbiological counts [
 <xref rid="B87-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>]. Papain is a proteolytic enzyme obtained from the papaya (
 <italic class="italic">Carica papaya</italic> L.) plant and has the strongest effect among all papaya products [
 <xref rid="B88-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>]. Papain, with its proteolytic activity against the amino acid, has been extensively used in the fields of medicine and food [
 <xref rid="B90-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>]. Papain-containing materials have shown successful results when used against 
 <italic class="italic">S. mutans</italic> biofilm [
 <xref rid="B89-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">M. alternifolia</italic> is known as “tea tree”. The antibacterial activity of this plant has been utilized for many years. Several studies found that the 
 <italic class="italic">M. alternifolia</italic> essential oil and its main components are effective against pathogenic flora. Due to its broad spectrum, a strong inhibition against gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria, including 
 <italic class="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">S. gordonii</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">S. mutans</italic>, was found [
 <xref rid="B92-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>,
 <xref rid="B93-pathogens-08-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>]. The antibacterial effect of Splat Organic may be due to its 
 <italic class="italic">Aloe vera</italic> and papain content. Splat Biocalcium does not contain fluoride, triclosan, chlorhexidine, and alcohol, but contains nano-hydroxyapatite and papain like Splat Organic. The similar antibacterial effect of Splat Biocalcium to the positive control group may be due to its papain content.
</p>
