<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030" class="p">Genetically modified poplar trees and the corresponding wild types were grown in a field in Orleans, France. Three types of transgenic lines were produced with 
 <italic class="italic">COMT</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">CAD</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">CCoAOMT</italic> downregulation as described in Van Doorsselaere et al. [
 <xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>], Baucher et al. [
 <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>], Lapierre et al. [
 <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] and Meyermans et al. [
 <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. The 
 <italic class="italic">COMT</italic> (Li09, Li11) and 
 <italic class="italic">CAD</italic> lines (Li18, Li21, Li22) and corresponding control line (Tin) were grown in a single field that was planted in June 2008, coppiced in March 2010 and harvested after 2 years of growth in February 2012. 
 <italic class="italic">CCoAOMT</italic> down-regulated lines were grown on a neighbouring field along with their corresponding wild-type (reference Tbr). On this second plot, trees were planted in May 2009, coppiced in 2010 at the same time as the other plot, and collected in February 2012 as well. Both fields were divided into five blocks, with each block containing 24 clonal replicates per line (
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). Poplar was first debarked, and the dried wood chips collected from each line and each block were first ground using a 6 mm grid and then further ground using a high-frequency grinder (Retch 300, 200 Hz) and sieved to remove particles larger than 500 μm. 
 <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref> lists the samples used in the current work. The composition of lignin in terms of G or S units was obtained using the thioacidolysis procedure developed by Lapierre et al. [
 <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. The procedure involves removal of cell-wall extractives by incubating small amounts of sample (~12 mg) in water at 98 °C, followed by ethanol at 76 °C, chloroform at 59 °C and acetone at 54 °C. Each of these incubation steps was performed for 30 min, and the supernatant was removed by centrifuging at 14000 rpm for 3 min. The dried sample pellets free from cell-wall are then treated with a reaction mixture of boron trifluoride, ethanediol and dioxane. The sample vials were filled with liquid N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> vapours to maintain the inert atmosphere and placed in a water bath at 98 °C for 4 h. Further, tetracosane was added as an internal standard to each of the vials before extracting with dichloromethane and water. The organic phase was then pipetted into a new Eppendorf and dried using speedvac. S and G unit representatives present in the dried sample were first dissolved in dichloromethane and then derivatised using 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>-bis(trimethylsilyl)acetamide for GC–MS analysis.
</p>
