<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Tang et al. prepared two essential oils, chamomile oil (CO) and peppermint oil (PO) loaded gelatin (GEL) nanofibers via electrospinning for implementation in edible-packaging materials [
 <xref rid="B262-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">262</xref>]. The photographs of the different nanofibers’ diameter distribution and scanning electron microscope images are presented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-04017-f012">Figure 12</xref>. All groups of GEL/essential oil nanofibers had a smooth and bead-free structure. No apparent deviation was observed from pure GEL nanofibers, indicating the homogeneous distribution and incorporation of the essential oils in GEL nanofibers. With the rise in the concentration of essential oils, the diameter of GEL/essential oil nanofibers was vastly widened, which may be attributed to the increased viscosity of the spinning solution resulting from the inclusion of essential oils [
 <xref rid="B43-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B263-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">263</xref>,
 <xref rid="B264-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">264</xref>]. Incorporating essential oils turn the hydrophilic GEL polymer into a hydrophobic polymer to avoid moisture movement between food and the environment to prolong the food shelf-life [
 <xref rid="B265-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">265</xref>,
 <xref rid="B266-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">266</xref>]. Contrastingly, GEL nanofibers with CO were more hydrophobic than those with PO at the same quantity, as indicated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-04017-f013">Figure 13</xref> [
 <xref rid="B267-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">267</xref>,
 <xref rid="B268-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">268</xref>]. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-04017-f014">Figure 14</xref> shows that the GEL nanofiber incorporated with essential oils inhibited 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> growth; this inhibition was seen more against the former strain [
 <xref rid="B269-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">269</xref>,
 <xref rid="B270-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">270</xref>,
 <xref rid="B271-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">271</xref>]. The antibacterial activity also was enhanced as the concentration of essential oils was increased, and in comparison to CO, PO-containing GEL nanofibers exhibited more considerable antibacterial activity against both microorganisms. DPPH radical scavenging activity of the nanofiber loaded with different concentrations of PO, CO, and PO/CO essential oils (0%, 3%, 6%, and 9%) indicated that with the increase of the essential oil amount, the antioxidant activity increased, as illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-04017-f015">Figure 15</xref> [
 <xref rid="B272-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">272</xref>]. The CO-containing nanofibers displayed more excellent antioxidant activity than the PO groups, whereas the GEL/CO/PO nanofibers were mainly intermediate. The MTS assay results demonstrated that nanofibers of GEL/essential oils were harmless to NIH-3T3 cells, increasing their cell viability, which, as shown, made them eligible for edible packaging use [
 <xref rid="B51-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The role of evolved GEL/PO/CO as a promising candidate for edible packaging is reflected in these findings.
</p>
