<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The essential oil of 
 <italic>Angelica sinensis</italic> (Oliv.) herb, known in Chinese as Dong-gui, has been shown to have excellent antibacterial and antioxidant activities that could be useful as a possible bioactive ingredient in food packaging. Zhou et al. fabricated gelatin (GEL) nanofibers loaded with different concentrations (0%, 3%, 6%, and 9%) of angelica essential oil (AEO) through electrospinning [
 <xref rid="B273-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">273</xref>]. In general, as the viscosity increased, the nanofiber diameter also increased due to less stretching of fiber. Moreover, with the addition of electrical conductivity, the diameter was reduced because of more elongation of the fiber. In this analysis, the rise in the AEO concentration also increased the viscosity and the electric conductivity, which led to the final increase in the nanofiber diameter [
 <xref rid="B264-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">264</xref>]. The best food-packaging material has a high water-contact angle (hydrophobic), antioxidant activity, and antibacterial activity. The GEL nanofiber’s water-contact angle improved as the concentration of AEO increased, which could be related to the hydrophobic nature of AEO [
 <xref rid="B274-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">274</xref>,
 <xref rid="B275-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">275</xref>]. Likewise, the increased amount of AEO enhanced the antioxidant activity of GEL/AEO nanofibers, and hence protected the food from oxidative damage. Due to the presence of an E-3 butylidenephthalide component, AEO had outstanding antioxidant properties [
 <xref rid="B276-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">276</xref>]. The GEL nanofibers with 9% AEO concentration showed the highest bactericidal effect against 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> as revealed by the shake-flask method [
 <xref rid="B277-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">277</xref>]. The results demonstrated that the GEL/AEO nanofiber was essential in extending the shelf life of the products.
</p>
