<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">
 <italic>Erythrina</italic> is a genus of flowering plants in the pea family Fabaceae [
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] which are often cultivated as an ornamental and soil improvement tree to fix nitrogen for other tree crops [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This genus has been introduced and cultivated in India and Kenya [
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and over 130 species are distributed in tropical and subtropical regions of the world. Nine of these trees are found in southern Africa where the most common species are probably the 
 <italic>Erythrina caffra</italic> and 
 <italic>Erythrina lysistemon</italic> growing up to 30 m in height. The stem barks of 
 <italic>Erythrina</italic> species have many physiologically active alkaloids [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Their alkaloids are attractive synthetic targets resulting from their use in indigenous medicine [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The prenylated flavonoids, prevalent in the stem and root bark [
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], has displayed a variety of biological activities. Traditionally, 
 <italic>Erythrina</italic> genus has been prominently used in folk medicine [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Mitscher 
 <italic>et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and Burkill [
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] indicated that many of these species have been used for the treatment of female infertility, inflammation, stomach pain, gonorrhea and other microbial infections and as tranquilizers against insomnia [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. 
 <italic>Erythrina caffra,</italic> the Coastal Coral Tree, native to southeastern Africa, is used for treating sores, tuberculosis, respiratory and wound infections, arthritis and toothache while the extracts of 
 <italic>E. senegalensis, E. velutina</italic> and 
 <italic>E. mulungu</italic> have demonstrated the presence of analgesic and anti-inflammatory effects [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. However, while there are sufficient scientific reports confirming the ethnopharmacological importance of 
 <italic>E. caffra</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], the chemical composition of its essential oil, its antioxidant and antibacterial properties remains vague and the pharmacological effectiveness needed to be investigated. Therefore, this study aimed at identifying the chemical composition of the essential oil of 
 <italic>Erythrina caffra</italic> using gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) technique, evaluate its antioxidant and antibacterial potentials using standard procedures and to justify their possible multi-functional roles in folklore uses.
</p>
