<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An updated and exclusive collection of results about yucca’s beneficial effects as a phytogenic additive for clean aquaculture activity are presented in this article. Yucca can clearly enhance the quality of rearing water by reducing ammonia emissions that result from aquatic organisms due to its potential as a medicinal herb. As a water remedy, yucca removes excess ammonia and reduces the water toxicity impacts on fish performances. The enhanced water quality clearly provides clean environmental conditions for aquatic organisms. Since aquatic organisms are known for their high sensitivity to environmental stressors, yucca’s application can be considered an active substance for the “blue clean aquaculture industry.” Additionally, yucca showed growth-promoting effects when included as a dietary additive, with possible feed utilization potential. The enhancement of feed digestion and nutrient absorption activates the local intestinal immunity, which leads to improved immunity and high resistance against infectious diseases. There are direct and indirect effects implicated for both axes involved in the aims of the present work: yucca can directly achieve improved water quality but immunity and growth may be indirectly affected. The review analyzed and reconsidered the published papers and presented their analyses and conclusions accordingly. The controlled aquaculture conditions were created to operate fish cultivation under strict veterinary and animal welfare regulations that were established after several decades of research and accumulated knowledge. Unfortunately, the ecosystem faces several environmental fluctuations (e.g., global warming and water pollution), which impact aquaculture requirements (e.g., water quality). Additionally, the controlled farming procedures are still not fully applied in several countries, especially the developing countries due to the lack of resources and technical experience; this motivates more investigative efforts toward sustaining aquaculture activity. The overall performances of aquatic organisms that were treated with yucca as a dietary additive or a water cleaner encourage performing further studies to prove its mode of action based on biochemical and biological techniques. </p>
