<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Optimization of Somatic Embryogenesis and Regeneration</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In second set of experiment, the cumin seeds were surface-sterilized following the procedure previously described [
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>]. To obtain plantlets, the sterilized seeds were cultured in the half-strength MS medium and stored in the growth chamber [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>]. One month after seed culturing, when grown plantlets were about 5 cm in height, about 0.5 cm of each explant including hypocotyl and cotyledon was prepared. The prepared explants were cultured in MS medium containing 3% (w/v) sucrose and 0.8% (w/v) agar and supplemented with 7 different concentrations of PGRs (2,4-D and Kin) (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>). The cultured explants were incubated in the growth chamber at 24°C ± 2°C, 75% relative humidity, and dark condition during the first month of culture. After this step, the formed calli were subcultured into fresh mediums containing the previous combination of PGRs and then were stored in the growth chamber at 24°C ± 2°C and 75% relative humidity under 16/8 h photoperiod with 50 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>mol
  <span class="sup">−2</span> s
  <span class="sup">−1</span> photosynthetic photon flux density provided by cool white fluorescent light. Data related to the percentage of callus formation was recorded five weeks after culture. Seven weeks after culture, calli images were taken by a camera under the same situations and then perimeter and area of calli were calculated by Digimizer, an image analysis software (version 4.3.1, MedCalc Software, Belgium). In the eighth week, the symptoms of somatic embryogenesis in some of the studied mediums were observed without transferring the calli to the PGRs-free medium; then different stages of the somatic embryogenesis were recorded using a microscope.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thereafter, the calli were transferred to the PGR-free medium for excluding of auxin effect and further stimulation of somatic embryogenesis. The percentage of induced calli with embryogenic potential was calculated on the basis of a number of explants producing somatic embryogenesis/number of total cultured explants in each Petri dish after two to three weeks. Data related to the percentage of plant regeneration were recorded during 12 weeks after the first culture. The percentage of plant regeneration was calculated on the basis of the number of regenerated explants/the number of induced calli with embryogenic potential in each Petri dish.</p>
 <sec id="sec2.3.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.1. Experimental Design and Data Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiment was performed in a factorial form using a completely randomized design with three factors and three replications (as Petri dishes). Five explant segments were placed in each Petri dish containing 25 ml different medium. Studied factors included two Iranian cumin landraces, Golestan and North Khorasan, two explants, hypocotyl and cotyledon, and 7 different concentrations of PGRs (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>). The data related to the percentage of callus formation, perimeter, and area of calli were subjected to ANOVA and DMRT to evaluate the statistical significance and were expressed as the mean ± SE. Since the distribution of the recorded data related to measured characters including the percentage of induced calli with embryogenic potential and the percentage of plant regeneration was not normal and no transformation was able to induce normality, the Kruskal-Wallis and the Mann–Whitney nonparametric tests were used and median grouping was made [
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>]. SAS 9.2, SPSS 16.0, and Excel software were used for data analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
