<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the agriculture, fungi are the major plant pathogen in the field crops and storage food commodities (
 <xref rid="B116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sharifi-Rad et al., 2018</xref>), where by producing mycotoxins and several toxic metabolites they affect the nutritional value of food and make them unhealthy for human consumption (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Paranagama et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sonker et al., 2015</xref>). Fungi reported to infect the plants in the field and storage include the genera of 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus, Cladosporium, Fusarium, Penicillium, Alternaria, Macrophomina, Rhizoctonia, Colletotrichum, and Botrytis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pandey et al., 2017</xref>), they are responsible for the 40–50% loss of the crop produce. For the management of these pathogens several synthetic fungicides like carbendazim, capton, and mancozeb are available in the market, however, these fungicides have their own limitations, use of such fungicides cause several side effect to the host as well as beneficial microorganisms. Also due to climate change some fungal pathogens has started to develop the resistance against the commercial fungicides (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chang et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Price et al., 2015</xref>). Therefore, researchers were use the botanical fungicides for the management of these fungal pathogens which have broad range of toxicity, eco-friendly and renewable in nature. During recent years several essential oils have been proved as effective fungitoxicant against these pathogens including 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> essential oils (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Iacobellis et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Teixeira et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Goudjil et al., 2016</xref>). For the screening of essential oils against fungal pathogens basically few methods such as poison food method (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mishra et al., 2013</xref>), inverted Petri plate method (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pandey et al., 2013</xref>) and agar dilution methods (
 <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vishvakarma et al., 2015</xref>) have been used. Poison food method was used to develop contact fungicides, while inverted Petri plate method was used to develop fumigant fungicides against the fungal pathogens. 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha longifolia</italic> oil was fungistatic against 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus niger, A. versicolor, Cladosporium fulvum, Fusarium tricinctum, F. sporotrichioides, Penicillium funiculosum, P. ochrochloron</italic> at 2.5 μl/ml and against 
 <italic class="italic">C. cladosporioides</italic> at 12.5 μl/ml (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mimica-Dukic et al., 2003</xref>). The MIC of 
 <italic class="italic">M. piperita</italic> varied from 1.13 to 2.25 mg/ml and 2.25 to 4.5 mg/ml for 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum, A. flavus, A. niger, Mucor</italic> spp, and 
 <italic class="italic">F. oxysporum</italic> (
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tyagi and Malik, 2011</xref>). The essential oil and their chemical constituent’s like menthone and β-caryophyllene showed a different degree of inhibition against twenty-five microorganisms with more efficacy against 
 <italic class="italic">A. niger</italic> (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Marotti et al., 1994</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Džamić et al. (2010)</xref> reported that 10 μl/ml of 
 <italic class="italic">M. longifolia</italic> essential oil showed fungicidal activity against 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Fusarium</italic> species, 
 <italic class="italic">P. funiculosum, Trichoderma viride</italic> and 2.5 μl/ml to 
 <italic class="italic">C. fulvum, C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">cladosporioides</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">P. ochrochloron</italic>. A variable range of inhibition zones (11–32, 19–30, and 16–29 mm) were reported for 
 <italic class="italic">M. longifolia, M. piperita</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">M. spicata</italic> essential oils, respectively, against 
 <italic class="italic">Rhizopus solani, A. niger</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Alternaria alternata</italic> infecting stored food commodities. Correspondingly, these oils showed 44.1–157.8, 52.9–130.1, and 53.2–133.1 μg/mL respective range of MICs values against these fungal strains (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hussain et al., 2010a</xref>). Our laboratory bioassay revealed that essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">M. arvensis</italic> was found to be inhibited the growth of postharvest fungi of pigeon pea seeds and papaya fruits especially 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Fusarium</italic> species (
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Singh, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pandey and Tripathi, 2011</xref>). However, on the contrary, results of 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bouchra et al. (2003)</xref> showed that 
 <italic class="italic">M. pulegium</italic> oil had moderate activity against 
 <italic class="italic">Botrytis cinerea</italic> at 250 ppm where only 58.5% growth inhibition was reported. This differentiation in the toxicity may be due to the oils used from different plants and also it depends on the fungal strains of different hosts. 
 <italic class="italic">M. piperita</italic> exhibited fungicidal nature against 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus</italic> strains at 0.5–4 μl/ml (
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Saharkhiz et al., 2012</xref>). Fungal pathogens such as 
 <italic class="italic">Geotrichum citri-aurantii, P. digitatum</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">P. italicum</italic> causing fruit decay in citrus were controlled when treated with 750 μl/l dose of 
 <italic class="italic">M. spicata</italic> oil (
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Regnier et al., 2014</xref>). Also formulation of essential oils has been tested for the control of fungal pathogens and they proved more effective than that of pure oil due to their formulation in adjuvant. The encapsulated oil of 
 <italic class="italic">M. piperita</italic> was very effective at 800 ppm in controlling 
 <italic class="italic">A. flavus</italic> causing postharvest rot in food commodities than that of pure oil which failed to caused complete mycelial inhibition at tested concentration range (upto 3000 ppm) (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beyki et al., 2014</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">M. piperita</italic> oil is also found to be effective against tomato pathogen 
 <italic class="italic">F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. 
 <italic class="italic">lycopersici</italic> causing wilting with MIC of 0.3 μl/ml of air and at increased MFC, i.e., &gt;0.6 μl/ml of air (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Djordjevic et al., 2013</xref>). This oil has also been reported as effective antifungal agent against few soil borne pathogens 
 <italic class="italic">Drechslera spicifera, F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. 
 <italic class="italic">ciceris</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Macrophomina phaseolina</italic> at effective concentration 1600 ppm by agar dilution method (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moghaddam et al., 2013</xref>). Some 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> oils showed poor efficacy and were reported as phytotoxic in nature. In this regard, 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lopez-Reyes et al. (2013)</xref> reported that 
 <italic class="italic">M. arvensis</italic> oil (10% concentration) was poor antifungal agent in controlling 
 <italic class="italic">B. cinerea</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">M. laxa</italic> growing on apricots and oil was also phytotoxic. Also, in their earlier research (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lopez-Reyes et al., 2010</xref>), 1 and 10% essential oil emulsion of 
 <italic class="italic">M. arvensis</italic> was poor effective than that of others oils and fungicide tebuconazole in controlling fruit rot in apple due to 
 <italic class="italic">B. cinerea</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">P. expansum</italic>. Similar results were reported for the fungitoxicity of 
 <italic class="italic">M. arvensis</italic> oil against 
 <italic class="italic">F. oxysporum</italic> causing wilt in crops (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gupta et al., 2011</xref>) at 10 and 20% oil concentration. In macro and microdilution methods, 
 <italic class="italic">M. spicata</italic> essential oil exhibited 1.0–2.5 μl/ml range of MIC value in ethanol and 0.5–1.5 μl/ml in Tween against plant pathogens namely 
 <italic class="italic">A. niger, A. ochraceus, A. versicolor, A. flavus, A. terreus, A. alternata, P. ochrochloron, P. funiculosum, C. cladosporioides, T. viride, F. tricinctum</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Phomopsis helianthi</italic>. However, MICs of 
 <italic class="italic">M. piperita</italic> essential oil were higher, 1.5–3.0 μl/ml in ethanol and 1.0–2.5 μl/ml in Tween against the same pathogens (
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Soković et al., 2009</xref>). These both oils, i.e., 
 <italic class="italic">M. spicata</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">M. piperita</italic> also performed significant antifungal activity against major pathogens of button mushroom, i.e., 
 <italic class="italic">Verticillium fungicola</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. harzianum</italic> (
 <xref rid="B122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sokovic and van Griensven, 2006</xref>) by micro and macro-dilution methods. 
 <italic class="italic">M. spicata</italic> oil was fungistatic at 0.5–2.5 μl/ml, while fungicidal at 1.5–2.5 μl/ml. While MIC (2.5–3.5 μl/ml) and MFC (3.0–4.0 μl/ml) values of 
 <italic class="italic">M. piperita</italic> oil (
 <xref rid="B122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sokovic and van Griensven, 2006</xref>) increased by micro and macro-dilution methods.
</p>
