<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0215">Methanolic extracts of 
 <italic>Ov</italic> from Romania were reported to have higher TFC compared to 
 <italic>Tv</italic> (43.6 mg rutin/g and around 39 mg rutin/g) (
 <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Spiridon et al., 2011</xref>), which is in agreement with our results. However, these results are not in accordance with the results obtained after summarizing the total flavonoids in HPLC analysis for methanolic and aqueous extracts of plants from Greece, where it was reported that methanolic 
 <italic>Ov</italic> extract has 8.90 mg flavonoids/g and 
 <italic>T. capitatus</italic> 9.08 mg/g, while aqueous 
 <italic>Ov</italic> extract has 0.49 mg/g and 
 <italic>T. capitatus</italic> extract has 0.66 mg/g (
 <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Skendi et al., 2017</xref>). Their HPLC analysis showed that both methanolic and aqueous 
 <italic>Ov</italic> extracts have higher amount of rutin (0.50 and 0.04 mg/g) compared with the 
 <italic>T. capitatus</italic> extracts (0.008 mg/g for methanolic extract, while in aqueous extract rutin was not found), which is not in accordance with our results regarding the methanolic extracts, however the results for aqueous extracts are in line. Methanolic extract of 
 <italic>Tm</italic> from Serbia had higher TFC compared to the aqueous one (
 <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Stankovic et al., 2011</xref>), which is consistent with our results. On the other hand, regarding ethanolic extracts of 
 <italic>Teucrium</italic> species from N. Macedonia, 
 <italic>Tc</italic> had slightly higher TFC compared with 
 <italic>Tm</italic> (0.18% and 0.15%, respectively) (
 <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Kadifkova Panovska et al., 2005</xref>), which is not coherent with the results presented in our research. They have also identified luteolin in 
 <italic>Tc</italic> and 
 <italic>Tm</italic> diethyl ether extracts while apigenin was identified only in 
 <italic>T. polium</italic> extract. However, we have quantified similar flavonoids, luteolin-7-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucoside and quercetin in each of the 
 <italic>Tc</italic> and 
 <italic>Tm</italic> extract. Several factors are known to influence the content of phenolic compounds in plants such as climate, altitude, exposure and vegetation phase, to which the observed differences could be attributed.
</p>
