<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Normally, terpene biosynthetic genes are customarily located next to each other in one biosynthetic gene cluster, easing their exploitation and manipulation to produce bioactive compounds with desired quality and quantity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. Historically, more than half of the drugs in use, are sourced from natural substances or their derivatives. With the recent advancements in genomic analysis and analytical tools, new strategies and methods have been utilised for the exploitation of naturally synthesised compounds that are of biotechnological importance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]. The main aim of using such techniques was to predict the genes encoding molecules with novel bioactivity. These techniques have further established the fact that the capability of mushroom forming fungi to synthesise bioactive molecules has been overlooked. They have also revealed the presence of the so called “cryptic” or “orphan” biosynthetic gene clusters [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. The pressing need to produce new antibiotics due to the non-stop increase in antimicrobial resistance and the decline in efficiency of accessible drugs, highlights the importance of using unprecedented techniques such as genome mining in drug discovery. This approach can simplify the biosynthesis of biologically engineered compounds via reducing their commercial production and use [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. This genome mining method can be applied in many different ways. One way is the detection of compound’s coding genes, through “target directed genome mining”, which mainly consists in the identification of biosynthetic gene clusters with unknown function in terms of the corresponding molecule(s) produced [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. Another way is “the one strain many compounds approach”, this method can be used to induce the expression of cryptic genes through controlled alteration of growth conditions. Many silent metabolic pathways were activated using such technique, including activation of the biosynthesis of polypeptides and polyketides with pharmaceutical applications [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]. Metabolism regulation can also be manipulated to enhance the production of secondary metabolites with novel bioactivity. These treatments involve the use of chemicals or small organic molecules to modify or deregulate metabolic processes through the inhibition of fatty acids [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. Examples of other techniques used concurrently with genome mining-based studies are the heterologous expression of biosynthetic gene clusters that synthesise known bioactive molecules. These reconstructed routes ensure the production of pure and easily identifiable intermediates and eliminate unusable by-products. Despite that many terpenes with antimicrobial activity have been described, many more with potential unique derivatives are awaiting discovery [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>].
</p>
