<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">About 4% of world oil production is used as a feedstock to make plastics and a similar amount is used as energy in the process. Waste plastics management practices for the EOL plastics globally are land filling, industrial energy recovery from municipal solid waste incineration (MSWI), pyrolysis and recycling. Used plastics can be recycled up to six times. If it did not make economic or environmental sense to recycle, then the energy can be recovered through energy from waste incineration [
 <xref rid="B2-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Recycling reportedly has the lowest environmental impact on both global warming potential (GWP) and total energy use (TEU) in most cases [
 <xref rid="B1-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Waste plastics recycling include mechanical (material) recycling, and pyrolysis or feedstock recycling:
 <list list-type="simple" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">➢</label>
   <p class="p">Land filling results in no net greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions, no GHG benefits and a waste of valuable resources [
    <xref rid="B4-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">➢</label>
   <p class="p">Mechanical recycling corresponds to the reprocessing of plastic waste to produce new products.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">➢</label>
   <p class="p">Energy recovery option is used to generate heat, steam or electricity or as solid refuse fuel for co-fuelling of blast furnaces or cement kilns, or pyrolysis to diesel fuel or gasification. Highly mixed plastics, such as some electronic and electrical wastes and automotive shredder residues, are the candidates.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">➢</label>
   <p class="p">Pyrolysis, a recycling technique, includes non-catalytic thermal or catalytic thermal methods. High-temperature pyrolysis of plastics is particularly advantageous for metallurgical processes running at very high temperatures, e.g., the Corex Process, blast furnace, HTK Process (HTK: Hochtemperatur-Konversionsverfahren, aka High-Temperature Conversion Process) of Voestalpine-Österreichische Mineralölverwaltung (VOEST-ÖMV), and the Thermoselect Process [
    <xref rid="B5-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Unsorted plastic wastes are converted into fuels, monomers, and other valuable materials, such as liquid fuels, solids (char) and combustible gases, carbon, hydrogen chloride (from PVC) and bromine via thermal and catalytic cracking processes in the absence of oxygen at about 300° C to 500° C.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
 <list list-type="simple" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">▪</label>
   <p class="p">Gasification of plastics occurs approximately at 525–625 °C, much before the steel melting temperature [
    <xref rid="B5-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">▪</label>
   <p class="p">Chemical recycling routes can be broadly divided into thermochemical and catalytic conversion processes. Chemical or feedstock recycling breaks down heterogeneous, contaminated and hard-to-recycle waste polymers into their chemical constituents and converts them into monomers for new plastics or fuels, usually in blast furnaces.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">▪</label>
   <p class="p">Thermal depolymerization breaks down waste plastics into crude oil products under high temperatures and pressure (&gt;400 °C and 4 MPa) in the presence of water via hydrous pyrolysis. Long chain polymers depolymerise into short chain monomers. Small gaseous molecules like methane or carbon dioxide cannot be converted into oil using this process. In this process, organic toxins lose their toxicity due to the breaking down of chemical bonds. Heavy metals are eliminated from the samples as ionized or stable oxide forms. However, toxic by-products like furan and dioxin may be released in addition to methane and carbon dioxide. When applied to E-wastes, this process is effective in dealing with the plastics portion of the E-wastes but offers no method of bromine recovery. The solid fraction resulting from this process would have much higher concentrations of metals. Metal recovery from this metal-laden slag becomes complicated due to the high concentration of oxides, offering no overall increase in recycling efficiency. Thus, a thermal depolymerization process is not suitable for maximum metal extraction, or for increased recycling efficiency.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
