<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In STZ-induced diabetic mice, it has been confirmed that a polysaccharide isolated from MC (MCPIIa) [
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>] and 
 <italic>Momordica charantia</italic> polysaccharide-chromium (III) complex (MCPIIaC) [
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] are effective in protecting pancreatic cells and increasing plasma insulin; selenylated polysaccharide from MC can also increase insulin level [
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. A series of experiments on STZ-induced diabetic rats further confirmed this activity and investigated the underlying mechanism. MC juice treatment can raise the quantity of 
 <italic>β</italic> cells by promoting the renewal or recovery of destroyed 
 <italic>β</italic> cells [
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>], and it significantly improves insulin levels as well as the amount of insulin-positive cells per islet [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. MC juice taken orally can also improve the histopathological changes of pancreas and 
 <italic>β</italic> cell function percent in the way of reducing pancreatic malondialdehyde (MDA) content, increasing serum total antioxidant capacity (TAOC) and pancreatic glutathione (GSH) levels [
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The results are consistent with the findings of Wang et al. who reported that 
 <italic>Momordica charantia</italic> polysaccharide (MCP) distinctly improved antioxidant capacity by increasing superoxide dismutase (SOD) content and reducing MDA content, and therefore it mitigated the damage of pancreas caused by STZ and repaired pancreatic 
 <italic>β</italic> cells [
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Besides, treatment with ethanolic extract of MC almost doubles the total quantity and area of 
 <italic>β</italic> cells and keeps the quantity of 
 <italic>β</italic>-cell insulin granules equivalent to that of nondiabetic group [
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Subchronic studies of ALX-induced diabetic rats have similar findings. A standardized ethanolic extract of MC is valid for restoring the altered histological architecture and enhancing insulin secretion of the islets of Langerhans [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The hypoglycemic effects of acetone extract [
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>] and alcoholic extract [
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] have also been found to be closely related to the promotion of 
 <italic>β</italic>-cell regeneration (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>).
</p>
