<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To support the analysis of the molecular events during SE and other in vitro morphogenetic processes in centaury, we have recently sequenced six 
 <italic>C. erythraea</italic> transcriptomes (embryogenic calli, globular somatic embryos, cotyledonary somatic embryos, adventitious buds, leaves and roots of in vitro grown plants) and de novo assembled referent transcriptome comprising 105.726 genes [
 <xref rid="B116-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. The high quality and completeness transcriptome were functionally annotated and made publicly available. The transcriptome, along with a set of validated housekeeping genes, comprises a framework for the search for genes involved in SE and organogenesis [
 <xref rid="B116-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. A subset of genes potentially involved is SE was selected as transcripts with ≥8-fold higher expression (FPKM values) in embryogenic tissues as compared to non-embryogenic tissues, and their expression was further analyzed by qRT-PCR in 16 tissue samples [
 <xref rid="B117-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. The most intriguing finding of this preliminary research was the expression profile an unknown gene (provisionally termed 
 <italic>UN1</italic>), a 725 bp long transcript with no BLAST hits or homology with any known sequence. 
 <italic>UN1</italic> was highly expressed in leaf-derived embryogenic calli, while its expression progressively decreased in globular and cotyledonary embryos. The 
 <italic>UN1</italic> expression in seedlings, roots, leaf-derived adventitious buds and leaves from flowering plants was below the qPCR detection limits, implying that its expression is restricted to the initial ISE stages [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The investigation of 
 <italic>UN1</italic> structure and function is ongoing; for now, we can only speculate that 
 <italic>UN1</italic> may have an impact on the acquisition of the embryogenic potential, and as such it may be a novel SE marker.
</p>
