<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dengue virus, also referred to as DENV, belongs to the family of 
 <italic>Fliviviridae</italic> and can be transmitted to humans by mosquito bite. Currently, dengue still poses a serious threat to public health. In 2015, more than two million cases of dengue occurred in America alone, and about ten thousand infected people had serious clinical symptoms often due to hemorrhagic complications. It is estimated that this disease is endemic in over 100 countries in Southeast Asia, the Americas, the western Pacific, Africa and as far as the Eastern Mediterranean regions [
 <xref rid="B68-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Todays, dengue, is one of the most important arboviruses capable of affecting humans and is widespread mainly in subtropical and tropical countries, with environmental playing an important role in the development and proliferation of 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> mosquitoes, i.e., main vectors transmitting the virus to humans. They are classified into four major subtypes namely DENV-1, DENV-2, DENV-3 and DENV-4 [
 <xref rid="B69-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. The initial infection of dengue virus is characterized by mild flu-like symptoms that subsequently can change to dengue fever. This can lead to development of the most hazardous form of dengue hemorrhagic fever (DHF) which is characterized by increased vascular fragility and coagulopathy. In severe cases, latter step can progress to dengue shock syndrome (DSS) and possibly cause death. The onset of disease is characterized by fever that is followed by headache, myalgia, gastrointestinal discomfort, rashes and hemorrhagic manifestations [
 <xref rid="B70-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Currently, there are no known specific treatments for dengue, and no document approving new drugs against this disease has been produced in recent times by official validation bodies such as the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA). The only therapeutic weapon consists of adequate and timely medical assistance with supportive therapies. People who heal, develop immunity for life, but only for the infectious serotype while only partial and transitory immunity develops to other serotypes. There have been several problems in developing vaccines that are able to immunize patients against DENV and, to date, various techniques have been used to develop vaccines potentially usable for this purpose. Some therapeutic agents have been considered for the treatment of dengue, primarily chloroquine [
 <xref rid="B71-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. This drug was found to inhibit the replication of the virus in vitro but does not have a great impact on the duration of the viral infection, in addition to presenting various side effects [
 <xref rid="B72-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Another drug tried to treat dengue was balapiravir, an inhibitor of hepatitis C virus replication in vivo. Although it appears to be well tolerated, balapiravir did not give very positive results, in fact it was not able to reduce plasma concentrations of cytokines or to ensure the time to eliminate the fever [
 <xref rid="B73-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>].
</p>
