<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nest predation by black rats in Hawaii can vary across the landscape from high to extremely low (e.g., 87% [Stone et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">1984</xref>] to 4% [Amarasekare, 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">1993</xref>]). Although dead biomass can subsidize predator populations, it does not contribute demographically to the dynamics of prey populations (Wolkovich et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). However, the availability of alternative resources, as live prey or as carrion, may be equally influential in supporting higher numerical response or population densities of invasive omnivores impacting populations of conservation concern (David et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Grendelmeier et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Holt &amp; Bonsall, 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Thus, determining the degree of scavenging versus predation is key to determining the impact of invasive rats on bird populations. Our paired diet and microbial forensics approach could be used to examine regional patterns of rat predation versus scavenging on native and introduced bird species, where particular focus would be on identifying localities where rats or other invasive omnivores are shown to be more likely to be consuming native birds through predation. Rat removal is extremely time and labor intensive; therefore, being able to target rat populations that are having direct impacts on native Hawaiian avifauna can be integral to their conservation. Specifically, researchers could collect fecal material from a variety of localities with nonlethal sampling or trapping. Our molecular‐based approaches could then be used to detect bird DNA in diet and look for the informative bacterial biomarkers of predation or carrion consumption, as identified here (carrion consumption biomarkers only) or in future research. Specific areas could then be targeted for validation with on ground observations, and appropriate management decisions could be made. Forensic genomic and microbiology methods applied in wildlife ecology have great potential to detect and quantify species interactions that are remote, rare, and challenging to measure. However, there is a need for basic research, such as the research we present here and those by others (Guo et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Pechal &amp; Benbow, 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), before this can be formalized as a widely accepted tool.
</p>
