<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Three samples of each light condition were used for total RNA extraction. The third leaves of 2-month-old plants were collected at the same time, after 6 h exposed to the light regime in a daily 12 h light cycle. Total RNA was isolated from 
 <italic>A. roxburghii</italic> leaves by using TRizol
 <sup>TM</sup> Reagent (Invitrogen
 <sup>TM</sup>) following manual instruction and then transcribed to cDNAs using RevertAid First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (ThermoFisher Scientific). The expressional levels of flavonoid biosynthesis-related genes (
 <italic>pal</italic>, 
 <italic>chs</italic>, 
 <italic>chi</italic>, and 
 <italic>fls</italic>) together with 
 <italic>actin</italic>2 as housekeeping gene was determined by real-time PCR system (Rotor-Gene Q, QUIAGEN). PCR was conducted by using SYBR Green (SsoAvanced Universal SYBR Green Supermix, BioRad) by following manufacturing instruction. PCR thermal program was performed as following: pre-denature 95 °C/3 min; 40 cycles of denature 95 °C/10 s; annealing 57 °C/20 s; extension 72 °C/20 s. DNA melting curve was determined by ramp heating from 65 °C to 95 °C and holding within 5 s at 95 °C for the analysis. The different relative level of gene expression between lighting conditions was determined based on the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) method [
 <xref rid="B66-plants-09-01344" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The experiment is considered to be different when processing ANOVA statistics of 03 replications with 
 <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05. Specific primers for analysis were described by Yang et al. [
 <xref rid="B67-plants-09-01344" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]; Zhang et al. [
 <xref rid="B68-plants-09-01344" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], and Zhang et al. [
 <xref rid="B69-plants-09-01344" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-plants-09-01344" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. The specific gene primers involved in flavonoids biosynthesis-related genes expression are presented in 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-plants-09-01344">Supplementary Table S1</xref>.
</p>
