<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nanoparticles have attained widespread attention for the development of green, facile, and sustainable synthesis of nanoparticles. Physicochemical methods such as direct precipitation, microwave, and hydrothermal methods are widely used [
 <xref rid="B132-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>,
 <xref rid="B133-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>]. Therefore, plant-derived polymers such as gums and mucilages are effectively used for the preparation and functionalization of nanoparticles. Mucilage used for the formulation of microparticles was also exploited in nano-formulations using vitamin D loaded nanoparticles on cress seed mucilage and gelatin. The prepared particles enhanced encapsulation efficiency (around 70%), with better in vitro release percentages of vitamin D in intestinal fluids and simulated gastroitestinal conditions [
 <xref rid="B130-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. Consequently, a study conducted by Pathak et al. [
 <xref rid="B134-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>] explained the achievement of using mucilage as an anionic ocular polymer for the synthesis of nanoparticles with a cationic polysaccharide polymer (chitosan). The antibacterial activity of the prepared sample was investigated against Gram-positive (
 <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>) and Gram-negative bacteria (
 <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> and 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>). This type of nanoparticle can be useful in the medicinal industry for sustaining the anti-bacterial effect of antibiotics. Furthermore, the negative charge of the mucilage was additionally subjugated through the preparation of cephalexin-loaded/basil seed mucilage-coated iron oxide (Fe
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub>) magnetic nanoparticles. The in vitro release of antibiotic (cephalexin) from the drug-loaded coated nanoparticles at pH 7.4 displayed biphasic form, starting with an initial quick release, then a continuous release phase. Apart from abusing the negative charge of the mucilage, phase inversion techniques and anti-solvent supercritical gas using supercritical carbon dioxide as an anti-solvent were applied for the preparation of mucilage nanoparticles loaded with the cytotoxic drug paclitaxel. The nanoparticles showed high drug loading above 75, and small particle size (around 200 nm) [
 <xref rid="B135-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. Mucilage contains flavonoids and polyphenolic contents. These compounds can efficiently bind zinc ions from an aqueous medium, and they function as stabilizing agents and natural reducers during the synthesis of nanoparticles. During the oxidation process, several carbohydrates and the counter acetate ions are also decomposed to produce high amounts of carbonate ions (Ag, Zn, Cu, and Co) and carbon dioxide; therefore, the binders can be removed [
 <xref rid="B136-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>,
 <xref rid="B137-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B139-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>,
 <xref rid="B140-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>]. 
</p>
