<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Currently, it can be observed that global sustainability challenges are all closely interconnected, such as pollution, climate change, biodiversity loss, poverty, energy, and food security. As stated by Liu et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>], only holistic and disruptive approaches integrating various components of human and natural systems are effective in identifying and proposing suitable solutions for these challenges, especially those related to research, development, and innovation (RD&amp;I) in interdisciplinary and transdisciplinary studies. To exemplify this systemic view, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> illustrates the Earth surface that, based on the “Dymaxion map” (the Fuller Projection Map), shows the planet as a continuum without splitting any continents, seas, and oceans, where cycles are integrated through flows of matter, energy, and information [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>]. Here, Brazil, China, the Caribbean, and Africa interact across space, time, and organizational levels in many ways. For instance, the expansion of soybean production aggravates deforestation in Brazil, but also provides food and feedstock to China. The food trade between both countries also affects other areas, including the Caribbean and Africa. Dust particles from the Sahara Desert, also increased due to unbalanced agricultural practices, can reach the Caribbean and have an impact on coral reefs and soil fertility, diminishing tourism in this region. In addition, nutrient-rich particles from Africa can reach Brazil, improving its forest productivity.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Representation of an integrated planetary flow system based on the Dymaxion map, emphasizing some coupled cycles related to food production and socio-environmental impacts among (1) Brazil, (2) China, (3) the Caribbean, and (4) the Sahara Desert.</p>
    <p>Adapted from [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41061_2017_182_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the Director-General of the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) of the United Nations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>], after years of progress, world hunger has increased since 2015. Around 60% of the world’s starving people are from countries affected by conflict and climate change, including northeast Nigeria, Somalia, South Sudan, and Yemen with 20 million people, often suffering extreme climatic events such as droughts and floods. Not surprisingly, some of the FAO’s top priorities for the next 2 years include topics such as sustainable agriculture, climate change mitigation and adaptation, water scarcity and support of subsistence rural practices, and fisheries and forestry [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>]. The challenges related to this demanding context can be intensified and better understood when taking into account that the world population is expected to increase by about 30% over the next 35 years, reaching more than 9.5 billion people in 2050 and 11.2 billion in 2100 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As pointed out by Xia et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>], the global food waste of approximately 1.3 billion tons per year is shocking in this context and, although it should be avoided or minimized, it cannot be completely prevented nowadays. Primary and secondary processing generates unpreventable food supply chain waste. This can be due to a number of factors along the supply chain, differing by the commodity and country in question. In general terms, developing countries such as some African countries suffer the greatest loss during the early, upstream part of the primary processing, corresponding to 75% of food losses during production and postharvest. Various initiatives, e.g., building better infrastructure through knowledge transfer (more efficient storage and transport technologies) and improving collaboration and market opportunities in the food supply chain could have a positive role. In industrialized countries, waste occurs especially in the consumption stage, accounting for 50% of overall loss of crops in some countries of North America, Europe, and Oceania. In this case, together with educational and cultural actions, other aspects such as developing legislation to make date labels more user-friendly for consumers (sell-by, best-before, and consume-by), redesigning packaging characteristics (avoiding the “buy 1 get 2” offers) and retailer marketing strategies should be considered [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is estimated that around 140 billion tons of biomass from the agricultural sector are generated every year in the world [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>], and a considerable part is recognized as waste and not conflicting with food availability, e.g., leaves, roots, stalks, bark, bagasse, straw residues, seeds, wood and animal residues. Using alternative strategies to avoid additional losses and produce several high value-added chemicals could minimize the volume of non-renewable materials used today (i.e., roughly 50 billion tons of fossil fuels), enough to greatly reduce greenhouse gas emissions and dependence on non-sustainable resources. Therefore, considering their available volume and practically low costs locally and globally, associated to rich function, structure and chemical heterogeneity, all agro-industrial waste should also be considered for their chemical and material potential, as well as a source of energy [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An important proposal related to waste hierarchy as a framework for residue management can be seen in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>], which was reformulated to include agro-industrial waste. In this case, the agro-industrial waste hierarchy has a different meaning from top to bottom, since all biomass is valued as raw material. ‘Prevention’ is an intrinsic part of optimized processes, avoiding overproduction. Therefore, the least probable option is ‘disposal’ as the supply chain is designed to attend sustainable consumption, using all bio-based material generated. Here, sustainable production also includes eco-efficiency, cleaner and green productivity, whereas sustainable consumption allows greener choices to be made by individuals based on eco-procurement, supply chain management, waste minimization, recycling, and resource efficiency measures. Both sustainable production and consumption comprises ‘life-cycle thinking’, aiming at preventing problems shifting from one life-cycle stage to another, one geographical area or environmental compartment to another.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The agro-industrial waste hierarchy modified from [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. The main idea is to promote sustainable production and consumption systems through zero-waste biorefinery
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41061_2017_182_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the most important and cited references highlighting the advances in genetics, biotechnology, process chemistry, and engineering that has helped establish a new manufacturing concept to convert renewable biomass into valuable fuels and products, known as biorefinery, was published by Ragauskas and collaborators in the mid-2000s [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. According to these authors and other researchers [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>], integrating biomass and biorefinery technologies has the potential to develop sustainable bio-based energy and materials leading to a new manufacturing paradigm (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Holistic biorefinery model integrating biomass, biofuel, biomaterials and bioenergy cycle, based on green and sustainable technologies in the scope of bioeconomy and circular economy. Updated and expanded from [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>, 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>]
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41061_2017_182_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In fact, this paradigm is currently connected to other strong concepts, i.e., bioeconomy and circular economy; the latter is described as an industrial system that is restorative by intention and design. This idea replaces the end-of-life notion with regeneration, focusing on the use of renewable energy, elimination of toxic chemicals, reutilization, return and eradication of “waste through the superior design of materials, products, systems, and business models” [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As can be noted, new generations of biorefinery combine innovative biomass resources from different origins, chemical extraction and purification and/or synthesis of biomaterials, biofuels and bioenergy via benign processes. From the very beginning, the identification and quantification of all potentially high value-added compounds that could be removed from the available renewable feedstocks requires another analytical approach, also connected to green chemistry [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
