<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Consistent with previous research results on other clonal plants [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], the AFLP results showed that the genetic diversity of 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic> was relatively low, and the average values of the Shannon information index (I) and percentage of polymorphic loci (PPL) in 17 populations were 0.035 and 6.79%, respectively (
 <xref rid="plants-10-00291-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). According to the previous research of our research group, 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic> has the characteristics of seed reproduction and rhizome asexual reproduction. In the process of upward expansion, sexual colonization was carried out at first, and then the ramets produced by clonal reproduction grew rapidly in the new habitat. In addition, although the offspring produced by sexual reproduction have higher genetic diversity, the efficiency of asexual reproduction is relatively high [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], so the expansion mode based on clonal reproduction is very important to the rapid occupation of the niche and the success of expansion. Due to the lack of meiosis mechanism, especially the basic stages such as hybridization and gene recombination, vegetative reproduction is expected to reduce genetic diversity. In the process of plant invasion, invasive plants, especially clonal plants, may maintain a low level of genetic diversity after gene drift during invasion [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], so genetic drift may be one reason for the low genetic diversity of the invasive population. In addition, studies on clonal plant species showed that ramets exhibit different phenotypes in different environments and thrive in different environments, leading to a serious reduction or lack of biological genetic diversity [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. AMOVA results showed that there was very little genetic variation in 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic>, and only 5% of the genetic variation came from within the population (
 <xref rid="plants-10-00291-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), which may be related to the rapid occupation of the habitat by a large number of clones after expansion and colonization. Similar to the genetic variation of 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic>, the results of studies on 
 <italic>A.donax</italic> and 
 <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> showed that the genetic variation is very small within the scope of invasion [
 <xref rid="B43-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. In addition, the study on 
 <italic>Capsella rubella</italic> showed that although the genetic variation is very low, plants can quickly produce phenotypic variation through the massive amplification of transposons, thus improving their adaptability [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. PCoA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00291-f001">Figure 1</xref>a) and clustering analysis (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-plants-10-00291">Figure S2a</xref>) indicated that there were significant genetic variations in different populations. In addition, we found that the genetic variation of different populations is basically distributed along the elevation gradient, which may be due to the influence of geographic distance formed by the elevation gradient.
</p>
