<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The healthy adult gut microbiota is composed primarily of the phyla Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes, and to a lesser extent the phyla Actinobacteria, Proteobacteria, and Verrucomicrobia [
 <xref rid="B30-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. As with any age-group, due to the extensive inter-individual variation, it has been virtually impossible to define the composition of the ‘healthy’ adult gut microbiota. However, the ‘enterotype’ concept was introduced in 2011 [
 <xref rid="B32-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]) when faecal metagenomes of individuals from America, Europe and Japan were found to be dominated by one of three different bacterial communities, namely 
 <italic class="italic">Bacteroides</italic> (enterotype 1), 
 <italic class="italic">Prevotella</italic> (enterotype 2) or 
 <italic class="italic">Ruminococcus</italic> (enterotype 3). The enterotype ‘concept’ has since been used in other studies when evaluating the gut microbiota as we will see further on, although further analysis has resulted in the identification of only two enterotypes, one of which is dominated by 
 <italic class="italic">Prevotella</italic> and the other by 
 <italic class="italic">Bacteroides</italic> which have been linked to long term carbohydrate-, or animal fat and protein-rich diets, respectively [
 <xref rid="B33-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. More recently, it has been suggested that 
 <italic class="italic">Prevotella</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Bacteroides</italic> should be interpreted as ‘biomarkers’ of diet, lifestyle and disease state given that gradients of both 
 <italic class="italic">Bacteroides</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Prevotella</italic> have been found within gut communities as opposed to distinct and consistent community taxa [
 <xref rid="B34-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. 
</p>
