<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Reports on the estimated number of species and strains in an individual have varied greatly but in a study examining the stability of the gut microbiota in 37 US adults over a five year period, Faith et al. [
 <xref rid="B35-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>] reported an average of 101 ± 27 species and 195 ± 48 strains in the faecal gut microbiota of each individual with family members sharing strains, which was not observed in unrelated individuals. However, other studies estimate the number of species to be greater than 1000 [
 <xref rid="B36-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. More recently, Forster et al. [
 <xref rid="B38-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>] presented the Human Gastrointestinal Bacteria Culture Collection which consisted of 737 whole-genome-sequenced bacterial isolates, representing 273 different species, including 105 novel species from 31 families found in the human gastrointestinal microbiota. The healthy adult microbiota has been shown to be stable over long periods of time [
 <xref rid="B35-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>] but can be influenced by a number of factors. These include geographical location [
 <xref rid="B24-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>] albeit diet would appear to be an important contributing factor in this regard [
 <xref rid="B40-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>], direct antibiotic usage [
 <xref rid="B43-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>], and indirectly by consumption of antibiotic containing animal derived products, such as beef and chicken as a result of their use in livestock production [
 <xref rid="B44-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>], non-antibiotic drugs [
 <xref rid="B45-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>], illness, injury [
 <xref rid="B46-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>] and hormonal changes [
 <xref rid="B48-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. The healthy gut microbiota is generally characterised by rich species diversity [
 <xref rid="B49-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>] which has been found to be reduced/altered in individuals with certain diseases, particularly those typified by a dysregulated immune response (as discussed further on). 
</p>
