<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In general, the elderly microbiota has been characterised by a decline in microbial diversity, an increase in the abundance of opportunistic pathogens and a decrease in species associated with short chain fatty acid (SCFA) production, in particular butyrate [
 <xref rid="B52-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. The inter-individual variation observed in the gut microbiota of adults is even greater in the elderly cohort. Indeed, while Bacteroidetes was found to be the dominant phylum in an elderly Irish cohort (age 65 years and older), the proportion of Bacteroidetes within individual composition datasets ranged from 3% to 92%, while the proportion of Firmicutes ranged from 7% to 94% [
 <xref rid="B53-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. Mariat et al. [
 <xref rid="B54-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] reported a change in the ratio of Firmicutes: Bacteriodetes with age, which was recorded as 0.4 in infants (3 weeks to 10 months old), 10.9 in adults (25–45 years old) and 0.6 in the elderly cohort (70-90 years), of which the latter two consumed an unrestricted Western-type diet. In a study involving 178 elderly Irish subjects (65–96 years), Claesson et al. [
 <xref rid="B55-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>] identified distinct microbiota composition groups as a result of residence location (community versus day-hospital versus rehabilitation versus long-stay residential care) which also overlapped with diet (low fat/high fibre versus moderate fat/high fibre versus moderate fat/low fibre versus high fat/low fibre, respectively). The gut microbiota of people in long-stay care was found to be significantly less diverse than that of healthy community dwellers, which was found to be more similar to healthy young adults. Furthermore, increased frailty as observed in the less healthy, long-stay subjects correlated with a loss of community-associated microbiota. Indeed, a distinct negative correlation between frailty and gut microbiota alpha diversity has been reported [
 <xref rid="B56-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. In the same study, the species 
 <italic class="italic">Eubacterium dolichum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Eggerthella lenta</italic> were found to be more abundant with frailty, while a 
 <italic class="italic">Faecalibacterium prausnitzii</italic> operational taxonomic unit (OTU) was less abundant in frailer individuals. Interestingly, 
 <italic class="italic">F. prausnitzii</italic> is an important butyrate producer [
 <xref rid="B57-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>], while 
 <italic class="italic">E. lenta</italic> is considered a pathogen [
 <xref rid="B58-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. More recently, Haran et al. [
 <xref rid="B59-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>] also reported lower abundances of butyrate-producing organisms in the microbiota of American elderly nursing home residents (age 65 years or older) consuming a low-fibre, typical nursing home diet with increasing frailty and higher abundances of recognised dysbiotic species. Increasing age was also associated with a decrease in the abundance of microbiome-encoded genes and pathways associated with vitamin B, a nitrogenous base and essential amino acid production. 
</p>
