<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Somatic Embryogenesis and Regeneration</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two types of embryogenic and nonembryogenic calluses were observed in different treatment combination (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The knotted and compact calluses were embryogenic calluses. Nonembryogenic calluses were agglomerate and fragile and their size was much larger than embryogenic calluses. Somatic embryos were observed in the outer layer of calluses about 2-3 weeks after the transfer of calluses to embryogenesis induction medium (PGRs-free). It is worth noting that different developmental stages of somatic embryos (from globular to cotyledonary stage) were simultaneously observed on a callus with embryogenic potential (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This observation suggests that development of somatic embryos is highly unsynchronized process in cumin. The long-term culture of embryo increased the number of embryos, but all embryogenic callus sections were not able to produce globular embryos. It is worth noting that researchers found that the embryogenic ability was not the same in calluses; only the globular calluses with soft surfaces had the embryogenic ability and rough, dry, and brittle calluses did not have embryogenic ability [
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">38</a>, 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">39</a>]. Some researchers reported that differentiation of somatic embryos in cumin was observed about two weeks after calluses transfer to PGRs-free MS medium [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>]. Results of another study suggested that somatic embryos appeared one week after the calluses transfer to a PGRs-free medium [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>]. The results of the present study indicated that, among the studied factors and their interactional effects on the percentage of callus formation, only explants effect was significant, so that cotyledon explant showed a superior response compared to hypocotyl explant (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The sensitivity of cultured cells and tissues to external hormones signaling can determine their embryogenic ability. Some researchers stated that somatic tissues of plants varied in terms of callus production and also cotyledon embryogenesis sensitivity was higher than hypocotyls [
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">40</a>, 
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">41</a>]. Results showed that the interactional effect of medium, landrace, and explant on the percentage of callus formation was not significant, while these significantly influenced callus perimeter and area (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>). It is worth noting that most perimeter and area of callus were observed in hypocotyl explant of North Khorasan on 0.5 mg/L 2,4-D + 0.1 mg/L Kin medium (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>). In order to study the effect of hypocotyl length and placement in the medium on callus properties such as callus perimeter, area, and density, Mansouri et al. [
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">42</a>] stated that the main and interactional effects of intended factors had no significant effect on the callus properties. In the present study, the overall assessments suggested that most callus dimensions (callus perimeter and area) have been obtained in 0. 5 mg/L 2,4-D + 0.1 mg/L Kin growth medium and also hypocotyl explant was superior in terms of the callus properties (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>). Since no induced calli with embryogenic potential and regeneration were observed in most treatment combinations, their analysis was excluded. Due to the fact that the data associated with the percentage of induced calli with embryogenic potential and regeneration percentages were not normally distributed and were not made normally distributed through data transformation methods, Kruskal-Wallis nonparametric method was used to analyze these. The results showed that the highest percentage of induced calli with embryogenic potential and regeneration was achieved in treatment combination of cotyledon explant of Golestan landrace in a medium containing 0.1 mg/L Kin (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">4</a>, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">5</a>, and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6</a>). In this study, it was observed that cotyledon was superior to hypocotyl in terms of induced calli with embryogenic potential and regeneration and hypocotyl showed no somatic embryogenesis response.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It should be noted that the level of endogenous hormones is one of the required factors affecting the responding ability of explants. Quantity and quality of endogenous hormones vary across explants, so they affect their responding potentiality [
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">43</a>, 
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">44</a>]. Some researchers believe that although the totipotency property is a very important trait in plants, cells only gain this ability under certain conditions. Even when it is thought that all cells are equally totipotent, the number of embryos as compared to the number of cells in cellular mass is insignificant. Thus, only a limited portion of the cell mass has the ability to produce somatic embryos, and this process is confined to the particular tissue of a genotype [
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>, 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">39</a>, 
  <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">45</a>]. Experiences gained through tissue culture indicate that there is a type of slope between different parts of the plant in response to embryogenesis, so that embryogenic ability has been high in embryo-derived tissues and low in hypocotyl and root [
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">41</a>]. Results of the present study suggest that somatic embryogenesis is highly dependent on the type of explant, genotype, and culture medium. Other researchers have also reported that the type and concentration of growth regulators and physiological state of explants are the most important factors, which play a role in somatic embryogenesis [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>, 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">39</a>]. In the present study, the level of percentage of induced calli with embryogenic potential and regeneration under the treatment of 0.1 mg/L Kin was significantly higher than other treatments, which suggest the role of cytokinin hormones in somatic embryogenesis (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">5</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is worth noting that, in the first embryogenesis experiment conducted on cumin, the role of cytokinin hormones for the occurrence of this process has been emphasized [
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>]. According to the results of the present study, although induced calli with embryogenic potential have been observed in other media containing hormone combination of auxin and cytokinin (0.5 mg/L 2,4-D + 0.1 mg/L Kin) or auxin alone (0.5 mg/L 2,4-D), the rate of regeneration in these was significantly lower than that in the medium containing cytokinin (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">5</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6</a>). It would be worth noting that induced calli with embryogenic potential were also observed in some treatment combinations containing 2,4-D in the present study (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Figure 5</a>). This process can be attributed to the key role of auxin in the induction of somatic embryogenesis which can directly or indirectly regulate embryogenesis process through affecting the internal metabolism of other phytohormones [
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">39</a>, 
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">46</a>]. It should be mentioned that, in the presence of 2,4-D, embryos were not able to pass through the globular stage to heart-shaped stage and then complete embryogenesis. The inhibitory effect of 2,4-D hormone was also reported in other plants belonging to Apiaceae family including carrot and celery [
  <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">47</a>]. It is worth noting that percentage of induced calli with embryogenic potential and the rate of regeneration have decreased in treatment combinations containing higher auxin concentration compared to treatment combinations containing lower auxin concentration (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">5</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6</a>). Higher concentration of auxin hormones in the culture medium resulted in the biosynthesis of hydrocarbons such as ethylene, which results in cells and plant organs getting old. In fact, auxin acts as an effective inducer of somatic embryogenesis whose reduction and omission from the culture medium resulted in developing somatic embryogenesis [
  <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">48</a>]. Therefore, researchers have recommended prevention from continued exposure to high levels of auxin during the somatic embryogenesis process [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>, 
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>]. Some researchers also believe that sometimes auxin in the culture medium is decomposed through photooxidation and leads to undesirable effects on the effectiveness of somatic embryogenesis through the production of unwanted compositions [
  <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">49</a>, 
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">50</a>]. It should be noted that plants in Apiaceae family such as cumin contain high levels of secondary metabolites and endogenous growth regulators, particularly auxin and cytokinins. Therefore, it is possible that high levels of endogenous regulators in the plant have caused the external use of them to be unnecessary [
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">51</a>]. Valizadeh et al. [
  <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">52</a>] have mentioned the occurrence of regeneration in some kinetin-free treatments as reasons for this claim. The researchers believe that the most important factor involved in differences between embryogenic and nonembryogenic cultures is their difference in terms of the level of endogenous hormones because these regulate explants differentiation processes in the media [
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">38</a>, 
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">53</a>]. In general, factors such as plant genetic properties, type of explants, the explant growth phase, and cells position in plant cultured tissue are effective for their somatic embryogenic ability.
 </p>
</sec>
