<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. In Vitro Rooting and Acclimatization</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results showed that the hormone treatment IAA (0.35 mg/L) + NAA (0.37 mg/L), as compared to other treatments, was superior in terms of rooting rate, the percentage of lateral root production, and survival rate of regenerated seedlings (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig7" href="#fig7">Figure 7</a>). According to these results, it can be said that IAA and NAA auxin have synergistic effects on properties related to rooting and act supplementally (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab5" href="#tab5">Table 5</a>). Ginger also was observed among medical plants, regenerated organs of which have produced roots under the application of IAA and NAA hormones [
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">54</a>]. Rooting in plants is usually induced in media containing auxin hormones [
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">54</a>]. In the present study, in the medium free of auxin, limited rooting was also observed which may be associated with plant genotypes and endogenous hormone levels (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab5" href="#tab5">Table 5</a>). It is worth noting that some researchers also reported that cumin regenerated seedlings have produced roots in the auxin-free medium, but roots produced in the growth medium containing IBA auxin were much more and stronger [
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">55</a>]. Other researchers reported that rooting in calluses obtained from hypocotyl of cumin has been significantly increased with an increase in concentration of NAA hormone [
  <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">52</a>]. Researchers found that the usage of IBA hormone to induce rooting in cumin is effective and reported that although the usage of PEG in the medium has led to decreased rooting in cumin, it has increased survival ability of regenerated plants [
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">55</a>]. The researchers believe that PEG has induced morphological and anatomical changes associated with increased viability and adaptability of plants [
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">56</a>, 
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">57</a>]. Since the survival rate of plants regenerated in the present study was lower than the rate observed by Tawfic and Noga [
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">55</a>], perhaps in addition to differences in the type of genotype, lack of PEG can be mentioned as another reason for it. One of the most important problems of micropropagation is the survival rate of the seedling during transferring to ex vitro conditions to acclimatization to the new climate in the greenhouse or field. The type of environment and pot soil are also factors affecting the establishment and the survival rate of regenerated seedlings [
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">55</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Generally, decreased survival rate of plants regenerated in tissue culture experiments can be attributed to different factors including low photosynthetic capacity resulting from the presence of sugar in the culture medium, low light, inadequate amount of CO
  <sub>2</sub>, and high relative humidity in the medium, which eventually undesirably affect the efficiency of the plant's photosynthesis and its survival rate [
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">58</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
