<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Chemical Characters</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antioxidant enzymes play a role in metabolizing reactive oxygen species and preventing damage due to oxidative stresses, auxin metabolism, cross-links in the cell wall, and response to environmental stresses [
   <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>, 
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">32</a>]. Results of the present study showed that level of catalase and ascorbate peroxidase enzymes in Golestan landrace was significantly much more than that in North Khorasan landrace (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2(a)</a>). The presence of catalase in plant cells plays an important role in increasing resistance to oxidative stresses. In addition to ascorbate peroxidase catalyzing the H
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub> reduction reaction, also this enzyme plays a role in many cellular processes such as auxin metabolism, cross-links in cellular wall, and response to environmental stresses [
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>, 
   <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>, 
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">32</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results suggested that, in terms of protein contents, there was no significant difference between the two landraces of Golestan and North Khorasan (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2(b)</a>). The protein content of cells is regarded as one of the most important factors of cell growth [
   <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>]. Proteins play important physiological roles such as structural and enzymatic roles on the level of cells and it is not possible for cells to continue growing in the long run without these materials. Any factors that inhibit protein synthesis lead to cell growth failure [
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">32</a>, 
   <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">34</a>]. Proline is also the key amino acid that develops stress tolerance in plants through protection and sustainability of cell membranes [
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">32</a>, 
   <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">34</a>]. The results showed that Golestan landrace had higher proline content than North Khorasan landrace (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2(b)</a>). Proline in addition to its osmotic role is effective as a source of nitrogen for rapid growth of plant cells [
   <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>, 
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">35</a>]. There was no significant difference between the two landraces in terms of the amount of essential oil (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2(c)</a>). In terms of chemical structure, the essential oils are not homogeneous and have different compositions. Dubey et al. [
   <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">36</a>] reported significant differences between the Indian landraces of cumin in terms of the amount of essential oil. 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3"> Table 3</a> represents GC-MS profile of essential oil of two studied cumin landraces. The results showed that the identified compounds in their essential oil may be classified into five organic groups including terpenic hydrocarbons, alcohols and phenols, aldehydes, epoxides, and other compositions (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It should be mentioned that the two groups of terpenic hydrocarbons and aldehydes were the highest existing compositions in the essential oil of the studied cumin. In a study on the chemical compositions of the landraces of Indian cumin, the main ingredients of essential oil of terpenic hydrocarbons and aldehydes were reported [
   <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>]. In the present study, the extracted essential oil from Golestan landrace contained 62.27% terpenic hydrocarbons, while the amount of these compositions was 51.14% in North Khorasan landrace (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>). It would be worth noting that two compositions of alpha-thujene and gamma-terpinene were the main constituent elements of terpenic hydrocarbons and their expanding range varied from 6.91% to 24.8%. Alpha-thujene was significantly higher in North Khorasan landrace, while the number and amount of other identified terpenic hydrocarbons in Golestan landrace were higher compared to North Khorasan landrace (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>). In the present study, a total of 45 compositions were identified by GC-MS based analysis of cumin essential oil, representing 98.42 to 99.15% of the total compositions (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>). In other studies, some researchers reported that the total numbers of identified compositions in Egyptian landraces, Indian landraces, Chinese landraces, and Tunisian landraces were 41, 29, 19, and 38, respectively [
   <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>]. Discrepancies in the results reported on chemical compositions of cumin essential oil may be due to factors including the sensitivity of the system used or method adapted for analysis. The chemical compositions of the essential oil of medicinal plants are affected by numerous internal and external factors including plant genotypes, geographical location, climatic conditions, growth season, and essential oil extraction method [
   <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>, 
   <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">37</a>]. Analysis of essential oils of the two landraces showed that, among the identified compositions in the essential oils, cumin aldehyde has been the main constituent of cumin essential oil whose value in the Northern landrace has been significantly higher compared to Golestan landrace (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>). Cumin aldehyde smells good and is the main reason for the aromatic smell of cumin seeds and spice. This substance is commercially used in perfume and in hygienic and cosmetic industries. It is worth noting that, in local and international markets, cumin seeds containing more cuminaldehyde are preferred to cumin seeds containing terpinene [
   <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Somatic Embryogenesis and Regeneration</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two types of embryogenic and nonembryogenic calluses were observed in different treatment combination (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The knotted and compact calluses were embryogenic calluses. Nonembryogenic calluses were agglomerate and fragile and their size was much larger than embryogenic calluses. Somatic embryos were observed in the outer layer of calluses about 2-3 weeks after the transfer of calluses to embryogenesis induction medium (PGRs-free). It is worth noting that different developmental stages of somatic embryos (from globular to cotyledonary stage) were simultaneously observed on a callus with embryogenic potential (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This observation suggests that development of somatic embryos is highly unsynchronized process in cumin. The long-term culture of embryo increased the number of embryos, but all embryogenic callus sections were not able to produce globular embryos. It is worth noting that researchers found that the embryogenic ability was not the same in calluses; only the globular calluses with soft surfaces had the embryogenic ability and rough, dry, and brittle calluses did not have embryogenic ability [
   <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">38</a>, 
   <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">39</a>]. Some researchers reported that differentiation of somatic embryos in cumin was observed about two weeks after calluses transfer to PGRs-free MS medium [
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>]. Results of another study suggested that somatic embryos appeared one week after the calluses transfer to a PGRs-free medium [
   <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>]. The results of the present study indicated that, among the studied factors and their interactional effects on the percentage of callus formation, only explants effect was significant, so that cotyledon explant showed a superior response compared to hypocotyl explant (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The sensitivity of cultured cells and tissues to external hormones signaling can determine their embryogenic ability. Some researchers stated that somatic tissues of plants varied in terms of callus production and also cotyledon embryogenesis sensitivity was higher than hypocotyls [
   <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">40</a>, 
   <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">41</a>]. Results showed that the interactional effect of medium, landrace, and explant on the percentage of callus formation was not significant, while these significantly influenced callus perimeter and area (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>). It is worth noting that most perimeter and area of callus were observed in hypocotyl explant of North Khorasan on 0.5 mg/L 2,4-D + 0.1 mg/L Kin medium (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>). In order to study the effect of hypocotyl length and placement in the medium on callus properties such as callus perimeter, area, and density, Mansouri et al. [
   <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">42</a>] stated that the main and interactional effects of intended factors had no significant effect on the callus properties. In the present study, the overall assessments suggested that most callus dimensions (callus perimeter and area) have been obtained in 0. 5 mg/L 2,4-D + 0.1 mg/L Kin growth medium and also hypocotyl explant was superior in terms of the callus properties (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>). Since no induced calli with embryogenic potential and regeneration were observed in most treatment combinations, their analysis was excluded. Due to the fact that the data associated with the percentage of induced calli with embryogenic potential and regeneration percentages were not normally distributed and were not made normally distributed through data transformation methods, Kruskal-Wallis nonparametric method was used to analyze these. The results showed that the highest percentage of induced calli with embryogenic potential and regeneration was achieved in treatment combination of cotyledon explant of Golestan landrace in a medium containing 0.1 mg/L Kin (Figures 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">4</a>, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">5</a>, and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6</a>). In this study, it was observed that cotyledon was superior to hypocotyl in terms of induced calli with embryogenic potential and regeneration and hypocotyl showed no somatic embryogenesis response.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It should be noted that the level of endogenous hormones is one of the required factors affecting the responding ability of explants. Quantity and quality of endogenous hormones vary across explants, so they affect their responding potentiality [
   <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">43</a>, 
   <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">44</a>]. Some researchers believe that although the totipotency property is a very important trait in plants, cells only gain this ability under certain conditions. Even when it is thought that all cells are equally totipotent, the number of embryos as compared to the number of cells in cellular mass is insignificant. Thus, only a limited portion of the cell mass has the ability to produce somatic embryos, and this process is confined to the particular tissue of a genotype [
   <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>, 
   <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">39</a>, 
   <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">45</a>]. Experiences gained through tissue culture indicate that there is a type of slope between different parts of the plant in response to embryogenesis, so that embryogenic ability has been high in embryo-derived tissues and low in hypocotyl and root [
   <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">41</a>]. Results of the present study suggest that somatic embryogenesis is highly dependent on the type of explant, genotype, and culture medium. Other researchers have also reported that the type and concentration of growth regulators and physiological state of explants are the most important factors, which play a role in somatic embryogenesis [
   <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>, 
   <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">39</a>]. In the present study, the level of percentage of induced calli with embryogenic potential and regeneration under the treatment of 0.1 mg/L Kin was significantly higher than other treatments, which suggest the role of cytokinin hormones in somatic embryogenesis (Figures 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">5</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is worth noting that, in the first embryogenesis experiment conducted on cumin, the role of cytokinin hormones for the occurrence of this process has been emphasized [
   <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>]. According to the results of the present study, although induced calli with embryogenic potential have been observed in other media containing hormone combination of auxin and cytokinin (0.5 mg/L 2,4-D + 0.1 mg/L Kin) or auxin alone (0.5 mg/L 2,4-D), the rate of regeneration in these was significantly lower than that in the medium containing cytokinin (Figures 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">5</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6</a>). It would be worth noting that induced calli with embryogenic potential were also observed in some treatment combinations containing 2,4-D in the present study (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Figure 5</a>). This process can be attributed to the key role of auxin in the induction of somatic embryogenesis which can directly or indirectly regulate embryogenesis process through affecting the internal metabolism of other phytohormones [
   <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">39</a>, 
   <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">46</a>]. It should be mentioned that, in the presence of 2,4-D, embryos were not able to pass through the globular stage to heart-shaped stage and then complete embryogenesis. The inhibitory effect of 2,4-D hormone was also reported in other plants belonging to Apiaceae family including carrot and celery [
   <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">47</a>]. It is worth noting that percentage of induced calli with embryogenic potential and the rate of regeneration have decreased in treatment combinations containing higher auxin concentration compared to treatment combinations containing lower auxin concentration (Figures 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">5</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6</a>). Higher concentration of auxin hormones in the culture medium resulted in the biosynthesis of hydrocarbons such as ethylene, which results in cells and plant organs getting old. In fact, auxin acts as an effective inducer of somatic embryogenesis whose reduction and omission from the culture medium resulted in developing somatic embryogenesis [
   <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">48</a>]. Therefore, researchers have recommended prevention from continued exposure to high levels of auxin during the somatic embryogenesis process [
   <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>, 
   <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>]. Some researchers also believe that sometimes auxin in the culture medium is decomposed through photooxidation and leads to undesirable effects on the effectiveness of somatic embryogenesis through the production of unwanted compositions [
   <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">49</a>, 
   <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">50</a>]. It should be noted that plants in Apiaceae family such as cumin contain high levels of secondary metabolites and endogenous growth regulators, particularly auxin and cytokinins. Therefore, it is possible that high levels of endogenous regulators in the plant have caused the external use of them to be unnecessary [
   <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">51</a>]. Valizadeh et al. [
   <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">52</a>] have mentioned the occurrence of regeneration in some kinetin-free treatments as reasons for this claim. The researchers believe that the most important factor involved in differences between embryogenic and nonembryogenic cultures is their difference in terms of the level of endogenous hormones because these regulate explants differentiation processes in the media [
   <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">38</a>, 
   <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">53</a>]. In general, factors such as plant genetic properties, type of explants, the explant growth phase, and cells position in plant cultured tissue are effective for their somatic embryogenic ability.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. In Vitro Rooting and Acclimatization</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results showed that the hormone treatment IAA (0.35 mg/L) + NAA (0.37 mg/L), as compared to other treatments, was superior in terms of rooting rate, the percentage of lateral root production, and survival rate of regenerated seedlings (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig7" href="#fig7">Figure 7</a>). According to these results, it can be said that IAA and NAA auxin have synergistic effects on properties related to rooting and act supplementally (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab5" href="#tab5">Table 5</a>). Ginger also was observed among medical plants, regenerated organs of which have produced roots under the application of IAA and NAA hormones [
   <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">54</a>]. Rooting in plants is usually induced in media containing auxin hormones [
   <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">54</a>]. In the present study, in the medium free of auxin, limited rooting was also observed which may be associated with plant genotypes and endogenous hormone levels (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab5" href="#tab5">Table 5</a>). It is worth noting that some researchers also reported that cumin regenerated seedlings have produced roots in the auxin-free medium, but roots produced in the growth medium containing IBA auxin were much more and stronger [
   <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">55</a>]. Other researchers reported that rooting in calluses obtained from hypocotyl of cumin has been significantly increased with an increase in concentration of NAA hormone [
   <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">52</a>]. Researchers found that the usage of IBA hormone to induce rooting in cumin is effective and reported that although the usage of PEG in the medium has led to decreased rooting in cumin, it has increased survival ability of regenerated plants [
   <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">55</a>]. The researchers believe that PEG has induced morphological and anatomical changes associated with increased viability and adaptability of plants [
   <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">56</a>, 
   <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">57</a>]. Since the survival rate of plants regenerated in the present study was lower than the rate observed by Tawfic and Noga [
   <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">55</a>], perhaps in addition to differences in the type of genotype, lack of PEG can be mentioned as another reason for it. One of the most important problems of micropropagation is the survival rate of the seedling during transferring to ex vitro conditions to acclimatization to the new climate in the greenhouse or field. The type of environment and pot soil are also factors affecting the establishment and the survival rate of regenerated seedlings [
   <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">55</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Generally, decreased survival rate of plants regenerated in tissue culture experiments can be attributed to different factors including low photosynthetic capacity resulting from the presence of sugar in the culture medium, low light, inadequate amount of CO
   <sub>2</sub>, and high relative humidity in the medium, which eventually undesirably affect the efficiency of the plant's photosynthesis and its survival rate [
   <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">58</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Evaluation of the Relationship between Chemical Composition and Somatic Embryogenesis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The processes of cell differentiation and somatic embryogenesis are highly dependent on the genetic and chemical composition of plants. Measurement of chemical parameters can be used as a marker to assess somatic embryogenesis [
   <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>, 
   <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>]. Studies suggest that antioxidant enzymes such as catalase and ascorbate peroxidase play an important role in the growth and differentiation of plant cells and tissues and their high activities are associated with cell differentiation process [
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>, 
   <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>, 
   <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>]. The results of the present study showed that the contents of catalase and ascorbate peroxidase and the percentage of induced calli with embryogenic potential in Golestan landrace were significantly higher compared to North Khorasan landrace. Since somatic embryogenesis is heavily dependent on the genotype, one of the factors which are effective in somatic embryogenesis differences among the studied cumin landraces may be significant differences in their chemical compositions [
   <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>, 
   <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">59</a>, 
   <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">60</a>]. Studies have shown that ascorbate peroxidase is required to maintain size and shape of cells during embryogenesis. It also plays an important role in the formation of lignin and protects embryo cell walls [
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>, 
   <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">61</a>]. Researchers have also stated that variations in the content of antioxidant enzymes correlate with the regeneration of plants [
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>, 
   <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>, 
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">32</a>]. It is worth noting that catalase and ascorbate peroxidase have been used as markers to study the developmental stages of somatic embryos and their highest activity level was observed in torpedo stage of the somatic embryogenesis [
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>]. In the present study, Golestan landrace, in addition to antioxidant enzymes, had much more proline and protein. These compositions may be considered as other genetic properties of this landrace which lead to increased somatic embryogenesis in it. It should be mentioned that increased somatic embryogenesis through proteins and amino acids is due to the fact that the compositions easily supply the source of nitrogen for the cell growth [
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">35</a>]. Proline plays an important role in somatic embryogenesis and stress conditions in plants [
   <a rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60">62</a>]. For example, studies have shown that the proline-rich protein is required in the cell wall of
   <span class="italic"> Arabidopsis</span> for correctly placing cell plate during cytokinesis process for embryos development. The carrot cell wall protein has been secreted into the growth medium and regulates somatic embryogenesis development [
   <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">63</a>]. Researchers observed that protein content of cells in preembryogenesis calluses was higher than that in embryogenic calluses. In fact, as the callus enters somatic embryogenesis stage, its protein level decreases, which indicates protein consumption for somatic embryogenesis development. Studies have shown that cells use their protein content to initiate embryogenesis, so it can be said that the cellular protein content is among genetic properties that lead to increased somatic embryogenesis [
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>, 
   <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">34</a>]. As somatic embryogenesis initiates and develops, an increase in protein consumption has also been reported in other studies [
   <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>, 
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>]. The cultured cells are naturally able to synthesize all their necessary amino acids; however, embryogenesis and regeneration levels in cumin can be increased by adding proline and other amino acids to the culture medium, and this ability can be applied in gene transfer programs [
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">35</a>, 
   <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">59</a>]. Results of the essential oil analysis showed that phytochemical profiles of the two landraces of Golestan and North Khorasan have significant differences with each other, which is another confirmation of the existence of genetic differences between them. For example, the number of terpenic hydrocarbons was higher in essential oil of Golestan landrace than that in North Khorasan landrace (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>). Researchers have reported that the genetic characteristics are regarded as terpenic hydrocarbons, which could have a positive effect on somatic embryogenesis in plants [
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>]. The results of this study suggest that one of the main factors affecting the occurrence of somatic embryogenesis in Golestan landrace is the phytochemical properties, especially the high terpenic hydrocarbons content. It should be noted that North Khorasan landrace has higher alcoholic and phenolic compositions and these compositions along with other factors may lead to decreased somatic embryogenesis in it. How phenolic compositions affect the induction and development of somatic embryo is not clear yet, but these compositions may be involved in the metabolism of endogenous hormones such as auxin [
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>, 
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>]. Phenolic compositions prevent the growth and development of somatic embryogenesis from going beyond the globular stages. Embryos formed in the presence of phenolic compositions lack sufficient amounts of sucrose to carry out the metabolic activity and thus stop in the globular stage. It should be noted that the inhibitory effect of phenolic compositions due to their high concentration in cells leads to protein deposition, enzyme deactivation, or membrane damage [
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>, 
   <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">64</a>]. However, in some studies, it has been reported that phenols usually have a reinforcing effect on somatic embryogenesis, but it is possible that phenols interaction with alcohols and other phytochemical compositions of essential oil inhibits their reinforcing effect on embryogenesis. Results of the present study showed that essential oil percentage of North Khorasan was higher than Golestan landrace; however, the difference was not significant. Also, it should be noted that cuminaldehyde content, the most primarily essential oil composition of cumin, was significantly higher in North Khorasan landrace than in Golestan landrace. A high percentage of essential oil and more cuminaldehyde content in North Khorasan landrace may be regarded as two of the factors affecting the lack of its somatic embryogenesis. As no study has been reported on the effect of cuminaldehyde on somatic embryogenesis in cumin, the final decision on this issue requires further studies. Results of the present study showed that variation in the genetic and chemical structure of cumin landraces is among the important factors determining somatic embryogenesis process and can be used as a marker for assessment of occurrence of this process.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. Evaluation of Somaclonal Variation in the Regenerated Plants in Comparison with the Mother Plants</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Somaclonal variation is a common process in plants cell and tissue culture and was firstly introduced by Larkin and Scowcroft [
   <a rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63">28</a>]. This process has led to changes in nuclear and cytoplasmic genomes and is of genetic and epigenetic nature [
   <a rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63">28</a>, 
   <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">29</a>]. Ten primers were initially used, 7 of which generated informative and reproducible bands (6–10 bands per primer), ranging from approximately 200 to more than 1000 bp in size. The 7 primers generated a total of 52 scorable bands, with an average of 7.4 per primer, which were polymorphic across all the analyzed in vitro regenerated plantlets originating from cotyledons of the mother plant (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig8" href="#fig8">Figure 8</a>). In the present study, RAPD markers suggested polymorphism bands between regenerated plants of Golestan landrace and seed plants (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig8" href="#fig8">Figure 8</a>). It may be said that the variation is associated with the heterozygous nature of the cumin landrace and its pollination system. Some studies suggest somatic variations in plants regenerated from tissue culture and some others suggest genetic stability [
   <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>–
   <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">67</a>]. Bakhtiar et al. [
   <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">67</a>], in their study on the genetic diversity of
   <span class="italic"> Thymus</span> regenerated seedlings and seedlings from mother plant, found that RAPD marker suggests the presence of polymorphism bands among them.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">They believed that the observed variation may be related to
   <span class="italic"> Thyme</span> pollination system. They also stated that the optimized protocol for
   <span class="italic"> Thyme</span> regeneration is a useful tool to protect germplasm and it does not seem that interferences have been made in the genetic uniformity of the regenerated plants [
   <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">67</a>]. Analysis of
   <span class="italic"> Arabidopsis</span> regenerated using RAPD and RFLP markers indicated the lack of diversity in the DNA profile of regenerated plants [
   <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">68</a>]. Evaluation of somatic variation frequency is valuable for any regeneration system, but the variation has been studied in few regenerated plants [
   <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">43</a>]. Although molecular markers have been used as a molecular tool to evaluate somaclonal variation, with regard to the fact that morphological and cytogenetic diversity cannot be detected at DNA level, there is a little doubt about their effectiveness [
   <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">29</a>]. In regenerated plants, changes in DNA methylation levels are considered as another source of somaclonal variation. It is believed that the occurrence of somaclonal variation resulting from DNA methylation, especially when auxin is consumed, is more than somatic variation due to changes in the DNA sequence [
   <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">69</a>, 
   <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">70</a>]. It is also well known that increasing numbers of subcultures increases the likelihood of somaclonal variation [
   <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">70</a>]. Genetic uniformity of produced plants through tissue culture depends on several factors; the most important ones are the propagation method and genotype [
   <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">51</a>, 
   <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">67</a>]. As compared to classical methods of vegetative propagation, the regenerated plants from calluses, depending on the species, origin, and culture age, may show varying amounts of structural or physiological disorders. Although these disorders seem inappropriate at first, since a limited number of the above-mentioned plants have desirable characteristics missing in the main plants, breeders will use this genetic variation in breeding programs [
   <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">51</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
