<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Gene therapy aims at regulating cells’ apoptosis and function at the level of genes to treat disease. Most cancer-related gene therapy introduced exogenous DNA segments or delivered siRNA or miRNA into target cells to regulate DNA expression (Fitzgerald et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Wang, Yu, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0134" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Lima et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Till November 2017, almost 2600 gene therapy clinical trials had been completed and about 85% of these trials used a virus as vectors or naked/plasmid DNA (Ginn et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). However, The clinic applications are limited because of the drawbacks of nucleic acids. The free nucleic acid in blood could be degraded by various cells (reticuloendothelial system, mononuclear phagocyte system) and biomolecules (nucleases). The size of plasmid DNA could hinder it into cells (Zhou, Liu, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0152" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Several non-viral vectors were fabricated to deliver nucleic acid, including cationic polymers like polylysine (PLL), poly(ethyleneimine) (PEI), PAMAM, PEG, CS, cationic lipids (Chen, Yue, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), inorganic NPs (gold, silica, iron oxide and quantum dot) (Zhou, Liu, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0152" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In many types of research, gene therapy cooperated with PTT to anti-cancer relying on nano delivery systems (Kim et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Wang, Yu, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0134" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Chu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Knockdown of BMPR1a in breast cancer cells through Adenovirus-mediated RNA interference was reported to suppress the production of RANKL via p38 pathway and inhibit cancer-induced osteoclast genesis (Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0075" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). However, few delivery systems of optimizing gene delivery to stop the ‘vicious circle’ were available. Actually, the aforementioned nanomaterials or nanotechnology can be applied to optimize the relevant DNA/RNA delivery to hinder osteolysis.
</p>
