<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">The cultivation of herbal plants in hilly areas generates good business possibilities for local drug development organizations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. Under traditional medicinal practices, such type of herbal medicines were commonly implemented by general people in small quantities but in recent times large demand for such plant species is generated due to its extended commercialization and subsequent exploitation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. Now, extinction of such plant species by human interferences is estimated 100–1000 times faster than natural extinction and became a big threat for natural bio-resources [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. Already wild population of many such plant species including 
 <italic>Swertia Chirayita</italic> are reduced to a large extent due to developmental activities of Himalayan region. Due to multiple applications as traditional medicinal drug, the demand of the plant has been largely increased for both national and international trading and it causes rapid depletion of the plant wild populations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Unlikely the wild medicinal plants have been extensively collected by untrained workers from the wild state. Such unskilled practices comes up with removal of whole plants, bulbs, rhizomes, tubers and roots before planting seeds and hence diminishes possibilities of regeneration of same plant species in the environment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. On the other side, over-exploitation practices of these species from the natural habitat caused substantial depletion of bio-resources and gradual loss of other associated species. Due to that fact, Indian National Medicinal Plant Board considered the plant among priority plant to support its conservation (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nmpb.nic.in" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.nmpb.nic.in</ext-link>). Hence proper conservation practices of such critically endangered medical plant became essential to ensure its sustainability. The strategies like micropropagation, cryopreservation, utilization of suitable bioreactor systems which supports modern plant tissue culture techniques, commercial productions and conservation of such endangered herbs, can play effective role to improve such situation. In vitro efficient culture technique like micropropagation has received increased attention in recent years as most feasible method for mass proliferation of such endangered medicinal plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>]. In order to endorse extended production and ex situ conservation of 
 <italic>S. chirayita</italic>, Balaraju et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>] tried to upgrade the procedure for fast micropropagation by implanting explants of shoot tips from in vitro growing seedling. In recent times, in vitro propagation using somatic embryogenesis gained immense attention as most necessary technique for rapid development of uniform plants for investigation and also for its extended production [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>]. The technique can be ideally used for formation of artificial seeds, as a complementary to the natural seeds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. For ideal preservation of critically endangered medicinal plant like 
 <italic>S. chirayita</italic>, Kumar and Chandra, [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] developed most efficient plant regeneration protocol through induction of somatic embryo and formation of artificial seeds using in vivo leaf explants. Above all, spreading awareness about scientific protection, conservation and management of endangered medicinal plants among herbal plant collectors was already started from forest authority [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. To ensure sustainable harvesting of such herbs, policies of rotational harvesting from demarcated areas have been also considered by concern agencies.
</p>
