<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>
  <bold>Background:</bold>
  <italic>Haemonchus contortus</italic> is an important pathogenic nematode parasite and major economic constraint of small ruminants in tropics and subtropics regions. This review is an attempt to systematically address the; (a) efficacy of different plants against 
  <italic>H. contortus</italic> by 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
  <italic>in vivo</italic> proof; (b) toxicology, mechanism of action, and active phyto-compounds involve in anti-haemonchiasis activity; (c) and comparative analysis of plant species evaluated both 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
  <italic>in vivo</italic>. 
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Methods:</bold> Online databases (Google Scholar, PubMed, Scopus, and ScienceDirect) were searched and published research articles (1980–2020) were gathered and reviewed. 
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Results:</bold> A total of 187 plant species were reported belonging to 59 families and 145 genera with Asteraceae and Fabaceae being frequently used. Out of the total plant species, 171 species were found to be evaluated 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> and only 40 species 
  <italic>in vivo</italic>. Twenty-four species were commonly evaluated for 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
  <italic>in vivo</italic> anti-haemonchiasis activity. Among the reported assays, egg hatching test (EHT) and fecal egg count reduction (FECR) were the most widely used assays 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
  <italic>in vivo</italic>, respectively. Moreover, sheep were the frequently used experimental model 
  <italic>in vivo</italic>. After comparative analysis, 
  <italic>Lachesiodendron viridiflorum</italic>, 
  <italic>Corymbia citriodora</italic>, 
  <italic>Calotropis procera</italic>, and 
  <italic>Artemisia herba-alba</italic> were found highly effective both 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
  <italic>in vivo</italic>. 
  <italic>L. viridiflorum</italic> inhibited enzymatic activities and metabolic processes of the parasite and was found to be safe without toxic effects. 
  <italic>C. citriodora</italic> was moderately toxic 
  <italic>in vivo</italic>, however, the plant extract produced promising nematicidal effects by causing muscular disorganization and changes in the mitochondrial profile. Additionally, 
  <italic>C. procera</italic> and 
  <italic>A. herba</italic>
  <italic>-alba</italic> despite of their high anti-haemonchiasis activity were found to be highly toxic at the tested concentrations. 
  <italic>C. procera</italic> caused perforation and tegumental disorganization along with adult worm paralysis. Nineteen compounds were reported, among which anethole and carvone completely inhibited egg hatching 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> and significantly reduced fecal egg count, decreased male length, and reproductive capacity of female 
  <italic>in vivo</italic>. 
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Conclusion:</bold> This review summarized different medicinal plants owing to nematicidal activities against 
  <italic>H. contortus</italic> eggs, larvae, and adult worms. Plants like 
  <italic>L. viridiflorum, C. citriodora, C. procera,</italic> and 
  <italic>A. herba-alba</italic>, while compounds anethole and carvone having promising nematicidal activities and could be an alternative source for developing novel drugs after further investigation.
 </p>
</abstract>
