<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The amino acid cysteine is the precursor of sulphur-containing biomolecules like Fe-S clusters, modified tRNAs, thiamine, biotin, and glutathione, which are essential components in bacteria for fitness and virulence. Moreover, in pathogens possessing long latent phases such as 
 <italic class="italic">Trichomonas vaginalis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Mycobacterium tuberculosis,</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella enterica serovar</italic> Typhimurium (hereafter 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic>), sulphur-containing biomolecules are pivotal in surviving the hostile oxidative environment created by the host defences
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">1–4</sup>
 </xref>. Interestingly, studies in macrophages as well as mouse models have demonstrated that the deletion of those genes involved in sulphur metabolism reduces both virulence and survival of 
 <italic class="italic">M. tuberculosis</italic>, especially during chronic infection
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">1</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">2</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">4–6</sup>
 </xref>. While mammals use sulphur-containing amino acids like methionine and cysteine from diet to fulfil sulphur supply, bacteria actively transport sulphate and thiosulphate and reduce sulphate to sulphide in a highly demanding energetic process. To this scope, O-acetylserine (OAS), synthesised by serine acetyl transferase (SAT), incorporates sulphide to produce cysteine in a β-replacement reaction catalysed by the pyridoxal 5'-phosphate (PLP)-dependent enzyme OAS sulfhydrylase (OASS). OASS is a well-studied enzyme that exists in two isoforms, namely OASS-A, -coded by 
 <italic class="italic">cysK,</italic> and OASS-B, coded by 
 <italic class="italic">cysM</italic>. The reaction mechanism of both isoforms is of a ping-pong type, in which OAS binds to the internal aldimine linkage between enzyme and PLP, forming an α-aminoacrylate intermediate with the release of acetate. In the second half reaction, bisulphide binds as the second substrate to the α-aminoacrylate and cysteine is released
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">1</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">7</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">8</sup>
 </xref>.
</p>
