<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We applied a pairwise sampling technique to conduct a comparative study in the southern European limit of this IAS. We identify 19 couples of 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> dominated forests and native forests. A total of 38 phytosociological relevés (vegetation plots) were performed in a non-tree-lined row to avoid edge effects and detect only the real influence of the alien species on the understory layer, within an area of at least 100 m
 <sup>2</sup>, with a clear dominance of 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> or the native forests species (Braun-Blanquet cover-abundance values from 3 to 5), with an average age of at least 20 years assessed by photo-interpretation of 1994, 2000, 2006 geo-referenced images available on the Geo-portale Nazionale (
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.pcn.minambiente.it/GN/accesso-ai-servizi/servizi-di-visualizzazione-wms" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.pcn.minambiente.it/GN/accesso-ai-servizi/servizi-di-visualizzazione-wms</uri>). The vegetation survey was conducted according to the phytosociological methods [
 <xref rid="B51-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. In each plot, for each vascular plant taxa recorded according to the vegetation structure, a cover-abundance value was given, following a seven-grade scale of abundance and dominance [
 <xref rid="B52-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. The vegetation layers considered were three, defined as tree layer (height &gt; 7 m), shrub layer (height 20 cm–7 m), and herb layer (height &lt; 20 cm). The nomenclature of the vascular species follows the check-list of Italian flora [
 <xref rid="B53-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and the check-list of the vascular flora alien to Italy [
 <xref rid="B13-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The life forms of the species follow Flora d’Italia [
 <xref rid="B54-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Data on Competitive, Stress-Tolerant and Ruderal (CSR) strategies sensu Grime [
 <xref rid="B33-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] for the herbaceous species were partly available from the online databases BiolFlor [
 <xref rid="B55-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], database of the Czech flora and vegetation [
 <xref rid="B56-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], and from Hunt et al. [
 <xref rid="B57-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. For 8 taxa, information on the CSR strategies follows specific literature reference: 
 <italic>Bellevalia romana</italic> (L.) Sweet from Astuti et al. [
 <xref rid="B58-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], 
 <italic>Arundo donax</italic> L., 
 <italic>Asparagus acutifolius</italic> L., 
 <italic>Rubia peregrina</italic> L., 
 <italic>Olea europaea</italic> L., 
 <italic>Orobanche minor</italic> Sm., 
 <italic>Pistacia terebinthus</italic> L. from Benhamiche-Hanifi et al. [
 <xref rid="B59-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>], 
 <italic>Umbilicus horizontalis</italic> (Guss.) DC. from Bocchieri and Iiriti [
 <xref rid="B60-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. For the identification of the nemoral species of each relevé, we considered the syntaxonomic attribution of the species, according to the Prodrome of the Italian Vegetation [
 <xref rid="B61-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], as present on the updated site of the Italian Botanical Society (
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.prodromovegetazioneitalia.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.prodromovegetazioneitalia.org/</uri>), with references to that of the European vegetation [
 <xref rid="B62-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Nemoral species are those herbaceous species that are diagnostic of forest classes according to the syntaxonomic system, e.g.,: 
 <italic>Querco roboris-Fagetea sylvaticae</italic> class. Those herbaceous species, expressed in weighted percentage values for each plot, are linked to forest environments and are indicators of environmental quality.
</p>
