<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The fresh rhizomes of three mango ginger (
 <italic>C. amada</italic>) accessions (ZO45, ZO89, ZO114) in comparison with one turmeric (
 <italic>C. longa</italic>) accession (ZO138) from the collection of the GRC UT were analyzed by GC-TOF-MS. A total of 122 VOCs were tentatively identified, of which 73 compounds were significantly different and cause of observed within/between-species variation. α-Santalene, β-caryophyllene, trans-α-bergamotene, teresantalol, cuparene, β-bisabolene, (E)-γ-bisabolene, (Z)-α-bisabolene, and α-funebrene were major VOCs contributing to the differentiation of 
 <italic>C. amada</italic> and 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> genotypes. Major VOCs contributed variation within 
 <italic>C. amada</italic> genotypes were 1,8-cineole, α-humulene, α-zingiberene, β-sesquiphellandrene, β-caryophyllene, β-sesquiphellandrene, γ-curcumene, β-curcumene, γ-amorphene, β-caryophyllene, ar-turmerone, and (E)-γ-atlantone. The significant differences regarding identified VOCs among three 
 <italic>C. amada</italic> accessions were higher compared with differences detected between 
 <italic>C. amada</italic> and 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> accessions. In total, 54 compounds among three 
 <italic>C. amada</italic> samples and 30 compounds between 
 <italic>C. amada</italic> and 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> samples were significantly different. The result reflects the existing chemical variation within each genotype rather that each genotype is a separate chemotype. Considering the utilization of the plant and the plant-based alternative products used in ethnic medicine of Myanmar, 
 <italic>C. amada</italic> can also be a potential resource for future research with ample medicinal, pharmaceutical, and chemical applicability. The geographical distribution of 
 <italic>C. amada</italic> species can influence not only the morphological features but also the presence or absence of secondary metabolites, their amount in different tissues (rhizome, steam, leaf, flower), genotypes, and populations. This is a considerable gap for future research in this direction.
</p>
