<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the small gas molecule hydrogen sulfide (H
 <sub>2</sub>S) has long since been thought to be toxic, evidence shows that H
 <sub>2</sub>S is the third endogenous gaseous transmitter besides nitric oxide (NO) and carbon monoxide.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>
 </sup> H
 <sub>2</sub>S functions in a majority of physiological processes in animals, including neuronal excitability, vasorelaxation, anti-inflammatory response, smooth muscle relaxation, and blood pressure regulation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>
 </sup> Recently, the positive effect of H
 <sub>2</sub>S in improving the ability of plants to adapt to multiple environmental stimuli has also been reported.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>
 </sup> In addition, H
 <sub>2</sub>S acts as a critical signal in response to abiotic stress, modulating processes such as stomatal closure, iron availability, leaf senescence, osmotic stress, heat shock, and hypoxia stress.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>
 </sup> Cystathionine β-synthase (CBS, EC4.2.1.22) and cystathionine γ-lyase (CSE, EC 4.4.1.1) are mainly used by mammalian cells for the synthesis of H
 <sub>2</sub>S. CBS hydrolyses 
 <sc>l</sc>-cysteine to 
 <sc>l</sc>-serine and CSE hydrolyses l-serine to H
 <sub>2</sub>S, pyruvate, and ammonia.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>
 </sup> In plants, H
 <sub>2</sub>S generation is mainly related with the pyridoxal 5′-phosphate (PLP)-dependent 
 <sc>d</sc>/
 <sc>l</sc>-cysteine desulfhydrases (
 <sc>d</sc>/
 <sc>l</sc>-CDs) enzymes. Meanwhile, another PLP-dependent enzyme (β-cyanoalanine synthase) could convert cysteine and cyanide to H
 <sub>2</sub>S and β-cyanoalanine.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>
 </sup> However, H
 <sub>2</sub>S is consumed by the cysteine synthesis complex in the synthesis of 
 <sc>l</sc>-cys from O-acetyl serine which is catalyzed by O-acetylserine-thiol-lyase.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> DES1 encodes the cytosolic 
 <sc>l</sc>-CDes, which modulates endogenous H
 <sub>2</sub>S levels in the cytosol.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>
 </sup> Abscisic acid (ABA), which triggers stomatal closure, induces a 
 <italic>DES1</italic> expression in 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> guard cells. ABA treatment could not close the stomata in isolated epidermal strips of the 
 <italic>des1</italic> mutant, and this defect was restored because of exogenous H
 <sub>2</sub>S addition.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>
 </sup> These data demonstrate the essential function of H
 <sub>2</sub>S in response to the environmental stress in the plant.
</p>
