<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Each compound investigated was applied by immersing louse eggs on hair in the fluid for 30 min after which the eggs were subjected to the slip-peel test. The effects of the chemicals were evaluated both with and without a wash off procedure. Materials compatible with water were simply rinsed off but oily materials required a shampoo wash. The initial measure of effectiveness was whether a compound or mixture produced a lower Peak Force measurement than was observed with a simple hair conditioner (
 <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burgess, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lapeere et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ortega-Insaurralde et al., 2014</xref>). Each material was initially tested using just one batch of 10 louse eggs. If it showed a consistency of effect, i.e., all the readings were similar without any extremely high Peak Force outliers, further batches were tested. In some cases, e.g., dipentaerythrityl pentaisononanoate (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3" class="xref">Fig. 3</xref>) and isononyl isononanoate + PEG-8 dimeticone phosphate (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">Fig. 4</xref>), there was considerable variability in effect so these chemical entities were rejected and no further batches were tested. Other examples, e.g., octyl palmitate and isopropyl myristate, were less clear, because some Peak force readings were quite low but other eggshells remained fixed to the hair so strongly that the hair broke before the eggshell started to move. For materials with these characteristics no more than two batches of louse eggs were investigated. All “formulated” mixtures, i.e., where potential active substances were incorporated into either existing preparations like 4% dimeticone gel or into new mixtures such as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">Figs. 4</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5" class="xref">5</xref>, between two and five batches of eggs were used according to the consistency or variability of effect on the Peak Force measurement.
</p>
