<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We here demonstrate how reverse docking can be used to assess large numbers of anti-mycobacterial NPs to suggest key interactions and imply a mode of action. Our approach was to examine the literature for NPs with anti-mycobacterial activities, but whose targets had not been previously characterized. Then, proteins known to be targeted by established anti-mycobacterial drug leads were screened using the NP chemical structures. The aim was to identify natural product interactions whose docking energies were as good as, or superior to, the established drug lead. The “druggable” mycobacterial targets ClpP1P2, DprE1, InhA, KasA, PanK, PknB and Pks13, were all known to play important roles in maintaining mycobacterial viability. ClpP1P2 carries out the energy-dependent degradation of abnormal proteins within the cells during in vitro growth and infection [
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. DprE1 is a decaprenylphosphoryl-d-ribose oxidase involved in the biosynthesis of decaprenylphosphoryl-
 <sc>d</sc>-arabinose, an essential component of the mycobacterial cell wall and thus is essential for cell growth and survival [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. InhA is a known target of isoniazid, a first-line anti-tuberculosis drug essential for the synthesis of mycolic acids. KasA is one of the enzymes responsible for the elongation of C16–26 fatty acyl primers in the FAS-II system for mycolic acid production of 
 <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B59-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Pantothenate kinase (PanK) is a ubiquitous and essential enzyme that catalyzes the first step of the coenzyme A biosynthetic pathway [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. PknB is a very well-characterized mycobacterial serine/threonine-protein kinase that determines cell shape, morphology and possibly cell division [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Pks13 is a polyketide synthase that catalyzes the final condensation step in mycolic acid biosynthesis and is therefore essential for mycobacterial growth [
 <xref rid="B60-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>].
</p>
