<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The herbaceous perennial legume 
 <italic>Mimosa pudica</italic> was first introduced into Taiwan Province of China in 1645 as an ornamental plant (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2003</xref>) and it has been dispersed throughout the tropical and subtropical China. It is a plant serving as valuable bio-resource for various uses, such as green manure, fodder crops, honey source, as well as a medicine used in zoster therapy (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Wang, 2014</xref>) and treating kidney disease. However, this naturalized plant is highly invasive causing considerable ecological damage e.g., by affecting the growth of grass lawns and as a common exotic weed in rice paddy fields (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Guan et al., 2006</xref>). Therefore, 
 <italic>M. pudica</italic> and 
 <italic>M. diplotricha</italic> another invasive plant without history record, are considered to be serious pests widely dispersed in waste-grounds and city suburbs of China. It has been estimatied that the access to compatible rhizobial strains in new environments is a critical factor for the successful establishment of exotic nodulating legumes (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Parker et al., 2007</xref>). For getting the compatible symbionts in the introduced region. The invasive legumes, such as 
 <italic>Mimosa</italic> species (see above) and the invasive papilionoid legume 
 <italic>Dipogon lignosus</italic> (L.) Verdc., may have been introduced into their invasive environments together with the symbionts from their original region (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2014</xref>). Or they may form the symbiosis with rhizobia adapted to the local environment and adopted the corresponding symbiotic genes through lateral gene transfer, like the cases of chickpea (
 <italic>Cicer arietinum</italic> L.) rhizobia in China (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Previously, 
 <italic>Burkholderia</italic> spp. and 
 <italic>Cupariavidus taiwanensis</italic> have been isolated from 
 <italic>Mimosa</italic> species grown in China (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2001</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2005a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). In which 
 <italic>C. taiwanensis</italic> was recognized as native to Taiwan and the 
 <italic>Burkholderia</italic> spp. were estimated as rhizobia introduced together with the host plants (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2005a</xref>). Furthermore, preference for 
 <italic>Cupriavidus</italic> by 
 <italic>M. pudica</italic> and 
 <italic>Burkkholderia</italic> by 
 <italic>M. pigra</italic> in Taiwan (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2005b</xref>), while 
 <italic>Cupriavidus</italic> by 
 <italic>M. diplotricha</italic> and 
 <italic>Burkkholeria</italic> by 
 <italic>M. pudica</italic> in Yunnan (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2012</xref>) demonstrated that both the host plants and the geographic regions affected the symbiosis combination between the legume and the rhizobia in the introduced regions. However, no soil conditions were considered in these previous studies about the 
 <italic>Mimosa</italic> rhizobia in China.
</p>
