<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIALS AND METHODS</div>
 <sec id="sec2-1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Preparation of essential oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The plant was collected from herbal farm, Mysore, India. Leaves are washed thoroughly, dried in shade, and powdered. The essential oil was obtained from hydrodistillation using a Clevenger-type apparatus in accordance with the method recommended by the European Pharmacopoeia.[
   <a rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref39">39</a>] The extraction was performed for 180 min and 200 g of powder yield the 1000 μL of oil. The oil obtained was stored at 4°C and protected from light for subsequent use and chemical analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry analysis of oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The GC-MS analyses were performed in EI mode (70 eV) with an Agilent 7890 GC system, equipped with model 5975 mass selective detector (Agilent Technologies, USA). SGE BPX5 fused silica capillary columns (30 m × 0.32 mm i.d., 0.25 µm film thickness) were employed for separation; the column oven temperature was raised linearly from 80°C (hold for 2 min) to 280°C (hold for 5 min) at 20°C/min. Helium was used as carrier gas at constant flow of 1.2 mL/min. The samples were analyzed in splitless mode at injection temperature of 250°C, EI source temperature 230°C, and quadrupole analyzer at 150°C, ionization current at 235 eV.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Culture and preparation of 
   <span class="italic">Fusarium sporotrichioides</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">F. sporotrichioides</span> Microbial Type Culture Collection 1894[
   <a rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref40">40</a>] was used as the test organism and was obtained from the Department of Microbiology, Defence Food Research Laboratory, Mysore. The fungus was purified and harvested at 37°C on potato dextrose broth (PDB). The spores concentration was adjusted to 5 × 10
   <span class="sup">5</span> CFU/mL using a hemocytometer.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Minimum inhibitory concentration and minimum fungicidal concentration</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) determination was performed using 96-well microtiter plates. The 
   <span class="italic">F. sporotrichioides</span> fungal inocula in 96-well microtiter plates were treated with MPE at different concentrations and incubated for 24 h; then, absorbance was measured at 575 nm. Fluconazole was used as the standard and also to compare the cell viability under inverted microscope. The minimum fungicidal concentration (MFC) was regarded as the lowest concentration that prevented growth of the fungus following 72 h incubation at 28°C in a fresh potato dextrose agar (PDA) plate, indicating more than 99.5% killing of the original inocula.[
   <a rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref41">41</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Scanning electron microscopy</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 24 h old fungal culture on PDB treated with MPE at varied concentrations of control, MIC and MFC were used for scanning electron microscope (SEM) observation. The 
   <span class="italic">F. sporotrichioides</span> cells were fixed in glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M PBS for 30 min, washed with 0.1 M PBS, and dehydrated by immersing in ice-cold ethanol for 10 min. The dehydrated samples were smeared on silver stub like a thin film and were coated by cathodic spraying (Polaron gold). The SEM observations were made using a ZEISS Instrument (EHT = 15.00 kV, signal A = VPSE G3).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Release of cellular constituents</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The release of cellular constituents into the supernatant was measured following Paul 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
   <a rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref42">42</a>] method. The 2 days old mycelia from PDB were collected by centrifugation at 4000 g for 20 min, washed 3 times, and resuspended in 100 mL phosphate buffer saline (pH 7.0). The resulting suspension was treated with MPE with MIC and MFC for 0, 30, 60, and 120 min. Then, 2 mL of sample was collected and centrifuged at 12,000 g for 2 min, and 1 mL of supernatant was used to measure the cellular constituents in spectrophotometer at 260 nm.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurement of extracellular pH</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The extracellular pH was measured by Shao 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
   <a rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref43">43</a>] method. The extracellular pH of 
   <span class="italic">F. sporotrichioides</span> was determined by eutech pH meter. The fungal suspension 10
   <span class="sup">5</span> CFU/mL were added to 20 mL PDB and incubated in a moist chamber at 28°C ± 2°C for 2 days. The mixtures were centrifuged at 4000 g for 20 min, and the resulting pellet was collected, washed for 2–3 times with sterilized double-distilled water, and resuspended in 20 mL sterilized double-distilled water. After the addition of the MPE, the extracellular pH was determined.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Determination of lipid content</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Total lipid content of 
   <span class="italic">F. sporotrichioides</span> cells with the MPE at various concentrations (control, MIC, and MFC) was determined using phosphovanillin method.[
   <a rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref44">44</a>
   <a rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref45">45</a>] The 2-day-old mycelia from 50 mL PDB were collected and centrifuged at 4000 g for 10 min. Then, the samples are lyophilized. About 0.1 g of dry mycelia were homogenized with liquid nitrogen and extracted with 4.0 mL of methanol: chloroform: water mixture (2:1:0.8, v/v/v) with vigorous shaking for 30 min. The resulting sample was centrifuged at 4000 g for 10 min. The lower phase containing lipids was mixed with 0.2 mL saline solution and centrifuged at 4000 g for 10 min. To the lipid mixture add 0.2 mL chloroform and 0.5 mL of H
   <sub>2</sub> SO
   <sub>4</sub> and warm in a boiling water bath for 10 min. After that, 3 mL phosphovanillin was added and shaken vigorously, and then incubated at room temperature for 10 min. The absorbance was measured at 520 nm. Cholesterol was used as a standard.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
