<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Fusarium sporotrichioides</span>, a filamentous fungi of the section sporotrichiella, necrotrophic pathogen associated with 
  <span class="italic">Fusarium</span> head blight of cereals.[
  <a rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref1">1</a>
  <a rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref2">2</a>
  <a rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref3">3</a>] 
  <span class="italic">F. sporotrichioides</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Fusarium acuminatum</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Fusarium Sambucinum</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Fusarium poae</span> are predominant species widespread in the soil and on plants, throughout the cold and cool regions of the world. They invade cereal crops and are responsible for the production toxic metabolites such as type A trichothecenes: T-2 toxin, HT-2 toxin, T-2 tetraol, T-2 triol, scirpentriol (STO), and diacetoxyscirpenol which may contaminate animal and human food.[
  <a rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref4">4</a>
  <a rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref5">5</a>
  <a rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref6">6</a>
  <a rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref7">7</a>
  <a rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref8">8</a>
  <a rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref9">9</a>
  <a rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref10">10</a>
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">11</a>
  <a rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref12">12</a>
  <a rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref13">13</a>] Trichothecene is sesquiterpenoid highly toxic; T-2 toxin and HT-2 toxin are potent inhibitor of protein synthesis and are highly cytotoxic to eukaryotes.[
  <a rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref14">14</a>] T-2 toxin, HT-2 toxin found to be contaminants in wheat, maize, barley, oats, rice, beans, and soybeans as well as in some cereal-based products and have played a role in plant diseases. These toxins are an important agricultural problem due to their detrimental effects on both human and animal health.[
  <a rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref15">15</a>
  <a rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref16">16</a>
  <a rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref17">17</a>] Trichothecene has acute symptoms in man associated with high-level intake of trichothecenes include necrotic lesions of the oral cavity, esophagus, and stomach, nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, diarrhea, dizziness, headache, and marked leukopenia.[
  <a rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref18">18</a>
  <a rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref19">19</a>] Within the outbreak of the so-called “alimentary toxic aleukia” documented.[
  <a rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref18">18</a>
  <a rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref20">20</a>] Therefore, control of 
  <span class="italic">F. sporotrichioides</span> growth in agricultural products is essential to reduce food-borne illness. Several low-molecular organic acids antifungal chemical have been used to control the growth of 
  <span class="italic">F. sporotrichioides</span> during grain storage. These chemical fungicides show serious health issues in humans and animals due to their toxicity by the migration of chemical residue into food chain and they also produce resistance in fungi.[
  <a rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref21">21</a>
  <a rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref22">22</a>
  <a rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref23">23</a>] Hence, natural plant components may act as an alternative to these chemical preservatives and fungicides.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plants essential oils have long been researched for their antibacterial, antifungal, antiviral, and antioxidant properties. Essential oils and their principle compounds, such as menthol, eugenol, cinnamaldehyde, thymol, carvacrol, terpineol, and citral, have been considered to be effective against many filamentous fungi. The several studies on essential oils cinnamon, citral, 
  <span class="italic">Litsea cubeba</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Zingiber officinale</span>, clove, eucalyptus, anise, peppermint, spearmint, and camphor oils show inhibitory activity against pathogenic microorganisms. cinnamon essential oil showed potent antifungal activity against mycotoxigenic fungi 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus flavus</span>,[
  <a rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref24">24</a>] citral, octanal, and a-terpineol volatile oils against 
  <span class="italic">Geotrichum citri-aurantii</span>[
  <a rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref25">25</a>] and clove and Cinnamon oils were found to be effective against 
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> which is responsible for aflatoxin production in maize under favorable conditions.[
  <a rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref26">26</a>
  <a rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref27">27</a>
  <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">28</a>] Growth inhibition and morphological alterations of 
  <span class="italic">Fusarium verticillioides</span> and inhibition of fumonisin B1 by 
  <span class="italic">Z. officinale</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span> L., cinnamon essential oil reported by Xing 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 2014,[
  <a rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref29">29</a>] Yamamoto-Ribeiro 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 2013[
  <a rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref30">30</a>] da Silva Bomfim 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 2015.[
  <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">31</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Mentha piperita</span> essential oil (MPE) is commonly known as peppermint. Leaves of mint plant are aromatic perennial herb cultivated in most part of the world. It is used as folk medicine and frequently used in herbal tea and for culinary purpose to add flavor and aroma. The essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> rich in menthol, l-menthone, pulegone, piperitone, menthol acetate, piperitenone menthone, carvone, menthofuran, isomenthone, menthyl acetate, isopulegol, menthol, 3-octanol, pulegone; hence, it also used as natural antioxidants.[
  <a rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref32">32</a>
  <a rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref33">33</a>
  <a rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref34">34</a>
  <a rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref35">35</a>] MPE have shown potent inhibitory activity against several microorganisms such as 
  <span class="italic">Penicillium digitatum</span>, 
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus niger</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</span>
  <span class="italic">Mucor</span> spp., and 
  <span class="italic">Fusarium oxysporum</span>,[
  <a rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref33">33</a>
  <a rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref36">36</a>] further MPE reported as antifungal agent for several mycotoxigenic speceies by Silva 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 2012;[
  <a rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref37">37</a>] 
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">A. parasiticus</span>, Freire 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., in 2012[
  <a rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref38">38</a>] reported against 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus ochraceous</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Colletotrichum gloeosporioides</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Colletotrichum musae</span>, 
  <span class="italic">F. oxysporum</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Fusarium semitectum</span>. Currently, it has been widely used in cosmetic, food and pharmaceutical industries no studies of which we are aware have reported the effects of MPE on 
  <span class="italic">F. sporotrichioides</span>. Therefore, the present study was undertaken to evaluate the effects of MPE against the growth of 
  <span class="italic">F. sporotrichioides</span>. Morphological alteration was investigated by scanning electron microscopy.
 </p>
</sec>
