<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Orange is one of the most important fruit tree crops in the world. Brazil and China are the world’s leading producers of orange, and the production in 2017/18 is about 16.03 and 7.30 million tons, respectively [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-24-00499" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. ‘Newhall’ navel orange (
 <italic class="italic">Citrus sinensis</italic>) is broadly cultivated in the Gannan region of Jiangxi province in China, with a total annual output of more than one million tons. ‘Gannanzao’ is a new variety selected from the bud mutation of ‘Newhall’ navel orange, which has the characteristics of early maturity (the harvest time is one month earlier than the latter), excellent flavor, and easy peeling [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-24-00499" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-24-00499" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. A large amount of peel is produced during orange processing. It contains several functional natural products, such as EO, pectin, carotenoids, and hesperidin, etc., which are important raw materials in the chemical and pharmaceutical industries [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-24-00499" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Exploring efficient methods to extract EO from orange peel and provide value-added products has become an important part of the citrus processing industry. In the present study, we optimized the hydrodistillation conditions for extracting EO from ‘Gannanzao’ orange peel by response surface design and identified its components. Our previous research [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-24-00499" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] found that ‘Newhall’ navel orange EO has a significant inhibitory effect on human lung cancer cell line A549 and prostate cancer cell line 22RV-1. As well as we know, there are no literature reports on extraction and anticancer activities of ‘Gannanzao’ orange essential oil (GOEO). A preliminary study of its proliferation and migration effects on HepG2 hepatocellular carcinoma cells and HCT116 colon cancer cells was carried out. Our research results will provide information for efficient extraction of GOEO and potential utilization of it as a source of natural anticancer agent.
</p>
