<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">To offer some context to the meaning of PHC teamwork in Poland, it is important to acknowledge the cultural context in which medical and nursing professionals have practiced in recent decades. Today, nursing in Poland is an autonomous profession. Two decades ago, however, nurses were considered “auxiliary” medical personnel. The 
 <italic>Act on Professional Self-governance of Nurses and Midwives</italic> passed in 1991 established a single independent professional organization to regulate nursing and midwifery care. The structure of nursing self-governance consists of the Central Council of Nurses and Midwives at the national level and Regional Chambers of Nurses and Midwives at the provincial level. The 
 <italic>Act on the Occupations of Nurses and Midwives</italic> from 1996 helped to further establish the professional autonomy of nurses and midwives in Poland. Today, Polish nurses are educated consistent with the European Union (EU) requirements. Polish nurses and midwives have access to three levels of educational preparation: Bachelor of Nursing, Master of Nursing, and a PhD in Nursing Science. Additionally, postgraduate education prepares nurses for work in various specialized sectors of the healthcare system [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Moreover, some nurses in Poland hold specialty certifications, including PHC nurses. These nurses have completed a postgraduate qualifying course in family nursing or another field relevant to primary health care, such as pediatric nursing, community nursing, or care for chronically ill or disabled patients. A typical PHC nurse is prepared to plan and carry out a comprehensive nursing care plan within the scope of nursing practice with consideration of the point of care, patient health status, gender, level of patient abilities, and age (except for newborns and infants under 2 months of age who receive primary care exclusively from physicians). In sum, PHC nurses are well prepared to provide health education, nursing assessments and care, and coordinate diagnostic, therapeutic, and rehabilitation services.
</p>
