<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Analysis based on SIP is a typical strategy for bacterial community study that combines culture-dependent and culture-independent approaches. First, cultivation is necessary to obtain molecular markers (DNA, RNA, proteins, or PLFA) that are labeled with a stable isotopic element (e.g., 
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C, 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N, and 
 <sup class="sup">18</sup>O). The labeled molecular markers can then be analyzed by 16S rRNA gene sequencing (clone library or NGS), metagenomic analysis, metatranscriptomic analysis, and mass spectrometer (MS) analysis. These methods can be used to generate data to reveal the bacterial community and activity. SIP analysis is a powerful tool for linking microbial species and metabolism (Dumont and Murrell, 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>). By using DNA-SIP in combination with 16S rRNA gene clone libraries and T-RFLP analysis, Redmond and Valentine (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>) demonstrated that bacteria in the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Colwellia</italic> were active in ethane and propane oxidation in oil polluted deep-sea water plumes. Mason et al. (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014b</xref>) used surface sediments polluted by the DWH oil spill and 
 <sup class="sup">14</sup>C-labeled hydrocarbons to perform mineralization experiments. They successfully found that the key hydrocarbon degradation pathway by sediment microbes was as follows: propylene glycol, dodecane, toluene, and phenanthrene. By monitoring the biodegradation efficiency of 
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C-labeled different hydrocarbons (aliphatic and aromatic), Gutierrez et al. (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>) applied 16S rRNA gene-based NGS and qPCR detection to reveal the activity of bacterial communities. The results indicated that the different bacterial phyla were responsible for the degradation of different hydrocarbons. For instance, bacteria in the genera 
 <italic class="italic">Alcanivorax</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Marinobacter</italic> were found to be enriched in the experimental setups with the addition of aliphatic hydrocarbons, whereas 
 <italic class="italic">Alteromonas, Cycloclasticus</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Colwellia</italic> dominated the experimental setups supplemented with polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon.
</p>
