<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Additionally, several publications point out the importance of the modifications of the lateral chains of RG-I in the firmness of fruit (
 <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gross, 1984</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Orfila et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ng et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cornuault et al., 2018</xref>). RG-I consists of a backbone of rhamnose and galacturonic acid, with side chains of arabinan, galactan, and arabinogalactan, which can be linked to hemicelluloses/celluloses (
 <xref rid="ref128" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vidal et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Guillon et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <xref rid="ref134" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wang et al. (2018)</xref> indicated that RG-I content is three-fold the RG-II in the fruit cell wall, and RG-I represented the most important branched pectic component of the primary cell wall and middle lamella (
 <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Goulao et al., 2012</xref>). β-galactosidases and α-arabinosidases have been described as enzymes that remove galactan and arabinan side chains of RG-I in fruit ripening (
 <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brummell, 2006</xref>). In avocados, the pectin distribution has not been described. However, RG-I has been recently associated with the softening in avocados, where galactose (the main component of the side chains of this polysaccharide) amount decreases as firmness decreases. Moreover, β-galactosidase activity increases during softening (
 <xref rid="ref119" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tateishi et al., 2001</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Defilippi et al., 2018</xref>). Another component of the RG-I side chains, arabinose, also showed a decrease during softening and an α-L-arabinofuranosidase activity increase have been reported (
 <xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kamiyoshihara et al., 2018</xref>). Additionally, the rhamnose content remained constant suggesting that the changes observed in RG-I correspond to a disassembly of the RG-I side chains and not to its backbone structure (
 <xref rid="ref111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sakurai and Nevins, 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Defilippi et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
