<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Glucans are glucose homopolysaccharides, while mannans are mannose homopolysaccharides [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Hydrophilic groups like OH, COOH, and NH
 <sub>2</sub> groups can form a bioadhesive layer with epithelial and mucous membrane tissues [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The most common constituent of polysaccharides is 
 <sc>d</sc>-glucose; however, 
 <sc>d</sc>-fructose, 
 <sc>d</sc>-galactose, 
 <sc>l</sc>-galactose, 
 <sc>d</sc>-mannose, 
 <sc>l</sc>-arabinose, and 
 <sc>d</sc>-xylose are also frequent, some monosaccharide derivatives found in polysaccharides include the amino sugars (
 <sc>d</sc>-glucosamine and 
 <sc>d</sc>-galactosamine) as well as their derivatives (
 <italic>N</italic>-acetylneuraminic acid and 
 <italic>N</italic>-acetylmuramic acid), and simple sugar acids (glucuronic and iduronic acids). Polysaccharides can be differentiated according to the nature of monosaccharides components, length of chains, and the branching of those chains. The glycosidic linkage through the anomeric carbon atom between the glycosidic bond donor and the acceptor form either linear or branched chains, which make them distinguished from proteins and peptides since the latter has only linear chains. Polysaccharides naturally have storage properties like starch or structural properties, e.g., cellulose (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), which provides physical structure and stability [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Polysaccharides can also be classified based on polyelectrolyte to positively charged polysaccharides (chitosan) and negatively charged polysaccharides (alginate, heparin, hyaluronic acid, and pectin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Another primary components of the cell surface and the cell-extracellular matrix (ECM), Glycosaminoglycans (GAGs), they were studied extensively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], heparin, heparan sulfate, hyaluronan, chondroitin sulfate, dermatan sulfate, and keratan sulfate are the most important GAGs polysaccharides in mammalian tissues [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], some biological importance of these GAGs will be explained in this review.
</p>
