<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The variability of green ham weight, and ham weight after first salting and at the end of the salting period showed to be associated with the same markers, indicating a pleiotropic effect of these mutations. The LSM estimated for these markers were concordant among the measured traits, with the same genotypic class displaying higher estimated LSM for the weights of the fresh thigh and the ham after first salting and at the end of salting. This pattern was expected given the degree of shared variability between these three traits, as demonstrated by their high and positive phenotypic correlations, indicating that the higher the weight of the fresh thigh, the heavier are the same hams after first salting and at the end of salting period. Ham weights at the first salting and at the end of salting were significantly associated with the two markers ASGA0026341 and WU_10.2_7_118557013. An additive effect was found for both these markers, which are located in intergenic regions on SSC5 and SSC7, respectively. This is not surprising, since the literature indicates that the majority of GWAS peaks are located in non-coding or intergenic regions [
 <xref rid="B44-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], and may therefore be a signal indicating that the found association may be due to causal mutations in closely located genes or to mutations in a still unknown gene. Among the genes located near WU_10.2_7_118557013 is 
 <italic>Calmodulin 1</italic> (
 <italic>CALM1</italic>), which encodes for one of three calcium-binding calmodulin proteins. 
 <italic>CALM1</italic> mediates the control of a large number of enzymes, ion channels, aquaporins, and other proteins through calcium-binding, and controls also the transport of glucose and other sugars in hepatic cells [
 <xref rid="B45-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Its gene expression was also found to be downregulated in the 
 <italic>Longissimus</italic> muscle of pigs with a high deposition of intramuscular fat [
 <xref rid="B46-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], suggesting that this gene may have a role also in the metabolic pathways influencing pig meat quality.
</p>
