<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The ham weight loss after first salting was found to be associated with ASGA0031014, on SSC7. The alleles for this marker show a significant additive effect and balanced genotype distributions in the considered sample. The most favorable genotype for this locus was GG, which displayed the lowest weight losses during processing. This mutation is an intron variant of the gene 
 <italic>NEDD9</italic>, which codes for a focal adhesion protein that acts as a scaffold to regulate signaling complexes important in cell attachment, migration, and invasion [
 <xref rid="B47-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], as well as apoptosis and the cell cycle [
 <xref rid="B48-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Some studies of different authors reported that 
 <italic>NEDD9</italic> is essential for the Transforming Growth Factor β (TGF-β) signaling pathway [
 <xref rid="B49-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Moreover, members of the TGF-β superfamily can profoundly regulate mesenchymal stem cell differentiation, as well as adipogenesis and myogenesis [
 <xref rid="B51-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Due to the involvement of 
 <italic>NEDD9</italic> in TGF-β signaling, it is, therefore, possible that changes in its gene sequence may affect also TGF-β signaling and the differentiation of mesenchymal stem cells during muscle development. Furthermore, 
 <italic>NEDD9</italic> is known to take part in the inhibition of primary cilia formation during embryogenesis [
 <xref rid="B53-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Primary cilia are non-motile organelles that have been shown to play an important role as antennae to extracellular stimuli during embryogenesis [
 <xref rid="B53-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], adipogenesis, and myofibrogenesis [
 <xref rid="B54-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. In our previous study, we found several genes related to primary cilia associated with intramuscular fat deposition [
 <xref rid="B55-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], and 
 <italic>NEDD9</italic> may take part in this complex signaling pathway related to muscle and adipose tissue development in embryogenesis. Interestingly, the marker ASGA0031014 fell into an intronic region harboring several sequences recognized by FOXO transcriptional regulators. In particular, this intronic variant is located in a site matching the motifs recognized by 
 <italic>FOXO1, FOXO3,</italic> and 
 <italic>FOXO4</italic> transcription regulators, suggesting that changes in this sequence may also affect the ability of those transcription regulators to recognize this binding site. This hypothesis seems to be supported in the literature, which indicated that 
 <italic>NEDD9</italic> gene expression was found to be regulated by another forkhead box member (
 <italic>FOXC1</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B56-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] and that 
 <italic>FOXO1</italic> has a major role in the regulation of skeletal muscle differentiation and fiber type specification in mammals [
 <xref rid="B57-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Taken together, these results suggest that ASGA0031014 may be a useful marker for the improvement of ham yield during processing. Our hypothesis needs anyway a validation with further specific studies.
</p>
