<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to these markers, other mutations were associated with the ham traits, even though they did not present significant additive effects. Among the markers associated with the ham weights at the first and at the end of the salting steps is CASI0010463, an intron variant of the 
 <italic>Neurexophilin 2</italic> (
 <italic>NXPH2</italic>) gene. A Run of Homozygosity (ROH) region was found in the 
 <italic>NXPH2</italic> gene in Valdostana Black Pied and Valdostana Chestnut bovine breeds [
 <xref rid="B58-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. This evidence seems to suggest a possible role of 
 <italic>NXPH2</italic> in livestock traits related to muscle development and production efficiency. However, this gene has never been studied before in pigs and the limited knowledge of the 
 <italic>NXPH2</italic> gene does not permit to reach a complete interpretation of the associations found for this gene in the present study. Another marker associated with green ham weight, ham weight after first salting, and ham weight at the end of salting is WU_10.2_14_144250775. This marker results to be unmapped in the latest release of the Ensembl database [
 <xref rid="B59-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>], while it was located at 132,664,262 bp on SSC14 in Illumina 11.1 mapping. Following the latter mapping, WU_10.2_14_144250775 is an intergenic variant. The closest genes to this marker are 
 <italic>Acyl-CoA Dehydrogenase Short/Branched Chain</italic> (
 <italic>ACADSB</italic>), 
 <italic>H6 Family Homeobox 2</italic> (
 <italic>HMX2</italic>), 
 <italic>H6 Family Homeobox 3</italic> (
 <italic>HMX3</italic>), and 
 <italic>BUB3 Mitotic Checkpoint Protein</italic> (
 <italic>BUB3</italic>). The sequence comprising 
 <italic>ACADSB</italic>, 
 <italic>HMX2</italic>, 
 <italic>HMX3</italic>, and 
 <italic>BUB3</italic> is highly conserved between mammals [
 <xref rid="B60-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], suggesting that this region could be of primary biological importance. Anyway, no clear association exists between muscle development and deposition, and these genes. Further investigation should be dedicated to testing the role of these genes located in this SSC14 region on production traits and porcine muscle development. Also of interest is the marker ASGA0102337, an intron variant of the 
 <italic>GRAM Domain Containing 1B</italic> (
 <italic>GRAMD1B</italic>) gene. This gene codes for a cholesterol transporter that mediates non-vesicular transport of cholesterol from the plasma membrane to the endoplasmic reticulum [
 <xref rid="B61-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. 
 <italic>GRAMD1B</italic> gene expression in muscle was found associated with obesity in the mouse model [
 <xref rid="B63-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], and mutations in its sequence were associated with feed efficiency in a beef cattle population with individuals from various breeds [
 <xref rid="B64-animals-11-00068" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. As fat deposition is important in determining salting losses and salt uptake of the green hams, mutations in the 
 <italic>GRAMD1B</italic> sequence may also influence salting and maturation traits. However, the possible effect of this gene on ham quality traits needs confirmation with studies in larger samples.
</p>
