<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Activation of PPAR-γ, ligand-activated transcription factors of the nuclear hormone receptor superfamily, causes insulin sensitization and enhances glucose metabolism. PPARs function as heterodimer in association with the co-activator complex that binds to the DNA sequence present in the promoter of target genes, which leads to their transactivation or transrepression [
 <xref rid="B86-jof-07-00058" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. PPAR-γ enhances the expression of a number of genes encoding proteins involved in glucose and lipid metabolism [
 <xref rid="B87-jof-07-00058" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. In the absence of the ligands, these heterodimers are associated with a co-repressor complex which blocks gene transcription. Thiazolidinediones (TZDs) are the most widely studied PPAR-γ ligands. Recent studies show that the ability of TZD to bind and activate PPAR-γ correlate with their ability to reduce hyperglycemia in animal models of type 2 diabetes and obesity [
 <xref rid="B88-jof-07-00058" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-jof-07-00058" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. Bearing in mind TZD side-effects, finding novel insulin sensitizers without TZD-like side-effects will be invaluable to diabetic patients [
 <xref rid="B90-jof-07-00058" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Lanostane-type triterpenes, such as pachymic acid and dehydrotrametenolic acid obtained from 
 <italic>Poria cocos</italic> were analyzed for their ability to activate PPAR-γ in vitro. Transactivation experiments performed using transfected NIH3T3 cells that express PPAR-γ and PPAR-response element containing a reporter construct showed that these terpene compounds activate the reporter construct in a dose-dependent manner [
 <xref rid="B91-jof-07-00058" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Moreover, application of lanostane-type triterpene dehydrotrametenolic acid reduced hyperglycemia in mouse models of type 2 diabetes and acted as an insulin sensitizer (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jof-07-00058-f003">Figure 3</xref>) as indicated by the results of the glucose tolerance test, which makes it a promising candidate for a new type of insulin-sensitizing drug [
 <xref rid="B91-jof-07-00058" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>].
</p>
