<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Antiobesity Effects</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Besides its scientifically proven antimicrobial, antioxidant, cytotoxic, anxiolytic, and antidiabetic effects, 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> extract has been commonly utilized for the weight loss and as sports performance enhancer, in dietary supplements [
  <a rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60">60</a>–
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">62</a>]. Therefore, the use of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> extract and its constituent 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-synephrine (C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>13</sub>NO
  <sub>2</sub>), for the treatment of obesity in 360 subjects, was reviewed. More than 50% of the subjects involved in these clinical studies were overweight, and approximately two-thirds of them consumed caffeine (132–528 mg/day) and 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-synephrine (10–53 mg/day). Approximately 44% of the subjects used a 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span>/
  <span class="italic">p</span>-synephrine product, while the remaining consumed a combination product containing multiple ingredients with 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-synephrine. The results showed that 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> extract alone or in combination with other ingredients did not cause significant adverse effects including an increase in heart rate or blood pressure or change in electrocardiographic data, serum chemistry, blood cell counts, or urinalysis. 
  <span class="italic">p-</span>Synephrine, alone or in combination products, was demonstrated to enhance metabolic rate and energy expenditure and to promote weight loss when given for six to 12 weeks [
  <a rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63">63</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study by Verpeut et al. [
  <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">64</a>] investigated the effect of the combination of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> (standardized to 6% 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-synephrine) and 
  <span class="italic">Rhodiola rosea</span> L. (golden root) (standardized to 3% rosavins and 1% salidroside) on diet-induced obesity in Sprague-Dawley rats. Acute administration of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> (1–10 mg/kg) or 
  <span class="italic">R. rosea</span> (2–20 mg/kg) alone did not decrease food intake in normal weight animals; however, the combination of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> (5.6 mg/kg) and 
  <span class="italic">R. rosea</span> (20 mg/kg) provided a 10.5% feeding suppression. On the other hand, 10 days of treatment with 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> (5.6 mg/kg) or 
  <span class="italic">R. rosea</span> (20 mg/kg) alone, or in combination, to the animals fed on a high-fat diet (60% fat) during the 13-week period led to a 30% decline in visceral fat weight, compared with other treatments. Coadministration of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> and 
  <span class="italic">R. rosea</span> also resulted in an elevation in hypothalamic norepinephrine and frontal cortex dopamine, indicating the beneficial role of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> and 
  <span class="italic">R. rosea</span> in the treatment of obesity [
  <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">64</a>]. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2"> Figure 2</a> illustrates the various pharmacological effects of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> extracts.
 </p>
</sec>
