<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Adverse Effects</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because of the possible adverse effects of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> in the cardiovascular system, the use of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span>-containing products has been questioned mainly due to the 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-synephrine content [
  <a rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" href="#B96">96</a>]. As a fat decreasing agent, it was used in traditional medications, but it has been banned by the National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA), due to its risks such as cardiovascular hazards and alkaloid toxicity [
  <a rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" href="#B97">97</a>]. However, the cardiovascular effects of 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-synephrine have been opposed by several studies [
  <a rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" href="#B98">98</a>–
  <a rid="B101" ref-type="bibr" href="#B101">101</a>]. The study by Rodrigues et al. [
  <a rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" href="#B102">102</a>] was designed to investigate the herb-drug interactions between a standardized extract of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> and amiodarone, an antiarrhythmic medication, in rats. In the first step of the study, a single-dose of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> and amiodarone was administered orally to the rats at 164 mg/kg and 50 mg/kg doses, respectively. In the second step, the rats were pretreated with 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> for 14 days, and on the 15th day, the amiodarone was administered at the same dose. On the other hand, the control group rats received vehicle only. The results demonstrated a significant enhancement of the peak plasma concentration of amiodarone in rats pretreated with 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> extract, indicating a potential herb-drug interaction between 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> extract and amiodarone [
  <a rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" href="#B102">102</a>]. Most recent clinical studies on 16 individuals have indicated that 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> extract and its principal alkaloid, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-synephrine, had no adverse effects on the cardiovascular system after 15 days of treatment [
  <a rid="B103" ref-type="bibr" href="#B103">103</a>]. Moreover, Stohs et al. [
  <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">67</a>] reported approximately 30 human studies indicating that 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-synephrine and bitter orange extracts do not result in cardiovascular effects; the effects in rodents cannot be directly extrapolated to humans at commonly used doses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding the adverse effects of formulations for body weight loss containing 
  <span class="italic">Ephedra sinica</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Citrus aurantium</span>, Arbo et al. used theuterotrophic assay to test the antiestrogenic activity of ephedrine, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-synephrine, 
  <span class="italic">E. sinica</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> in immature female rats. Only ephedrine at 0.5 mg/kg/day presented a significative antiestrogenic effect [
  <a rid="B104" ref-type="bibr" href="#B104">104</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
