<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To date, there is a lot of evidence confirming that viral infections can be treated by the antiviral drugs obtained by traditional medicine and herbal sources rich in phytochemicals. A collection of the main results relating to antiviral plant extracts was presented in 
 <xref rid="pharmaceuticals-14-00381-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, while 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pharmaceuticals-14-00381-f005">Figure 5</xref> depicts the major phytochemical classes with antiviral activity. Several authors have considered a group of plants or a particular species from which to recover bioactive compounds with antiviral properties. Below are some relevant examples of plants or plant extracts with high antiviral power. Following this strategy, in 1995 McCutcheon and his co-workers screened about one hundred medicinal plants from British Columbia for their antiviral activity. It was found that about 12 herbal extracts had antiviral action, and this included 
 <italic>Rosa nutkana</italic> that was active against enteric coronavirus [
 <xref rid="B190-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>]. The root extracts isolated from 
 <italic>Potentilla arguta</italic> exerted antiviral activity against respiratory syncytial virus. The antiviral activity against parainfluenza virus type 3 was exerted by 
 <italic>Ipomopsis aggregata</italic>. Rota virus related infection can be treated using root extracts of 
 <italic>Lomatium dissectum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B191-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>]. The herpes virus comprises of HSV-1 and HSV-2 both are double stranded linear DNA and comprises of icosahedral proteins as genetic composition. The infection of HSV involves painful reaction and generally can be spread or restricted around the genital area, mouth, skin and eyes. The entrance is based on interaction with glycoproteins that relies on viral envelope and transmembrane receptors of host cells. As such no permanent cure exists, but the viral shedding can be reduced by providing treatment with phytochemicals [
 <xref rid="B18-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B192-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>,
 <xref rid="B193-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>]. 
</p>
