<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot4-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Antifungal Activity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ijms-19-00033-t003" href="#ijms-19-00033-t003">Table 3</a>, antifungal activity was not observed against 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> spp., 
  <span class="italic">Cryptococcus neoformans</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Microsporum canis</span>. A weak action against 
  <span class="italic">Trichophyton mentagrophytes</span> was found, and 
  <span class="italic">Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</span> demonstrated a moderate degree of sensitivity to the essential oil based on the minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) classification adopted by Holetz et al. (2002) [
  <a rid="B44-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijms-19-00033">44</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oils with strong antimicrobial activity against yeasts are characterized by a high content of thymol, carvacrol, cymene, linalool or α-pinene [
  <a rid="B45-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijms-19-00033">45</a>]. Among the compounds found in the essential oil from 
  <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span>, linalool (0.14%) and α-pinene (3.22%) may have exerted some antifungal action against yeasts of 
  <span class="italic">P. brasiliensis</span>, the causative agent of paracoccidioidomycosis. Few studies related to the action of essential oils against this fungus are available, possibly because it is a mycoses restricted to some countries of Latin America. In addition to previously published studies, this work provides an indication that some terpenes from 
  <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span> can be related to inhibition of 
  <span class="italic">P. brasiliensis</span> growth and this essential oil is therefore a relevant target for future investigation regarding its isolated compounds. Essential oil from 
  <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span> showed inhibition with an MIC value lower than already found for other essential oils or isolated compounds tested against this fungus [
  <a rid="B46-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijms-19-00033">46</a>,
  <a rid="B47-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijms-19-00033">47</a>,
  <a rid="B48-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijms-19-00033">48</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Until now, with regard to the antifungal activities of essential oil of the leaves from 
  <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span>, only a fungistatic effect against 
  <span class="italic">Phyllosticta citricarpa</span> was described [
  <a rid="B28-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijms-19-00033">28</a>]. Against fungi that are pathogenic to humans, the essential oil of this species had not yet been evaluated. Except for 
  <span class="italic">P. brasiliensis</span>, the results found for the other fungi indicate that this essential oil was not capable of acting in any mechanism that could provide the fungistatic or fungicidal activity, and therefore, the present terpenes in 
  <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span> were not efficient against these species.
 </p>
</sec>
