<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot2-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Gas Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry (GC/MS) Analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oils from 
  <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span> leaves were analyzed using a gas chromatograph coupled to a mass spectrometer, model FOCUS ISQ 230ST (Thermo Scientific, Austin, TX, USA), equipped with a TraceGOLD TG-5MS capillary column (Thermo Scientific, 30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm film thickness). The carrier gas was helium, at a flow rate of 1 mL·min
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. Injector and detector temperatures were 220 °C and 240 °C, respectively; the injection volume was 1 μL and split ratio was 1:20. The oven temperature was programmed from 60 °C to 246 °C, at 3 °C/min. The electron impact energy was set at 70 eV and fragments from 40 to 415 
  <span class="italic">m</span>/
  <span class="italic">z</span> were collected [
  <a rid="B37-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijms-19-00033">37</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The identification of the essential oil components was carried out by comparison of the mass spectrum obtained with that stored in the software library (Nist08), and by comparing the calculated arithmetic retention index (AI) according to the equation proposed by Van Den Dool and Kratz (1963) [
  <a rid="B60-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-ijms-19-00033">60</a>] with arithmetic retention index reported in the literature [
  <a rid="B37-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijms-19-00033">37</a>,
  <a rid="B38-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijms-19-00033">38</a>]. AI calculation was based on retention times of linear alkane standards (C8-C40, Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) run under the same operating conditions as previously described. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantitative analysis was carried out in triplicate and the amounts of volatile compounds were calculated using the internal standard method, taking into account the relative response factor (RRF) according to IOFI Working Group on Methods of Analysis [
  <a rid="B61-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-ijms-19-00033">61</a>]. For this purpose, heptanal (Sigma-Aldrich; 0.0092 mg·mL
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) was selected as the internal standard. Phellandrene, linalool, caryophylene and nerolidol (Sigma-Aldrich) were selected to represent the response factors for monoterpene hydrocarbons, oxygenated monoterpenes, sesquiterpene hydrocarbons and oxygenated sesquiterpenes, respectively. Analyses for the RRF calculation were completed five times at four concentrations (0.0104, 0.0146, 0.0187 and 0.0229 mg·mL
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) [
  <a rid="B62-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-ijms-19-00033">62</a>] and the average response factors were obtained.
 </p>
</sec>
