<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Yield and Chemical Composition of the Essential Oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The average yield of the essential oil from 
   <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span> was 0.86% (
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">w</span>). This is similar when compared to the percentage yield of plants already explored commercially in essential oil production, such as 
   <span class="italic">Ocimum basilicum</span> (1.24%) and 
   <span class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</span> (1.05%) [
   <a rid="B35-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijms-19-00033">35</a>] or 
   <span class="italic">Eucalyptus citriodora</span> (1.05%) [
   <a rid="B36-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijms-19-00033">36</a>]. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to chemical analysis, 29 compounds were identified from the essential oil of the leaves from this species, and sesquiterpene hydrocarbons were predominant (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="ijms-19-00033-t001" href="#ijms-19-00033-t001">Table 1</a>). Major compounds identified were bicyclogermacrene (17.50%), globulol (14.13%), viridiflorol (8.83%), γ-eudesmol (7.89%), α-eudesmol (6.88%), rosifoliol (4.54%), (
   <span class="italic">E</span>)-caryophyllene (4.49%), cubeban-11-ol (4.40%), palustrol (3.83%) and α-pinene (3.22%). 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These results for major compounds are similar to those reported in the literature regarding globulol [
   <a rid="B17-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijms-19-00033">17</a>,
   <a rid="B18-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijms-19-00033">18</a>], γ-eudesmol and α-eudesmol [
   <a rid="B22-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijms-19-00033">22</a>], (
   <span class="italic">E</span>)-caryophyllene [
   <a rid="B21-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijms-19-00033">21</a>,
   <a rid="B23-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijms-19-00033">23</a>] and α-pinene [
   <a rid="B17-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijms-19-00033">17</a>,
   <a rid="B18-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijms-19-00033">18</a>,
   <a rid="B20-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijms-19-00033">20</a>,
   <a rid="B21-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijms-19-00033">21</a>,
   <a rid="B27-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijms-19-00033">27</a>]. Other terpenes, such as bicyclogermacrene, viridiflorol, rosifoliol, cubeban-11-ol and palustrol, are being described here for the first time as major components of the essential oil in leaves of 
   <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span>. Previous studies showed a diverse chemical constitution for the essential oil of this same species, probably because many factors, such as soil characteristics, extraction techniques, climatic characteristics, and others, can affect the quantitative and qualitative constitution of the essential oil [
   <a rid="B17-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijms-19-00033">17</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Cytotoxic Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cytotoxic effect of the essential oil was tested in estrogen-receptor positive MCF-7 and estrogen-receptor negative MDA-MB-231 human breast cancer cell lines. Additionally, the human normal breast cell line, MCF-10A, was evaluated. The results of the cytotoxicity assays are shown in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="ijms-19-00033-t002" href="#ijms-19-00033-t002">Table 2</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil was toxic against MDA-MB-231 (46.60 μg·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) cancer cell lines. MDA-MB-231 cells, which represent an aggressive phenotype, responded more favorably to the cytotoxic effect of the essential oil than the less-aggressive MCF-7 breast cancer cell line. Several difficulties are associated with the treatment of estrogen-receptor negative breast cancer cells because these usually have poor prognosis and hormone therapies are not effective [
   <a rid="B39-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijms-19-00033">39</a>], which makes the results found here considered of great relevance. Moreover, this essential oil presented similar results compared to other plant essential oils considered active and with relevant action against this cell type, such as 
   <span class="italic">Decatropis bicolor</span>, which had a CC
   <sub>50</sub> of 53.81 μg·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span> [
   <a rid="B40-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijms-19-00033">40</a>] and 
   <span class="italic">Hedychium spicatum</span> with values around 65 μg·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span> [
   <a rid="B41-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijms-19-00033">41</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The normal breast cell line, MCF-10A (314.44 μg·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>), was around sevenfold more resistant to essential oil action than MDA-MB-231 cancer cells. A relationship between normal breast cell lines and breast cancer cell lines was established through the selectivity index (SI) (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="ijms-19-00033-t002" href="#ijms-19-00033-t002">Table 2</a>) in order to check specificity. A positive SI value is desirable, and represents more selectivity against cancer cells than toxicity to normal cells. The negative value of SI for MCF-7 (−0.21) showed selectivity by normal cells, but the SI for the MDA-MB-231 cells was 0.83, which means selectivity by cancer cells and confirms the potential of this essential oil as a good candidate as a cytotoxic agent.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Against MCF-7, the essential oil did not present cytotoxic action at the tested concentrations. Methanolic extract, chalcones and ursolic acid isolated from the leaves of this species presented cytotoxic activity against such cellular types [
   <a rid="B9-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijms-19-00033">9</a>,
   <a rid="B42-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijms-19-00033">42</a>]. This suggests that differential content or concentration, especially of polar compounds in 
   <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span>, may be related to cytotoxic action against MCF-7 cells.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Flow Cytometry Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Flow cytometry analysis was performed to investigate if the cytotoxicity effect induced by 
   <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span> essential oil is related to pathways that activate cell death. As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-19-00033-f001" href="#ijms-19-00033-f001">Figure 1</a>, the treatment with essential oil did not induce cell death in MDA-MB-231 and MCF-10A at the doses of 46 μg·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span> and 314 μg·mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, respectively, when compared to control cells. Therefore, the cytotoxicity of this essential oil is not involved with the activation of cell death mechanisms, but with the reduction of the cellular metabolic capacity. The resazurin reduction to verify cell viability may be indicating that there was impairment in cellular metabolism and not necessarily an interruption of electron transport and mitochondrial dysfunction [
   <a rid="B43-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijms-19-00033">43</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot4-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Antifungal Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="ijms-19-00033-t003" href="#ijms-19-00033-t003">Table 3</a>, antifungal activity was not observed against 
   <span class="italic">Candida</span> spp., 
   <span class="italic">Cryptococcus neoformans</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Microsporum canis</span>. A weak action against 
   <span class="italic">Trichophyton mentagrophytes</span> was found, and 
   <span class="italic">Paracoccidioides brasiliensis</span> demonstrated a moderate degree of sensitivity to the essential oil based on the minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) classification adopted by Holetz et al. (2002) [
   <a rid="B44-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijms-19-00033">44</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oils with strong antimicrobial activity against yeasts are characterized by a high content of thymol, carvacrol, cymene, linalool or α-pinene [
   <a rid="B45-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijms-19-00033">45</a>]. Among the compounds found in the essential oil from 
   <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span>, linalool (0.14%) and α-pinene (3.22%) may have exerted some antifungal action against yeasts of 
   <span class="italic">P. brasiliensis</span>, the causative agent of paracoccidioidomycosis. Few studies related to the action of essential oils against this fungus are available, possibly because it is a mycoses restricted to some countries of Latin America. In addition to previously published studies, this work provides an indication that some terpenes from 
   <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span> can be related to inhibition of 
   <span class="italic">P. brasiliensis</span> growth and this essential oil is therefore a relevant target for future investigation regarding its isolated compounds. Essential oil from 
   <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span> showed inhibition with an MIC value lower than already found for other essential oils or isolated compounds tested against this fungus [
   <a rid="B46-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijms-19-00033">46</a>,
   <a rid="B47-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijms-19-00033">47</a>,
   <a rid="B48-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijms-19-00033">48</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Until now, with regard to the antifungal activities of essential oil of the leaves from 
   <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span>, only a fungistatic effect against 
   <span class="italic">Phyllosticta citricarpa</span> was described [
   <a rid="B28-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijms-19-00033">28</a>]. Against fungi that are pathogenic to humans, the essential oil of this species had not yet been evaluated. Except for 
   <span class="italic">P. brasiliensis</span>, the results found for the other fungi indicate that this essential oil was not capable of acting in any mechanism that could provide the fungistatic or fungicidal activity, and therefore, the present terpenes in 
   <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span> were not efficient against these species.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot5-ijms-19-00033" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Antibacterial Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antibacterial activity of the essential oil from leaves of 
   <span class="italic">B. salicifolius</span> was determined against some microorganisms of clinical importance, as shown in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="ijms-19-00033-t004" href="#ijms-19-00033-t004">Table 4</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oils from the leaves of this species has not been investigated previously against any bacterial organism. This study shows that, against the tested bacteria, the essential oil did not have antibacterial activity. However, some studies [
   <a rid="B2-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijms-19-00033">2</a>,
   <a rid="B23-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijms-19-00033">23</a>] showed activity of extracts from this species against 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span>, which leads to a conclusion that, regarding metabolites from this species, antibacterial activity is dependent on the presence of polar compounds not present in the essential oil. (
   <span class="italic">E</span>)-caryophyllene and α-pinene may be responsible for a certain effect against the MRSA and MSSA strains, since other authors have reported antibacterial activity against 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> when these compounds are in a majority in essential oils [
   <a rid="B49-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijms-19-00033">49</a>,
   <a rid="B50-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-ijms-19-00033">50</a>,
   <a rid="B51-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-ijms-19-00033">51</a>,
   <a rid="B52-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijms-19-00033">52</a>,
   <a rid="B53-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-ijms-19-00033">53</a>,
   <a rid="B54-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-ijms-19-00033">54</a>,
   <a rid="B55-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-ijms-19-00033">55</a>]. It was observed that the essential oil had greater difficulty in acting against the Gram-negative bacteria. In general, essential oils are more effective against Gram-positive than Gram-negative bacterial strains, because the outer membrane surrounding the cell wall restricts the diffusion of hydrophobic compounds through the lipopolysaccharide covering [
   <a rid="B56-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-ijms-19-00033">56</a>]. Furthermore, the species 
   <span class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> is generally less susceptible to a diverse range of antimicrobial compounds, including essential oils [
   <a rid="B57-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57-ijms-19-00033">57</a>]. This reduced susceptibility has been attributed to the outer membrane and associated properties, such as drug efflux [
   <a rid="B58-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-ijms-19-00033">58</a>,
   <a rid="B59-ijms-19-00033" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijms-19-00033">59</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
