<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12" class="p">In the present investigation selected plant EOs of Mp, As, Os, Em and Cl showed promising lethal effects against larval and adult stages of 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes aegypti</italic>. Larvicidal activity of EO of Mp was recorded highest with LC50 value of 0.42 ppm followed by EOs of As, Os and Em having LC50 value below 50 ppm at 24 h. These findings were in line with the previous studies carried on mosquitoes and another dipteran flies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>. Although larvicidal potency of Cl was comparatively lower with LC50 value of 163.65 ppm at 24 h than other EOs, its adulticidal potential was found highest having LC50 value of 23.37 ppm at 24 h. EOs of Mp, As and Em also showed good adulticidal potential having LC50 value within the range of 100–120 ppm at 24 h exposure period but comparatively lower than their larvicidal efficiency. On the other hand, EO of Os showed negligible adulticidal effect even at the highest dose of treatment. Thus, the result reflects that the toxicity of the plant EOs may vary with respect to developmental stages of the mosquito
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>. It also depends on penetration rate of EO into the insect body, their interaction with specific target enzymes and detoxification ability of the mosquito at each developmental stage
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup>. A good number of studies indicate that the major constituent compound(s) are responsible factor for bioactivity of an EO as it comprises the major fraction of the total compounds
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, we considered two major compounds from each EO. From GC-MS result Diallyldisulfide and Diallyltrisulfide were identified as the major compounds of EO of As which was in conformity with the previous reports
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>. Again, Carvone and Limonene were identified as the major compounds of EO of Mp although the previous report suggested menthol as one of its major compound
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>. Constituent profile of the EO of Os revealed Eugenol and Methyl Eugenol as the major compounds showing similarity with the findings of earlier researchers
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>. Eucalyptol and Eudesmol were recorded as principal compounds present in Em leaf oil which was in line with the findings of some researchers
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup> but contradicting the findings of Olalade 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>. Dominance of Eucalyptol and α- pinene was observed in EO of 
 <italic class="italic">Callistemon linearis</italic> showing similarity with previous studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. Whatever intraspecific variation for constituent composition and concentration of EO extracted from the same plant species from different places has been reported and also observed in the present study were influenced by geographical conditions where the plant grows, harvesting time, development stage or age of the plant and occurrence of chemotypes etc.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup>. The identified major compounds were then purchased and tested for their larvicidal and adulticidal effects against 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes aegypti</italic>. The result revealed that the larvicidal activity of Diallyldisulfide was equal to the activity of crude EO of As. But the activity of Diallyltrisulfide was higher than EO of As. These findings were similar to the findings of Kimbaris 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>
 </sup> working on 
 <italic class="italic">Culex pipines</italic>. However, these two compounds did not show good adulticidal activity against the target mosquito which was in conformity with the findings of Plata- Rueda 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>
 </sup> worked on 
 <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic>. EO of Os was found effective against larval stages of 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes aegypti</italic> but not against adult stages. The larvicidal activity of major individual compound was found lesser than the activity of crude EO of Os. This implies the role of other compounds and their interactions in crude EO. Methyl Eugenol individually possessed negligible activity whereas Eugenol individually possessed moderate larvicidal activity. This finding one-way supported
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup> and other way contradicted the findings of earlier investigators
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup>. The difference in the functional group between Eugenol and Methyl Eugenol might make the differences of their toxicity against the same target insect
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>. Limonene was found to possess moderate larvicidal activity while the Carvone showed negligible effect. Similarly, comparatively lower toxicity of Limonene and higher toxicity of Carvone against adults supported the findings of some previous studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>
 </sup> and opposed others
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup>. Possession of double bond both in endocyclic and exocyclic position might add advantage of these compounds as larvicidal agent
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup> while as a ketone Carvone with unsaturated α and β carbon might show higher toxicity as adulticides
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>
 </sup>. However, individual performance of Limonene and Carvone were quite lower than the whole EO of Mp (Tables 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" class="xref">3</xref>). Among the terpene compounds tested, Eudesmol was found to possess highest effects both as larvicide and adulticide with LC50 value below 2.5 ppm and emerged as promising compound for 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes</italic> control. Its performance was better than whole EO of Em though it was not in line with the finding of Cheng 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>
 </sup>. Eudesmol, a sesquiterpene with two isoprene units are less volatile than oxygenated monoterpene like Eucalyptoland thus have a greater potential as insecticide. Eucalyptol by its own showed higher adulticidal than larvicidal activity and both supported and opposed by the findings of earlier workers
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>
 </sup>. The individual activity was almost at par with the activity of whole EO of Cl. Another bicyclic monoterpene, α- pinene was found to possess lower adulticidal effect than larvicidal effect against 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes aegypti</italic> which was opposite to the performance of whole EO of Cl. Overall insecticidal activity of a terpene compound is affected by its lipophilicity, volatility, branching of the carbon-atom, projection area, surface area, functional group and their position etc.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>. The compounds may exert effects by disintegrating cell mass, blocking respiratory activity, interrupting nerve impulse transmissionetc
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>. The larvicidal activity of synthetic organophosphate-Temephos was found to have highest effect with LC50 value of 0.43 ppm, which was in accordance with the findings of Lek- Uthal
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup>. The adulticidal activity of synthetic organophosphate -Malathion was recorded as 5.44 ppm. Although, both the organophosphates showed good response against the laboratory strain of 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes aegypti</italic>, development of resistance by mosquitoes against these compounds have been reported from different parts of the globe
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>. However, no such reports of resistance development were found to documentagainst botanicals
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, botanicals are considered as potential alternative to chemical insecticide in vector control programme.
</p>
