<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13" class="p">Out of 28 binary combinations (1:1) prepared from effective terpene compounds and terpene compound with Temephos to test for larvicidal action, nine combinations were found to have synergistic, 14 combinations with antagonistic and five combinations were found to have no effect. On the other hand, in case of adulticidal bioassay, seven combinations were found to have synergistic, 15 combinations antagonistic, while six combinations were recorded to have no effect. The reason for synergistic action of some combinations might be due to the interactions of candidate compounds on different vital pathways at a time or due to the serial inhibition of different key enzymes of a particular biological pathway
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
 </sup>. Combinations of Limonene with Diallyldisulfide or Eudesmol or Eugenol were found synergistic both in small scale and large-scale application (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table" class="xref">6</xref>) while its combination with Eucalyptol or α-pinene was found to show antagonistic effect against larvae. On an average Limonene was found as a good synergist which might due to the presence of Methyl group, good cuticular penetration and different mode of actions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup>. It was reported earlier that Limonene could exert its toxic effect by penetrating through insect cuticle (contact toxicity) or targeting digestive system (anti-feeding) or acting on the respiratory systems (fumigant activity)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup> while phenylpropanoid like Eugenol might target metabolic enzymes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, compounds with the different mode of actions in combination might increase total lethal actions in mixtures. Eucalyptol with Diallyldisulfide or Eudesmol or α-pinene was found synergistic but rest of the combination with other compounds were either having no larvicidal effect or having antagonistic action. Earlier studies demonstrated inhibitory activity of Eucalyptol on AChE as well as octapamine and GABA receptors
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>
 </sup>. As cyclic monoterpenes, Eucalyptol, Eugenol, etc. might share the same mode of action like neurotoxic activity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>
 </sup> thereby minimizing their combined effect by inhibiting each other. Again, the combination of the Temephos with Diallyldisulfide, α-pinene and Limonene were found synergistic that supported previous reports of synergism that occurred between plant product and synthetic organophosphate
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
