<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15" class="p">On the other hand, antagonistic effect indicates that the selected compounds in a combination are less active than the individual effect of each compound. The reason for antagonism in some combinations might due to the alternation of behavior of one compound by the other compound by changing the rate of absorption, distribution, metabolism or excretion as has been suggested as possible mechanism of antagonism in combination of drug molecules by earlier researchers
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">65</xref>
 </sup>. Again, the possible cause of antagonism might be due to the competition of constituent compounds for single receptor or target site due to similar mode of action. In some cases, non-competitive inhibition of target protein might also occur. In the present study the two organosulfur compounds namely Diallyldisulfide and Diallyltrisulfide showed antagonism possibly for the competition for the same target site. Again, these two sulfur compounds while combined with Eudesmol and α-pinene showed antagonistic and no effect. Eudesmol and α-pinene are cyclic in nature while Diallyldisulfide and Diallyltrisulfide are aliphatic in nature. Based on the chemical structure the total lethal activity supposed to enhance in combination of these compounds as their target sites are usually different
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup> but experimentally we found antagonistic effect which might be due to some unknown biological interactions of these compounds in living system. Similarly, combination of eucalyptol with α-pinene resulted antagonistic response though the target site of action of these two compounds were reported differently by earlier researchers
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>
 </sup>. As both of the compounds are cyclic monoterpene, there may have certain common target site to which they might compete for binding and influenced overall toxicity of the combination pair in the study.
</p>
