<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">Nutraceuticals and functional food ingredients that are beneficial to vascular health may represent useful compounds that are able to reduce the overall cardiovascular risks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>]. Ascorbic acid is one of the most strong and least toxic natural antioxidant. It is the main water soluble antioxidant present in milk and free radical scavenging activity of ascorbic acid is due to low oxidation-reduction potential (330 mV). Ascorbic acid is the major water-soluble antioxidant in milk and can act as strong free radical scavenger [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>]. Ascorbic acid can scavenge superoxide anion radicals, alkoxyl radicals and singlet oxygen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>]. Ascorbic acid can scavenge superoxide, iron oxide, nitric oxide and alkoxyl radicals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>]. Ascorbic acid significantly inhibited the degradation of riboflavin in cream in presence of 1000 Lux light for four days [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>]. Ascorbic acid and tocopherol were added in milk to enhance the flavor and photo-oxidative stability. Ascorbic acid and tocopherol supplemented samples revealed better flavor and photo-oxidative stability as compared to non-supplemented samples [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>]. Ascorbic acid significantly inhibited the degradation of riboflavin in light exposed milk, antioxidant activities were mainly attributed to the scavenging effect on singlet oxygen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>]. A study was conducted to determine the effect of tocopherol and vitamin C against the development of atopy in infants. Increased concentration of vitamin C in breast milk reduced the risk of atopy in infants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>]. Ascorbic acid is extremely helpful for the infants as it plays a pivotal role in the formation of neuro transmitters, synthesis of carnitine and improves the absorption of iron. Human and cow milk contains about 40 and 20 mg/Liter [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>]. Oxidation of ascorbic acid depends upon temperature, light, oxygen and amount of catalysts. Vitamin A and E are regarded as primary lipid soluble antioxidants and main job of these vitamins is to protect the polyunsaturated fatty acids and associated bio-chemical compounds from peroxidation (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" class="xref">4</xref>). α-tocopherol can be considered one of the most important lipid-soluble antioxidants in milk, due to it is presence in milk fat globule membrane [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>]. It can act as a preventative, chain breaking antioxidant and quencher of singlet oxygen in milk [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>]. Milk can develop off flavor as a result of photo-oxidation and contamination with copper. The existence of antioxidants in milk can inhibit the free radical mechanism by donating the proton and thus inhibit the onset of auto-oxidation. Vitamin E can inhibit the activity of plasmin; a proteolytic enzyme and secondly it can directly scavenge the free radicals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>]. Among the tocopherols, α-tocopherol is regarded as more powerful scavenger of free radicals and antioxidant activity of β-, γ- and δ-tocopherol is about 80–90% less than α-tocopherol [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>]. γ-tocopherol is of high functional value as it can trap the nitrogen oxide species. It helps the body to prevent cardiovascular diseases and cancers. The concentration of vitamin E in cow milk has been reported about 0.9 mg/mL while summer milk possessed higher concentration than winter milk. Concentration of vitamin in human milk ranges from 3 to 13 mg/mL [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>]. Addition of 100 mg α-tocopherol/kg milk fat and 100 mg ascorbyl palmitate/kg milk fat to UHT milk decreased the concentration of hexanal during the storage period of 4 weeks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>]. Khan et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>] studied the effect of vitamin E supplementation on oxidative stability of sheep butter and supplementation of sheep butter with 60 mg/kg efficiently inhibited the lipid peroxidation and raised the shelf stability. Antioxidant activity of zinc and selenium for the inhibition of superoxide dismutase is scientifically proven [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>]. Glutathione and selenium enhanced the functional value and antioxidant capacity of milk [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>]. Mineral content of cow, buffalo, goat and sheep milk have been presented in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" class="xref">5</xref>.
</p>
