<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ERGMs were constructed by adding terms following the methods of Goodreau et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0239345.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>], starting with the structural covariates (M1), including the two geometrically-weighted structural variables (GWOD and GWESP). For GWOD we specified a fixed decay-parameter value of θS = 0.5 to apply equal popularity effects to nodes with high and low out degree [
 <xref rid="pone.0239345.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. For the three GWESP terms we specified a fixed decay-parameter value of θT = 0.01 to represent a higher chance of node “A” learning from node “B” if they both have social learning relationships with person “C”, with a very slightly increased chance for every person that “A” and “B” both have social learning relationships with (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0239345.g001">Fig 1</xref> H1d, H2b-c) [
 <xref rid="pone.0239345.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. One additional model (M2) was constructed by adding all edge and node variables except medicinal plant knowledge to M1. Five additional models (M3-7) were constructed by one of the five measurements of medicinal plant knowledge to M2. After all seven ERGMs were complete, Variance Inflation Factor (VIF) values were calculated using the 
 <italic>vif</italic>.
 <italic>ergm</italic> command for each model term [
 <xref rid="pone.0239345.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Model terms with VIF values greater than 10 (“use uniqueness: same” and “species uniqueness: same”) were removed to avoid multicollinearity [
 <xref rid="pone.0239345.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. To confirm that adding terms improved model fit we used Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) to test if more complex models had lower AIC than simpler models (M3-7&lt;M2&lt;M1), which indicates a better fit [
 <xref rid="pone.0239345.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. ERGM goodness-of-fit (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0239345.s004">S4</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0239345.s010">S10</xref> Figs) and Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) diagnostics (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0239345.s011">S11</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0239345.s017">S17</xref> Figs) were used to evaluate model performance. To test alternative explanations for non-significant results we visualized the probability of edges forming between all nodes in the network using the 
 <italic>edgeprob</italic> command [
 <xref rid="pone.0239345.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. All analyses were performed in R version 3.6.1 [
 <xref rid="pone.0239345.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>].
</p>
