<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30" class="p">The present study has demonstrated that an essential oil extracted from pistachio hulls was effective against clinical strains of 
 <italic class="italic">Candida</italic>. The dramatic rise in antimicrobial resistance is now considered a major health treat, with an estimated 700,000 people dying every year from antibiotic, antiviral, antifungal and antimalarial resistance infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>]. Therefore, natural products have become an important source for drug development. Geraniol has been tested against 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> species and its mechanism of action has been elucidated [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>]. Ebani et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>] have recently demonstrated the activity of five essential oils (star anise, basil, oregano, clary sage and thymus) against multidrug-resistant strains of 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Enterococcus</italic> spp., 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. famata</italic> responsible for urinary tract infections. The pistachio hull essential oil tested in the present work was effective against 
 <italic class="italic">Candida sp</italic>., whereas polyphenol-rich extracts from pistachios (natural raw shelled and roasted salted pistachios) and white grape juice used in our previous investigations were not effective against yeasts [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>]. Amongst the major components identified in the pistachio hull EO, D-limonene and 3-carene were effective against 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> strain 16, 
 <italic class="italic">C. glabrata</italic> strain 9 and 
 <italic class="italic">C. parapsilosis</italic> strain 26 (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" class="xref">3</xref>). This is in agreement with the demonstrated antifungal activity against 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> of the 
 <italic class="italic">Chamaecyparis nootkatensis</italic> essential oil [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>].
</p>
