<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32" class="p">In the present study, the interactions between pistachio hull EO and the selected antifungal compounds were antagonistic (FIC index &gt; 4) and droplet size distribution was used to investigate the mechanisms responsible for such interactions. PdI values close to 1.0 are indicative of polydispersed systems [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>], whereas values close to 0.6 suggesting monomodal systems. Interestingly, amongst the antifungal used, caspofungin is the most hydrophilic one as shown by its logP value of − 4.59. This property is due to the numerous hydroxyl groups, which makes it able to donate and accept 16 and 18 hydrogen bonds respectively (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>c). This allows an excellent dispersion of the molecule in the aqueous medium leading to a homogeneous droplet system. In fact, addition of pistachio hull EO to the system did not lead to substantial changes in the average diameter of the droplets or in the PdI of the culture medium. On the contrary, addition of the EO to the system containing either fluconazole or voriconazole (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>a and b) led to a system stabilization as highlighted by the decrease both of the droplet diameter average then of the PdI. These two drugs, which only differ for the presence of one more fluorine atom on position 5 of the pyrimidine ring and a 2-butanol as aliphatic chain instead of 2-propanol in the voriconazole (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>b), are less hydrophilic and possess a smaller steric encumbrance compared to caspofungin (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" class="xref">4</xref>). In fact, fluconazole and voriconazole are able to donate a single hydrogen bond and to accept 7 and 8 hydrogen bonds, respectively. Therefore, on the contrary of which happens in presence of caspofungin, fluconazole and voriconazole are not able to stabilize alone the system but at the same time, the addition of EO, which behaves like a non-ionic surfactant, stabilise the emulsions by reducing interfacial tension and promote steric repulsion between droplets [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>]. The main mechanism for emulsion destabilization is actually associated with Ostwald ripening, which induces formation of larger droplets [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>]. PdI values range from 1.0 to 0.688 and 0.426 for EO + fluconazole and EO + voriconazole, respectively, reflecting the homogeneity in the droplet size distribution of the new stabilized system. These events could be responsible for the difficulty of both EO and drugs to carry out their antifungal activity against 
 <italic class="italic">Candida</italic> strains, which results in an antagonistic effect.
</p>
