<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In recent years, enormous amounts of research have been carried out on solutions to the disadvantages of hydrated salts. In order to reduce the supercooling degree, the study on the nucleating agents for different hydrated salts has been strongly promoted. Lane [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] conducted experiments to evaluate different nucleating agents for calcium chloride hexahydrate (CaCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·6H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O). The experimental results showed that BaI
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·6H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O, SrCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·6H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O, and SrBr
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·6H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O could effectively suppress the supercooling of CaCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·6H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O. As for sodium acetate trihydrate, the introduction of aluminum nitride [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>], silver nanoparticles [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>], Si
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>N
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, ZrB
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and SiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] were all proven to be able to effectively reduce the supercooling degree. On the other hand, the phase separation of hydrated salts can be the solved by adding thickeners, such as hydroxyethyl cellulose (HEC) [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>] and carboxymethylcellulose sodium (CMC) [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Furthermore, the combination of porous carriers and hydrated salts can mitigate the negative effects of the phase separation and improve the thermal reliability of the hydrated salts. Due to the large specific surface area, expanded graphite [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>], expanded perlite [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>] and diatomite [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] were widely used for the preparation of stable composites. In addition to the addition of nucleating agents and thickeners and the combination with porous carriers, a mixture composed of two or more hydrated salts have attracted the attention of more and more scholars. In some hydrated salt systems, mixing with other hydrated salts can not only adjust the melting point, but also reduce the supercooling degree and mitigate phase separation. Nagano et al. [
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>] added 20 wt% MgCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·6H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O to MgNO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>·6H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O to obtain a eutectic mixture. They reported that the mixture exhibited a melting point of about 60 °C, which was much lower than those of two components and was suitable for recovering waste heat. Moreover, Li et al. [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>] investigated the CaCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·6H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O-MgCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·6H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O salt system with various mass fraction of MgCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·6H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O. It was found that the mixing of two hydrated salts not only reduced the melting point of CaCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·6H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O but also retained most of the melting enthalpy. Note that hydrated salt mixtures usually exhibit different phase change temperatures and latent heat values from those of their components [
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. Therefore, exploration of mixtures is an effective route for developing novel hydrated salt PCMs. According to the requirements of SWH systems, such as suitable melting point, low cost and excellent performance, the mixtures with high latent heat and appropriate phase change temperatures are highly desirable.
</p>
