<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Essential oils (EOs) are a complex phytochemical mixtures of aroma compounds with a high value in a wide spectrum of industrial applications such as food and pharmaceutical ingredients but also fragrance or pesticide[
 <xref rid="pone.0207401.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0207401.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Regardless of the application, EOs are often used after encapsulation in synthetic or bio based materials to protect them against losses during processing and storage, to protect their components against heat-induced degradation, to stabilize them against unwanted changes, and to control their release or facilitate their manipulation[
 <xref rid="pone.0207401.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0207401.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Even after encapsulation, EOs can suffer alterations upon aging, and it is indispensable to monitor their composition during use and storage assuring quality[
 <xref rid="pone.0207401.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0207401.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Characterization and quantification of EOs are mostly based on precise chromatographic analytical techniques such as gas chromatography FID (flame ionization detector) and gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS); this last would be the most used technique to identify and quantify unknown components in EOs. GC-MS is expensive and time consuming despite the extension of devices[
 <xref rid="pone.0207401.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. When pure essential oils are studied, only a dilution is needed using an adapted organic solvent. Nevertheless, when essentials oils are encapsulated or incorporated into a product, an extraction step is required before analysis, which is a time consuming procedure. In addition, the use of organic solvents needs to be limited in relation to their toxicity for humans and environment. However, GC-MS is a very sensitive method, which is powerful to the analysis of compounds present in traces with high accuracy and to early evidence the formation of new components responsible to off-flavor. Another mean to quantify and measure of the release of EOs encapsulated in complex matrices is the use of spectrophotometric techniques[
 <xref rid="pone.0207401.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. However, most of the aroma compounds present in EOs lack of 
 <strike class="strike">a</strike> chromophore. Therefore, the global quantification of the EO could not be specifically studied by spectrophotometric techniques[
 <xref rid="pone.0207401.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>].
</p>
