<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>On February 24
 <sup>th</sup> of 1958, Janine Beisson presented a paper at the 
 <italic>Académie des Sciences</italic> reporting that the transformation of 
 <italic>Podospora anserina s
  <sup>S</sup>
 </italic> strains to the 
 <italic>s</italic> phenotype (now written respectively [Het-s*] and [Het-s]) is induced by a single cytoplasmic contact and that this transformation invades the mycelium at a rate of up to 7 cm per day (that is about an order on magnitude faster than the radial growth rate of the mycelium). In this paper, she proposed that this invasive [Het-s*] to [Het-s] transformation results ‘from multiplication in the [Het-s*] strains of particles brought in by the [Het-s] strain’ (‘
 <italic>résulte de la multiplication dans la souche</italic> s
 <sup>s</sup>
 <italic>de particules apportées par la souche</italic> s’) [
 <xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It is now known that these particles are prions [
 <xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This study was based on micromanipulation techniques allowing for controlled anastomoses of individual fungal filaments and their re-isolation. Beisson would use these micromanipulation and microsurgery techniques anew in Tracy Sonneborn’s group in Bloomington in the context of their now classic common work on cortical inheritance in Paramecia [
 <xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Janine Beisson who sadly passed away last august once explained that her initial intent as a young student was to study the ‘transforming principle’ under the supervision of Harriett Ephrussi-Taylor who had been a co-worker of Avery. Instead, she was re-directed by Boris Ephrussi to Georges Rizet. Rizet a founding father of French genetics had introduced 
 <italic>Podospora</italic> as a genetic model organism. He described in 1950, the peculiar genetics and cytology of s/S incompatibility as ‘
 <italic>un phénomène tout à fait origin</italic>al’, a thoroughly original phenomenon [
 <xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. It is thus delightful enough that this initial impetus to pursue the ‘transforming principle’ led Janine Beisson to develop a body of work completing the DNA heredity paradigm, in the study of epigenetics of structural inheritance in both fungi and protists. The seminal studies by Rizet and Beisson in the 1950s and 1960s lay the groundwork for ongoing developments in the characterization in 
 <italic>Podospora</italic> and beyond, of genetic systems related to ‘petit 
 <italic>s</italic>’ 
 <italic>aka</italic> [Het-s]. After a few years of practising experimental biology, one is likely to have faced at least once – when exposed to biological unorthodoxy – the choice between engaging the risky path of additional experimentation and autoclaving the whole business. In retrospect, one can only marvel at the insight and dedication of these scientists who simply would not let the 
 <italic>‘petit s’</italic> genetic oddity rest unquestioned and who thus established the solid theoretical and experimental foundations, on which recent studies of such systems are based on. We will here very rapidly describe the biology of the [Het-s] prion and the path leading from the [Het-s] prion to the characterization of amyloid signalling in fungi. We then discuss three recent papers on [Het-s]-related systems that collectively expand the evolutionary span of amyloid signalling and attempt to integrate these systems into the broader picture of regulated cell death in animal, plant and prokaryotic organisms.
</p>
