<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During type 2 diabetes, hyperglycemia promotes oxidative stress, which induces cerebral endothelial dysfunctions and BBB alterations, aggravating cerebrovascular complications, such as stroke. The present study evaluated the protective effects of polyphenols on redox, inflammatory, and vasoactive markers of murine bEnd3 cerebral endothelial cells during hyperglycemic condition. This experimental hyperglycemic condition was mimicked by treating cells with a high glucose concentration (33 mM) after a glucose starvation related to normoglycemia (5.5 mM). Similar treatments with high glucose level were reported to mimic hyperglycemia in in vitro cellular models and led to demonstrate high glucose-caused redox and pro-inflammatory alterations that are associated with endothelial dysfunctions, such as altered permeability and reduced NO production [
 <xref rid="B40-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Here, four characterized polyphenol-rich extracts from 
 <italic>A. borbonica</italic>, 
 <italic>A. triplinervis</italic>, 
 <italic>D. viscosa</italic>, and 
 <italic>T. bentzoe</italic> medicinal plants were assessed for their capacity to protect endothelial functions during hyperglycemic condition. Furthermore, quercetin, caffeic, chlorogenic, and gallic acids were used as reference polyphenols due to their identification in plant extracts. When considering that our previous study conducted on bEnd3 cerebral endothelial cells showed that hyperglycemic condition led to time-dependent redox alterations between 3–24 h of exposure [
 <xref rid="B42-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], the same experimental condition was achieved here. Regarding the dose of 10 µM of polyphenols used, it is consistent with the pharmacological doses broadly used in literature and in our published studies [
 <xref rid="B37-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. This dose could be considered to be close to circulating concentrations reaching less than 10 µM in nutritional situations, given that polyphenols are poorly absorbed through the intestinal tract and that their bioavailability largely depends on their structure and microbial catabolism [
 <xref rid="B27-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Of note, our present data demonstrate that polyphenols used at 10 μM did not alter the viability of bEnd3 cerebral endothelial cells after 24 h of treatment. Therefore, the biological effects of polyphenols observed could not be associated with a damaged cellular viability. Similar results were obtained when bovine aortic endothelial cells were treated with curcumin (10 μM) during 18 h of exposure. However, when the impact of different concentrations (0–30 μM) of curcumin was assessed, it was found that the cellular viability significantly decreased in the presence of 25 and 30 μM of curcumin [
 <xref rid="B48-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Conversely, Chen et al. [
 <xref rid="B49-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] demonstrated that a treatment with 10 and 25 μM of resveratrol for 24 h did not alter bEnd3 cell viability. These results suggest that the possible cytotoxic action of polyphenols might depend on their structure, the concentration used, the time of exposure, as well as the cell line considered. Several authors also reported polyphenol structure-antioxidant activity relationships [
 <xref rid="B29-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Thus, it was essential here to characterize the chemical nature of polyphenols extracted from the medicinal plants selected. More particularly, leaves were used, since they constitute the most commonly and easily collected plant parts for the preparation of herbal remedies [
 <xref rid="B50-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. 
</p>
