<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our UPLC-ESI-MS-MS data show the presence of different types of polyphenols in medicinal plant extracts that are widely found in the human diet due to their abundance in several vegetables, fruits, and plant-derived beverages, such as coffee [
 <xref rid="B27-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Indeed, for 
 <italic>A. borbonica</italic> plant extract, the major polyphenols identified were caffeic and chlorogenic acids that are members of the family of phenolic acids well known to be abundant in many red fruits and coffee [
 <xref rid="B27-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. In agreement with our published data [
 <xref rid="B38-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], quercetin and kaempferol glycosides that belong to the flavonoid family were also detected in 
 <italic>A. borbonica</italic> plant extract. 
 <italic>D. viscosa</italic> plant extract also contained different flavonoids, including the methylated form of quercetin, called isorhamnetin, procyanidins, and a trimethoxyflavone. While this trimethoxyflavone was reported as one of the bioactive phytochemicals responsible for the anti-inflammatory activity of 
 <italic>Artemisia asiatica</italic> [
 <xref rid="B51-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], quercetin, kaempferol, and procyanidins are flavonoids more commonly provided by the diet through the consumption of foods, such as onion, broccoli, grape, or cocoa. Noteworthy, literature data indicate that flavonoids may account for about two-thirds of the daily polyphenol intake in humans [
 <xref rid="B27-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Quercetin glycosides and caffeic acid derivatives were also depicted in 
 <italic>A. triplinervis</italic> plant extract. In addition, UPLC-ESI-MS-MS analysis helped to characterize the coumarin derivatives ayapin and ayapanin that we previously identified in 
 <italic>A. triplinervis</italic> essential oil and correlated with oil composition variations, depending on the developmental stage and geographical location of the medicinal plant [
 <xref rid="B52-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. For 
 <italic>T. bentzoe</italic> plant extract, the predominant polyphenols identified were gallic and ellagic acids as well as their sugar conjugates comprising the ellagitannins punicalin and punicalagin. Interestingly, these compounds may represent unique ellagitannins from specific dietary sources, like pomegranate, and be responsible for most of the antioxidant properties that were attributed to this fruit [
 <xref rid="B53-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Altogether, our UPLC-ESI-MS-MS results demonstrate that the polyphenol composition was dependent on the medicinal plant considered. Concomitantly, the total polyphenol content ranging from 0.5 to 8.1 g GAE/100 g of plant also depended on the nature of the medicinal plant. It led to identifying 
 <italic>T. bentzoe</italic> plant as the richest polyphenol source, followed by both 
 <italic>A. borbonica</italic> and 
 <italic>D. viscosa</italic> plants, and 
 <italic>A. triplinervis</italic> plant. This agrees with literature data reporting that medicinal plants may naturally provide high levels of polyphenols similarly to dietary sources, such as tea, cocoa, grape, or curcuma [
 <xref rid="B27-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Despite it being established that the total polyphenol content from fruits and vegetables varies depending on cultivars, climatic environment, cultural practices, and harvest conditions [
 <xref rid="B55-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], there is still a lack of data regarding medicinal plants. Nevertheless, the total polyphenol content remains a relevant indicator of the antioxidant capacity of food matrix and a useful preliminary marker for identifying natural sources of polyphenols as functional foods [
 <xref rid="B56-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. 
</p>
