<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The antioxidant properties of medicinal plant polyphenols on cerebral endothelial cells in hyperglycemic condition may result from their ability to scavenge and neutralize ROS, as demonstrated by DPPH assay. Indeed, through electronic delocalization on their phenolic nucleus, polyphenols can react with free radicals. Subsequently, the phenoxyl radicals produced are stabilized by the resonance effect of the phenolic nucleus. Moreover, the antioxidant activity of polyphenols depends on the number and the position of hydroxyl groups in the molecular structure [
 <xref rid="B29-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Given that flavonoids are composed of three phenolic rings, such a chemical structure may explain why quercetin and the medicinal plant extracts containing quercetin derivatives exerted high free radical-scavenging and reducing capacities. The antioxidant properties of these molecules could also be associated with their capacity to modulate the mitochondrial function, keeping in mind that mitochondria constitute a main source of ROS [
 <xref rid="B65-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Here, we show, for the first time, that all polyphenolic plant extracts, quercetin, and chlorogenic acid improved the mitochondrial MnSOD gene expression deregulated by hyperglycemic condition. In parallel, only 
 <italic>A. triplinervis</italic> plant extract, quercetin, chlorogenic, and gallic acids significantly elevated MnSOD enzymatic activity, suggesting their possible specific impact on MnSOD mitochondrial marker. Our previous data demonstrated the ability of pure polyphenols, such as caffeic and gallic acids, to improve mitochondrial respiration and biogenesis in adipose cells that were exposed to hydrogen peroxide-mediated oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="B66-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. It will be relevant to evaluate the impact of medicinal plant extracts on mitochondrial functions of cerebral endothelial cells in hyperglycemic condition. It is known that cerebral endothelial cells are rich in mitochondria [
 <xref rid="B67-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Additionally, brain is not well equipped with antioxidant defenses, despite its high consumption of oxygen [
 <xref rid="B58-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], leading to an increased risk of brain damages during high glucose-induced oxidative stress. Thus, antioxidant strategies that aim to limit mitochondrial alterations at the cerebral level are of high interest. 
</p>
