<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The armillarioid genera 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> and 
 <italic>Desarmillaria</italic> are among the most important fungal plant pathogens causing a root disease that has long been recognized as a severe ecological and economical threat worldwide. Armillarioid species are well-known white-rot-specific wood-decaying fungi [
 <xref rid="B1-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. They target hundreds of tree species and woody shrubs, and affect several million hectares of forests, commercial orchards, vineyards, as well as trees in urban areas (e.g., parks, gardens) in all boreal, temperate, and tropical regions [
 <xref rid="B2-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Before tree mortality, colonization may lead to crown dieback, lower-stem deformation, resinous-root lesion, down-wood accumulation, and growth reduction in several tree species [
 <xref rid="B12-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Most armillarioid species can inherently survive for decades in infected stumps and parts of their root system due to their vigourous and persistent nature. This long persistence in susceptible plant tissues may then cause serious damage in the developmental process of plants. Severe losses can occur in coniferous and deciduous trees, orchards, or vineyards if planting occurs in infected soils [
 <xref rid="B16-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The majority of armillarioid species, acting as facultative necrotrophs, are primary pathogens carrying an innate infectious potential in colonizing living hosts, while others are considered as opportunistic or “weak” pathogens invading already compromised trees. The observed virulence of pathogenic species depends on the individual infectious abilities, host species, age of the tree and influence of the environment [
 <xref rid="B9-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].
</p>
