<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Inflammation, a non-specific response that is part of innate immunity, occurs as a protective response that does not depend on the type of pathogen or previous infection (Chen et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). This response is initiated when pathogens are recognized by pathogen recognition receptors (PRRs). Pathogens such as bacteria, fungi and viruses interact with different PRRs, including Toll-like receptors (TLRs), retinoic acid-inducible gene-I-like receptors (RLRs), nucleotide-binding oligomerization domain-like receptors (NLRs) and C-type lectin receptors (CLRs) (Takeuchi and Akira 
 <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Lipopolysaccharides (LPSs), a component of the cell wall in Gram negative bacteria, are recognized by TLR4, which resides on the surface of macrophages and transmits inflammatory signals inside the cells (Sabroe et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). LPS-stimulated TLR4 recruits myeloid differentiation primary response 88 (MyD88) and TIR-domain-containing adapter-inducing interferon-β (TRIF), known as adaptor molecules, and activates nuclear factor-kappa B (NF-κB) and activator protein 1 (AP-1) by mediating phosphorylation-dependent signalling enzyme cascades (Akira and Takeda 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Kagan and Medzhitov 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Kagan et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Tanimura et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). In NF-κB activation, phosphorylation and degradation of inhibitor of nuclear factor kappa B (IκBα) are central steps, and this reaction is facilitated by activation of Src, Syk and p85 (Li et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Kawai and Akira 
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Lee et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Meanwhile, AP-1 signalling is mainly activated by sequential phosphorylation of signalling kinases such as interleukin-1 receptor associated kinases (IRAKs) and mitogen-activated protein kinases (MAPKs) such as extracellular-signal-regulated kinase (ERK), c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) and p38 (Janssens and Beyaert 
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Then, the activated transcription factors (NF-κB and AP-1) modulate expression of cytokines and inflammatory genes, including inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS), cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) and tumour necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), thereby treating infectious lesions or repairing tissue (Baeuerle and Henkel 
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; Liu et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). However, excessive inflammation can cause tissue damage or chronic inflammatory diseases. Chronic inflammatory diseases such as ulcerative colitis, rheumatoid arthritis, lupus and Crohn’s disease are painful and can adversely affect quality of life; they may also serve as the precursors to cardiovascular disease, diabetes and cancer (Roifman et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Schett et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Therefore, after the danger signals such as pathogens and irritants are eliminated, post-inflammatory resolution is critical (Schett and Neurath 
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).
</p>
