<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Salt Stress</italic>. Plant SMs may undergo increase or decrease in their concentration in response to salinity-induced osmotic stress or specific ion toxicity. Salinity increased SMs and antioxidant potential in cotton (namely tannic acid, flavonoids and gossypol), in safflower plants growing under &lt;100 mM of NaCl (flavonoids), in buckwheat (carotenoids, phenolic compounds and antioxidant activity), in artichoke and cultivated cardoon (flavonoids and chlorogenic acid) in response to moderate and high levels of salinity [
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Increase in SMs in response to salt stress has been reported also in 
 <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic>, maize, wheat, pea, strawberry, spinach, 
 <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic>, barley, basil, 
 <italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic> and some other spontaneous herbs (
 <italic>Mentha pulegium</italic>, 
 <italic>Nigella sativa</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B8-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Differently, a decrease in SMs was observed in lentil and 
 <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>. The increase in SMs (i.e., polyphenols), induced by salinity stress, involves an improvement in the antioxidant activity in some important crops (wheat, buckwheat, artichoke, rice and cultivated cardoon), thus improving their nutritional quality [
 <xref rid="B8-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Salt stress also resulted in a significant rise in alkaloid concentration in 
 <italic>Achillea fragrantissima</italic>, 
 <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> and 
 <italic>Solanum nigrum</italic>. There are contrasting reports on the production of essential oils in aromatic plants upon salinity stress, and the levels of SMs also vary in response to the availability of different nutrients [
 <xref rid="B19-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
</p>
