<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For this work, we adapted protein marking techniques developed by Hagler et al. for studying insect predation and movement (Hagler 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">2011</xref>; Slosky et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">2012</xref>). In South Dakota, mature dandelion seeds were collected from plants near the study sites using a vacuuming leafblower (Poulan PRO® leafblower, Electrolux Home Products, Augusta, GA). Fresh seeds were collected each year of study from the earliest flowers; viability of collected seeds was not evaluated in the study. Seeds were returned to the laboratory, dried, and the pappus and debris were removed from the seed. Seeds for the experiment in the Czech Republic were purchased from Herbiseed®, Twyford, U.K. Cleaned seeds were kept at 10°C until they could be marked. In South Dakota, individual batches of cleaned seeds were marked (approximately 41 g; seeds from our research site weighed approximately 469 μg each which roughly confirms other studies; Hale et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">2010</xref>) using a filtration approach. Each cohort of seeds was soaked in 75 mL 1 × phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and 410 μL of rabbit IgG (Product number I8140; Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) for 2 min. The samples were then air-dried at 25°C for approximately 12 h. In the Czech Republic, a quantity of 42 g of seeds (per cohort) was soaked in 100 mL of the PBS and 420 μg of rabbit IgG overnight at 5°C. Soaked seeds were then lyophilized (PowerDry LL3000, Thermo, Shanghai, China) for 24 h, at which point the seeds were dry. Seeds were spread within a few hours of being dried at a rate of 3500 seeds per m
 <sup>2</sup> (A. H. determined this as an average seed density in the Czech Republic) evenly throughout the central region (5 × 5 m) of each plot at 08:00 on the first morning of each observation period. Granivory of marked seeds was examined over five temporal periods that spanned the flowering period of dandelion in each study year. In 2009, the South Dakota observation periods were initiated on May 22, June 2, 10, 16, and 23 and in the Czech Republic on May 12, 19, 26, and June 2 and 9. In 2010, observations were initiated in South Dakota on May 26, June 2, 8, 15, and 22. Pitfall traps were activated at 08:00 on the first day of the trial; they were checked twice daily (at 10:00 and 22:00 in South Dakota, and at 08:00 and 20:00 in the Czech Republic) for 48 h in the South Dakota and for 24 h in the Czech Republic. All arthropods collected were identified to species level and were frozen at −20°C within 30 min of collection. All specimens from the Coleoptera, Orthoptera (Ensifera and Caelifera), Diplopoda, Isopoda: Oniscidea, and Hymenoptera: Formicoidea had their gut contents analyzed for the presence of the protein marker; spiders, phalangiids, and centipedes were not advanced for gut analysis.
</p>
