<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Fucoidan, a sulfated polysaccharide isolated from 
 <italic>Cladosiphon okamuranus</italic> (marine alga) inhibited DENV-2 infection tested in BHK-21 cells using the focus-forming assay. The compound reduced infectivity by 20% at a concentration of 10 µg/mL. However, based on the structure–activity relationship, conversion of glucuronic acid—a residue present in the fucoidan—to glucose resulted in the loss of the compound inhibitory activity, suggesting its critical involvement in fucoidan antiviral function, whereas removal of the sulfated functional group resulted in the attenuation of DENV-2 infection similar to that of fucoidan (21%). This suggests that the sulfated group does not have any significant effect on antiviral activity against DENV-2 infection [
 <xref rid="B121-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>]. Another sulfated polysaccharide, galactans isolated from 
 <italic>Cryptomenia crenulata</italic> [
 <xref rid="B122-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>] and 
 <italic>Gymnogongrus tolulosus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B123-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>], were reported to inhibit DENV-2 replication in Vero cells with IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 1.0 µg/mL and 0.19–1.7 µg/mL, respectively. Galactan obtained from 
 <italic>C. crenulata</italic> has selective activity. The compound was reported to be totally inactive against DENV-1, but exhibited good inhibitory effects against DENV-2 and DENV-3, but displayed weak effect on DENV-4 [
 <xref rid="B122-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>], where the protective effects could be via inhibition of the virus adsorption or virus internalization [
 <xref rid="B124-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. Another isolated sulfated polysaccharide called kappa-carrageenan from 
 <italic>Gymnogongrus griffithsiae</italic> selectively inhibited DENV-2 replication (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.9 µg/mL), but exhibited lower effects against DENV-3, and was totally inactive against DENV-1 and DENV-4. This compound was also obtained from 
 <italic>Meristiella gelidium</italic> and exhibited anti-DENV-2 activity with IC
 <sub>50</sub> between 0.14–1.6 µg/mL [
 <xref rid="B125-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. The findings suggest that both sulfated polysaccharides have the potential to be developed as anti-DENV-2 and anti-DENV-3 drugs.
</p>
