<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">Even the widespread application of 
 <italic>Swertia chirayita</italic> plant extract was also explored with respect to antihelmintic activity and antimicrobial activity. Iqbal et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] examined crude aqueous extract (25 mg/ml) and methanolic extracts of 
 <italic>Swertia chirayita</italic> in different conditions for its anthelmintic activities. Plant extracts in crude aqueous and methanolic form were tested against mature live 
 <italic>Haemonchus contortus</italic>, present in sheep to identify anthelmintic activity. Complete mobility of isolated worms was inhibited by methanolic plant extract with concentration at 25 mg/ml and the result was fully comparable with the result, obtained by the treatment of standard anthelmintic agent levamisole at concentration 0.55 mg/ml. Rehman et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] screened antibacterial properties of same plant extracts in aqueous as well as ethanolic form against some pathogenic bacteria from clinical sources by applying Kirby Bauer’s disk diffusion method. The achieved results were evaluated against the application of standard antibiotic drug on the basis of zone of inhibition formation. Antibacterial effect of S. 
 <italic>Chirayita</italic> was confirmed against some of the gram negative bacteria like 
 <italic>K. pneuomoniae, P. vulgaris</italic> and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>. Similarly antibacterial activities of four plants including 
 <italic>Swertia chirayita</italic> (stem) in the form of methanolic and aqueous extract were screened by Khalid et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>], specifically to inhibit gram positive bacteria like 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (ATCC 6538), 
 <italic>Entereococcus faecalis</italic> (ATCC 14,506) and 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> (ATCC 6633). Positive inhibitory effect of the plant extract was achieved against 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> (ATCC 6633). Sultana et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>] evaluated the antibacterial potential of rectified spirit extracts, developed from fresh stem part of the plant by using disc diffusion method (concentration: 200 µg/disc) against few gram positive and gram negative bacteria. Observations were highly comparative with respect to standard antibiotic Kanamycin and significant antibacterial activity was observed against 
 <italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic>, 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, 
 <italic>Salmonella typhi-A</italic>, 
 <italic>Shigella flexeneriae</italic> and 
 <italic>Klebsiella</italic> spp. Ahirwal et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>] evaluated both antibacterial and antifungal properties of same plant extract against standard drug Gentamycin and Amphotericin by using agar diffusion method. Presence of tannins and glycosides in plant extract was confirmed by phytochemical tests and presences of such phytochemicals were mainly responsible for the overall antimicrobial activity of the plant extract.
</p>
