<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The novel object recognition test (NORT) was conducted in order to evaluate recognition memory in mice [
 <xref rid="B36-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The apparatus was comprised of a white coloured plywood box (40 cm × 40 cm × 66 cm) with a network floor that was carefully cleaned with 70% 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic> ethanol after every trial. The apparatus was illuminated with a 60 W light suspended 50 cm over the crate. The arena of the apparatus and objects were cleaned with 70% 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic> ethanol between trials to avoid olfactory cues. NORT consisted of habituation, sample, and test phases. For behavioural assessment, 1 h after dosing the mice were habituated to the experimental apparatus in the absence of objects twice a day (with 5 h interval) in a 10 min session for three consecutive days to explore the objects. On the fourth day, two similar objects were placed in two opposite places of the box and exploration was recorded for 15 min session called sample phase (first trial: T1). After this session the animals were kept for a retention break of 1 h. Exploration was considered when an animal touches the object or it directs its nose at a distance less than 2 cm to the object. The mouse was then returned to its home cage after test. At the 2nd day of the test (day 10th of drug treatment), 30 min after scopolamine injection (except for the distilled water group) called test phase (second trial: T2), each mouse was placed again in the open field in which a novel object (plastic square) was replaced by one of the objects placed in the 1st day trial and mice were left individually in the box for 5 min. The location of the object was counterbalanced so that one half of the mice in each group saw the novel object on the left side of the box arena, and the other half saw the novel object on the right side of the box arena to eliminate bias of sides. The time spent by the animal for exploring the novel object (N) and the familiar (F) objects was recorded during 5 min. A mouse was scored as exploring when its head was oriented towards the object within a distance of 2 cm or when the nose was in contact with the object. Parameters including the time (seconds) spend in exploring familiar (F) object, time (in seconds) spend on exploring the novel (N) object, and total time (in seconds) spend on exploring both objects (N + F) were measured separately. Percentage of discrimination index (DI) was calculated by the following equation:
 <disp-formula id="FD7-brainsci-11-00259">
  <label>(7)</label>
  <math id="mm8">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mo>%</mo>
      <mi>DI</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mfrac>
      <mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
         <mi mathvariant="normal">N</mi>
         <mo>−</mo>
         <mrow>
          <mo> </mo>
          <mi mathvariant="normal">F</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
       </mrow>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
         <mi mathvariant="normal">N</mi>
         <mo>+</mo>
         <mrow>
          <mo> </mo>
          <mi mathvariant="normal">F</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
       </mrow>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
     <mo>×</mo>
     <mn>100</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
