<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis of the essential oil</div>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analytical GC: essential oil composition was established by gas chromatograph: HP 5890-series II equipped with flame ionization detectors (FID), HP-5 (30 m × 0.25 mm ID, 0.52 μm film thickness) fused silica capillary column, carrier gas nitrogen (1.2 mL/min). The temperature oven was programmed from 50 °C (1 min) to 280 °C at 5 °C/min (1 min). Injector and detector temperatures were 250 °C and 280 °C, respectively. 0.1 μL of 1% hexane solution was injected. The identification of the different components was carried out when comparing their retention times with those of pure authentic samples and by mean of their linear retention indices (L.R.I) relative to the series of 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-hydrocarbons.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analytical GC–MS: GC/EIMS analyses were carried out with a Varian CP-3800 gas-chromatograph equipped with a HP-5 capillary column (30 m × 0.25 mm; coating thickness 0.25 μm) and a Varian Saturn 2000 ion trap mass detector. The analytical conditions were: injector and transfer line temperatures 220 and 240 °C respectively; oven temperature programmed from 60 °C to 240 °C at 3 °C/min; carrier gas helium at 1 mL/min; injection of 0.2 μL (10% hexane solution); split ratio 1:30. Identification of the compounds was based on comparison of the retention times with those of authentic samples, comparing their linear retention indices relative to the series of 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-hydrocarbons, and on computer matching against commercial (NIST 2014 and ADAMS) and home-made library mass spectra built up from pure substances and components of known essential oils and MS literature data [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
