<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Glucomannan-based products are foodstuffs not directly involved in the production of ketone bodies; however, being glucomannan a non-digestible soluble dietary fiber obtained from 
 <italic class="italic">Amorphophallus konjac</italic> plant tubers [
 <xref rid="B129-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">129</xref>], these products can be included in a ketogenic food plan as alternative foods to traditional cereal-based foods. Konjac flour is used as low calorie substitute in the food industry for the production of foodstuffs such as noodles and spaghetti [
 <xref rid="B129-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">129</xref>,
 <xref rid="B130-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">130</xref>]. Being dietary fiber-rich products, such foodstuffs can delay the stomach emptying, increasing satiety and, for this reason they are mainly used as an anti-obesity agent. Moreover, these products, being low-caloric foods, are also used in KDs as alternative products to traditional cereal based foodstuffs. Beyond that, the inclusion of glucomannan-based products in KDs can lead to some benefits in patients’ health status. Some small-sized studies have shown that glucomannan supplementation can reduce, in both children and adults, the risk of constipation, increasing defecation frequency and the stool bulk without increasing the risk of side effects like abdominal cramping, borborygmi, bloating, and flatulence [
 <xref rid="B131-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">131</xref>,
 <xref rid="B132-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">132</xref>,
 <xref rid="B133-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">133</xref>,
 <xref rid="B134-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">134</xref>,
 <xref rid="B135-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">135</xref>,
 <xref rid="B136-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">136</xref>]. In addition, there is some evidence that glucomannan has prebiotic effects, as it increases the proportion of bifidobacteria and lactobacilli, and reduces the proportion of clostridia to total fecal bacteria [
 <xref rid="B135-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">135</xref>]. Such effects seem to be partially related to the increment of short chain fatty acids and the decreased fecal pH following the consumption of glucomannan [
 <xref rid="B135-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">135</xref>]. However, a further double-blind, placebo-controlled randomized trial did not find any amelioration of constipation in children treated with glucomannan compared to the children treated with a placebo [
 <xref rid="B137-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">137</xref>]. Further benefits, resulting from glucomannans consumption, are related to lipid and glucose metabolism. Recent meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials shows that glucomannans lowered total and LDL cholesterol, triglycerides, and fasting blood glucose, whereas the use of glucomannan did not appear to affect HDL cholesterol or either systolic or diastolic blood pressure [
 <xref rid="B138-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B139-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">139</xref>]. In the light of this, there are no contraindications to the use of glucomannan-based products in KDs. However, since these are highly-satiating foods, caution should be exercised when including portions in the dietary plan. Excessive portions of these products can lead to early satiety, with consequent non-consumption of the whole meal, resulting in KR variation and a possible effect on the level of circulating ketone bodies.
</p>
