<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">In Baringo, 30 years of grassland restoration was not sufficient to restore plant species richness. This may be partly due to the long history of land degradation in the study area
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>
 </sup> and a likely depletion of the soil seed bank. In Afar Region, Ethiopia, experimental studies to restore grasslands after removal of 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> led to the establishment of species-rich communities within a few years (B. Megersa, unpubl. results). Restoration of high plant diversity may considerably increase carbon capture and storage rates on degraded and abandoned land
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, in order to accelerate the restoration of species-rich plant communities, particularly on land with a long degradation history, reseeding of a diverse set of native species should be considered. Areas with low 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> invasion tended to have a higher species richness than degraded, restored and areas with high 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> invasion. At low densities, 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> trees may provide shade for annual plants to grow underneath their canopy. Annual plants do not, however, provide the same ES as perennial plants, e.g. the bunch grass 
 <italic>Cenchrus ciliaris</italic>, as they do not build up extensive below-ground biomass and the above-ground biomass dries up soon after the rains stop. Furthermore, 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> is highly prolific hence cover densities transition rapidly which suppresses the understory vegetation. Plant species richness in 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic>-invaded habitats drops to very low levels once 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> has reached 50% cover
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>
 </sup>, which has been attributed to competitive exclusion of the slow-growing shade-intolerant herbaceous savanna species by 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic>, either due to its allelopathic effects or through competition for water during the dry seasons
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
