<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par112">
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par113">To shape public opinion on the significance of cannabis and cannabinoids use for medical and scientific purposes both among specialists (doctors, pharmacists, scientists), and Ukrainian citizens: 58% of pharmacy students from the Bogomolets National Medical University has noted that it is ‘very important’, and 38% – that it is ‘rather important’. Moreover, it is worth focusing on the principal difference between recreational and medical cannabis. Because of prejudices, lack of knowledge and negative convictions in the society there may occur marginalization of potential patients (Bottorff et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2013</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par114">A significant role in shaping public opinion on medical cannabis is played by active participation of various stakeholders, in particular by public organizations, opinion leaders among representatives of science, health care, business, politics, other spheres of public activity. For this, various instruments of communication with the public should be used, considering the reach of audience, impact effectiveness and the possibilities of integration to increase a desirable result. For instance, for the second year in a row, the International Cannabis Conference is held in Ukraine. There are physicians, scientists and patients from the USA, Czechia, Switzerland, Germany, Portugal, France, Spain, Israel among the speakers experienced in practical application of cannabis-based products and with information on the achievements of contemporary science (Ukrainian Association of Medical Cannabis 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2019</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par115">To develop and put into practice informational training programs in educational institutions (schools, colleges, universities) concerning importance of using narcotics-containing plants as medicinal products for the treatment of certain symptoms and diseases, with a focus on the risks of their application for recreational purposes, especially by children and teenagers.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par116">Among the professional community, in particular among the representatives of the health care system, who to a large extent determine availability of medicinal products and CBMP for patients, it is necessary to run awareness campaigns concerning cannabis plant, cannabinoids, their properties and advantages, usage risks, interaction with endocannabinoid system, etc. Such campaigns can be organized in the form of practical seminars, lectures, courses, congresses, conferences, working sessions including those with the participation of state bodies. It will result in the development and publishing of recommendations and guidelines, conference, articles, monographs and other scientific and practical materials.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par117">Cannabis plant should be considered in complex speaking of high attractiveness of potential cannabis markets. It can be applied in various economic industries, different from health care, beauty and well-being, like building materials (hempcrete), seed-pressed oils for paints and sealants, biocomposites, green energy and others.(Riboulet-Zemouli et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2019</xref>). To implement the win-win strategy, value orientations should be formed in a society that can create long-term benefits for all stakeholders.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par118">Creation of new cannabis-related spheres and markets will directly influence various social and economic indices in the country, especially if high value-added products are manufactured. It will improve humans and pets’ health and life quality, create additional workplaces, promote the entrepreneurship, science, innovative technologies, and consequently provide a steady revenue for local and state budgets.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
