<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Variability observed among populations is not surprising since a high level of genetic heterogeneity is expected in plant species that are able to grow in a wide range of environmental conditions. Morphological differences have been reported in ecotypes and populations of many weeds (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Bajwa et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Van Etten et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2020</xref>). A higher level of variability in morphological parameters is maintained in many of the weedy or wild relatives of crop plants (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Pickersgill, 1981</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Hubner et al., 2003</xref>). In fact, identification of weed species based solely on their morphological traits can be difficult (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Sammour et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Khaing et al., 2013</xref>) as weeds can exhibit a large number of morphs depending on the environment in which they are grown. The observed variation in morphological appearance might be explained in three possible ways: (1) naturally existing variations (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Chan and Sun, 1997</xref>); (2) mixed mating system that may facilitate the natural introgression process; (3) polyploidy, leading to gene combination, might have resulted in higher morphological variation (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Andini et al., 2013</xref>). Weedy plants are regarded as rich sources of variation and a repository of genetic diversity. These weedy populations are known to be able to survive in a large variety of habitats (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Frankton and Mulligan, 1987</xref>) and the populations studied were collected from a variety of locations across their range; therefore, it is unsurprising that the different selection pressures they faced in their past have shaped the morphologies they adopt in a common garden experiment. Although self-pollination is more likely to occur, Amaranths can also cross pollinate through wind, with mean outcrossing rates ranging from 4 to 34% (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Kulakow and Hauptli, 1994</xref>); therefore, Amaranths have the capacity to maintain beneficial traits as well as accumulate new ones. Polyploidy is common among plant species and recent large-scale transcriptomics indicates that whole-genome duplications have occurred repeatedly throughout flowering plants evolution (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Leebens-Mack et al., 2019</xref>).
</p>
