<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>After chemical treatment, an overall trend of a decrease in non-structural carbohydrate content and an increase in lipid content was observed in xylem. Similar results were observed in a study of growth regulator-induced sapwood discoloration of 
 <italic>Quercus serrata</italic> (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Moungsrimuangdee et al., 2011</xref>) and consistent with the chemical changes during the formation of natural heartwood (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Magel et al., 1994</xref>). The depletion of storage starch was thought to be associated with parenchyma cells’ death, and this relationship controlled the formation of heartwood (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Islam et al., 2012</xref>). When the xylem was exposed to these chemicals, large amounts of phytoalexins (heartwood substances) were synthesized in the parenchyma cells and transported into the infected vessels to inhibit further infection. As precursors, the NSCs supplied a large quantity of carbon skeletons for the synthesis of heartwood substances (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Magel et al., 1994</xref>). In addition, these chemicals may affect the storage functions of NSCs by altering the pH of the xylem (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Pagliarani et al., 2019</xref>). After one month of treatment, the levels of NSCs in positions II and III decreased significantly, while those in position I did not decline until after six months when the NSCs in position III were almost exhausted. These results indicated that when the NSCs in position III were consumed to a certain extent, the NSCs in positions II and I were successively consumed. Since no lipid accumulated in position I, it was speculated that the NSCs in position I might be transferred to position II or III in wood ray parenchyma. Some studies have suggested that NSCs could be transported in both directions in wood ray parenchyma (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Furze et al., 2018</xref>). The NSCs transported outward could maintain the “Leakage-retrieval Mechanism” of phloem (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">De Schepper et al., 2013</xref>), and the NSCs transported inward might be used as substrate for secondary metabolism in xylem, such as for the synthesis of heartwood substances (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Magel et al., 1991</xref>). In addition, stachyose, galactose, and arabinose were exhausted first, which might be related to their characteristics and functions. These oligosaccharides or monosaccharides are small storage materials and are the most easily utilized carbohydrates in trees (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Saranpää and Höll, 1989</xref>). Interestingly, after six months of treatment, the arabinose and galactose contents increased in position III of each treatment. The arabinose and galactose produced in position III might be derived from partial hydrolysis of hemicellulose in the cell wall during the formation of heartwood (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Saranpää and Höll, 1989</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Fischer and Höll, 1992</xref>). Galactose has been reported to stimulate the production of ethylene in tomato fruits (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 1987</xref>), and ethylene was thought to be closely associated with heartwood formation (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Hillis, 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Cui et al., 2019</xref>). Therefore, NSCs can directly provide raw materials for the synthesis of heartwood substances and also indirectly regulate physiological processes related to heartwood formation. In general, as observed in the formation of natural heartwood, in the process of chemical induction, NSCs were continuously consumed, and heartwood substances were gradually synthesized in xylem, while hemicellulose in the xylem cell wall might have been partially hydrolyzed. However, the metabolic characteristics and physiological functions of specific carbohydrates involved in the synthesis of heartwood substances are little known and deserve further study.
</p>
