<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31">Although mammals were not included in the current stimulus sets, it is very likely that younger Kune speakers—especially young adults and children—would struggle to name all but the largest mammals that are present on their lands. While assisting an elderly Kune speaker in a language and culture class at Maningrida College in 2014, the author noted that the children in the mixed-age classroom (the eldest child being around 14 years old) labelled all local kangaroo species with the general term 
 <italic>kunj</italic> ‘wallaby/kangaroo’, instead of using the highly specialised terminology that would presumably be known to their parents. Kune and related languages recognize several kangaroo and wallaby ethnotaxa, and have distinct words to describe the different life stages and gender of each kangaroo/wallaby species, as well as distinct verbs to describe their hopping action [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. However, it appeared that the children in that classroom were hearing many of these words for the first time from their elderly teacher. A reduction in the consumption of wild meat in modern times is probably responsible for this phenomenon, but equally responsible is the local extinction of a number of small mammals from around Buluhkaduru, and Arnhem Land in general. External factors such as more intense bushfires, prior to Indigenous-style land management that started in 2006 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], and the arrival of invasive species such as the cane toad (
 <italic>Bufo marinus</italic>) have led to the disappearance of once common species like the Northern Quoll (
 <italic>Dasyurus hallucatus</italic>) and the Northern Hopping Mouse (
 <italic>Notomys aquilo</italic>). Both species are officially listed as endangered, with the IUCN Red List of Threatened Species even stating that the latter may no longer occur on the Australian mainland [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. No wonder, then, that most Kune children will have never seen, and may probably never see, the animals that their elders once called 
 <italic>yulukyuluk</italic> and 
 <italic>kidjikidjidayhdayh.</italic>
</p>
