<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The proteomic analysis involves an analysis of the proteome profile of untreated and essential oil-treated cells to identify and quantify differentially expressed proteins signals. Methods that allow such a comparison are 2D-SDS PAGE and LC-MS/MS. Kovács et al used 2D-SDS PAGE coupled with LC-MS/MS to compare the proteome of untreated and peppermint essential oil-treated 
 <italic>C. jejuni</italic>. Their study showed an increased expression of oxidative stress-related proteins such as 
 <italic>dps, sodB</italic>, and 
 <italic>katA</italic> following treatment with peppermint essential oil.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr42-1176934320938391" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>
 </sup> In a similar approach, Barbosa et al investigated the effect of oregano essential oil on 
 <italic>Salmonella enteritidis</italic>. A total of 15 oxidative stress-related proteins (
 <italic>clpB, htpG, luxS</italic>, toxic shock protein, and 
 <italic>usp</italic>) were upregulated in oregano essential oil-treated 
 <italic>S. enteritidis</italic> cells based on the assay developed using 2D-SDS PAGE coupled with LC-MS/MS.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr44-1176934320938391" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>
 </sup> Yang et al observed similar oxidative stress induction by comparing the proteome profile of untreated and cinnamon bark essential oil-treated clinical-relevant strain of 
 <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> cells using nano LC-MS/MS. The group has previously performed biochemical studies on the mode of action of cinnamon bark essential oil against the same clinically relevant strains of 
 <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic>, revealing that essential oil disrupts bacterial membrane using zeta potential measurement, outer membrane permeability assay, and electron microscopy.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr9-1176934320938391" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 </sup> The follow-up study using nano LC-MS/MS showed an increase in the abundance of oxidative stress-sensitive proteins such as glycyl radical cofactor, catalase peroxidase and DNA mismatch repair protein, which indicates the presence of oxidative stress during cinnamon bark essential oil treatment.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr45-1176934320938391" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>
 </sup> Thus, they postulated that cinnamon bark essential oil induces oxidative stress that disrupts the bacterial membrane via lipid peroxidation. In a separate study, Yang et al investigated the mode of action of lavender essential oil on the proteome of 
 <italic>K. pneumoniae.</italic> The team performed proteomic profiling between untreated and lavender essential oil-treated 
 <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> which has revealed an increase in the abundance of oxidative stress regulators such as NAD(P)H dehydrogenase (quinone) and autonomous glycyl radical cofactor while decreasing the abundance of oxidative stress-sensitive proteins, suggesting the presence of oxidative stress. The proteome profile also showed a drastic decrease in membrane-related proteins (NADH-quinone oxidoreductase subunit B, outer membrane protein A and ATP synthase subunit C), and cytoplasmic proteins (mannitol-1-phosphate 5-dehydrogenase and D-erythrose-4-phosphate dehydrogenase), showed signs of membrane disruption.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr5-1176934320938391" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
 </sup> Subsequent biochemical assays were carried out to validate the observation from the comparative analysis. For instance, scanning electron microscopy, zeta potential assay, outer membrane permeability assays, and intracellular material leakage assays were carried out to show membrane disruption whereas reactive oxygen species measurement and lipid peroxidation assays were performed to verify the presence of oxidative stress during lavender essential oil treatment. The assays mentioned previously revealed that lavender essential oil-treated cells have disrupted the bacterial membrane and increased reactive oxygen species, as well as lipid peroxidation activity. The team concluded that lavender essential oil disrupts the bacterial membrane by inducing oxidative stress and causing membrane disruption.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr5-1176934320938391" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
 </sup> Both studies by Yang et al showed similarities in the mode of action of cinnamon bark and lavender essential oil in terms of proteomic profile, with both essential oil-treated proteomic profiles decreasing in membrane-related protein and cytoplasmic protein while increasing in oxidative stress response proteins. This indicated that both essential oils induced oxidative stress, which later resulted in lipid peroxidation of the bacterial membrane. Such a process disrupts the bacterial membrane, which leads to intracellular leakage and eventually kills the cell. Also, the presence of reactive oxygen species damages oxidative stress-sensitive materials such as protein and genetic material that would also be lethal to the treated cells.
</p>
