<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The turn of the 21st century has seen great developments and efforts directed toward containing and eradicating the spread of infectious diseases around the globe. Drug research and innovation within the pharmaceutical industry and academia, as well as government vaccination campaigns, are at the forefront of these endeavours. The elimination of wildtype cases of the infectious viral disease, polio, which has been recently declared “eradicated” from the African continent, attests to the progress made within the field of infectious diseases [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Despite these successes, infectious diseases like malaria remain prevalent and still burden the health-care sector and threaten the lives of many in endemic regions in Sub-Saharan Africa and parts of Asia. Of the estimated 228 million cases of malaria, in 2018, Africa was reported to have borne the largest burden, accounting for approximately 93% (213 million) of these cases [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Unfortunately, treatment of this disease is proving challenging, due in part to the emergence of new, tenacious strains of the malaria parasite that are displaying resistance to current frontline drugs used to treat this disease. Of the five 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> species known to cause malaria, 
 <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> is the most virulent, and according to the World Health Organisation accounted for more than 400,000 deaths in 2018 alone [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The plight of antimalarial drug resistance prompted the introduction of artemisinin-based combination therapies (ACTs), which have proven fruitful in this struggle, as this treatment regimen involves combining antimalarials with independent modes of action to improve treatment outcomes and counter the threat of resistance [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. However, reports of 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> strains developing resistance to ACTs have already been recorded [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This demands an expansion of the antimalarial drug arsenal and search for innovative drug candidates possessing novel mechanistic modalities unknown to the malaria parasite to combat the development of clinical resistance.
</p>
