<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Complement Altern Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Complement Altern Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Complementary and Alternative Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6882</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6560905</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2548</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-019-2548-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Gut microbial modulation in the treatment of chemotherapy-induced diarrhea with Shenzhu Capsule</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jing</given-names></name><address><email>wangjing2018@foxmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Wuwen</given-names></name><address><email>fengwuwen1990@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Shiyang</given-names></name><address><email>zhangshiyang2017@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Lu</given-names></name><address><email>chenlu_cdutcm@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Fei</given-names></name><address><email>tangfei0227@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>Yongcheng</given-names></name><address><email>shengyongcheng1996@foxmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5763-6147</contrib-id><name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><address><email>aohui2005@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Cheng</given-names></name><address><email>pengchengcxy@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0376 205X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411304.3</institution-id><institution>School of Pharmacy, </institution><institution>Chengdu University of Traditional Chinese Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Chengdu, 611137 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0376 205X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411304.3</institution-id><institution>Innovative Institute of Chinese Medicine and Pharmacy, </institution><institution>Chengdu University of Traditional Chinese Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Chengdu, 611137 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>126</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Gut microbiota plays a crucial role in the treatment of gastrointestinal (GI) diseases such as chemotherapy-induced diarrhea (CID). Shenzhu Capsule (SZC) is a Chinese herbal formula, which is composed of Renshen (rhizomes of <italic>Panax ginseng</italic> C. A. Mey.) and Baizhu (rhizomes of <italic>Atractylodes macrocephala</italic> Koidz.). Many Chinese traditional anti-diarrheal formulae that contain Renshen and Baizhu are capable of effectively alleviating CID. However, the efficacy in vivo and potential mechanism of SZC (the form of compatibility of Renshen and Baizhu) in the treatment of CID had not been elucidated. Here, this study aimed to investigate whether SZC exhibited the anti-diarrheal activity, and whether gut microbiota was involved in the therapeutic effect of SZC on CID.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">High performance liquid chromatography (HPLC), gas chromatography-mass spectrometer (GC-MS) and infrared spectroscopy (IR) analyses were used to characterize the extracted components in SZC. The mice were orally administrated with SZC in a preventive mode on the first 2&#x02009;days of this experiment, and then intraperitoneally injected with 5-FU (40&#x02009;mg/kg/d) for 6&#x02009;days. SZC treatment lasted until the 3rd day after the end of 5-FU chemotherapy. We investigated the effects of SZC on body weights, diarrhea, thymus/spleen indexes, colonic tissues, and gut microbiota. Colonic histology was examined by hematoxylin-eosin (HE) staining. 16S rDNA Amplicon Sequencing was used to analyze the gut microbial structure from fecal samples.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">SZC significantly increased the body weights and thymus/spleen indexes, alleviated diarrhea, and reversed histopathological changes of colons. In addition, gut microbiota analysis revealed that the overall structure of gut microbiota in CID mice was disturbed, but reversed to the normal state after SZC treatment. At genus level, SZC significantly inhibited the growth of some potential pathogens associated with diarrhea, such as <italic>Clostridiumm</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Parabacteroides</italic>, <italic>Alloprevotella</italic>, <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> and <italic>Pseudomonas</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">In our study, these data illustrated that SZC inhibited the growth of many potential pathogens during the alleviation of CID. Gut microbial modulation was associated with the anti-diarrheal activity of SZC.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Gut microbiota</kwd><kwd>Chemotherapy-induced diarrhea</kwd><kwd>Herbal medicine</kwd><kwd>5-fluorouracil</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>81891012</award-id><award-id>81630101</award-id><award-id>81503272</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Cheng</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Department of Science and Technology of Sichuan Province </institution></funding-source><award-id>2017JY0187</award-id><award-id>2017TD0001</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par24">Gut microbiota, known as a complex ecological community colonized in human gastrointestinal (GI) tract, can interact with host factors to affect normal physiology and diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Healthy gut microbiota contributes to the metabolism of nutrition and drugs, structural integrity of intestinal mucosal barrier, immune regulation, and inhibition of pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Gut microbiota in the disordered state is likely to trigger many diseases, such as diarrhea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], inflammatory bowel disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], metabolism disturbances (obesity, insulin resistance and diabetes) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], and cardiovascular diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Due to its ubiquitous roles in the maintenance of gut homeostasis and human health, gut microbiota exhibits great effects on the development and progression of diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par25">Among the diseases related to altered gut microbiota, chemotherapy-induced diarrhea (CID) is one of the most common digestive complications in cancer patients treated with chemotherapeutic drugs such as fluoropyrimidines and irinotecan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. CID has been found to occur in 50&#x02013;80% of cancer patients, especially those with advanced cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In addition, severe diarrhea (grade 3/4) was reported in 16.6% colorectal cancer patients receiving 5-fluorouracil (5-FU), the first-line chemotherapeutic drug for colorectal cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. A growing number of evidences showed that CID could directly threaten the lives of patients, or indirectly affect the cycle and efficacy of chemotherapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Therefore, at present, medication is being introduced into the treatment of CID. Modern medicines such as loperamide and octreotide are often used to relieve CID in clinical practices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. However, their therapeutic effects are not satisfactory sometimes. For example, loperamide cannot alleviate several diarrheal features including abdominal cramps, an inability to eat, increasing fatigue, increasing weakness, chest pain, gastrointestinal bleeding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Long-acting octreotide acetate was not effective in preventing or relieving diarrhea in cancer patients undergoing chemoradiation therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In a word, there is still a lack of safe and effective modern medicines for the prevention and treatment of CID. Therefore, considerable attentions have been paid to complementary or alternative medicines such as traditional herbal medicines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p><p id="Par26">Shenzhu Capsule (SZC), a formula of Chinese herbal medicine, is composed of ginsenosides and polysaccharides from Renshen (rhizomes of <italic>Panax ginseng</italic> C. A. Mey.), essential oil and polysaccharides from Baizhu (rhizomes of <italic>Atractylodes macrocephala</italic> Koidz.). In the past few years, our researches mainly focused on the therapeutic effects of SZC for gastrointestinal diseases. For example, we had reported that SZC induced apoptosis of gastric cancer cells through mitochondrial pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In addition, SZC could reversely regulate the expression of some genes (metabolic, ion channels and transport proteins) in SGC-7901 tumor-bearing mice, resulting in the improvement of gastric cancer through multiple targets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Moreover, SZC not only regulated immune and inflammatory responses during the treatment of ulcerative colitis (UC), but also acted on UC complications (bloody diarrhea) and prevented UC from developing into colorectal cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. At present, our attentions are being paid to investigate whether SZC exhibits therapeutic effect on CID, the GI side effect of chemotherapeutic drugs. As is known, many Chinese traditional anti-diarrheal formulae such as Shenling Baizhu Powder, Buzhong Yiqi Decoction and Sijunzi Decoction, all of which contain Renshen and Baizhu, had been proved to possess the ability of alleviating CID [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. However, no study has determined if SZC (the form of compatibility of Renshen and Baizhu) exerts any therapeutic effect on CID. In recent years, gut microbiota has become an important frontier to reveal the therapeutic mechanisms of medicines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Therefore, it is of great significance to investigate the therapeutic effect of SZC on CID based on gut microbiota.</p><p id="Par27">In this study, we simulated a CID model in mice receiving 5-FU chemotherapy to evaluate the efficacy and interpret the potential mechanism of SZC in the treatment of diarrhea. Both diarrhea rates and histological changes of colonic tissues were recorded. 16S rDNA Amplicon Sequencing was used to analyze the gut microbial structure from fecal samples.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Chemicals and reagents</title><p id="Par28">5-FU injection (25&#x02009;mg/mL, No. 1708061) was provided by Tianjin JinYao Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd. (Tianjin, China). Standard compounds (purity &#x0003e;&#x02009;98%) of ginsenosides Rg1, Rc, Rd, Re, Rb1, Rb2 and Rf were purchased from Chengdu Must Bio-Technology Co. Ltd. (Chengdu, China). Other chemicals and reagents were obtained from commercial sources.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Experimental animals</title><p id="Par29">Twenty-four, 8-week-old SPF graded Kunming mice (12 males and 12 females) (Chengdu Dossy Experimental Animal Co., LTD., Chengdu, China, No. SCXK (chuan) 014&#x02013;028) were adapted to the laboratory environment for 3&#x02009;days before the experiment. The mice were housed under the standard environment (temperature of 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, humidity of 50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5%, and a 12&#x02009;h light/12&#x02009;h dark cycle) with free access to the same water and diets. All efforts were made to minimize animal suffering. All experimental procedures involving animals were agreed by Animal Ethics Committee (Approval No. AEC-201706) in Chengdu University of Traditional Chinese Medicine (CDUTCM) (Chengdu, China).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Collection of Renshen and Baizhu</title><p id="Par30">The materials were purchased from Lotus Pond Chinese herbal medicine market, Chengdu, Sichuan Province, People&#x02019;s Republic of China. They were respectively identified as the rhizomes of <italic>Panax ginseng</italic> C. A. Mey. and <italic>Atractylodes macrocephala</italic> Koidz. by Associate Professor Lu Chen from School of Pharmacy in CDUTCM. The voucher specimens of Renshen and Baizhu (No. 17102101 and 17102102, respectively) were deposited at School of Pharmacy in CDUTCM.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Preparation and characterization of SZC</title><p id="Par31">SZC is composed of ginsenosides and polysaccharides isolated from Renshen, essential oil and polysaccharides isolated from Baizhu. In this study, we extracted and characterized those components according to the preparing process of SZC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Preparation and high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) characterization of ginsenosides from Renshen in SZC</title><p id="Par32">Renshen powder (200&#x02009;g) was refluxed 3 times by 60% ethanol (8 &#x000d7;) for total 6&#x02009;h. Then, the combined extracts were concentrated by vacuum-rotary evaporation. The concentrate was eluted by 70% ethanol on D101 macroporous adsorptive resin. All the collected eluents were concentrated, and then dried at 40&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in a vacuum oven. Final residue of ginsenosides (1.4&#x02009;mg) was dissolved in 1&#x02009;mL methanol and then filtered through a 0.45&#x02009;&#x003bc;m filter membrane. Ginsenosides were characterized by HPLC (1260, Agilent, USA) with a C18 column (250&#x02009;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;4.6&#x02009;mm i.d., particle size 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;m) (Cosmosil, Japan). The column was eluted at 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with a detection wavelength at 203&#x02009;nm and an injection volume of 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;L. The flow rate of the mobile phase of water (A) and acetonitrile (B) was set at 1.0&#x02009;mL/min. Gradient separation was based on the following: 0&#x02013;10&#x02009;min, 18&#x02013;21% B; 10&#x02013;20&#x02009;min, 21&#x02013;22% B; 20&#x02013;30&#x02009;min, 22&#x02013;26% B; 30&#x02013;40&#x02009;min, 26&#x02013;30% B; 40&#x02013;55&#x02009;min, 30&#x02013;32% B; 55&#x02013;75&#x02009;min, 32&#x02013;33.8% B; 75&#x02013;90&#x02009;min, 33.8&#x02013;38% B; 90&#x02013;105&#x02009;min, 38&#x02013;45% B; 105&#x02013;110&#x02009;min, 45&#x02013;18% B. And the standard curves were obtained based on the absorbencies of different concentrations of standard ginsenosides Rg1, Re, Rf, Rc, Rd, Rb1 and Rb2.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Preparation and gas chromatography-mass spectrometer (GC-MS) characterization of essential oil from Baizhu in SZC</title><p id="Par33">Baizhu powder (200&#x02009;g) was refluxed by distilled water (10 &#x000d7;) for 12&#x02009;h. Final essential oil was gathered by steam distillation from the powder. Essential oil was characterized by GC-MS (GC 7890A and MS 5975C, Agilent, USA). Chromatographic separation was achieved on a capillary column HP-5MS (30&#x02009;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;mm i.d.; film thickness 0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;m). The electron ionization system operated at 70&#x02009;eV of ionization energy. Helium was used as the carrier gas. 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;L sample (essential oil: n-hexane, 1: 100 dilution) was injected and the injector temperature was set at 230.0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Initial oven temperature was set at 100.0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, then increased to 120.0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C at the rate of 3.0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C/min and held at 120.0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min, and finally increased to 220.0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C at the rate of 3.0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C/min. MS was recorded in the range of 35&#x02013;550&#x02009;m/z at the rate of 1.0 scan/s. Identification of different components in essential oil was based on the comparison with the known constituents that stored in National Institute of Standards and Technology Library (NIST14.0).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Preparation and infrared spectroscopy (IR) characterization of polysaccharides from Renshen and Baizhu in SZC</title><p id="Par34">Renshen (200&#x02009;g) or Baizhu (200&#x02009;g) powder was refluxed by distilled water (10 &#x000d7;) for 2&#x02009;h. The procedure was repeated 3 times. Then these extracted solutions were combined, concentrated, and cooled (4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) for 12&#x02009;h. The cooled concentrate solution was precipitated in 60% ethanol, and final residues were dried at 40&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in a vacuum oven. The characterization was carried out on a FTIR Spectrum (cary 660, Agilent, USA). Polysaccharides (1&#x02009;mg) from Renshen or Baizhu were mixed with 150&#x02009;mg KBr and homogenized by a pestle in the mortar. The mixture was then made by a hydraulic press into a slice, which was analyzed in IR at the wavenumber region from 400 to 4000&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Experimental design</title><p id="Par35">According to the clinical dosages of Renshen (3&#x02009;g per time) and Baizhu (3&#x02009;g per time) (two Chinese medicines in SZC) in China Phannacopeia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], we chose the oral doses of ginsenosides and polysaccharides from Renshen as 126.7&#x02009;mg/kg/d and 176.3&#x02009;mg/kg/d respectively, and the oral doses of essential oil and polysaccharides from Baizhu as 35.3&#x02009;&#x003bc;L/kg/d and 192.3&#x02009;mg/kg/d respectively for mice. SZC was mixed in 0.1% sodium carboxymethyl cellulose solution. Twenty-four mice were randomly assigned into three groups (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8): the control, model and SZC groups, with 4 males and 4 females per group. Our modeling method was based on the existing literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The mice were orally administrated with SZC in a preventive mode on the first 2&#x02009;days of the experiment, and then intraperitoneally injected with 5-FU (40&#x02009;mg/kg/d) for 6&#x02009;days. Mice in the SZC group were orally administrated with SZC half an hour before 5-FU chemotherapy. SZC treatment lasted until the 3rd day after the end of 5-FU chemotherapy. Mice in the control group received equal volume of liquid solvent for the whole 11&#x02009;days, while the untreated mice in the model group received 5-FU chemotherapy on the 3&#x02013;8&#x02009;days.</p><p id="Par36">Both body weights and diarrhea states were recorded every day. For the diarrhea evaluation, the mice with moist and unformed stools, or perianal stains, were deemed to show the clinical symptoms of diarrhea. The calculation formula of diarrhea rates in each group was given as follow: the diarrhea rate (%)&#x02009;=&#x02009;the number of diarrheal mice/the number of mice &#x000d7;&#x02009;100%. Twenty-four hours after the last administration, fecal sample (4&#x02009;g) was collected in sterile plastic tube and stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. All the animals were sacrificed by cervical dislocation. Then thymuses and spleens were removed after the sacrifice of mice. Thymus and spleen indexes of each mouse were calculated according to the following formula: thymus (spleen) index&#x02009;=&#x02009;thymus (spleen) weight/body weight (mg/g).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Histological observation</title><p id="Par37">The colon segments (2&#x02009;cm) of each mouse were collected and fixed in 4% formaldehyde solution after the sacrifice of mice. Then the colonic samples were embedded by paraffin, sliced (4&#x02009;&#x003bc;m), and stained with hematoxylin-eosin (HE). The histological changes of colonic segments were observed with the microscope (DMI300B, Leica, Germany).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Gut microbiota analysis</title><p id="Par38">The genomic DNA of fecal samples was extracted by sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS). After that, the concentration of DNA was detected using agarose gel electrophoresis. The V3&#x02013;V4 region of bacterial 16S rRNA gene was amplified by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) with 341F&#x02013;806R primer set. All PCR reactions were induced by High-Fidelity PCR Master Mix (New England Biolabs, USA). PCR products were detected by electrophoresis with 2% agarose gel, and then purified by Qiagen Gel Extraction Kit (Qiagen, Germany). TruSeq&#x000ae; DNA PCR-Free Sample Preparation Kit (Illumina, USA) was used to generate sequencing library. Library quality was evaluated on Qubit@2.0 Fluorometer (Thermo Scientific, USA) and Agilent Bioanalyzer 2100 system. Finally, the Library was conducted on Illumina HiSeq 2500 platform (Novogene, Beijing, China).</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Bioinformatics analysis</title><p id="Par39">Paired-end reads of each sample were merged by FLASH (Version 1.2.7) to get raw tags. High-quality clean tags were generated from the strict filtration of raw tags by QIIME (Version 1.9.1). Final effective tags were produced after the removal of chimera sequences in the tags, which were detected by gold database (Version 1.9.1) and UCHIME Algorithm. The sequences at 97% identity were clustered into the same operational taxonomic units (OTUs) by Uparse (Version 7.0.1001). Then the representative sequence of each OTU was selected for the species annotation. MUSCLE (Version 3.8.31) was used for the multiple sequence alignments to get the phylogenetic relationships. The OTUs abundance information was normalized by the sequence number standard. ACE and Shannon indexes that respectively indicated richness and diversity of gut microbiota were calculated on QIIME (Version 1.7.0). Linear discriminant analysis effect size (LEfSe) was used to detect the dominant bacterial community difference among groups. The lowest screening value of linear discriminant analysis (LDA) in LEfSe software was defaulted to 4. Venn, LEfSe and Non-Metric Multi-Dimensional Scaling (NMDS) diagrams were built on R software (Version 2.15.3). Unweighted Pair-group Method with Arithmetic Means (UPGMA) Clustering was performed on QIIME software (Version 1.7.0).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par40">Statistical analysis was performed on SPSS (Version 21). Data were presented as means &#x000b1; Standard Error of Mean (SEM). One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Least Significant Difference (LSD) test was used to analyze the statistical differences between multiple groups. Kruskal-Wallis test was applied if the data did not meet the assumptions of ANOVA. A value of <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>Chemical compositions of SZC</title><p id="Par41">As shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, the quantitations of ginsenosides standards showed good linearities within 6.25&#x02013;200.00&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL. The compositions of ginsenosides Rg1, Re, Rf, Rb1, Rc, Rb2 and Rd in total ginsenosides were 46.98&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.25, 55.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.66, 12.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11, 132.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.96, 83.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.39, 70.66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.34, and 31.61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.32&#x02009;mg/g, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b, the five main constituents such as <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-eudesmene (3.82%), eudesma-3,7(11)-diene (12.49%), atractylone (51.67%), isopetasan (2.07%), and 1-methoxy-2-(1-methyl-2-methylenecyclopentyl) benzene (5.10%) were identified in essential oil of Baizhu. Atractylone was considered as the representative constituent of essential oil in Baizhu.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Linear relationships with correlation coefficients for ginsenosides standards</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Standards</th><th>Linear relationships</th><th>
<italic>r</italic>
</th><th>Linear range(&#x003bc;g/mL)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Rg1</td><td><italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;18.72 <italic>X</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;40.44</td><td>0.9999</td><td>6.25&#x02013;200.00</td></tr><tr><td>Re</td><td><italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;14.48 <italic>X</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;40.82</td><td>0.9995</td><td>6.25&#x02013;200.00</td></tr><tr><td>Rf</td><td><italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;20.58 <italic>X</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;55.34</td><td>0.9993</td><td>6.25&#x02013;200.00</td></tr><tr><td>Rb1</td><td><italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13.99 <italic>X</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;47.49</td><td>0.9995</td><td>6.25&#x02013;200.00</td></tr><tr><td>Rc</td><td><italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;14.30 <italic>X</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;25.17</td><td>0.9998</td><td>6.25&#x02013;200.00</td></tr><tr><td>Rb2</td><td><italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13.79 <italic>X</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;13.62</td><td>0.9999</td><td>6.25&#x02013;200.00</td></tr><tr><td>Rd</td><td><italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;16.78 <italic>X</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;25.37</td><td>0.9995</td><td>6.25&#x02013;200.00</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Chemical characterization in SZC. (<bold>a</bold>) HPLC profile of ginsenosides from Renshen. (<bold>b</bold>) GC-MS profile of essential oil from Baizhu. (<bold>c</bold>) IR absorption spectrum of polysaccharides from Renshen. (<bold>d</bold>) IR absorption spectrum of polysaccharides from Baizhu</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2019_2548_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par42">IR scanning results showed that both polysaccharides extracts of Renshen and Baizhu showed characteristic functional groups of polysaccharides (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c and d). The bands at 3524.26&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> and 3535.44&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> were due to O-H groups of polysaccharides from Renshen and Baizhu, respectively. The C=O groups in Renshen and Baizhu polysaccharides caused the increases of the absorption bands at 1741.45&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> and 1748.61&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup>, respectively. In addition, the bands at 1158.56&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> and 1150.02&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> (polysaccharides of Renshen and Baizhu, respectively), which were also the characteristic absorption bands of polysaccharides, resulted from the stretching vibration of C-O in C-O-C cyclic ether.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>SZC ameliorates diarrhea and increases thymus/spleen indexes in mice with CID</title><p id="Par43">The mice were injected with 5-FU for 6&#x02009;days during the treatment of SZC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). During the first 4&#x02009;days, there was no significant difference in body weights among the control, model and SZC groups. Mice in the model group injected with 5-FU experienced weight loss compared with the control group from days 5&#x02013;10, and had the lowest weight at the end of the experiment. Treatment with SZC significantly prevented weight loss in CID mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). From days 4&#x02013;8, diarrhea rates increased in the untreated model group, while the clinical symptoms of diarrhea were not observed in the control group. At all time points, the diarrhea rates of the SZC group were obviously lower than those of the model group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c). In addition, the thymus and spleen indexes in the model group decreased significantly after 5-FU chemotherapy, whereas SZC markedly inhibited the decreases of thymus and spleen indexes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The effects of SZC on body weight, diarrhea, and thymus/spleen indexes in mice with CID (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8, male/femal&#x02009;=&#x02009;4). (<bold>a</bold>) Experimental process of CID. (<bold>b</bold>) The daily-changed body weight of each group. (<bold>c</bold>) The daily-changed diarrhea rate of each group. (<bold>d</bold>) Thymus and spleen indexes of each group. Data were presented as means &#x000b1; SEM. <sup>*</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>**</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 compared with model, <sup>#</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>##</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 compared with control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2019_2548_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>SZC reduces colonic pathological changes in mice with CID</title><p id="Par44">HE-stained colonic section of the model group exhibited remarkable destructions of colonic mucosa and surface epithelia, which were not observed in the control group. Also, in the model group, goblet cells were obviously damaged by 5-FU, and the numbers of goblet cells decreased significantly compared with the control group. However,&#x000a0;these histological changes in colonic section were significantly reduced by SZC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The effects of SZC on histological changes of colon sections in mice with CID (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;8, male/femal&#x02009;=&#x02009;4). (<bold>a</bold>) Representative images of HE-stained colonic sections (200&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;and 1000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;magnifications). (<bold>b</bold>) Number of goblet cells in HE-stained colonic sections (1000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;magnification). Red arrows in colonic sections (200&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;magnification) indicated amplified target areas of pictures, and red arrows in colonic sections (1000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;magnification) indicated damaged goblet cells. Data were presented as means &#x000b1; SEM. <sup>*</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>**</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 compared with model, <sup>#</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>##</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 compared with control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2019_2548_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>SZC modulates the overall structure of gut microbiota in mice with CID</title><p id="Par45">To detect structural differences in gut microbiota between the three groups, a total of 883,537 sequences and an average of 58,902 sequences per group were obtained from the 15 samples. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a showed that the position of box diagram in species accumulation boxplot tended to be gentle as the increase of samples number, which suggested that samples number and species richness both were adequate and stable. At this sequencing depth, the overall&#x000a0;bacterial diversity had already been covered. Then the sequences were clustered into OTUs at 97% similarity, and 935 OTUs in total were obtained from 15 fecal samples. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b, there were 424 OTUs in all three groups, and 17, 329 and 13 unique OTUs were detected in the control, model and SZC groups, respectively. Additionally, the model group showed a significant increase in the number of OTUs compared with the control group. But no significant difference of OTUs number existed between the control and SZC groups (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c). Consistent with the changes of OTUs, both ACE richness and Shannon diversity values of bacterial community were significantly increased in the model group. After the treatment of SZC, ACE richness and Shannon diversity values reduced to the normal levels (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>d and e). NMDS plot showed that the structure of overall bacterial community in the model group was quite different from those in the control and SZC groups (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>f). The clustering tree based on UPGMA also showed a significant separation in gut microbiota between the control and model groups. Notably, gut microbiota of mice treated with SZC did not significantly differ from that of the control group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>g).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>The effects of SZC on the overall structure of gut microbiota in mice with CID (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5, male/femal&#x02009;=&#x02009;2&#x02013;3). (<bold>a</bold>) Species accumulation boxplot was used for the estimations of samples number and species richness. (<bold>b</bold>) Venn diagram indicated the overlap of OTUs in the feces. (<bold>c</bold>) OTUs were clustered from high-quality sequences with 97% similarity. (<bold>d</bold>&#x02013;<bold>e</bold>) ACE and Shannon values indicated the bacterial community richness and diversity, respectively. (<bold>f</bold>) NMDS plot showed distinct structural changes of the overall bacterial community in each group. (<bold>g</bold>) UPGMA clustering was used to interpret the distance matrix of each sample by the average linkage. Data were presented as means &#x000b1; SEM. <sup>*</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>**</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 compared with model, <sup>#</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>##</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 compared with control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2019_2548_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>SZC modulates the key phylotypes of gut microbiota in mice with CID</title><p id="Par46">The histogram of LDA value distribution showed that there were significant differences in dominant microbiota among the three groups (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). 1, 8 and 4 taxa of dominant communities were found in the control, model and SZC groups, respectively. <italic>Bacteroidales_S24-7_group</italic> was the dominant bacteria in the control group. The gut microbiota in the model group was dominated by <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic>, <italic>Bacteroidaceae</italic>, <italic>Prevotellaceae</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic> and <italic>Alloprevotella</italic>. Dominant microbiota in the SZC group included <italic>Firmicutes</italic> and <italic>Clostridia</italic>. An evolutionary branch graph based on LDA scores further revealed the important microbiota in the three groups. The results showed that <italic>Bacteroidales_S24-7_group</italic> was identified as the dominant bacteria in the control group. In the model group, predominant microbiota consisted of <italic>Bacteroidaceae</italic> and <italic>Prevotellaceae</italic>. <italic>Lachnospiraceae</italic>, <italic>Clostridiales</italic> and <italic>Clostridia</italic> were the predominant flora in the SZC group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Statistical difference in dominant microbiota among groups (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;5, male/femal&#x02009;=&#x02009;2&#x02013;3). (<bold>a</bold>) The histogram of LDA value distribution. (<bold>b</bold>) The evolutionary branch graph</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2019_2548_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par47">Histograms with respect to phylum, family and genus were used to reveal the microbial species and their relative abundances (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a&#x02013;c). In fecal samples, <italic>Firmicutes</italic>, <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> and <italic>Proteobacteria</italic> were the 3 dominate phyla, whose relative abundances were 77.62, 18.83 and 1.83% respectively in the control group. The abundances of <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> (26.41%) and <italic>Proteobacteria</italic> (8.76%) increased in the model group, whereas the abundance of <italic>Firmicutes</italic> (61.75%) decreased. However, SZC treatment could restore the proportions of <italic>Firmicutes</italic> (80.54%), <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> (11.74%) and <italic>Proteobacteria</italic> (3.22%) after 5-FU chemotherapy. At family level, our result showed that relative abundances of families such as <italic>Bacteroidaceae</italic> (8.19%) and <italic>Prevotellaceae</italic> (8.03%) significantly increased in the model group, compared with those (2.49 and 2.04%, respectively) in the control group. Moreover, SZC treatment significantly reduced the abundances of <italic>Bacteroidaceae</italic> (2.53%) and <italic>Prevotellaceae</italic> (2.87%).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>The effects of SZC on the key phylotypes of gut microbiota in mice with CID (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;5, male/femal&#x02009;=&#x02009;2&#x02013;3). (<bold>a</bold>) Relative abundance of different bacterial phyla. (<bold>b</bold>) Relative abundance of different bacterial families. (<bold>c</bold>) Relative abundance of different bacterial genera. (<bold>d</bold>) Relative abundances within <italic>Firmicutes</italic>. (<bold>e</bold>) Relative abundances within <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic>. (<bold>f</bold>) Relative abundances within <italic>Proteobacteria</italic>. Data were presented as means &#x000b1; SEM. <sup>*</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>**</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 compared with model, <sup>#</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>##</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 compared with control</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2019_2548_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par48">In addition, at genus level, the model group gave rise to high abundances of some potential pathogens such as <italic>Clostridiumm</italic> (0.50%), <italic>Bacteroides</italic> (8.19%), <italic>Parabacteroides</italic> (1.01%), <italic>Alloprevotella</italic> (6.53%), <italic>Desulfovibrio</italic> (0.73%), <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> (0.40%) and <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> (0.46%). However, the relative abundances of these genera in the control group were significantly different, with <italic>Clostridiumm</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Parabacteroides</italic>, <italic>Alloprevotella</italic>, <italic>Desulfovibrio</italic>, <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> and <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> constituting 0.01, 2.49, 0.35, 1.66, 0.30, 0.00% and 0, respectively. In the SZC group, the inhibitory effects on <italic>Clostridiumm</italic> (0.10%), <italic>Bacteroides</italic> (2.53%), <italic>Parabacteroides</italic> (0.37%), <italic>Alloprevotella</italic> (2.28%), <italic>Desulfovibrio</italic> (0.48%), <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> (0.00%) and <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> (0.00%) were observed compared with those in the untreated model group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>d&#x02013;f).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par49">In this study, all the model mice showed the clinical symptoms of diarrhea. We also found that thymus and spleen indexes in the model mice decreased significantly compared with those of the control group. Thymus and spleen indexes, whose levels depend on the extent of lymphocyte proliferation, can be used to partly reflect host immune function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. The results indicated that the immune system of the model group was affected by 5-Fu chemotherapy. In addition, some histological changes of colonic sections were observed in model mice. Especially, the numbers of goblet cells in the model group were remarkably lower than those of the control group. Goblet cells play important roles in producing and maintaining protective mucus blankets by synthesization and secretion of high molecular weight glycoprotein such as mucin. The reduction of goblet cell number could directly or indirectly impact intestinal health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. However, diarrhea and intestinal histological changes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) were significantly alleviated by SZC, which indicated that SZC was effective in the treatment of CID. More importantly, the potential mechanism behind this anti-diarrheal effect of SZC needed to be investigated in this study.</p><p id="Par50">Previous studies have demonstrated that the pharmacological effects of Renshen and Baizhu were closely associated with gut microbiota. Renshen could effectively reduce body weight and change gut microbial composition in obese middle-aged Korean women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. And Baizhu was capable of reducing intestinal pH value, improving the adhesion of <italic>Bacillusbifidus</italic>, and fostering the normal gut microbiota in lincomycin-induced mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Therefore, SZC, a formula composed of active herbal extracts from Renshen and Baizhu, might exert potentially modulatory effects on gut microbiota. In addition, gut microbiota is a contributing factor of many diseases including diarrhea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Therefore, we further analyzed gut microbiota from the feces of CID mice.</p><p id="Par51">Gut microbial composition in fecal samples was determined by 16S rDNA Amplicon Sequencing. Species accumulation boxplot indicated that the species richness of gut microbiota was sufficient and stable for the following analyses when the total number of samples was 15 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 in each group) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>d and e, gut microbial richness and diversity were significantly increased in the model group. In general, the richness and diversity of microbial populations should be reduced under a pathological condition. The possible cause behind our results was that the richness and diversity of original microbiota was not reduced, and some potential pathogenic bacteria was introduced or increased in CID mice. Our results also showed that microbial richness and diversity decreased to normal levels after SZC treatment. Furthermore, the remarkable differences of distance existed among the three groups in NMDS plot, but a shorter distance was presented between the control and SZC groups. UPGMA clustering showed no obvious structural shift between the SZC and control groups, whereas the gut microbiota in the model group significantly deviated from that of the control group. Taken together, these results demonstrated the overall structure of gut microbiota in CID mice could be reversed to normal by SZC treatment.</p><p id="Par52">Redundancy information uncovered the structural changes in the key phylotypes of gut microbiota based on the following classification: phylum, family and genus. Statistical results revealed that the abundances of <italic>Firmicutes</italic> and <italic>Proteobacteria</italic> significantly changed in the model group. But there was no difference between the SZC and control groups in the abundances of <italic>Firmicutes</italic> and <italic>Proteobacteria</italic>. Also, mice in the model group significantly increased the abundances of some genera such as <italic>Clostridiumm</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Parabacteroides</italic>, <italic>Alloprevotella</italic>, <italic>Desulfovibrio</italic>, <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> and <italic>Pseudomonas</italic>, which might provide opportunities for the occurrence of diarrhea. For example, high-abundant <italic>clostridium</italic> belonging to <italic>Firmicutes</italic> is one of the causes of diarrhea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. <italic>Bacteroides</italic> (<italic>Bacteroidaceae</italic> family and <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> phylum), a complex organism colonized in the gut, may be the key factor influencing the integrity and immune development of intestinal mucosa in the process of diarrhea. Increased <italic>Bacteroides</italic> may also&#x000a0;induce inflammation or even carcinogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. <italic>Parabacteroides</italic> in high abundance was found in immune-related diarrhea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In addition, <italic>Alloprevotella</italic> (<italic>Prevotellaceae</italic> family) is an anaerobic Gram-negative bacilli with the high relative abundance in patients with inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Both <italic>Desulfovibrio</italic> and <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> (<italic>Proteobacteria</italic> family) were associated with bloody diarrhea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> is commonly found in patients with malnourished and infectious diarrhea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. These above studies indicated that the growth of these genera (potential pathogens) was associated with diarrhea. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, SZC treatment reduced the abundances of these genera in CID mice. Therefore, our results suggested that SZC could inhibit the growth of potential pathogens and modulated microbial structure in the feces. Moreover, <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> is an important genus for relieving diarrhea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. On the contrary, no significant difference in the abundances of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> (probiotic) existed among the three groups, which was not in accordance with the results of 5-FU-induced decrease of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> in the previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. The reason behind the difference might be that our results were based on fecal microbiota in mice, while the previous study focused on fecal microbiota in rats. Therefore, the relationship between <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and CID still needs a deeper investigation. Conclusively, these results suggested that amelioration of CID with SZC treatment might be mainly mediated by inhibition of potential pathogens.</p><p id="Par53">Although SZC could modulate gut microbial structure of fecal samples in CID mice, the specific relationship between the anti-diarrheal activity of SZC and gut microbiota remained undefined. For example, fecal collection in a non-invasive manner was chosen as the sampling method for gut microbial analysis. However, fecal communities may not completely represent bacterial communities living in intestines, although they play an important role in maintaining intestinal homeostasis and microbial diversity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. In addition to structural modulation of gut microbiota, the therapeutic effects of herbal drugs could also be influenced by gut microbial metabolism and pharmacokinetics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Therefore, there is still no systematic and comprehensive interpretation for the association between the anti-diarrheal effect of SZC and gut microbiota, which will be our focus in the future researches.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par54">In conclusion, our study found that gut microbial structure was modulated by SZC (the Chinese herbal formula) during the alleviation of CID. Especially, at genus level, SZC significantly inhibited the growth of potential pathogens closely related to diarrhea, including <italic>Clostridiumm</italic>, <italic>Bacteroides</italic>, <italic>Parabacteroides</italic>, <italic>Alloprevotella</italic>, <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> and <italic>Pseudomonas</italic>. These results indicated that gut microbial modulation was associated with the anti-diarrheal activity of SZC.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>5-FU</term><def><p id="Par5">5-Fluorouracil</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ANOVA</term><def><p id="Par6">Analysis of variance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CDUTCM</term><def><p id="Par7">Chengdu University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CID</term><def><p id="Par8">Chemotherapy-induced diarrhea</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GC-MS</term><def><p id="Par9">Gas chromatography-mass spectrometer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GI</term><def><p id="Par10">Gastrointestinal</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HE</term><def><p id="Par11">Hematoxylin-eosin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HPLC</term><def><p id="Par12">High performance liquid chromatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IBD</term><def><p id="Par13">Inflammatory bowel disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IR</term><def><p id="Par14">Infrared spectroscopy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LDA</term><def><p id="Par15">Linear discriminant analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LEfSe</term><def><p id="Par16">Linear discriminant analysis effect size</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LSD</term><def><p id="Par58">Least Significant Difference</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NMDS</term><def><p id="Par59">Non-Metric Multi-Dimensional Scaling</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OTUs</term><def><p id="Par18">Operational taxonomic units</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCR</term><def><p id="Par19">Polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SDS</term><def><p id="Par79">Sodium dodecyl sulfate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SEM</term><def><p id="Par20">Standard Error of Mean</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SZC</term><def><p id="Par21">Shenzhu Capsule</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UC</term><def><p id="Par22">Ulcerative colitis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UPGMA</term><def><p id="Par23">Unweighted Pair-group Method with Arithmetic Means</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Jing Wang and Wuwen Feng contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>JW and WWF performed the experiments, analyzed data and wrote the manuscript. SYZ, FT and YCS contributed to data analysis and technical graphics. LC contributed to the identification of medicinal materials. HA designed the experiment and wrote the manuscript. CP supported and supervised the study. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81891012, 81630101, and 81503272) and Department of Science and Technology of Sichuan Province (NO. 2017JY0187 and 2017TD0001).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The data supporting this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par55">All experimental procedures involving animals were conformed to the strict standards of Animal Ethics Committee (Approval No. AEC-201706) in CDUTCM.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par56">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par57">All the authors declared there was no conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lozupone</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stombaugh</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity, stability and resilience of the human gut microbiota</article-title><source>Nature.</source><year>2012</year><volume>489</volume><issue>7415</issue><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22972295?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22972295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of the gut microbiota in nutrition and health</article-title><source>Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22945443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jandhyala</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Talukdar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanyam</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuyyuru</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasikala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of the normal gut microbiota</article-title><source>World J Gastroenterol</source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><issue>29</issue><fpage>8787</fpage><lpage>8803</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26269668?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26269668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ringel-Kulka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddle</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ringel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alterations in composition and diversity of the intestinal microbiota in patients with diarrhea-predominant irritable bowel syndrome</article-title><source>Neurogastroenterol Motil</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22339879?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22339879</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>St Amand</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Boedeker</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Harpaz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pace</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular-phylogenetic characterization of microbial community imbalances in human inflammatory bowel diseases</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><issue>34</issue><fpage>13780</fpage><lpage>13785</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17699621?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17699621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tremaroli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;ckhed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional interactions between the gut microbiota and host metabolism</article-title><source>Nature.</source><year>2012</year><volume>489</volume><issue>7415</issue><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22972297?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22972297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gut microbiota: an environmental risk factor for cardiovascular disease</article-title><source>Atherosclerosis.</source><year>2013</year><volume>229</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23880200?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23880200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gut microbiota: a potential new territory for drug targeting</article-title><source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18239669?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18239669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faith</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guruge</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Charbonneau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Seedorf</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The long-term stability of the human gut microbiota</article-title><source>Science.</source><year>2013</year><volume>341</volume><issue>6141</issue><fpage>1237439</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23828941?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23828941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kornblau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelking</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ippoliti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Management of cancer treatment&#x02013;related diarrhea</article-title><source>Issues and therapeutic strategies J Pain Symptom Manage</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10699539?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10699539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Voigt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemotherapy-induced diarrhea: pathophysiology, frequency and guideline-based management</article-title><source>Ther Adv Med Oncol</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21789126?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21789126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iacovelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietrantonio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Palazzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maggi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricchini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>de Braud</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Incidence and relative risk of grade 3 and 4 diarrhoea in patients treated with capecitabine or 5-fluorouracil: a meta-analysis of published trials</article-title><source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2014</year><volume>78</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1228</fpage><lpage>1237</lpage><?supplied-pmid 24962653?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24962653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobish</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemotherapy induced diarrhea</article-title><source>J Oncol Pharm Pract</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18045778?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18045778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Keefe</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer chemotherapy-induced diarrhoea and constipation: mechanisms of damage and prevention strategies</article-title><source>Support Care Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>890</fpage><lpage>900</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16604351?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16604351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andreyev</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnellan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lennan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Guidance on the management of diarrhoea during cancer chemotherapy</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e447</fpage><lpage>e460</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25186048?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25186048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zachariah</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gwede</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ajani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Donath</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Octreotide acetate in prevention of chemoradiation-induced diarrhea in anorectal cancer: randomized RTOG trial 0315</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2010</year><volume>102</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>556</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20339140?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20339140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitahara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagasawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Aono</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Saireito (TJ-114), a Japanese traditional herbal medicine, reduces 5-fluorouracil-induced intestinal mucositis in mice by inhibiting cytokine-mediated apoptosis in intestinal crypt cells</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e0116213</fpage><?supplied-pmid 25565296?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25565296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The advantages of using traditional Chinese medicine as an adjunctive therapy in the whole course of cancer treatment instead of only terminal stage of cancer</article-title><source>Biosci Trends</source><year>2015</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25787906?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25787906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>QX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of Shenzhu capsules on upstream genes in mitochondrial pathway of cell apoptosis in gastric cancer mice with spleen-deficience</article-title><source>Chin Pharmacol Bulletin</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>1034</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>QX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of Shenzhu capsules on downstream genes in mitochondrial pathway of cell apoptosis in gastric cancer mice with spleen-deficience</article-title><source>Chin Pharmacol Bulletin.</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>888</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>QX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of Shenzhu capsules on the microstructure and ultrastructure of gastric cancer MKN45 cells</article-title><source>Pharmacology and Clinics of Chinese Materia Medica</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>152</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study on gene expression profile induced by the model with spleen-deficiency and gastric cancero-metastasis in mice treated by Shenzhu Capules</article-title><source>J Yunnan Coll Tradit Chin Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>33</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systems pharmacology reveals the unique mechanism features of Shenzhu capsule for treatment of ulcerative colitis in comparison with synthetic drugs</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16160</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30385774?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30385774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>EQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical observation of Shenling Baizhu powder improving post-chemotherapy patients with rectal excision</article-title><source>Chinese Traditional Patent Medicine</source><year>2017</year><volume>39</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>282</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>BZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective effect of Bu-Zhong-Yi-Qi decoction, the water extract of Chinese traditional herbal medicine, on 5-fluorouracil-induced intestinal mucositis in mice</article-title><source>Hum Exp Toxicol</source><year>2016</year><volume>35</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1243</fpage><lpage>1251</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26801985?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26801985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>PMH</given-names></name><name><surname>Leu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Modified Sijunzi decoction can alleviate cisplatin-induced toxicity and prolong the survival time of cachectic mice by recovering muscle atrophy</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2019</year><volume>233</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30590199?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30590199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gut microbiota, short-chain fatty acids, and herbal medicines</article-title><source>Front Pharmacol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1354</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30532706?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30532706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Chinese Pharmacopoeia Commission. Pharmacopoeia of the People&#x02019;s Republic of China</collab></person-group><source>China Medical Science Press.</source><year>2015</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Chinese Pharmacopoeia Commission. Pharmacopoeia of the People&#x02019;s Republic of China</collab></person-group><source>China Medical Science Press</source><year>2015</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>104</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of Banxia Xiexin tang on intestinal immune function in fluorouracil-induced diarrhea mice</article-title><source>Chin J Exp Tradit Med Form</source><year>2014</year><volume>20</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>184</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bu</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of antioxidant and immune activity of <italic>Phellinus ribis</italic> glucan in mice</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>115</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>584</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Specian</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional biology of intestinal goblet cells</article-title><source>Am J Phys</source><year>1991</year><volume>260</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>C183</fpage><lpage>C193</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of Panax ginseng on obesity and gut microbiota in obese middle-aged Korean women</article-title><source>J Ginseng Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>38</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><?supplied-pmid 24748834?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24748834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study on the effect and mechanism of Chinese herbs on intestinal normal flora of mice</article-title><source>Chin Arch Tradit Chin Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>395</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sekirov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>LCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Finlay</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gut microbiota in health and disease</article-title><source>Physiol Rev</source><year>2010</year><volume>90</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>904</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20664075?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20664075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polage</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Solnick</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nosocomial diarrhea: evaluation and treatment of causes other than <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic></article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>55</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>982</fpage><lpage>989</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22700831?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22700831</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Arjumand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Faruque</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of enterotoxigenic <italic>Bacteroides fragilis</italic> infection with inflammatory diarrhea</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>47</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>803</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18680416?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18680416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Bacteroides</italic> spp. and diarrhea</article-title><source>Curr Opin Infect Dis</source><year>2010</year><volume>23</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>470</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20697287?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20697287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Tian</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intestinal microbiota to predict risk for immune-related diarrhea in patients with lung cancer patients</article-title><source>Journal of Clinical Oncology</source><year>2018</year><volume>36</volume><issue>5_suppl</issue><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>132</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiely</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2018. The microbiome of translocated bacterial populations in patients with and without inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>Intern Med J</source><year>2018</year><volume>48</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1346</fpage><lpage>1354</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29893034?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29893034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polanco</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Manzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxigenic effect of <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> isolated from children with acute diarrhoea</article-title><source>Investig Clin</source><year>2008</year><volume>49</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18524332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kushkevych</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissimilatory sulfate reduction by various <italic>Desulfovibrio sp.</italic> strains of the human intestine</article-title><source>&#x0041c;&#x00456;&#x0043a;&#x00440;&#x0043e;&#x00431;&#x00456;&#x0043e;&#x0043b;&#x0043e;&#x00433;&#x00456;&#x0044f; &#x00456; &#x00431;&#x00456;&#x0043e;&#x00442;&#x00435;&#x00445;&#x0043d;&#x0043e;&#x0043b;&#x0043e;&#x00433;&#x00456;&#x0044f;</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>63</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omoike</surname><given-names>IU</given-names></name><name><surname>Abiodun</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Upper small intestinal microflora in diarrhea and malnutrition in Nigerian children</article-title><source>J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr</source><year>1989</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>314</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><?supplied-pmid 2614617?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2614617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porco</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name><name><surname>Visconte</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> as a cause of infectious diarrhea successfully treated with oral ciprofloxacin</article-title><source>Ann Pharmacother</source><year>1995</year><volume>29</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1122</fpage><lpage>1123</lpage><?supplied-pmid 8573957?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8573957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guandalini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotics for prevention and treatment of diarrhea</article-title><source>J Clin Gastroenterol</source><year>2011</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>S149</fpage><lpage>S153</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21992955?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21992955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Volatile oil from Amomi Fructus attenuates 5-fluorouracil-induced intestinal mucositis</article-title><source>Front Pharmacol</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>786</fpage><?supplied-pmid 29170638?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29170638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eckburg</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bik</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Purdom</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dethlefsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sargent</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diversity of the human intestinal microbial flora</article-title><source>Science.</source><year>2005</year><volume>308</volume><issue>5728</issue><fpage>1635</fpage><lpage>1638</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15831718?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15831718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>da Cunha</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezende</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cialic</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Bry</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The host shapes the gut microbiota via fecal microRNA</article-title><source>Cell Host Microbe</source><year>2016</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26764595?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26764595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gut microbiota, a new frontier to understand traditional Chinese medicines</article-title><source>Pharmacol Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30818043?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30818043</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>