<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although clinical data regarding cardiovascular benefits of MO and its different formulations are limited, there are some encouraging results from novel clinical trials (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Namely, double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled trial of efficacy and safety was conducted in order to investigate and justify traditional use of MO for heart palpitations. It was found that 2 weeks of consumption lyophilized aqueous MOE (500 mg; two times per day) reduced heart palpitation episodes by 36% compared to 4.2% reduction in the placebo group. Additionally, no side effects were noted in the subjects who finished the study (
 <italic>n</italic> = 55) (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Alijaniha et al., 2015</xref>). Other available clinical trial results were focused on the influence of MO on cardiometabolic parameters, such as lipid status, glycemia, and inflammatory status as factors promoting cardiovascular risk in diabetic patients (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Asadi et al., 2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Both trials came to similar results that MO application improves lipid ratios (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Alijaniha et al., 2015</xref>), high-density lipoprotein (HDL), triglycerides (TGs), high-sensitivity C-reactive protein (hs-CRP) levels, systolic blood pressure (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Asadi et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Nayebi et al., 2019</xref>), and diastolic blood pressure (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Ibragic et al., 2014</xref>), thus preventing cardiovascular risk in this patient population. It is noteworthy that these beneficial effects were achieved by a higher dose of MO (700 mg, 2 × a day, 
 <italic>per os</italic>) and longer (3 months) usage (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Asadi et al., 2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) than for heart palpitations (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">Zhao and Zhang, 2017</xref>). Nonetheless, no dose-dependent adverse reactions were reported (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Asadi et al., 2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Beneficial effects of hot water MOE were highlighted by 
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">Yui et al. (2017)</xref>, in the aspect of the reductions in brachial-ankle pulse wave velocity, which reflects arterial stiffness in healthy adult subjects.
</p>
