<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>M. vulgare</italic> can be applied as herbal tea for oral use (single dose: 1–2 g of herbal material in 250 mL of boiling water, as a herbal infusion, 3 times a day; daily: dose 3–6 g), powdered herbal substance (single dose: 225–450 mg, 3 times a day; daily dose: 675–1350 mg), expressed juice (single dose: 10–20 mL, 3 times a day; daily dose: 30–60 mL) and liquid extract (single dose: 1.5–4.0 mL, 3 times a day; daily dose: 4.5–12 mL). The use in children under 12 years of age is not recommended. Safety during pregnancy and lactation has not been established [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-02898" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. However, results showed that a group of normal rats treated with the ethanol–water extract of 
 <italic>M. vulgare</italic> (80:20, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) and pregnant rats treated with the extract exhibited a significant decrease in hematological parameters: red blood cells, hematocrit, hemoglobin, and mean corpuscular volume. The extract of 
 <italic>M. vulgare</italic> caused a significant decrease on the mean implantations of fetuses and their size. As for the macroscopic and histological appearance of uterus; these data showed no change in normal treated rats. Contrary to these, the treated pregnant rats showed a severe histological change characterized by interrupted gestation, as well as the lysing of placental and embryo tissue in the uterus. All these results support the hypothesis of an abortifacient effect of 
 <italic>M. vulgare</italic> [
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-25-02898" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Possibly, the furanic labdane diterpene marrubin and premarrubin could be responsible for these effects, since they are structural analogues with leosibiricin, an active diterpene of 
 <italic>Leonorus cardiaca</italic>, which is a plant that is known for its emenagogue activity and contraindicated in pregnancy [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-25-02898" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Additionally, the effects of alcoholic extract of 
 <italic>Marrubum vulgare</italic> on hormonal parameters in a female rat model (receiving 500 mg/kg and 1000 mg/kg of 
 <italic>M. vulgare</italic> extract for 21 days) of polycystic ovarian syndrome were studied. Luteinizing hormone (LH) hormone significantly decreased at a dose of 1000 mg/kg, and estradiol and progesterone decreased at doses of 500 mg/kg and 1000 mg/kg, while testosterone decreased at a dose of 1000 mg/kg. These findings contribute to the potential influence of examined extract on female hormones, thus questioning their safe usage in pregnancy [
 <xref rid="B64-molecules-25-02898" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. In addition, 
 <italic>M. vulgare</italic> is mentioned in certain literature as a potentially nephrotoxic plant [
 <xref rid="B65-molecules-25-02898" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. However, there is no relevant scientific evidence to confirm these claims.
</p>
