<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The effects of quercetin on the different steps of the SGIV life cycle in GS cells were further investigated. The results indicated that quercetin could interfere with SGIV binding to targets on host cells (by 76.14%), disturb SGIV invading into host cells (by 56.03%), and effect SGIV replication in host cells (by 52.73%), respectively. Quercetin had the best antiviral effects during the SGIV life cycle of binding to the receptors on the membrane of host cells, representing the critical stage of SGIV infection. It was consistent with a previous study reported by 
 <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Ganesan et al. (2012)</xref>. Rhinovirus (RV) could cause exacerbations in patients with asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. 
 <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Ganesan et al. (2012)</xref> proved that quercetin could inhibit RV endocytosis and replication. Furthermore, as reported by 
 <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. (2016)</xref>, (−) epigallocatechin gallate could prevent GCRV from adsorbing and invading host cells by blocking laminin receptor on the surface of host cells, which resulted in its inhibitory effects on grass carp reovirus. We concluded that quercetin could competitively bind to some host cells’ receptors and further prevented SGIV from adsorbing to the host cells. These results were consistent with quercetin’s effects on other viruses (
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Rojas et al., 2016</xref>). 
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Rojas et al. (2016)</xref> assessed the effects of quercetin on the different steps of the HCV life cycle and proved that quercetin inhibited HCV mainly through three ways: (i) affecting the virion integrity (by 65%), (ii) decreasing the production of infectious HCV particles, and (iii) reducing the infectivity of newly produced HCV particles (
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Rojas et al., 2016</xref>). 
 <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Bisignano et al. (2017)</xref> determine quercetin’s effects on the replication of HSV-1. It indicated that quercetin not only blocked the production of infectious HSV-1 particles but also inhibited HSV-1 adsorption to cells (
 <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Bisignano et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
