<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">The term endophyte describes those taxa that can live within plant tissues, either within or between host cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. These endophytes include bacteria, fungi, archaea and unicellular eukaryotes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The internal niches of plants provide a protective barrier from environmental influences that allow bacteria to live and reproduce [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In return, plants may benefit from endophytic associations. First, endophytic bacteria can promote the growth and development of host plants by producing a range of nutrients and promoting primary and secondary nutrient uptake through atmospheric nitrogen fixation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Second, endophytic bacteria can participate in aspects of the plant’s phosphate solubilization activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], such as osmotic adjustment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] and stomatal regulation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], to increase the plant’s ecological adaptability. Furthermore, endophytic bacteria may overcome environmental stress conditions, such as drought and soil salinity stress [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], and improve plant growth. Also as biological control agents, endophytic bacteria can produce or promote the production of secondary metabolites by host plants to reduce or prevent damage caused by certain pathogens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Numerous studies have shown that an in-depth understanding of the diversity of endophytic bacteria will elucidate the function of the interaction between microorganisms and plants, which will be conducive to the development of strategies for ecological environment restoration and sustainable agricultural, such as remediation of the soil environment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and increasing crop production [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].
</p>
