<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Hexadecatrienoic acid is a possible chemotaxonomic marker of the species belonging to the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Codium</italic> [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>] along with clerosterol [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. These species also contain long chain fatty acids with palmitic acid as the main saturated fatty acid (SFA) and oleic acid as the most common monounsaturated fatty acid (MUFA) [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. α-Linolenic acid (C18:3ω3) was the most abundant polyunsaturated fatty acid (PUFA) found in green algae [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. The investigation of green algae showed that their ω6/ω3 ratio was very preferable for including them in diets with potential beneficial effect for human health [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. During the growth and adaptation to abiotic stress, algae produce different volatile organic compounds (VOCs) which serve for the communication and interaction with the surrounding environment. Their concentration and composition depend on the environmental conditions, species, and geographical origin, as well as drying process and method used for their extraction [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Gressler et al. [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] reviewed about 295 volatile compounds isolated from 31 species of marine macroalgae. Our research group have also been investigating algae VOCs by different isolation techniques. Hydrocarbons were the most common volatile compounds found in algae, followed by alcohols, terpenes, ketones, and aldehydes. Volatile oils, as well as the extracts, from brown and red algae, were tested for the inhibition of several bacteria growths [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Hydrocarbons were found to be dominant in the volatile oil of 
 <italic class="italic">Codium fragile</italic> [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>], while long-chain aliphatic alcohols were the major compounds in 
 <italic class="italic">Codium tomentosum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. In general, the presence of dimethyl sulfide in the algae contributes to the distinct algae flavor [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-24-00842" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>].
</p>
