<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Generally, the first site of action of essential oils on the bacterial cells is the membranes. This is directly related to the hydrophobicity of the essential oils components. This property ensures and facilitates permeability of membrane phospholipids bilayer to these molecules. The result is a destabilization of the plasma membrane structure and a change in its permeability to ions, protons, and other cellular components [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In addition to the induced membrane alterations, such molecules can cross the lipid bilayer and interact with intracytoplasmic targets [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Given the molecular diversity of the essential oils, it appears more likely that their antibacterial activity results from the combination of several mechanisms, acting synergistically on different cellular targets [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In fact, among the dominant molecules in the five studied essential oils, caryophyllene and 
 <italic>β</italic>-caryophyllene oxide have antibacterial and antifungal activities [
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Oxygenates (caryophyllene oxide, 1.8-cineole, etc.) have
 <italic> in vitro</italic> antibacterial activity [
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]; citral (neral and geranial) has a strong antibacterial effect [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The interaction between p-cymene, ‎
 <italic>γ</italic>-terpinene, and the phenolic compounds could exhibt an antibacterial activity [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Furthermore, the essential oils showing high antibacterial activity are phenol and cinnamic aldehyde rich oils (thymol, carvacrol, and eugenol) as in the essential oils of
 <italic> Thymus vulgaris</italic>,
 <italic> Origanum compactum</italic>,
 <italic> Satureja montana</italic>,
 <italic> Eugenia caryophyllata</italic>, and
 <italic> Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. However, antimicrobial effectiveness of an essential oil is due to the nature and content of these various constituents that may act synergistically; the effect of minor compounds is not always negligible. Synergism between constituents can cause a much more pronounced effect than the expected activity of the major compounds [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].
</p>
