<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The potential antidepressant-like effects of 
 <italic class="italic">Eugenia uniflora</italic> L. essential oil showed in a dose-dependent manner after acute administration in the TST in mice [
 <xref rid="B38-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. The chemical composition of 
 <italic class="italic">Eugenia uniflora</italic> L. oil was analyzed by gas chromatography/mass spectroscopy; and it contains mainly sesquiterpenes: germacrene B (22%), selina-1,3,7-trien-8-one-oxide (19%), β-caryophyllene (13%), germacrene A (11%), germacrene D (11%), selina-1,3,7-trien-8-one (9%) and curzerene (4%). Only β-caryophyllene has been tested for the effects on depression states. The acute administration of β-caryophyllene induced robust antidepressant-like effects, as replicated in distinct animal models in mice: FST, TST, and novelty-suppressed feeding behavior [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Indeed, the antidepressant effects of the isolated constituent β-caryophyllene were prevented by the pretreatment with a CB
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> receptor antagonist, AM630 [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Interestingly, β-caryophyllene acts as a CB2 receptor agonist [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. The CB
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> receptor is expressed also in the brain, and is involved in the modulation of anxiety and depressive states [
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]. Victoria et al. [
 <xref rid="B38-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>] showed the involvement of monoamines neurotransmission mediating the 
 <italic class="italic">Eugenia uniflora</italic> L. oil-induced antidepressant actions. The blockade of 5-HT
 <sub class="sub">2A/C</sub>, α
 <sub class="sub">1</sub>- and α
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-receptors prevented the antidepressant effects of this essential oil in the mouse TST. Additional studies aimed to investigate the effects of chronic administration of 
 <italic class="italic">Eugenia uniflora</italic> L. oil in animal models of depression and putative mechanisms of action are worth carrying out.
</p>
