<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Gene duplication supplies the raw materials for the diversity of organisms [
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2</italic> genes have been duplicated multiple copies during evolution to perform a variety of functions such as fatty acids biosynthesis, plant development, and responses to cold and salt stresses [
 <xref rid="B2-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. The evolution process of 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2</italic> genes is interesting. In algae, 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2</italic> is single copy with seven or nine introns. With the landing of plants, the copy numbers of 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2</italic> genes began to increase, but the introns disappeared or decreased. In basal land plants, the introns were totally lost, whereas, in seed plants, the introns emerged again and ranged from zero to four. The introns are important for regulating expression through their cis-regulatory elements. Therefore, the existence of a single copy of 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2</italic> in algae with many introns might be for adapting to the complicated aquatic environment through gene expression. In contrast, for land plants, copies of 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2</italic> genes increased, while the introns decreased. Thus, in land plants, FAD2s fulfilled their functions through their homologs, as well as expressional regulation of promoters and introns that has been reported [
 <xref rid="B2-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. Nevertheless, the function of FAD2 is to insert a double bond at the delta-12 position of OA to form LA. In this study, the activity of FAD2, highly or specifically expressed in seeds, was found significantly positive related to the content of total oil in soybean, rice, perilla, and spruce seeds. Therefore, the results indicated that the FAD2s in seeds might play a role in influence the content of total oils. Why do FAD2s influence the total oil content? The reason might be related to their function, involving in the biosynthesis of fatty acids. OA, LA, and ALA are the main components of majority of the vegetable oils [
 <xref rid="B14-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. FAD2 catalyzes the conversion of LA from OA, then ALA. Therefore, the activity of FAD2 might represent the synthesis efficiency of oil and influence the content of total oil in seeds. However, the prediction needs to be investigated and the correlation between the activity of FAD2 and the total oil content also needs to be further verified in more seed plants in the future. 
</p>
