<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Different 
 <italic class="italic">Padina</italic> species possess different sterol compositions. In French Polynesian 
 <italic class="italic">Padina pavonica</italic> we tested, fucosterol appeared to be exceptionally high (7.40% of EPP) in respect of cholesterol (0.97% of EPP), leading to a ratio between fucosterol and cholesterol (F:C) of 7.6:1. Comparing our sterols pattern with literature data, we can see that F:C for 
 <italic class="italic">Padina pavonica</italic> from French Polynesia is higher than what previously found in the Aegean Sea 
 <italic class="italic">Padina pavonica</italic>, 0.7:1 [
 <xref rid="B17-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], Adriatic Sea 
 <italic class="italic">Padina pavonica</italic>, 0.3:1 [
 <xref rid="B2-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>] and in Turkish Mediterranean Sea 
 <italic class="italic">Padina pavonica</italic> [
 <xref rid="B11-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. The differences found in the sterol composition could be attributed to differences in the ecological conditions, life cycle of the algae and seasonal variations. [
 <xref rid="B2-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Fucosterol is the main phytosterol in brown algae [
 <xref rid="B20-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Many studies have described the biological and pharmacological effects of fucosterol including antidiabetic, antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, ability to reduce blood cholesterol levels in in hyper- and normocholesterolemic subjects. Fucosterol has been demonstrated to possess pro-apoptotic activity toward several cancer cell lines (colon carcinoma [
 <xref rid="B21-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>], breast carcinoma [
 <xref rid="B22-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>], promyelocytic leukemia [
 <xref rid="B21-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]) by promoting activation of caspase-3 [
 <xref rid="B20-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. These data strongly suggest the potential anti-cancer activity of EPP, analogously with what reported for 
 <italic class="italic">Turbinaria ornata</italic> sterols [
 <xref rid="B21-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>] or fucosterol from 
 <italic class="italic">Turbinaria conoides</italic> [
 <xref rid="B23-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Furthermore, fucosterol has bone regenerative effects as demonstrated by in vivo and vitro studies [
 <xref rid="B24-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. In an estrogen-deficient ovariectomized (OVX) animal model, oral administration of fucosterol ameliorated several bone-quality parameters (bone mineral density, bone microarchitecture and BV/TV ratio, osteocalcin and CTx serum biomarkers [
 <xref rid="B24-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. At cell level, fucosterol increased MG63 osteblast-like cells proliferation, alkaline phosphatase activity and mineralization capacity, while preventing osteoclasts differentiation and RANK expression [
 <xref rid="B24-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-marinedrugs-16-00504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>].
</p>
