<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-insects-09-00025" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-insects-09-00025" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Insect Cultures and Rearing Conditions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Larvae of 
   <span class="italic">C. quinquefasciatus</span> were collected from water tanks in the Sanctorum Cemetery in Mexico City, Mexico (19°27′17″ N, 99°12′47″ W). Identification of adults and larvae was done based on Harwood and James descriptions [
   <a rid="B20-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-insects-09-00025">20</a>]. Mosquitoes larvae were pooled into groups of 50 individuals of first and second instars in glass bottles containing distilled water. Afterwards, larvae were maintained at 26 ± 2 °C with a natural photoperiod and supplied with powdered mixture of dog food and baking powder (3:1). The third instar emerging larvae were then separated into groups of 10 individuals in 100 mL tubes containing distilled water.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-insects-09-00025" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Plant material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the vegetative materials used in this study, cinnamon cortex (
   <span class="italic">Cinnamomum verum</span>), cumin leaves (
   <span class="italic">Cuminum cyminum</span>), clove bottoms (
   <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span>), laurel leaves (
   <span class="italic">Laurus nobilis</span>), Mexican oregano leaves (
   <span class="italic">Lippia berlandieri</span>) and anise seeds (
   <span class="italic">Pimpinella anisum</span>) were purchased as commercial spices from Commercial Cardona S. A. (Chihuahua Chihuahua, México). Mexican lime (
   <span class="italic">Citrus aurantifolia</span>) bagasse was obtained from fruits brought at a local supermarket. Pure chemical compounds identified as major components of the essential oils were purchased from a Sigma-Aldrich (San Louis, MI, USA) distributor.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-insects-09-00025" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Essential Oils Extraction and Characterization</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A modified Schilcher apparatus was used for hydrodistillation; 200 g of plant material (dried and chopped) was added to 4 L of water and introduced into the boiling flask and the system was heated at 100 °C for 5 h [
   <a rid="B21-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-insects-09-00025">21</a>,
   <a rid="B22-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-insects-09-00025">22</a>]; for Mexican lime essential oil, 400 g of fresh lime bagasse and 4 L of water were used and the system was heated at 100 °C for 4 h (Aldana et al. 2014 [
   <a rid="B23-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-insects-09-00025">23</a>]); the essential oil extracted was dried over anhydrous sodium sulfate and stored at 4 °C in amber glass vials. For chemical analysis, conditions were similar to those reported by Aldana et al. [
   <a rid="B23-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-insects-09-00025">23</a>] for gas chromatographic separation followed by mass spectrometry. Analysis were done in a Perkin Elmer AUTOSYSTEM XL Gas Chromatograph (Waltham, MA, USA) and TurboMass Gold Spectrometer (Hewlett-Packard In., Palo Alto, CA, USA).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot4-insects-09-00025" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Bioassays and Statistical Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mosquito larvicidal assays were carried out according to standard World Health Organization (WHO) larvicidal assay method with slight modifications [
   <a rid="B24-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-insects-09-00025">24</a>]. The essential oils and the binary mixtures of the most effective essential oils (i.e., the oils which achieved the lowest LC
   <sub>50</sub> values on 
   <span class="italic">C. quinquefasciatus</span> larvae) were diluted in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) (Sigma-Aldrich, San Louis, MI, USA) preparing a serial dilution of test dosages. For each experimental treatment, 1 mL of serial dilution was added to 224 mL of distilled water in a 500-mL glass bowl and shaken lightly to ensure a homogenous test solution. The selected larvae were transferred in distilled water into a bowl of prepared test solution with final surface area of 125 cm
   <span class="sup">2</span> (25 larvae/beaker) and maintained in starvation throughout the experimental period; the surviving larvae were counted to record larval mortality. Five replicates were run simultaneously with at least 10 dosages (300, 200, 100, 75, 50, 25, 15, 10, 5, and 2.5 µg/mL). The larvicidal activity of DMSO was also determined under the same conditions; a DMSO concentration of 1000 µg/mL had no larvicidal activity. The lethal concentrations (LC
   <sub>50</sub> and LC
   <sub>90</sub>) were calculated using Probit analysis. Data were processed using MS Excel 2010 (Microsoft, WA, USA) and SAS v.9 (Proc Probit) (SAS Institute Inc. Cary, NC, USA) computer programs.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot5-insects-09-00025" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. The Effect of Lethal Doses on Larval Development</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Twenty-five larvae (third instar) were put into a 500-mL glass bowl containing 200 mL drinking water. Upon acclimatization (after approximately 1 h), a dose of essential oil or pure components was mixed to the water, corresponding to the calculated dose LC
   <sub>50</sub>. The essential oils and pure compounds were emulsified using DMSO; water with an adequate DMSO content was used for the control larvae. Larval mortality was observed 24 h following termination of exposure, during which time, no food was offered to the larvae. Five replicates were run simultaneously.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot6-insects-09-00025" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6. Oviposition Deterrent Effect</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The oviposition deterrent test was done using the method described by Xue et al. [
   <a rid="B25-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-insects-09-00025">25</a>]. The percent of effective repellency for was calculated using the formula:
   <div class="disp-formula">
    <span class="italic">ER</span> (%) = ((
    <span class="italic">NC</span> − 
    <span class="italic">NT</span>)/(
    <span class="italic">NC</span> + 
    <span class="italic">NT</span>) × 100
    <span class="label">(1)</span>
   </div> where 
   <span class="italic">ER</span> is the percent of effective repellency; 
   <span class="italic">NC</span> is the number of eggs in the control sample; and 
   <span class="italic">NT</span> is the number of eggs in treatment bowl. 
   <span class="italic">ER</span> was determined and transformed to arcsine square root values for analysis of variance.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot7-insects-09-00025" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7. Effects of Dose and Time Period on Larvicidal Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oils that yielded more than 90% mortality after 30 min of treatment in preliminary screening were further evaluated at different concentrations from 2.5 to 200 µg/mL at different time intervals (10 to 120 min) for the determination of LC
   <sub>50</sub> and LC
   <sub>90</sub> values. Larvae were considered dead if they were immobile and unable to reach the water surface [
   <a rid="B26-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-insects-09-00025">26</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot8-insects-09-00025" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.8. Effects of the Binary Mixtures</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three test groups were run concurrently for each binary combination tested: the binary mixture and each of the pure compounds. The compounds were combined in a 1:1 ratio (doses LC
   <sub>25</sub>/LC
   <sub>25</sub>). The application method and experimental conditions were identical to the methods described previously in 
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot4-insects-09-00025" href="#sec2dot4-insects-09-00025">Section 2.4</a>. Four replications of 25 larvae were tested per dose.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Actual mortalities were compared to expected mortalities based on the formula: 
   <div class="disp-formula">
    <span class="italic">E</span> = 
    <span class="italic">O
     <sub>a</sub>
    </span> + 
    <span class="italic">O
     <sub>b</sub>
    </span> (1 − 
    <span class="italic">O
     <sub>a</sub>
    </span>/100)
    <span class="label">(2)</span>
   </div> where 
   <span class="italic">E</span> is the expected mortality and 
   <span class="italic">O
    <sub>a</sub>
   </span> and 
   <span class="italic">O
    <sub>b</sub>
   </span> are the observed mortalities of pure compounds at the given concentration. The factor of 100 was used to calculate the value of 
   <span class="italic">E</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effects of mixtures were designated as either antagonistic, additive, or synergistic by analysis using 
   <span class="italic">x</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> comparisons:
   <div class="disp-formula">
    <span class="italic">x</span>
    <span class="sup">2</span> = (
    <span class="italic">O
     <sub>m</sub>
    </span> − 
    <span class="italic">E</span>)
    <span class="sup">2</span>/
    <span class="italic">E</span>
    <span class="label">(3)</span>
   </div> where O
   <sub>m</sub> is the observed mortality from the binary mixture and E is the expected mortality, 
   <span class="italic">x</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> with 
   <span class="italic">df</span>  = 1, and 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.05 is 3.84. A pair with 
   <span class="italic">x</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> values &gt; 3.84 and having greater than expected mortality were considered to be synergistic (or antagonistic), with 
   <span class="italic">x</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> values &lt; 3.84 representing additive effects [
   <a rid="B19-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-insects-09-00025">19</a>,
   <a rid="B27-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-insects-09-00025">27</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
