<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To our knowledge, this is the first report of the chemical composition and biological activity of the essential oil distilled from leaves of 
  <span class="italic">V. capitata, V. gardneriana</span> and 
  <span class="italic">V. rufescens</span>. Of the chemical constituents detected, 88.7, 94.5, 80.5, and 90.2% were sesquiterpenes, and 2.3, 0.3, 17.1, and 8.6% were monoterpenes for 
  <span class="italic">V. capitata, V. megapotamica, V. gardneriana</span> and 
  <span class="italic">V. rufescens</span>, respectively. Similar chemical compositions were found in the essential oil extracts from 
  <span class="italic">V. capitata</span> and 
  <span class="italic">V. megapotamica</span>, where α-copaene, (
  <span class="italic">E</span>)-caryophyllene, γ-elemene, α-humulene, gamma-muurolene, viridiflorene and γ-cadinene were the major components (
  <span class="bold">Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">2</a>
  </span> and 
  <span class="bold">Table 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T2" href="#T2">2</a>
  </span>). Characterization of 
  <span class="italic">V. gardneriana</span> revealed that the most abundant compounds were 6,9–guaiadiene (19.3%), caryophyllene oxide (18.6%), 
  <span class="sc">L</span>-calamenene (13.9%) and α-cadinol (3.8%). In the case of 
  <span class="italic">V. rufescens</span>, (
  <span class="italic">E</span>)-caryophyllene (21%), ledol (15.7%) and germacrene D (9.3%) were the main constituents detected.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemotaxonomy, or chemical variation in a group of compounds, is one of the tools used to define intra- and inter-specific variability in plants (
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">Sena Filho et al., 2007</a>, 
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">2012</a>; 
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">Duran-Peña et al., 2015</a>). Our objective was to use the chemical profile in the four 
  <span class="italic">Vitex</span> species we studied, plus 13 others from the literature, to develop a system for classification of plant specimens derived from this genus. The content of sesquiterpenes with seven and nine members in their ring system in the four 
  <span class="italic">Vitex</span> species described in this study was remarkable. Recently, genes responsible for sesquiterpene cyclization were evaluated in fungi, which involved scaffolds generated by terpene synthases and cyclases (
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">Quin et al., 2014</a>). Our data indicates that sesquiterpene synthase is likely highly expressed in this genus and hypothesize that this enzyme plays an important role in its chemosystematics. Enzyme mechanisms of sesquiterpene biosynthesis are well known: 5-
  <span class="italic">epi</span>-aristolochene synthase (TEAS) found in 
  <span class="italic">Nicotiana tabacum</span> L. (tobacco) was the first cloned and sequenced sesquiterpene synthase from 
  <span class="italic">Angiospermae</span> species (
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">Maillea et al., 2006</a>), and could serve as a useful model for understanding how these compounds are built in the plant.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For both the chemical compound and genetic markers evaluated by clustering (
  <span class="bold">Figures 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3</a>
  </span>), 
  <span class="italic">V. gardneriana</span> was isolated from the other three species. This may be related to genotypic differences for this species, as it is found in a different biome (
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">Sena Filho et al., 2008</a>) which may influence the expression of genes used for synthesis of chemical compounds. The use of two data tools (chemical and genetic diversity) more thoroughly supports systematic characterization of the species studied (
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">Rahalia et al., 2016</a>), and validates our chemical marker proposal for the 
  <span class="italic">Vitex</span> genus, namely, using the sesquiterpene skeleton with seven member rings as a biomarker candidate.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interestingly, the chemical structure of the sesquiterpene viridiflorene found in 
  <span class="italic">V. megapotamica, V. capitata</span> and 
  <span class="italic">V. rufescens</span> possesses a very unique ring system, similar to 6,9-guaiadiene found in 
  <span class="italic">V. garnderiana</span> (
  <span class="bold">Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">4</a>
  </span>). The enzymatic activity of recombinant 
  <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span> in TPS 31 from 
  <span class="italic">Solanum lycopenium</span> led to the discovery of viridiflorine synthase (
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">Bleeker et al., 2011</a>). This compound possesses a similar structure to the africanone scaffold with a 2,6 ring closure (
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">Quin et al., 2014</a>); this type of ring closure could be considered as a more specific signature of the chemoprofile for species in the 
  <span class="italic">Vitex</span> genus.
 </p>
 <div id="F4" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">FIGURE 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Biosynthesis of the 5,10-cycloaromadendrane type sesquiterpenoids and the seven-member ring compounds found in 
    <span class="italic">Vitex</span> species viridiflorene 
    <span class="bold">(A)</span> and 6,9-guaidiene 
    <span class="bold">(B)</span>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fpls-08-01931-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the toxicity bioassays, the essential oil extracted from 
  <span class="italic">V. gardneriana</span> was highly toxic to 
  <span class="italic">A. guerreronis</span>, indicating its potential for use in controlling this major coconut pest. On the other hand, it was not possible to estimate the LC
  <sub>50</sub> from 
  <span class="italic">V. capitata, V. megapotamica</span> and 
  <span class="italic">V. rufescens</span> essential oils. This differential toxicity may be explained by the diversity and amount of sesquiterpenes found only in 
  <span class="italic">V. gardneriana</span>, such as 6,9-guaiadine (19%), 
  <span class="sc">L</span>-calamenene (13.9%), and caryophyllene oxide (18.6%). However, these compounds should be further evaluated concerning the toxicity to 
  <span class="italic">A. guerreronis</span> using more modern toxicology bioassays. Further, predatory mites, especially those belonging to the family Phytoseiidae, are natural enemies of 
  <span class="italic">A. guerreronis</span> worldwide (
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">McMurtry and Croft, 1997</a>; 
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">Návia et al., 2013</a>). These beneficial mites are naturally found foraging on coconut plants and help to control 
  <span class="italic">A. guerreronis</span>. Therefore, future research should also assess the acaricidal activity of 
  <span class="italic">V. gardneriana</span> essential oil to predatory mites aiming at determining its selectivity toward non-target organisms, including pollinators and seed dispersers.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biological activity of some of the prominent compounds we saw in the 
  <span class="italic">Vitex</span> species studied here has been defined previously: 6,9-guaiadiene, prominent in 
  <span class="italic">V. gardneriana</span>, was also found in essential oils extracted from 
  <span class="italic">Bracteosa ruilopezia</span> (Standl.) Cuatrec and 
  <span class="italic">Baccharis salicifolia</span> (Ruiz &amp; Pav.) Pers. (Asteraceae)-both oils demonstrated antibacterial activity (
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">Carrizo et al., 2009</a>). It has also been suggested that caryophyllene oxide is toxic; this was evaluated using a direct spray test for females and eggs of the predatory mite 
  <span class="italic">Neoseiulus californicus</span> (McGregor) (
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Momen et al., 2014</a>). Further, α-cadinol and caryophyllene oxide were the main volatile compounds found in essential oil extracted from aerial parts of 
  <span class="italic">Teucrium polium</span> L. – Lamiaceae. The essential oil showed fumigant and repellency effects against the cowpea weevil 
  <span class="italic">Callosobruchus maculatus</span> F. (Coleoptera: Bruchidae) (
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">Khani and Asghari, 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">Khani and Heydarian, 2014</a>). α-Cadinol also showed excellent inhibitory action against the termite 
  <span class="italic">Coptotermes formosanus</span> Shiraki (Isoptera: Rhinotermitidae) (
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">Cheng et al., 2014</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
