<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For almost 10 years, antivirulence activities of endemic plants from Madagascar have been regularly reported. Indeed, the bark of 
 <italic>D. pervillei</italic> Vakte and 
 <italic>D. trichocarpa</italic> Baker (Fabaceae; hexane extracts tested at 300 µg/mL) inhibit the production of 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> virulence factors pyocyanin and elastase by 43% and 25%, respectively, and the expression of QS-related (
 <italic>lasI</italic>, 
 <italic>lasR</italic>, 
 <italic>rhlI</italic>, and 
 <italic>rhlR</italic>) and QS-regulated (
 <italic>lasB</italic> and 
 <italic>rhlA</italic>) genes [
 <xref rid="B64-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Further investigations on the hexane bark extract of 
 <italic>D. trichocarpa,</italic> traditionally used to treat various ailments—such as laryngitis, diarrhea, and rheumatic pains—led to the generation of active fractions which exert anti-QS and/or antibiofilm activities. Particularly, an active fraction exerts antibiofilm activities at 200 µg/mL (63% inhibition) without affecting bacterial viability or QS mechanism of 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PAO1. The inhibition of biofilm formation is probably linked to a reduction in flagellar-dependent motilities (swimming and swarming) as well as in exopolysaccharides production [
 <xref rid="B56-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. In Madagascar, a mixture of 
 <italic>Tephrosia purpurea</italic> L. (Fabaceae) and 
 <italic>Buddleja madagascariensis</italic> Lam (Buddlejaceae) macerated in cow dung manure is traditionally used as a phytotreatment against potato crops diseases such as potato leaf spots caused by the phytophatogen 
 <italic>R. solanacearum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B65-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. The study of their antibacterial effects demonstrated that the methanolic extracts of both plants, tested at 100 µg/mL, reduce the expression of 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 QS-regulated 
 <italic>lasB</italic> (45% and 52% inhibition, respectively) and 
 <italic>rhlA</italic> (32% and 33% inhibition, respectively) genes; but only 
 <italic>T. purpurea</italic> extracts exhibit antibiofilm activities against 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 and 
 <italic>R. solanacearum</italic> (52% and 30% inhibition, respectively) without affecting bacterial growth [
 <xref rid="B55-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>].
</p>
