<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Ecol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Ecol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Ecology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6785</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6880604</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">264</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12898-019-0264-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impact of global warming scenarios on life-history traits of <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5911-086X</contrib-id><name><surname>Ghazy</surname><given-names>Noureldin Abuelfadl</given-names></name><address><email>noureldinghazy@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gotoh</surname><given-names>Tetsuo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Takeshi</given-names></name><address><email>tszk@cc.tuat.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.136594.c</institution-id><institution>Graduate School of Bio-Applications and Systems Engineering, </institution><institution>Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>Koganei, Tokyo 184-8588 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000103426662</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10251.37</institution-id><institution>Department of Agricultural Zoology, Faculty of Agriculture, </institution><institution>Mansoura University, </institution></institution-wrap>El-Mansoura, 35516 Egypt </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.444632.3</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Economics, </institution><institution>Ryutsu Keizai University, </institution></institution-wrap>Ryugasaki, Ibaraki 301-8555 Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>48</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The tomato red spider mite, <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> Baker &#x00026; Pritchard (Acari: Tetranychidae), is an agricultural pest of solanaceous crops. Although <italic>T. evansi</italic> is of South American subtropical origin, it has recently expanded its distribution range to many tropical and temperate areas around the world. Its potential distribution range in response to scenarios of global warming was recently modeled, confirming its current and possible future distributions. Here, we experimentally investigated the biological traits of <italic>T. evansi</italic> in the context of the current and future global warming (2100) scenarios. Using an environmental simulation system, we tested the life-history traits of <italic>T. evansi</italic> under current summer temperatures (as of June, July, and August 2016) and under expected temperature increases based on two IPCC scenarios: RCP2.6 (+&#x000a0;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) and RCP8.5 (+&#x000a0;3.7&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C). The mites were introduced into each scenario on 1 June and their sequential progeny were used for testing in each following month.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">The mite could develop and reproduce under all scenarios. There was a decrease in the duration of lifespan and female fecundity at RCP8.5 during June and August, but this may be compensated for by the high intrinsic rate of increase, which implies faster population growth and shorter generation time.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par3">Our study and other reports reveal the high adaptability of <italic>T. evansi</italic> to a wide range of summer temperatures; this may explain its current distribution. We anticipate that global warming will favor the spread of <italic>T. evansi</italic> and may further expand its distribution to a large area of the globe. These findings should be of ecological and practical relevance for designing prevention and control strategies.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Biological invasion</kwd><kwd>Climate change</kwd><kwd>Life table</kwd><kwd>Pest</kwd><kwd>Simulation</kwd><kwd>Tomato red spider mite</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</institution></funding-source><award-id>JP25450069</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Takeshi</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par21">Global warming is expected to have measurable impacts on terrestrial organisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. According to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) and Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs) for greenhouse gas concentration scenarios, the global mean surface temperature is projected to rise by 0.3 to 4.8&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C by the end of the 21st century [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Biological consequences of global warming may include invasion and extinction rate acceleration; interruption of biological timing (reproduction, migration, growing season length, outbreaks, and distributions); disruption of ecological interactions (phenology, food sources, and predators); and alteration of ecosystem composition and functions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. However, the magnitude of these effects will depend largely on a species&#x02019; ability to adapt and cope with global warming or to migrate into more suitable environments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Therefore, understanding the way organisms may adjust to global warming is a key challenge to research into climate change and biological invasion. To visualize the impacts of, and species adjustments to, global warming, accumulation of detailed ecological and biological data are important for predicting potential problems and formulating appropriate countermeasures to conserve rare species and protect against invasive ones.</p><p id="Par22">The tomato red spider mite, <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> Baker &#x00026; Pritchard (Acari: Tetranychidae), was reported for the first time in Brazil by Silva [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. At the time, the species was misidentified as <italic>Tetranychus marianae</italic> McGregor, but it was later described as <italic>T. evansi</italic> by Baker and Pritchard [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. For a summary of the taxonomic status of <italic>T. evansi</italic>, see Navajas et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> is a pest that is destructive to several economically important members of the family Solanaceae, including tomato, eggplant, potato, tobacco, and other nightshade species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Recently, <italic>T. evansi</italic> emerged as an invasive pest distributed in the tropical and temperate areas of nearly 43 countries; it is associated with 136 host plants of 36 plant families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Although <italic>T. evansi</italic> is not a serious pest in its native habitat, it causes severe losses&#x02014;sometimes reaching 100%&#x02014;in tomato and other solanaceous plants, and it also disrupts the community composition of other <italic>Tetranychus</italic> species in invaded areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> does not enter diapause and is able to produce throughout the year if environmental conditions are favorable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Characteristics such as a higher intrinsic rate of increase (particularly at high temperatures: the thermal optimum is&#x02009;~&#x02009;35&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) than other <italic>Tetranychus</italic> species, absence of effective biological control agents, resistance to pesticides, and the ability to manipulate plant defenses account for the high invasive potential of <italic>T. evansi</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p><p id="Par23">In Japan, <italic>T. evansi</italic> was first reported in Osaka in 2001. Its distribution has now expanded throughout the country, particularly in areas with temperate or tropical climates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. According to Boubou et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], two distinct genetic lineages of <italic>T. evansi</italic> have colonized areas outside their region of origin: Lineage 1 has the most invasive potential and has been recorded in several countries around the world, whereas lineage 2 has been found only in some parts of southern Europe. Accordingly, the population of <italic>T. evansi</italic> in East Asia (including Japan) belongs to lineage 1. This lineage has broader adaptability to the climatic gradient in temperate ecosystems and can exploit a wider range of host plants than lineage 2. It might have been accidentally introduced into Japan from neighboring countries in Asia (e.g., Taiwan) or from African or European countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par24">Predicting the geographical distribution range of a species such as <italic>T. evansi</italic>, with its strong invasive abilities, is essential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Using available data, Meynard et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] statistically predicted the current distributions of <italic>T. evansi</italic> in its native range and its invaded range, as well as its expected future expansion range in response to climate change. However, to date, there has been no conclusive, solid, and empirical evidence demonstrating the likely impacts of global warming on the biological activities of <italic>T. evansi</italic>. Assessing population growth, survival, reproduction, and the rate of increase, as influenced by scenarios of global warming, on an individual species basis could be a valid approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Here, we experimentally examined the life-history traits of <italic>T. evansi</italic> under three temperature scenarios: the current temperature, plus two global warming scenarios according to the IPCC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], namely the mean values for &#x0201c;a stringent mitigation scenario&#x0201d; (RCP2.6) and &#x0201c;high greenhouse gas emissions&#x0201d; (RCP8.5) in 2100. For the current temperature scenario, Tokyo summer (June, July, and August) temperatures of 2016 were used. For the future scenarios, current temperatures were increased by 1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C to represent RCP2.6 or by 3.7&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C to represent RCP8.5. We selected summer because this is the season of greatest population expansion of several mite species in the field [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Accuracy of temperature simulation</title><p id="Par25">The set temperatures values under the current and 2100 IPCC scenarios are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. More than 98% of the variance in temperature set values could be explained by changes in the measured values (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Simulated global warming scenarios. &#x0201c;Current,&#x0201d; natural temperature measured at 10-min interval (Japan Meteorological Agency); RCP2.6, current temperature increased by 1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C; RCP8.5, current temperature increased by 3.7&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Mites were introduced to these conditions on 1 June and their sequential progeny were used in each subsequent month</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12898_2019_264_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Pearson correlation coefficient (<italic>r</italic>) of the relationships between set and measured values of temperature in the simulation system under the three scenarios</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12898_2019_264_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Relative humidity</title><p id="Par26">Relative humidity was not controlled (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1). The measured relative humidity during the experiment was&#x02009;~&#x02009;80%,&#x02009;~&#x02009;70%, and&#x02009;~&#x02009;65% under the current, RCP2.6, and RCP8.5 scenarios, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Development and lifespan</title><p id="Par27">Two-way ANOVA for the impact of month and RCP scenario on immature development time, lifespan, and reproduction (eggs/female) showed significant main effects and interactions of both factors (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Different temperature scenarios and months did not have significant effects on hatchability percentage (% hatch) or survival to adulthood (% survival) of immature <italic>T. evansi</italic> (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Two-way ANOVA of factors (months and Representative Concentration Pathway [RCP] scenarios) affecting immature development time (egg-to-adult), lifespan, and reproduction of <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Parameter</th><th align="left">Source</th><th align="left">df</th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Egg-to-adult</td><td align="left">Month</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">34.74</td><td align="left">3992.26</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RCP</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">8.03</td><td align="left">922.94</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Interaction</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">0.19</td><td align="left">21.33</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Residuals</td><td char="." align="char">484</td><td char="." align="char">0.01</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Lifespan</td><td align="left">Month</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">33.17</td><td align="left">41.98</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RCP</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">29.65</td><td align="left">37.53</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Interaction</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">3.86</td><td align="left">4.89</td><td align="left">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Residuals</td><td char="." align="char">469</td><td char="." align="char">0.79</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Reproduction</td><td align="left">Month</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">67.16</td><td align="left">11.58</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RCP</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">131.42</td><td align="left">22.66</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Interaction</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">81.21</td><td align="left">14.00</td><td align="left">&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Residuals</td><td char="." align="char">422</td><td char="." align="char">5.80</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Effects of simulated global warming scenarios on number of days to development at each stage, survival rate to adult, and adult longevity and lifespan of <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Parameter</th><th align="left" colspan="6">Global warming scenario</th></tr><tr><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">Current</th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">RCP2.6</th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">RCP8.5</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">June</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Hatchability (%)</td><td char="." align="char">129</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">96.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5 a</td><td char="." align="char">176</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">94.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7 a</td><td char="." align="char">231</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">93.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Egg</td><td char="." align="char">51</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0 a</td><td char="." align="char">66</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">61</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Larva</td><td char="." align="char">47</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">62</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">61</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Protonymph</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">59</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td><td char="." align="char">59</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Deutonymph</td><td char="." align="char">43</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">57</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td><td char="." align="char">58</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Egg-to-adult</td><td char="." align="char">43</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">57</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td><td char="." align="char">58</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Survival rate (%)</td><td char="." align="char">77</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">90.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.3 a</td><td char="." align="char">77</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">87.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.8 a</td><td char="." align="char">80</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">89.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.4 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Longevity</td><td char="." align="char">36</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6 a</td><td char="." align="char">51</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">17.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0 a</td><td char="." align="char">45</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Lifespan</td><td char="." align="char">41</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">31.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.8 a</td><td char="." align="char">57</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3 a</td><td char="." align="char">51</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">July</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Hatchability (%)</td><td char="." align="char">112</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">98.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3 a</td><td char="." align="char">106</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">99.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9 a</td><td char="." align="char">104</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">98.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Egg</td><td char="." align="char">65</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">4.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">60</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">4.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td><td char="." align="char">58</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Larva</td><td char="." align="char">65</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">60</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td><td char="." align="char">58</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Protonymph</td><td char="." align="char">65</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0 a</td><td char="." align="char">58</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td><td char="." align="char">57</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Deutonymph</td><td char="." align="char">64</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">58</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">54</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Egg-to-adult</td><td char="." align="char">64</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">11.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">58</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td><td char="." align="char">54</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Survival rate (%)</td><td char="." align="char">75</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">96.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0 a</td><td char="." align="char">74</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">96.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2 a</td><td char="." align="char">76</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">92.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.9 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Longevity</td><td char="." align="char">61</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9 a</td><td char="." align="char">54</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">17.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8 b</td><td char="." align="char">50</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.1 ab</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Lifespan</td><td char="." align="char">62</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9 a</td><td char="." align="char">58</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">25.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0 a</td><td char="." align="char">54</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">23.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">August</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Hatchability (%)</td><td char="." align="char">207</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">96.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3 a</td><td char="." align="char">146</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">93.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0 a</td><td char="." align="char">310</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">91.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Egg</td><td char="." align="char">68</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">4.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0 a</td><td char="." align="char">60</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">62</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Larva</td><td char="." align="char">68</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0 a</td><td char="." align="char">56</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td><td char="." align="char">59</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Protonymph</td><td char="." align="char">67</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">42</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td><td char="." align="char">56</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Deutonymph</td><td char="." align="char">65</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">42</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td><td char="." align="char">52</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Egg-to-adult</td><td char="." align="char">65</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">42</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td><td char="." align="char">52</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Survival rate (%)</td><td char="." align="char">78</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">92.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.9 a</td><td char="." align="char">67</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">86.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">78</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">79.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.6 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Longevity</td><td char="." align="char">48</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0 a</td><td char="." align="char">37</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0 a</td><td char="." align="char">50</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Lifespan</td><td char="." align="char">51</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">23.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">42</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3 a</td><td char="." align="char">62</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 b</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM, in days unless noted otherwise. Values with the same letter in rows are not significantly different (<italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par28">There were significant differences in the durations of the immature stages and in adult longevity and lifespan among different temperature scenarios during June (eggs: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 175</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;621.7; larvae: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 167</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17.93; protonymphs: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 159</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;43.66; deutonymphs: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 155</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;64.03; egg-to-adult: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 155</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;497.4; longevity: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 129</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;14.95; lifespan: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 149</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17.91; <italic>P</italic><sub>all</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Post-hoc comparisons revealed no significant differences between the current and RCP2.6 scenarios in the lengths of the egg and larval periods and in adult longevity and lifespan (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05), but significant differences were found between these two scenarios for the duration of the protonymph (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001) and deutonymph (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0055) stages and for total egg-to-adult period duration (<italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The durations of the immature stages, as well as adult longevity and lifespan, of mites reared under the current scenario were all significantly different from those of mites reared under the RCP8.5 scenario (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). The immature development and adult longevity and lifespan were generally longer in mites reared under RCP2.6 than in those reared under RCP8.5 (protonymphs, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0343; others, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001).</p><p id="Par29">During July there were significant differences among different temperature scenarios in the durations of the egg incubation period (<italic>F</italic><sub>2, 180</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;140.4, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001), the larval period (<italic>F</italic><sub>2, 180</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13.26, <italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001), the protonymph stage (<italic>F</italic><sub>2, 177</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;34.5, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001), and the egg-to-adult period (<italic>F</italic><sub>2, 173</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;229.8, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001), but not in the length of the deutonymph stage (<italic>F</italic><sub>2, 173</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.466, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.234). Adult longevity differed significantly among scenarios (<italic>F</italic><sub>2, 162</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.316, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0388) but lifespan did not (<italic>F</italic><sub>2, 171</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.656, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.194). Post-hoc comparison showed that, with the exception of deutonymph period duration and lifespan (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05), all other developmental periods differed significantly among different temperature scenarios in July (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p><p id="Par30">In August there were significant differences among temperature scenarios in the durations of the immature stages and the adult longevity and lifespan of <italic>T. evansi</italic> (eggs: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 187</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;37.98; larvae: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 180</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;32.47; protonymphs: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 162</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;19.24; deutonymphs: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 156</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;32.06; egg-to-adult: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 156</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;265.6; longevity: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 132</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;27.36; lifespan: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 152</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;31.01; <italic>P</italic><sub>all</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). The larval, deutonymph, and egg-to-adult periods, but not the egg incubation period (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0571), were significantly longer in mites reared at the current temperature than in those reared at RCP2.6 (<italic>P</italic><sub>all</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001), whereas the protonymph stage was significantly shorter in the former. The immature stages (except protonymphs) of mites reared under the current temperature were significantly longer than those of mites reared at RCP8.5. The egg incubation, protonymph, and egg-to-adult periods of mites reared at RCP8.5 were significantly shorter than those of mites reared at RCP2.6 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). Adult longevity and lifespan did not differ significantly between the current and RCP2.6 scenarios (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05), but both were significantly greater under these two scenarios than under RCP8.5 (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). Male egg-to-adult duration was slightly shorter than that of females under all test conditions (data not shown).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Reproductive phases, fecundity, and sex ratio</title><p id="Par31">The durations of the reproductive phases (pre-oviposition period [PrOP], oviposition period [OP], and post-oviposition period [PsOP]), as well as fecundity (total eggs/female [TEF]), varied among different temperature scenarios (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). In June there were significant differences among temperature scenarios in the durations of the reproductive phases and in fecundity (PrOP: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 140</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.148, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0011; OP: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 129</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;15.4, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001; PsOP: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 129</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.931, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0034; TEF: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 128</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13.31, <italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). Duration of the oviposition and post-oviposition periods, as well as total eggs/female, did not differ significantly between mites under the current and RCP2.6 scenarios during June (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05), whereas the pre-oviposition period was significantly longer under current conditions (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0182). During June, mites reared under RCP8.5 had a significantly shorter oviposition period and fewer total eggs/female than those under the current and RCP2.6 scenarios (<italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). There were no significant differences in sex ratio among different temperature scenarios in June (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Effects of simulated global warming scenarios on length of reproductive phases, fecundity, and sex ratio of <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Parameter</th><th align="left" colspan="6">Global warming scenario</th></tr><tr><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">Current</th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">RCP2.6</th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">RCP8.5</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">June</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Pre-oviposition</td><td char="." align="char">36</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">56</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0 b</td><td char="." align="char">51</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Oviposition</td><td char="." align="char">36</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5 a</td><td char="." align="char">51</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9 a</td><td char="." align="char">45</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Post-oviposition</td><td char="." align="char">36</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 ab</td><td char="." align="char">51</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 a</td><td char="." align="char">45</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Eggs/female (no.)</td><td char="." align="char">36</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">93.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.5 a</td><td char="." align="char">51</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">90.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.9 a</td><td char="." align="char">45</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">50.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.3 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x02640; ratio (%)</td><td char="." align="char">197</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">87.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.4 a</td><td char="." align="char">177</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">85.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.6 a</td><td char="." align="char">171</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">87.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.5 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">July</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Pre-oviposition</td><td char="." align="char">63</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="." align="char">56</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0 b</td><td char="." align="char">54</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Oviposition</td><td char="." align="char">61</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8 a</td><td char="." align="char">54</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 b</td><td char="." align="char">50</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0 ab</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Post-oviposition</td><td char="." align="char">61</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 a</td><td char="." align="char">54</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 a</td><td char="." align="char">50</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Eggs/female (no.)</td><td char="." align="char">61</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">78.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.7 a</td><td char="." align="char">54</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">105.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.6 b</td><td char="." align="char">50</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">108.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.1 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x02640; ratio (%)</td><td char="." align="char">442</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">91.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3 a</td><td char="." align="char">433</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">91.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3 a</td><td char="." align="char">383</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">90.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">August</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Pre-oviposition</td><td char="." align="char">65</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0 a</td><td char="." align="char">40</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0 b</td><td char="." align="char">50</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 ab</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Oviposition</td><td char="." align="char">48</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0 a</td><td char="." align="char">37</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9 a</td><td char="." align="char">50</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Post-oviposition</td><td char="." align="char">48</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 a</td><td char="." align="char">37</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 a</td><td char="." align="char">50</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Eggs/female (no.)</td><td char="." align="char">48</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">89.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.9 a</td><td char="." align="char">37</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">97.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.5 a</td><td char="." align="char">50</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">45.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.6 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;&#x02640; ratio (%)</td><td char="." align="char">425</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">83.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.8 a</td><td char="." align="char">292</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">86.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0 a</td><td char="." align="char">331</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">79.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.2 a</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM, in days unless otherwise stated. Values with the same letter in rows are not significantly different (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par32">In July, there were significant differences among temperature scenarios in the durations of the pre-oviposition and oviposition periods, as well as in total eggs/female, but not in the post-oviposition period (PrOP: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 170</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;12.85, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001; OP: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 162</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.052, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0074; PsOP: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 162</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.101, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.335; TEF: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 162</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.182, <italic>P&#x02009;</italic>=&#x02009;0.0010). In July, mites under RCP2.6 or RCP8.5 had pre-oviposition periods significantly shorter than those under the current temperature; the oviposition period under RCP2.6 was significantly longer than that under the current scenario but similar to that under RCP8.5, and total eggs/female under RCP2.6 and RCP8.5 was significantly greater than under the current scenario. There were no significant differences in sex ratio among different temperature scenarios in July (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05).</p><p id="Par33">In a pattern similar to that in July, there were significant differences among temperature scenarios in the durations of the pre-oviposition and oviposition periods and in total eggs/female, but not in the duration of the post-oviposition period (PrOP: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 152</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.785, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0249; OP: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 132</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;28.11, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001; PsOP: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 132</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.89, <italic>P&#x02009;</italic>=&#x02009;0.155; TEF: <italic>F</italic><sub>2, 132</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;37.13, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). The oviposition period was significantly shorter, and total eggs/female significantly fewer, under RCP8.5 than under the other two temperature scenarios (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001). The ratio of females to males under RCP8.5 was slightly smaller than those under the current and RCP2.6 scenarios, but the differences were not significant (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Life tables</title><p id="Par34">A steeper decline in the age-specific survival rate (<italic>l</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub>) curve was observed in mites under RCP8.5 in June and August (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) owing to higher mortalities among adults in both months. In June and August the declines under the current and RCP2.6 scenarios were similar. In July, the <italic>l</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub> curves all declined in a similar manner. The age-specific fecundity (<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub>, females/female/day) curves revealed that the onset of reproduction and the reproduction peak approached earlier in mites reared under RCP8.5 than in mites reared under RCP2.6 or the current scenario, regardless of the month. The highest peak in June occurred under RCP2.6 (7.8 females/female/day), in July under RCP2.6 (11.2 females/female/day), and in August under the current scenario (10 females/female/day).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Age-specific survival rate (<italic>l</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub>) and age-specific fecundity (<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub>) of <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> under different global warming scenarios</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12898_2019_264_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par35">In June, there were significant differences among temperature scenarios of current and RCP8.5 in all life table parameters (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The mean values of <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub> (41.5), and <italic>T</italic> (17.8) were lower under RCP8.5 and differed significantly from those under RCP2.6. The intrinsic rate of increase and finite rate of increase under RCP8.5 were significantly higher than those under current scenario. To a similar extent, in July there were significant differences among temperature scenarios in the life table values; the means of the life-table values under RCP2.6 and RCP8.5 differed significantly from those under the current temperature. In August, there were significant differences among temperature scenarios of current and RCP2.6 in <italic>T</italic> (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001), <italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub> (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0085), <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0085) and <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>t</italic></sub> (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0087) but not <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub> (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Effects of simulated global warming scenarios on life-table parameters of <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Parameter</th><th align="left" colspan="6">Global warming scenario</th></tr><tr><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">Current</th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">RCP2.6</th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">RCP8.5</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">June</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td align="left" rowspan="5">41</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">72.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.8 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char" rowspan="5">59</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">73.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.5 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char" rowspan="5">55</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">39.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.0 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>T</italic></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">23.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">22.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">17.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.178&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.193&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004 ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.205&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.006 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>&#x003bb;</italic></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.195&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.006 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.213&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004 ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.228&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.007 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>D</italic><sub><italic>t</italic></sub></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 ab</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">July</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td align="left" rowspan="5">67</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">70.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.8 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char" rowspan="5">59</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">93.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.5 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char" rowspan="5">53</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">90.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.8 ab</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>T</italic></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">17.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.245&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.005 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.272&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.298&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.006 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>&#x003bb;</italic></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.278&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.006 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.312&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.005 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.347&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.008 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>D</italic><sub><italic>t</italic></sub></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">August</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td align="left" rowspan="5">58</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">73.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.0 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char" rowspan="5">43</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">77.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.5 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char" rowspan="5">75</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.4 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>T</italic></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.262&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.283&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.006 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.264&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.008 ab</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>&#x003bb;</italic></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.300&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.006 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.328&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.008 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.302&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.011 ab</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;<italic>D</italic><sub><italic>t</italic></sub></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 ab</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM. Values with the same letter in rows are not significantly different at <italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 by using paired bootstrap test</p><p><italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>, net reproductive rate; <italic>T</italic>, generation time; <italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub>, intrinsic rate of population increase; <italic>&#x003bb;</italic>, finite rate of population increase; <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>t</italic></sub>, population doubling time</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par36">The tomato red spider mite, <italic>T. evansi</italic>, is a serious agricultural pest with high invasion potential and is currently spread over many countries worldwide. Unlike other <italic>Tetranychus</italic> species, <italic>T. evansi</italic> develops at a range of temperature between 12 and 45&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C; it has a high thermal optimum (~&#x02009;35 to 43&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) and a high rate of population increase (<italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;~&#x02009;0.4 at 35&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. These features enhance the ability of <italic>T. evansi</italic> to invade and adapt to a variety of geographical areas with varying climates and to become an emerging agricultural pest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. It is therefore not surprising that we found here that <italic>T. evansi</italic> developed and reproduced even under the 2100 RCP8.5 scenario, in which the temperature was 3.7&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C above the current temperature and the maximum temperature experienced by the mites was 41.1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, during August. In general, development was favored by high temperatures (i.e., faster development with increased temperature), but reproduction was still high within moderate temperature ranges (i.e., under the current and RCP2.6 scenarios).</p><sec id="Sec9"><title>Development and reproduction</title><p id="Par37">The egg hatchability of <italic>T. evansi</italic> decreased slightly (but not significantly across scenarios within months) with increasing temperature and was as low as 91.3% at RCP8.5 in August. Different strains of <italic>T. evansi</italic> reared at a constant range of temperatures (15 to 35&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) have shown 95% to 99% hatchability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Our results suggested that the hatchability, as well as several life-history traits, of <italic>T. evansi</italic> exposed to natural fluctuations in temperature to high levels in August (peaking at more than 40&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C under RCP8.5) might be hindered. In a manner similar to other mite species, <italic>T. evansi</italic> generally developed faster as the temperature increased. Under the current temperature scenario, the egg-to-adult period was 16.1&#x000a0;days in June, 11.0&#x000a0;days in July, and 9.2&#x000a0;days in August, when the monthly average temperatures were 22.4, 25.4, and 27.1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, respectively. The egg-to-adult period was&#x02009;~&#x02009;1&#x000a0;day shorter under RCP2.6 (+&#x000a0;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) than in the current scenario. Under RCP8.5 (+&#x000a0;3.7&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C), the egg-to-adult period was 2 to 4&#x000a0;days shorter than in the current scenario and 1 to 3&#x000a0;days shorter than under RCP2.6. Under semi-field conditions in Mauritius, Moutia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] reported that the egg-to-adult period of <italic>T. evansi</italic> was about 6.5&#x000a0;days in summer (mean temperature 22.8&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) and 18.5&#x000a0;days in winter (mean temperature 19.4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C). The value of 6.5&#x000a0;days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] is much shorter than the values we obtained here&#x02014;for example, under the current scenario in June, when the average temperature was&#x02009;~&#x02009;22&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. This difference undoubtedly is a result of differences in the diurnal temperature fluctuation patterns between the tropical climate of Mauritius (20.3484&#x000b0;&#x000a0;S, 57.5522&#x000b0;&#x000a0;E) and the temperate to humid subtropical climate of Tokyo (35.6895&#x000b0;&#x000a0;N, 139.6917&#x000b0;&#x000a0;E). Our <italic>T. evansi</italic> males developed slightly faster than the females (data not shown), and this trend was common among all conditions tested. This phenology is common among <italic>Tetranychus</italic> species and has been reported before in <italic>T. evansi</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The immature survival rate (i.e., rate of survival to adulthood) ranged from 80% to 97%, with no significant effects of different temperature scenarios within the same month. To a similar extent, different strains of <italic>T. evansi</italic> reared at temperatures between 15 and 35&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C have survival rates between 88 and 98%, with no significant differences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par38">The lifespan of mites reared at RCP8.5 in June was about two-thirds those of mites reared under the other scenarios, and the total eggs/female was about half that under the current and RCP2.6 scenarios. This trend was reversed during July, in which month the lifespan was similar among the different temperature scenarios. Interestingly, total eggs/female during July was significantly greater for females at RCP2.6 (~&#x02009;106 eggs/female) and RCP8.5 (~&#x02009;109 eggs/female) than under the current scenario (~&#x02009;78 eggs/female). In accordance with our experimental design, whereby the mites were introduced to each climate change scenario at the beginning of June and their offspring were used in the experiment the following month, the mites under RCP2.6 and RCP8.5 may have had the advantage of being adapted to temperature increases. Nevertheless, with the further increase in temperature during August under RCP8.5 the mites suffered a huge reduction in their lifespans and reproduction as compared with under other scenarios (see Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). This can be explained by the maximum thermal limit for <italic>T. evansi</italic>, which might have been reached under RCP8.5 in August, resulting in large mortality rates among adults (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The percentage of females among the offspring ranged from 79% to 92% (see Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). A female-biased sex ratio is common among different strains of <italic>T. evansi</italic>, and to some extent it is higher than in other <italic>Tetranychus</italic> species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Life tables</title><p id="Par39">Life tables are very convenient tools for assessing environmental effects on population development, survival, and reproduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] The net reproductive rate (females/female/generation) was highest under current and RCP2.6 in June and August, but it differed significantly from that in the current scenario in July and from that under RCP8.5 only in June and August (see Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Generation time (days) was shortest under RCP8.5 and ranged from 17.8&#x000a0;days in June to 12.9&#x000a0;days in August. The intrinsic rate of population increase was, in general, higher at increased temperature owing to the short development time and early peak reproduction. This might also explain the wide temperature range at which <italic>T. evansi</italic> is able to develop and cause economic crop losses. The finite rate of increase (females/female/day) displayed a trend similar to <italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub>. Population doubling times were similar between RCP2.6 and RCP8.5 temperature scenarios in June, significantly shorter under the two scenarios in July, and similar between current and RCP8.5 and between RCP2.6 and RCP8.5 in August. Because of the fluctuating nature of temperature regimens that mimic natural conditions, the life-history and life-table trait measurements that we obtained here are, to some extent, different from those in previous reports that have relied solely on laboratory studies at constant temperatures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Environmental factors other than temperature might be involved (e.g., host plant, see Murungi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]). However, these differences among results further highlight the importance of and the need for gathering biological measurements under conditions that mimic the natural diurnal fluctuations in environmental factors such as temperature.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par40">Invasive alien pest species pose great challenges to world agriculture, biodiversity, and ecosystems. Empirical evidence of the likely impact of global warming on agricultural pests is essential. Our findings indicated that <italic>T. evansi</italic> is able to rapidly adapt to the increases in temperature; therefore, with long-term adaptation, the mite will be able to spread more widely and to a broad range of environmental temperatures. As well as possessing the advantages of a high thermal optimum, short generation time, and high rate of population growth, <italic>T. evansi</italic>&#x02014;as is becoming evident in other organisms&#x02014;might have already undergone what is known as &#x0201c;micro-evolutionary change in situ&#x0201d;; through its journey from its native range to almost everywhere around the world this species may already have encountered large environmental variations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. This speculation is supported by the fact that <italic>T. evansi</italic> has already spread to a geographical area that has climatic gradients different from those in its native habit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Our findings and previous modeling results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] are in agreement that the greatest <italic>T. evansi</italic> threat will be shifted to higher latitudes. However, it might be difficult to generalize our findings to other pest mites, because development and reproduction temperatures are species-specific and have to be assessed on an individual species basis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Mite culture</title><p id="Par41">The founder population of <italic>T. evansi</italic> was originally collected from black nightshade plant (<italic>Solanum nigrum</italic> L.) in Tokyo (Japan, 35&#x000b0;35&#x02032;&#x000a0;N, 139&#x000b0;36&#x02032;&#x000a0;E) in November 2006 and was maintained on black nightshade at 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C under a 16:8-h (light:dark) photoperiod at the Laboratory of Applied Entomology and Zoology, Faculty of Agriculture, Ibaraki University, Japan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. A colony of <italic>T. evansi</italic> was brought to our laboratory at Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology in May 2017 and thereafter maintained on detached leaves of eggplant (<italic>Solanum melongena</italic> L. cv. Senryo #2) at 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with a 16:8-h photoperiod. The mites were maintained on eggplant for about 3&#x000a0;months before they were used in the experiments.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Climate data</title><p id="Par42">Temperature data for Tokyo in 2016 (June, July, and August) in 10-min measurement intervals were obtained from the Japan Meteorological Agency (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jma.go.jp/jma/index.html">http://www.jma.go.jp/jma/index.html</ext-link>). To examine the effects of predicted global warming, the average temperature increase values in two scenarios defined by the IPCC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] were used. Under RCP2.6 the temperature was projected to increase by 1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, and under RCP8.5 by 3.7&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, on average. An environmental simulation system (ESS) was used to simulate temperature data and create the three scenarios. ESS is a computer-based closed system for simulating natural climate conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Briefly, the system software created a schedule of 10-min intervals with corresponding set values of air temperature (set temperature, TSVs) and continuously measured the process values of air temperature (measured temperature, TPVs). TPV was adjusted to TSV by switching on or off an air heater (TSR210-A; Tescom, Tokyo, Japan) and a refrigerator (JF-NU40B; Haier Japan Sales, Osaka, Japan) every 10&#x000a0;min. The daily natural photoperiod was also created by the system by turning on or off light-emitting diodes. Relative humidity was not simulated but was recorded throughout the experiments (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Development and reproduction</title><p id="Par43">Three units of the ESS were used simultaneously. Each unit was assigned to one of the temperature scenarios. A random-aged egg-laying adult females of <italic>T. evansi</italic> were introduced onto a detached eggplant leaf (ca. 40&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;40&#x000a0;mm) placed upside down on a water-saturated cotton pad in a polystyrene square Petri dish (100&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;15&#x000a0;mm). Then, on 1 June, each dish was transferred to one of the ESS units; the females were left to lay eggs for 24&#x000a0;h and then removed. The eggs were categorized into two groups: one group was kept on the same detached leaf until hatching and used to calculate hatchability percentages. The other group (approximately 80 eggs) was transferred separately onto eggplant leaf discs (1&#x000a0;cm in diameter) and observed daily throughout the mites&#x02019; whole lifespan. Leaf discs were replaced every 3&#x000a0;days or when necessary. Upon adult female emergence, one adult male was introduced for copulation. To determine the sex ratio, 2 or 3&#x000a0;days after the onset of oviposition, the eggs laid by females in each treatment during 2 consecutive days were collected and transferred to a new detached eggplant leaf. The collected eggs were kept to develop to adulthood and then sexed. These adults were maintained under the same conditions and used to produce eggs for the consecutive-month experiment. For example, the June progeny under the current scenario were transferred to a new detached leaf on 1 July under the same scenario and allowed to lay eggs for 24&#x000a0;h; the adults were then discarded and the eggs treated as previously. The same observations and experimental procedures were applied to other months and scenarios.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par44">Pearson&#x02019;s correlation coefficient was used to examine the relationship between TSVs and TPVs as evidence of simulation accuracy. Percentages (hatchability, survival to adulthood, and sex ratio) were compared by using a Chi-squared test with Bonferroni correction. Two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to test the effects of month and temperature scenario on development time (egg-to-adult), lifespan, and reproduction (eggs/female). One-way ANOVA with Tukey&#x02019;s post hoc test was used for means separation with &#x003b1;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05. The development and reproduction data were square-root transformed to meet assumptions of normality when necessary and retransformed for representation purposes. The data for development, survival rate, longevity and female daily fecundity were analyzed according to the age-stage, two-sex life table approach using the computer program TWOSEX-MSChart [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. The following parameters were calculated as described by Chi &#x00026; Liu [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]: age-stage-specific survival rate (<italic>s</italic><sub><italic>xj</italic></sub>, the probability that a newly laid egg will survive to age <italic>x</italic> and stage <italic>j</italic>), age-specific survival rate (<italic>l</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub>, the percentage of females alive at age <italic>x</italic>), age-specific fecundity (<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub>, the number of female offspring produced by a female in a unit of time), age-stage specific fecundity (<italic>f</italic><sub><italic>xj</italic></sub>, the mean fecundity of females at age <italic>x</italic>), intrinsic rate of natural increase (<italic>r</italic>), finite rate of increase (<italic>&#x003bb;</italic>, the number of times the population multiplies in a unit of time), net reproductive rate (<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>, number of female offspring/female/generation), mean generation time (<italic>T</italic>, mean age of mothers at time of birth of female offspring) and population doubling time (<italic>D</italic><sub><italic>t</italic></sub>, the time needed for the population to double). The age-specific survival rate (<italic>l</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub>) and age-specific fecundity (<italic>m</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub>) are calculated as:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$l_{x} = \mathop \sum \limits_{j = 1}^{k} s_{xj}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">xj</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12898_2019_264_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$m_{x} = \frac{{\mathop \sum \nolimits_{j = 1}^{k} s_{xj} f_{xj} }}{{\mathop \sum \nolimits_{j = 1}^{k} s_{xj} }}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">xj</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">xj</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">xj</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12898_2019_264_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>k</italic> is the number of life stages. The reproductive rate (<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>) is calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="Equc"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_{0} = \mathop \sum \limits_{x = 0}^{\infty } l_{x} m_{x}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12898_2019_264_Article_Equc.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p><p id="Par46">The intrinsic rate of population increase (<italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub>) was calculated by using the Euler&#x02013;Lotka equation as follows:<disp-formula id="Equd"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathop \sum \limits_{x = 0}^{\infty } e^{{ - r_{m} \left( {x + 1} \right)}} l_{x} m_{x} = 1$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x0221e;</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12898_2019_264_Article_Equd.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>x</italic> is a female age in days. The finite rate of increase (<italic>&#x003bb;</italic>), mean generation time (<italic>T</italic>) and population doubling time (<italic>D</italic><sub><italic>t</italic></sub>) are calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="Eque"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$T = \ln \frac{{R_{0} }}{{r_{m} }},$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12898_2019_264_Article_Eque.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="Equf"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\lambda = e^{{r_{m} }} ,$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12898_2019_264_Article_Equf.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="Equg"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$D_{t} = \frac{\ln 2}{{r_{m} }}.$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12898_2019_264_Article_Equg.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p><p id="Par48">The bootstrap procedure (B&#x02009;=&#x02009;100,000) was used to estimate means and standard errors for the life tables parameters and the paired bootstrap test&#x000a0;was used to compare different treatment based on the confidence interval of the differences using TWOSEX-MSChart [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. ANOVAs were performed in R v. 3.4.0 software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Pearson&#x02019;s correlation coefficient was determined by using scipy.stats.pearsonr in Python [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Data were visualized with Matplotlib in Python [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec17"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12898_2019_264_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Figure S1.</bold> Relative humidity (%) measurements made during the experiments.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ESS</term><def><p id="Par4">environmental simulation system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>fig</term><def><p id="Par5">figure</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IPCC</term><def><p id="Par6">intergovernmental panel on climate change</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>l</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub></term><def><p id="Par7">age-specific survival rate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>m</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub></term><def><p id="Par8">age-specific fecundity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OP</term><def><p id="Par9">oviposition period</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PrOP</term><def><p id="Par10">pre-oviposition period</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PsOP</term><def><p id="Par11">post-oviposition period</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub></term><def><p id="Par12">net reproductive rate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>T</italic></term><def><p id="Par13">generation time</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>r</italic><sub>m</sub></term><def><p id="Par14">intrinsic rate of population increase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RCP</term><def><p id="Par15">representative concentration pathway</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TEF</term><def><p id="Par16">total eggs/female</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TPV</term><def><p id="Par17">measured temperature</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TSV</term><def><p id="Par18">set temperature</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>&#x003bb;</italic></term><def><p id="Par19">finite rate of population increase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>D</italic><sub><italic>t</italic></sub></term><def><p id="Par20">population doubling time</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1186/s12898-019-0264-6.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Masao Ohyama for his technical assistance in developing the simulation system used in this study.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>NAG and TS designed the study and performed the research. NAG, TS and TG analyzed the data. NAG and TS wrote the first draft of the manuscript. All authors contributed to revisions. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study is supported by the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science JSPS (Grants Numbers JP25450069, L17551). The funding sources had no roles in the design of the study, data collection and data analysis, interpretation of data or in the writing of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The data used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding authors on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par49">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent to publish</title><p id="Par50">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par51">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bale</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Masters</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodkinson</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Awmack</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezemer</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Butterfield</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Buse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Good</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbivory in global climate change research: direct effects of rising temperature on insect herbivores</article-title><source>Glob Change Biol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2486.2002.00451.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Regniere</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the impacts of global warming on forest pest dynamics</article-title><source>Front Ecol Environ</source><year>2003</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/1540-9295(2003)001[0130:ATIOGW]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deutsch</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tewksbury</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghalambor</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Haak</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impacts of climate warming on terrestrial ectotherms across latitude</article-title><source>PNAS</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>6668</fpage><lpage>6672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0709472105</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18458348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18458348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macfadyen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From species distributions to climate change adaptation: knowledge gaps in managing invertebrate pests in broad-acre grain crops</article-title><source>Agric Ecosyst Environ</source><year>2018</year><volume>253</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agee.2016.08.029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pachauri</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Broome</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Christ</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Climate change 2014: synthesis report. Contribution of Working Groups I, II and III to the fifth assessment report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</source><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>IPCC</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological consequences of global warming: is the signal already apparent?</article-title><source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><year>2000</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-5347(99)01764-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10652556?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10652556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lad&#x000e1;nyi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Horv&#x000e1;th</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of the potential climate change impact on insect populations-general and agricultural aspects</article-title><source>Appl Ecol Environ Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15666/aeer/0802_143151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Arakaki</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannistra</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kharouba</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingsolver</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insect development, thermal plasticity and fitness implications in changing, seasonal environments</article-title><source>Integr Comp Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>988</fpage><lpage>998</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/icb/icx032</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28662575?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28662575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arribas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Abell&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mill&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conservation of insects in the face of global climate change</article-title><source>Global climate change and terrestrial invertebrates</source><year>2017</year><publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>367</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Um novo a&#x000b4;caro nocivo ao tomateiro na Bahia</article-title><source>Bol Inst Biol Bahia.</source><year>1954</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The tetranychoid mites of Africa</article-title><source>Hilgardia</source><year>1960</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3733/hilg.v29n11p455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navajas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Moraes</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Migeon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review of the invasion of <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic>: biology, colonization pathways, potential expansion and prospects for biological control</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>2013</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-012-9590-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22824945?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22824945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moutia</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution to the study of some phytophagous Acarina and their predators in Mauritius</article-title><source>Bull Entomol Res</source><year>1958</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007485300053438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qureshi</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Oatman</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleschner</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biology of the spider mite, <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic></article-title><source>Ann Entomol Soc Am</source><year>1969</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>898</fpage><lpage>903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aesa/62.4.898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Moraes</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McMurtry</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of temperature and sperm supply on the reproductive potential of <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae)</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>1987</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01270471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Migeon A, Dorkeld F. Spider Mites Web: a comprehensive database for the Tetranychidae. 2006&#x02013;2017. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www1.montpellier.inra.fr/CBGP/spmweb/">http://www1.montpellier.inra.fr/CBGP/spmweb/</ext-link>. Accessed 5 Mar 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gotoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Boubou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Migeon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferragut</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Navajas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence of co-specificity between <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> and <italic>Tetranychus takafujii</italic> (Acari: Prostigmata, Tetranychidae): comments on taxonomic and agricultural aspects</article-title><source>Int J Acarol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01647950903431156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Migeon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferragut</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Escudero-Colomar</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiaboe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Moraes</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueckermann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Navajas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modelling the potential distribution of the invasive tomato red spider mite, <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae)</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>2009</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-008-9229-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19153813?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19153813</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kazak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000f6;ker</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Karut</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First record of invasive tomato spider mite <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae) in Turkey</article-title><source>Int J Acarol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01647954.2017.1294199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferragut</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Garz&#x000f3;n-Luque</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pekas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The invasive spider mite <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae) alters community composition and host-plant use of native relatives</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>2013</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-012-9645-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23238959?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23238959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furtado</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name><name><surname>De Moraes</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreiter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Flechtmann</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tixier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant inhabiting phytoseiid predators of midwestern Brazil, with emphasis on those associated with the tomato red spider mite, <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> (Acari: Phytoseiidae, Tetranychidae)</article-title><source>Acarologia.</source><year>2014</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/acarologia/20142138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonato</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of temperature on life history parameters of <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae)</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>1999</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1006144610009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gotoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pallini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez-Suarez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferragut</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Migeon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Navajas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nachman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reproductive performance of seven strains of the tomato red spider mite <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae) at five temperatures</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>2010</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-010-9362-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20383565?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gotoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitashima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Susceptibility to acaricides in nine strains of the tomato red spider mite <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae)</article-title><source>Int J Acarol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01647954.2010.497498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nyoni</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mzilahowa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Navajas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pyrethroid resistance in the tomato red spider mite, Tetranychus evansi, is associated with mutation of the para-type sodium channel</article-title><source>Pest Manag Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>891</fpage><lpage>897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ps.2145</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21432985?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21432985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schimmel</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ataide</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chafi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Villarroel</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alba</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuurink</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kant</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overcompensation of herbivore reproduction through hyper-suppression of plant defenses in response to competition</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2017</year><volume>214</volume><fpage>1688</fpage><lpage>1701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.14543</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28386959?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28386959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new species of <italic>Tetranychus</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae) from the Kinki district, Japan</article-title><source>Acta Arachnol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2476/asjaa.51.19</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boubou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Migeon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roderick</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Navajas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent emergence and worldwide spread of the red tomato spider mite, <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic>: genetic variation and multiple cryptic invasions</article-title><source>Biol Invasions</source><year>2011</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10530-010-9791-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boubou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Migeon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roderick</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornuet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Magalh&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Navajas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Test of colonisation scenarios reveals complex invasion history of the red tomato spider mite <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic></article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e35601</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035601</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22539983?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22539983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Migeon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hufbauer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Navajas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic traits leading to invasion: plasticity in cold hardiness explains current distribution of an invasive agricultural pest, <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae)</article-title><source>Biol Invasions</source><year>2015</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2275</fpage><lpage>2285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10530-015-0873-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meynard</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Migeon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Navajas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uncertainties in predicting species distributions under climate change: a case study using <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae), a widespread agricultural pest</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e66445</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0066445</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23799105?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23799105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santamar&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Migeon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Casta&#x000f1;era</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Navajas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortego</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host plant use by two distinct lineages of the tomato red spider mite, <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic>, differing in their distribution range</article-title><source>J Pest Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10340-017-0852-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takafuji</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamibayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Life cycle of a non-diapausing population of the two-spotted spider mite, <italic>Tetranychus urticae</italic> Koch in a pear orchard</article-title><source>Res Popul Ecol.</source><year>1984</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02515511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montserrat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sah&#x000fa;n</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Guzm&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can climate change jeopardize predator control of invasive herbivore species? A case study in avocado agro-ecosystems in Spain</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>2013</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-012-9560-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22527837?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22527837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montserrat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guzm&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sah&#x000fa;n</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Belda</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hormaza</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pollen supply promotes, but high temperatures demote, predatory mite abundance in avocado orchards</article-title><source>Agric Ecosyst Environ</source><year>2013</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agee.2012.09.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghazy</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Osakabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Negm</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schausberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Amano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytoseiid mites under environmental stress</article-title><source>Biol Control</source><year>2016</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2016.02.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghazy</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Amano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and reproduction of <italic>Neoseiulus californicus</italic> (Acari: Phytoseiidae) and <italic>Tetranychus urticae</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae) under simulated natural temperature</article-title><source>Environ Entomol</source><year>2018</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1005</fpage><lpage>1012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ee/nvy067</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29767731?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29767731</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maia</surname><given-names>ADH</given-names></name><name><surname>Luiz</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Campanhola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Statistical inference on associated fertility life parameters using jackknife technique: computational aspects</article-title><source>J Econ Entomol</source><year>2000</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0022-0493-93.2.511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10826207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murungi</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyende</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wesonga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Masinde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of African nightshade species (Solanaceae) on developmental time and life table parameters of <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae)</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>2010</year><volume>52</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-010-9350-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20229322?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20229322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change and evolutionary adaptations at species&#x02019; range margins</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><year>2011</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-ento-120709-144746</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20809802?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20809802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pauls</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e1;lint</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfenninger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of global climate change on genetic diversity within populations and species</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>2013</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>925</fpage><lpage>946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mec.12152</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23279006?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23279006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishide</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synchrony in the hatching of eggs in the desert locust <italic>Schistocerca gregaria</italic> (Orthoptera: Acrididae): egg condition influences hatching time in the laboratory and under simulated field temperatures</article-title><source>Appl Entomol Zool</source><year>2017</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13355-017-0517-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishide</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The hatching time of <italic>Locusta migratoria</italic> under outdoor conditions: role of temperature and adaptive significance</article-title><source>Physiol Entomol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/phen.12184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two new methods for the study of insect population</article-title><source>Bull Inst Zool Acad Sin.</source><year>1985</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>240</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Life table analysis incorporating both sexes and variable development rates among individuals</article-title><source>Environ Entomol</source><year>1988</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ee/17.1.26</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chi H. TWOSEX-MSChart: a computer program for the age-stage, two-sex life table analysis. Taichung: National Chung Hsing University; 2019. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://140.120.197.173/Ecology/">http://140.120.197.173/Ecology/</ext-link>. Accessed 20 Feb 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Timing of control based on the stage structure of pest populations&#x02014;a simulation approach</article-title><source>J Econ Entomol</source><year>1990</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>1143</fpage><lpage>1150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jee/83.4.1143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Efron</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>An introduction to the bootstrap</source><year>1985</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chapman &#x00026; Hall</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akca</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayvaz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaz&#x00131;c&#x00131;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Demography and population projection of <italic>Aphis fabae</italic> (Hemiptera: Aphididae): with additional comments on life table research criteria</article-title><source>J Econ Entomol</source><year>2015</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>1466</fpage><lpage>1478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jee/tov187</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26470285?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26470285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Core Team. R: a language and environment for statistical computing. R Found Stat Comput. 2016. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.R-project.org/">https://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Seabold S, Perktold J. Statsmodels: econometric and statistical modeling with python. In: Proceedings of the 9th python in science conference 2010 Jun 28, vol. 57. Scipy; p. 61.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Matplotlib: a 2D graphics environment</article-title><source>Comput Sci Eng.</source><year>2007</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/MCSE.2007.55</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>