<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">Invasive 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> genotypes from the three regions grew a larger total leaf area, a heavier shoot mass, a larger total mass and had a higher shoot-structural root ratio than native genotypes in the control treatment at the final harvest at 12 weeks (Control T2, Table 1 and Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). This was already evident at 8 weeks except for total plant mass (Control T1, Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). This is in line with the study by Joshi and Vrieling
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>, who, in a common garden experiment, found that after eight months of growth, invasive 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> had a higher vegetative growth and a 37% higher reproductive output than native plants. Indeed in several plant species, invasive genotypes have a superior growth ability compared to their native congeners as predicted by the EICA hypothesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. However, defoliation of the shoot had reversed the outcome. Therefore we hypothesize that invasive plants trade their regrowth ability for better growth ability. In our study, we found that native 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> performed better than invasive genotypes after 4 weeks of regrowth following complete removal of the shoot. Similar results were found by Joshi and Vrieling
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup> who observed higher regrowth of native 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> genotypes after complete defoliation when compared with invasive genotypes. Furthermore, Lin, 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup> found that native 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> genotypes regrew better than invasive genotypes after herbivory by the generalist 
 <italic>Mamestra brassicae</italic> and by the specialist 
 <italic>T</italic>. 
 <italic>jacobaeae</italic> under an intra-specific competition setup. This result indicates that native 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> are better adapted to complete defoliation than invasive ones. Apparently this comes at the cost of a reduced growth rate because in the invasive areas where 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> does not have to cope with severe defoliation by specialist herbivores they have lost part of their regrowth ability but attain higher growth. In contrast, other studies found that invasive Chinese tallow tree (
 <italic>Sapium sebiferum</italic>) genotypes have higher regrowth ability than native genotypes after both simulated and natural herbivory
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>. It was argued that fast regrowth may be an important defense against local generalist herbivory after invasion. Higher regrowth ability might also contribute to the invasion success, especially after disturbances such as mowing, fire and grazing
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. In the invasive range, 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> mostly occurs in extensively grazed pastures, where it is avoided by cattle that are repelled by the toxic pyrrolizidine alkaloids. In the invasive range, 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> genotypes produce more toxic pyrrolizidine alkaloids, which could effectively defend them against grazers and other local generalist herbivores
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. Ragwort does occur in temperate climates in the invasive ranges which are less likely to be disturbed by fire. It suggests that the role of disturbances on regrowth capacity by grazing and fire in the invasive range are limited. Storage in roots is also needed to survive cold winters
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. Here we found that, on average, the mean temperature of the coldest quarter in the sampled invasive populations was equal to that in the native range and that storage was not correlated with the mean temperature of the coldest quarter. It suggests that the decrease in carbohydrate storage in 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> is not related to the colder winters in the invasive ranges.
</p>
