<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">The regrowth ability we estimated, reflects the fraction biomass in root and how well plants can compensate for its aboveground loss. In general, native 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> genotypes have relatively more biomass in the roots, so a smaller fraction of aboveground biomass is removed at the moment of defoliation which gives these plants an advantage at the beginning of regrowth. Native genotypes also stored more inulin in their roots than invasive genotypes. Our data showed that the increase in biomass after regrowth is positively correlated with the root inulin content at the moment of defoliation, and negatively correlated with the size of the structural root at the moment of defoliation (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Several studies, mainly on grasses, have reported that the root carbohydrate storage is positively associated with plant regrowth after defoliation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, Danckwerts and Gordon
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup> used isotopes to confirm that stored root carbohydrates in the grass 
 <italic>Lolium perenne</italic> have been remobilized to the newly regenerated leaves in response to defoliation. Our results also show that the regrowth performance of 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> depends on root inulin storage. It suggest that invasive 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> in the absence of its main specialist herbivore 
 <italic>T</italic>. 
 <italic>jacobaeae</italic> have been selected to produce smaller roots and store less inulin resulting in poorer regrowth ability. Our study is the first that shows a positive correlation between root carbohydrate storage and regrowth ability for invasive plants, in comparison to native plants which had greater root carbohydrate storage and greater regrowth ability.
</p>
