<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">A model proposed by de Jong and van der Meijden
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup> suggested that under repeated disturbance such as the outbreak of a specialist herbivore, plant genotypes that allocate more resources to storage are better adapted to herbivory and recover quickly through regrowth since a smaller fraction of their total biomass is removed by herbivory. Due to herbivory, plants have been selected to evolve different allocation strategies and store more resources in the roots. We found that the root carbohydrate storage in native 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> counts for 50% of the root biomass while other herb species often contain less (ca. 10%~20%) carbohydrate storage
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup>. The presence of the specialist 
 <italic>T</italic>. 
 <italic>jacobaeae</italic> larvae in the native range may explain why native 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> developed increased carbohydrate storage. The larvae of this univoltine specialist herbivore have broken through all plant defenses and 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> uses regrowth as a strategy to overcome defoliation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. It suggests that the lack of selection pressure by the specialist herbivore 
 <italic>T</italic>. 
 <italic>jacobaeae</italic> in the invasive range plays an important role in the evolution of a decreased regrowth ability of invasive 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic>. The foliar-feeding larvae of this specialist herbivore regularly defoliate all the aboveground parts of 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> in the native range during June
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup>. We show that the higher shoot-structural root ratio in the non-defoliated invasive 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgaris</italic> genotypes in our experiment represents a redistribution of resources from root storage to aboveground parts, thus contributing to a better growth performance.
</p>
