<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study provides more direct support for these expectations. First, plastic responses resulted in a higher probability that 
 <italic>average fitness</italic> remained positive across a broader set of climatic and habitat conditions (i.e., a 
 <italic>JT</italic> strategy 
 <xref rid="pone.0032323-Richards1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>), thereby broadening the species climate envelope into wetter climates in the north and drier climates in the south (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032323-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). Second, average fitness without plasticity was higher at the range centre than at the margins, but plasticity resulted in a further log-normal amplification of average fitness between the range centre and margins (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032323-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>) (i.e., a 
 <italic>MS</italic> strategy 
 <xref rid="pone.0032323-Richards1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>). The measure of average fitness also measures the instantaneous and asymptotic growth rates of population abundance (see methods section), so plasticity also amplified the existing abundance centre of 
 <italic>P. aculeata</italic> distribution 
 <xref rid="pone.0032323-Sagarin1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0032323-Sagarin2" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Our results therefore support previous expectations that plasticity can provide both greater robustness for species to respond geographically to climate change 
 <xref rid="pone.0032323-Matesanz1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> than through genetic differentiation 
 <xref rid="pone.0032323-Davis1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> (i.e, 
 <italic>JT</italic> startegy) and greater responsiveness in their ability to expand their range more quickly when conditions are already good 
 <xref rid="pone.0032323-Sexton1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0032323-Santamaria1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0032323-Sagarin2" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref> (i.e, 
 <italic>MS</italic> stategy). In our case, the invasive plant 
 <italic>P. aculeata</italic> is able to use these two strategies and therefore behaves like a 
 <italic>JM</italic> species.
</p>
