<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We analyzed volatile compounds according to 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pérez et al. (2016)</xref> using headspace solid-phase microextraction (SPME) and gas chromatography (GC). Oil samples (0.5 g) were taken in 10 mL vials and placed in a vial heater at 40°C. After 10 min of equilibrium time, volatile compounds from headspace were adsorbed on a SPME fiber DVB/Carboxen/PDMS 50/30 μm (Supelco Co., Bellefonte, PA, United States). Sampling time was 50 min at 40°C. Desorption of volatile compounds trapped in the SPME fiber was done directly into the GC injector. Compounds were identified on a 7820A/GC-5975/MSD system (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, United States), housing a DB-Wax capillary column (internal diameter: 60 × 0.25 mm; film thickness: 0.25 μm; J&amp;W Scientific, Folsom, CA, United States) under the following conditions: injection port operated in splitless mode at 250°C; He carrier gas flow rate of 1 mL min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>; column held for 6 min at 40°C, then programmed at 2°C min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> to 168°C; the mass detector was operated in electronic impact mode at 70 eV; source temperature set at 230°C; and, the mass spectra scanned at 2.86 scans s
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> in the m/z 40–550 amu range. Compounds were identified by mass spectrum comparison with Wiley/NBS and NIST libraries, retention index in agreement with the literature, and co-elution with chemical standards when available. For quantification, the volatile fraction was analyzed three times on a HP-6890 GC system (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, United States) equipped with the same column as previously, and operated under the following operating conditions: N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> as the carrier gas at 17 psi; injector and detector at 250°C; oven held for 6 min at 40°C and then programmed at 2°C min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> increase to 168°C. Calibration curves were obtained using re-deodorized, high-oleic sunflower oil containing pure standards. The concentration ranges and the limits of quantification were established according to the typical volatile contents in VOO. Linear regression curves were found for all compounds, with regression coefficients greater than 0.99, and calculated Rf used for quantitation [concentration (ng/g) = Rf × area compound]. During the sample analysis, a blank that did not contain oil and a mixture of volatile standards were repeatedly run.
</p>
