<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Being a cryptic invader, 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> has emerged as an important model system for understanding mechanisms of invasion. There have been few population-level studies to directly evaluate differences in genetic diversity, reproductive mode, and dispersal between native and non-native 
 <italic>P. australis</italic>, particularly in western North America [
 <xref rid="B62-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. In view of the lack of any population genetics studies on 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> in India, we have attempted here to assess its genetic diversity through allelic and population variation of microsatellite loci. It is noteworthy that the mean number of alleles per locus in the present study (
 <italic>A</italic> = 8.56) was comparable to the findings of Saltonstall [
 <xref rid="B73-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] on European 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> populations (
 <italic>A</italic> = 8.0), although it was greater than the average (
 <italic>A</italic> = 7.6) as reported by Paul et al. [
 <xref rid="B75-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] on 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> in the United Kingdom. In the present study, we most frequently came across tetraploidy and hexaploidy among regional groupings of invasive populations of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> that were collected across Quebec and Kashmir, although the native population in Quebec seems to be diploid. Hence, it appears that polyploidy might have played some role in invasiveness of this species. Clevering and Lissner [
 <xref rid="B76-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>] found that tetraploidy was the most common ploidy of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> in Europe and North America, while octaploids (8x) were predominated in Asia. Such results suggest that invasive plants are more likely to be polyploids, while native plants are more likely to be diploids as was reported in some other studies [
 <xref rid="B77-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Pandit et al. [
 <xref rid="B79-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>] showed that invasive plant species are generally found to have high chromosome counts and to be polyploids, in contrast to rare species that are diploids and have lower ploidy ratios. In a related study, it was shown that the highly invasive plant species in Singapore were all polyploids [
 <xref rid="B80-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>], thereby indicating that polyploidy contributes to invasion success. Interestingly, invasive Kashmir and invasive Quebec populations of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> were more similar to one another, both in terms of the number of alleles and fragment size, than to the native Quebec population that showed unique numbers of alleles and fragment sizes. With an increased native population size, more differences might be seen. However, Saltonstall (2003a) [
 <xref rid="B30-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] reported the same allelic variation among native 
 <italic>P. australis</italic>, while highest allelic diversity was observed among introduced 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> that were collected in North America.
</p>
