<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0037">In this study, both genders are interested in herbal medicines. However, the numbers of male participants were higher than those of females. Men were predominantly represented in the sample because of their work. Females were rarely found at herbal markets during our interviews. These outcomes validate the findings of other ethnobotanical national and international studies [
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] which have confirmed that men are predominantly knowledgeable in traditional herbs. Regarding the age groups, results showed that herbalists over 50 years old had more experience with traded medicinal species, while herbalists younder than 30 years old were less informed about it. It is due to the high secrecy of ancestral information by older people; these factors are very interesting in determining the transmission of traditional knowledge from one generation to another in a Prefecture. Concerning the academic level, our results revealed that more than half of the informants (53.33%) had secondary education. None of the herbalists participating in our survey had a certificate or diploma in herbalism. While the Dahir of February 19, 1960, with Article 17 stipulates that to hold and sell the plants or parts of medicinal plants, whether fresh or dry, except plants classified in the various tables of poisonous substances, the person concerned must provide a herbalist certificate and authorized under the conditions provided in Article 2 of the same Dahir. This indicates that with a greater level of instruction, the experience of traditional herbal medicine decreases. Therefore, advanced instruction reduces the ancestral therapeutic knowledge of the young generation 
 <xref rid="bib0062" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>. Previous ethnobotanical studies 
 <xref rid="bib0063" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0064" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0066" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0067" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref> report similar findings. All stated that they had acquired their traditional knowledge and experience in medicinal plants from their parents, friends, and elderly relatives. 41.18% of the herbalists had experience as herbalists over 20 years.
</p>
