<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0130">The intestinal microflora plays an important role in protecting the integrity of the intestinal mucosa (
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Jazi et al., 2020</xref>). Impairing this integrity leads to a progressive increase of mucosal permeability, which facilitates pathogens infection. One of the most important biological properties of phytogenic products is their antibacterial activity against less favorable and pathogenic bacteria residing in the gut (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Brenes and Roura, 2010</xref>). In vivo researches in poultry indicated that phytogenic products such as cinnamon essential oil and herbal extracts rich in phenolic compounds could act against colonization of intestinal pathogens such as 
 <italic>E</italic>. 
 <italic>coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Clostridium perfringens</italic> because of the antibacterial action of their phenolic ingredients (
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Chowdhury et al., 2018b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Giannenas et al., 2018</xref>). Furthermore, there is evidence that phytogenics in some cases enhances the proliferation of beneficial bacteria in the gut. For example, 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Murugesan et al. (2015)</xref> reported that adding a commercial phytogenic feed additive (combination of 30 essential oils) to broiler diets increased LAB counts in cecal digesta. Other reports also showed that essential oils (thymol, eugenol, carvacrol, and cinnamaldehyde) fortify the gut microflora by reducing harmful bacteria numbers and increasing beneficial bacteria populations (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Jamroz et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">McReynolds et al., 2009</xref>). The antibacterial activities of EEO against pathogens such as 
 <italic>E</italic>. 
 <italic>coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Salmonella typhi</italic>, 
 <italic>Moraxella catarrhalis</italic>, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> has significantly been demonstrated in vitro (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Ghalem and Mohamed, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Mekonnen et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Dhakad et al., 2018</xref>). These effects could be attributed because of the presence of ingredients such as 1.8-cineole, limonene, and α-pinene (
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Dhakad et al., 2018</xref>). Our study indicated that EEO dietary supplementation tended to reduce 
 <italic>E</italic>. 
 <italic>coli</italic> in the ceca digesta contents. Also, we found that EEO's dietary supplement led to a trend of the increased LAB population in cecal. The mode of actions of phytogenic products to exert their antibacterial activity varies among such sources of products. Nonetheless, the general proposed mechanism of action is through affecting bacterial cell permeability (
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Windisch et al., 2008</xref>), dissipating the pH gradient in the bacterial cell (
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 2020</xref>), providing the substrate for growth and proliferation of lactic acid-producing bacteria in intestinal such as 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> which utilizes phenolic compounds of essential oils as carbon sources (
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Pacheco-Ordaz et al., 2018</xref>). In addition, phytogenic products were reported to stimulate intestinal production of mucus in broiler chickens, an effect that was assumed to impair adhesion of pathogenic bacteria such as coliforms and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> and thus to contribute to stabilizing the microbial eubiosis in the gut of the animals (
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Windisch et al., 2008</xref>). Accordingly, the improvement in the microbial population observed in the ceca of birds fed EEO diets could be contributed to the increased digestibility of OM and EE and improved growth performance.
</p>
