<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0135">A well-functioning and healthy gut is the cornerstone of the optimum performance of animals. When the gut function and health are impaired, digestion and absorption of nutrients are affected, and thus, the health and performance might be compromised. Determination of nutrients digestibility is a quantitative assessment of the nutritional and physiological phenomena associated with digestion capacity and gut functionality (
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Soumeh et al., 2019</xref>). In response to increasing EEO supplementation, the AID of OM and EE were linearly and quadratically increased at the end of the study. Potential modes of action of phytogenic products are an increase in digestive secretions such as mucin, saliva, bile acid, and enzyme activity enhancement. In line with our results, dietary supplementation with phytogenic extracts containing carvacrol, cinnamaldehyde, and capsaicin improved nutrient digestibility in broiler chickens (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Jamroz et al., 2003</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hashemipour et al. (2013)</xref> reported that dietary supplementation phytogenic products containing an equal mixture of carvacrol and thymol at 4 dosages (0, 60, 100, and 200 mg/kg) in broiler diets linearly increased activities of trypsin, lipase, and protease in the pancreas and intestinal. 
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al. (2003)</xref> also demonstrated that ileal digestibility coefficients for starch and protein in broiler chickens fed diets containing essential oils (thymol and carvacrol) were higher owing to greater the activity of amylase, compared with the control group. Furthermore, the inclusion of phytogenic products in broiler diets has shown positive effects on intestinal morphology, gut microbial balance, antioxidant status, and also an intestinal barrier and nonspecific immunity (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hashemipour et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Chowdhury et al., 2018b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Giannenas et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Mohebodini et al., 2019</xref>), which could lead to better nutrient digestion and absorption.
</p>
