<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lipids derived from cereals are another potential α‐glucosidase and α‐amylase inhibitors (Table 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-tbl-0004" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The Soxhlet hexane and ethyl acetate extracts of wheat bran were effective inhibitors of α‐glucosidase in vitro (Liu, 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). The isolated phosphatidic acids in wheat germ, 1,2‐dilinoleylglycerol‐3‐phosphate and 1‐palmitoyl‐2‐linoleoyl glycerol‐3‐phosphate (Figure 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), showed the highest α‐glucosidase inhibitory activity among the test lipids with the IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 38.9 and 47.9 μM (Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). The structure–activity relationship studies suggested that the unsaturated fatty acids and phosphate group in the glycerides were significant structural requirements for the inhibitory activity. Alkylresorcinols are another important components that are responsible for the α‐glucosidase inhibitory activity of wheat bran lipids (Tu et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0067" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Alkylresorcinols showed IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 37.58 μg/ml by noncompetitive type of inhibition. It has been reported that the important biological role of alkylresorcinols is to directly regulate enzyme activity, such as inhibition of acetylcholinesterase, and the inhibitory activity is affected by the length of the alkyl side chain (Athukorala et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Stasiuk et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). However, its effects on inhibition of α‐glucosidase still require further investigation. Additionally, there is some evidence that fatty acids, saponins, and terpenes found in fruits, vegetables, and mushrooms contribute to the in vitro α‐glucosidase and α‐amylase inhibition activities of hexane extracts (Papoutsis et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31987-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). However, limited work has been conducted on elucidation of the α‐glucosidase and α‐amylase inhibition activities of different lipophilic compounds found in cereals. Future studies are encouraged to investigate the individual inhibitors of cereal lipids and their inhibition mechanism.
</p>
