<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Both male and female mosquitoes rely on plant sugar for flight and survival [
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], with possible additional reproductive and pathogen susceptibility benefits for female mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Recent studies have confirmed that certain secondary metabolites (toxins) from plants are ingested by mosquito vectors along with common plant sugars [
 <xref rid="B80-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. However, the fate and impact of the ingested plant secondary metabolites remains unclear, particularly for arboviral mosquito vectors. For malaria it is known that 
 <italic>An. gambiae</italic> preferentially feeds on 
 <italic>P. hysterophorus</italic>, though because of the plant’s relatively inferior sugar profile it appears that in terms of nutrition the plant does not have any adaptive significance to the vector [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Hence the vector’s feeding preference for 
 <italic>P. hysterophorus</italic> could be a mere reflection of its wide availability caused by the rapid replacement of native vegetation by this highly aggressive IAP, its attractive odour [
 <xref rid="B70-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>], or due to other underlying physiological benefits that the plant offers the vector. It was therefore hypothesized that besides sugars, other constituents present in 
 <italic>P. hysterophorus</italic> could benefit 
 <italic>An. gambiae</italic> [
 <xref rid="B64-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Parthenin, a sesquiterpene lactone present in 
 <italic>P. hysterophorus,</italic> was isolated from recently plant-fed 
 <italic>An. gambiae</italic> [
 <xref rid="B80-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] and was later shown to block the transmission of the asexual stages of 
 <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> in infected mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], leading to speculations that the female mosquitoes preferentially seek sugar from 
 <italic>P. hysterophorus</italic> to rid themselves of a plasmodium infection [
 <xref rid="B80-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Though some of the anti-microbial properties of parthenin are well documented [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-viruses-13-00032" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>], its antiviral potential remains unknown and merits further investigation. 
</p>
