<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Given that 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> plants sampled in this study were of different ploidy levels, descriptive statistics were performed using Polysat version 1.3 [
 <xref rid="B101-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. These statistics included the percentage of polymorphic loci (
 <italic>P</italic>), the mean number of alleles (
 <italic>A</italic>), the mean number of alleles per polymorphic locus (
 <italic>A</italic>
 <sub>p</sub>), allelic richness (
 <italic>A</italic>
 <sub>R</sub>), and observed and expected heterozygosities (
 <italic>H</italic>
 <sub>O</sub> and 
 <italic>H</italic>
 <sub>E</sub>) for each population [
 <xref rid="B102-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>], together with unbiased estimates of population differentiation for microsatellites (
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>ST</sub>; [
 <xref rid="B103-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]). Prior to analysis of molecular data, gametic disequilibrium verification between loci was performed using Fisher’s exact tests. Bruvo distances [
 <xref rid="B104-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>] were estimated between genotypes using Polysat version 1.3 and principal coordinates analysis was used to display population structure, using R package [
 <xref rid="B105-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. To measure the informative character of the SSR markers that were used in the present study, the polymorphism information contents (PIC) for each marker was calculated using as follows [
 <xref rid="B106-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]:
 <disp-formula>PIC = 1 − Ʃ
  <sub>i=1</sub>
  <sup>k</sup> P
  <sub>i</sub>
  <sup>2</sup>
  <label>(4)</label>
 </disp-formula> where k is the total number of alleles detected per locus and P
 <sub>i</sub> the frequency of the allele i in all populations. Genetic similarity (GS) [
 <xref rid="B107-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>] was calculated as follows:
 <disp-formula>GS = 2N
  <sub>ij</sub>/(N
  <sub>i</sub> + N
  <sub>j</sub>)
  <label>(5)</label>
 </disp-formula> where N
 <sub>ij</sub> is the number of fragments common to individuals i and j, and (Ni + Nj) is the total number of fragments in both individuals.
</p>
