<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The liver is an important organ and plays vital functions in the human body by regulating many biochemical pathways (Sharma et al., 
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>). Hepatotoxicity caused by certain drugs/antibiotics, chemicals, microbial infections, and consumption of alcohol is a major concern. Protection of liver using medicinal plants is the best alternative and many plants were reported for anti-hepatotoxicity effect. The seed oil of 
 <italic>M. peregrina</italic> was used for its proteceive effect against doxorubicin induced hepatotoxicity in mice. The reduction in caspase-3 immunoreactivity and apoptotic index were noted in 
 <italic>M. peregrina</italic> seed oil treated mice. Seed oil with the dose of 150 mg/kg treatment reduced the liver damage induced by doxorubicin (Sliai and Abdel-Rahman, 
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). The seed oil of 
 <italic>M. peregrina</italic> was studied along with other two 
 <italic>Moringa</italic> species for liver tissue oxidative stress state in high fat diet induced liver damage. Hepatic marker enzymes, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, total serum cholesterol, triacylglycerol, glucose, lipid peroxidation, antioxidant enzymes such as catalase, superoxide dismutase, and glutathione peroxidase were analyzed after the treatment. The results indicated that glucose, total serum cholesterol, alanine transaminase, aspartate transaminase, and body weights significantly increased in the rats fed with high fat diet. The post administration of seed oil was significantly improved the liver enzymes, lipid profile, and glucose content (Elabd et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The hepatoprotective effect of ethanol leaf extract of 
 <italic>M. peregrina</italic> through oral administration showed that the extract significantly decreased the activities of serum hepatic marker enzymes. The effect of 
 <italic>M. peregrina</italic> leaf extract on oxidative stress markers of acetaminophen induced hepataotoxicity showed that the administration of extract was successful in replenishing the reduced glutathione level in the liver, blood, and brain. In the meantime, the superoxide dismutase, catalase, and glutathione peroxidase activities were reduced significantly in the rats intoxicated with acetaminophen. The superoxide dismutase, catalase and glutathione peroxidase activities enhanced in successful way when the 
 <italic>M. peregrina</italic> leaf extract was administrated (Azim et al., 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In literature, triterpenoids have been reported as one of the most important anti-hepatotoxic agents. In the past few decades, more than 350 triterpenoids have been reported for hepatoprotective potential (Xu et al., 
 <xref rid="B147" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). So, structure-based investigations are advised to isolate a potent hepatoprotective agent from 
 <italic>M. peregrina</italic>.
</p>
