<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For the DPPH test, the essential oils and some of their constituents, germacrene D (isolated from 
 <italic class="italic">S. macrotepala</italic>, through silica gel column chromatography using 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hexane as mobile phase), β-pinene, 1,8-cineole, 
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>-β-caryophyllene were diluted 2, 5, 10, 50, 100, 200-fold in dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO) and an aliquot of 100 μL of each solution (or DMSO, for the blank) was added to 2.9 mL of DPPH (1 × 10
 <sup class="sup">−4</sup> in ethanol). All solutions were stirred vigorously for 30 min in the dark at room temperature. The absorbances were measured at 517 nm in a Helios spectrophotometer, (Thermo Spectronic, Cambridge, UK). ABTS radical was prepared mixing 10 mL of 2 mM ABTS aqueous solution with 100 μL of 70 mM K
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>S
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">8</sub> aqueous solution: the reaction is complete after 12–16 h, in the dark and at room temperature. 1 mL of the last solution was diluted with ethanol since to achieve an absorbance of 0.70 ± 0.02 at 734 nm. Similarly to DPPH test, we proceeded mixing 10 μL of each diluted essential oils (or DMSO for the blank) with 0.990 mL of ABTS solution. Absorbances were measured at 734 nm. The antiradical activity for each mixture was calculated according to the following formula:
 <disp-formula class="disp-formula">Ip DPPH or ABTS% = (A
  <italic class="italic">b</italic> − A
  <italic class="italic">a</italic>)/A
  <italic class="italic">b</italic> × 100
  <label class="label">(1)</label>
 </disp-formula>where A
 <italic class="italic">b</italic> and A
 <italic class="italic">a</italic> are the absorbances of the blank and the samples respectively after 30 min for DPPH and 1-min for ABTS assay. The antiradical activity of the essential oil is evaluated by calculation of the IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value, which is equivalent to the concentration providing 50% of the DPPH or ABTS inhibition, calculating from curves obtained plotting inhibition percentage against essential oil concentration [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-24-01637" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>].
</p>
