<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The endophytic fungi contain a broad classification of bioactive secondary metabolites (BSMs) with distinctive nature including alkaloids, flavonoids, phenols/polyphenols, benzopyranones, quinones, chinones, terpenoids, steroids, tetralones, and xanthones [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Most of the BSMs are effectively used in the medicinal field as cancer therapeutic agents which prevented/treated successfully. Wu et al. [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] explored that the anti-cancer activity exhibited by the potential endophytic fungal strains in breast cancer cell lines. The strains of 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> produced the anti-tumor compounds and explored its therapeutic properties in inhibiting the growth of MCF-7 cells [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Majoumouo et al. [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] has reported that the potential anti-cervical cancer properties in metabolites extracted from the endophytic fungal strains such as 
 <italic>Fusarium</italic>, 
 <italic>Phoma</italic>, and 
 <italic>Colletotrichum</italic> species. He et al. [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] reported that the anti-cancer activities of BSMs from the endophytic fungi and the BSMs explicated the anti-cervical cancer activity efficiently in animal models. On comparing to other therapeutic metabolites epicatechins and its derivatives were found to exhibit the highest cancer therapeutic properties especially in treating and preventing the cervical cancer [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. These epicatechins and its derivatives have been reported to exhibit the anti-tumor activities by the inactivation of tumor metabolic pathways in various kinds of cancer. The epicatechins derivatives inhibits the activation of STAT3 pathway which has a significant role in the formation of tumor, and this was reported in nasopharyngeal carcinoma [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Few researches supports the anti-cancer activities explicated by the epicatechin derivatives in the prevention and decrease of tumor formation, progression, and metastasis stages [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. These epicatechins are also helpful in the prevention and curing of neurodegenerative diseases [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Elbaz et al. [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] reported the anti-pancreatic cancer activity exhibited by the epicatechins where the metabolites stimulated the mitochondrial activity upon radiation exposure. Moreover, the epicatechins are a good anti-proliferative agents in breast cancer cells when there are bio catalytically oligomerized [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].These epicatechins family are highly present in tea plant but this epicatechin derivatives was remarkably present in an endophytic fungus 
 <italic>Curvularia australiensis</italic>. The presence of epicatechins in 
 <italic>C. australiensis</italic> was from the metabolic process mimicked from the host tree 
 <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The 
 <italic>Curvularia</italic> species are found to contain more medically important metabolites and few research reports were found to explicate the results on potential metabolites. The 
 <italic>Curvularia</italic> sp. was isolated from 
 <italic>Murraya koengii</italic> was found to exhibit the inhibition of 
 <italic>Phytophthora capsica</italic> zoospores [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Khiralla [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-00654" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] reported that the cytotoxicity effects of metabolites produced by an endophytic fungus 
 <italic>C. papendroffi</italic> and its effect on cancer cells. There are only few researches on the metabolites produced by the 
 <italic>C. australiensis</italic> in medicinal fields. The goal of this current investigation was to evaluate the effects of dimer of epicatechin (DoE) on anti-angiogenesis, anti-inflammation, and anti-cervical cancer properties through in vitro and in vivo animal studies.
</p>
