<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, the positive effect of endophytic nitrogen-fixing bacteria on 
 <italic>A. adenophora</italic> growth was proposed. However, native plants also commonly harbor endogenous nitrogen-fixing bacteria with positive effects (
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Olivares et al., 1996</xref>). Thus, whether the endogenous nitrogen-fixing bacteria enriched by invasive plants and native species are different, both in the species composition and in the growth-promoting of their hosts, must be further compared. A previous study on the competition of 
 <italic>A. adenophora</italic> with native species in new habitats mainly involved its leaf litter allelopathy (
 <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Inderjit et al., 2011</xref>). Therefore, it would be interesting to determine whether the secondary metabolites of 
 <italic>A. adenophora</italic> or soil type in the invaded sites influence the population dynamics of rhizosphere and endophytic nitrogen-fixing bacteria, which in turn enhance the growth advantage of 
 <italic>A. adenophora</italic>. In addition, for each sampling region, only three plant individuals were collected, and nearly 30 bacteria were isolated in this study. Because the species rarefaction curve did not reach a plateau (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-2">Fig. S1</xref>), it is expected that new OTUs will be discovered if more isolates are taken. Therefore, more strains should be isolated; particularly, new techniques such as high-throughput sequencing should be performed to indicate the reNFB diversity of 
 <italic>A. adenophora</italic> in Yunnan Province. Physiological and morphological characteristics should also be taken into taxonomic classification of strains because solely using 16S rRNA gene sequences is not reliable below genus level. More importantly, it is worth determining the nitrogenase activity capacity as well as the nifH gene diversity for these reNFB to establish the direct relationship between nitrogen-fixing bacteria and 
 <italic>A. adenophora</italic> invasion.
</p>
