<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mainly, 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> species are distributed in the Mediterranean region. Out of the 43 species, 35 species occur solely in the east Mediterranean. Four species can only be found in the western Mediterranean, while three species grow in Libya exclusively [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Three taxa grow in Morocco and the south of Spain restrictedly, two taxa are found in Algeria and Tunisia, three taxa are endemic to Cyrenaica, and nine taxa are found in Greece, South Balkans, and Asia Minor. Six out of these nine taxa are local Greek endemics. Twenty-one local Turkish endemics are found in Turkey, Syria, Lebanon, and Cyprus. Eight taxa are distributed locally in Israel, Jordan, and Sinai Peninsula [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. 
 <italic>O. vulgare</italic> is the only species that grows in a very large area extended from the Azores to Taiwan, while most of the other species occupy small areas. A total of 70% of 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> groups are endemic to a single island or mountain [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Natural and artificial hybrids of 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> are found when 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> species co-occur. Usually, hybrids are considered as species initially [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Despite that 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> hybridization is common, hybrids are not usually found in large numbers. Hybridization is hypothesized to be the main method for the origin of 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> species. It may be achieved between two species of 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> or between an 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> species and a related genera species [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The most widely distributed hybrid is O. x intercedens Rechinger, which is found in large populations in the Aegean islands [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Most 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> species grow in mountains and headland areas. They often grow in open or mixed coniferous woods in a partially shaded environment. However, some species, especially those belonging to the Majorana section, are found in lower altitude levels. 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> species mostly grow on calcareous soils and almost all of them can grow on stony slopes, rocky places, and cliffs [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].
</p>
