<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In recent years, several works concerning the release of functional compounds from microparticles have been reported [
 <xref rid="B95-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">97</xref>]. Comparatively, few works can be found on release mechanisms involved at the nanoscale. Literature suggests that in the case of biopolymer particles, the release behavior depends mostly on the permeability and on the disassembly or erosion of the structure, together with other experimental variables which are much less reported, as well as on the dependence on the matrix composition and the way the compound is released—i.e. release may follow a Fickian or an anomalous transport behavior [
 <xref rid="B98-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">98</xref>]. Also, some authors attribute the observed behavior to a Fickian transport through the particle, followed by release due to polymer dissolution. However, there are still a lot of unknown variables affecting the release of compounds from protein-based nanostructures, especially regarding the effect of environmental conditions on the matrix of the protein and its structure. During gastro intestinal digestion, proteins are highly degraded (by low pH, high ionic strength, and hydrolysis by enzymes) and consequently, their bioaccessibility is low. One of the strategies to improve the protein-based structure stability during gastro intestinal digestion is the application of a biopolymer layer to protect the protein particles. Recently, Bourbon et al. (2018) evaluated the effect of gastro intestinal conditions on protein nanohydrogels, with and without a chitosan layer, on active compounds release (curcumin and caffeine). These authors concluded that the chitosan layer improved the stability and bioaccessibility of active compounds during in vitro digestion. Furthermore, the degradation of the lipophilic compound was lower when compared with the system without the chitosan layer [
 <xref rid="B99-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>].
</p>
