<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To predict the binding affinity of plant constituents, molecular modelling studies with bioactive constituents were accomplished. Boeravinone of 
 <italic>B. diffusa</italic>, emodin of 
 <italic>R. emodi</italic>, lupeol of 
 <italic>C. nurvala,</italic> and armepavine of 
 <italic>N. nucifera</italic> were selected for docking studies with XO proteins by the MOPAC6 software package (Stewart Computational Chemistry, Colorado Springs, CO, USA). XO enzyme with 1333 AA protein (Accession: NP_000370.2 GI: 91823271) was downloaded from protein data bank and processed with MOPAC2009 software package. All the docking calculations were achieved on different protein models. In AutoDock tools, solvation parameters, essential hydrogen atoms and Kollman united atom type charges were added. The auto grid programme was employed for the generation of affinity (grid) maps of × Å grid points and 0.375 Å spacing. Vander Waals and electrostatic terms were generated by AutoDock parameter set and distance-dependent dielectric functions, respectively. Simulations of docking were executed using Lamarckian genetic algorithm and Solis and Wets local search method (Solis and Wets 
 <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">1981</xref>). Orientation, initial position and torsions of the ligand molecules have been randomly selected. During docking, all rotatable torsions were released. A translational step of 0.2 Å was used, whereas five quaternion and torsion steps were utilized in each search. In each docking experiment, two different runs were set, and it was terminated after the assessment of a maximum 2,50,000 Kcal energy was reached. The structure of molecules in mol format was generated in the CDX format using the tool ChemDraw Ultra 7.0.1 (CambridgeSoft Corporation, PerkinElmer, Waltham, MA, USA) and transformed to input ligand format (pdb) for docking by OpenBabel version 2.3.2 (O'Boyle et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).
</p>
