<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12" class="p">In addition to the well-known flat-wave forms of 
 <italic class="italic">B. burgdorferi</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">s.l.</italic>) spirochetes, the existence of non-motile atypical morphologies such as looped or ring shaped forms, blebs, round bodies (RB) and cell wall deficient forms, spirochete colonies or biofilm aggregates have been described [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" class="xref">95</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" class="xref">105</xref>]. The generalized definition of “round bodies” also includes coccoid-, globular- or spherical bodies, granules, cysts, sphaeroplasts or vesicles; all of these are viable reproductive propagules whose formation is induced by hostile environmental conditions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" class="xref">106</xref>]. The morphological changes of motile 
 <italic class="italic">B. burgdorferi</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">s.l.</italic>) spirochetes are observed 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> in response to incubation with water or serum starvation, a change of media composition, gas composition, oxidative stress, pH or temperature fluctuation, media acidity-alkalinity fluctuation, concentrations of salts, sugars or other organic compounds, or as a response to antibiotic treatment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" class="xref">100</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104" class="xref">104</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" class="xref">108</xref>]. The formation of RBs in culture is induced by aging, and the appearance of RBs correlates with the disappearance of motile spirochetes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" class="xref">106</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" class="xref">108</xref>]. Mistakenly, transformation of the motile form into a RB was considered as a decrease of pathogen viability. However, even though RBs are less motile than spirochetes in a log phase culture, they are able to twitch or move laterally and revert to the active growing reproductive wave-form spirochetes under the favorable conditions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" class="xref">100</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" class="xref">101</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" class="xref">103</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107" class="xref">107</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109" class="xref">109</xref>]. In addition to spirochetes from the 
 <italic class="italic">B. burgdorferi</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">s.l.</italic>) complex, reversible pleomorphism has been confirmed in other species from the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Spirochaeta</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110" class="xref">110</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113" class="xref">113</xref>] and strengthened by the discovery of 
 <italic class="italic">Spirochaeta coccoides</italic>, a new member of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Spirochaeta</italic> that grows and reproduces in RB forms only [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111" class="xref">111</xref>]. The formation of RBs 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> as a response to exposure to the β-lactam antibiotics commonly recommended for LD treatment was described more than 20 years ago [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" class="xref">105</xref>]. Persistence of 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic> in hosts after antibiotic treatment has been already confirmed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">85</xref>]. Atypical cystic forms were also observed in the cerebral cortex of a patient with chronic Lyme neuroborreliosis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" class="xref">101</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic> aggregates or biofilms have been detected in skin biopsies isolated from patients who developed rare but typical lymphocytomas after a tick bite [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114" class="xref">114</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115" class="xref">115</xref>]. Biofilms, consisting of bacteria embedded in a self-produced polysaccharide matrix, are known to cause chronic infections due to their tolerance to antibiotic treatment and resistance to host serum complement [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" class="xref">94</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" class="xref">96</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" class="xref">106</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114" class="xref">114</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116" class="xref">116</xref>].
</p>
