<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Three soil cores were extracted from a heavily invaded unimproved grassland area (80 × 70 m) at Sraheens, Co Mayo, Ireland, where 
 <italic>G. tinctoria</italic> forms a largely monospecific stand (Longitude: 53.920769, Latitude: −9.947208). The soil in this area is a fine minerotrophic peaty gley (Hickey 
 <xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) consisting of fine particles and with little earthworm activity, meaning that seed movement within this soil would likely be relatively low (Chambers et al. 
 <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>). Based on pollen dating, the arrival of 
 <italic>G. tinctoria</italic> at this site was estimated to be in the 1920s (Hickey 
 <xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). The location of each soil core within the Sraheens site was chosen to maximize the distance between the samples (25 m minimum separation distance). Plastic piping with a diameter of 12.5 cm and a length of 35 cm was used to obtain soil cores, and these were driven into the soil up to their maximum length. The pipes containing the soil cores were then carefully removed from the ground and stored at 4°C within 24 h. Each soil core was then divided into 2-cm-thick slices. Soil from each layer was filtered through a sieve (4 mm diameter) to remove any fragments of rhizome or root that may have been present and then refrigerated at 4°C for up to a month. Potting trays (length: 52 cm, width: 42 cm, depth: 10 cm) were lined with vermiculite, and 2 cm of sand was added to the bottom of each tray to facilitate drainage. Slices from depths 0–2, 4–6, 8–10, 12–14, 16–18, 20–22, 24–26 cm, from each soil core, were mixed with compost (John Innes no. 2) and potted in the trays. The trays were grouped by soil core in a greenhouse and kept at ∼20°C under ambient light conditions for 3 months. Soil was periodically stirred using a glass rod to encourage seed germination; mixing of soil continued until no new germination was observed for a 30-day period. The number of seedlings that germinated from each soil layer is shown in Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1</xref>.
</p>
