<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">Phenolic is a group metabolite associated with several pharmacological activities; therefore, the content of phenolics (TPC) in the plant needs to be determined
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. TPC ranged 1.48 mg GAE/g DW (A6) to 36.08 (A15) mg GAE/g DW (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). TPC found in the leaves of 
 <italic>O. aristatus</italic> is varied based on the different solvent used in the extraction process, different extraction methods, different extraction time and different environments the plant as well as the different of genotypes. Farhan et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>, found the total phenolic content in the leaves as 230 mg GAE/g DW using methanol for extraction, Abdelwahab et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>, reported TPC as 52.10 mg GAE/g DW from 60% methanol extract, and the lowest TPC content found is 20.03 mg GAE/g DW for extraction using 40% ethanol for 120 min at 65 ℃
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>. The solvent for extraction used in this study is 70% ethanol, so the TPC of the extract in this study compares with the reports of Chew et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>. The difference is our experiment without additional heat and Chew et al. using 65 ℃. Based on the dried weight of the leaves, the TPC of the genotype A15 is higher than reported by Chew et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>. Phenolic compounds in 
 <italic>O. aristatus</italic> leaves are from flavonoid groups, tannins, and simple phenolics. Simple phenolic compounds include rosmarinic acid (RAC) that is also determined in this study (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). RAC ranged 0.06 mg/g DW (A6) to 7.25 mg/g DW (A7). There is no correlation between TPC and RAC (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). It means the phenolic extracted by 70% ethanol is not only rosmarinic acid. Genotype A15 and A7 could be used to 
 <italic>O. aristatus</italic> varieties development for high phenolics productivity in plant breeding program.
</p>
