<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Previous studies on the chemical composition of 
 <italic class="italic">T. camphoratus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. carnosus</italic> essential oils reported some chemical variability,as frequently shown for other thyme species. For example, 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Salgueiro et al. (1997)</xref> studied different populations of 
 <italic class="italic">T. camphoratus</italic> collected in Algarve and Baixo Alentejo (south of Portugal) and showed a high chemical variability, particularly among individual samples or small populations, being α-pinene (7.0–11.0%), borneol (1.0–24.0%), and 1,8-cineole (3.9–20.0%) the major compounds identified. In another study, the essential oils from both flowers and leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">T. camphoratus</italic> collected in Algarve, Portugal, showed very high amounts of 1,8-cineole, 56.7 and 62.7% for flowers and leaves, respectively (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Faleiro et al., 2003</xref>). Similarly, for 
 <italic class="italic">T. carnosus</italic> of different regions of Algarve and Baixo Alentejo, Portugal, a chemical variability was observed between the samples. Nevertheless, most of the essential oils were characterized by high amounts of borneol (23.0–32.0%), camphene (6.0–13.0%), terpinen-4-ol (4.0–12.2%), and 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-sabinene hydrate (2.5–10.7%) (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Salgueiro et al., 1995</xref>). In our study, plants growing in large populations of the Algarve region (Portugal) were collected for essential oil extraction, therefore, the chemical profile described is the most prevalent in 
 <italic class="italic">T. carnosus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. camphoratus</italic> growing in the south of Portugal. Furthermore, Stahl-Biskup (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stahl-Biskup, 2003</xref>) described that thymol and carvacrol, both terpene phenols, as well as their biogenetic derivatives are important compounds in the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus</italic>, followed by linalool, borneol, terpinen-4-ol, and 1,8-cineole. Indeed, thymes rich in 1,8-cineole, such as 
 <italic class="italic">T. mastichina</italic> have a very high industrial interest, having an ISO monograph (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">ISO 4728:2003, 2015</xref>), thus highlighting the potential industrial interest for the species herein described.
</p>
