<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To the best of our knowledge, the present study is the first report on the effect of 
 <italic class="italic">T. camphoratus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. carnosus</italic> essential oils on 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> germ tube formation. Assessing this feature is of great relevance since the yeast-to-hypha transition represents the main virulence factor associated with candidosis. Also, filamentation is essential for the development of robust biofilms, another major virulence factor associated with the pathogenesis of 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Romo et al., 2017</xref>). Indeed, fluconazole, the main antifungal used in the clinic, is ineffective on germ tube inhibition. Our findings show that very low doses of the essential oils are able to inhibit filamentation in 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic>, being more effective than the isolated compounds tested. The stronger effect of the essential oils may be explained by the presence of active minor compounds. Indeed, linalool, a minor compound in both oils has been described as an effective natural compound for inhibiting germ tube formation in 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hsu et al., 2013</xref>). Regarding other thyme species, few studies have demonstrated inhibitory effects, but with variable results between species. Interestingly, although phenolic thyme essential oils, such as those from 
 <italic class="italic">T. vulgaris</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. zygis</italic>, show potent antifungal activities they are much less effective in inhibiting 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> germ tube formation than 
 <italic class="italic">T. camphoratus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. carnosus</italic> oils. Indeed 
 <italic class="italic">T. vulgaris</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. zygis</italic> essential oils were only able to achieve significant inhibitions of filamentation (over 50%) at MIC values (0.16–0.32 μL/mL) (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pina-Vaz et al., 2004</xref>), whereas 
 <italic class="italic">T. camphoratus</italic> essential oil attained about 40% of inhibition at much lower concentrations (0.07 mg/mL) and at MIC/4, ca. 90% of inhibition was observed (
 <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>).
</p>
