<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Regarding 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> viability, once again, as far as it is known, the present study is the first to report the effect of 
 <italic class="italic">T. camphoratus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. carnosus</italic> oils on 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> mitochondrial activity. Previously, other thyme essential oils were tested, namely 
 <italic class="italic">T. villosus</italic> subsp. 
 <italic class="italic">lusitanicus</italic>. Nevertheless, contrarily to our results, only detrimental effects were observed at concentrations close to the respective MIC (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pinto et al., 2013</xref>). Moreover, both 
 <italic class="italic">T. camphoratus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. carnosus</italic> essential oils were effective in disrupting 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> biofilms, being 
 <italic class="italic">T. carnosus</italic> oil slightly more active in reducing yeast viability. It is well known that, similarly to bacteria, fungi in biofilms show a higher resistance toward antifungals than planktonic fungi, due to the expression of several resistance genes and phenotypic modifications. Indeed, 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> biofilms have been reported as highly resistant to fluconazole (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Uppuluri et al., 2011</xref>). Therefore, the disruption of this highly organized system is a very attractive target for the development of effective antifungals (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Alves-Silva et al., 2016</xref>). It is important to emphasize that studies evaluating the effect of thyme essential oils on preformed biofilms are lacking. Nevertheless, regarding isolated compounds, several terpenes found in 
 <italic class="italic">T. carnosus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. camphoratus</italic> essential oil have been previously tested. Some compounds such as 1,8-cineole showed an inhibitory effect at high concentrations, 8 mg/mL (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hendry et al., 2009</xref>). Moreover, several other compounds showed an inhibitory effect on the biofilm formation, namely camphor, camphene, and borneol (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Manoharan et al., 2017</xref>) as well as α-pinene (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Silva et al., 2012</xref>). Furthermore, linalool, a minor compound found in both oils, was able to disrupt preformed 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> biofilms (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hsu et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Raut et al., 2013</xref>) and terpinen-4-ol was able to disrupt preformed single and dual-species 
 <italic class="italic">Candida</italic> biofilms in a dose-dependent manner (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Francisconi et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
