<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Rich Chinese flora is reported to possess good antifungal properties and has been widely used in food preservation for centuries [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Huge scientific studies regarding the application of plant extracts in food preservation have reported the potential antifungal agents from this enriched flora [
 <xref rid="B5-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. The major sources of 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> antiseptic preservatives have been isolated from members of majority of the plant genus including 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Origanum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Artemisia</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Heracleum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Foeniculum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Ligusticum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Murraya</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Phellodendron</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Cinnamomum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus, Amomum, Curcuma</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Lippia</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Solanum</italic>, et al. Various advanced techniques have been employed to isolate such antifungal agents, including column chromatography, liquid chromatography, mass spectrometry high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC-MS), gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS), and nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy (
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H-NMR, 
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C-NMR). The studies involving such advanced techniques showed the presence of coumarins, flavonoids, phenolic acids, triterpenoids and natural antibiotics [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. The recent trend of studies has been to isolate and screen the active ingredients in the plant extracts. At the same time, the antifungal activity, its mechanism, antifungal properties and structure-activity relationship of active ingredients have not been involved in recent studies. However, it provides a great number of preliminary foundations for the future studies on plant-derived 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> postharvest preservatives. Initially, a sequential screening of postharvest antiseptic preservatives for plant sources was done to isolate hundreds of plant extracts which were found to be effective against 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">P. italicum</italic>. The current manuscript focused on two major pathogenic fungal strains viz. 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">P. italicum</italic>, and their inhibition by plant extracts during the past 30 years, application in 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> preservation and antisepsis (
 <xref rid="plants-08-00026-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). The manuscript further aims to provide a theoretical basis for the research on the preservative agents for 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> postharvest.
</p>
