<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Joining the nutritional vocabulary of the masses at least three decades ago, the concept of “antioxidants” remains one poorly understood in the field of life sciences, and the clinical relevance of antioxidants is still rather fuzzy, with many knowledge gaps [
 <xref rid="B111-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. However, partly because the assessment of antioxidant potential is easily accessible and relatively cheap, for many herbal products, the antioxidant properties are evaluated repeatedly, and 
 <italic>S. virgaurea</italic> makes no exception, the first study on this topic dating from 1995 [
 <xref rid="B96-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. In this study, ethanolic extracts of the plant were shown in vitro to inhibit lipoxygenase and xanthine oxidase pathways [
 <xref rid="B96-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. A methanol extract obtained from the young shoots and leaves had stronger antioxidant effects (measured in vitro with a DPPH-based assay) than an extract prepared with hot water [
 <xref rid="B95-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Autoclaving of an 80% ethanol extract resulted in decreased scavenging effects on DPPH and ABTS (associated with a decline in polyphenol and flavonoid contents), but it increased the chelating effects on ferrous ions [
 <xref rid="B112-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. Although a slightly higher antioxidant effect was observed when using pressurized fluid extraction over the ultrasonic extraction method on 
 <italic>S. virgaurea</italic> L. leaves (94.0% vs. 89.0% inhibition), the difference was not statistically significant [
 <xref rid="B91-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Both leaf and stem powders, as well as extracts obtained from those parts, prevented lipid oxidation when applied on ground pork samples [
 <xref rid="B113-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. Among 23 herbal species examined for their antioxidant effect in one study, 
 <italic>S. vigaurea</italic> L. had an average antioxidant activity (in decreasing order, it occupied the 11th position out of 23) [
 <xref rid="B44-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].
</p>
