<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A previous study demonstrated the anticancer effect of steroidal glycosides isolated from A.S. in human cervical cancer cells [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. To confirm the anticancer effect in the other types of disorders, we evaluated the effect of A.S. extract on T-ALL cell proliferation and IL-2-mediated immune response. Our study showed that the methanol extract of the leaves and stem of A.S. induced caspase-dependent apoptosis in T-ALL Jurkat cells. This apoptosis inducing effect of A.S. extract might have been mediated by ROS production and the activation of MAPK p38 signaling. ROS are generated through various extracellular or intracellular actions associated with cell growth, differentiation, and cell death [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The homeostasis of intracellular ROS plays an important role in the determination of cell fate and is affected by several signaling pathways and mechanisms such as NF-κB, mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK), and PI3K/Akt signaling [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In particular, oxidative stress directly or indirectly affects MAPK p38 and JNK phosphorylation through MKK3/6 and MKK4/7 activation, respectively [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. A.S. extract stimulated phosphorylation of p38, but JNK was suppressed. In a cross-talk between ROS and MAPK signaling pathway, internal oxidative stress can suppress the phosphorylation of MKP, subsequently activate JNK, and induce the phosphorylation of MEKK1/2/3/4, MKK3/6, and p38 [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In addition, it is known that the upregulation of p38 MAPK is involved in T-ALL Jurkat cell death [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In this regard, though further experiments will be needed, examining the change in cytotoxic effects and signaling pathway after ROS inhibitors treatment, our results suggest that the production of ROS induced by A.S. extract stimulated the phosphorylation of p38 and inhibited the phosphorylation of JNK. Therefore, the activation of p38 phosphorylation by A.S. extract led to the apoptosis of T-ALL Jurkat cells. In addition, A.S. extract exerted an inhibitory effect on NF-κB signaling and IL-2 expression. IL-2 production by activated T cells promotes T cell proliferation and autocrine signaling, and the regulation of IL-2 expression is important in T-cell-mediated immune system tolerance and auto-immunity control [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Additionally, NF-κB signaling is a major mediator in T-cell-mediated immune responses, and it can activate IL-2 production and related inflammatory responses [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Our results showed that A.S. extract may be used for new natural-product-derived drugs development, especially T-ALL.
</p>
