<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Objective(s):</title>
  <p class="p">The purpose of this study was to evaluate variations in yields, volatile composition and biological activities of essential oils (EOs) obtained from the aerial parts of 
   <italic class="italic">Zhumeria majdae </italic>collected from five localities of the south of Iran. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Materials and Methods:</title>
  <p class="p">The EOs were analyzed using gas chromatography and gas chromatography-mass spectrometry techniques. The antioxidant activity of the EOs was tested using DPPH and β-carotene/linoleic acid assays. 
   <italic class="italic">In vitro</italic> cytotoxicity was tested against two cancer cell lines (A375 and MCF7) using MTT assay. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results:</title>
  <p class="p">The oils yield varied from 6.3% (S2) to 10.2% (V/W) (S4). All of five investigated EOs samples presented three major compounds: linalool (24.4-34.6%), camphor (26.1-34.7%) and trans-linalool oxide (7.6-28.6%). Although the main constituents were common, their percentages were different. Among samples, S1 had a better antioxidant activity in both DPPH and β-carotene/linoleic acid methods (IC
   <sub class="sub">50</sub>= 8.01 and 11.77 mg/ml, respectively). 
   <italic class="italic">In vitro</italic> cytotoxicity against two cancer cell lines of human melanoma cell line (A375) and breast cancer cell line (MCF7), showed a moderate cytotoxicity of S3 against A375 cells with IC
   <sub class="sub">50</sub> value of 624 μg/ml. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusion:</title>
  <p class="p">Tangezagh (S4) plant materials revealed the highest level of oil yield as the region is recommended for collecting the plant samples.Taken together, despite the weak antioxidant and moderate cytotoxic activities of tested EOs, this study suggested a proper potential for possible use of the EOs of 
   <italic class="italic">Z. majdae</italic> for pharmaceutical and perfume industries.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
