<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bone formation and bone resorption are known as two counteracting processes at remodelling sites. A failure in the delicate balance between these two processes leads to osteoarthritis and osteoporosis (Logar et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Feng and McDonald 
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Clinical and preclinical studies agree that an increase in osteoclast and decrease in osteoblast activity compromises bone strength (Bloomgarden 
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Several studies have suggested that STZ-induced diabetes is an excellent model for understanding the pathophysiological mechanisms of bone loss in diabetes (Ying et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The selective toxicity of STZ was used to create animal models of diabetic osteoporosis in mice (Coe et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Chen et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) and rats (Guo et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Zheng et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Intriguingly, STZ induces similar bone pathologies changes as seen in human T1DM (Motyl and McCabe 
 <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). It has been demonstrated that STZ is not only particularly toxic to the insulin-producing beta cells of the pancreas but also the skeletal muscles. STZ is transported into the cell by the glucose-transport protein GLUT2 that would lead to DNA damage. Skeletal muscle and beta cells have high levels of GLUT2 expression, thus tend to be more susceptible to STZ-induced bone loss. It is important to note that skeletal muscle is a potential mediator and determinant of bone quality (Kalaitzoglou et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). These observations sit well with other studies showing that STZ reduced bone formation (Peng et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) and increased the number of active osteoclasts (Zheng et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Xie et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) reported that STZ decreases BMD, and induces trabecular bone loss due to oxidative stress and hyperglycaemia.
</p>
