<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Ficus deltoidea</italic> Jack (Moraceae) is an evergreen shrub or a small tree that is easily found in Malaysia and widely distributed in Southeast Asian countries such as Thailand, Sumatra, Java, Kalimantan, Sulawesi, and Moluccas. The decoction of 
 <italic>F. deltoidea</italic> has traditionally been used in postpartum care specifically to improve uterine strength, regain energy, and prevent postpartum bleeding (Sulaiman et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Salleh and Ahmad 
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). It is also served as a health tonic or taken as herbal tea to relieve headache, fever, and toothache (Bunawan et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Acute toxicity studies showed that the LD
 <sub>50</sub> of aqueous and ethanolic leaf extracts of 
 <italic>F. deltoidea</italic> was greater than 5000 mg/kg body weight (Farsi et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) and 2000 mg/kg body weight (Nugroho et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>), respectively. These observations suggest that 
 <italic>F. deltoidea</italic> extract can be considered safe and non-toxic for therapeutic use. Our previous study showed that 
 <italic>F. deltoidea</italic> is not only capable of reducing blood glucose but also improving tissue function, structure, and behavioural performance of diabetic rats (Nurdiana et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). In addition, treatment with 
 <italic>F. deltoidea</italic> increased the percentage of circulating amylin and n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids, in particular, docosahexaenoic acid (DHA) (Nurdiana et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Amylin and DHA are known to have antidiabetic (Adeghate and Kalász 
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Li et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and bone protective effects (Horcajada-Molteni et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>).
</p>
