<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Undoubtedly, the Covid-19 outbreak has become a major health challenge, especially with continuous searching for safe and effective therapeutic agents and vaccines [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>]. Polysaccharides with their broad antiviral activity are considered one of the promising candidates in COVID-19 prevention and control from both sides as a therapeutic agent and carriers. GAGs, Traditional Chinese Medicine, and marine polysaccharides have shown potent anti-coronavirus activity. The entry of the virus to the host cell can be interfered with by sulfated polysaccharides by blocking the positive charge of the pathogen surface receptors. The cationically modified chitosan shows significant inhibition against the human coronavirus HCoV-229E, HCoV-OC43, HCoV-NL63, and HCoV-HKU1, which indicate its inhibitory effect against low-pathogenic human coronaviruses. Traditional Chinese herbal medicine contains potential anti-SARS-CoV-2 active compounds, especially Hedysarummultijugummaxim, coptidis rhizoma, and forsythiae fructus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>]. In vitro experiments show that sulfated polysaccharides bind tightly to the S-protein of SARS-CoV-2, this interfering of protein binding to the heparan sulfate co-receptors has a potent inhibitory effect on viral infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>]. Polysaccharides from different origins have also shown anti-pulmonary fibrosis activities, which render them an alternative agent for preventing or treating pulmonary fibrosis in COVID-19 patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>]. One of the most complications of COVID-19 is the susceptibility of the infected patients to the bacterial secondary infection, polysaccharides can play a major role in this regard such as 
 <italic>Glycyrrhiza</italic> polysaccharide displayed antimicrobial activity, inhibiting the growth of 
 <italic>B. cereus, Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>E. Aerogens, </italic>and
 <italic> Escherichia coli</italic>. The purified Chinese yam polysaccharide showed inhibitory activity against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, with a minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of 2.5 mg/mL. A recent study found that 
 <italic>Poria cocos</italic> polysaccharide could inhibit the growth of 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>. 
 <italic>Asarum</italic> polysaccharides in the Lung Cleansing and Detoxifying Decoction play an important role in relieving cough symptoms, which are prevalent in COVID-19 patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>].
</p>
