<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Glycerol, as a by-product in biodiesel production, is widely applied in microbial production, biomedical applications and plasticizers [
 <xref rid="B89-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="B92-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>]. Palacios et al. synthesized glycerol-based plasticizers and applied them as an alternative of phthalates [
 <xref rid="B93-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>]. They prepared ight kinds of glycerol triesters from butanoic (butyric), propanoic, isobutanoic (isobutyric), isopentanoic (isovaleric), and benzoic acids. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="polymers-10-01303-f019" class="xref">Figure 19</xref> shows their synthesis routes. These low-molecular-weight glycerol triesters are all compatible with PVC and have effective plasticizing effect on PVC. Sahu et al. studied the biodegradation of rosin-glycerol ester derivative [
 <xref rid="B94-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>]. They explored the biodegradation mechanism of rosin glycerol ester and applied it as a biodegradable material. Thomazine et al. found that the addition of glyceryl ester enhances the elongation at break and water vapor permeability (WVP) of gelatin blend [
 <xref rid="B95-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>]. McHugh et al. also reported that sorbitol and glycerol together significantly reduce tensile strength, intensifying elongation of protein edible films [
 <xref rid="B96-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>]. Glyceryl ester is also an ideal addition for starch plasticizers [
 <xref rid="B97-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">97</xref>,
 <xref rid="B98-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>]. Chang et al. prepared glycerol plasticized wheat starch (GPS)/CN nanocomposite through a casting process [
 <xref rid="B99-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>]. As the content of such nanoparticles is increased from 0 to 5 wt %, the tensile strength also increases from 3.15 to 10.98 MPa. The effect of glyceryl ester on performance of thermoplastic starch (TPS) blends is investigated; the results illustrate that the shear viscosity of thermoplastic starch (TPS) blends decreases by 20% when the percentage of glycerol increases from 36% to 40% [
 <xref rid="B100-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>,
 <xref rid="B101-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>].
</p>
