<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110">Ultrasound has a significant influence on plant phytochemicals, especially polyphenols [
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. For example, using US for extraction of gingerols from ginger powder at 50 °C enhanced the extraction of gingerol yield. However, a degradation of the active compound occurred at higher temperatures [
 <xref rid="b0370" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Boulatov [
 <xref rid="b0360" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] reported that the mechanochemical effects of the US results in overstretching of macromolecules polymers (like carbohydrate and protein chains) that lead to their fragmentation. This stretching process helps in releasing small molecules that are bound in the polymer chain. A comparison study of US-assist and conventional extraction methods on herbal tea bioactive compounds showed that total phenols and α-tocopherol were increased by 44% and 20%, respectively. The breakdown of cells cytoarchitecture has been found to release these bioactive compounds [
 <xref rid="b0375" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. According to Ranalli, Malfatti, Lucera, Contento and Sotiriou [
 <xref rid="b0380" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>], the increase in bioactive components in oil extracted by US could be due to the breakage of cross-links between these compounds and other macromolecules like polysaccharides and protein. Also, Rashed, Tong, Abdelhai, Gasmalla, Ndayishimiye, Chen and Ren [
 <xref rid="b0385" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>] reported that higher total phenolic content was extracted from 
 <italic>Lavandula pubescent</italic> herb using US compared to a maceration extraction. For most herbs, the US acoustic cavitation can facilitate the flow of solvent into the plant cells, and enhance desorption of bioactives from the matrix of solid samples. Thus, US enhances the efficiency of phenolic extraction. In another study that investigated 
 <italic>Elsholtzia ciliata</italic> herb, Pudziuvelyte, Jakštas, Ivanauskas, Laukevičienė, Ibe, Kursvietiene and Bernatoniene [
 <xref rid="b0390" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] reported that US significantly increased the extracted apigenin phenolic yield (855.54 μg/g) compared to the maceration method (141.06 μg/g). The authors reported that US-assisted extraction for 11 min increased the mass fraction of total phenols by 20% compared to water bath shaker for 30 min with the same solvent. Also, US treatment increased chlorogenic acid content up to 2174.70 μg/g after 30 min compared to the percolation extraction method that resulted in 683.40 μg/g [
 <xref rid="b0390" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>].
</p>
