<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Recently, researches were addressed to identify the optimal combination of temperature and time during pre-sowing and sprouting treatments, to obtain higher quality sprouts, especially in terms of phytochemical content. These goals are achieved through the use of sophisticated statistical techniques including the response surface methodology approach. For example, in Ecuadorian brown rice cultivars, soaked grains (deionized water, 28 °C, 24 h) were introduced in a germination cabinet at 28 and 34 °C in darkness for 48 and 96 h [
 <xref rid="B112-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>]. The multiple linear regression predicted optimal germination conditions for accumulation of GABA and antioxidant activity after soaking followed by germination at 34 °C for 96h, while the highest total phenolic content was obtained in the combination of 28 °C for 96 h, although differences between genotypes were recorded [
 <xref rid="B112-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>]. In foxtail millet the highest total phenolic content, total flavonoid content and antioxidant activity were obtained with 15.84 h of soaking in tap water at room temperature and 40 h of germination at 25 °C [
 <xref rid="B113-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>]. The optimum germination conditions for sorghum suitable for supplementary food formulations (i.e., low tannin and high protein contents) were established to be steeping for 24 h at 31 °C plus germination for 4.5 days at 30 °C [
 <xref rid="B114-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>]. The highest antioxidant concentrations in wheat sprouts were achieved following 7 days of germination at 16.5 °C [
 <xref rid="B89-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>] while in purple corn sprouts it was possible to maximize the content of GABA, total phenolic compounds and antioxidant activity using a germination temperature of 26 °C for 63 h [
 <xref rid="B115-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>]. The same conditions were guaranteed by kiwicha (Amaranthus caudatus) sprouts richer in GABA and phenolic compounds [
 <xref rid="B116-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>], whilst the highest phenolic content in sprouted quinoa was obtained at 20 °C for 42 h [
 <xref rid="B117-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">117</xref>]. The results reported here refer to specific experiments conducted in controlled environments, under specific laboratory conditions and germination times, so that the stage of cereal grass is not always reached. Accordingly, the optimization of seedling growth parameters needs to be deeply investigated (see also 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2-nutrients-11-00421" class="xref">Section 2</xref>).
</p>
