<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Chemistry of 
  <span class="italic">Citrus aurantium</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chemical composition of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> is responsible for health-promoting effects. The chemical composition includes vitamins, minerals, phenolic compounds, and terpenoids [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>–
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>]. Among the diverse chemical components in 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span>, flavonoids belonging to phenolics have been recognized as important due to their physiological and pharmacological role and their health benefits [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>–
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The flavonoids contained in 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> can be divided into four groups, including flavones, flavanones, flavonols, and anthocyanins (only in blood oranges) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="sch1" href="#sch1">Scheme 1</a>)[
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>–
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Flavonoids are mainly present in 
  <span class="italic">Citrus</span> fruits as glycosyl derivatives. Aglycones are mainly present in specific parts of the fruit as peel and seeds, owing to their lipophilic nature and consequently their low solubility in water [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>–
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>]. For glycoside forms, O-glycosides, C-glycosides, rutinosides, glucosides, and neohesperidosides are common [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>–
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>]. The presence of a relatively large number of glycosylated flavonoids in 
  <span class="italic">Citrus</span> is a result of many different combinations possible between polyhydroxylated aglycones and a limited number of mono- and disaccharides [
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Flavanones are the main flavonoids contained in 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> [
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>]. The most abundant detected free flavanones are hesperetin (4′-methoxy-3′,5,7-trihydroxyflavanone) and naringenin (4′,5,7-trihydroxyflavanone) [
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>]. Hesperetin and naringenin present a common skeleton: two hydroxyl group in positions C-5 and C-7, respectively, and they can be found as aglycone and/or as glycosides [
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>]. The most widely distributed glycosides of hesperetin are hesperidin and neohesperidin, which are conjugates with rutinose and neohesperidose, respectively, while, for naringenin, the most abundant glycosyl derivatives are naringin (naringenin-7-neohesperidoside) and narirutin (naringenin-7-rutinoside) [
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The flavones in aglycon or/and glycosidic form are the second major group of flavonoids in 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span>. The most commonly detected free flavones are apigenin, luteolin, and diosmetin. O-Glycosides and C-glycosides are the two main forms of flavone glycosides, and the most common linked sugar moieties include glucose, rutinose, and neohesperidose [
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium,</span> the flavones may be present also in the methoxylated form, in which all or almost all hydroxyls are capped by methylation, as nobiletin and tangeretin [
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>]. Furthermore, the 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> may contain low amounts of flavonols, as kaempferol and quercetin, mainly in glycosidic form.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second class of secondary metabolites found in 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> are the limonoids (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="sch2" href="#sch2">Scheme 2</a>). The latter were considered as oxygenated triterpenoids as they contain relatively high numbers of oxygen atoms (7–11) in their structures. All components have a furan ring attached to the D-ring at C-17. Limonoids occur both in glucosidic and aglyconic form. Limonoid aglycones are water-insoluble and responsible for a bitter taste of the 
  <span class="italic">Citrus</span> fruits, while limonoid glucosides are water-soluble and tasteless [
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>]. Among limonoids, the most important one is limonin, known as 
  <span class="italic">Citrus</span> constituent since 1841. Limonoid glucosides are more abundant in juices and pulps, such as limonin glucoside, nomilin glucoside, obacunone glucoside, nomilinic acid glucoside, and deacetylnomilinic acid glucoside, because they are water-soluble, while limonoid aglycones such as limonin, nomilin, obacunone, ichangin, and deacetyl nomilin are water-insoluble and are present mainly in seeds and peels [
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>, 
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another class of compounds contained in 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> are phenylethylamine alkaloids with 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-synephrine being the most abundant. This compound has a hydroxyl group in the para position on the benzene ring and has some structural similarity to ephedrine. The peel of unripe fruits is the part of the plant which has the highest level of 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-synephrine [
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Zarrad and coworkers [
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>] explored the chemical composition of Tunisian 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> fruits using gas chromatography (GC) and gas chromatography-mass spectroscopy (GC-MS). 25 compounds were identified in 97.696% exploration, but the most prominent one was limonene with 85.52%, followed by linalool and 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-myrcene with 3.365% and 1.628%, respectively. The remaining compounds were in traces. Earlier, Villafane et al. [
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>] reported the presence of D-limonene and nootkatone in the essential oil of the plant. Similarly, Sanei-Dehkordi et al. [
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>] identified 21 compounds in peel essential oil of the plant. Of the total explored 98.62% composition, the quantity of limonene was 94.81% while the LC
  <sub>50</sub> was 31.20 ppm against 
  <span class="italic">Anopheles stephensi.</span> However, the concentration of limonene was only 0.5–2.5% in 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> from Algeria and linalool and 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-terpineol were 18.6% and 15.1%, respectively [
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>]. Thus, overall considerable variation was observed in the concentration of these major components in 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> grown in different parts of the world [
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>–
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>]. Carvalho-Freitas and Costa observed strong anxiolytic and sedative-like effects of the essential oil derived from 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> [
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">42</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
