<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Anxiolytic and Sedative effects</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The anxiolytic and sedative effects of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> by 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span> light-dark box and the marble-burying assays were evaluated
  <span class="italic">. C. aurantium</span> essential oil enhanced the period the mice spent in the light chamber, as well as the number of transitions between the two compartments in the light-dark box test [
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>]. Moreover, single and repeated treatments with the essential oil were reported to suppress marble-burying behavior [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>]. The anxiolytic activity of the blossom of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> was also evaluated clinically on 60 patients undergoing minor surgical operation with no organic pathology. Two hours before the anesthesia induction, two groups consisting of 30 patients were administered at 1 mL/kg of either 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> distillate or saline solution. Anxiety was assessed by using the Spielberger state-trait anxiety inventory, the Amsterdamd preoperative anxiety, and information scale. The outcome of this study revealed that 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> could be active by reducing preoperative anxiety before minor operation [
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In traditional Chinese medicine (TCM), the combination of the aqueous extracts of the fruits of 
  <span class="italic">Gardenia jasminoides</span> Ellis, 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span>, and the bark of 
  <span class="italic">Magnolia officinalis</span> Rehd. et Wils. is called Zhi-Zi-Hou-Po (ZZHPD) and has been used to treat depression-like symptoms. Xing et al. [
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>] explored 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span> antidepressant activity of ZZHPD in rats, by using coat state test, sucrose preference test, forced swimming test, and open-field test. The effects of ZZHPD on hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis were determined by measuring the hormone levels. The results showed that ZZHPD improved depressive behaviors and normalized the adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) and corticosterone levels, by restoring the function of HPA axis, and increasing brain-derived neurotrophic factor expression in hippocampus and promoting hippocampal neurogenesis [
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>]. ACTH/corticotropinis a peptidic hormone secreted from the anterior pituitary, which regulates glucocorticoid cortisol production from the adrenals [
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">52</a>]. Stress increases ACTH release, which induces the stress hormone cortisol, together they cause numerous diseases [
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">53</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Letie et al. [
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">54</a>] conducted another study 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span>, where rat models were exposed to the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> at 1.0%, 2.5%, and 5.0% concentrations by inhalation, in acrylic boxes before employing elevated plus maze and open-field assays. 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> essential oil increased the time of the animals in the open arms of the elevated plus maze test and the time of active social interaction in the open field [
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">54</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wolfenbuttel et al. [
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">55</a>] investigated the influence of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantium</span> essential oil on melatonin and corticosterone in mice after inhalation for 30 min. Melatonin provides protective effects on neuronal cells and acts as an antidepressant by restoration of corticosterone levels. After treatment, the hormone levels did not present variation, whereas behavioral tests showed that the inhalation of 10% essential oil causes an anxiolytic-like and sedative effect. From these data, 
  <span class="italic">Citrus</span> essential oil represents a valuable tool for the treatment of the anxiety disturbs, apparently without interference with melatonin and corticosterone physiological levels [
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">55</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
