<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another material rich in polyphenols exhibiting properties that protect skin cells is green tea. The leaves of 
 <italic>Camelia sinensis</italic> contain four major polyphenols: epicatechin (EC), epicatechin gallate (ECG), epigallocatechin (EGC) and epigallocatechin gallate (EGCG), the last of which accounts for 40% of all the polyphenols [
 <xref rid="B211-nutrients-13-00203" ref-type="bibr">211</xref>]. Green tea polyphenols (GTPs) are an example of a component of plant-based dietary supplements used to prevent the adverse biological effects of UV radiation, including immunosuppression and photocarcinogenesis [
 <xref rid="B212-nutrients-13-00203" ref-type="bibr">212</xref>]. Research also indicates that GTPs can alleviate the symptoms of premature skin ageing induced by UVB radiation [
 <xref rid="B213-nutrients-13-00203" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>]. Chiu et al. studied the effect of GTPs on the symptoms of photoaging of the skin in a double-blind trial using a placebo in a group of 40 women. In half of the subjects a 10-percent green tea cream was applied together with 300 mg, twice-daily green tea oral supplementation, while the other half received the placebo. Histological examination showed significant improvements in elastic tissue content, but no significant changes were demonstrated clinically. The authors concluded that a clinically perceptible improvement might require a longer period of GTP administration. GTPs also exhibit anti-inflammatory and antioxidant properties and the ability to scavenge free radicals [
 <xref rid="B214-nutrients-13-00203" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>]. In vivo studies indicate an increase (from 2 to 15%) in plasma antioxidant activity following the consumption of tea or tea polyphenols [
 <xref rid="B215-nutrients-13-00203" ref-type="bibr">215</xref>]. A study by Vayalil et al. demonstrated the inhibition of oxidative stress induced by UVB radiation in the skin of SKH-1 hairless mice that received GTPs in their drinking water (0.2%, 
 <italic>w</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) and were then exposed to multiple doses of UVB light (90 mJ/cm
 <sup>2</sup>) for two months. The inhibition of protein oxidation was observed, as was the inhibition of the UVB-induced expression of matrix-degrading MMPs, such as MMP-2 (67%), MMP-3 (63%), MMP-7 (62%) and MMP-9 (60%) [
 <xref rid="B213-nutrients-13-00203" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>]. A study in C57BL/6 mice showed that green tea extract reduced collagen cross-linking and UVB-induced oxidative changes in the structures of proteins [
 <xref rid="B216-nutrients-13-00203" ref-type="bibr">216</xref>]. 
</p>
