<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As previously shown, tannins have been demonstrated to be inhibitors of lipid peroxidation and scavengers of free radicals, which are the main reason for the appearance of rancid off-flavors/aromas in foods. Therefore, the utilization of tannins as a natural antioxidant in food applications is drawing attention. Among the purified tannins, the most tested is tannic acid, which has been demonstrated to reduce lipid oxidation induced by ferrous ions in a plant-based emulsion of flaxseed oil droplets. In this assay, the antioxidant activity of the tannic acid was attributed to the metal binding properties of tannins [
 <xref rid="B103-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. The same molecule was applied to ground chicken breast meat to determine its ability to reduce lipid and protein oxidation, maintain color and prevent rancid volatiles. The addition of 5 to 10 ppm of tannic acid improved both cooked and raw quality parameters, showing low oxidation markers, off-odor volatiles and high color parameters [
 <xref rid="B104-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. Extracts of tannin-rich plants such as quebracho (
 <italic>S. balansae</italic> and 
 <italic>S. lorentzii</italic>) or conifers (
 <italic>P. abies</italic> or 
 <italic>Pinus sylvestris</italic> L.) have also been tested as natural food preservatives with antioxidant properties to improve the shelf life of different products. Quebracho tannins (0.5–1.5%) were applied to beef patties, showing that the lowest amount was able to improve lipid stability. On the other hand, higher concentrations reduced the tenderness, softness and juiciness of meat [
 <xref rid="B66-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Another study analyzed conifer tannins as antioxidants in a liposome model and in meat snacks. The tested tannins showed a high activity to prevent lipid oxidation without causing organoleptic interference in meat snacks [
 <xref rid="B52-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Altogether, this research suggests that tannins, as for other polyphenols, could be added to food matrices as alternative antioxidants.
</p>
