<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection and speciation of oral isolates of 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethical clearance for the study was obtained from Central Ethical Committee of the University. The procedure was explained to the patient in his/her mother tongue and a signed consent was obtained. Swabs from the tissue surface of the maxillary denture were taken from the patients who showed clinical symptoms of CADS.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Speciation of the 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> from the clinical samples was done, and they were further subcultured on Sauboraud Dextrose Agar (SDA) twice to confirm pure isolation of the yeast. The different species of 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> were first identified by Gram staining and later on confirmed by germ tube test, corn meal agar for chlamydospore formation and Chromagar, and other biochemical tests. Chrome 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> differentiation agar was used to differentiate 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> species. Chromagar for differentiation of 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> (Himedia, Mumbai, India) was prepared following manufacturer's instructions. 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> was differentiated as the colony exhibited light green color. Along with colonies of 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span>, steel-/blue-colored colonies of 
  <span class="italic">Candida tropicalis</span> and light pink-colored colonies of 
  <span class="italic">Candida glabrata</span> were observed and identified [
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Figure 2</a>].
 </p>
 <div id="F2" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="italic">Candida</span> speciation
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="CCD-9-3-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fungal inoculum was prepared from overnight culture (24 h) on SDA. Colonies were directly suspended in saline to obtain turbidity comparable to that of 0.5 McFarland Standards (approximately 1.5 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> CFU/ml).
 </p>
</sec>
