<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparison of efficacy of extracts from maceration technique with hydrodistillation technique for Origanum vulgare [
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a>]
 </div>
 <div id="T1" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Comparison of efficacy of extracts from maceration technique with hydrodistillation technique for 
    <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span>
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="CCD-9-3-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maceration method</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The different extracts of 
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> were obtained from maceration method using petroleum ether, chloroform, ethyl acetate, n-butanol, and methanol [
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Figure 4</a>].
 </p>
 <div id="F4" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Maceration extracts of 
    <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span>
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="CCD-9-3-g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Preparation of ethanolic extract</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The shade-dried powdered leaves (1 kg) of 
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> were soaked in ethanol (95%) for 4 days. After 4 days, the ethanolic layer was decanted off. The process was repeated for four times. The solvent from the total extract was distilled off, and the concentrate was evaporated on a water bath to a syrupy consistency and then evaporated to dryness.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fractionation of ethanolic extract</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The extract (70 g) was suspended in distilled water (1500 ml) and then extracted successively with petroleum ether (60°C–80°C, 8 × 500 ml), chloroform (8 × 500 ml), ethyl acetate (8 × 500 ml), n-butanol (8 × 500 ml), and methanol (8 × 500 ml). All the fractions were then washed with distilled water (30 ml), dried over anhydrous sodium sulfate, and freed of solvent by distillation. The ethanolic extract was thus fractionated into petroleum ether soluble extract (13 g), chloroform soluble extract (10 g), ethyl acetate soluble extract (7 g), n-butanol soluble extract (6 g), and methanol soluble extract (23 g).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The above extracts and the essential oil obtained through hydrodistillation method were tested and compared for their antifungal efficacy using well diffusion method against all the 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> species used in this study.
 </p>
</sec>
