<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Efficacy of various extraction methods for 
  <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We compared essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> obtained through hydrodistillation and the various extracts obtained through maceration method. It was observed that the antifungal activity of the essential oil obtained by hydrodistillation method was higher against the 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> species included in this study (zone of inhibition 30 ± 6 mm) [
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a>]. The extracts obtained through maceration technique did not show significant activity as compared to the essential oil. Among extracts, isolate of 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> showed susceptibility to only chloroform extract (10 mm). 
  <span class="italic">C. tropicalis</span> showed mild susceptibility to petrol ether (7–8 mm), ethanol (12–14 mm), and chloroform (9–10 mm). 
  <span class="italic">C. glabrata</span> did not show susceptibility to any of the extracts but was susceptible to the essential oil (36 ± 2 mm) [
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hence, in the present study, the hydrodistillation method was proved to be better than maceration method for this novel herb. The hydrodistillation method for 
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> has been found to affect the quantity and quality of the essential oil obtained.[
  <a rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref27">27</a>
  <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">28</a>
  <a rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref29">29</a>
  <a rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref30">30</a>] It has been observed by Kawase 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
  <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">31</a>] that when compared to other techniques, the quantity of the essential oil and its phytochemicals may contain higher concentration of active components. This could be the reason for the difference where essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> from hydrodistillation process showed better efficacy than extracts from maceration among 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, in contrast, in a study by Malabadi and Kumar,[
  <a rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref32">32</a>] the effect of extracts of four herbal plants on 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> were assessed. The extracts included acetone, hexane, dichloromethane, and methanol. They observed that methanol extracts exhibited maximum antifungal effect against these 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> species. The conflicting result observed by them as compared to our study could be due to the fact that the plants used were different from 
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span>. Herbal plants have different range of activity depending on their composition of phytochemicals and pathogens exhibit varied response to the different products.
 </p>
</sec>
