<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, a novel medicinal plant 
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> was investigated for its antifungal activity against oral isolates of 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span>, a unique research which has never been carried out in prosthodontics so far.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> has been extensively used as antimicrobial agent against 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> infections in animals and human beings. The antifungal effects of 
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> have been studied against 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> spp. isolated from systemic infections. However, on review of existing literature, no study was available where it has been used against isolates of 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> from the oral cavity of a denture wearer.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CADS is a form of oral candidiasis and a chronic inflammatory reaction of the oral mucosa in a denture-wearing patient. It is usually characterized by erythema and edema of the palatal area localized to denture bearing tissues causing discomfort in wearing prosthesis. Localized trauma from a poorly maintained, ill-fitting denture and/or allergy to the material used for the prosthesis are the most common reasons for the causation of CADS.[
  <a rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref2">2</a>] In an immunosuppressed status such as diabetes mellitus,[
  <a rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref20">20</a>] long-term antibiotics therapy, chemotherapy for cancer, transplant recipient,[
  <a rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref21">21</a>
  <a rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref22">22</a>] and AIDS/HIV,[
  <a rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref3">3</a>
  <a rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref23">23</a>] the normal oral commensal fungus 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> turns virulent causing infection which if not treated can prove fatal. The present-day antifungal agent like fluconazole has been found to be causing toxicity on long-term application, and it also results in the development of resistance in the causative agent.[
  <a rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref5">5</a>
  <a rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref6">6</a>
  <a rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref7">7</a>
  <a rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref8">8</a>
  <a rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref9">9</a>
  <a rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref10">10</a>
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">11</a>
  <a rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref12">12</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hence, this research was undertaken to explore the characteristics of 
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> for its possible antifungal activity against oral isolates of 
  <span class="italic">Candida spp</span>. among patients with CADS.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The clinical isolates of 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> used in our study were collected from patients affected with CADS and they were subjected to speciation procedure using Chromagar to identify the species responsible. It was observed that 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> was the highest followed by 
  <span class="italic">C. tropicalis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. glabrata</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The herb 
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> is rich in its antifungal activity which has been tried against clinical isolates from systemic diseases but never in oral isolates of 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> from denture wearers. Hence, it is justified to explore its possible antifungal activities against the microorganisms causing the disease in the denture wearing section of the population. It is a novel study of its kind in the literature. In this study, the antifungal effects of 
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> were assessed and efficacy of different extraction procedures was compared. The MIC and MFC of the herb were determined and the active functional component present in it also was identified.
 </p>
 <sec id="sec2-5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antifungal activity of 
   <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antifungal activity of the experimental herb 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> was confirmed by comparing it with the known antifungal agent like nystatin. Antifungal susceptibility testing was carried out using agar well diffusion method. Antifungal activity showed zone of inhibition as 30 mm for 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> as compared to 22 mm for nystatin. This observation proved that the experimental herb 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> is antifungal in nature and also it is superior in its activity when compared to nystatin. This result is in accordance with a similar study carried out by Stiles 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
   <a rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref4">4</a>] where they observed a zone of inhibition for nystatin as 22–25 mm and that for 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> was 40–45 mm. However, their study was on 
   <span class="italic">Candida</span> isolates that were obtained from human stools. Cleff 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
   <a rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref24">24</a>] studied the effect of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> against reference strains of Candida and found that all were susceptible to the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span>. Rosato 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
   <a rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref25">25</a>] and Souza 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
   <a rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref26">26</a>] evaluated and observed that the essential oil 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> appeared to be effective, inhibiting all the 
   <span class="italic">Candida</span> species in their study.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Efficacy of various extraction methods for 
   <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We compared essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> obtained through hydrodistillation and the various extracts obtained through maceration method. It was observed that the antifungal activity of the essential oil obtained by hydrodistillation method was higher against the 
   <span class="italic">Candida</span> species included in this study (zone of inhibition 30 ± 6 mm) [
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a>]. The extracts obtained through maceration technique did not show significant activity as compared to the essential oil. Among extracts, isolate of 
   <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> showed susceptibility to only chloroform extract (10 mm). 
   <span class="italic">C. tropicalis</span> showed mild susceptibility to petrol ether (7–8 mm), ethanol (12–14 mm), and chloroform (9–10 mm). 
   <span class="italic">C. glabrata</span> did not show susceptibility to any of the extracts but was susceptible to the essential oil (36 ± 2 mm) [
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hence, in the present study, the hydrodistillation method was proved to be better than maceration method for this novel herb. The hydrodistillation method for 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> has been found to affect the quantity and quality of the essential oil obtained.[
   <a rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref27">27</a>
   <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">28</a>
   <a rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref29">29</a>
   <a rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref30">30</a>] It has been observed by Kawase 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
   <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">31</a>] that when compared to other techniques, the quantity of the essential oil and its phytochemicals may contain higher concentration of active components. This could be the reason for the difference where essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> from hydrodistillation process showed better efficacy than extracts from maceration among 
   <span class="italic">Candida</span> species.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, in contrast, in a study by Malabadi and Kumar,[
   <a rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref32">32</a>] the effect of extracts of four herbal plants on 
   <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> were assessed. The extracts included acetone, hexane, dichloromethane, and methanol. They observed that methanol extracts exhibited maximum antifungal effect against these 
   <span class="italic">Candida</span> species. The conflicting result observed by them as compared to our study could be due to the fact that the plants used were different from 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span>. Herbal plants have different range of activity depending on their composition of phytochemicals and pathogens exhibit varied response to the different products.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Minimum inhibitory concentration/minimum fungicidal concentration of 
   <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After the antifungal action the essential oil was established, the research was continued to determine the MIC/MFC using serial dilution method. Serial dilution method for determination of MIC and MFC of the herbal oils have been implemented by Chitwood[
   <a rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref33">33</a>] and Johnson (2008)[
   <a rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref34">34</a>] and it was found to be satisfactory to use in laboratories. Furthermore, according to the NCCLS standards, it is an efficient method to evaluate MIC/MFC of the antifungal agents.[
   <a rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref35">35</a>] In the present study, the MIC of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> was found to be 0.024% and MFC was observed as 0.097% [
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T2" href="#T2">Table 2</a>] when it was tested against Candida. In a study by Manohar 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.,[
   <a rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref17">17</a>] the authors showed that 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> can be fungicidal on 
   <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> from mice with a MIC of 0.125% and MFC of 0.25%. In their study, they also observed that a daily dose of 1.0 μl of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> oil for 30 days can cure systemic candidiasis in mice.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We compared the MIC/MFC of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> with existing value for fluconazole (0.25%)[
   <a rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref36">36</a>] and it was observed that the MIC/MFC of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> (0.024% and 0.097%) was much lower. The MIC of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> (0.024%) which was determined in our study is in par with a study carried out by Hammer 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.,[
   <a rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref37">37</a>] wherein it was found to be 0.03% against 
   <span class="italic">C. albicans</span>. In a study by Xu 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.,[
   <a rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref38">38</a>] MIC of fluconazole was found to be 125 times more in azole-resistant 
   <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> than in susceptible 
   <span class="italic">C. albicans</span>. The present experimental herb 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> showed much lesser MIC/MFC as compared to fluconazole indicating that the herb can be effective even in a lower dose of MIC/MFC. In a comparative study by Lambert 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.,[
   <a rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref39">39</a>] they also observed that 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> had a total inhibitory effect on the pathogens involved. However, their study was against bacteria and not the fungi affecting human beings.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparison of the MIC/MFC results obtained in the present study with earlier studies available may not be reliable, as the composition of the essential oil used in the present study could be different from those used in the previous studies. It is known that the composition of an essential oil can vary according to the local climatic and environmental situations and the time of harvesting the herb.[
   <a rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref40">40</a>
   <a rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref41">41</a>] Furthermore, there are no comparable studies on effect of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> on human oral isolates from denture stomatitis patients, as the present study is the first of its kind in the literature.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Active functional group in 
   <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Herbal antifungal agents have been shown to contain active phytochemicals that are responsible for their activity against fungal pathogens. We analyzed our experimental herb 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> using IR spectroscopy to identify the active functional group present in it. It was observed that 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> contained a compound which had a similar chemical structure like carvacrol (C
   <sub>6</sub>H
   <sub>3</sub> CH
   <sub>3</sub> (OH) (C
   <sub>3</sub>H
   <sub>7</sub>)). The peaks in the spectrum showed OH, CH, and C = C groups indicating carvacrol[
   <a rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref42">42</a>
   <a rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref43">43</a>] and/or related constituent is present in the test material. The hydroxyl group (OH) has been found to be responsible for the antifungal actions by carvacrol.[
   <a rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref44">44</a>
   <a rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref45">45</a>] In this aspect, the present study is in consistency with earlier researchers where carvacrol has been found to be the primary active component giving antifungal property to 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span>[
   <a rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref40">40</a>
   <a rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref41">41</a>
   <a rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref43">43</a>] and that it inhibited 
   <span class="italic">Candida</span>.[
   <a rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref4">4</a>
   <a rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref46">46</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
