<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oil extraction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dried leaves and bracts of 
  <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> were procured and essential oil [
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Figure 3</a>] was extracted using hydrodistillation method. The dry leaves were used in a Clevenger apparatus for 4 h to extract the oils with CHCl
  <sub>3</sub>, and then, it was dried over anhydrous sodium sulfate. The oil yield was stored in sealed amber-colored vial at 4°C until use.
 </p>
 <div id="F3" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Dry leaves and essential oil of 
    <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span>
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="CCD-9-3-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <sec id="sec3-1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Determining the antifungal activity of Origanum vulgare</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antifungal activity of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> was determined by agar diffusion test. Modified Kirby–Baeur method was used. SDA plates were prepared according to the CLSI guidelines.[
   <a rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref19">19</a>] These plates were then inoculated within 15 min of the preparation of the suspension so that the density does not change. The medium was inoculated by even streaking with the help of a sterile cotton wool swab.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Six-millimeter wells were punched out on agar. These wells were then inoculated with 20 μl of the test material. The plates were incubated for 48 h at 37°C aerobically. After the incubation period, plates were removed and zones of inhibition were recorded.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The diameter of zone of inhibition was measured to the nearest millimeter with a thin transparent millimeter scale. Nystatin (HiMedia, Mumbai), a proven antifungal agent, was taken as the control for the test material.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3-2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparison of efficacy of extracts from maceration technique with hydrodistillation technique for Origanum vulgare [
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a>]
  </div>
  <div id="T1" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Comparison of efficacy of extracts from maceration technique with hydrodistillation technique for 
     <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="CCD-9-3-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maceration method</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The different extracts of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> were obtained from maceration method using petroleum ether, chloroform, ethyl acetate, n-butanol, and methanol [
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Figure 4</a>].
  </p>
  <div id="F4" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Maceration extracts of 
     <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="CCD-9-3-g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Preparation of ethanolic extract</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The shade-dried powdered leaves (1 kg) of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> were soaked in ethanol (95%) for 4 days. After 4 days, the ethanolic layer was decanted off. The process was repeated for four times. The solvent from the total extract was distilled off, and the concentrate was evaporated on a water bath to a syrupy consistency and then evaporated to dryness.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fractionation of ethanolic extract</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The extract (70 g) was suspended in distilled water (1500 ml) and then extracted successively with petroleum ether (60°C–80°C, 8 × 500 ml), chloroform (8 × 500 ml), ethyl acetate (8 × 500 ml), n-butanol (8 × 500 ml), and methanol (8 × 500 ml). All the fractions were then washed with distilled water (30 ml), dried over anhydrous sodium sulfate, and freed of solvent by distillation. The ethanolic extract was thus fractionated into petroleum ether soluble extract (13 g), chloroform soluble extract (10 g), ethyl acetate soluble extract (7 g), n-butanol soluble extract (6 g), and methanol soluble extract (23 g).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The above extracts and the essential oil obtained through hydrodistillation method were tested and compared for their antifungal efficacy using well diffusion method against all the 
   <span class="italic">Candida</span> species used in this study.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3-3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Minimum inhibitory concentration/minimum fungicidal concentration of Origanum vulgare [
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T2" href="#T2">Table 2</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figure 5</a>]
  </div>
  <div id="T2" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Minimum inhibition concentrations/minimum fungicidal concentration of 
     <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="CCD-9-3-g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="F5" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Minimum inhibitory concentration/minimum fungicidal concentration of 
     <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="CCD-9-3-g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Determining MIC and MFC of 
   <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> was done according to the CLSI guidelines.[
   <a rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref19">19</a>]
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A pure culture of 
   <span class="italic">Candida</span> spp. was grown in Sabouraud Dextrose Broth. The optical density of planktonic suspension of each culture was adjusted to 1.5 × 10
   <span class="sup">8</span> CFU/ml (McFarland 0.5 standard). A known concentration of the essential oil was serially diluted to two folds in sterile test tubes.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After the experimental agent was diluted, a volume of the standardized inoculum equal to the volume of the diluted antimicrobial agent was added to each dilution tube, bringing the microbial concentration to approximately 500,000 cells/ml. Two control tubes were also included, one tube containing only the candidal culture which served as the positive control and other tube containing undiluted oil and the fungal culture which served as the negative control.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inoculated, serially diluted extract was incubated aerobically for 37°C for 18 h.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After incubation, the series of dilution tubes were observed for microbial growth, indicated by turbidity and/or a pellet of microorganisms in the bottom of the vessel. The last tube in the dilution series that did not demonstrate growth corresponds with the MIC of the antimicrobial agent. The MIC endpoint is the lowest concentration of the oil at which there is no visible growth in the tubes.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The test tubes demonstrating no visible turbidity were subcultured to solid agar plates and MFC was determined by comparing the growth with the positive control. The MFC endpoint is defined as the lowest concentration of antimicrobial agent that kills &gt;99.9% of the initial fungal population where no visible growth of the fungi was observed on the SDA plates. The tests were repeated in triplicates.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3-4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Infrared spectroscopy to determine the active functional group in Origanum vulgare</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">IR spectroscopy method was used to identify the active functional group using Bruker Fourier transform infrared alpha model, Germany [
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Figure 6</a>]. The transmitted light frequencies were recorded to obtain IR spectrum [
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F7" href="#F7">Figure 7</a>], and it was later compared with existing database for the presence of active groups.
  </p>
  <div id="F6" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Bruker Fourier transform infrared alpha model</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="CCD-9-3-g008" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="F7" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 7</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Infrared spectrum for 
     <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="CCD-9-3-g009" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
</sec>
