<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The allelopathic activity of the EOs and the MeOH extract of 
 <italic>H. curassavicum</italic> aerial parts was assessed against the weed, 
 <italic>C. murale</italic>. The ripe seeds of this weed were collected from cultivated fields with wheat in Manzalla city, Dakahlia Governorate, Egypt (31°07′06.9′’ N, 31°51′53.3′’ E). Seeds were surface sterilized by 0.3% sodium hypochlorite for 3 min, and then washed with distilled and sterilized water, and dried over sterilized filter paper. To test the allelopathic activity of the EOs, concentrations of 0.2, 0.4, 0.6, 0.8, and 1.0 mg mL
 <sup>−1</sup> were prepared using dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) (Sigma-Aldrich, Germany). On the other hand, similar concentrations (0.2, 0.4, 0.6, 0.8, and 1.0 mg mL
 <sup>−1</sup>) of the residue from the MeOH extract (its preparation is mentioned above) were prepared in DMSO. Subsequently, 20 
 <italic>C. murale</italic> seeds were arranged in Petri plates (Ø: 9 cm), lined with a Whatman No. 1 filter paper, and then 4 mL of each concentration was added. The experiment was designed with three replications, and a control treatment with either DMSO instead of the EO or MeOH extract. The plates sealed with a Parafilm
 <sup>®</sup> tape (Sigma, USA), and incubated at 25 ± 2 °C in a growth chamber with a controlled light cycle of 16 h light and 8 h dark. After seven days of incubation, the germinated seeds were counted as well as the root and shoot length of all seedlings were measured. The inhibition of either germination or seedling length was calculated as follows: 
 <disp-formula id="FD1-plants-08-00482">
  <label>(1)</label>
  <math id="mm1">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi>Inhibition</mi>
      <mtext> </mtext>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mo>(</mo>
      <mo>%</mo>
      <mo>)</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mn>100</mn>
     <mo>×</mo>
     <mfrac>
      <mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
         <mi>No</mi>
         <mo>/</mo>
         <mrow>
          <mi>Length</mi>
          <mtext> </mtext>
          <mi>of</mi>
          <mtext> </mtext>
          <mi>control</mi>
         </mrow>
         <mo>−</mo>
         <mi>No</mi>
         <mo>/</mo>
         <mrow>
          <mi>Length</mi>
          <mtext> </mtext>
          <mi>of</mi>
          <mtext> </mtext>
          <mi>tretamnet</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
       </mrow>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mi>No</mi>
       <mo>/</mo>
       <mrow>
        <mi>Length</mi>
        <mtext> </mtext>
        <mi>of</mi>
        <mtext> </mtext>
        <mi>control</mi>
       </mrow>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
     <mo>.</mo>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
