<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The ERT technology is only suitable for measurements in vertical pipes, since the electrodes are in direct contact with the flow. If the electrodes are frequently exposed to the gas phase (non-conducting phase), as will happen in horizontal pipes under stratified, wave, slug or plug flow, the electrodes might lose their continuous electrical contact with the measured flow [
 <xref rid="B89-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>]. In [
 <xref rid="B89-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>] a method is presented, so ERT can be implemented for two-phase flow in horizontal pipes. The method is called Liquid Level Detection and takes account for the electrodes that are exposed to gas (air) and hereby monitors the position of the water surface. M. Wang [
 <xref rid="B90-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>] has also invented a method for ERT sensors to address the challenges of electrodes with no contact to the conductive fluid. A disadvantage regarding ERT is that the technology is primarily suitable when the continuous phase is conducting. Therefore, when the flow is water continuous, ERT should be applied. This is due to the electrical conductivity of water compared to oil, which will appear as an insulator [
 <xref rid="B91-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>]. Due to this it can be beneficial to combine the ERT and ECT technology, to obtain a sensor technique that can obtain capacitive and resistive properties simultaneously [
 <xref rid="B92-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>]. The design of a multi-modal tomography system based on ERT and ECT has been described in [
 <xref rid="B93-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>,
 <xref rid="B94-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B95-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>]. In [
 <xref rid="B97-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">97</xref>] a dual-modal sensor is presented, which is able to measure the multi-phase distribution in a flow. For a gas-oil-water concentration consisting of 50% oil/water (30% water and 20% oil), the sensor is able to reconstruct the images such that the concentration is calculated to 49.69% oil/water (30.17% water and 18.53% oil). The ECT mode is used when WLR is less than 40% (oil-continuous flows) and ERT is used when WLR is higher than 40% (water-continuous flows).
</p>
