<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Various crude extracts from 
 <italic>H. antidysenterica</italic> seeds such as water, ethanol, hydro alcoholic etc. were studied for their acute oral toxicity by Sheikh et al. [
 <xref rid="B108-biomolecules-10-01341" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>] and Pathak et al. [
 <xref rid="B149-biomolecules-10-01341" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>]; they were found to be safe up to 2000 mg/kg BW in albino rats. Singh [
 <xref rid="B150-biomolecules-10-01341" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>], conducted a pre-clinical safety study of 
 <italic>H. antidysenterica</italic> stem bark in both mice and rats. Albino mice (Swiss) treated with 2000, 1000 &amp; 500 mg/kg, p.o. showed dullness and writhing, and a 30% mortality was recorded within 96 h. However, the authors further studied subacute toxicity in rats with lower doses (50, 100, 200 mg/kg, p.o.) and found no significant changes in hematological or biochemical parameters and histopathological examinations. An acute toxicity study conducted by Keshri et al. [
 <xref rid="B109-biomolecules-10-01341" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>] and Kumar and Yadav [
 <xref rid="B151-biomolecules-10-01341" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>] in albino rats revealed that ethanolic extracts of 
 <italic>H. antidysenterica</italic> seeds showed no toxicity at 3000 mg/kg. Saha and Subrahmanyam [
 <xref rid="B116-biomolecules-10-01341" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>] and Hegde and Jaisal [
 <xref rid="B111-biomolecules-10-01341" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>] found ethanolic extracts of 
 <italic>H. antidysenterica</italic> seed and leaves, respectively, to be safe when administrated at 3000 mg/kg. Other studies showed the nontoxic nature of 
 <italic>H. antidysenterica</italic> when administered in albino rats at different oral doses, including 200 and 400 mg/kg [
 <xref rid="B110-biomolecules-10-01341" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-biomolecules-10-01341" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-biomolecules-10-01341" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. A similar study conducted by Bhusal et al. [
 <xref rid="B113-biomolecules-10-01341" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>] in male Swiss albino mice also detected no toxicity at 250 and 500 mg/kg (p.o) for methanolic extract of 
 <italic>H. pubescens</italic> stembark.
</p>
