<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Stimulus-responsive drug delivery systems based on nanocarriers can be triggered by pH, enzymatic catalysis, magnetic, thermal, ultrasonic, electric, and irradiation stimuli (Liu, Yang, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Saravanakumar et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0104" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Jain et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Smart delivery systems for treating osteolysis can be activated by the osteolytic microenvironment such as low pH, high concentration of calcium, and active redox reaction to release drugs responsively (Karimi et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Tan et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0118" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Bai et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Designed pH-sensitive delivery systems release drugs through protonation or deprotonation of groups (carboxylic acid group, amino group) or break of chemical bonds (hydrazone, acetal, cis-Aconityl, β-thiopropionate, etc.) in an acidic environment. Aryl boronate group, as an acid–labile linker, was employed to construct pH-sensitive delivery systems. Mingming Wang et al. made polyamidoamine (PAMAM) dendrimer with catechol and PEG ligands modification (Wang, Cai, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0126" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Boronate-catechol linkage was pH-responsive and linked bortezomib (BTZ) to dendrimer for responsive BTZ delivery to low pH. BTZ was released from the polymer less than 5% at pH 7.4 at 12 h but nearly 57% at pH 5.0 at 6 h. PH 5.0 is usually known as the lysosomal pH (pH 4.5) (Wang, Cai, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0126" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). A similar design was made by Jianhua Zhu et al. (Zhu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0153" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). In a study, Zol-anchored MSNs (DOX@MSNs − ZOL) loaded DOX and had obvious pH-sensitive DOX release behavior because MSNs − ZOL did not have enough hydroxyl radicals to create hydrogen bond with the amino group of DOX. DOX@MSNs − ZOL entered cells through an ATP-dependent pathway and then localized in the lysosome to achieve effective intracellular DOX release (Chen, Boda, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Chunyan Li et al. fabricated a Ag
 <sub>2</sub>S QD-based nanosystem (Ald/DOX@Ag
 <sub>2</sub>S) with surface-anchored ALN and encapsulated DOX (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0006">Figure 6(a)</xref>). These NPs were deposited in bone tissues and then DOX was released in the tumor site triggered by the acidic tumor microenvironment. The drug release kinetics was exhibited in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0006">Figure 6(b)</xref>. Ald/DOX@Ag
 <sub>2</sub>S caused a time and dose-dependent increase in caspase-3 activity (apoptosis assay) and inhibited the osteoclastic differentiation of RAW264.7 cells stimulated by RANKL (Li et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Likewise, redox acted as a trigger in some targeted delivery systems because of the active redox at the osteolytic site. Glutathione (GSH) is an antioxidant and its concentration is 7–10 times higher in tumor cells than normal cells (1–10 mmol L
 <sup>−1</sup>) (Wu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0137" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Aluri et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0133" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Disulfide bonds can be broken by GSH so that it was utilized by many scientists to fabricate micelles or polymeric NPs in response to the active redox. J.P. Vanderburgh et al. developed aqueous and intravenously injectable micellar NPs to encapsulate GANT58 via a combination of anionic and reversible addition-fragmentation chain transfer (RAFT) polymerization. Poly[(oligo ethylene glycol)
 <sub>9</sub> methyl ether acrylate]
 <sub>17</sub> formed the hydrophilic NPs surface while polymer poly(propylene sulfide) formed the hydrophobic core that sequestered GANT58. In response to reactive oxygen species (ROS), poly(propylene sulfide) became hydrophilic and degraded to initiate drug release. In an intratibia breast cancer bone metastasis model, these NPs decreased bone lesion area and lesion number by 49% and 38% respectively, and increased trabecular bone volume (Vanderburgh et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0124" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Stimulus-release systems also can be triggered by two or more stimuli. Metal-organic frameworks (MOFs), mainly in a cubic shape, with an average size &lt;100 nm in diameter, were utilized to construct a multi-stimuli ‘gated scaffold.’ The frameworks based on zirconium, remained tightly and controlled release at the normal Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> concentration, pH, and temperature, but released drugs around/in bone tumor cells with increasing Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> concentration, decreasing pH, and/or by using thermal therapy. During this process, carboxylatopillar[5]arene played a vital role in regulating the binding between the rings-structure and the stalk-structure (Tan et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0118" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Multi-stimuli responsive systems are more sensitive to the osteolytic microenvironment and deliver the drug more rapidly but less specifically. It may be optimized through integration with implantable materials or targeted NPs. Another NPs, DOX@ALN-(HA-PASP)CL, were prepared with pH sensitivity and redox sensitivity. During the synthesis of these NPs, ALN and HA were linked by a hydrazone bond which was responsive to the acidic microenvironment. HA and PASP [poly(aspartic acid)] were cross-linked by a disulfide bond to increase the stability of the NPs. Release kinetics of DOX from DOX@ALN-(HA-PASP)CL was showed in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0006">Figure 6(c)</xref>. Tumor and bone resorption was inhibited obviously in the research (Zhao et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0150" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The responsive delivery embodied the prevention theory. But if osteolysis already happened, stimulus-release aimed to reduce the drug release of miss-targeted NPs to further reduce the side effects and accelerate the drug release in the osteolytic microenvironment.
</p>
