<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another common method to let the fragrant substances appear is through nectaries activity, where the secretory functions are performed by the epidermis (or trichomes) or cells below it. Nectar is also secreted by external walls into the intercellular spaces, from which it is extracted outside through special stomata. They are located in generative (floral) as well as vegetative parts of plants (extrafloral) [
 <xref rid="B112-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. Fragrant substances secreted through the nectaries are crucial for reproduction of all entomophile plants and serve as communicator agents with mutualist pollinators, or antagonists, such as florivores and herbivores. Examples of following fragrant compounds can be found in nectaries: (
 <italic>S)</italic>-(+)-linalool 
 <bold>27</bold>, methyl nicotinate 
 <bold>44</bold>, β-caryophyllene 
 <bold>45</bold>, methyl benzoate 
 <bold>46</bold>, or phenylacetonitrile 
 <bold>47</bold> [
 <xref rid="B113-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-02473-f007">Figure 7</xref>). Other specialized structures providing fragrant substances in plants are osmophores present in the following families: mainly Araceae Juss. and Orchidaceae Juss., but also Iridaceae Juss., Passifloraceae Juss. ex Kunth in Humb., Fabaceae Lindl., Solanaceae Juss, Apocynaceae Juss. [
 <xref rid="B116-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. According to fragrant volatiles from nectars, Burdon et al. [
 <xref rid="B118-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>] found an interesting relation between plants and bacteria colonizing floral tissue of 
 <italic>Penstemon digitalis</italic> Nutt. ex Sims. (Plantaginaceae Juss.). Since bacterial activity negatively affects the quality and quantity of nectar of this plant, they employ chemical (allelochemical) agents to suppress the bacteria colonies in nectar tissue. (
 <italic>S</italic>)-(+)-linalool 
 <bold>27</bold>, which is emitted from nectar (but not from petals), reduces bacteria density. Moreover, this compound only affects the bacteria isolated from nectar (bacteria isolated from leaves were not affected). On the other hand, Junker et al. [
 <xref rid="B115-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>] found that some bacterial strains (Enterobacteriaceae), originating from flowers 
 <italic>Saponaria officinalis</italic> L. (Caryophyllaceae Juss.), are adapted to native volatiles more than those settled on leaves, although isolates from petals characterize with less microbial diversity (both at the family and genus levels).
</p>
