<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemical composition of S. officinalis essential oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 49 constituents, representing 97.97 % of the total oil, have been identified from the essential oil extracted from the leaves of 
   <span class="italic">S. officinalis</span>. In Table 1
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="T1" href="#T1">(Tab. 1)</a> the compounds of the volatile oil and their relative percentages are listed in the order of their Kovats index. The monoterpene fraction of the oil amounted to 75.93 % with oxygen containing monoterpenes as the largest group of this fraction (48.43 %). Camphor (25.14 %), α-thujone (18.83 %), 1,8-cineole (14.14 %) and β-thujone (4.46 %) were the main compounds of the monoterpenoidic fraction. Among the sesquiterpene fraction (17.4 %), sesquiterpene hydrocarbons dominated (9.33 %) with β-caryophyllene (3.30 %) as the major component while viridiflorol (7.98 %) was identified as the main constituent of sesquiterpene alcohol fraction. Other components were present at amount lower than 3 % of the total yield. Our composition differs from that reported by other Tunisian studies, mostly due to the different geographic experimental areas. The EO contents of 
   <span class="italic">S. officinalis</span> collected from north of Tunisia, were 1,8-cineole (33.27 %), β-thujone (18.40 %), α-thujone (13.45 %), borneol (7.39 %), β-elemene (4.82 %), camphor (3.31 %) and α-pinene (2.74 %) (Hayouni et al., 2008[
   <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">20</a>]). Fellah et al. (2006[
   <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">15</a>]) found that SoEO from mountainous region in the center-west of Tunisia was mainly composed by α-thujone (26.49 %), 1,8-cineole (16.96 %), viridiflorol (13,04 %), β-thujone (11.55 %) β-caryophyllene (9.04 %), β-pinene (5.19 %) and camphre (3,38 %). However, essential oil analysis of sage from south of Tunisia revealed that β-thujone (17.76 %), 1,8-cineole (16.29 %), camphor (14.19 %), α-thujone (7.41 %), trans-Caryophyllene (5.45 %) were the major components (Bouaziz et al., 2009[
   <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">5</a>]). Studies on 
   <span class="italic">S. officinalis</span> performed in Spain (Laborda et al., 2013[
   <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">27</a>]), Italy (Marino et al., 2001[
   <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">34</a>]) and Brazil (Delamare Longaray et al., 2007[
   <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">10</a>]) also showed a significant variation in the chemical composition of the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">S. officinalis</span> compared to our results. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Compared to the other 
   <span class="italic">Salvia</span> species, our sage was particularly rich in camphor (25.14 %), α-thujone (18.83 %), 1,8-cineole (14.14 %), viridiflorol (7.98 %), β-Thujone (4.46 %), β-Caryophyllene (3.30 %), borneol (2.81 %), α-Humulene (2.48 %), β-Myrcene (1.93 %), limonene (1.43 %), α-Terpineol (1.33 %) and bornyl acetate (1.05 %). The main characteristic constituents of SoEO found in this study, are in accordance with the profile defined by standard ISO 9909 (Bruneton, 1999[
   <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">6</a>]) for official 
   <span class="italic">S. officinalis</span> essential oil, which is cis-thujone (18-43 %), camphor (4.5-24.5 %), cineole (5.5-13 %), humulene (0-12 %), trans-thujone (3-8.5 %), camphene (1.5-7 %), pinene (1-6.5 %), limonene (0.5-3 %), bornyl acetate (2.5 % maximum) and linalool [free and esterified (1 % maximum)].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This variation is probably due to the different growth habitat. Indeed, the oil composition is highly influenced by genetic (Mader et al., 2010[
   <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">31</a>]), environmental factors (Bettaieb et al., 2009[
   <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">4</a>]), the developmental stage of the plants and extraction method (Hadri et al., 2010[
   <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">18</a>]). Previous studies revealed that SoEO composition varies significantly depending on light intensity (Li et al., 1996[
   <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">29</a>]), soil mineral fertilization (Piccaglia and Marotti, 1993[
   <a rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" href="#R42">42</a>]), climate conditions, organ, culture site and season (Santos-Gomes and Fernandes-Ferreira, 2001[
   <a rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" href="#R47">47</a>]).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antioxidant activity of S. officinalis essential oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The IC
   <sub>50</sub> values (the concentration reducing 50 % of DPPH) obtained for scavenging activity on DPPH radical are shown in Table 2
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="T2" href="#T2">(Tab. 2)</a>. According to the recorded results, SoEO exhibited a good antioxidant power with an IC
   <sub>50 </sub>of 6.7 mg/mL but relatively lower than the synthetic antioxidant BHT used as positive control (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 3.2 µg/mL). The reducing power and the inhibition of linoleic acid peroxidation of SoEO showed a mild to moderate activity compared to the positive controls (Table 2
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="T2" href="#T2">(Tab. 2)</a>). It seems that the antioxidant activity of sage oil is due to the presence of monoterpenes such as α-pinene, a known potent antioxidant (Wang et al., 2008[
   <a rid="R56" ref-type="bibr" href="#R56">56</a>]) and several sesquiterpenes (Tamil Selvi et al., 2015[
   <a rid="R52" ref-type="bibr" href="#R52">52</a>]) and it is assumed that the contribution of minor and major compounds exhibited this activity and not only one or few active molecules (Wang et al., 2008[
   <a rid="R56" ref-type="bibr" href="#R56">56</a>]). 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antimicrobial activity of S. officinalis essential oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ability of the SoEO to inhibit bacteria and fungi (indicator organisms) was summarized (see Table 3
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="T3" href="#T3">(Tab. 3)</a> and 4
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="T4" href="#T4">(Tab. 4)</a>). Both Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria were inhibited by the SoEO. According to MIC and MBC values reported in Table 3
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="T3" href="#T3">(Tab. 3)</a>, the SoEO showed an interesting activity against the Gram-positive pathogens (
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">M. luteus</span>) and also a very good activity against 
   <span class="italic">B. cereus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">B. subtilis</span> with MIC values of 0.625 and 0.312 mg/mL, respectively. However, the SoEO cultivated in south Brazil, showed no activity against several 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus</span> strains (Delamare Longaray et al., 2007[
   <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">10</a>]).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concerning the Gram-negative bacteria, the sample was slightly active against 
   <span class="italic">E. coli</span>, 
   <span class="italic">S. enteretidis</span> and 
   <span class="italic">A. tumefaciens</span> which showed the lowest values of MIC (2.5 mg/ mL). Our results are similar to those previously reported in the literature, indicating that Gram-positive bacteria are more sensitive to essential oils than Gram-negative bacteria (Mangena and Muyima, 1999[
   <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">33</a>]). The microorganisms tested in this study cover some human pathogens known as opportunists for man and animals and cause food contamination and deterioration. Our results are of a great importance, particularly in the case of 
   <span class="italic">B. cereus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">S. enteretidis</span> which are well known for their resistance to a number of phytochemical compounds and for the production of several types of enterotoxins that cause gastroenteritis (Halpin-Dohnalek and Marth, 1989[
   <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">19</a>]). As shown in Table 4
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="T4" href="#T4">(Tab. 4)</a>, the SoEO exhibited varying degrees of antifungal activity against all tested strains. The inhibition zones were in the range of 09 - 15 mm, with MIC values of 0.156 - 5 mg/mL. The most sensitive one was 
   <span class="italic">Fusarium oxysporum</span> (MIC = 0.156 mg/mL), but the SoEO showed also a very good activity against 
   <span class="italic">Botrytis cinerea</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Alternaria alternata</span> (MIC = 0.625 mg/ mL for both). Interestingly, we have demonstrated the capacity of the SoEO to control some fungal strains, particularly fungi (
   <span class="italic">A. niger</span>, 
   <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">A. alternata</span>) responsible for biodeterioration of food during postharvest processing, transport and storage and agricultural phytopathogenic fungi. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies reported that there is a relationship between the chemical composition of the most abundant components in the EO and the antimicrobial activity (Deans and Sbodova, 1990[
   <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">9</a>]). In this context, camphor, α -thujone and 1,8-cineole (herein, abundants in SoEO) are well-known chemicals having antimicrobial potentials (Pattnaik et al., 1997[
   <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">41</a>]). α-pinene, 2-β-pinene and limonene also had a strong antibacterial activity (Sökmen et al., 2003[
   <a rid="R50" ref-type="bibr" href="#R50">50</a>]). These chemical components exerted their toxic effects against microorganisms through the disruption of bacteria or fungal membrane integrity (Knobloch et al., 1989[
   <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">24</a>]). In addition, the SoEO contained relatively high proportions of oxygenated monoterpenes (Table 1
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="T1" href="#T1">(Tab. 1)</a>) and it is well known that essential oils containing high proportions of oxygenated monoterpenes have strong antifungal activities compared to EO relatively rich in monoterpene hydrocarbons or sesquiterpenes (Kordali et al., 2005[
   <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">26</a>]). Therefore, the obtained antibacterial and antifungal activities were related to synergistic effects between different major and minor components of the SoEO, suggesting that the SoEO may potentially be useful in food preservation and pest management.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Insecticidal activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SoEO was assayed on 
   <span class="italic">S. littoralis</span> larvae and 
   <span class="italic">T. castaneum</span> adults. The percentage of mortality produced by each strain at different SoEO concentrations was shown in Figure 1
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">(Fig. 1)</a>. Mortality increased by increasing the SoEO concentration, which revealed a dose-dependent effect. The LC
   <sub>50</sub> of SoEO was also calculated for each pest species. The fumigant assay indicated that SoEO showed interesting insecticidal activity against the third instar larvae of 
   <span class="italic">S. littoralis</span> and adults of 
   <span class="italic">T. castaneum</span>, with an LC
   <sub>50</sub> value of 55.99 ± 7.95 µl/L air and 97.43 ± 11.85 µl/L air, respectively. To our knowledge, there is limited information concerning the activity of SoEO against Lepidopteran larvae 
   <span class="italic">S. littoralis. </span>Ben El Hadj Ali et al. (2015[
   <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">3</a>]) reported an approximately similar toxicity exhibited by 
   <span class="italic">Thymus algeriensis</span> EO against the third instar larvae of
   <span class="italic"> S. littoralis</span>. The high insecticidal potency of SoEO could be attributed to monoterpenoids compounds such as camphene, α-pinene and γ-terpinene, which were well known for their strong insecticidal activity against 
   <span class="italic">T. castaneum</span> adults (Kim et al., 2010[
   <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">23</a>]). In addition, 1-8-cineole and limonene possessed fumigant toxicity against this insect (Lee et al., 2004[
   <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">28</a>]). These monoterpenoids are known for their inhibitory effects on acetylcholinesterase, a key enzyme in the insect central nervous system (Abdelgaleil et al., 2009[
   <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">1</a>]; Zarrad et al., 2015[
   <a rid="R57" ref-type="bibr" href="#R57">57</a>]). Caryophyllene oxide, a sesquiterpene compound, also showed high fumigant toxicity against this pest. Its high toxicity may result from the inhibition of the mitochondrial electron transport system because changes in the concentration of oxygen or carbon dioxide may affect respiration rate of 
   <span class="italic">T. castaneum</span>, thus eliciting fumigant toxicity effects (Emekci et al., 2004[
   <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">14</a>]).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phytotoxicity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A series of experiments was conducted to assess the level of toxicity of the SoEO on the seed germination, hypocotyl and root lengths and fresh weights of 
   <span class="italic">T. aestivum</span>, 
   <span class="italic">R. sativus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">S. lycopersicum</span> and 
   <span class="italic">T. foenum-graecum</span> (Figure 2
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">(Fig. 2)</a> and 3
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">(Fig. 3)</a>). The SoEO affected the germination and the seedling growth of tested seeds in a different way. Although the level of the major compounds in the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">S. officinalis </span>was closed to those of other
   <span class="italic"> Salvia </span>species, the interaction between seed species and treatments (with or without SoEO) was statistically significant (P &lt; 0.01). The SoEO did not statistically inhibit the germination of all tested seeds (Figure 2
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">(Fig. 2)</a>). 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our data disagree with the literature on inhibitory activity exerted by essential oils of 
   <span class="italic">Salvia </span>species on seed germination (Mancini et al., 2009[
   <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">32</a>]; Muller and Muller, 1964[
   <a rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" href="#R37">37</a>]; Singh et al., 2006[
   <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">48</a>]). Significant interactions (p &lt; 0.05) between seed species and treatments (with or without SoEo) were also noted in radicle and hypocotyl lengths and weights (Figure 3
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">(Fig. 3)</a>). Indeed, radicle length and hypocotyl length of 
   <span class="italic">T. aestivum</span> and 
   <span class="italic">T. foenum-graecum</span> seeds were significantly inhibited by the SoEO, while stimulation was observed on 
   <span class="italic">S. lycopersicum </span>and 
   <span class="italic">R. sativus </span>seeds, in comparison to untreated seeds. Fresh weight of roots and hypocotyls of 
   <span class="italic">T. aestivum</span> and 
   <span class="italic">T. foenum-graecum</span> also decreased by the SoEO, compared to the untreated seeds (Figure 3
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">(Fig. 3)</a>). 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inhibition of seedling growth could be attributed to camphor and 1,8-cineole, the main compounds of the SoEO
   <span class="italic">, </span>which are potent inhibitors of oxygen uptake by mitochondrial suspensions (Romagni et al., 2000[
   <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">44</a>]). Moreover, several monoterpenoids of the SoEO, including linalool (Singh et al., 2006[
   <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">48</a>]), α-pinene (Singh et al., 2006[
   <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">48</a>]) and limonene (Singh et al., 2006[
   <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">48</a>]) are potent inhibitors of seedling growth. Previous studies have documented that essential oil and their constituents induce oxidative stress and inhibit root growth (Singh et al., 2006[
   <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">48</a>], 2009[
   <a rid="R49" ref-type="bibr" href="#R49">49</a>]; Mutlu et al., 2011[
   <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">38</a>]). They reported an enhancement of lipid peroxidation and hydrogen peroxide accumulation and an increase of electrolyte leakage in root tissue (Singh et al., 2009[
   <a rid="R49" ref-type="bibr" href="#R49">49</a>]; Mutlu et al., 2011[
   <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">38</a>]). However, the SoEO does not cause any inhibitory effect on root and hypocotyl elongation and fresh weight on
   <span class="italic"> S. lycopersicum</span> seeds. López-Iglesias et al. (2014[
   <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">30</a>]) suggested that enhanced plant growth/plant growth inhibition, could be the result of a positive or negative balance between nutrient and polyphenol concentration. Santana-Méridas et al. (2014[
   <a rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" href="#R46">46</a>]) reported a stimulating effect of rosemary residues on 
   <span class="italic">L. sativa </span>and a moderate phytotoxic effect of 
   <span class="italic">L. perenne</span>. The phytotoxic effects of the SoEO appeared to be species seeds-dependent.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results obtained in this study clearly demonstrate that 
   <span class="italic">S.officinalis </span>essential oil from Eastern Center of Tunisia showed a high variation in its chemical composition compared to those isolated from other country regions. Moderate antioxidant activity of SoEO was demonstrated. This oil exhibited promising antimicrobial and antifungal activities and seems to have a potent fumigant activity against Lepidoptera and Coleoptera pests. Both phytotoxic and stimulating effects on 
   <span class="italic">T. aestivum</span>, 
   <span class="italic">R. sativus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">S. lycopersicum</span> and 
   <span class="italic">T. foenum-graecum</span> radicle and hypocotyl growth were observed. The high biological activities of 
   <span class="italic">S. officinalis </span>could be attributed to the components identified by GC-MS analysis. All those results valorize Tunisian 
   <span class="italic">S. officinalis</span> as a medicinal plant which can be a source of biological active compounds. Therefore, Tunisian 
   <span class="italic">S. officinalis </span>essential oil could be used as a natural agent in pest management, in cosmetic and pharmaceutical industries.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
