<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Insecticidal activity</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Insect cultures</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The insects used in the tests were reared at the Laboratory of Entomology at the Regional Research Center on Horticulture and Organic Agriculture (RRCHOA), University of Sousse, Tunisia. 
   <span class="italic">Spodoptera littoralis</span> (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) was reared on artificial diet consisting of a mixture of wheat germ, beer yeast, maize semolina, ascorbic acid, nipagine, benzoic acid, agar and water (Poitout and Bues, 1970[
   <a rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" href="#R43">43</a>]) at 26 ± 2 °C, with a photoperiod of 16:8 h light: dark (L:D) and 75 ± 5 % relative humidity (RH) in a growth chamber. The third instar larvae of 
   <span class="italic">S. littoralis </span>were used for the test. 
   <span class="italic">Tribolium castaneum</span> (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae) was reared on wheat flour mixed with yeast (10:1, w/w). The cultures were maintained in a growth chamber at 28 ± 2 °C, with a RH of 75 ± 5 %, in the dark. Only new emerged adults were used for the test. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bioassays</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The insecticidal activity of the SoEO, against the third instar larvae of 
   <span class="italic">S. littoralis</span> and the adults of 
   <span class="italic">T. castaneum</span>, was determined by fumigant bioassay using closed container method. A group of 10 larvae or adults were put into the bottom of plastic container of 40 mL. Treatments (concentrations of SoEO 0, 25, 50, 100, 200 and 400 µl/L air) were applied to paper discs, attached at the top of the container, which will be closed. The concentrations quoted above and further in this paper correspond to the volume of the essential oil put on the filter and the volume of the air in the container. Five replicates of each concentration and the control were made. Mortality was recorded after 48 h of the treatment for both 
   <span class="italic">S. littoralis </span>larvae and 
   <span class="italic">T. castaneum</span> adults and the fifty percent lethal concentration (LC
   <sub>50</sub>) was calculated from pooled raw data by probit analysis using programs written in the R. Language (Venables and Smith, 2004[
   <a rid="R54" ref-type="bibr" href="#R54">54</a>]).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
