<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Insecticidal activity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SoEO was assayed on 
  <span class="italic">S. littoralis</span> larvae and 
  <span class="italic">T. castaneum</span> adults. The percentage of mortality produced by each strain at different SoEO concentrations was shown in Figure 1
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">(Fig. 1)</a>. Mortality increased by increasing the SoEO concentration, which revealed a dose-dependent effect. The LC
  <sub>50</sub> of SoEO was also calculated for each pest species. The fumigant assay indicated that SoEO showed interesting insecticidal activity against the third instar larvae of 
  <span class="italic">S. littoralis</span> and adults of 
  <span class="italic">T. castaneum</span>, with an LC
  <sub>50</sub> value of 55.99 ± 7.95 µl/L air and 97.43 ± 11.85 µl/L air, respectively. To our knowledge, there is limited information concerning the activity of SoEO against Lepidopteran larvae 
  <span class="italic">S. littoralis. </span>Ben El Hadj Ali et al. (2015[
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">3</a>]) reported an approximately similar toxicity exhibited by 
  <span class="italic">Thymus algeriensis</span> EO against the third instar larvae of
  <span class="italic"> S. littoralis</span>. The high insecticidal potency of SoEO could be attributed to monoterpenoids compounds such as camphene, α-pinene and γ-terpinene, which were well known for their strong insecticidal activity against 
  <span class="italic">T. castaneum</span> adults (Kim et al., 2010[
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">23</a>]). In addition, 1-8-cineole and limonene possessed fumigant toxicity against this insect (Lee et al., 2004[
  <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">28</a>]). These monoterpenoids are known for their inhibitory effects on acetylcholinesterase, a key enzyme in the insect central nervous system (Abdelgaleil et al., 2009[
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">1</a>]; Zarrad et al., 2015[
  <a rid="R57" ref-type="bibr" href="#R57">57</a>]). Caryophyllene oxide, a sesquiterpene compound, also showed high fumigant toxicity against this pest. Its high toxicity may result from the inhibition of the mitochondrial electron transport system because changes in the concentration of oxygen or carbon dioxide may affect respiration rate of 
  <span class="italic">T. castaneum</span>, thus eliciting fumigant toxicity effects (Emekci et al., 2004[
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">14</a>]).
 </p>
</sec>
