<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>C. citratus</italic> EO had a citral component of 55% which was slightly below the levels referred to in other studies where concentrations of nearly 60% of this bioactive mixture (neral + geranial [C
 <sub>10</sub>H
 <sub>16</sub>O]) were present [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-25-04447" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The composition of the EO varies in relation to the genetic component of the plant, its cultivation conditions, harvest time, the harvested part of the plant, the management of the plant material, and the extraction methods, among other factors. Researchers [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-04447" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-04447" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], evaluated the antimicrobial effect of the individual citral and geranial components present in 
 <italic>Cymbopogon</italic> sp on the horticultural pathogens 
 <italic>Rhizoctonia solani</italic> (
 <italic>Ceratobasidiaceae</italic>), 
 <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> (
 <italic>Nectriaceae</italic>), and 
 <italic>Sclerotium rolfsii</italic> (
 <italic>Atheliaceae</italic>). A variant of the poisoned food technique was used to verify the efficiency of these molecules and its selectivity according to the phytopathogen evaluation of the biocontroller. Citral was more effective in the control of 
 <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> (
 <italic>Nectriaceae</italic>), reaching 85% of the inhibition of radial mycelial growth with the addition of 0.4 µL mL
 <sup>−1</sup>, while geranial was much more effective in the control of 
 <italic>Sclerotium rolfsii,</italic> reaching 85% growth inhibition when 2 µL mL
 <sup>−1</sup> was used. This level of inhibition of the individual molecules of the 
 <italic>C. citratus</italic> EO as citral could suggest a possible synergistic effect of the 24 components identified in the EO on the growth control of 
 <italic>C. gloesporioides</italic> since 100% inhibition of mycelial growth was achieved in this study.
</p>
