<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>G. Bader et al. investigated the antifungal potential of 
 <italic>S. virgaurea</italic> extracts and reported that deacylated saponins tend to have a stronger effect on different 
 <italic>Candida</italic> species and 
 <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> than the corresponding mixture of ester saponins, and among the deacylated saponins, the bidesmosides had stronger activity than monodesmosides [
 <xref rid="B9-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B149-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>]. 
 <italic>S. Pepeljnjak</italic> et al. (1998) claimed antimycotic activity on several dermatophyte species (
 <italic>Trichophyton mentagrophytes</italic>, 
 <italic>Microsporum gypseum</italic> and 
 <italic>Microsporum canis</italic>) for a hydroalcoholic extract (75%) [
 <xref rid="B150-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>], but the MIC values (between 9.7% and 50%) seem too high to support the claim for clinical purposes, the effect being modest at best. M. Chevalier et al. (2012) reported no inhibitory effect of an aqueous extract from 
 <italic>S. virgaurea</italic> on four strains of 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> on agar mediums or in liquid medium, but they found that it was able to inhibit the transition between yeast and hyphal growth, a significant inhibition of biofilm formation, as well as a decrease of pre-formed biofilms of 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>, an effect speculatively attributed to the saponin fraction of the extract [
 <xref rid="B72-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. This attribution seems reasonable considering the inherent surfactant properties of saponins, as well as their hemolytic and iron chelator qualities, iron being necessary for the growth and development of 
 <italic>Candida</italic> [
 <xref rid="B72-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B151-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>]. To confirm this, the same research group carried out a bioassay-guided fractionation that led to the isolation of six triterpene saponins (oleanane-type), of which four caused significant inhibition of 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> yeast-hyphal switch [
 <xref rid="B73-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. What is the clinical relevance of this effect only time will tell.
</p>
