<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Interestingly, at the genus level, 
 <italic class="italic">Akkermansia</italic> was identified as the only biomarker that inversely correlated with the obese phenotype and was enriched by puerarin treatment in HFD+PUE mice, but not obviously changed in NC+PUE mice in the current study, which may explain for the fact that puerarin did not alter the body mass of the control group (NC+PUE mice, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0218490.s005" class="xref">S5 Fig</xref>). In consistent, in NC+PUE mice, the inflammation cytokines, both pro- and anti-, were not further improved (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0218490.s004" class="xref">S4 Fig</xref>). So were the Treg marker Foxp3, as well as the epithelial integrity markers (Figs 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218490.g006" class="xref">6</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218490.g007" class="xref">7</xref>). These results suggested that puerarin had a limited effect on normal control mice. RT-qPCR revealed its identity as 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">muciniphila</italic>: the dominant species of 
 <italic class="italic">Akkermansia</italic> in the intestine. 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">muciniphila</italic> is a gram-negative anaerobic bacterium that degrades mucin and manifests no serious pathogenicity in the intestinal microecological system [
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. It stabilizes host immunity and intestinal homeostasis [
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">muciniphila</italic> administration counteracts diet-induced metabolic disorders and mucosal barrier dysfunction and was believed to be beneficial to both type I and type II diabetes conditions at least in animal models [
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>], and it has been recently used in the treatment of diabetes and obesity [
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. Notably, the suggested beneficial bacterial genus 
 <italic class="italic">Faecalibacterium</italic> that was enriched upon oral administration of Gegen Qinlian Decoction, which alleviated type 2 diabetes mellitus [
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>] was not enriched in our study. This finding suggests that puerarin and Gegen Qinlian Decoction may have different effects on dysbiosis.
</p>
