<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Red imported fire ants, 
 <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic> Buren (hereafter, fire ants), are a significant threat to public health and a danger to livestock, pets and wildlife due to their venomous stings. Fire ants are also a significant agricultural pest because they can damage many crops [
 <xref rid="B1-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. As one of the worst invasive species, fire ants, which are originally from South America, have been introduced into many countries and regions and have become an important global pest [
 <xref rid="B2-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Synthetic insecticides continue to be a common tool for managing fire ants. Some of synthetic insecticides are structurally adapted from natural toxins; however, the modified synthetic versions were often preferred by manufacturers for several possible reasons including (1) natural toxins are often not suitable to be directly used as an insecticide due to their physiochemical properties, (2) structural complexity of the natural toxins often makes their synthesis economically infeasible, (3) alteration of natural toxins often improve their efficacy, and (4) intellectual property rights of synthetic insecticides are easier to obtain and defend than the natural toxins [
 <xref rid="B3-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. However, due to the ever-increasing concern over the negative impact of synthetic insecticides on public health and the environment, there is a growing desire to use more toxicological benign and environmentally friendly products and methods in pest management. Fire ant management is no exception. In addition to biological control [
 <xref rid="B4-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], physical and cultural practices [
 <xref rid="B5-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], and semiochemicals [
 <xref rid="B8-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], natural products continue to be one of the most attractive sources of alternatives.
</p>
