<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A greater percentage of people in tropical and sub-tropical regions rely on herbal medicine to cure various diseases and infections. Therefore, natural products could be one of the major sources for the development of antiviral drugs. About 80% of the population in developing countries, especially in Asia and Africa, use natural products from plants for their primary healthcare [
 <xref rid="B41-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Plant extracts from different plant parts (stem, root, leaves, seeds, fruits, and flowers) [
 <xref rid="B42-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], phytoconstituents (isolated compounds), nutraceuticals, and dietary supplements have been extensively used in treating a wide range of infectious and non-infectious diseases. They have also become the main sources of tested material in the development of several drugs including antiviral drugs based on ethnomedicinal practices [
 <xref rid="B43-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. According to the WHO, 25% of the commonly used drugs contain compounds that are purified from plants [
 <xref rid="B44-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Due to many harmful side effects of synthetic drugs and increased microorganism resistance to standard antimicrobial therapy, alternative treatments from traditional herbal medicines have been widely explored [
 <xref rid="B45-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Several medicinal plants have been reported to possess significant antiviral properties at different stages of viral growth [
 <xref rid="B46-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] and many have been used for treating viral infections, both in humans and animals including DENV infection [
 <xref rid="B48-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Moreover, many phytoconstituents have been suggested to be potential inhibitors of SARS-CoV through in silico studies [
 <xref rid="B51-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and molecular docking/modeling [
 <xref rid="B52-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. The aim of this article is therefore to provide a concise review on the potential medicinal plants for the treatment of DENV infection and SARS-CoV by providing more insights on the role of natural remedies such as medicinal plants and pure bioactive metabolites on the development and advancement of anti-DENV and anti-SARS-CoV drugs.
</p>
