<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bacterial growth in gilthead seabream mucus was evaluated for both dietary groups, control and phytogenic-supplemented diets, using two pathogenic fish bacteria, 
 <italic>V. anguillarum</italic> and 
 <italic>P. anguilliseptica</italic>, as well as a non-pathogenic fish bacterium, 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>. Our study revealed that the tested feed additive reduced bacteria growth capacity, suggesting an enhanced skin mucus inhibitory capacity against both 
 <italic>V. anguillarum</italic> and 
 <italic>P. anguilliseptica</italic>. The chosen pathogenic bacteria are widely recognized as disease causing agents in several fish species (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>), including gilthead seabream (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>). The observed reduced growth capacity of 
 <italic>V. anguillarum</italic> in the skin mucus of gilthead seabream fed the phytogenic-supplemented diet is especially relevant because of the evidence that 
 <italic>Vibrio</italic> strains exhibit a chemotactic response to mucus (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). In the last years, disease records indicate that 
 <italic>Vibrio</italic> spp. infections are the most common bacterial infections in gilthead seabream, mostly reported during the hatchery phase (
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>). Besides, 
 <italic>P. anguilliseptica</italic> is one of the main agents responsible for outbreaks associated with “winter disease” in gilthead seabream farming, being considered a more opportunistic pathogen whose infections in gilthead seabream usually occur when fish are under environmental stress (
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>). The different growth curves behavior of 
 <italic>V. anguillarum</italic> and 
 <italic>P. anguilliseptica</italic> in gilthead seabream mucus may be attributed to different virulence of pathogenic bacteria, differences in chemotaxis to skin mucus and adherence capacity.
</p>
