<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>From a physiological perspective, bacterial pathogens such 
 <italic>V. anguillarum</italic> are able to elicit strong cortisol-mediated stress responses when they adhere to the mucosal surface (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). For this reason, in this current study we also measured classic skin mucus stress biomarkers in order to establish a correlation between the gene expression profile, antibacterial response and the fish physiological status. Therefore, only cortisol was observed to be significantly reduced in fish fed the phytogenic-supplemented diet. Although the exact mechanisms involved in cortisol exudation through fish mucus are still unclear, cortisol is the main glucocorticoid and the final product of the HPI axis response to stress, varying considerably among species and according to the duration and severity of the stressor (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>). Cortisol decrease also favors the fish local mucosal immunity, promoting more effective defense responses against pathogens (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>). Besides the hypothesized decrease in skin pathogenic bacteria and its potential impact on cortisol-induced responses, and 
 <italic>vice versa</italic>, several phytogenic active substances have been reported to have sedative properties in fish (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>). For instance, garlic powder inclusion in common carp diet (0.5, 1, and 1.5%) decreased plasma cortisol and glucose levels, mitigating ammonia stress-induced effects (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>). Similar results were obtained in rainbow trout fed 3% garlic powder supplemented diets (
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>). Accordingly, the dietary supplementation of a similar additive containing garlic and Labiatae plant essential oils (0.02% inclusion) reduced significantly plasma cortisol levels in European seabass (
 <italic>Dicentrarchus labrax</italic>) challenged by confinement (
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>). Although the diet effect on fish stress response is usually evaluated in blood, a positive correlation between cortisol levels on plasma and fish mucus was demonstrated (
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>) including for gilthead seabream (
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>). Therefore, the observed decrease in mucus cortisol may suggest a decrease in the allostatic load due to the properties of the phytogenics used in this current study and/or as a consequence of the promotion of the non-specific innate immunity, although these two hypotheses are not mutually excluding.
</p>
