<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Fish SALT is characterized by both humoral and cellular components which intimately communicate to mount an immune response in which both innate and adaptive defense mechanisms are involved (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). For instance, the Interferon Related Developmental Regulator 1 (
 <italic>ifrd1</italic>) was up-regulated by the functional diet. 
 <italic>Ifrd1</italic> gene encodes a protein related to interferon family. In fish is widely recognized by its involvement in the innate immune antiviral response (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>), while it is also highly expressed in differentiating neutrophils, playing an important role in neutrophils effector function (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). An increase of 
 <italic>ifrd1</italic> transcripts was observed in the skin of zebrafish (
 <italic>Danio rerio</italic>) infected by 
 <italic>Aeromonas hydrophila</italic> (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>), whereas its up-regulation was also related to its role in the immediate response of the fish immune system to stress (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Moreover, transcripts of the Complement Factor H (
 <italic>cfh</italic>) increased in the skin of gilthead seabream fed the phytogenic-supplemented diet. CFH, a major regulator of the complement system, is essential for directing the complement system toward pathogen-related infections, since its transcription is induced by lipopolysaccharide (LPS) (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), whereas it increases the contact between neutrophils and pathogens, increasing cell's phagocytosis capacity and antimicrobial activity (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). CFH is also reputed for protecting host cells and tissues from the self-innate immunity (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). This occurs due to the interaction of the factor H with the C3 convertase and the C3b component (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Although CFH is predominantly expressed in the liver compared to other tissues and organs like the muscle, intestine, fins, eyes, and gills (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), present data indicate that the skin may also play a relevant role in the regulation of the alternative pathway of complement in skin secretions. This data is in agreement with different studies that have identified several complement factors in fish skin mucus secretions for several species (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>), including gilthead seabream (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).
</p>
