<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Cara et al. showed that enrichment of a high-fat meal with fibers from cereals, i.e., 10 g oat bran, wheat fibers or 4.2 g wheat germ, led to a decreased postprandial serum TG concentration in 6 healthy male adults compared to a low-fiber control meal, while only wheat fibers led to a decrease in postprandial CM-TG concentration. Rice bran did not have any effect on postprandial TG concentration. All fiber sources led to a decrease in postprandial CM-cholesterol concentration [
 <xref rid="B124-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">124</xref>]. In another study involving six ileostomized subjects, oat bran added to a test meal (43.8 g fat) was shown to elicit a 37% reduction in postprandial CM-TG concentration and a 43% reduction in postprandial CM-cholesterol concentration compared to a low fiber test meal, although the limited sample size did not allow for these differences to reach statistical significance [
 <xref rid="B125-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">125</xref>]. This was accompanied by an increase in ileum excretion of fat and cholesterol. Dubois et al. observed that the addition of 10 g pea or soybean fibers to a high-fat meal did not result in a decrease in postprandial TG concentration in six healthy male adults but both fibers led to a decrease in CM-cholesterol and -phospholipid concentrations [
 <xref rid="B126-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">126</xref>]. However, Sandstrom et al. showed that consumption of pea fibers by eight healthy adults in two consecutive meals (containing 7.4 g and 9.3 g fibers respectively) resulted in a reduction in CM-TG and intermediate-density lipoprotein-TG concentrations compared to a low-fiber meal [
 <xref rid="B127-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">127</xref>]. The meals provided in this study had less fat (19 and 43 g), and hence more carbohydrates, than those used by Dubois et al. (70 g), which could partly explain the discrepancies between the two studies.
</p>
