<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Several authors have reported that NTAP treatment of water and other aqueous solutions causes an increase in both their electrical conductivity and oxidation-reduction potential (Tian et al., 
 <xref rid="B122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>; Xu et al., 
 <xref rid="B127" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). In addition, several studies have detected through various analytical techniques the presence of reactive oxygen species and reactive nitrogen species in plasma treated water (Ryu et al., 
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Surowsky et al., 
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; Ercan et al., 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). However, apart from the presence of these highly reactive species, the rapid acidification that NTAP treatment causes in non-buffered solutions, due to the dissociation of water and the formation of nitric acid and nitrous acid if nitrogen is available, is also believed to be responsible for the inactivation capacity of NTAP in liquid media. Several authors (Rowan et al., 
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>; Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Na誰tali et al., 
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Ryu et al., 
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Ma et al., 
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) have shown that the pH of plasma treated water decreases gradually with treatment time up to values close to pH 3.0. This same behavior has been observed in non-buffered saline solutions (Oehmigen et al., 
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Ryu et al., 
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Ziuzina et al., 
 <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>), which would justify the greater antimicrobial effectiveness of NTAP in these media as compared to that observed in media containing substances with buffering capacity (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Na誰tali et al., 
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Ryu et al., 
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Ziuzina et al., 
 <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). However, several authors have observed that the level of microbial inactivation attained in NTAP treated media (reaching ~pH 3.0) is much higher than that observed for media acidified at pH 3.0 with different acidulants (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Na誰tali et al., 
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Ercan et al., 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). In order to explain this behavior, several authors have speculated about the possibility that low pH values could contribute to the stabilization of some of the reactive species generated in plasmas (Yost and Joshi, 
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) or to the formation of new compounds with antimicrobial potential (Na誰tali et al., 
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). A possible synergistic effect of low pH and NTAP-derived reactive species on microbial inactivation has been also proposed (Oehmigen et al., 
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Sun et al., 
 <xref rid="B116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>).
</p>
