<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Regarding microbial inactivation on solid media, NTAP is a very efficient technology for surface decontamination of abiotic surfaces, such as stainless steels, various packaging materials, paper, glass and plastics of diverse nature (Muranyi et al., 
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>; Leipold et al., 
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Miao and Yun, 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Klämpfl et al., 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>; Patil et al., 
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; Butscher et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>; Gabriel et al., 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016b</xref>). In addition, it is also highly effective for surface decontamination of a wide variety of foods, such as fruits, vegetables, spices, nuts, cereal grains, seeds, seaweed, meat and meat products, eggs, egg products, cheese slices, and dried squid shreds (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). However, microbial survival on different solids is conditioned by surface characteristics, which will determine its possible heating during NTAP treatment, the degree of microbial adhesion, as well as the level of formation and/or adsorption of active species. In particular, surface roughness, porosity and topography are of special relevance (Song et al., 
 <xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Noriega et al., 
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). A large number of studies have demonstrated a great variability in NTAP effectiveness against both vegetative cells and bacterial spores when identical treatments were applied onto different surfaces (Yun et al., 
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Noriega et al., 
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Yong et al., 
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015a</xref>; Butscher et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). For example, Miao and Yun (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>) studied the inactivation of 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> on PET (polyethylene terephthalate), PVC (polytetrafluoroethylene) and PTFE (polytetrafluoroethylene-teflon), and obtained the greatest lethal effect on PET, while the lowest inactivation was found on PTFE. These authors attributed the observed differences to differences in surface wettability of the materials, which was higher for PET, followed by PVC and, finally, PTFE. Fernández et al. (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>) obtained 2.7 log reductions in 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. Typhimurium viability on polycarbonate filters after a 2 min NTAP treatment, while it took 15 min to reach 2.7; 1.8 and 0.9 log cycles of inactivation on lettuce, strawberries and cut potato, respectively. Similarly, Lee et al. (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>) and Butscher et al. (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>), comparing the effectiveness of NTAP for the inactivation of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">G. stearothermophilus</italic> on abiotic surfaces and foods, observed that the highest antimicrobial activities were obtained on abiotic surfaces, such as agar plates or polypropylene grains. In addition, it has also been demonstrated that the effectiveness of NTAP as a food decontamination technique varies among different foods. Thus, inactivation of 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> was more effective on tomato than on lettuce (Bermúdez-Aguirre et al., 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>) or strawberries (Ziuzina et al., 
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>), also being faster on carrots than on apples (Baier et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). For 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> a greater lethal effect was also observed on cheese slices than on ham (Song et al., 
 <xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>), on sliced ham than on chicken breast filets (Lee et al., 
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>), or on tomato than on strawberries (Ziuzina et al., 
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). These results show that food topography should be taken into account when designing effective NTAP treatments. Additionally, differences can be also attributed to the fact that bacteria could have been in the form of planktonic cultures on the surface, biofilms or internalized in the food tissues, and it is well-known that this can show a very important influence on the inactivation effectiveness of NTAP (Ziuzina et al., 
 <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015b</xref>; Berardinelli et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
