<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This Southeast Asian plant belongs to the family of 
 <italic>Saururaceae</italic>, which is traditionally used for the treatment of lung disorders such as cough, lung abscess, phlegm, and dyspnea. 
 <italic>Houttuynia cordata</italic> Thorn (HCT) is a Chinese herbal plant well-known for its potent effects in the treatment of pneumonia, refractory hemoptysis, and SARS-CoV-1 infection [
 <xref rid="B62-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. It has anti-inflammatory, anti-allergic, antioxidant and anticancer properties [
 <xref rid="B62-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. The bioactive compounds present in HCT are comprised of rutin, hyperin, isoquercitrin, quercetin, afzelin, reyoutrin, kalium sulfuricum, cordarine, decanoyl acetaldehyde, lauric aldehyde, myrcene, α-pinene, methyl nonyl ketone, d-limonene, linoleic acid, aspartic acid, palmitic acid, water-soluble polysaccharides, amino acids, vitamins, manganese, potassium, zinc, iron and copper [
 <xref rid="B64-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. During the SARS-CoV-1 infection, the leaves of this Chinese medicinal plant were used to treat patients and showed good efficacy against SARS-CoV-1 [
 <xref rid="B48-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Lau et al. conducted one experiment using HCT against SARS-CoV-1. Results showed that HCT can inhibit SARS-CoV-1 activity including an immunomodulatory effect [
 <xref rid="B63-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. However, the mode of action of HCT is to inhibit the 3CLpro activity of SARS-CoV-1 and obstruct the activity of RdRp [
 <xref rid="B63-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Hence, it can block the entry of the virus and impede viral replication [
 <xref rid="B63-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. This inhibitory mechanism makes HCT a good choice to be used against SARS-CoV-2 infections.
</p>
