<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The FatA and FatB enzymes are essential to maintain the necessary 
 <italic class="italic">de novo</italic> fatty acid flux from plastids to the endoplasmic reticulum. Based on its expression and the profile of fatty acid accumulation, FatA is the dominant thioesterase during the period of oil accumulation in sunflower seeds. The novel information available on the 3D structure of plant thioesterases allowed the 
 <italic class="italic">Ha</italic>FatA and 
 <italic class="italic">Ha</italic>FatB binding pockets to be modeled, indicating that the kinetic and structural differences of both enzymes are driven mainly by the residues that determine the interaction with the acyl moiety of the substrate, independent of the interaction with the ACP or the catalytic residues. Confocal microscopy showed that 
 <italic class="italic">Ha</italic>FatA is a soluble protein that is translocated to the stroma of the chloroplast in BY-2 tobacco cells. By contrast, the distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">Ha</italic>FatB was far less clear and it was affected by the experimental design. These results do not allow us to conclude whether this protein is localized in the stroma or membrane anchored. Nevertheless, the data obtained from the stromal and membrane plastidial fractions of sunflower seeds strongly suggest that the 
 <italic class="italic">Ha</italic>FatB protein is removal anchored to the membrane through its hydrophobic region. While we cannot be sure if the protein anchors to the thylakoid membrane or to the inner membrane of the plastid, it is clear that both thioesterases differ in their fatty acid selectivity and localization. These differences probably reflect how differential interactions with the soluble plastidial FAS I and FAS II, and soluble acyl-ACP desaturase, affect the export of the 
 <italic class="italic">de novo</italic> synthesized fatty acids in sunflower seeds, supporting the hypothesis of a different role of these enzymes within plant lipid metabolism.
</p>
