<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A slightly different set of mAbs, comprisingJIM4, JIM8, JIM13, JIM15, LM2, LM14, and MAC207, was used to investigate the distribution of the corresponding AGP epitopes during ISE from 
 <italic>C. erythraea</italic> leaf explants [
 <xref rid="B104-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. As discussed above, in this system, light induces simultaneous development of both somatic embryos and adventitious buds, whereas in darkness, only ISE occurs. Generally, in globular somatic embryos, a different distribution pattern of JIM4, JIM13, JIM15, LM2, and MAC207 epitopes was observed, while with the progression of SE, the number of detected AGPs decreased. When the explants are cultivated in darkness, the JIM4 epitope was strongly expressed from the earliest stages of SE: It localized in the epidermal and subepidermal cells which formed meristematic centers, in the embryogenic cells in meristematic calli, as well as in four-cell proembryo. During further proembryo development, strong expression was detected only in the extracellular matrix surrounding the proembryogenic nodule. At the globular stage, JIM4 epitopes were found in the cell walls of the protodermal cells, while at the early cotyledonary stage, the JIM4 fluorescence was moderate [
 <xref rid="B104-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. Even though this mAb was not exclusively present in embryogenic tissues, its expression in adventitious buds formed in the light was weak. In maize callus culture, JIM4 was as also an early marker of embryogenic competence [
 <xref rid="B98-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. A similar labeling pattern to JIM4 in globular somatic embryos was found for MAC207 since its strong signal was detected in the cell walls of protodermal cells [
 <xref rid="B104-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>], just as was seen in protodermal cells of the globular embryos developed from roots [
 <xref rid="B102-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>].The JIM13 epitope, which was not observed during SE from the root explants at all [
 <xref rid="B102-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>], showed an intense signal in the whole globular embryos developed from leaf explants in darkness but was not restricted only to the embryogenic tissues [
 <xref rid="B104-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. The expression of JIM13 decreased in late embryos. In adventitious buds developed in the light, this epitope was not detected. Strong JIM13 labeling was also found in the embryogenic sector during SE in peach palm, where it was associated with extracellular matrix surface network [
 <xref rid="B108-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. Likewise, high-intensity JIM15 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00070-f004">Figure 4</xref>c) and LM2 fluorescence were localized to the whole globular embryos, but not in later developmental stages. A strong LM2 signal was observed in the cell walls of meristematic cells from which somatic embryos develop and in cells of embryogenic swellings in 
 <italic>Trifolium nigrescens</italic> [
 <xref rid="B100-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. Both JIM15 and LM2 signals were also seen in developing adventitious buds, so they were not an exclusive feature of SE. Unlike other tested epitopes, which appeared early during ISE, the LM14 signal was not present in globular somatic embryos but was strong and evenly distributed throughout the longitudinal sections of the heart embryo. Finally, theJIM8 epitope was detected in the extracellular matrix, as well as in adventitious buds, but not in somatic embryos of any stage [
 <xref rid="B104-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>].
</p>
