<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In March 2017, a randomized, single-group interventional, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase I, first-time-in-human (FTIH) study (NCT03075410) to evaluate the safety, tolerability, and pharmacokinetics of single and repeated doses of 
 <bold>8</bold> in healthy participants (expected 
 <italic>n</italic> = 58) was launched in the UK [
 <xref rid="B73-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. The study was conducted in two parts, including part A (single dose, two cohorts, nine subjects/cohort) and part B (repeat dose, four cohorts, ten subjects/cohort). In part A, single doses (5 mg, 15 mg, 25 mg, or placebo) of 
 <bold>8</bold> were administered orally. In part B, repeat doses (5 mg, 15 mg, or placebo) of 
 <bold>8</bold> were administered orally once a day for 14 days. The increase in the absorption rate was proportional to the increase in both the single dose and 14-day repeat doses [
 <xref rid="B22-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Based on the PK parameters C
 <sub>max</sub> and AUC, accumulation with repeated administration increased approximately 2- to 3-fold, and food intake did not influence the PK parameters. Notably, 
 <bold>8</bold> was not easily metabolized in plasma, but approximately 90% of 
 <bold>8</bold> and 10% of deboronated metabolites by oxidation were detected in urine. Based on drug-related materials detected in urine, the absorbed amounts of 
 <bold>8</bold> from single (25 mg) and repeat (15 mg) dosing were at least 50% and 78%, respectively. From this phase I clinical study completed in August 2017, the safety and tolerability of 
 <bold>8</bold> was acquired after single and multiple doses with no reports of serious adverse events. Importantly, the results from the clinical laboratory, vital signs, electrocardiogram (ECG), and telemetry presented no cardiotoxicity concerns. Clinical trial simulations (CTS) were performed to predict the dose range of 
 <bold>8</bold> that produces the highest possible early bactericidal activity (EBA
 <sub>0–14</sub>) for the phase II clinical trial, and 10 to 15 mg was suggested to be the optimal dosage of 
 <bold>8</bold> for TB treatment.
</p>
