<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020" class="p">Among the different sources of natural antioxidants, walnuts (
 <italic class="italic">Juglans regia L.</italic> family 
 <italic class="italic">Juglandaceae</italic>) are rich in compounds with potent antioxidant and antibacterial activity such as tocopherols and polyphenols (gallic acid and ellagic acid), tannins and melatonin (
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tapsell, 2010</xref>). Production of walnuts is almost 1,500,000 Tons and the United States, China, Iran, Turkey and Ukraine are the main producers of walnut. Different parts of it such as kernel, leaves and septum have a significant antioxidant effects. It has been recognized that about 50 g of walnuts contains further entirety of phenolics than about 240 ml of apple juice or even a milk chocolate (43 g) (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Miraliakbari and Shahidi, 2008</xref>). Polyphenols have been recognized to be capable of disturbing the activities of enzymes concerned in the generation of reactive oxygen species, chelating transition metals (
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pereira et al., 2008</xref>). Besides antioxidant activity, numerous researches confirmed the antimicrobial activity of phenolic extracts such as walnut extract (
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sousa et al., 2006</xref>), making them a good option to synthetic preservatives. 
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ajaiyeoba and Fadare (2006)</xref> reported that African walnut has antibacterial and antifungal activities linked to phenolic compounds against 
 <italic class="italic">Staphyloccocus aureus</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic>), coliforms and molds. 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ajaiyeoba, Onocha, Nwozo, and Sama (2003)</xref> showed that the chloroform, methanol, hexane and ethyl acetate fractions of the kernel extract of walnut displayed good antimicrobial activities which were concentration-dependent. Generally, little information in the literature is connected to the augmented shelf life of butter using natural or synthetic antioxidants. 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Li et al. (2006)</xref> have confirmed the antimicrobial and antioxidant activity of walnut products, but information about the kernel septum membranes is almost inexistent.
</p>
