<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Conversely, the structural diversity of 
 <italic>Euphorbia</italic> triterpenoids has also been reported. The pharmacological activities of these triterpenoids have been associated with the important functional groups on the ring. Indeed, the various pharmacological activities reported for some pentacyclic triterpenoids like anticancer, have been attributed to the presence of the hydroxyl group. This was evident by racemosol, a polyhydroxy triterpenoid that showed significant anticancer activities against human cancer cells [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-04019" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Other studies have further shown that the activities of hydroxylated pentacyclic triterpenoids are significantly affected by the number of hydroxyl groups contained in ring A. This was observed on chemically modified 18β-Glycyrrhetinic acid, an oleanane-type triterpene [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-04019" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Furthermore, a highly hydroxylated and bioactive pentacyclic triterpenoid named 1β, 2α, 3β, 16β, 19β,)-1, 2, 3, 16, 19,pentahydroxyolean-12-en-28-oic acid from 
 <italic>E. sieboldiana</italic> exhibited modest anticancer activities against human liver carcinoma (HepG2) cells, human cervical cancer cells (HT-3), and normal human carcinoma (HeLa) cells [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-04019" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The observed anticancer activities of this triterpenoid were attributed to the presence of tetra hydroxyl groups in ring A [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-04019" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Plants derived terpenes have further been associated with therapeutic effects like anticancer and anti-inflammatory [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-04019" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], as well as the ability to overcome drug resistance, and cancer migration [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-04019" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. This is due to their ability to block the NF-κB activation, induce apoptosis, and inhibit proliferation as exhibited by a reduced lantadene A triterpenoid [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-04019" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and rosamultic acid against human carcinoma [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-04019" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Undeniably, plants are known to biosynthesize complex and diverse triterpenes to protect them against predators like herbivores and against pathogens and pests [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-04019" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
