<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Diarylureas with antiparasitic activity are summarized in 
 <xref rid="antibiotics-10-00092-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. TCC and several analogues have been studied in schistosomiasis. This disease, also called bilharzia, is one of the most dramatic parasitic diseases in tropical countries and remains a serious public health problem in the tropics and subtropics, affecting one billion people, with 250 million infected in 74 countries [
 <xref rid="B40-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. It is considered one of the most widespread infectious diseases among the WHO-prioritized 17 neglected tropical diseases (NTDs) [
 <xref rid="B41-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Schistosomiasis is caused by the trematode worms of the genus 
 <italic>Schistosoma</italic> (Platyhelminthes Trematoda). The clinically most relevant species are 
 <italic>Schistosoma japonicum</italic>, 
 <italic>S. haematobium</italic>, and 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> [
 <xref rid="B42-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. 
 <italic>S. japonicum</italic> is responsible for intestinal and hepatosplenic schistosomiasis in China, the Philippines, and Indonesia; 
 <italic>S. haematobium</italic> determines urogenital schistosomiasis in Africa and in some countries of the Arabian Peninsula (it has also recently emerged on the French island of Corsica); 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> causes intestinal and hepatic disease in Africa, the Arabian Peninsula, and Latin America [
 <xref rid="B43-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Praziquantel (PZQ) discovered in the 1970s, is the only drug available for the treatment of schistosomiasis [
 <xref rid="B44-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]; no schistosomiasis vaccines have been accepted for public use yet [
 <xref rid="B45-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Despite many benefits of PZQ, most notably its high efficacy and excellent tolerability, the drug has important disadvantages, above all its inefficacy against juvenile schistosomes. Furthermore, the increasing administration of PZQ to millions of people annually results in high drug pressure, and thus drug-resistant parasites are likely to evolve. The Medicines for Malaria Venture (MMV) Malaria Box is a collection of over 400 compounds including families of structures identified in phenotypic screens of pharmaceutical and academic libraries against the 
 <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> malaria parasite [
 <xref rid="B46-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The antischistosomal properties of some of these compounds with confirmed in vitro activity against 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> were studied. Diarylurea MMV665852, a structural analog of TCC, which showed activity against 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> 3D7, was also evaluated against 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> in vitro on newly transformed schistosomula (NTS) and adult 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> worms and showed IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 4.7 and 0.8 µM, respectively. All the compounds were then tested in vivo using the chronic 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> mouse model. The compound MMV665852 showed the highest in vivo activity, given that treatment of 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> infected mice with a single oral 400 mg/kg dose of MMV665852 reduced worm burden by 52.5% [
 <xref rid="B47-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Then, a search for structures similar to that of MMV665852, using a Tanimoto-Rogers similarity coefficient of 0.85 as the cutoff, identified 46 compounds, 13 of which were diarylureas. All compounds were first tested in vitro on NTS and adult 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> worms. MMV665852, TCC and 
 <bold>1</bold> showed IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 4.7, 0.07, and 1.3 µM, respectively against NTS; TCC and 
 <bold>1</bold> showed IC
 <sub>90</sub> of 0.3 and 2.8 µM, respectively, against NTS. TCC, compounds 
 <bold>1</bold> and 
 <bold>2</bold>, tested at 33.3 µM, showed high in vitro activity against adult 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic>, showing IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 0.4, 0.7 and 0.2 µM, and IC
 <sub>90</sub> of 1.4, 2.2 and 0.8 µM, respectively, after a 72-h incubation period. Interestingly, compounds 
 <bold>3</bold> and 
 <bold>4</bold> were found to be schistosomicidal against the adult 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> 72 h post incubation, with calculated IC
 <sub>50</sub> values are of 3.6 and 7.0 µM, respectively [
 <xref rid="B48-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. In another work, in order to enlarge the structure-activity relationships for compounds analogues of MMV665852, a series of diarylureas was studied in vitro against the juvenile 
 <italic>S. japonicum</italic>. Compounds 
 <bold>5</bold> and 
 <bold>6</bold>, tested at 32 μM, killed the juvenile worms within 72 h, and exhibited a higher activity than the positive control MMV665852 (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 2.5 and 2.8 μM versus 4.4 μM of MMV665852). IC
 <sub>50</sub> values against the adult worms were lower than those for juvenile worms (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 1.5 and 2.2 μM versus 2.2 μM of MMV665852) [
 <xref rid="B49-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. However, compound 
 <bold>6</bold> had been described previously in the literature, as an insecticide known to be highly toxic to fish and invertebrates, named flucofuron [
 <xref rid="B50-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Recent studies also address it as a toxicant [
 <xref rid="B52-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Wu et al. studied twenty diarylureas and found that compound 
 <bold>7</bold> had antischistosomal activity against 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> higher than that of MMV66558, by killing the NTS at a concentration of 10 µM. This compound killed both NTS and adult 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 0.15 and 0.19 µM, respectively. In this paper, studies regarding the relationships existing between lipophilicity and metabolic stability were also carried out. The authors found that there were no clear relationships between lipophilicity and metabolic stability. Compound 
 <bold>7</bold> had the best in vivo antischistosomal activity, with worm burden reduction value of 40% following administration of single 100 mg/kg oral doses [
 <xref rid="B19-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In the last years, protein kinase inhibitors were used as starting points for drug discovery in studies on helminth growth and development. Sorafenib and its structurally related analogue regorafenib were tested in vitro against the larval and adult stage of 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> and they were lethal to NTS within 24 h (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 4.1 and 1.1 µM, respectively, for sorafenib; IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 6.9 and 1.0 µM, respectively for regorafenib). Sorafenib caused the death of all adults, at 33.3 μM, within 24 h [
 <xref rid="B54-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].
</p>
