<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec016" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The activity of 
  <span class="italic">EgFAD8</span> promoter response to growth environment treatments
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Promoter prediction analysis suggested that the 
  <span class="italic">EgFAD8</span> promoter contained some stress-responsive elements, including light-responsive elements. Therefore, further work was carried out to investigate whether it was induced under various stress conditions, such as cold and dark. The 
  <span class="italic">ProEgFAD8</span>::
  <span class="italic">GUS</span> transgenic Arabidopsis T3 lines were cultivated at 15°C and in the dark, respectively, with other conditions are the same with the control. The GUS activity of transgenic plants under the darkness or low temperature treatment was no obvious difference with that of the control after 24 hours treatment (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196693.g004" href="#pone.0196693.g004">Fig 4</a>). However, 48 hours treatment later, the GUS activity of the transgenic plants under the darkness treatment showed obvious increase by 26% when compared with that of the control, and the transgenic plants under the low temperature treatment exhibited the extraordinarily significant increase of GUS activity by about 14-fold comparing with the control (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196693.g004" href="#pone.0196693.g004">Fig 4</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0196693.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0196693.g004</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Quantification of GUS activity in leaves of transgenic Arabidopsis transformed with 
    <span class="italic">ProEgFAD8</span>::
    <span class="italic">GUS</span> under the treatment of darkness or low temperature (15°C) for 24h and 48h.
   </div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0196693.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
