<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent experiments have shown that the small molecules E-64d and PC-0626568 (SID26681509) can block the cathepsin L-dependent cell entry of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Note that cathepsin L is one of 11 cysteine cathepsin proteases encoded by the human genome, and the cathepsins share a high sequence similarity to papain, a non-specific plant protease [
 <xref rid="B86-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. E64-d is a broad spectrum inhibitor which can inhibit proteases cathepsins B, H, L and calpain, while PC-0626568 is a specific inhibitor of cathepsin L [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Moreover, a recent study [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] used the specific inhibitor PC-0626568 of cathepsin L to conclude that cathepsin L rather than cathepsin B is important for cell entry of SARS-CoV-2. As both cathepsin L and cathepsin B are expressed in several mammalian tissues, it is important to design specific inhibitors of cathepsin L [
 <xref rid="B75-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>] to avoid any off-target toxicity. Along with the above-mentioned two inhibitors of cathepsin L, we have also considered the co-crystallized inhibitor GH4 present in the crystal structure of cathepsin L (PDB 5MQY) as another reference inhibitor of cathepsin L. We remark that while recent experiments [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] have shown that E-64d and PC-0626568 can block the cathepsin L-dependent cell entry of SARS-CoV-2, similar experimental data specific to SARS-CoV-2 infection is lacking for cathepsin L inhibitor GH4. By docking these—three known inhibitors to cathepsin L using AutoDock Vina with exhaustiveness set at 50, the predicted binding energies of E-64d, PC-0626568 and GH4 were found to be −5.0 kcal/mol, −8.0 kcal/mol and −6.3 kcal/mol, respectively. Notably, the docked binding energies are in line with known specificity of E-64d and PC-0626568 to cathepsin L. 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-molecules-25-03822">Supplementary Figure S6c–e</xref> show the best docked poses of PC-0626568, E-64d and GH4 with cathepsin L. It is seen that both E-64d and PC-0626568 form hydrogen bonds with both catalytic residues C25 and H163. Based on above observations, we decided on a stringent criteria of docked binding energy ≤−8.0 kcal/mol for screened ligands to be identified as potential inhibitors of cathepsin L. We have also compared the docked pose of GH4 obtained from AutoDock Vina with the pose of GH4 in the co-crystallized structure of cathepsin L, and the RMSD between the heavy atoms in the two poses was found to be 0.786 Å. 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-molecules-25-03822">Supplementary Figure S7</xref> shows the superimposed structures of the docked pose of GH4 from AutoDock Vina and the pose of GH4 in the co-crystallized structure of cathepsin L. Apart from PC-0626568 and E-64d, seven other cathepsin-L inhibitors namely, dec-RVKR-CMK, K11777, small molecule 5705213, MDL28170, SSAA09E1, EST and oxocarbazate, have been reported in literature to exhibit ant-coronavirus activity [
 <xref rid="B87-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>].
</p>
