<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Hydnora</italic> species are underground holoparasitic herbs and their rhizomes are attached to the host. The rhizomes are 1 cm wide, 4–5 angled, terete, and sometimes flattened. The periderm is well developed, brick-red, apart from the tip of the rhizome. Fresh rhizomes are pink to flesh-red with gummy exudate, which is very bitter and severe. The whole rhizome is enclosed with warty outgrowths of haustoria which can be spread sometimes regularly up to 0.8 mm long or unevenly, and less than 0.5 mm long, except at the tip. The rhizomes are covered with latent and active outgrowths in groups of 2–4. Flowers are 3, 4, or 5 merous. The floral envelope is clear and rests on the ground; sometimes they are not reflexed, and they open flowers by separating the floral envelope. Flowers vary in size from 5 to 25 cm depending on the distance of the rhizome from the ground and pedicel (4–9 cm). The ovary is inferior, unilocular, and highly enfolded pendant placentae. The stigma is sessile with distinctive indentations on the surface. Stamens are attached at the base, and anthers are 2.5–3 × 2–2.5 cm in length. Pollen adhering to anthers is very sticky. The floral envelope is 6–8 cm; some species have “bait bodies” in between the internal margin of the envelopes (lobes) while some contain well-developed petals that are concave in shape. The fruits are fleshy, globose, 10–15 cm wide, with many seeds. The mature pedicel is very short and easily disconnected from the rhizome. The outer skin is scaly, and the internal layer is white. The placenta is similar to the internal layer of the pericarp in texture. Seeds are brown, very hard, irregularly shaped, and oblong to globose [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Their pollination mechanism generally follows the same floral phenology as that of 
 <italic>H. africana</italic> and 
 <italic>H. esculenta</italic> [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
</p>
