<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The taxonomic placement of the Hydnoraceae family is unresolved and studies have classified it differently using a molecular approach. Regardless of them lacking some morphological features (leaves), the Hydnoraceae family was grouped within Rafflesiales [
 <xref rid="B41-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Another study compared Hydnorales and Rafflesiales to the Aristolochiaceae family [
 <xref rid="B42-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Based on floral characteristics, geographic distributions, and embryology, Hydnoraceae was connected to the Annonaceae and Mistrastemonaceae families [
 <xref rid="B43-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Using the molecular approach, the Hydnoraceae family was grouped in Piperales under the Aristolochiaceae family but did not include Asaroideae [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The relationship of families in order Piperales is unresolved in the Angiosperm phylogeny group classification (APG III) system [
 <xref rid="B44-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Some research studies support the placement of Hydnoraceae within the Aristolochiaceae family [
 <xref rid="B45-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. This has contributed to the placement of Hydnoraceae within Aristolochiaceae due to their past paraphyly APG IV [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. However, a recent study grouped the Hydnoraceae family as a sister group to the Winteraceae family (
 <italic>Drimys granadensis</italic>) because of the long branching problem [
 <xref rid="B45-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Another study indicated that the Hydnoraceae family formed a monophyletic clade with a low bootstrap support value of 13%, which cannot justify the grouping of Hydnoraceae [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. To date, only 
 <italic>H. visseri</italic> and 
 <italic>H. abyssinica</italic> complete genomes have been studied in this genus (5, Mkala et al. in press). In genus 
 <italic>Prosopanche</italic>, only the 
 <italic>Prosopanche americana</italic> genome has been documented [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. More studies on the genomes of the remaining species need to be analyzed. This will enable researchers to match particular characteristics observed in plants to their underlying genetic features.
</p>
