<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Countryside areas that are popular with recreationists face many environmental pressures as a result of human activities. The evidence reviewed suggests that recreationists can be instrumental through their outdoor activities in spreading unwanted species that can be damaging to environments such as forests (for a review, see [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]). Also, forests on public land open to recreation have been found to have a higher prevalence of 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> than do forests on private lands that are not open for public recreation [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Several studies demonstrate the role of recreation and tourism in spreading pathogens [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C14" ref-type="bibr">14–18</xref>], non-native species [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C19" ref-type="bibr">19–21</xref>], plant seeds [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and weeds [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Mechanisms by which recreational activities can introduce harmful species or pathogens into forests include footwear, vehicles and bicycle tyres [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. This applies broadly across ecosystems and is found to be the case in forest, other terrestrial, freshwater and marine environments, including the Antarctic [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. For example, hikers are believed to have spread the 
 <italic>P. cinnamomi</italic> spores on boots and camping equipment in some parts of Australia, and to change environmental conditions in ways that increase plant stress [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> has been found to be more common in soil on hiking trails in California than in soil from areas away from trails where the vegetation is undisturbed [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Studies have suggested that cleaning boots and equipment before arriving at a countryside destination and again before leaving could reduce the risks of dispersal by recreationists [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Overall, the evidence reveals that unintentional pathogen dispersal by recreationists including hikers is likely, thus their engagement in the biosecurity actions such as cleaning boots and other equipment as highlighted by Pickering and Mount [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] is important to protect against future dispersal of tree diseases into new areas.
</p>
