<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Herbs and spices, grown wildly in various regions of the world have been used for culinary and medicinal purposes since ancient times. 
  <span class="italic">Anethum sowa</span> L. (Bengali-Shulfa) belonging to the family 
  <span class="italic">Apiaceae</span> (
  <span class="italic">Umbelliferae</span>), comes under genus 
  <span class="italic">Anethum</span> and it is an annual and winter spice crop in Bangladesh. It is mostly grown in the northern part of Bangladesh. A variant called Indian dill or sowa (
  <span class="italic">Anethum sowa</span> Roxb.) is largely cultivated in Bangladesh, India, Egypt and Japan. Indigenous people consume it as a spice for a flavouring agent in food preparation. The herb grows ordinarily 2–2.5 ft. in height with small feathery leaves, tapped and branched roots [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>]. The chemical composition of the essential oil of the two chemotypes i.e. European dill (
  <span class="italic">Anethum graveolens</span> L.) and Indian dill (
  <span class="italic">Anethum sowa</span> L.) are differentiated mainly by the apiol and carvone content. 
  <span class="italic">Anethum sowa</span> is rich in apiol whereas 
  <span class="italic">Anethum graveolens</span> is rich in carvone. The typical flavor of dill herb oil is due to α-phellandrene, limonene and dill ether (anethofuran) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. The green herb, seeds and its roots are used as folkloric medicine e.g. aromatic, carminative especially useful in the treatment of flatulence, colic and hiccups of infants and children [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>]. Recently, it has been reported that seed essential oils are the potential source of antioxidant and also have antimicrobial and antispasmodic properties [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to commercial interest, extensive studies have been done on dill seed (fruit) and weed (herb) essential oil for its sensory qualities, physical and chemical composition. Very few reports [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>] have been found in the essential oil and mineral content of the root part of 
  <span class="italic">Anethum graveolens</span> L (Dill) species to the best of our knowledge. But the chemical composition and pharmacological studies of 
  <span class="italic">Anethum sowa</span> root are still to the unveiled. Therefore, the aims of this study were to elucidate the chemical composition as well as its pharmacological activities of the essential oil, elemental composition, amino acid, fatty acid profile and thermal behavior of its root part. This information can be helpful in the formulation of various herbal forms of medicines.
 </p>
</sec>
