<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In certain world populations where staples like wheat, maize and rice are the major or the only source of nutrition, PA as antinutritional factor attracts higher attention because the reduced bioavailability of minerals complexed by it can lead to significant deficiencies in humans (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>). Also, Arendt et al. (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>) reported that gluten free flours/ingredients have variable concentrations of phytate, i.e., rice, 0.12%; pearl millet, 0.25%; amaranth, 0.47%; teff, 0.70%; lupin, 0.77%; corn, 0.92%; oats,1.13%; quinoa, 1.18%; and soybean, 1.33%. Micronutrient deficiencies affect more than half of the world population, especially in developing countries where plants are the major source of food. Thus, improving the nutritional value of such type of food will improve the nutritional status of entire population (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>). High content of phytates in the diet, especially of infants, children, elderly, and people in clinical situations, can significantly decrease the retention of calcium, iron and zinc (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>). Reddy et al. (
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>) reported that PA also is present in the diets of non-ruminant animals, representing 50–80% of total phosphorus content in cereal grains and legumes frequently used in livestock animal feeds. However, phytate phosphorus present in food and feed has low bioavailability and is underutilized due to the lack or low levels of gastrointestinal phytases in monogastric animals (swine, poultry, and fishes) (
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">97</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">98</xref>). In order to meet the phosphorus requirements in these animals, inorganic phosphorus has to be added to the animal feedstuff as an additional nutrient, which in turn increases the feed cost and phosphorus pollution (
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>). Undigested phytate and unabsorbed inorganic phosphate are excreted to a large extent (70%) and remains in manure and can lead to its accumulation in the soil and waters. This fact can generate the eutrophication of water, a serious phosphorus pollution problem in areas of intensive livestock production. The eutrophication of water surfaces can then generate cyanobacterial blooms, hypoxia and death of aquatic animals and nitrous oxide production, a potential green- house gas producing a severe environmental problem (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>).
</p>
