<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mushrooms native to North America have been explored for anti-proliferative activity against cancer cell lines. For instance, out of 29 species of mushrooms examined from north-central BC [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and Haida Gwaii, BC [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], 27 species exhibited anti-proliferative activity. Sixteen out of the 27 species (59%) had their anti-proliferative activity reported for the first time [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. These species include 
 <italic>Amanita augusta, Cantharellus cibarius, Chroogomphus tomentosus, Guepinia helvelloides, Gyromitra esculenta, Hydnellum</italic> sp., 
 <italic>Inocybe</italic> sp., 
 <italic>Laetiporus conifericola, Leucocybe connata, Phellodon atratus, Pleurotus ostreatus, Ramaria cystidiophora, Russula paludosa, Trichaptum abietinum, Tricholomopsis rutilans</italic>, and 
 <italic>Tyromyces chioneus</italic>. It would be of interest to further investigate what the anti-proliferative compounds from these mushrooms are. Another study was conducted on 38 species of mushrooms collected from the greater Seattle area (WA, USA). Out of 38 species, aqueous extracts from three species were identified as anti-proliferative in human estrogen receptor negative (MDA-MB-231, BT-20) and estrogen receptor positive (MCF-7) breast cancer cells. These included 
 <italic>Coprinus comatus</italic>, 
 <italic>Coprinellus</italic> sp., and 
 <italic>Flammulina velutipes</italic> [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The anti-proliferative effects of these 3 species were compared with 5-fluorouracil, a known anticancer drug [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Elsewhere, the ethanol and water extracts of 
 <italic>Pleurotus tuber-regium</italic> from Washington State displayed anti-proliferative effects in HCT-116 colon and HeLa cervical cancer cell lines [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Although in most parts the identity of anti-proliferative compounds from the mushroom species described above remains unknown, there were detailed structural elucidation and mechanistic studies of both bioactive small molecules and polysaccharides isolated from selected species. For example, a growth-inhibitory polysaccharide GIPinv that caused growth inhibition in several cancer cell lines and induced apoptosis in HeLa cancer cells was isolated from 
 <italic>Paxillus involutus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. It has an IC50 of 0.05 mg/mL and 0.04 mg/mL against HeLa cells and MCF-7 cells respectively. In the future, GIPinv should be evaluated for its anticancer activity in animal models. Small molecules grifolin, neogrifolin and confluentin were found to be the major growth-inhibitory compounds in the ethanol extracts of 
 <italic>Albatrellus flettii</italic> [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. It was also discovered that confluentin can inhibit the RNA-binding function of the oncogenic protein insulin-like growth factor 2 mRNA-binding protein 1 (IMP1) [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. This is potentially a novel inhibitory pathway leading to the suppression of KRAS expression in human colon cancer cells. To determine the significance of this finding, it will be important to evaluate the inhibitory function of confluentin using in vivo models. Elsewhere, an exopolysaccharide isolated from 
 <italic>P. tuber-regium</italic> inhibited the growth of chronic myelogenous leukemia K562 cells [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Another example is orenalline, a small molecule isolated from 
 <italic>Cortinarius armillatus</italic> that inhibited renal carcinoma in a dose-dependent manner [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].
</p>
