<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Diterpenoid quinine metabolite tanshinones (tanshinone I, tanshinone IIA, tanshinone IIB, isotanshinone I, and cryptotanshinone), found in the roots of 
 <italic>Salvia</italic> spp., are considered to be potent anticancer, antiatherosclerosis, antihypertensive, and neuroprotective agents. Tanshinones’ antitumor mechanism involves the inhibition of DNA duplication, cell cycle arrest, regulation of oxidative stress, and reduction of the mitochondrial membrane potential and PTEN-mediated inhibition of the PI3K/AKT pathway to induce apoptosis. Tanshinone I inhibits tumor angiogenesis by the phosphorylation of STAT3 at Tyr705 and hypoxia-induced HIF-1α accumulation in neoplastic cells. The cardiovascular protective effect of tanshinones is exerted by the inhibition of myocardial apoptosis, cardiac fibrosis, atherosclerosis, oxidized low-density lipoprotein (ox-LDL) uptake, thrombin activation, and thrombosis. Tanshinones exhibit significant neuroprotective effects in various neurodegenerative diseases by selectively suppressing pro-inflammatory gene expression in activated microglia, protecting neurons from the neurotoxicity of Aβ, and down-regulating the expression of phosphorylated tau [
 <xref rid="B366-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">366</xref>]. Endophytic fungi 
 <italic>Phoma glomerata</italic> and 
 <italic>Alternaria</italic> sp. residing in the roots of 
 <italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic> produced tanshinones [
 <xref rid="B352-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">352</xref>,
 <xref rid="B353-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">353</xref>]. It has also been secreted by endophytic fungi from 
 <italic>Panex</italic> (
 <xref rid="microorganisms-09-00197-t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>). Interestingly, elicitors from the endophytic fungi 
 <italic>T. atroviride</italic> and 
 <italic>C. globosum</italic> promoted the biosynthesis of tanshinones via enhanced expression of related genes in hairy roots of 
 <italic>S. miltiorrhiza</italic> [
 <xref rid="B367-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">367</xref>,
 <xref rid="B368-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">368</xref>].
</p>
