<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Main Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par1">The drought conditions and the application of ABA reduce the photosynthetic activity, and the processes related to the transpiration of 
   <italic>Dracocephalum moldavica</italic> L. At the same time, the plant increases the production of phenolic compounds and essential oil as a response to stress conditions.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Abstract</title>
  <p id="Par2">In the semi-arid regions, drought stress is the most important environmental limitations for crop production. Abscisic acid (ABA) plays a crucial role in the reactions of plants towards environmental stress such as drought. Field experiments for two consecutive years in 2016 and 2017 were conducted to evaluate the effect of three watering regimes (well-watered, moderate and severe drought) and five exogenous ABA concentrations (0, 5, 10, 20 and 40 μM) on growth, photosynthesis, total phenolic and essential oil content of 
   <italic>Dracocephalum moldavica</italic> L. Without ABA application, the highest photosynthetic rate (6.1 μmol CO
   <sub>2</sub> m
   <sup>−2</sup> s
   <sup>−1</sup>) was obtained under well-watered condition and, moderate and severe drought stress decreased photosynthesis rate by 26.39% and 34.43%, respectively. Some growth parameters such as stem height, leaf area, leaf dry weight and biological yield were also reduced by drought stress. ABA application showed a decreasing trend in photosynthesis rate and mentioned plant growth parameters under all moisture regimes. The highest seed yield (1243.56 kg ha
   <sup>−1</sup>) was obtained under well-watered condition without ABA application. Increasing ABA concentration decreased seed yield in all moisture regimes. The highest total phenolic content (8.9 mg g
   <sup>−1</sup> FW) and essential oil yield (20.58 kg ha
   <sup>−1</sup>) were obtained from 20 and 5 μM ABA concentration, respectively, under moderate drought stress.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
