<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4" class="p">Cutaneous mosquito repellents (MR) are one means to reduce the frequency of mosquito bites. N,N-diethyl-meta-toluamide (DEET) is an effective mosquito repellant
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>
 </sup> but is cost prohibitive for rural sub-Saharan populations. Targeting indigenous plants as a source of mosquito repellents will stimulate local economies and at the same time protect the population. Odalo 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup> extracted and tested the topical repellency of essential oils indigenous to Kenya from 
 <italic class="italic">Conyza newii (Compositae)</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Plectranthus marrubioides (Lamiaceae)</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Lippia javanica (Verbenaceae)</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Tetradenia riparia (Lamiaceae)</italic>, as well as 
 <italic class="italic">Tarchonanthus camphoratus (Asteraceae)</italic>. The oils, under their experimental conditions (3 min, forearm exposure), repelled mosquitoes better than DEET. 
 <italic class="italic">N. cataria</italic>, commonly known as catnip or catmint, is a species of the Lamiaceae family. It is native to temperate and tropical zones in Asia and in Europe and is widely cultivated
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic class="italic">Nepeta cataria</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">N. cataria</italic>) has many uses in traditional medicine including treatment of chills, colds, constipation, headaches, infections, inflammations, rheumatism, sore throats, spasms, and stomach aches
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic class="italic">N. cataria</italic>’s essential oil possesses antibacterial and antimicrobial properties
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup>. Nepetalactone (NPL) is the major constituent of this oil
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. DEET, applied to the forearm, repelled 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes aegypti</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles quadrimaculatus</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles albimanus</italic> for 426 min, 96 min, and 87 min, respectively
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. A 25% volume fraction of DEET in ethanol repelled 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes aegypti</italic> for 8 h
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>. Whereas, Bernier found that a dose of 0.5 mg cm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> of DEET applied to a muslin cloth patch was active for 24 h. Catnip’s oil is a better spatial repellent than DEET and demonstrated effective topical repellency properties
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
