<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Steroid hormones, which are produced in various endocrine organs, easily cross the BBB because of their lipophilic nature [
 <xref rid="B51-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Circulating steroid hormones serve as precursors for the synthesis of neurosteroids, which are steroid hormones formed within the brain, as enzymes typically produced in steroidogenic tissues are also found in the nervous system [
 <xref rid="B53-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Neurosteroids can also be synthesized in the brain itself without the aid of peripheral resources. Neuroactive steroids modulate neuronal function by both genomic (as in classical intracellular steroid receptors) [
 <xref rid="B11-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and non-genomic rapid actions (as in ion channels and membrane receptors) [
 <xref rid="B13-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] in the brain. When zebrafish were treated with PTZ, an antagonist of the GABA
 <sub>A</sub> receptor, the levels of Prog and its metabolites 5α-dihydroProg and Allo-P were decreased (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-01285-f003">Figure 3</xref>D–F). Prog and its metabolites positively modulate GABA
 <sub>A</sub> receptors by putatively binding at distinct sites of the α subunit and at the α/β subunit interface [
 <xref rid="B55-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Allo-P has shown anticonvulsant activity in diverse preclinical models [
 <xref rid="B56-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>], and protected rats from chemoconvulsant-induced seizures in a model of refractory status epilepticus, where seizures are unremitting, in a dose-dependent manner [
 <xref rid="B60-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. The levels of Prog and its metabolites were increased by GM-90432 treatment, and co-treatment of GM-90432 and PTZ effectively restored these steroids to the levels of the control group (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-01285-f003">Figure 3</xref>D–F). The steroid hormone E2 inhibits N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA)-induced whole cell currents and NMDA-stimulated increase in intracellular free calcium, and protects against NMDA-induced neuronal death [
 <xref rid="B61-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Oxidative stress, and lipid peroxidation in particular, plays a significant role in neuronal death initiated by NMDA receptor activation [
 <xref rid="B62-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Neuroprotection via E2 is mediated by direct inhibition of NMDA-stimulated calcium entry. Furthermore, E2 is a potent antioxidant, and reduces the levels of free radicals [
 <xref rid="B64-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] and apoptosis via increased production of antiapoptotic proteins Bcl-2 and Bcl-xL [
 <xref rid="B65-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-ijms-22-01285" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The levels of E2 that were reduced upon exposure to PTZ were increased by GM-90432 co-treatment to the level of the control group (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-01285-f003">Figure 3</xref>A). These results indicate that GM-90432 reduces PTZ-induced neurotoxicity through increased levels of E2, Prog, 5α-dihydroProg, and Allo-P.
</p>
