<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the multiple functional roles of vitamin D in humans, its deficiency has been reported in many different populations worldwide [
 <xref rid="B185-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>,
 <xref rid="B186-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>,
 <xref rid="B187-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">187</xref>,
 <xref rid="B188-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">188</xref>]. Seafood, mainly oily fish species or fish liver from non-fatty fish, are the main source of vitamin D in the human diet, since it is the only food product, other than mushrooms and egg yolk, that have this vitamin at relatively high levels [
 <xref rid="B186-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>]. Special care should be taken when selecting a type of seafood as a source for vitamin D, since many processed seafood products, such as fish fingers (or sticks), do not contain high levels [
 <xref rid="B189-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">189</xref>]. Some edible seaweeds have high levels of vitamin D
 <sub>2</sub>, while others, like combu and wakame, have levels below the detection limit (0.05 µg/g) [
 <xref rid="B182-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>]. Fortifying foods with vitamin D has shown positive outcomes in both children and adults [
 <xref rid="B190-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>,
 <xref rid="B191-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>,
 <xref rid="B192-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>]. However, Jahn et al. [
 <xref rid="B193-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>] indicated that not all products fortified with vitamin D have met with a positive consumer response. To successfully use food fortification as a tool to fight vitamin D deficiency, the following issues have to be addressed: consumers have to have a positive attitude towards the food product, consumers have to see a personal benefit from the fortified food, have cultural appropriateness and have an awareness of the prevalence of vitamin D deficiency in society. 
</p>
