<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>α-Tocopherol is often obtained from seafood during crude oil extraction. Having strong antioxidant properties, α-tocopherol is often responsible for better oil stability during storage [
 <xref rid="B199-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">199</xref>,
 <xref rid="B200-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">200</xref>]. Although in general low temperature oil extraction yields better stability of fish oil, Honold et al. [
 <xref rid="B201-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">201</xref>] observed, that different oil extraction temperatures (70 vs. 90 °C) did not affect the α-tocopherol content of the oil extracted from rainbow trout by-products (head, bone, tail and intestine), with the content ranging from ~90 to 160 µg/g of oil. Crude oils with high levels of α-tocopherol can be obtained from various fish by-products. For example, Šimat et al. [
 <xref rid="B177-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>] used tuna gill and gut to obtain crude oils with a high yield of 26.1%, which was an α-tocopherol content of 76 µg/g. On the other hand, extraction of crude oil from sardine head, gut and fin resulted in a yield of only 9.2% which was 36 µg/g of α-tocopherol. Therefore, the choice of fish species and type of by-product are important factors to recover high levels of α-tocopherol. Processing of crude oil also negatively affected the α-tocopherol content, as reported by Šimat et al. [
 <xref rid="B94-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>] who observed a 31–45% reduction in α-tocopherol content after refining of crude oil from fish by-products. Araújo et al. [
 <xref rid="B179-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>] compared 5 different methods of vitamin E extraction from rainbow trout flesh: Soxhlet extraction, Folch extraction, solid-liquid extraction with n-hexane and with methanol-BHT, and saponification with KOH with magnetic agitation and n-hexane extraction. They determined that the solid-liquid extraction with n-hexane was the most suitable method after further optimization.
</p>
