<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0210">Formation of unusual blood clots in the arteries and veins is called thrombosis which is a contributor to cardiovascular complications. There are several drugs available in the market to dissolve the blood clots [
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. In the present study, DrFME showed remarkable thrombolytic activities. The other two extracts also showed good results. Previous studies reported the cardioprotective effect of the 
 <italic>Delonix regia</italic> leaf extract where it exhibited a vasodilation effect on heart vessels [
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. While thrombolytic agents are used to dissolving blood clots, arterial and venous thrombotic disorders are treated by the anticoagulants. It is worth mentioning that, drug therapy for the dissolution of blood clots is the first-line approach while inhibition of the intrinsic and extrinsic pathways in the blood clotting cascade is used in acute and intensive care approaches. These two therapeutic approaches are not identical [
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The PT and aPTT tests are popular tests for monitoring coagulation and anticoagulant therapy where PT assay monitors the extrinsic coagulation pathway and the aPTT test is concerned with the intrinsic coagulation [
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. In addition to the thrombolytic activity, DrFME also showed remarkable anticoagulant activities. The thrombolytic and anticoagulant potential of 
 <italic>Delonix regia</italic> flower extracts further validate its ethnomedicinal importance. Previously, the thrombolytic potential of some medicinal plants such as 
 <italic>Averrhoa bilimbi, Clerodendrum viscosum, Drynaria quercifolia, Trema orientalis, Bacopa monnieri, Capsicum frutescens, Brassica oleracea, Urena sinuata, Geodorum densiflorum, Pistia stratiotes, Smilax zeylanica, Pandanus foetidus, Tabernaemontana coronaria</italic> etc. has been explored and reported in Bangladesh [
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>]. The present study also demonstrated that the flower extracts had potent clot lysis activity very similar to the results previously observed.
</p>
