<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As per our survey data, most people are taking kadha only one time a day and they are using ginger, clove, cinnamon, black pepper, and tulsi as main ingredients in kadha. We have analyzed that cinnamon, black pepper, tulsi, and turmeric play vital role against SARS‐CoV‐2 (COVID‐19) as well as other viral infections, which was also supported by some other recent studies mentioned in Tables 
 <xref rid="ptr7019-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="ptr7019-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Our findings were also well supported by Rastogi, Pandey, and Singh (
 <xref rid="ptr7019-bib-0082" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>), who proposed the use of 
 <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> (Giloy), 
 <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> (Ginger), 
 <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> (Curcumin), and 
 <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> (Tulsi) due to their antiviral property. Shrivastava (
 <xref rid="ptr7019-bib-0098" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>) reported that tulsi leaves increase the level of helper T cells as well as natural killer cells, which helps fight against viral infection. Tulsi is being used for curing pain, pneumonia, diarrhea, cough, and fever of ancient times, which are the common symptoms of COVID‐19 (Goothy et al., 
 <xref rid="ptr7019-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Black pepper provides relaxation from sinusitis and nasal congestion, which are the most common symptoms of COVID‐19 (Pathak &amp; Khandelwal, 
 <xref rid="ptr7019-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). Quercetin, a flavonoid present in black pepper, improves the body's immunity constantly due to its antiviral properties (Yao et al., 2017). Our findings were also well supported by Rajagopal et al. (
 <xref rid="ptr7019-bib-0081" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>) who recommended the consumption of black pepper and ginger in a daily diet, as it may be helpful in the prevention of coronavirus. According to our survey, people (83.1%) are boosting immunity by taking Amla/lemon or other fruits as a rich source of vitamin C for boosting their immunity. Arandomized controlled trial to carry out in the USA in 167 patients with sepsis‐related ARDS indicated that uptake of ~15 g/day of vitamin C for 4 days may decrease mortality in these patients (Flower et al., 2020). A randomized, controlled clinical trial was also performed on patients with confirmed SARS‐CoV‐2 infection in the ICU at three hospitals in Hubei, China. They have given high‐dose intravenous vitamin C, that is, 12 g of vitamin C/50 mL every 12 h for 7 days and found that the high‐dose intravenous vitamin C may provide a defensive effect without any side effects in critically COVID‐19 patients (Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="ptr7019-bib-0122" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Utomo et al. (
 <xref rid="ptr7019-bib-0109" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>) reported that the 
 <italic>Citrus sp</italic>. exhibits the best prospective as an inhibitor to the development of the SARS‐CoV‐2.
</p>
