<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The responses (attractiveness or repellence) of 
 <italic class="italic">S. zeamais</italic> to the 
 <italic class="italic">C. nubigenum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. tomentosum</italic> EOs were evaluated by a still-air arena. The arena (15 × 15 × 1 cm), made of polymethylmethacrylate, consisted of three circular chambers (4 cm ∅). Two lateral chambers were connected to a central one (release chamber) by linear paths (2 cm in length, 1 cm in width), forming a 90° angle. The top of the arena was covered by means of a removable glass panel. In each replicate, a square of filter paper (0.5 × 0.5 mm) was treated with 3 μL of 0.3, 0.6, 1.25, 2.5, 3.5, 5.0 and 10.0% EO hexane solution (corresponding to 0.7, 1.4, 3.0, 6.0, 8.4, 12.0, and 23.9 μL/L air). After hexane evaporation, the treated filter paper was placed in one of the lateral chambers (cue chamber). A square of filter paper (0.5 × 0.5 mm) treated with 3 μL of hexane only was placed after hexane evaporation in the other lateral chamber (control chamber). At the beginning of the test, an adult was gently transferred to the floor of the release chamber and observed for 6 min. The insect was considered to have made a valid choice when it entered in one of the two lateral chambers after at least 20 s and remained in the chamber for at least 30 s. Insects that did not make a choice within 6 min after being released were disregarded. For each replicate we recorded (a) the latency time (i.e., the time between the insect release and the entering in one of the chambers), (b) the choice made and (c) the permanence time (i.e., the time spent in the chosen chamber). At each test, the arena was rotated clockwise 90° to avoid positional effects, the cue sources were renewed, and a new insect was placed in the arena. After three consecutive tests, the arena and the glass lid were washed for about 30 s with hexane, then with warm water at 35–40 °C and a mild soap for about 5 min, rinsed with hot water for about 30 s and finally, rinsed with distilled water at room temperature. For each EO concentration, the test was replicated until 30 unsexed adults made a valid choice. All behavioral assays were carried out over a period of several weeks to account for any daily variability. For each replicate, each insect was replaced by a new one of the same age (2–4 days old). All experiments were performed between 8:30 a.m. and 2:30 p.m. and conducted in a room uniformly lit with daylight fluorescent tubes (Philips 30 W/33). Light intensity was approximately 1000 lux (estimated over the 300–1100 nm waveband using a LI-1800 spectroradiometer LI-COR Inc., Lincoln, NE, USA equipped with a remote cosine receptor). Room temperature was set at 25 ± 1 °C and the relative humidity at 50 ± 5%.
</p>
