<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An abundant number of studies have reported the antimicrobial activities of 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> essential oil and its components. These activities have been mainly classified as antibacterial and antifungal activities. It is believed that phenols are the most powerful antimicrobial compounds in the essential oil. The next most powerful antimicrobial compounds are alcohols, followed by ketones, ethers, and then hydrocarbons [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The antibacterial activity gives plants importance in treating infectious bacterial diseases. 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> has an antibacterial property against both Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria, which make it useful for both bacterial infectious diseases and food preservation. Essential oils’ hydrophobic nature allows them to be embedded in the membranes of the cell and the mitochondria, break them, and throw out their contents. Some conditions such as low pH, temperature, and oxygen levels can improve its antibacterial activity. Similarly, antifungal activity is also an important property of 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> essential oils. It plays a role in preserving food and treating infectious diseases, as well as plant pathogenic fungi that can cause significant losses for farmers [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Many microbes were found to be sensitive to 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> essential oil at different degrees. Variable concentrations and concentration units were used by the studies. 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> essential oil’s antimicrobial effect is mostly concentration-dependent. It has interesting inhibitory effects that are comparable to synthesized antimicrobial effects. It was also reported in a study that 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> essential oil could improve the effect of some antimicrobials [
 <xref rid="B41-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> essential oil was effective against antimicrobial-resistant bacterial strains in two studies [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Some studies even found antimicrobial effects of the individual components in 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> essential oil [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Different factors were found to affect the antimicrobial activity of 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> essential oil. It was reported that the essential oils with the richest γ-terpinene and α-terpinene levels have the highest antibacterial activity in a study [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Cultivated 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> essential oil was found to exhibit higher antimicrobial activity than wild 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> essential oil in a study [
 <xref rid="B22-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. 
 <xref rid="plants-10-01001-t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref> shows the microorganisms that are affected by 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic>.
</p>
