<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Forensic genomics used in an ecological context is an increasingly valuable tool for (a) detecting and identifying consumed prey in predator diet samples (invasively or noninvasively collected) and (b) determining rates of decomposition of an animal carcass, among others. First, molecular analyses of fecal material or gastrointestinal (GI) samples represent a technique to study diet and elucidate trophic interactions (McInnes et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Rytkonen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>; Zarzoso‐Lacoste et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). These methods are based on PCR amplification of targeted diet items, using universal or species‐specific primer pairs, in samples collected from the consumer. DNA sequencing is then performed on the amplified PCR products either through Sanger sequencing (Zarzoso‐Lacoste et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>) or high‐throughput sequencing (Rytkonen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>) and the resulting DNA sequences are compared to customized and/or public DNA reference databases (e.g., BOLD, NCBI GenBank) to identify the diet item. Second, molecular analyses of microbial community change over carcass decomposition time represents a unique way to study time since death (Belk et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Metcalf et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Pechal et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). This method is based on PCR amplification with universal primer pairs to target microbiota at domain‐level scales (e.g., bacteria, fungi) to identify microbial biomarkers associated with different time periods of decomposition. Microbial succession of particular taxa is often predictable across soil types, seasons and host species (Belk et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Metcalf et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Uniting these molecular methods can provide important food web insight into what omnivores/carnivores are consuming as diet items and whether particular diet items were likely consumed as prey through predation or carrion through scavenging. Quantifying rates of predation versus scavenging can provide novel insights into food web ecology and foster a more integrated understanding of how complex web dynamics interact (e.g., how prey or scavenging affects invasive population size, influences predation on vulnerable prey or affects food web stability; Moleon et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Wolkovich et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Zou et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0073" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>).
</p>
