<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec22" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other modern separation techniques</div>
 <sec id="Sec23" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular distillation (MD)</div>
  <p id="Par86" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular distillation separates the molecular by distillation under vacuum at a temperature far below its boiling point. It is a suitable distillation method for separating thermosensitive and high-molecular-weight compounds. Borgarello et al. obtained a thymol (
   <span class="bold">125</span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig16" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig16">16</a>) enrichment fraction from oregano essential oil by molecular distillation modeled by artificial neural networks. The obtained fraction had antioxidant properties and could stabilize the sunflower oil [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>]. Three kinds of phthalates were effectively removed from sweet orange oil by molecular distillation under the optimal conditions (evaporation temperature of 50 °C, evaporator pressure of 5 kPa and a feed flow rate of 0.75 ml/min) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>].
   <div id="Fig16" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 16</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Structure of compounds 
      <span class="bold">125</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig16_HTML" id="MO16" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec24" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Preparative gas chromatography (Prep-GC)</div>
  <p id="Par87" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography (GC) with high separation efficiency and fast separation and analysis makes it potentially the ideal preparative method for the separation of volatile compounds. The injection port, column, split device and trap device of GC equipment must be modified for preparative separation due to a lack of commercial Prep-GC [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par88" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Five volatile compounds, namely, curzerene (
   <span class="bold">98</span>) (6.6 mg), 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-elemene (
   <span class="bold">100</span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig12">12</a>) (5.1 mg), curzerenone (
   <span class="bold">126</span>) (41.6 mg), curcumenol (
   <span class="bold">127</span>) (46.2 mg), and curcumenone (
   <span class="bold">128</span>) (21.2 mg) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig17" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig17">17</a>), were separated from the methanol extract of Curcuma Rhizome by Prep-GC over a stainless steel column packed with 10% OV-101 (3 m × 6 mm, i.d.) after 83 single injections (20 μl) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>]. Prep-GC was also applied for the separation of natural isomers. A total of 178 mg of 
   <span class="italic">cis</span>-asarone (
   <span class="bold">129</span>) and 82 mg of 
   <span class="italic">trans</span>-asarone (
   <span class="bold">130</span>) were obtained from the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">Acorus tatarinowii</span> after 90 single injections (5 μl) on the same column as above [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>]. Prep-GC has become an important separation method for natural volatile compounds; however, a heavier sample load and the large-diameter preparative column employed decreased the efficiency [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">89</a>]. Meanwhile, the disadvantages of Prep-GC, including the lack of commercial Prep-GC equipment, consumption of a large volume of carrier gas, the decomposition of thermolabile compounds under high operation temperature, the difficulties of fraction collection, and low production, still restrict the usage of Prep-GC.
   <div id="Fig17" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 17</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Structures of compounds 
      <span class="bold">126</span>–
      <span class="bold">130</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig17_HTML" id="MO17" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec25" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supercritical fluid chromatography (SFC)</div>
  <p id="Par89" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SFC uses supercritical fluid as the mobile phase. SFC integrates the advantages of both GC and liquid chromatography (LC) as the supercritical fluids possess properties of high dissolving capability, high diffusivity and low viscosity, which allows rapid and efficient separation. Thus, SFC can use a longer column and smaller particles of the stationary phase than HPLC, which provides greater numbers of theoretical plates and better separation. SFC can be used for the separation of non-volatile or thermally labile compounds to which GC is not applicable. SFC systems are compatible with a wide range of different detectors including those used in LC and GC systems. The polarity of the widely used mobile phase, S-CO
   <sub>2</sub>, in SFC is close to the polarity of hexane, with the result that SFC was used for the separation of non-polar natural products such as fatty acids, terpenes and essential oils for many years. Eluent modifiers such methanol and acetonitrile enhance the elution strength, which is increasing the interest in separating polar natural products by SFC [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">90</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par90" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Zhao et al. successfully separated three pairs of 25 
   <span class="italic">R</span>/
   <span class="italic">S</span> diastereomeric spirostanol saponins (
   <span class="bold">131</span>–
   <span class="bold">136</span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig18" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig18">18</a>) from the TCM Trigonellae Semen (the seed of 
   <span class="italic">Trigonella foenum</span>-
   <span class="italic">graecum</span>) on two CHIRALPAK IC columns coupled in tandem [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>]. Yang et al. applied SFC for the preparative separation of two pairs of 7-epimeric spiro oxindole alkaloids (
   <span class="bold">137</span>–
   <span class="bold">140</span>) from stems with hooks of 
   <span class="italic">Uncaria macrophylla</span> (a herbal source for TCM Uncariae Ramulus Cum Uncis) on a Viridis Prep Silica 2-EP OBD column using acetonitrile containing 0.2% DEA modified S-CO
   <sub>2</sub>. The non-aqueous mobile phase used in SFC prevented the tautomerization of the separated spiro oxindole alkaloids [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">94</a>]. SFC is also applied in the separation of natural enantiomers. (
   <span class="italic">R</span>,
   <span class="italic">S</span>)-goitrin (
   <span class="bold">141</span>–
   <span class="bold">142</span>) is the active ingredient of TCM Isatidis Radix. The chiral separation of (
   <span class="italic">R</span>) and (
   <span class="italic">S</span>) goitrins was successfully achieved by prep-SFC on a Chiralpak IC column using acetonitrile as the organic modifier [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>].
   <div id="Fig18" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 18</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Structures of compounds 
      <span class="bold">131</span>–
      <span class="bold">142</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig18_HTML" id="MO18" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec26" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular imprinted technology</div>
  <p id="Par91" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular imprinted technology has been an attractive separation method in the last decade due to its unique features, which include high selectivity, low cost and easy preparation. Many complementary cavities with the memory of size, shape, and functional groups of the template molecules are generated when the template molecules are removed from the molecular imprinted polymer (MIP). Thus, the template molecule and its analogs will have the specific recognition and selective adsorption for the MIP. MIPs have been widely used in the separation of natural products or as solid-phase extraction sorbents for sample preparation of herbal materials to enrich the minor compounds.</p>
  <p id="Par92" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ji et al. developed multi-template molecularly imprinted polymers using DL-tyrosine and phenylpyruvic acid as the template molecules to separate dencichine (
   <span class="bold">143</span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig19" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig19">19</a>) from the water extract of 
   <span class="italic">Panax notoginseng</span>. Both dencichine and the template molecule of DL-tyrosine (
   <span class="bold">144</span>) contain an amino (NH
   <sub>2</sub>) group and a carboxylic acid (COOH) group, and the other template molecule, phenylpyruvic acid (
   <span class="bold">145</span>), has an α-keto acid (COCOOH) group that can also be found in the structure of dencichine [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>]. Ma et al. developed a preparative separation method to separate solanesol (
   <span class="bold">146</span>) from tobacco leaves by flash chromatography based on MIP. The MIP was prepared with methyl methacrylate as the monomer, solanesol as the template molecule and ethylene glycol dimethacrylate as the crosslinker by a suspension polymerization method. A total of 370.8 mg of solanesol with 98.4% purity was separated from the extract of tobacco leaves with a yield of 2.5% of the dry weight of tobacco leaves [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">97</a>]. You et al. used the thermo-responsive magnetic MIP to separate the three major curcuminoids, curcumin (
   <span class="bold">147</span>), demethoxycurcumin (
   <span class="bold">148</span>), and bisdemethoxycurcumin (
   <span class="bold">149</span>), from the TCM Curcumae Longae Rhizoma (the rhizome of 
   <span class="italic">Curcuma longa</span>). The designed thermo-responsive magnetic MIP showed good imprinting factor for curcuminoids in a range between 2.4 and 3.1, thermo-responsiveness [lower critical solution temperature at 33.71 °C] and rapid magnetic separation (5 s) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">98</a>].
   <div id="Fig19" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 19</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Structures of compounds 
      <span class="bold">143</span>–
      <span class="bold">149</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig19_HTML" id="MO19" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec27" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulated moving bed chromatography</div>
  <p id="Par93" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulated moving bed (SMB) chromatography uses multiple columns with stationary phases (bed). The countercurrent movement of the bed is simulated through rotary valves, which periodically switch the inlet (feed and eluent) and outlet (extract and raffinate). The SMB process is a continuous separation method and a powerful tool for the large-scale separation of natural products with the advantage of lower solvent consumption over a shorter period of time.</p>
  <p id="Par94" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two cyclopeptides, cyclolinopeptides C and E (
   <span class="bold">150–151</span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig20" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig20">20</a>), were obtained from flaxseed oil using a three zone SMBC with eight preparative HPLC normal phase spherical silica gel columns and using absolute ethanol as the desorbent [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">99</a>]. Kang et al. developed a tandem SMB process consisting of two four-zone SMB units in a series with the same adsorbent particle sizes in Ring I and Ring II to separate paclitaxel (taxol, 
   <span class="bold">74</span>) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig11">11</a>), 13-dehydroxybaccatin III (
   <span class="bold">152</span>), and 10-deacetylpaclitaxel (
   <span class="bold">153</span>). Paclitaxel was recovered in the first SMB unit while 13-dehydroxybaccatin III and 10-deacetylpaclitaxel were separated in the second SMB unit [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">100</a>]. Mun enhanced this SMB chromatography method by using different particle sizes adsorbent in Ring I and Ring II [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" href="#CR101">101</a>]. Supercritical fluids can also be used as the desorbent in SMB chromatography. Liang et al. successfully applied supercritical carbon dioxide with ethanol as the desorbent for a three-zone SMB to separate resveratrol (
   <span class="bold">60</span>) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig9">9</a>) and emodin (
   <span class="bold">44</span>) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>) from a crude extract of the TCM Polygoni Cuspidati Rhizoma et Radix [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" href="#CR102">102</a>].
   <div id="Fig20" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 20</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Structures of compounds 
      <span class="bold">150</span>–
      <span class="bold">153</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig20_HTML" id="MO20" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec28" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Multi-dimensional chromatographic separation</div>
  <p id="Par95" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The components in the extract subjected to separation were complex, and generally, no pure compound will be separated in one column chromatography. Multi-dimensional separation based on the solid phase extraction and coupling of multiple columns with different stationary phases greatly improves the separation efficiency. With more commercial multiple dimensional separation equipment entering the market, the separation of natural products is becoming more rapid, efficient and automated.</p>
  <p id="Par96" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Usually, the target compound was enriched by first dimensional separation and purified by last dimensional separation. Multi-dimensional separation can be achieved using the same type separation equipment (LC or GC) or different types of equipment (GC and LC). A novel volatile compound, (2
   <span class="italic">E</span>,6
   <span class="italic">E</span>)-2-methyl-6-(4-methylcyclohex-3-enylidene)hept-2-enal (
   <span class="bold">154</span>), was purified by a three-dimensional prep-GC from wampee essential oil [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">103</a>]. Five antioxidant compounds, including two alkaloids [glusodichotomine AK (
   <span class="bold">155</span>) and glusodichotomine B (
   <span class="bold">156</span>)] and three flavonoids [tricin (
   <span class="bold">157</span>), homoeriodictyol (
   <span class="bold">158</span>) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig21" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig21">21</a>), and luteolin (
   <span class="bold">3</span>) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>)], were separated using a two-dimensional HPLC (RP/HILIC) method from 
   <span class="italic">Arenaria kansuensis</span> on a RP-C18HCE and a NP-XAmide preparative columns [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104" href="#CR104">104</a>]. Sciarrone et al. exploited the separation of sesquiterpenes in patchouli essential oil by three dimensional Prep-GC. Patchouli alcohol (
   <span class="bold">111</span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig12">12</a>) (496 μg) was separated in the first dimension on a poly(5% diphenyl/95% dimethylsiloxane) column, and 295 μg of 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-bulnesene (
   <span class="bold">159</span>) was from a second column coated with high molecular weight polyethylene glycol as well as 160 μg 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-guaiene (
   <span class="bold">160</span>) from the third dimension on an ionic-liquid based column (SLB-IL60) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">105</a>]. Pantò et al. applied two three-dimensional approaches (GC–GC–GC and LC–GC–GC) to separate the sesquiterpene alcohols [(
   <span class="italic">Z</span>)-
   <span class="italic">α</span>-santalol (
   <span class="bold">161</span>), (
   <span class="italic">Z</span>)-
   <span class="italic">α</span>-
   <span class="italic">trans</span> bergamotol (
   <span class="bold">162</span>), (
   <span class="italic">Z</span>)-
   <span class="italic">β</span>-santalol (
   <span class="bold">163</span>), 
   <span class="italic">epi</span>-(
   <span class="italic">Z</span>)-
   <span class="italic">β</span>-santalol (
   <span class="bold">164</span>), 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-bisabolol (
   <span class="bold">165</span>), (
   <span class="italic">Z</span>)-lanceol (
   <span class="bold">166</span>), and (
   <span class="italic">Z</span>)-nuciferol (
   <span class="bold">167</span>)] from the sandalwood essential oil. They found that the first dimensional separation using LC reduced the sample complexity and increased the productivity of low-concentration components [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" href="#CR106">106</a>].
   <div id="Fig21" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 21</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Structures of compounds 
      <span class="bold">154</span>–
      <span class="bold">167</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig21_HTML" id="MO21" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
