<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Enzyme assisted extraction (EAE)</div>
 <p id="Par63" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The structure of the cell membrane and cell wall, micelles formed by macromolecules such polysaccharides and protein, and the coagulation and denaturation of proteins at high temperatures during extraction are the main barriers to the extraction of natural products. The extraction efficiency will be enhanced by EAE due to the hydrolytic action of the enzymes on the components of the cell wall and membrane and the macromolecules inside the cell which facilitate the release of the natural product. Cellulose, α-amylase and pectinase are generally employed in EAE.</p>
 <p id="Par64" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Polysaccharide is one of the bioactive ingredients in the TCM Astragali Radix. Chen et al. studied the EAE of polysaccharide from the radix of 
  <span class="italic">Astragalus membranaceus</span> using various enzymes and found that glucose oxidase offered better performance in extracting polysaccharide than the other seven enzymes tested (amyloglucosidase, hemicellulase, bacterial amylase, fungal amylase, pectinase, cellulose and vinozyme). The polysaccharide yield under the optimized EAE condition using glucose oxidase increased more than 250% compared with that from non-enzyme treated method [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. The extraction yield of chlorogenic acid (
  <span class="bold">66</span>, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig10">10</a>) from 
  <span class="italic">Eucommia ulmoides</span> leaves was greatly improved when using cellulase and ionic liquids [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. Strati el al. found that carotenoid and lycopene (
  <span class="bold">67</span>) extraction yields from tomato waste were increased by the use of pectinase and cellulase enzymes. Compared to the non-enzyme treated solvent extraction method, sixfold and tenfold higher yields of the two target compounds were obtained in samples treated with cellulase and pectinase, respectively [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>].
  <div id="Fig10" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 10</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Structures of compounds 
     <span class="bold">66</span>–
     <span class="bold">67</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig10_HTML" id="MO10" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
