<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Percolation</div>
 <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Percolation is more efficient than maceration because it is a continuous process in which the saturated solvent is constantly being replaced by fresh solvent.</p>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Zhang et al. compared the percolation and refluxing extraction methods to extract 
  <span class="italic">Undaria pinnatifida</span>. They found that the contents of the major component, fucoxanthin (
  <span class="bold">4</span>, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>), from the percolation extraction method was higher than that from the refluxing method while there was no significant difference in extract yield between the two methods [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. Goupi patch is a compound Chinese medicine preparation consisting of 29 Chinese medicines. Fu et al. used the whole alkaloids content determined by acid–base titration as the index and optimized the ethanol percolation method as soaking the medicine with 55% alcohol for 24 h and then percolating with 12 times the amount of 55% alcohol [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. When using the extracting rate of sinomenine (
  <span class="bold">5</span>) and ephedrine hydrochloride (
  <span class="bold">6</span>) as the index, Gao developed another optimized percolation method: soaking the medicine with 70% ethanol for 24 h and then percolating with 20 times the amount of 70% ethanol. The transfer rates of sinomenine and ephedrine hydrochloride were 78.23 and 76.92%, respectively [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>].
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Structures of compounds 
     <span class="bold">4</span>–
     <span class="bold">6</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
