<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supercritical fluid extraction (SFE)</div>
 <p id="Par55" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supercritical fluid extraction (SFE) uses supercritical fluid (SF) as the extraction solvent. SF has similar solubility to liquid and similar diffusivity to gas, and can dissolve a wide variety of natural products. Their solvating properties dramatically changed near their critical points due to small pressure and temperature changes. Supercritical carbon dioxide (S-CO
  <sub>2</sub>) was widely used in SFE because of its attractive merits such as low critical temperature (31 °C), selectivity, inertness, low cost, non-toxicity, and capability to extract thermally labile compounds. The low polarity of S-CO
  <sub>2</sub> makes it ideal for the extraction of non-polar natural products such as lipid and volatile oil. A modifier may be added to S-CO
  <sub>2</sub> to enhance its solvating properties significantly.
 </p>
 <p id="Par56" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conde-Hernández extracted the essential oil of rosemary (
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span>) by S-CO
  <sub>2</sub> extraction, hydro distillation and steam distillation. He found that both yields of essential oil and antioxidant activity of SFC extract were higher than those from other two methods [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. S-CO
  <sub>2</sub> modified with 2% ethanol at 300 bar and 40 °C gave higher extracting selectivity of vinblastine (
  <span class="bold">53</span>, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7</a>) (an antineoplastic drug) from 
  <span class="italic">Catharanthus roseus</span>, which is 92% more efficient for vinblastine extraction compared to traditional extraction methods [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>].
  <div id="Fig7" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 7</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Structure of compounds 
     <span class="bold">53</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
