<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Cymbopogon citronella</italic> Stapf (
 <italic class="italic">C. citronella</italic>), also known as lemongrass, belongs to 
 <italic class="italic">Cymbopogon</italic> Spreng. family. 
 <italic class="italic">C. citronella</italic> is a perennial grass that is widely cultivated in tropic and subtropic regions of the eastern hemisphere, such as China [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">C. citronella</italic> is barren and drought resistant and can tolerate a temperature range from −25°C to 40°C, suggesting that it can be planted in a wide range of environmental conditions [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. The essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">C. citronella</italic> has been studied widely; Sriramavaratharajan et al. [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>] has found that the essential oil was mainly distributed in the 
 <italic class="italic">C. citronella</italic> leaves. In other research studies, the components of the 
 <italic class="italic">C. citronella</italic> essential oil were identified, including mainly citral (aldehydes geranial + neral) and terpenes (myrcene-monoterpene and geranial-terpenic alcohol) [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. As an economic oil crop, the fragrance odour together with the various pharmacological activities promote the essential oil widely used as a flavor enhancer in food, perfumery, soap, cosmetic, pharmaceutical, insecticide industries, etc. [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. For example, the citral from the essential oil could be used as a raw material to prepare vitamins (A, E, and K), ionone, methylionone, and perfumes [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Consequently, this essential oil-producing crop has attracted huge economic interests in China and abroad in recent years.
</p>
