<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One of the most common methods for the formation of gels, from macro- to nanoscale, with globular proteins is the application of heat [
 <xref rid="B46-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. Temperature affects the thermodynamic stability of whey proteins by reducing the activation energy and increasing the frequency of molecular collisions and the enhancement of hydrophobic interaction, which is a crucial step for the occurrence of physical protein aggregation. Consequently, high temperature, above the protein denaturation level is a key parameter for accelerating whey protein aggregation [
 <xref rid="B26-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Generally, globular proteins, such as β-lg, aggregate spontaneously and irreversibly if they are denatured at temperatures above 60 °C [
 <xref rid="B47-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. Above the denaturation temperatures thermal gelation and hydrogel production can be seen as a simple sequential three-step process, which involves: (1) unfolding of native protein and exposition of hydrophobic amino acid residues, (2) primary and secondary aggregation of unfolded proteins, where covalent and non-covalent bonds are established and (3) development of a protein network structure, when the aggregation exceeds a critical point of the concentration. Above a critical gel protein concentration, a system spanning network is formed which is tight and stable, but at lower concentrations it collapses under gravity, leading to precipitation or the formation of heterogeneous systems. These are some of the key concepts of the general model for globular protein gelation proposed by Ferry [
 <xref rid="B48-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. This model describes gelation based on the denaturation temperature, a critical protein concentration, a critical gelation time that is dependent on the rate of denaturation, and aggregation. More recently, some complexity has been added to this model taking into account the reverse pathway of protein folding and formation of intermediate states of protein aggregates that can form disordered aggregates or amyloid fibrils [
 <xref rid="B49-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. In this sense, it is important to clarify the molecular approach of protein aggregation, thus the precise details of association mechanisms that strongly impact the rheological performance of gels in food materials should be fully explained [
 <xref rid="B50-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. This technique has been widely used to obtain protein nanoparticles for food applications [
 <xref rid="B51-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>].
</p>
