<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The disc diffusion method is widely used as it is suitable for preliminary testing for screening the antimicrobial activity of plant extracts [
 <xref rid="B78-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. The susceptibility of microbes to the plant extract is determined by inoculating microbial suspension onto the medium agar surface and swabbing it evenly all over the agar surface with a cotton swab. The filter paper discs are dipped with plant extract and incubated for 24–48 h. The inhibition zones are observed, and their diameter measured, indicated by a clear area around the filter paper disc. A clear zone of inhibition reveals the microbes’ vulnerability to an extract, while the absence of such a zone shows the microbes’ resistance to the extract. This method is a low-cost and straightforward technique to determine the efficiency of a plant extract in inhibiting the growth of microbes [
 <xref rid="B79-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. For the agar well diffusion method, the agar is diffused with the plant extract before it is solidified, and each plate is inoculated with microbial culture and spread evenly with a sterile bent glass rod. The agar medium is cut with a sterile cork borer, and different concentrations of plant extract solution are loaded by micropipette into the agar well. Plates are incubated for 24–48 h before the zones of inhibition are observed. There is also the determination of the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) by the microdilution method using 96-well microtitration plates, the hole plate diffusion method, the two-fold method in a microtiter plate, the Versa Max Tunable microplate reader, and particular MIC methods such as the tetrazolium microplate method, liquid dilution method, and serial dilution method [
 <xref rid="B80-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. In terms of MIC, concentrations of extracts are varied in the preferred antimicrobial test to determine the lowest concentration of extract that effectively prevents microbial growth [
 <xref rid="B81-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>].
</p>
