<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Methanol extract of 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> from Soxhlet extraction was found to inhibit various types of fungi (e.g., 
 <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic>, 
 <italic>Alternaria alternata</italic>, and 
 <italic>F. oxysporum</italic>) and bacteria (e.g., 
 <italic>P. syringae</italic>, 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B17-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>], but petroleum ether extract did not show any antimicrobial activity against the microbes tested [
 <xref rid="B65-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Byakodi et al. [
 <xref rid="B10-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] also found that a methanolic extract obtained by the Soxhlet method exhibited antimicrobial activity against Gram-positive and -negative strains of bacteria. Ethanolic extract obtained by the Soxhlet method was found to exhibit better antimicrobial activity toward 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> (extended-spectrum β-lactamase-producing (ESBL) and carbapenem-resistant strains), 
 <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> (carbapenem-resistant strains), and 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (carbapenem-resistant strains) in contrast to the petroleum ether extract, which was only efficient in inhibiting 
 <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> (ESBL strains). However, both extracts were unable to inhibit the growth of 
 <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> [
 <xref rid="B90-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. ESBL-producing Enterobacteriaceae cause infections in the urinary tract, and drug-resistant infections were found to cause 9000 deaths, of which 600 were due to carbapenem-resistant 
 <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> [
 <xref rid="B90-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Therefore, new antibacterial agents are needed to counter the pathogen, and the extract of 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> could be one of them.
</p>
