<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>When parasites are host-specialists, they are less likely to spill over to a new host, but for generalist parasites, a diverse community is a larger pool of potential hosts [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. In this study, we expected to find host specificity of leptospires, based the strong host-specificity observed for different 
 <italic>Leptospira</italic> species shed by bats [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] and terrestrial mammals [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] endemic to Madagascar. In contrast to our expectations, the results presented here support cross-species transmission for cosmopolitan 
 <italic>Leptospira</italic> lineages. All rats were infected by 
 <italic>L</italic>. 
 <italic>interrogans</italic>, represented by a single 
 <italic>secY</italic> haplotype. This haplotype was found in one specimen of 
 <italic>Setifer setosus</italic> as well as in one specimen of 
 <italic>Mus musculus</italic>. The sequences were identical to that of a 
 <italic>secY</italic> haplotype originally from Kuwait and in 
 <italic>Rattus tanezumi</italic> from Thailand [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. This haplotype was also identical to that found in 
 <italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic> in eastern Madagascar [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], while it was distinct from that found in the rats sampled on Réunion and Seychelles, which were all infected with the 
 <italic>secY1</italic> haplotype [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. In contrast to 
 <italic>Rattus</italic>, the introduced mammals 
 <italic>Suncus etruscus</italic>, 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>murinus</italic>, and all but one 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>musculus</italic> were found to share the same 
 <italic>secY</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>3</italic>
 </sup>
 <italic>22</italic> haplotype corresponding to 
 <italic>L</italic>. 
 <italic>kirschneri</italic>. Although 
 <italic>Rattus</italic> were exclusively infected with 
 <italic>L</italic>. 
 <italic>interrogans</italic>, as previously reported in mostly urban settings [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], and 
 <italic>Suncus</italic> and 
 <italic>Mus</italic> almost exclusively infected with 
 <italic>L</italic>. 
 <italic>kirschneri</italic>, our results provide evidence of possible transmission between 
 <italic>Suncus</italic> and 
 <italic>Mus</italic>, and between 
 <italic>Rattus</italic>, 
 <italic>Mus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Setifer</italic>. In contrast to the results presented here, however, native mammals in intact and degraded forests on the island have rarely been found infected with 
 <italic>L</italic>. 
 <italic>interrogans</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Instead, endemic Tenrecidae were found infected by 
 <italic>L</italic>. 
 <italic>mayottensis</italic>, which is endemic to Madagascar and presumably established on Mayotte with the introduction of the tenrecine 
 <italic>Tenrec ecaudatus</italic> to that island [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].
</p>
