<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>FCB is one of the most ancient Traditional Chinese Medicine (TCM) associated with high economic and medical value [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In China, it has been used as a classical antitussive and expectorant agent for thousands of years [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. According to historical materials, before the Ming dynasty, FCB and other Fritillaria Bulbs such as Fritillariae Thunbergii Bulbus (known as zhebeimu, FTB) were collectively named “Beimu.” Beimu was firstly recorded in “Shen Nong Ben Cao Jing,” the earliest monograph of TCM, and has been described as a cough medicine with good throat clearing and detoxification effects [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Until Ming dynasty, another medical monograph called “Ben Cao Hui Yan” (Nizhumo, 1624, Ming dynasty) has summarized the differences between FCB and FTB, which indicated that FCB tended to moisten the lung, eliminate phlegm, and relieve cough and asthma and FTB tended to clear heat and detoxify. As the research moves along, medical workers have gained a deeper insight into the usages of FCB in the Qing dynasty. “Yao Xing Qie Yong” (Xudachun, 1741, Qing dynasty) has complementally noted that FCB has antidepressant effects. Moreover, “Ben Cao Gang Mu Shi Yi” (Zhaoxuemin, 1765, Qing dynasty) definitely indicated the differences between FCB and FTB on the treatment of cough for the first time. The author thought that FCB and FTB were suitable for the cough results from deficiency and heat, respectively, which is consistent with the modern application of FCB and FTB [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Of course, some modern medical books also summarized the pharmacology of FCB. For instance, “Zhong Yao Da Ci Dian” described that FCB had a wide spectrum of pharmacological properties, such as clearing heat, moistening lung, eliminating phlegm, relieving cough, and good therapeutic effects on respiratory and pulmonary disease [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Generally, FCB is routinely used to grind powder and dissolve it in water before taking it orally. Additionally, FCB as an important ingredient appears in many Chinese patent medicines (CPM) which have been made into various dosage forms, such as pills, ointments, powders, tablets, solutions, and syrups. There are 38 CPM containing FCB documented in Chinese Pharmacopoeia (2015) alone (
 <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). A well-known example is “Chuanbei Pipa Tangjiang.” It has been wildly used to relieve cough and eliminate phlegm [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. As the increasing studies of pharmacology of FCB, we have a deeper understanding of the role of FCB in human health. Emerging evidence has shown that FCB possesses diverse biological activities, such as expectorant, antitussive, antiasthma, anti-inflammatory, antitumor, and antioxidant activities [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].
</p>
