<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p id="Par1" class="p">Essential oil obtained from rhizomes of the 
   <italic class="italic">Zingiber zerumbet</italic> (L.) Smith (popularly known in Brazil as bitter ginger) is mainly constituted by the biomolecule zerumbone, which exhibit untapped antimicrobial potential
   <bold class="bold">.</bold> The aim of this study was to investigate the antimicrobial activity of the zerumbone from bitter ginger rhizomes against the cariogenic agent 
   <italic class="italic">Streptococcus mutans</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2" class="p">Firstly, the essential oil from rhizomes of 
   <italic class="italic">Zingiber zerumbet</italic> (L.) Smith extracted by hydrodistillation was submitted to purification and recrystallization process to obtain the zerumbone compound. The purity of zerumbone was determined through high-performance liquid chromatography analysis. Different concentrations of zerumbone were tested against the standard strain 
   <italic class="italic">S. mutans</italic> (ATCC 35668) by using microdilution method. The speed of cidal activity was determined through a time kill-curve assay. The biological cytotoxicity activity of zerumbone was assessed using Vero cell line through MTT assay.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p id="Par3" class="p">The zerumbone showed a minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of 250 μg/mL and a minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) of 500 μg/mL against 
   <italic class="italic">S. mutans.</italic> After six hours of bacteria-zerumbone interaction, all concentrations tested starts to kill the bacteria and all bacteria were killed between 48 and 72 h period at the concentration of 500 μg/mL (99,99% of bacteria were killed in comparison with original inoculum). In addition, zerumbone showed no cytotoxicity activity on mammalian continuous cells line.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par4" class="p">These results draw attention to the potential of zerumbone as antimicrobial agent against 
   <italic class="italic">S. mutans</italic> infection, indicating its possible use in the phyto-pharmaceutical formulations as new approach to prevent and treat tooth decay disease.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Electronic supplementary material</title>
  <p class="p">The online version of this article (10.1186/s12906-018-2360-0) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
