<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During the pre- and early post-infusion period, patients are generally admitted to inpatient unit, as the rapid 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> proliferation of CAR-T cells may be associated with adverse events, such as CRS and neurotoxicity (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>–
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). Currently, rapid advances have been made in the identification of clinical and biological predictors and in the design of appropriate standards of care to mitigate the severity and long-term consequences of these complications (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). CRS is the most common side effect following CAR-T cell therapy, occurring in 30 to 100% of cases, with CRS of grades 3–4 in 10–30% of patients (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). CRS may present with a spectrum of manifestations from low-grade fever to fulminant multiorgan failure (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>–
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). In some studies, approximately 10–15% of CAR-T cell patients required vasopressor support for hypotension and/or mechanical ventilation (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). The mainstays of treatment for severe CRS include the anti-IL6-R antibody (tocilizumab), anti-IL6 antibody (siltuximab), high-dose steroids, and supportive care delivered in ICU (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). Patients treated with CAR-T cells may develop concomitantly with CRS or as an isolated feature, a potentially fatal neurological toxicity, including delirium, encephalopathy, nerve palsies, and seizures, whose mechanism seems to be related to systemic inflammation due to rapid CAR-T cell expansion (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>). Different products have variable rates and patterns of toxicity, and clinical judgement remains the best method to assess CRS. Tisagenlecleucel induced severe CRS (grade 3 or 4 by the UPenn toxicity criteria) in 48% of pediatric and young adult ALL patients in the ELIANA trial (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) and 28% of adult patients with diffuse large B cell lymphoma (DLBCL) in the JULIET trial (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), while the ZUMA-1 trial reported a 13% rate (by NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events) for axicabtagene ciloleucel in adult DLBCL patients (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Nurses and ancillary medical personnel should be adequately trained about the recognition of CAR-T cells’ specific care and toxicities in order to expedite the evaluation for the transfer to ICU and treatment with tocilizumab. The second most common adverse event is the immune effector cell-associated neurotoxicity syndrome (ICANS) (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). The symptoms and signs are non-specific, and the severity is correlated with the increase of specific biomarkers such as C-reactive protein, ferritin and IL-6 (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). ICANS incidence has been reported in 12–55% of cases. Patients are monitored by nursing tools to identify early manifestations of CRS or neurotoxicity. In the latter case, serial cognitive testing and neurological expertise are needed. In addition to infectious events, CAR-T cell recipients are at increased risk of potential medium-term complications, depending on the type of CAR-T cell product, including delayed tumor lysis syndrome, delayed hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis/macrophage activation syndrome and CRS, B-cell aplasia, hypogammaglobulinemia. Neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, and anemia are commonly observed in CAR-T cell treated patients, but generally resolve over several months through the administration of growth factors following the observation at early stages of adverse events.
</p>
