<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10" class="p">To ascertain the repellent activity of the essential oils (EO) (at a concentration of 1 mg/ml) extracted from plants (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>) against 
 <italic class="italic">I</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">ricinus</italic> nymphs, the method described by Jaenson et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">2003</xref>) and Garboui et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">2007</xref>) was used. The walls of transparent-plastic Falcon tubes (50 ml centrifugal tube: 116 × 29 mm) were perforated, to prevent the internal air saturation with the observer odor, test or control substances. A 100 µl of each EO solution (1 mg/ml) was applied evenly on a cotton cloth with a pipette to get a final concentration of 15 µg/cm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>. Control cotton cloths were treated with 100 µl hexane. The treated and control cloths were air dried for 2 min for solvent evaporation. Freshly collected unfed 
 <italic class="italic">I</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">ricinus</italic> nymph was introduced into Falcon tube and firstly tested with hexane treated cloth (that fixed to the Falcon upper end with the help of rubber band) for 5 min and immediately after the same nymph was tested against the EO treated cloth for another 5 min (one cloth used for each nymph). In order to simulate the nymph, the observer held his hand palm on the outer surface of the cloth during the observation period (5 min). The same observer conducted the entire bioassay who was attractive to ticks. A tick nymph was considered “attracted” to the cloth if it detached all its legs from the wall of the Falcon tube and clung towards the treated cloth within 5 min, whereas the nymph which failed to reach the cloth in this time or/and turned around the Falcon tube wall was regarded as “repelled” (El-Seedi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">2012</xref>). Ten nymphs were used/each oil/each replicate. Five replicates were used, thus the overall tick number was 50 nymphs for each EO and control group. The percentage of repellency was calculated using the formula of Jaenson et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">2005</xref>) as follows: 
</p>
