<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The type II transmembrane serine-proteinase serine type 2 RSS2 type II transmembrane serine protease that cleaves the S spike proteins of SARS-CoV and MERS and ACE2 (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Iwata-Yoshikawa et al., 2019</xref>). Recently, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Hoffmann et al. (2020)</xref> demonstrated that besides using ACE2 receptor to enter the host cells, SARS-CoV-2 uses also TMPRSS2 for S protein priming. After the interaction between the S spike protein (SARS-CoV-2) and the ACE2 (host cell), the complex is cleaved by the TMPRSS2 to facilitate viral entry (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Rabi et al., 2020</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Matsuyama et al. (2020)</xref> found that an important TMPRSS2 expression in cells makes them highly susceptible to SARS-CoV-2. Since SARS-CoV-2 viral entry is conditioned by its binding to the ACE2 receptor, and the latter should be cleaved by the TMPRSS, finding agents able to suppress or downregulate the TMPRSS2 expression in human cells could represent a promising therapeutic or preventive approach (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">Schlagenhauf et al., 2020</xref>). Several studies have demonstrated that natural products could downregulate or suppress TMPRSS2. It has been shown that kaempferol was able to inactivate TMPRSS2 expression by 49.14 and 79.48% at 5 and 15 μM, respectively (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Da et al., 2019</xref>). Likewise, sulforaphane (an isothiocyanate) was found to downregulate the TMPRSS2 expression through the release and translocation of the Nrf2 (nuclear factor (erythroid-derived 2)-like 2) (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Gibbs et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Meyer and Jaspers, 2015</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Mamouni et al. (2018)</xref> found that a standardized flavonoids formulation including luteolin, quercetin, and kaempferol significantly suppressed TMPRSS2 expression. In spite of the diverse biological effects attributed to the three flavonoids, this study has demonstrated that at low concentrations, they exhibited an important synergic effect. Nonetheless, the efficacy and safety of these compounds in COVID-19 patients is still unclear. Moreover, modes of administration, the health of the patients’ digestive system, and disease stage may limit the clinical usefulness of such formulations and compounds (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Fuzimoto and Isidoro, 2020</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al. (2012)</xref> demonstrated that cryptotanshinone at 0.5 µM effectively exhibited anti-TMPRSS2 activity (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">
  <bold>Figure 3</bold>
 </xref>).
</p>
