<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite several disadvantages, liquid-liquid and solid-liquid extraction are still the most commonly used extraction procedures for phenolic acids and flavonoids. For many years, the conventional techniques have been widely accepted, mainly because of their ease of use, efficiency, and wide-ranging applicability [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Maceration and decoction techniques are very useful methods for weakening the cell wall in vegetal tissues, but in different ways. The main difference between them regards temperature. High temperatures applied with decoction can destroy bioactive compounds, such as polyphenols, so the application of milder temperatures through a gentle maceration process would be a better option [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. However, applying high temperatures during a decoction process can also destroy enzymes, preventing the degradation of polyphenols [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Some modern extraction methods, such as microwave-assisted extraction, ultrahigh pressure extraction and supercritical carbon dioxide extraction, have been utilized for the preparation of plant extracts [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. These methods have various benefits, such as the improved penetration of solvents into plant particles, a low extraction temperature and reduced extraction time, but maceration is simple, more convenient and less costly in terms of instrumentation [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Therefore, it is more applicable in small and medium enterprises (SMEs) and in developing countries [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The use of medicinal plants is the first choice of treatment for areas where access to appropriate care is difficult, while traditional herbal medicines provided by traditional healers are fast and available at all times when needed. In this sense, extraction methods based on decoction and maceration are the most used generally [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-04672" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
