<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The anti-peroxyl radical activity was evaluated measuring the peroxides generated during the oxidation of linoleic acid at high temperature, according to the method of Hajlaoui 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-20-14402" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>] with some modifications. Briefly, 0.2 mg of β-carotene was dissolved in 2 mL of chloroform, and added to 20 mg of linoleic acid and 200 mg of Tween 40. After removing CHCl
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> under a vacuum, oxygenated water (100 mL) was added and the flask was vigorously shaken until all material dissolved. The emulsion obtained was freshly prepared before each experiment. An aliquot of 150 μL of emulsion was distributed in each of the wells of 96-well microtiter plates and 10 mg of essential oil or BHA standard solution (0.1–100 µg/mL) was added. An equal amount of emulsion was used for the blank sample. The microtiter plate was incubated at 45 °C and the absorbance was measured at 490 nm using a visible/UV microplate kinetics reader (EL x 808, Bio-Tek instruments, Winooski, VT, USA). Readings of all samples were performed immediately (
 <italic class="italic">t</italic> = 0 min) and after 120 min of incubation. The antioxidant activity (AA) of the essential oil was evaluated in term of β-carotene blanching using the following equation: 
 <disp-formula class="disp-formula"> AA% = [(A
  <sub class="sub">0</sub> − A
  <sub class="sub">t</sub>)/A
  <sub class="sub">0</sub>] × 100 
  <label class="label">(3)</label>
 </disp-formula> where A
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> is the absorbance of the control at 0 min and A
 <sub class="sub">t</sub> is the absorbance of the sample (essential oil or BHA) at 120 min. The results are expressed as IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values (μg/mL). The IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values are the concentrations required to inactivate 50% of the preformed peroxyl radicals. All samples were analyzed in triplicate.
</p>
