<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Indeed, several international long-term studies, sponsored by the World Health Organization (WHO), such as the MONICA (monitoring of trends and determinants in cardiovascular disease) study during the 1980s and more recently the PREDIMED (Prevención con Dieta Mediterrénea) Project, revealed the health benefits of wine that was associated with a diet rich in fruits, vegetables, and olive oil, commonly called the Mediterranean diet. The MONICA study has shown that in France, as compared with other western countries (such as the UK or the US), despite a fat-containing diet, a strikingly low incidence of coronary heart diseases was observed and is partly attributed to the moderate consumption of red wine [
 <xref rid="B7-diseases-06-00106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-diseases-06-00106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-diseases-06-00106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. The Mediterranean diet can be described as abundant in plant-based foods such as whole grains, legumes, seeds, fruits, and vegetables, with olive oil the main source of dietary fat; a limited intake of red and processed meat, favoring a low to moderate intake of low-fat dairy and a moderate consumption of fish; and emphasizing regular, but moderate, alcohol (mostly red wine) consumption with meals [
 <xref rid="B10-diseases-06-00106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. The Mediterranean diet has thus gained strong scientific support for providing protection against relevant chronic diseases such as cardiovascular diseases (CVDs), diabetes, as well as protection against some cancers [
 <xref rid="B11-diseases-06-00106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-diseases-06-00106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. These observations have aroused increasing interest in the scientific community in understanding the underlying mechanisms involved. In view of these epidemiological results, it seems essential to standardize studies to describe the effects resulting from a consumption of red wine alone. In this way, to study the potential effect of red wine on cardiovascular events, we have shown an amelioration of blood parameters (decrease in total cholesterol andlow density lipoprotein, LDL); increase in erythrocyte membrane fluidity and antioxidant status) in a group of selected post-myocardial infarct patients receiving 250 mL/day of red wine for 2 weeks, in comparison to patients receiving water in a controlled environment in the hospital [
 <xref rid="B13-diseases-06-00106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. For the first time in a controlled environment, these results reinforced the idea that a moderate consumption of red wine, even for a short period, associated with a ‘‘Western prudent’’ diet, improves various blood parameters in the lipid and antioxidative status in patients with previous coronary ischemic accidents.
</p>
