<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="abstract" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Interest in essential oils was recently revived with their popularity increasing in medicine, pharmacy, and aromatherapy. This study was performed to identify the chemical compositions of the essential oil of
   <span class="italic"> Ruta chalepensis</span> growing wildly in three regions in Palestine and to assess and compare their antimicrobial and antioxidant activities.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Methods</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Identification of the essential oil was performed by gas chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry (GC-MS). Antimicrobial activity was tested against
   <span class="italic"> Staphylococcus aureus</span>,
   <span class="italic"> Escherichia coli</span>,
   <span class="italic"> Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span>, Methicillin-Resistant
   <span class="italic"> Staphylococcus aureus</span>, and
   <span class="italic"> Candida albicans</span> by using minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) assay, while antioxidant activity was analyzed by using the 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) free radical scavenging method.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Results</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> The essential oils of
   <span class="italic"> R. chalepensis</span> from Jerusalem and Hebron regions have almost identical components; the major compounds identified were linalyl acetate and 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-linalool; these essential oils exerted potential antioxidant and antibacterial activities. On the other hand, the major components of the plant essential oil from Jenin region were 2-undecanone and 2-nonanone, which exhibited potential antifungal activity.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Conclusions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> The phytoconstituents and antioxidant and antimicrobial properties of the essential oil of
   <span class="italic"> R. chalepensis</span> from different regions in Palestine were established in this study. The obtained results indicate possible applications for
   <span class="italic"> R. chalepensis</span> in the treatment of various infectious and noninfectious diseases. 
  </p>
 </sec>
</div>
