<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Here we illustrate that sampling approaches from floristic botany and plant ecology capture complementary dimensions of biodiversity. As hypothesized, opportunistic sampling generated a markedly more robust (nearly four times larger) empirical estimate of the greenway’s community species pool than did the transects. Yet, the transects revealed that only three species of introduced grasses comprised 50% of plant cover at the time of sampling. Generating this critical indicator of the greenway’s ecological condition necessarily traded off with a fuller assessment of the species pool. This long-acknowledged trade-off is typically addressed by using rarefaction and accumulation curves and species richness estimators based on transect or plot data [
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Our findings suggest that for sampling designs with limited areal coverage, such tools may not adequately capture the long tail of uncommon species that contribute disproportionately to species richness [
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. This issue was raised by Heilmann-Clausen and Læssøe [
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], who clarified that species accumulation curves and species richness estimators address “how many species will be recorded if [a particular] sampling regime is followed in perpetuity or extended to cover all available habitat,” rather than telling the size of the species pool in the system. Related, Newmaster et al. (2005) illustrated that rarefaction and Chao estimates of common forest moss species reached an asymptote at small sample sizes (25 plots), while estimates of richness for rare species never leveled off. Thus, the very transect- or plot-based studies that often rely on estimator tools to determine the completeness of sampling likely produce underestimates of the true species pool [
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Of course, many ecological questions can be rigorously answered without exhaustive documentation the species pool. Still, it is worthwhile to address these interpretive nuances when presenting results based on species estimators.
</p>
