<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While transects robustly captured patterns associated with functional groups and floristic quality, differences between the sampling approaches arose for Wetland Indicator Status and the presence of uncommon cultivated species. In particular, patchily distributed wetland areas and the obligate wetland species they harbor went largely undetected by the transects. This is a non-trivial miss in a Canal system where episodic drought and various management strategies strongly affect the hydrologic regime and thus persistence of sensitive wetland areas. Transects also failed to detect the nascent incursion of garden plants from adjacent private properties onto the Canal banks, potentially hindering Early Detection and Rapid Response (EDRR) management interventions [
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. These examples illustrate that without knowing the more complete species pool, the ability to thoroughly uncover sensitive ecological conditions along the greenway would be hampered. Still, if only species richness from the floristic inventory were used to assess the greenway, the high abundance of non-native grasses would go unreported. Without these abundance data, it would be impossible to assess costs associated with potential control or revegetation efforts, as well as to relate these dominant grasses to ecological processes of interest. For example, we are currently asking how the implementation of green stormwater infrastructure will affect vegetation along the Canal banks, and in turn, how in situ vegetation will affect stormwater infiltration, retention, and removal of pollutants. We are now positioned to take a two-pronged approach to this question by exploring how the most abundant species might shape stormwater dynamics, while also integrating information about the identity and location of uncommon species likely to be particularly responsive to hydrologic changes (e.g., obligate wetland species) and disturbance from infrastructure installations (e.g., establishing individuals of ruderal non-natives).
</p>
