<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our experience is that physical collections are not often considered by ecological principal investigators as essential to their field protocols (despite substantial movement in this direction by, e.g., the National Ecological Observatory Network). This is partly because it is no small task to integrate the disparate training, project planning, data curation, and analyses implemented in floristic botany and ecology [
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Thus, cross-disciplinary partnerships across non-profit, governmental, and academic institutions are key. We suggest that ecologists reach out to their campus or regional herbaria, connect with curators and collections managers, and dedicate a line item in their research budgets for vouchered floristic (or faunistic) surveys of their study sites (see [
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>] for discussion of under-funding in collections-based research). We similarly suggest that curators and collections managers build relationships with ecology principal investigators and members of their labs, sharing their skills as integral assets to be included a priori into the proper design of biodiversity-focused ecological fieldwork (i.e., it is imperative to quash the “end-user mode” attitude that views botanists as simply providing identification services to those who use their keys and field guides [
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]). For example, gaps in biodiversity data, including both species discovery and ecological monitoring, are high in tropical relative to temperate ecosystems [
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>], and would thus be best addressed by teams of floristic botanists and ecologists. As large-scale digitization of collections data has revealed, there are myriad, previously unimaged ways that natural history collections can inform ecological questions [
 <xref rid="pone.0244982.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. We believe our understanding of biodiversity 100 years from now can only benefit from thoughtful co-exploration of today’s ecosystems by floristic botanists and ecologists.
</p>
