<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The uptake of P and K varied significantly across the experimental years; however, the variation in N uptake in grain over the years was non-significant (
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.t003" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>). Chen et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>] also recorded non-significant difference in maize grain N uptake over two consecutive years of experimentation. The uptake of nutrient (N/ P/ K) and grain yield both were significantly (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> ≤ 0.05) affected by varied NPK levels and/or nutrient omission. Increasing doses of NPK up to 125% of RDF significantly (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> ≤ 0.05) increased the uptake of these macronutrients in maize grain, which is also supported by the results of other maize research [
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Application of 125% RDF might have caused higher nutrient concentration in maize grain, and for the same reason, unlike for the higher doses of NPK (150% RDF), the dilution effect of nutrients was not witnessed in grain [
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. In the present study, nutrient omission (-N/ -P/ -K) caused greater reductions both in nutrient uptake and grain yield, in the order of N omission &gt; K omission &gt; P omission. Such results clearly signify the mode of interaction among these nutrients. Therefore, interaction effect of macronutrients on nutrient uptake and grain yield was in the order of (N × K) &gt; (N × P) &gt; (P × K). Several investigators have already proved the positive interaction of N and K [
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>] and negative interaction of P with K [
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. The present study also observed the similar trend. Limited availability of N exacerbates the K dilution in maize plant [
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Higher absorption of P in the lower concentrations of K is believed to be due to high mobility of K. On the contrary, when K is present in the higher concentrations, it will tend to depress the absorption of other ions [
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. Several workers have reported positive interaction between N and P, which leads to increase in P absorption and higher yields due to undefined soil and plant related mechanisms [
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. Our results confirm that grain yield increased up to 125% RDF, and it was statistically at par with 100% RDF. However, further increase in NPK levels (150% RDF) failed to record any significant improvement. Such effects have also been confirmed in our previous study [
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>].
</p>
