<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.2.4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.4. Phytochemistry</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">(1) Active Ingredient</span>. Nearly sixty natural cannabinoids have been identified in the plant. They are non-nitrogen phenol derivatives of benzopyran. The main ones are cannabidiol (CBD), cannabinol, Δ9-trans-tetrahydrocannabinol (THC), Δ8-trans-tetrahydrocannabinol (Δ8-THC), and Δ8- and Δ9-tetrahydrocannabinolic acids.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main psychoactive component of cannabis is THC, a major psychodysleptic, more active in its levorotatory form.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to cannabinoids, cannabis smoke contains many other substances: carbon monoxide, phenols, acrolein, acetaldehyde, toluene, vinyl chloride, cresols, cyanides, acetone, ammonia, benzopyrene, benzanthracene, dimethylnitrosamine, methylethylnitrosamine, and so on, which also exhibit toxicity.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">(2) Chemical Structure</span>. CBD has the same chemical formula and molecular weight as THC (C
  <sub>21</sub>H
  <sub>30</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>, 314.46 g/mol), although its molecular structure is slightly different (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4</a>). Like THC and most other lipids, CBD is hydrophobic and lipophilic, which means that it does not dissolve in water and cannot be converted into an aqueous emulsion but dissolves in the fat (as well as in most organic solvents such as butane and alcohol).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In an acid medium, CBD is cyclized (it forms a new carbon ring) to become THC. In an alkaline medium (in the presence of water), CBD is oxidized to become cannabidiol-hydroxyquinone, which has been the subject of few studies to date but may have an inhibitory effect on liver enzymes (liver) that are vital for the metabolism of ingested drugs.</p>
</sec>
