<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.5.4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5.4. Phytochemistry</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">(1) Active Ingredient</span>. The active ingredient is a lectin: ricin, which interferes with protein synthesis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ricin content in castor seeds varies from 1 to 10% [
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">34</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Castor seeds contain about 50–70% of an oil, a triglyceride whose fatty acid chains are composed of almost 90% ricinoleic acid, which is remarkable consistency. Oleic and linoleic acids are the other two significant compounds, although present in much smaller quantities: they represent, respectively, about 4 and 3% of the fatty acid chains. The other very minor compounds are palmitic, stearic, and linoleic acids, which each represent less than 1%. It is noted that pure ricin is not available [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>, 
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">32</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">(2) Chemical Structure</span>. Ricin belongs to the ribosome inactivating protein family (RIP) whose main molecular target is the ribosome.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is a glycoprotein of high molecular weight (molecular weight of about 63 kDa), composed of two subunits, A and B, of glycoprotein nature. The A chain (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig7" href="#fig7">Figure 7</a>, blue), an enzyme, inactivates the 28S subunit of ribosomes of eukaryotic cells and, therefore, inhibits protein synthesis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Meanwhile, subunit B (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig7" href="#fig7">Figure 7</a> orange), a lectin, binds toxin to cell membranes having galactosylated sites as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig8" href="#fig8">Figure 8</a> [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>, 
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">34</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
