<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. 
  <span class="italic">Peganum harmala</span>
 </div>
 <sec id="sec3.3.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.1. Botanical Study</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The harmel is a herbaceous plant, perennial, glabrous, and bushy, from 30 to 90 centimeters in height with a thick rhizome, with strong and unpleasant odor.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The erect stems, very ramous, disappear in winter; they bear alternate leaves, cut into narrow strips.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The solitary flowers, rather large (25 to 30 mm), of a yellowish white veined with green are formed of
   <div list-type="roman-lower" class="list">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>five green, linear, persistent sepals that extend beyond the corolla,</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>five elliptical petals,</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>ten to fifteen stamens with a very broad mesh in their lower part,</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>the ovary, globular, resting on a fleshy disc and ending with a fruit which is a spherical capsule, with three boxes, 6 to 8 mm depressed at the top, surrounded by persistent sepals and opening with 3 or 4 valves for release the seeds.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> The seeds, many, small, angular, subtriangular, dark brown in color, with an external integument, have a bitter taste; and they are harvested in summer [
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">26</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.3.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.2. Biogeography</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Its normal habitat is semiarid rangelands, steppe areas, and sandy soils. The plant is widely distributed in Central Asia, North Africa, and the Middle East and has been introduced to America and Australia [
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">27</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.3.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.3. Toxic Part(s)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The whole plant is toxic via an alkaloid whose rate is higher in the seed (3 to 4%) than in the root or stem (0.36%) or the leaf (0.52%).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The toxicity appears for 3 g of ground seeds. The alkaloid content increases in summer, during the ripening phase of the fruit, at the time of harvest of the seed [
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">26</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.3.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.4. Phytochemistry</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">(1) Active Substances</span>. The main toxins are the alkaloids whose chemical structure is associated with an indole nucleus with a pyridinol: harmane, harmine, harmaline, and harmalol (= harmol) [
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">28</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">(2) Chemical Structure</span>. The toxins have the same indole structure derived from tryptophan which associates an indole ring with a pyridine ring. The harmaline is a methoxy-harmalol and a dihydroharmine; it constitutes 2/3 of the total alkaloids of the seed; it would be twice as toxic as the harmine (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Figure 5</a>) [
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">28</a>].
   <div list-type="roman-lower" class="list">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Harmane (a): C
      <sub>12</sub>H
      <sub>10</sub>N
      <sub>2</sub>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Harmine (b): C
      <sub>13</sub>H
      <sub>12</sub>N
      <sub>2</sub>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Harmaline (c): C
      <sub>13</sub>H
      <sub>14</sub>N
      <sub>2</sub>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Harmalol (harmol) (d): C
      <sub>12</sub>H
      <sub>12</sub>N
      <sub>2</sub>.
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
