<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. 
  <span class="italic">Atractylis gummifera</span>
 </div>
 <sec id="sec3.1.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.1. Botanical Study</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The glutton thistle is a perennial herbaceous plant with a voluminous, sweeping, fleshy rhizome 30 to 40 centimeters long. It has deeply cut leaves in spiky lobes grouped in a rosette. The pink flowers are grouped in capitula surrounded by bracts bristling with spines. After fruiting, a yellowish white latex exudes in the armpit of bracts [
   <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>]. The fruit is achene hairy, ellipsoidal, and surmounted by a white egret [
   <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.1.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.2. Biogeography</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Atractylis gummifera</span> is a thistle distributed throughout the world but particularly abundant in the Mediterranean regions.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In northern Africa (Algeria, Morocco, and Tunisia) and in southern Europe (Italy, Greece, Spain, and Portugal) [
   <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This species is found throughout Morocco except in desert or arid regions and Anti-Atlas [
   <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.1.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.3. Toxic Part(s)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All parts of the plant contain the toxic principles of the glue thistle. These parts, in order to decrease concentration, are root, stem, bracts, flower, seed, and leaf. The aerial parts of the plant are the least toxic [
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.1.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.4. Phytochemistry</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">(1) Active Ingredient</span>. The toxic principles of the glutton are diterpene-derived heterosides derived from kaurene. The genome of the major compound carboxyatractyloside (ATR) (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3(a)</a>), or gummiferin, is substituted at C-4 with 2 carboxyls and at 2 and 15 with 2 hydroxyls. The saccharide part of the molecule consists of a desulfated glucose at 3′ and 4′ and acylated at 2′ by an isovaleric acid.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The other compound: atractyloside is C-4 monocarboxylic (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3(b)</a>) [
   <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">(2) Chemical Structure</span>. See 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The amount of ATR varies from 0.12 to 1.57% depending on the source and the season [
   <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">11</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
