<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <bold>Micro-well dilution assay. </bold>For the preparation of bacterial inoculants (5.00 × 10
 <sup>6 </sup>CFU per mL), one isolated colony of each bacteria were inoculated into a tube containing 5.00 mL of Mueller-Hinton broth (MHB; Quelab) medium and incubated at 37.00 ˚C for 20 hr. The second transfer of 0.10 mL of cultures into 5.00 mL of MHB was grown in 37.00 ˚C for 20 hr. After twice incubation, the number of bacterial colonies was enumerated by serial dilution and plating on MHA in triplicate. The broth microdilution method was used to determine the MIC and the minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) according to the guideline of the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute with some modifications.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
 </sup> First, 10.00% (v/v) DMSO as an emulsifier of the essential oils was added in MHB medium. Different concentrations of the essential oils were set up in MHB medium containing DMSO. The sterile 96-well microplates were prepared and briefly 160 μL of MHB containing DMSO, 20.00 μL of different concentrations of the essential oils (final concentration in each well: 0.01 to 4.40%) or sodium benzoate (the equivalent of 0.01 to 4.40% in each well) and 20.00 μL of inoculum diluted in MHB with 5.00 × 10
 <sup>6 </sup>CFU per mL of the bacteria were inoculated into each well to achieve a concentration of 10
 <sup>5</sup> CFU per well. The last well as a positive control contained 180 μL of MHB containing DMSO and 20.00 μL of bacterial inoculum without essential oil or sodium benzoate. For negative control, an un-inoculated MHB containing DMSO was designed. The plates were prepared in triplicates. Then, contents of each well were mixed on a plate shaker at 300 rpm for 20 sec and incubated at 37.00 ˚C for 24 hr. The plates were placed in a wet container to ensure that the bacteria did not get dehydrated during incubation. For combination effects of sodium benzoate with essential oils, the procedure presented above was used, however, 140 μL of MHB containing DMSO, 20.00 μL of different concentrations sodium benzoate (final concentration in each well: 0.01 to 4.40%) with 20.00 μL of the equivalent of half MIC of the essential oils in a well for each bacteria and 20.00 μL of the bacterial inoculum were added into each well. The concentration of the first well without turbidity was considered as MIC. The MIC was determined as the lowest concentration of the essential oil or sodium benzoate that inhibited the growth of the bacteria. To detect MBC, the contents of the non-growth or clear wells were cultured on MHA plates and incubated at 37.00 ˚C for 24 hr. Afterward, the colonies were counted. The MBC was defined as the lowest concentration in which no bacterial growth was detectable on the plates. These procedures were repeated for three times and the average of the three values was calculated to provide the MIC and MBC values.
</p>
