<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_ISCI409 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEgr6 jpg ?><?FILEgr7 jpg ?><?FILEgr8 jpg ?><?FILEgr9 jpg ?><?FILEgr10 jpg ?><?FILEgr11 jpg ?><?FILEgr12 jpg ?><?FILEgr13 jpg ?><?FILEgr14 jpg ?><?FILEgr15 jpg ?><?FILEgr16 jpg ?><?FILEfx1 jpg ?><?FILEfx2 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 pdf ?><?FILEsi1 gif ?><?FILEsi2 gif ?><?FILEsi3 gif ?><?FILEsi4 gif ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">iScience</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">iScience</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>iScience</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2589-0042</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6532020</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2589-0042(19)30144-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.isci.2019.05.007</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Design of Nickel Supported on Water-Tolerant Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> Catalysts for the Hydrotreating of Lignin Streams Obtained from Lignin-First Biorefining</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>Glauco F.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>S&#x000e9;rgio</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gra&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>In&#x000ea;s</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carrer</surname><given-names>Heloise</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>Dean H.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Teixeira-Neto</surname><given-names>Erico</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Curvelo</surname><given-names>Antonio Aprigio S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rodella</surname><given-names>Cristiane B.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>Roberto</given-names></name><email>rrinaldi@ic.ac.uk</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">6</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Chemical Engineering, Imperial College London, South Kensington Campus, London SW7 2AZ, UK</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Physical Chemistry, Institute of Chemistry of S&#x000e3;o Carlos, University of S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Av. Trabalhador S&#x000e3;o Carlense, 400, S&#x000e3;o Carlos, S&#x000e3;o Paulo 13566-590, Brazil</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Brazilian Synchrotron Light Laboratory (LNLS), Brazilian Center for Research in Energy and Materials (CNPEM), Campinas, S&#x000e3;o Paulo 13083-970, Brazil</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Brazilian Nanotechnology National Laboratory (LNNano), Brazilian Center for Research in Energy and Materials (CNPEM), Campinas, S&#x000e3;o Paulo 13083-970, Brazil</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>School of Chemistry, University of the Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, South Africa</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author <email>rrinaldi@ic.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>6</label><p id="ntpara0010">Lead Contact</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>09</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>29</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><title>Summary</title><p>In biomass conversion, Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> has attracted increasing attention as a catalyst support presenting water-tolerant Lewis acid sites. Herein, we address the design of Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts for hydrotreating of lignin to hydrocarbons. To optimize the balance between acidic and hydrogenating properties, the catalysts were first evaluated in the hydrotreating of diphenyl ether. The best catalyst candidate was further explored in the conversion of lignin oil obtained by catalytic upstream biorefining of poplar. As primary products, cycloalkanes were obtained, demonstrating the potential of Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts for the lignin-to-fuels route. However, the Lewis acidity of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> also catalyzes coke formation via lignin species condensation. Thereby, an acidity threshold should be found so that dehydration reactions essential to the hydrotreatment are not affected, but the condensation of lignin species prevented. This article provides a critical &#x0201c;beginning-to-end&#x0201d; analysis of aspects crucial to the catalyst design to produce lignin biofuels.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Graphical Abstract</title><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="fx1"/></fig></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0020"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0010">Stable Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst for the hydrotreating of diphenyl ether produced</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0015">Key challenge in the design of solid catalysts for the HDO of lignin streams identified</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0020">Lewis acidity crucial to HDO also assists catalyst deactivation via coke formation</p></list-item><list-item id="u0025"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0025">Recommendations for the catalyst design for lignin hydrotreating put forward</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0025"><p>Catalysis; Biofuel; Energy Materials</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Subject Areas</title><kwd>Catalysis</kwd><kwd>Biofuel</kwd><kwd>Energy Materials</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><p id="misc0010">Published: May 31, 2019</p></notes></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0030">Niobia (Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>) has attracted a great deal of attention for catalytic applications in aqueous media owing to its water-tolerant Lewis acidity (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Barrios et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Brayner and Bozon-Verduraz, 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Chan et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Chary et&#x000a0;al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Francisco et&#x000a0;al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Gra&#x000e7;a et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Guan et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Herval et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Holtzberg et&#x000a0;al., 1957</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Jasik et&#x000a0;al., 2005</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Ko et&#x000a0;al., 1984</xref>, <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Lopes et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Nakajima et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>, <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Rojas et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>, <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Solcova et&#x000a0;al., 1993</xref>, <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Tanabe and Okazaki, 1995</xref>, <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Valencia-Balv&#x000ed;n et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Wojcieszak et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>). Generally, amorphous Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> shows high surface acidity, which is related to its high specific surface area and number of surface defects (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">do Prado and Oliveira, 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Ziolek and Sobczak, 2017</xref>). However, amorphous Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> is a fragile material, susceptible to changes by temperature and pressure (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Pinto et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Wojcieszak et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>). Considering Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> crystalline phases, they are formed by distorted octahedra (NbO<sub>6</sub>), connected by edges and corners. The distortion degree of NbO<sub>6</sub> octahedra depends on the polymorph structure (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Nico et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Pinto et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Valencia-Balv&#x000ed;n et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). This distortion leads to varied textural and structural stabilities as well as different surface acid properties and, therefore, impacts on catalytic properties. H-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> (monoclinic structure) and T-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> (orthorhombic structure) are the most common crystalline phases, whereas the TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> (pseudohexagonal structure) is the least thermodynamically stable phase and is often considered as a less ordered form of the T-phase. By increasing the temperature and pressure in hydrothermal synthesis, the conversion of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> phases takes place following the sequence: amorphous Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> &#x02192; TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> &#x02192; T-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> &#x02192; H-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Nowak and Ziolek, 1999</xref>, <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Pinto et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Valencia-Balv&#x000ed;n et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> phase transitions are typically followed by a progressive decrease in the surface area, porosity, and acidity (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ali et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Gra&#x000e7;a et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Kreissl et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Pinto et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Raba et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Valencia-Balv&#x000ed;n et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). Among the crystalline phases, the TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> phase is the one presenting the highest number of oxygen vacancies in the structure, and so the greatest degree of polyhedral distortion (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Pinto et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Rani et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> is characterized by the presence of distorted octahedra and pentagonal and hexagonal bipyramids, i.e., NbO<sub>6</sub>, NbO<sub>7</sub>, and NbO<sub>8</sub> polyhedra, which are the structural units also present in amorphous Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Nakajima et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Nico et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). Notably, TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> structural features translate into a highly polarized and disordered surface with high levels of Lewis and Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites, which are essential to the high performance of hydrodeoxygenation (HDO) catalysts.</p><p id="p0035">Metal-based (mainly Pt, Pd, Ru, Ni) catalysts supported on acidic materials have been widely examined in the HDO of lignin model compounds (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Cui et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Shao et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Teles et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Rinaldi, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et&#x000a0;al., 2009</xref>). For the HDO of lignin model compounds and lignin streams, niobium oxides have&#x000a0;been studied as supports for noble metals (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Shao et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Studies on multifunctional Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>/Co/Re catalysts have also been reported (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Parvulescu et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Pd catalysts supported on niobia revealed promising results for the dehydroxylation of phenol to benzene, presenting a reaction rate 90-fold higher than that observed for a Pd/SiO<sub>2</sub> catalyst (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Barrios et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Importantly, Pt/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>-Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> has been reported as an active catalyst for the hydrotreating of diphenyl ether, showing stability higher than that of Pt/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> owing to the water-tolerant nature of niobium(V) Lewis acid sites (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Jeon et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>). Subjecting lignin-derived dimers to a Ni<sub>0.92</sub>Nb<sub>0.08</sub> catalyst resulted in full conversion of the substrates into liquid alkanes at 200&#x000b0;C after 2 h, demonstrating the outstanding ability of this material for C&#x02013;O cleavage and HDO (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Jin et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). For the selective production of arenes from lignin, it was reported that Ru-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts present unique catalytic properties, compared with Ru supported on traditional oxide supports (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Shao et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="p0040">In an approach for lignin-to-liquid fuels, one of the challenges is to design inexpensive catalysts with high activity, selectivity, and stability under process conditions. Since the hydrotreating of lignin streams releases water, the solid catalyst must be stable in the presence of water under high-severity conditions. Commercial niobia (Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>&#x022c5;xH<sub>2</sub>O) is a bulk amorphous material that lacks stability under hydrothermal conditions, thus losing surface area and leading to the sintering of supported metallic particles (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Pham et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>). To overcome the poor structural stability of commercial Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>, various synthesis methods have been a subject of research in producing highly stable nanostructured materials (<xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et&#x000a0;al., 2012b</xref>). Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanoparticles with no defined shape can be obtained by precipitation and sol-gel synthesis methods followed by calcination. These routes have extensively been studied in the preparation of the Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> supports applied to the HDO of lignin and lignin-derived molecules with good results (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Shao et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> crystallization under low-severity solvothermal conditions constitutes another progress in this field. This synthetic route produces single TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods with controlled size and morphology, high surface area, and improved acid properties (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ali et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Leite et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods exhibit shape-dependent acidic sites (<xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et&#x000a0;al., 2012a</xref>). On (001) TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> surface of the nanorods, Lewis acid sites are much stronger than those of spherical Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> particles. Despite the interesting acidic properties, the production of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods employs oleic acid and trioctylamine as structure-directing agents in the solvothermal synthesis. Especially for catalytic applications, the use of such structure-directing agents surfactants in the synthesis of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> presents disadvantages owing to their high costs, low volume of material production limitation, and the need to remove the agents via calcination, which may modify the morphology, particle size, and surface chemistry of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ali et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et&#x000a0;al., 2012a</xref>).</p><p id="p0045">Hydrothermal synthesis of TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods in the presence of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> represents a route receiving far less attention, but with the most promising results regarding the textural and acidic properties of niobia (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Leal et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>). Despite the improved chemical and physical properties, such Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods have not yet been explored in the chemistry of lignin hydrotreating. Therefore, this knowledge gap brought us to the study of nickel supported on hydrothermally stable TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods as a potential catalyst for HDO of lignin streams. As about 80% of the primary interunit linkages of lignin are ether bonds (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Rinaldi et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>), and a considerable number of other oxygenated functionalities are present in lignin-derived phenolics, a highly stable and highly acidic niobia could well hold the key to produce efficient catalysts for lignin-to-liquid fuels, owing to an expected synergism between metal phase and support toward lignin depolymerization and acid-catalyzed deoxygenation of intermediates formed throughout the HDO course (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Cao et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Rinaldi, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Rinaldi, 2013</xref>).</p><p id="p0050">In this report, we examine the catalytic properties of Ni-supported on TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods for the hydrotreating of a model compound (diphenyl ether) and lignin oil produced by a lignin-first biorefining process based on H-transfer reductive processes, the so-called catalytic upstream biorefining (CUB), which is also denoted as &#x02018;<italic>reductive catalytic fractionation</italic>&#x02019; (RCF) by several research groups. CUB constitutes a class of methods for deconstruction of lignocellulose that renders high-quality pulps together with depolymerized and passivated lignin streams (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Ferrini and Rinaldi, 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Galkin and Samec, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Gra&#x000e7;a et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Renders et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Rinaldi, 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Schutyser et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Sultan et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Rinaldi et al., 2019</xref>). TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods were prepared via hydrothermal synthesis by employing ammonium niobium oxalate and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> as the structure-directing agent (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Leal et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Leite et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Pavia et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods were then loaded with several Ni contents. In this report, the results and discussion are organized as follows. First, the characterizations of the as-synthesized TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods and Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts are briefly presented. Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts are subsequently applied to the HDO of diphenyl ether at 160&#x000b0;C and 200&#x000b0;C under 4 MPa H<sub>2</sub>. The catalyst performance and stability in the HDO of diphenyl ether at 200&#x000b0;C under 4 MPa H<sub>2</sub> were assessed. Finally, under more severe conditions (300&#x000b0;C and 7 MPa H<sub>2</sub>), the 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst was applied to the hydrotreating of the lignin oil.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Characterizations of Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> Catalysts</title><p id="p0055"><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref> shows the X-ray diffraction (XRD) patterns obtained from both the hydrothermally as-synthesized Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> after calcination at 380&#x000b0;C and Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts reduced at 320&#x000b0;C. XRD pattern of the Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> support exhibits peaks characteristic of the pseudohexagonal TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> phase (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Ko and Weissman, 1990</xref>). Notably, a high-intensity signal is observed at 22.8&#x000b0;, which is associated with (001) reflection of TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>. In addition, a low-intensity and broad signal related to the (100) plane appears at 28.0&#x000b0;. As next confirmed by scanning transmission electron microscopic (STEM) imaging, a preferred growth of TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> along the (001) direction creates the preferential orientation feature in the XRD pattern, indicating the formation of TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> as nanorods (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ali et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). For the Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> materials, the XRD patterns demonstrated that the structural features of the TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> phase were preserved after the reduction procedure. Hence, for simplicity, when referring to the materials produced in this study, the TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> phase will be denoted as &#x0201c;Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>&#x0201d; henceforth. As expected, Ni(111) and Ni (200) reflections are observed at 44.6&#x000b0; and 52.1&#x000b0;. These reflections become more intense and sharper with an increase in Ni content from 5 to 25&#x000a0;wt %. Considering the Ni(111) reflection, the average Ni crystallite sizes estimated by the Scherrer equation grow from 7 to 15&#x000a0;nm with the rise in Ni content from 5 to 25 wt % (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>XRD Patterns of TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> and Reduced Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> Catalysts</p><p>The asterisks indicate Ni(111) and Ni (200) reflections at 44.6&#x000b0; and 52.1&#x000b0;, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Ni Content, Ni Crystallite Size, and Textural Properties of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> and Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> Materials</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Sample</th><th>Actual Ni Content (%)<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></th><th>Average Ni Crystallite Size (nm)<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></th><th>BET Surface Area (m<sup>2</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td align="char">196</td></tr><tr><td>5%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char">4.8</td><td align="char">7</td><td align="char">219</td></tr><tr><td>10%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char">9.4</td><td align="char">12</td><td align="char">181</td></tr><tr><td>15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char">13.9</td><td align="char">14</td><td align="char">180</td></tr><tr><td>25%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char">23.8</td><td align="char">15</td><td align="char">141</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0015">Determined by inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (ICP-MS) analysis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn2"><label>b</label><p id="ntpara0020">Estimated by XRD by applying the Scherrer equation to the reflection of Ni(111) at 44.6&#x000b0;.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn3"><label>c</label><p id="ntpara0025">Determined by N<sub>2</sub> physisorption measurements at &#x02212;196&#x000b0;C.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0060">To verify whether the synthesis rendered Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods, the Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> material was examined by using high-angle annular dark-field (HAADF)-STEM (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>). The HAADF-STEM images show that the hydrothermal synthesis produced Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods with approximately 8&#x02013;25&#x000a0;nm length and 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;nm width (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Leal et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>). The nanorod dimensions are in line with those of previous studies showing that the crystal growth in the hydrothermal method follows an oriented attachment mechanism (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Leite et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>), producing nanorods smaller than those synthesized in the presence of a surfactant as a shape-directing agent. In fact, surfactant-based syntheses yield large particles, owing to a decrease in the rate of crystal growth (<xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et&#x000a0;al., 2012a</xref>). In turn, longer (200&#x02013;500&#x000a0;nm) and thinner (5&#x02013;20&#x000a0;nm) TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> nanorods were produced by a synthesis employing oleic acid as a structure-directing agent and ammonium niobium oxalate hydrate as the starting material (<xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et&#x000a0;al., 2012b</xref>).<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>HAADF-STEM Images of TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> Nanorods</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p><p id="p0065"><xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes the textural properties of the support and Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> materials. N<sub>2</sub> adsorption-desorption isotherms are presented in <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S1</xref>. Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> and Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> materials exhibit a type II isotherm with an H3 hysteresis (<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Thommes et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>), corroborating the non-structural porosity created by the packing of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods. Niobium oxide nanoparticles can be obtained by various synthesis methods, which leads to the preparation of materials of different shapes with Brunauer-Emmett-Teller (BET) specific surface areas that can range from about 20 m<sup>2</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 530 m<sup>2</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>(<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Luisa Marin et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Morais et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Shao et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows the as-synthesized Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> support to possess a relatively high specific surface area (196 m<sup>2</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Notably, no significant decrease in the surface area of Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> materials, with 5&#x02013;15 wt % Ni loading on Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> was observed. Likewise, as the porosity of the Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> support is non-structural, the deposition of Ni phase onto the nest of nanorods does not significantly decrease the specific surface area. However, for 25%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>, the specific surface area slightly decreased (from 196 m<sup>2</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to 141 m<sup>2</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>).</p><p id="p0070">Temperature-programmed reduction (TPR) profiles of the Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods and Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> precursors (catalysts before reduction) are shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>. The TPR profiles of Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> precursors exhibit two reduction events. The first occurs at around 335&#x000b0;C. This event is assigned to the reduction of Ni(II) to Ni(0). The reduction temperature of the Ni(II) species supported on Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods is much lower than that of bulk NiO (450&#x000b0;C) (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Gra&#x000e7;a et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). Nevertheless, the range of Ni reduction temperatures between 320&#x000b0;C and 345&#x000b0;C is in line with previous studies on Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> materials containing high nickel loadings (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Jankovi&#x00107; et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Liu et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). Interestingly, and contrary to what has been previously observed by other research groups (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Chary et&#x000a0;al., 2003</xref>, <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Wojcieszak et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>), no shift of the Ni reduction peak to higher temperatures with an increase in Ni loading was observed. As will be presented later, in the 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> material, the Ni nanoparticles are embedded in a nest formed by Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods (<xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;11</xref>). Thereby, such an entanglement of metal phase and oxidic support may result in few (but strong) connecting points between these phases so that an effect of the increase in the Ni loading on the reduction temperature of NiO species is not apparently observed. However, in the second reduction (at about 800&#x000b0;C), which is related to the partial reduction of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> to NbO<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Wojcieszak et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>), the temperature required for the reduction of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> progressively decreases (from 870&#x000b0;C to 816&#x000b0;C) with increasing Ni content (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>). This observation indicates that there is an interaction between Ni and NbO<sub>5</sub> phases in which the hydrogen spillover appears to be more prevalent for the samples containing higher Ni loadings.<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>H<sub>2</sub>-TPR Profiles for Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> Support and Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> Catalyst Precursors</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p><p id="p0075">Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> polymorph crystals are formed by distorted octahedra (NbO<sub>6</sub>) connected by edges and corners, the degree of distortion depending on the polymorph structure (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Nico et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Pinto et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Valencia-Balv&#x000ed;n et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). In the TT-Nb<sub>2</sub>O phase, the highly distorted octahedra (NbO<sub>6</sub>) units exhibit Nb=O bonds, enabling the Nb(V) center to act as a Lewis acid site. In turn, the slighted distorted NbO<sub>6</sub>, as well as NbO<sub>7</sub> and NbO<sub>8</sub> groups, only present Nb-O bonds, which provide scaffolding for the [Nb(V)---OH<sub>2</sub><sup>2+</sup>] Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Chan et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). In this study, we found the quantity of Lewis acid sites on Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> (210&#x000a0;&#x003bc;mol g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) to be higher than that of Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites (143&#x000a0;&#x003bc;mol g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S2</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref>).</p><p id="p0080">To assess the nature of the acidic sites of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> support and Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts (after the reduction procedure), attenuated total reflection (ATR)-Fourier transform infrared (FTIR) spectra of adsorbed pyridine (Py) were collected (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4</xref>). We chose to assess the nature of acid sites by ATR technique because of the dark color of the activated Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>, which hinders FTIR transmission experiments (as those performed on the Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> support). Pyridine adsorbed on the materials exhibits infrared (IR) bands at around 1,446&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 1,606&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. These bands are related to the Py coordinated to Lewis acid sites. In addition, the IR spectra show bands at 1,639&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 1,540&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, which are assigned to the formation of the pyridinium ion (PyH<sup>+</sup>) on Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4</xref>) (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Datka, 1992</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Dollish et&#x000a0;al., 1974</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Iizuka et&#x000a0;al., 1983</xref>, <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Parry, 1963</xref>). An IR band of adsorbed Py common to both Lewis and Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites is also visible at 1,489&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. These observations indicate that both Lewis and Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites are present in the Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods. From the relative intensities of Py adsorbed on Lewis and Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites, it can be inferred that the Br&#x000f8;nsted acidity decreases as the Ni loading increases, as indicated by the reduction in the intensities of the bands at 1,639&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 1,540&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. This finding is explained by the ion exchange of Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites by the positively charged Ni species. However, in the 25%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst, the support still presents some residual Br&#x000f8;nsted acidity. Notably, the Lewis acidity (bands at around 1,606&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 1,446&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) appears to be mostly preserved even at such a high loading of Ni on Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods.<fig id="fig4"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>ATR-FTIR Spectra of Absorbed Pyridine on Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> and Reduced Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> Catalysts</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p><p id="p0085">Acid supports are active in the dehydration of cyclohexanol to cyclohexene and, therefore, are vital to the hydrotreating of lignin to alkanes and arenes (<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Rinaldi, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et&#x000a0;al., 2009</xref>). Hence, to further assess the effect of Ni loading on the acidic properties of the catalysts, cyclohexanol dehydration was carried out at 200&#x000b0;C. As will be presented in the next section, this reaction is key to produce cyclohexane from the conversion of diphenyl ether, as well as to obtain cycloalkanes from lignin. <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> summarizes the cyclohexanol conversion values obtained after 30&#x000a0;min of reaction at 200&#x000b0;C.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Cyclohexanol Conversion as a Function of Ni Amount Deposited on Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Catalyst</th><th>Cyclohexanol Conversion (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>No added catalyst</td><td align="char">3</td></tr><tr><td>Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char">75</td></tr><tr><td>5%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char">40</td></tr><tr><td>10%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char">37</td></tr><tr><td>15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char">31</td></tr><tr><td>25%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char">31</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0090">As expected, for the Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods, cyclohexanol conversion is considerably high. However, cyclohexanol conversion significantly decreases in the presence of 5%Ni/Ni<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst. By increasing Ni loadings, cyclohexanol conversion continually drops, plateauing at 31% for 25%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>. These results show that the activity of the catalysts is partially affected by Ni deposition. Overall, the results presented in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref> indicate that the decrease in Br&#x000f8;nsted acidity is detrimental to the dehydration performance. These results confirm that, at promoting the dehydration of cyclohexanol, Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites are more active for alcohol dehydration than the Lewis acid sites (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Foo et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Hydrodeoxygenation of Diphenyl Ether</title><p id="p0095">The catalytic performance of the Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts was evaluated for the conversion of diphenyl ether as a model reaction. The cleavage of diphenyl ether serves as a model reaction for the breakdown of 4-O-5 ether linkages occurring in lignins. Owing to its high bond dissociation enthalpy (BDE: 330&#x000a0;kJ mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), the 4-O-5 linkages are resistant against cleavage via non-catalytic thermal processes, compared with &#x003b1;-O-4 and &#x003b2;-O-4 ether linkages occurring both in native and technical lignins (BDE: 215&#x000a0;kJ mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for &#x003b1;-O-4 in phenylcoumaran subunits, and 290&#x02013;305&#x000a0;kJ mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for &#x003b2;-O-4 in lignin's aryl alkyl ether-bonding motifs) (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Dorrestijn et&#x000a0;al., 2000</xref>, <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Parthasarathi et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Rinaldi et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Rinaldi, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Younker et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>). Therefore, the ability of a Ni catalyst for hydrogenolysis can be evaluated with little contribution of thermolysis to the overall reaction results. In this instance, diphenyl ether is also a useful model compound for another reason. It allows for the evaluation of the activity of the Ni phase toward hydrogenation of phenol and benzene, the intermediates formed by the hydrogenolysis of diphenyl ether. In the presence of acid sites, the intermediate mixture is ultimately funneled to cyclohexane, as schematically represented by the reaction network presented in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;5</xref>.<fig id="fig5"><label>Figure&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Reaction Pathways Proposed for the Hydrotreating of Diphenyl Ether into Cyclohexane in the Presence of a Bifunctional Catalyst ([M] and [A] Stand for Metal and Acid Sites, Respectively)</p><p>In the reaction network, three ether linkages, with distinct reactivities toward hydrogenolysis catalyzed by Ni sites, are formed. The progressive saturation of diphenyl ether reduces the reactivity of the ether linkage toward hydrogenolysis over Ni sites (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">He et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>). Noteworthy, Ni catalysts are typically inactive for the cleavage of dialkyl ethers. Thereby, the hypothetical pathway for the HDO of dicyclohexyl ether will require acid sites to start and proceed via hydrolysis &#x02192; dehydration &#x02192; hydrogenation to yield cyclohexane. This pathway is, however, not followed under the reaction conditions of this study. In this manner, dicyclohexyl ether accumulated in the reaction mixtures. For clarity, cyclohexene was not numbered but indicated by an asterisk, as this intermediate is consumed upon its formation so that it is not detected in the reaction mixtures.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p><p id="p0100">To investigate the different catalyst functionalities, the hydrotreating of diphenyl ether was carried out at two temperatures, 160&#x000b0;C and 200&#x000b0;C. These two conditions were chosen because dehydration of alcohols has significant enthalpic barriers for the formation of carbocations (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Liu et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>), meaning that relatively high temperatures are required for the alcohol dehydration. By this choice, the hydrogenolysis and hydrogenation extents can be better discerned in the experiments carried out at 160&#x000b0;C, whereas the performance for the full HDO of diphenyl ether is better addressed by the experiments performed at 200&#x000b0;C.</p><p id="p0105">When targeting cycloalkanes, the results of a model compound reaction can be more conveniently compared by computing the HDO extent and degree of deoxygenation (DOD), as given by <xref rid="fd1" ref-type="disp-formula">Equations 1</xref> and <xref rid="fd2" ref-type="disp-formula">2</xref>, respectively (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Rinaldi, 2015</xref>).<disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(Equation&#x000a0;1)</label><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.gif"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(Equation&#x000a0;2)</label><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.gif"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="p0110"><xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref>A compares the performance of the Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> by evaluating the HDO extent achieved by the reaction network as a function of time for the conversion of diphenyl ether at 160&#x000b0;C. As expected, an increase in HDO extent with time for all tested catalysts was observed. By analyzing the results obtained at 180&#x000a0;min (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref>B), the HDO extent increased linearly from 28% to 46% with the rise in the Ni content (from 5 to 25 wt %). On the other hand, as expected at this temperature, low DOD was obtained for all catalysts at 180&#x000a0;min, with a decrease being in general noticed with the increase in Ni content, owing to the decline in the Br&#x000f8;nsted acidity, as previously discussed. In these experiments, conversions of diphenyl ether in the range of 55%&#x02013;98% at 180&#x000a0;min were achieved (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref>B). A blank test and a catalytic run with the pure Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> were also carried out (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S3</xref>). By stark contrast, in these control experiments, only very low conversion of diphenyl ether (8% and 15%, respectively) was achieved at 180&#x000a0;min, with no selectivity to a specific product. Furthermore, to verify whether there is a contribution of the leached species to the reactions, the catalyst 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> was contacted with the solvent under the same conditions of the reaction. After this, the catalyst was separated from the liquid product, and then diphenyl ether and the internal standard were added to the reaction media for reaction run. The results were similar to those of the blank reaction, confirming that the catalytic process is exclusively taking place on the catalyst surface.<fig id="fig6"><label>Figure&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Evaluation of Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> Catalysts in the Conversion of Diphenyl Ether at 160&#x000b0;C</p><p>(A and B) (A) HDO extent as a function of time (note that measurement began upon the reaction mixture reaching the temperature of 160&#x000b0;C, ca. 15&#x000a0;min ramp time); (B) relationships between conversion or HDO extent or DOD and Ni loading in Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>. Reaction conditions: diphenyl ether (13.5&#x000a0;mmol), <italic>n</italic>-dibutyl ether (3.64&#x000a0;mmol, as an internal standard for gas chromatography, GC, analysis), methylcyclohexane (70&#x000a0;mL, solvent), catalyst (0.500 g), H<sub>2</sub> pressure of 4 MPa (at room temperature), stirring rate of 400&#x000a0;rpm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig></p><p id="p0115">To examine in more detail the results of the experiments conducted at 160&#x000b0;C, the product distribution at a similar conversion level of about 50%&#x02013;60% was analyzed (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Two critical ratios of products' groups were considered. The ratio &#x003a3;(4&#x02013;7)/&#x003a3;(2,3) was used to define the selectivity to monocyclic products produced by the cleavage of the C&#x02013;O ether bond. The ratio &#x003a3;(5,7)/&#x003a3;(4,6) indicates the selectivity to HDO after ether bond cleavage, which reflects the ability of the catalyst to execute the following reaction sequence: phenol &#x02192; cyclohexanol &#x02192; cyclohexene &#x02192; cyclohexane. Evolution of the product selectivity with time at 160&#x000b0;C is given in <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S3</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Product Distribution, HDO Extent, and Degree of Deoxygenation (DOD) at Iso-Conversion for the Diphenyl Ether HDO at 160&#x000b0;C</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="13"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx2.gif"/><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="2">Catalyst</th><th rowspan="2">Conversion (%)</th><th rowspan="2">Time (min)</th><th colspan="6">Selectivity (%)<hr/></th><th rowspan="2"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.gif"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2,3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th rowspan="2"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si4.gif"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5,7</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4,6</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th rowspan="2">HDO Extent (%)</th><th rowspan="2">DOD (%)</th></tr><tr><th>2</th><th>3</th><th>4</th><th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>5%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char">55</td><td align="char">180</td><td align="char">23</td><td align="char">5</td><td align="char">1</td><td align="char">4</td><td align="char">29</td><td align="char">38</td><td align="char">2.57</td><td align="char">1.40</td><td align="char">28</td><td align="char">12</td></tr><tr><td>10%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char">51</td><td align="char">90</td><td align="char">25</td><td align="char">5</td><td align="char">1</td><td align="char">4</td><td align="char">32</td><td align="char">33</td><td align="char">2.33</td><td align="char">1.12</td><td align="char">24</td><td align="char">8</td></tr><tr><td>15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char">56</td><td align="char">90</td><td align="char">25</td><td align="char">6</td><td align="char">1</td><td align="char">4</td><td align="char">33</td><td align="char">31</td><td align="char">2.23</td><td align="char">1.03</td><td align="char">26</td><td align="char">7</td></tr><tr><td>25%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char">63</td><td align="char">60</td><td align="char">22</td><td align="char">11</td><td align="char">1</td><td align="char">3</td><td align="char">36</td><td align="char">27</td><td align="char">2.03</td><td align="char">0.81</td><td align="char">28</td><td align="char">5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0120"><xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows that diphenyl ether was converted into three main products: cyclohexyl phenyl ether (22%&#x02013;25%), cyclohexanol (29%&#x02013;36%), and cyclohexane (27%&#x02013;38%). Small quantities of dicyclohexyl ether, phenol, and benzene were also found in the reaction mixture (individual selectivity values lower than 11%). &#x003a3;(4&#x02013;7)/&#x003a3;(2,3) ratio higher than 1 was observed for all the Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts. This observation indicates the formation of monocyclic products to prevail over the partial or full saturation of diphenyl ether. The latter renders the bicyclic products 2 and 3, respectively. With the rise in Ni content in Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts (from 5 to 25 wt %), a gradual reduction in the &#x003a3;(4&#x02013;7)/&#x003a3;(2,3) ratio (from 2.57 to 2.03) was observed. Taking the results from the experiment carried out in the presence of 25 wt % Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst into account, the reduction in the &#x003a3;(4&#x02013;7)/&#x003a3;(2,3) ratio is related to the accumulation of dicyclohexyl ether in the reaction mixture. As previously reported, dialkyl ethers are not prone to undergo hydrogenolysis in the presence of Ni catalysts under relatively mild reaction conditions (<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Rinaldi, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et&#x000a0;al., 2012a</xref>). Should a dialkyl ether be cleaved, the reaction pathway would begin with a hydrolysis step instead (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;5</xref>). However, in this study, the formation of dicyclohexyl ether constitutes a dead end, as its conversion was not observed. Confirming this, we could successfully employ <italic>n</italic>-dibutyl ether in the reaction mixtures as an internal standard for gas chromatography (GC) analysis. Likewise, no decomposition of the internal standard was detected.</p><p id="p0125">The results in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> also shows a rise in the selectivity to cyclohexanol (from 6% to 11%) for the experiment carried out in the presence of 25 wt % Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst. This outcome agrees with the decrease in Br&#x000f8;nsted acidity at a high Ni content supported on Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>, as verified by ATR-IR spectra of pyridine adsorbed on the reduced Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4</xref>) and model reaction experiments (dehydration of cyclohexanol, <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Therefore, the increase in Ni loading on Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> has implications for both the accumulation of dicyclohexyl ether (i.e., raises the likelihood of full saturation of diphenyl ether to dicyclohexyl ether) and of cyclohexanol (i.e., lessens the extent of dehydration of cyclohexanol).</p><p id="p0130">The product distributions in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> show similar values of selectivity to cyclohexanol and cyclohexane, revealing that Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> plays a marginal role in the HDO extent at 160&#x000b0;C. Under these conditions, low DOD values (5%&#x02013;12%) were achieved. The catalyst's ability to dehydrate cyclohexanol significantly reduces with the rise in Ni content, as indicated by the decrease in the &#x003a3;(5,7)/&#x003a3;(4,6) ratio from 1.40 to 0.81. The decrease in the dehydration capability is correlated with the decrease in the number of Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites with the increase in Ni content, as discussed in the previous section.</p><p id="p0135">According to the results from <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, 10%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> and 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts present the best balance between HDO extent and selectivity to monocyclic deoxygenated products. These catalysts were thus chosen for the conversion of diphenyl ether carried out at 200&#x000b0;C. <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref> shows the monitoring of the reaction mixture components over time. For both experiments, full conversion was achieved at 180&#x000a0;min. Cyclohexane was the main product obtained, with selectivity values of 81% and 88% for the 10%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> and 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O catalysts, respectively. These results confirm that the dehydration of cyclohexanol is encouraged at 200&#x000b0;C. At 180&#x000a0;min, the HDO extent and DOD were both greater for 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> (HDO extent: 91%; DOD: 85%) than for the 10%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst (HDO extent: 82%; DOD: 72%). Based on these results, 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst was considered as the most efficient. Thus the 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst was selected for the recycling experiments and studies on the conversion of lignin oil.<fig id="fig7"><label>Figure&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Catalytic Conversion of Diphenyl Ether at 200&#x000b0;C</p><p>Monitoring of reaction mixture composition for the conversion of diphenyl ether at 200&#x000b0;C in the presence of (A) 10%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> or (B) 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst. Reaction conditions: diphenyl ether (13.5&#x000a0;mmol), <italic>n</italic>-dibutyl ether (3.64&#x000a0;mmol, as an internal standard for GC analysis), methylcyclohexane (70&#x000a0;mL, solvent), catalyst (0.500 g), H<sub>2</sub> pressure of 4 MPa (at room temperature), and stirring rate of 400&#x000a0;rpm. Note that time measurement began upon reaching a temperature of 200&#x000b0;C (ca.&#x000a0;20&#x000a0;min ramp time).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p><p id="p0140">The catalytic performance after five reaction cycles was investigated for the HDO of diphenyl ether at 200&#x000b0;C for 240&#x000a0;min using the 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst. Again, diphenyl ether serves as a model compound because, when targeting the full HDO of lignin streams, the accumulation of cyclohexanol (derived from hydrogenation of phenol) indicates a decay of the initial acidic properties of a bifunctional catalyst. After each reaction run, the catalyst was washed with solvent and reused in the following reaction run. <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;8</xref> displays the conversion and product distribution after each reaction run.<fig id="fig8"><label>Figure&#x000a0;8</label><caption><p>Sustained Catalyst Performance of 15% Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> in the Recycling Experiments at 200&#x000b0;C</p><p>Performance of 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> in the conversion of diphenyl ether at 200&#x000b0;C throughout the recycling experiments. Reaction conditions for each cycle: diphenyl ether (13.5&#x000a0;mmol), <italic>n</italic>-dibutyl ether (3.64&#x000a0;mmol, as an internal standard for GC analysis), methylcyclohexane (70&#x000a0;mL, solvent), catalyst (0.500 g), H<sub>2</sub> pressure of 4 MPa (at room temperature), reaction time of 240&#x000a0;min, and stirring rate of 400&#x000a0;rpm. Note that time measurement began upon reaching a temperature of 200&#x000b0;C (ca.&#x000a0;20&#x000a0;min ramp time).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr8"/></fig></p><p id="p0145"><xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;8</xref> shows that the catalyst presents a sustained performance, still producing a 91% yield of cyclohexane after five reaction runs. A slight decrease in the cyclohexane selectivity is, however, observed from the second to fourth reaction runs, with the formation of cyclohexanol and dicyclohexyl ether (around 4%&#x02013;5% each) from the third cycle on. These results translate into a slight decrease in both HDO extent (from 100% to 92%) and DOD (from 100% to 94%) throughout the recycling experiments.</p><p id="p0150">To examine surface, structural, and morphological alterations occurring in the 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst, the fresh and spent catalysts were analyzed by using a set of techniques (pyridine adsorption, XRD, and HAADF-STEM). <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;9</xref> shows the ATR spectra of adsorbed pyridine on the fresh catalysts and spent samples after five reaction runs. The data indicates that the population of Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites dramatically decreased after five successive reuses of the catalyst. This means that even though water is generated during the reaction, no regeneration of Br&#x000f8;nsted acidity takes place in the process. In this context, the accumulation of cyclohexanol appears to be related to a decrease in the population of Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites. On the other hand, Lewis acidity is preserved, which explains the sustained high selectivity to cyclohexane at 200&#x000b0;C, demonstrating that Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> Lewis acid sites are stable under the reaction conditions. Moreover, a modest decrease in BET surface area was observed (fresh catalyst: 180 m<sup>2</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> versus spent catalyst: 144&#x000a0;m<sup>2</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). The XRD pattern of the used catalyst (<xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;10</xref>) also shows that the crystalline structure of the catalyst is maintained after five reaction runs. Also, no significant change in the Ni average crystallite size occurred after five reaction runs (fresh catalyst: 14&#x000a0;nm versus spent catalyst: 15&#x000a0;nm). Finally, the comparison of STEM-HAADF images (<xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;11</xref>) indicates that the spent catalyst after the fifth reaction run maintains the original features of the fresh catalyst, that is, the arrangement and size distribution of Ni nanoparticles entangled in the Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorod nest remained, to a great extent, unaltered. Overall, these observations together with the sustained catalytic performance of the 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> indicated that this material holds potential as a robust and active catalyst for the conversion of phenolic streams derived from lignin.<fig id="fig9"><label>Figure&#x000a0;9</label><caption><p>ATR-FTIR Spectrum of Pyridine Adsorbed on the Catalyst 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> before and after Five Reaction Runs</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr9"/></fig><fig id="fig10"><label>Figure&#x000a0;10</label><caption><p>XRD Pattern for the 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> before and after Five Reaction Runs</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr10"/></fig><fig id="fig11"><label>Figure&#x000a0;11</label><caption><p>HAADF-STEM Images of 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> before and after Five Reaction Runs</p><p>HAADF-STEM images of (A and B) fresh 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst, and (C and D) spent 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst after five reaction runs. Images (B) and (D) correspond to the ratio of high-angle to low-angle ADF signal.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr11"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Hydrodeoxygenation of Lignin Oil</title><p id="p0155">To explore the potential of 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst in the conversion of lignin oil, lignin oil was subjected to hydrotreatment under an H<sub>2</sub> pressure of 7 MPa (measured at room temperature) at 300&#x000b0;C for 16 h. We chose to increase the reaction temperature from 200&#x000b0;C (as for the model compound experiments) to 300&#x000b0;C to encourage extensive HDO of lignin oil to cycloalkanes, leading to full conversion of lignin into products soluble in <italic>n</italic>-pentane (reaction solvent), thus avoiding the accumulation of lignin residues throughout the catalyst recycling experiments (<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Rinaldi, 2012</xref>). However, even under harsh conditions, an appreciable amount of a residue insoluble in <italic>n</italic>-pentane or even methanol (a good solvent for lignin oil species) was formed and, thus, accumulated with the catalyst. Thereby, in this study, the &#x0201c;conversion of lignin oil&#x0201d; is estimated as a &#x0201c;net conversion,&#x0201d; which takes into account the weight of residue insoluble in either <italic>n</italic>-pentane or methanol formed in each reaction run (in conjunction with the initial weight of fresh catalyst) and the amount of lignin oil added in each reaction run. For the catalyst recycling experiments, the spent catalyst was washed with methanol to extract soluble residue species. The spent catalyst containing lignin-derived residues insoluble in methanol was then recovered by filtration and dried at 40&#x000b0;C in a vacuum oven. The liquid products and the fraction of lignin residues soluble in methanol were characterized by elemental analysis, gas chromatography (GC)-flame ionization detector (FID)/mass spectrometry (MS), and gel permeation chromatography (GPC).</p><p id="p0160">Throughout the catalyst recycling experiment, which processed in total ca. 6.0&#x000a0;g of lignin oil, the amount of lignin-derived residue increased from ca. 0.23&#x000a0;g (first run) to 0.30&#x02013;0.31&#x000a0;g (second or third run, <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Logically, the accumulation of the lignin-derived residue impedes the precise determination of the initial quantity of substrate present in the second and third reaction runs, as it is not possible to discern whether a part of the lignin-derived residue was also consumed throughout the recycling experiment and replaced with a fresh, more oxygenated carbonaceous residue derived from the fresh substrate. Further exploration of the data listed in <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, that is, the determination of weight ratio of liquid-product-to-residue, should be carried out with caution. A mass ratio of liquid-product-to-residue is only meaningful if both liquid product and residue present similar values of O/C and H/C ratios, which is not the case when the catalyst loses part of its performance in the recycling experiments.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Overall Results for the HDO of Lignin Oil in the Recycling Experiments</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Reaction</th><th colspan="3">Weight (g)<hr/></th><th rowspan="2">Net Conversion (%)</th></tr><tr><th>Liquid Product</th><th>Residue Insoluble in <italic>n</italic>-Pentane and Methanol</th><th>Residue Soluble in Methanol</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1<sup>st</sup> Run</td><td align="char">0.2941</td><td align="char">0.2293</td><td align="char">0.0249</td><td align="char">89</td></tr><tr><td>2<sup>nd</sup> Run</td><td align="char">0.8663</td><td align="char">0.2990</td><td align="char">0.0204</td><td align="char">85</td></tr><tr><td>3<sup>rd</sup> Run</td><td align="char">0.5907</td><td align="char">0.3085</td><td align="char">0.0240</td><td align="char">85</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Reaction conditions for each cycle: lignin bio-oil (2 g), <italic>n</italic>-pentane (100&#x000a0;mL, solvent), 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst (initial weight: 0.400&#x000a0;g), H<sub>2</sub> pressure of 7 MPa (at room temperature), 16&#x000a0;h at 300&#x000b0;C, stirring rate of 400&#x000a0;rpm.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0165"><xref rid="fig12" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;12</xref> summarizes in a van Krevelen diagram the results obtained from the control experiment and catalyst recycling in the hydrotreating of lignin oil. In the absence of the catalyst, a 68% conversion of the lignin oil was achieved by thermal processes (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), increasing the H/C ratio from 1.51&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01, for the lignin oil, to 1.74&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.02 for the liquid fraction. Conversely, the O/C ratio decreased from 0.46&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01, for the lignin oil, to 0.23&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01 for the produced liquid fraction. This decrease in O/C ratio is associated with the elimination of the &#x003b3;-OH group of <italic>p</italic>-dihydrolignols, among other thermal processes, leading to deoxygenation (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S4</xref>). The solid residue exhibited an H/C ratio of 1.45&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.03 and an O/C ratio of 0.34&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01. These results indicate that the residue no longer corresponds to the initial lignin stream.<fig id="fig12"><label>Figure&#x000a0;12</label><caption><p>Snapshot of the HDO Performance of 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> Catalyst in the Recycling Experiments</p><p>van Krevelen plot comparing the H/C and O/C molar ratios for the lignin oil, residue fraction soluble in methanol, and liquid products obtained in the presence of 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst and from the control experiment (no added catalyst).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr12"/></fig></p><p id="p0170">In the catalytic experiments, an 89% conversion of lignin in the first reaction run was achieved. For the liquid product obtained from the first reaction run, a substantial increase in the H/C ratio from 1.51&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01, for the lignin oil, to 1.80&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01 was achieved. In parallel, the O/C molar ratio decreased from 0.46&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01 to 0.006&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.004 for the liquid product. These results demonstrate the extensive removal of oxygen and incorporation of hydrogen in the liquid product. In the subsequent catalyst reuse, the net conversion of lignin oil slightly decreased from 89% to 85%, for both the second and third reaction runs (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). For the liquid products, H/C ratios of 1.76&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01 and 1.75&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.03 for the second and third reaction runs, respectively, were obtained. These values are slightly lower than those of the liquid products from the first reaction run (H/C:1.80&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01). On the other hand, O/C ratios substantially increased from 0.006&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.004, for the first reaction run, to 0.14&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01 and 0.16&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01, for the second and third reactions runs, respectively. For the residue fraction soluble in MeOH, which corresponds to ca. 10% of the lignin-derived residues, the H/C ratio decreased from 1.73&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01 (first reaction run) to 1.62&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01 and 1.62&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.06, for the second and third reaction runs, respectively. In parallel, O/C ratios rose from 0.29&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.04 (first reaction run) to 0.33&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01 and 0.36&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 0.01 for the second and third reaction runs, respectively. Altogether, the O/C and H/C ratios found for the liquid products and residues indicate that the catalyst's hydrogenation activity deteriorated to an extent lesser than that of the deoxygenation ability.</p><p id="p0175">To gain an in-depth insight into the composition of the volatile fraction of the liquid products, GC-FID/MS analysis was carried out (<xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;13</xref>). In the volatile fraction of the lignin oil (corresponding to 28% at an injector temperature of 300&#x000b0;C), the main components were <italic>p</italic>-dihydrolignols [4-(3-hydroxypropyl)-2-methoxyphenol and 4-(3-hydroxypropyl)-2,6-dimethoxyphenol, <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S4</xref>] followed by other alkylphenol compounds. In the control experiment, thermolytic processes on the <italic>p</italic>-dihydrolignols caused the elimination of &#x003b3;-OH group, rendering 4-propylguaiacol and 4-propylsyringol. Other products from the cracking of the propyl side chain were formed (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S4</xref>). At a much lesser extent, cyclohexanols (6.6%) and cycloalkanes (1.3%) were also formed. In the presence of 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst, the primary volatile products were cycloalkanes (47%) and cyclohexanols (2%). Half of the cycloalkanes' fraction content corresponded to bicyclic aliphatic compounds. In the catalyst recycling, the content of cycloalkanes in the liquid product significantly decreased from 47%, for the fresh catalyst, to 8% and 5%, for the second and third reaction runs, respectively. As a result, the dominant species in the liquid products became cyclohexanols (31%&#x02013;35%). The high content of monophenolic species (18&#x02013;19%) reveals that the catalyst's hydrogenation ability was also impaired after the first use of the catalyst. However, the catalyst hydrogenation ability was affected to an extent lesser than that for the dehydration of cyclohexanol intermediates.<fig id="fig13"><label>Figure&#x000a0;13</label><caption><p>Distribution of compound classes in lignin oil and processed streams</p><p>Comparison of distributions of compound classes in the lignin oil, liquid products from the hydroprocessing of lignin oil in the presence of the 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst, and control experiment (no added catalyst). Reaction conditions for each cycle: lignin bio-oil (2 g), <italic>n</italic>-pentane (100&#x000a0;mL, solvent), catalyst (0.400 g), H<sub>2</sub> pressure of 7 MPa (at room temperature), 16&#x000a0;h at 300&#x000b0;C, stirring rate of 400&#x000a0;rpm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr13"/></fig></p><p id="p0180">To assess the extent of decrease in the acidity of the Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> support, ATR-IR measurements of pyridine adsorbed on the spent 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst were performed. After the third reaction run, <xref rid="fig14" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;14</xref> reveals that the spent catalyst no longer presents either Br&#x000f8;nsted or Lewis acid sites accessible to pyridine adsorption. These results demonstrate the decrease in the deoxygenation activity of 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> to be caused by the blocking of acid sites on the Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> support. Surprisingly, despite the loss of acidity, the structural properties of the Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods were not affected upon recycling (as shown by XRD pattern features, <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S4</xref>). By stark contrast, the size of the Ni particles increased from 14 to 80&#x000a0;nm after three reaction runs (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure&#x000a0;S4</xref>). Thereby, the decrease in the hydrogenating activity of the catalyst appears to be related to the decrease in metal surface area due to Ni particle growth.<fig id="fig14"><label>Figure&#x000a0;14</label><caption><p>ATR-FTIR Spectra of Pyridine Adsorbed on the 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> Catalyst before and after Recycling (Third Run)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr14"/></fig></p><p id="p0185">From the data presented in <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;13</xref>, the sum of compounds visible by the GC technique corresponds to approximately half of the content of species occurring in the liquid products. To expand our analysis toward the heavy species, GPC was performed on the hydrotreated liquid products and residue fractions soluble in methanol. Noteworthy, when applied to product mixtures obtained from lignin, direct information regarding the content of species cannot be retrieved from an ultraviolet-visible (UV-vis) detector (in this study, a photodiode array [PDA] detector), as the detector response is not universal. Furthermore, in samples containing aliphatic hydrocarbons, these compounds will be invisible to the UV-vis detector. Despite these limitations, the GPC technique coupled with UV-vis spectroscopy provides useful information on the apparent distribution of <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub> and spectral signature of the eluting species. <xref rid="fig15" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;15</xref> displays the chromatogram traces at a wavelength of 280&#x000a0;nm.<fig id="fig15"><label>Figure&#x000a0;15</label><caption><p>Gel Permeation Chromatogram Traces at a Wavelength of 280 nm</p><p>Gel permeation chromatograms for the (i) lignin oil, liquid products (blue-coded curves) and solid residues (gray-coded curves) obtained from the process with added catalyst in the (ii) first reaction run, (iii) second reaction run, and (iv) third reaction run, and (v) control experiment with no added catalyst. The apparent <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub> is given relative to polystyrene standards. Signal intensities of the curves are not scaled.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr15"/></fig></p><p id="p0190"><xref rid="fig15" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;15</xref> shows that the lignin oil substrate encompasses species of apparent <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub> from 100 to 66,000 Da. In the absence of the 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst (control experiment), thermal processes on lignin generate soluble species of <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub> lower than 1,200&#x000a0;Da for both the product oil and solid residues, at the expense of the heavy species. In the presence of the fresh 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst, both the liquid product and the residue fraction soluble in methanol still contain UV-absorbing species heavier and of much broader apparent <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub> distributions, compared with those from the control experiment. Surprisingly, the subsequent reaction runs yielded liquid products and residues of an apparent <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub> distribution comparable to the apparent <italic>M</italic><sub>w</sub> range of products formed in the control experiment.</p><p id="p0195">To gain further information about the chemical nature of the UV-absorbing species, the spectral data collected by the PDA detector in the GPC analysis was examined in detail (<xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;16</xref>). In the samples from the first reaction run, a key feature distinguishing the PDA images is the presence of species absorbing at wavelengths higher than 300&#x000a0;nm for the residue fraction soluble in methanol (indicated in <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;16</xref> by a yellow-coded dotted line). In lignin chemistry, this spectral feature is often related to the presence of quinone methide intermediates, stilbene species, and other conjugated unsaturated species associated with lignin condensation processes (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Lin, 1992</xref>, <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Schmidt, 2010</xref>). Overall these observations suggest that, in the presence of the fresh 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst, the condensation of lignin species could not entirely be suppressed by the reductive processes, as the former process appears to take place at a rate faster than the latter. Interestingly, similar PDA images are found for both liquid products and the residues soluble in methanol from the second and third reaction runs. These images show no strong absorption spot at wavelengths higher than 300&#x000a0;nm. Altogether, these observations support the hypothesis that Lewis acid sites of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> play a role in the condensation of lignin species. As these sites become largely blocked in the first reaction run, the condensation of lignin species should occur to a lesser extent in the subsequent reaction runs. This hypothesis appears to be plausible also considering that the weight of lignin residue accumulated with the catalyst plateaued after the second reaction run (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).<fig id="fig16"><label>Figure&#x000a0;16</label><caption><p>Spectral Signature of the Eluting Species in the GPC Analysis</p><p>PDA detector response images for the eluting species in the GPC analysis performed on lignin oil, liquid products, and residues obtained with no added catalyst (control experiment) and in the presence of 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst (recycling experiment). The yellow-coded dotted line in the PDA image of the solid residue (first reaction run) indicates the extension of the UV-vis absorption signal.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr16"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0200">This study provided a beginning-to-end analysis of the multifaceted picture of the design of water-tolerant catalysts for the hydrotreating of lignin streams. From the observations of this study, the following conclusions and recommendations for future research are given:<list list-type="simple" id="olist0010"><list-item id="o0010"><label>1.</label><p id="p0205">In the design of bifunctional Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>, the incorporation of the Ni phase reduces the population of Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites. However, the population of Lewis acid sites remained almost unaltered. The dehydration of cyclohexanol over Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites takes place at temperatures lower than those required for the reaction catalyzed by Lewis acid sites. By employing the hydrotreating of diphenyl ether to cyclohexane as a model reaction, it was possible to find a compromise between hydrogenation and dehydration catalyst's capabilities, thus taking the benefit from the catalyst Lewis acidity for the hydrotreatment. The 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst showed sustained results in the recycling experiments. As a result of the high stability of the water-resistant Lewis acid sites, a 91% yield of cyclohexane could be achieved even after five reaction runs.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0015"><label>2.</label><p id="p0210">Despite the promising results achieved in the hydrotreatment of diphenyl ether, the 15%Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalyst lost its activity toward dehydration of the cyclohexanol species already after the first reaction run performed on the lignin oil stream. This disappointing outcome is associated with the blocking of the Lewis acid sites.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0020"><label>3.</label><p id="p0215">In the current literature on lignin hydroprocessing, little attention has been given to the fact that the acid sites, needed for the dehydration of cyclohexanol species, can also catalyze the condensation of lignin oligomeric species. In this study, we demonstrated that lignin condensation occurs even under reductive conditions and when beginning the process with passivated streams from the lignin-first biorefining based on reductive processes.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0025"><label>4.</label><p id="p0220">The condensation of lignin catalyzed by Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods' Lewis acid sites appears to be a chemical process faster than the saturation or HDO of lignin species. As a result, in the presence of Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts, lignin condensation is not entirely suppressed by reductive processes. Consequently, carbonaceous matter is formed, blocking the Lewis acid sites.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0030"><label>5.</label><p id="p0225">Previous studies on hydrotreating of lignin oils in the presence of phosphided Ni/SiO<sub>2</sub> catalysts demonstrated that recyclable hydrotreating catalysts could be produced (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Cao et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Samec, 2018</xref>). Confronting those results with the current ones, it is concluded that the control of the surface acidity is mandatory for the success of lignin oil hydrotreating. Further research is required to define the type of acidity and a threshold of acidity required for the hydrotreating of lignin while not encouraging acid-catalyzed condensation processes on the lignin oligomeric species. Surprisingly, such a research line has not been receiving much attention from the community. Indeed, often studied model compounds (e.g., diphenyl ether, benzyl phenyl ether, (alkyl)guaiacols, and several others) cannot undergo condensation reactions. Therefore, the crucial role of lignin condensation in hydrotreating processes cannot be mimicked by the current set of model compounds employed in this research field. This fact clearly limits the translation of technologies designed for the HDO of model compounds to the hydrotreating of real-world lignin streams.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0035"><label>6.</label><p id="p0230">The balance of dehydration and hydrogenation abilities of a heterogeneous catalyst becomes a very complicated issue when considering the significant impact of lignin condensation throughout the hydrotreating process. Considering this, a tentative solution could be the utilization of two solid catalysts, one for hydrogenation and another one for dehydration, so that the balance of these specific tasks could be then more easily adjusted by the weight ratio of each catalyst component in the mixture of catalysts. This idea has been already exploited with success (<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Rinaldi, 2013</xref>). However, the conversion of a batch reaction process to a continuous flow process based on a mixture of catalysts constitutes a challenging task. A more practical approach appears to be the combination of flow-through reactors operating in series but at different temperatures. This approach could circumvent catalyst deactivation by the formation of coke via lignin condensation, by gradually saturating the lignin stream under conditions of gradual increase in process severity. A similar approach was demonstrated to be very fruitful for the hydrotreatment of pyrolysis oil in the presence of Ni-Cu catalysts (<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Yin et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>).</p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0235">In a broader context, this work provides substantial evidence that the use of model reactions has severe limitations for the design of catalysts for the hydroprocessing of lignin streams. Accordingly, the catalyst screening carried out on real-world lignin streams is a more productive enterprise to pursue, regardless of the complexity of the product mixtures obtained. In this quest, the evaluation of H/C and O/C ratios as the response variables (either for the catalyst discovery or in recycling experiments) constitutes a strategy effective in the simplification of characterization procedures applied to the lignin products. Such a strategy should become a gold standard in the high-throughput screening catalysts for the hydroprocessing of lignin streams to produce drop-in lignin biofuels, as it allows for the direct comparison of catalyst performance without the need of scrutinizing the lignin product compositions at an early stage of technology-readiness levels (TRL), thus contributing to accelerating catalyst discovery.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>Limitations of the Study</title><p id="p0240">The hydrothermal synthesis of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> is based on the decomposition of niobium peroxo species formed by the reaction of ammonium niobium(V) oxalate and hydrogen peroxide. <italic>CAUTION:</italic> As the hydrothermal synthesis is performed in a closed stainless-steel vessel, it is mandatory to check if the vessel is rated to operate under the pressure built by the decomposition of the full content of hydrogen peroxide employed in the synthesis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Methods</title><p id="p0245">All methods can be found in the accompanying <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Transparent Methods supplemental file</xref>.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazemi</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surfactant controlled growth of niobium oxide nanorods</article-title><source>Cryst. Growth Des.</source><volume>17</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>4637</fpage><lpage>4646</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0035">Ali, R.F., Nazemi, A.H., Gates, B.D.., 2017. Surfactant controlled growth of niobium oxide nanorods. Cryst. Growth Des. 17, 4637-4646.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barrios</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teles</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Souza</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabelo-Neto</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>B.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>L.E.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noronha</surname><given-names>F.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrodeoxygenation of phenol over niobia supported Pd catalyst</article-title><source>Catal. Today</source><volume>302</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>124</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0040">Barrios, A.M., Teles, C.A., De Souza, P.M., Rabelo-Neto, R.C., Jacobs, G., Davis, B.H., Borges, L.E.P., Noronha, F.B.., 2017. Hydrodeoxygenation of phenol over niobia supported Pd catalyst. Catal. Today 302, 115-124.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brayner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bozon-Verduraz</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Niobium pentoxide prepared by soft chemical routes: morphology, structure, defects and quantum size effect</article-title><source>Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>1457</fpage><lpage>1466</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0045">Brayner, R., Bozon-Verduraz, F.., 2003. Niobium pentoxide prepared by soft chemical routes: morphology, structure, defects and quantum size effect. Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys. 5, 1457-1466.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dierks</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dierks</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Castro</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A convergent approach for a deep converting lignin-first biorefinery rendering high-energy-density drop-in fuels</article-title><source>Joule</source><volume>2</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1118</fpage><lpage>1133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29955733</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0050">Cao, Z., Dierks, M., Clough, M.T., Rinaldi, R., Cao, Z., Dierks, M., Clough, M.T., Barros, I., De Castro, D., 2018. A convergent approach for a deep converting lignin-first biorefinery rendering high-energy-density drop-in fuels. Joule 2, 1118-1133.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parise</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of niobium oxide phase on the furfuryl alcohol dehydration</article-title><source>Catal. Commun.</source><volume>97</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>69</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0055">Chan, X., Pu, T., Chen, X., James, A., Lee, J., Parise, J.B., Kim, D.H., Kim, T.., 2017. Effect of niobium oxide phase on the furfuryl alcohol dehydration. Catal. Commun. 97, 65-69.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chary</surname><given-names>K.V.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sri Lakshmi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>M.R.V.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>K.S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrodechlorination of 1,2,4-trichlorobenzene over niobia supported nickel catalysts</article-title><source>Catal. Commun.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>535</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0060">Chary, K.V.R., Sri Lakshmi, K., Murthy, M.R.V.S., Rao, K.S.R., Papadaki, M.., 2003. Hydrodechlorination of 1,2,4-trichlorobenzene over niobia supported nickel catalysts. Catal. Commun. 4, 531-535.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Junge</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Topf</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A stable and practical nickel catalyst for the hydrogenolysis of C&#x02013;O bonds</article-title><source>Green. Chem.</source><volume>19</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>310</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0065">Cui, X., Yuan, H., Junge, K., Topf, C., Beller, M., Shi, F.., 2017. A stable and practical nickel catalyst for the hydrogenolysis of C-O bonds. Green. Chem. 19, 305-310.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Datka</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acidic properties of supported niobium oxide catalysts: an infrared spectroscopy investigation</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Catal.</source><volume>135</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>199</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0070">Datka, J.., 1992. Acidic properties of supported niobium oxide catalysts: an infrared spectroscopy investigation. J. Catal. 135, 186-199.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>do Prado</surname><given-names>N.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>L.C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nanostructured niobium oxide synthetized by a new route using hydrothermal treatment: high efficiency in oxidation reactions</article-title><source>Appl. Catal. B Environ.</source><volume>205</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>488</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0075">do Prado, N.T., Oliveira, L.C.A., 2017. Nanostructured niobium oxide synthetized by a new route using hydrothermal treatment: high efficiency in oxidation reactions. Appl. Catal. B Environ. 205, 481-488.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dollish</surname><given-names>F.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fateley</surname><given-names>W.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>F.F.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Characteristic Raman Frequencies of Organic Compounds</chapter-title><edition>First Edition</edition><year>1974</year><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0080">Dollish, F.R., Fateley, W.G., Bentley, F.F.., 1974. Characteristic Raman Frequencies of Organic Compounds, First Edition. ed. Wiley.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dorrestijn</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laarhoven</surname><given-names>L.J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arends</surname><given-names>I.W.C.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Occurrence and reactivity of phenoxyl linkages in lignin and low rank coal</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Anal. Appl. Pyrolysis</source><volume>54</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>192</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0085">Dorrestijn, E., Laarhoven, L.J.J., Arends, I.W.C.E., Mulder, P.., 2000. Occurrence and reactivity of phenoxyl linkages in lignin and low rank coal. J. Anal. Appl. Pyrolysis 54, 153-192.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catalytic biorefining of plant biomass to non-pyrolytic lignin bio-oil and carbohydrates through hydrogen transfer reactions</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><volume>53</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>8634</fpage><lpage>8639</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0090">Ferrini, P., Rinaldi, R.., 2014. Catalytic biorefining of plant biomass to non-pyrolytic lignin bio-oil and carbohydrates through hydrogen transfer reactions. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 53, 8634-8639.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foo</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sholl</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of Lewis and Br&#x000f8;nsted acid sites in the dehydration of glycerol over niobia</article-title><source>ACS Catal.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>3180</fpage><lpage>3192</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0095">Foo, G.S., Wei, D., Sholl, D.S., Sievers, C.., 2014. Role of Lewis and Bronsted acid sites in the dehydration of glycerol over niobia. ACS Catal. 4, 3180-3192.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Francisco</surname><given-names>M.S.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landers</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gushikem</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local order structure and surface acidity properties of a Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>/SiO<sub>2</sub> mixed oxide prepared by the sol&#x02013;gel processing method</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Solid State Chem.</source><volume>177</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>2432</fpage><lpage>2439</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0100">Francisco, M.S.P., Landers, R., Gushikem, Y.., 2004. Local order structure and surface acidity properties of a Nb2O5/SiO2 mixed oxide prepared by the sol-gel processing method. J. Solid State Chem. 177, 2432-2439.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galkin</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samec</surname><given-names>J.S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lignin valorization through catalytic lignocellulose fractionation: a fundamental platform for the future biorefinery</article-title><source>ChemSusChem</source><volume>9</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1544</fpage><lpage>1558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27273230</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0105">Galkin, M.V., Samec, J.S.M.., 2016. Lignin valorization through catalytic lignocellulose fractionation: a fundamental platform for the future biorefinery. ChemSusChem 9, 1544-1558.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gra&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>L.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacariza</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CO<sub>2</sub> hydrogenation into CH<sub>4</sub> on NiHNaUSY zeolites</article-title><source>Appl. Catal. B Environ.</source><volume>147</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>110</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0110">Gra&#x000e7;a, I., Gonzalez, L.V., Bacariza, M.C., Fernandes, A., Henriques, C., Lopes, J.M., Ribeiro, M.F.., 2014. CO2 hydrogenation into CH4 on NiHNaUSY zeolites. Appl. Catal. B Environ. 147, 101-110.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gra&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>R.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennema</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formation and fate of carboxylic acids in the lignin-first biorefining of lignocellulose via H-transfer catalyzed by Raney Ni</article-title><source>ACS Sustain. Chem. Eng.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>13408</fpage><lpage>13419</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0115">Gra&#x000e7;a, I., Woodward, R.T., Kennema, M., Rinaldi, R.., 2018. Formation and fate of carboxylic acids in the lignin-first biorefining of lignocellulose via H-transfer catalyzed by Raney Ni. ACS Sustain. Chem. Eng. 6, 13408-13419.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gra&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>M.P.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meireles</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nico</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valente</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanosize powders prepared by sol-gel - structure, morphology and dielectric properties</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Alloys Compd.</source><volume>553</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>182</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0120">Gra&#x000e7;a, M.P.F.., Meireles, A., Nico, C., Valente, M.A., 2013. Nb2O5 nanosize powders prepared by sol-gel - structure, morphology and dielectric properties. J. Alloys Compd. 553, 177-182.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>C.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Highly stable Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> &#x02013;Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> composites supported Pt catalysts for hydrodeoxygenation of diphenyl ether</article-title><source>Ind. Eng. Chem. Res.</source><volume>56</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>14034</fpage><lpage>14042</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0125">Guan, W., Chen, X., Jin, S., Li, C., Tsang, C.-W., Liang, C.., 2017. Highly stable Nb2O5 -Al2O3 composites supported Pt catalysts for hydrodeoxygenation of diphenyl ether. Ind. Eng. Chem. Res. 56, 14034-14042.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lercher</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ni-Catalyzed cleavage of aryl ethers in the aqueous phase</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Am. Chem. Soc.</source><volume>134</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>20768</fpage><lpage>20775</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23190332</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0130">He, J., Zhao, C., Lercher, J.A.., 2012. Ni-Catalyzed cleavage of aryl ethers in the aqueous phase. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 134, 20768-20775.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herval</surname><given-names>L.K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>von Dreifus</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabelo</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gobato</surname><given-names>Y.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>A.J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Godoy</surname><given-names>M.P.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of defects on the structural and magnetic properties of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Alloys Compd.</source><volume>653</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>362</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0135">Herval, L.K.S., von Dreifus, D., Rabelo, A.C., Rodrigues, A.D., Pereira, E.C., Gobato, Y.G., de Oliveira, A.J.A., de Godoy, M.P.F.., 2015. The role of defects on the structural and magnetic properties of Nb2O5. J. Alloys Compd. 653, 358-362.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holtzberg</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reisman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkenblit</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemistry of the group VB pentoxides. VI. The polymorphism of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Am. Chem. Soc.</source><volume>79</volume><year>1957</year><fpage>2039</fpage><lpage>2043</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0140">Holtzberg, F., Reisman, A., Berry, M., Berkenblit, M.., 1957. Chemistry of the Group VB pentoxides. VI. The polymorphism of Nb2O5. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 79, 2039-2043.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iizuka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogasawara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acidic and catalytic properties of niobium pentaoxide</article-title><source>Bull. Chem. Soc. Jpn.</source><volume>56</volume><year>1983</year><fpage>2927</fpage><lpage>2931</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0145">Iizuka, T., Ogasawara, K., Tanabe, K.., 1983. Acidic and catalytic properties of niobium pentaoxide. Bull. Chem. Soc. Jpn. 56, 2927-2931.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jankovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adnadevi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mentus</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The kinetic study of temperature-programmed reduction of nickel oxide in hydrogen atmosphere</article-title><source>Chem. Eng. Sci.</source><volume>63</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>575</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0150">Jankovi&#x00107;, B., Adnadevi&#x00107;, B., Mentus, S.., 2008. The kinetic study of temperature-programmed reduction of nickel oxide in hydrogen atmosphere. Chem. Eng. Sci. 63, 567-575.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jasik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wojcieszak</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteverdi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziolek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettahar</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study of nickel catalysts supported on Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, SiO<sub>2</sub> or Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> oxides</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Mol. Catal. A. Chem.</source><volume>242</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>90</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0155">Jasik, A., Wojcieszak, R., Monteverdi, S., Ziolek, M., Bettahar, M.M.., 2005. Study of nickel catalysts supported on Al2O3, SiO2 or Nb2O5 oxides. J. Mol. Catal. A. Chem. 242, 81-90.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saravanan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>H.-K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergistic effects of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> promoter on Ru/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> for an aqueous-phase hydrodeoxygenation of glycerol to hydrocarbons</article-title><source>Appl. Catal. A Gen.</source><volume>551</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0160">Jeon, S., Park, Y.M., Park, J., Saravanan, K., Jeong, H.-K., Bae, J.W.., 2018. Synergistic effects of Nb2O5 promoter on Ru/Al2O3 for an aqueous-phase hydrodeoxygenation of glycerol to hydrocarbons. Appl. Catal. A Gen. 551, 49-62.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>D.Y.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced hydroconversion of lignin-derived oxygen-containing compounds over bulk nickel catalysts though Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> modification</article-title><source>Catal. Letters</source><volume>147</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>2215</fpage><lpage>2224</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0165">Jin, S., Guan, W., Tsang, C.W., Yan, D.Y.S., Chan, C.Y., Liang, C.., 2017. Enhanced hydroconversion of lignin-derived oxygen-containing compounds over bulk nickel catalysts though Nb2O5 modification. Catal. Letters 147, 2215-2224.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>E.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hupp</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethane hydrogenolysis and carbon monoxide hydrogenation over niobia-supported nickel catalysts: a hierarchy to rank strong metal-support interaction</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Catal.</source><volume>86</volume><year>1984</year><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>327</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0170">Ko, E.I., Hupp, J.M., Wagner, N.J.., 1984. Ethane hydrogenolysis and carbon monoxide hydrogenation over niobia-supported nickel catalysts: a hierarchy to rank strong metal-support interaction. J. Catal. 86, 315-327.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>E.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structures of niobium pentoxide and their implications on chemical behavior</article-title><source>Catal. Today</source><volume>8</volume><year>1990</year><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0175">Ko, E.I., Weissman, J.G.., 1990. Structures of niobium pentoxide and their implications on chemical behavior. Catal. Today 8, 27-36.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kreissl</surname><given-names>H.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y.-K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>T.J.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soo</surname><given-names>Y.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>S.C.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural studies of bulk to nanosize niobium oxides with correlation to their acidity</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Am. Chem. Soc.</source><volume>139</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>12670</fpage><lpage>12680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28806077</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0180">Kreissl, H.T., Li, M.M.J., Peng, Y.-K., Nakagawa, K., Hooper, T.J.N., Hanna, J.V., Shepherd, A., Wu, T.-S., Soo, Y.-L., Tsang, S.C.E.., 2017. Structural studies of bulk to nanosize niobium oxides with correlation to their acidity. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 139, 12670-12680.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>S.J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira-Neto</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curvelo</surname><given-names>A.A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodella</surname><given-names>C.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological, structural, and chemical properties of thermally stable Ni-Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> for catalytic applications</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Phys. Chem. C</source><volume>123</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>3130</fpage><lpage>3143</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0185">Leal, G.F., Barrett, D.H., Carrer, H., Figueroa, S.J.A., Teixeira-Neto, E., Curvelo, A.A.S., Rodella, C.B.., 2019. Morphological, structural, and chemical properties of thermally stable Ni-Nb2O5 for catalytic applications. J. Phys. Chem. C 123, 3130-3143.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leite</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vila</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettini</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Longo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis of niobia nanocrystals with controlled morphology</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Phys. Chem. B</source><volume>110</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>18088</fpage><lpage>18090</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16970415</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0190">Leite, E.R., Vila, C., Bettini, J., Longo, E.., 2006. Synthesis of niobia nanocrystals with controlled morphology. J. Phys. Chem. B 110, 18088-18090.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Ultraviolet spectrophotometry</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dence</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Methods in Lignin Chemistry</source><year>1992</year><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-642-74065-7_15</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0195">Lin, S.Y.., 1992. Ultraviolet spectrophotometry, in: Lin, S.Y., Dence, C.W. (Eds.), Methods in Lignin Chemistry. Springer-Verlag, Berlim, pp. 217-232.https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-74065-7_15</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>W.-N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rick</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>C.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.-F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>B.-J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rational design of ethanol steam reforming catalyst based on analysis of Ni/La<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> metal&#x02013;support interactions</article-title><source>Catal. Sci. Technol.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>3449</fpage><lpage>3456</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0200">Liu, J.-Y., Su, W.-N., Rick, J., Yang, S.-C., Pan, C.-J., Lee, J.-F., Chen, J.-M., Hwang, B.-J.., 2016. Rational design of ethanol steam reforming catalyst based on analysis of Ni/La2O3 metal-support interactions. Catal. Sci. Technol. 6, 3449-3456.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vjunov</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckstein</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Camaioni</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar&#x000e1;th</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lercher</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancing the catalytic activity of hydronium ions through constrained environments</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28232748</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0205">Liu, Y., Vjunov, A., Shi, H., Eckstein, S., Camaioni, D.M., Mei, D., Barath, E., Lercher, J.A.., 2017. Enhancing the catalytic activity of hydronium ions through constrained environments. Nat. Commun. 8, 2-9.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>O.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paris</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanoparticles through the oxidant peroxide method applied to organic pollutant photodegradation: a mechanistic study</article-title><source>Appl. Catal. B Environ.</source><volume>144</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>800</fpage><lpage>808</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0210">Lopes, O.F., Paris, E.C., Ribeiro, C.., 2014. Synthesis of Nb2O5 nanoparticles through the oxidant peroxide method applied to organic pollutant photodegradation: a mechanistic study. Appl. Catal. B Environ. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apcatb.2013.08.031</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luisa Marin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallett-Tapley</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Impellizzeri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fasciani</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simoncelli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Netto-Ferreira</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scaiano</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, acid properties and catalysis by niobium oxide nanostructured materials</article-title><source>Catal. Sci. Technol.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>3044</fpage><lpage>3052</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0215">Luisa Marin, M., Hallett-Tapley, G.L., Impellizzeri, S., Fasciani, C., Simoncelli, S., Netto-Ferreira, J.C., Scaiano, J.C.., 2014. Synthesis, acid properties and catalysis by niobium oxide nanostructured materials. Catal. Sci. Technol. 4, 3044-3052.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morais</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ad&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names>A.P.M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marug&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, characterization, and photonic efficiency of novel photocatalytic niobium oxide materials</article-title><source>Glob. Chall.</source><volume>1</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1700066</fpage><lpage>1700074</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0220">Morais, L.A., Adan, C., Araujo, A.S., Guedes, A.P.M.A., Marugan, J.., 2017. Synthesis, characterization, and photonic efficiency of novel photocatalytic niobium oxide materials. Glob. Chall. 1, 1700066-1700074.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nH<sub>2</sub>O as a heterogeneous catalyst with water-tolerant Lewis acid sites</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Am. Chem. Soc.</source><volume>133</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>4224</fpage><lpage>4227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21370861</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0225">Nakajima, K., Baba, Y., Noma, R., Kitano, M., J.N. Kondo, Hayashi, S., Hara, M.., 2011. Nb2O5 nH2O as a heterogeneous catalyst with water-tolerant Lewis acid sites. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 133, 4224-4227.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Titania as an early transition metal oxide with a high density of Lewis acid sites workable in water</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Phys. Chem. C</source><volume>117</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>16028</fpage><lpage>16033</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0230">Nakajima, K., Noma, R., Kitano, M., Hara, M.., 2013. Titania as an early transition metal oxide with a high density of Lewis acid sites workable in water. J. Phys. Chem. C 117, 16028-16033.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nico</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gra&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>M.P.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Niobium oxides and niobates physical properties: Review and prospects</article-title><source>Prog. Mater. Sci.</source><volume>80</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>37</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0235">Nico, C., Monteiro, T., Gra&#x000e7;a, M.P.F.., 2016. Niobium oxides and niobates physical properties: Review and prospects. Prog. Mater. Sci. 80, 1-37.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziolek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Niobium compounds: preparation, characterization, and application in heterogeneous catalysis</article-title><source>Chem. Rev.</source><volume>99</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>3603</fpage><lpage>3624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11849031</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0240">Nowak, I., Ziolek, M.., 1999. Niobium compounds: preparation, characterization, and application in heterogeneous catalysis. Chem. Rev. 99, 3603-3624.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An infrared study of pyridine adsorbed characterization of surface</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Catal.</source><volume>2</volume><year>1963</year><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>379</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0245">Parry, E.P.., 1963. An infrared study of pyridine adsorbed characterization of surface. J. Catal. 2, 371-379.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parthasarathi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Redondo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnanakaran</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Theoretical study of the remarkably diverse linkages in lignin</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Phys. Chem. Lett.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>2660</fpage><lpage>2666</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0250">Parthasarathi, R., Romero, R.A., Redondo, A., Gnanakaran, S.., 2011. Theoretical study of the remarkably diverse linkages in lignin. J. Phys. Chem. Lett. 2, 2660-2666.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parvulescu</surname><given-names>V.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duraki</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krumeich</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Bokhoven</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lignin fragmentation onto multifunctional Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>@Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>@Co@Re catalysts: the role of the composition and deposition route of rhenium</article-title><source>ACS Catal.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>3257</fpage><lpage>3267</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0255">Parvulescu, V.I., Duraki, B., Krumeich, F., Van Bokhoven, J.A., 2017. Lignin fragmentation onto multifunctional Fe3O4@Nb2O5@Co@Re catalysts: the role of the composition and deposition route of rhenium.ACS Catal., 7, 3257-3267</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavia</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lampman</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriz</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyvyan</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Introduction to Spectroscopy</chapter-title><edition>Fourth Edition</edition><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Brooks/Cole, Cengage Learning</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0260">Pavia, D.L., Lampman, G.M., Kriz, G.S., Vyvyan, J.R.., 2010. Introduction to Spectroscopy, Fourth Edition. ed. New York.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>H.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagan-Torres</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Serrano-Ruiz</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumesic</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Datye</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved hydrothermal stability of niobia-supported Pd catalysts</article-title><source>Appl. Catal. A Gen.</source><volume>397</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>162</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0265">Pham, H.N., Pagan-Torres, Y.J., Serrano-Ruiz, J.C., Wang, D., Dumesic, J.A., Datye, A.K.., 2011. Improved hydrothermal stability of niobia-supported Pd catalysts. Appl. Catal. A Gen. 397, 153-162.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mella Orellana</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Abreu</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural, electronic, and thermodynamic properties of the T and B phases of niobia: first-principle calculations</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Phys. Chem. A</source><volume>121</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>2399</fpage><lpage>2409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28291341</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0270">Pinto, M.B., Soares, A.L., Mella Orellana, A., Duarte, H.A., De Abreu, H.A.., 2017. Structural, electronic, and thermodynamic properties of the T and B phases of niobia: first-principle calculations. J. Phys. Chem. A 121, 2399-2409.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raba</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bautista-Ru&#x000ed;z</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joya</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raba</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bautista-Ru&#x000ed;z</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joya</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and structural properties of niobium pentoxide powders: a comparative study of the growth process</article-title><source>Mater. Res.</source><volume>19</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1381</fpage><lpage>1387</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0275">Raba, A.M., Bautista-Ruiz, J., Joya, M.R., Raba, A.M., Bautista-Ruiz, J., Joya, M.R.., 2016. Synthesis and structural properties of niobium pentoxide powders: a comparative study of the growth process. Mater. Res. 19, 1381-1387.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rani</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoolfakar</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Mullane</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalantar-Zadeh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thin films and nanostructures of niobium pentoxide: fundamental properties, synthesis methods and applications</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Mater. Chem. A</source><volume>2</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>15683</fpage><lpage>15703</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0280">Rani, R.A., Zoolfakar, A.S., O&#x02019;Mullane, A.P., Austin, M.W., Kalantar-Zadeh, K.., 2014. Thin films and nanostructures of niobium pentoxide: fundamental properties, synthesis methods and applications. J. Mater. Chem. A 2, 15683-15703.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renders</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Bosch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koelewijn</surname><given-names>S.-F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schutyser</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sels</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lignin-first biomass fractionation: the advent of active stabilisation strategies</article-title><source>Energy Environ. Sci.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1551</fpage><lpage>1557</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0285">Renders, T., Van den Bosch, S., Koelewijn, S.-F., Schutyser, W., Sels, B.F.., 2017. Lignin-first biomass fractionation: the advent of active stabilisation strategies. Energy Environ. Sci. 10, 1551-1557.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A tandem for lignin-first biorefinery</article-title><source>Joule</source><volume>1</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>428</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0290">Rinaldi, R.., 2017. A tandem for lignin-first biorefinery. Joule 1, 427-428.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Catalytic Hydrogenation for Biomass Valorization</chapter-title><year>2015</year><publisher-name>Royal Society of Chemistry</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0295">Rinaldi, R.., 2015. Catalytic Hydrogenation for Biomass Valorization. Royal Society of Chemistry, Cambridge.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jastrzebski</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ralph</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennema</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruijnincx</surname><given-names>P.C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weckhuysen</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paving the way for lignin valorisation: recent advances in bioengineering, biorefining and catalysis</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><volume>55</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>8164</fpage><lpage>8215</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0300">Rinaldi, R., Jastrzebski, R., Clough, M.T., Ralph, J., Kennema, M., Bruijnincx, P.C.A., Weckhuysen, B.M.., 2016. Paving the way for lignin valorisation: recent advances in bioengineering, biorefining and catalysis. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 55, 8164-8215.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref78"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>R.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>H.J.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lignin-first biorefining of lignocellulose: The impact of process severity on the uniformity of lignin oil composition</article-title><source>J. Braz. Chem. Soc.</source><volume>30</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>491</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0420">Rinaldi R., Woodward R.T., Ferrini P., Rivera H.J.E., Lignin-first biorefining of lignocellulose: The impact of process severity on the uniformity of lignin oil composition, J. Braz. Chem. Soc. 30, 2019, 479-491.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrero-P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>M.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ba&#x000f1;ares</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Niobia-supported nanoscaled bulk-NiO catalysts for the ammoxidation of ethane into acetonitrile</article-title><source>Catal. Letters</source><volume>143</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0305">Rojas, E., Guerrero-Perez, M.O., Ba&#x000f1;ares, M.A., 2013. Niobia-supported nanoscaled bulk-NiO catalysts for the ammoxidation of ethane into acetonitrile. Catal. Letters 143, 31-42.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samec</surname><given-names>J.S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Holistic approach for converting biomass to fuels</article-title><source>Chem</source><volume>4</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1199</fpage><lpage>1200</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0310">Samec, J.S.M.., 2018. Holistic approach for converting biomass to fuels. Chem 4, 1199-1200.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Electronic spectroscopy of lignins</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Heitner</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimmel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Lignins and Lignans</source><year>2010</year><publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>102</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0315">Schmidt, J.., 2010. Electronic spectroscopy of lignins, in: Heitner, C., Dimmel, D., Schmidt, J. (Eds.), Lignins and Lignans. CRC Press, Boca Raton, pp. 49-102.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schutyser</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renders</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Den Bosch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koelewijn</surname><given-names>S.-F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckham</surname><given-names>G.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sels</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemicals from lignin: an interplay of lignocellulose fractionation, depolymerisation, and upgrading</article-title><source>Chem. Soc. Rev.</source><volume>47</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>852</fpage><lpage>908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29318245</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0320">Schutyser, W., Renders, T.., Van Den Bosch, S., Koelewijn, S.-F., Beckham, G.T., Sels, B.F., 2018. Chemicals from lignin: an interplay of lignocellulose fractionation, depolymerisation, and upgrading. Chem. Soc. Rev. 47, 852-908</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref59"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daemen</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez-Cuesta</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective production of arenes via direct lignin upgrading over a niobium-based catalyst</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>16104</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28737172</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0325">Shao, Y., Xia, Q., Dong, L., Liu, X., Han, X., Parker, S.F., Cheng, Y., Daemen, L.L., Ramirez-Cuesta, A.J., Yang, S., Wang, Y.., 2017. Selective production of arenes via direct lignin upgrading over a niobium-based catalyst. Nat. Commun. 8, 16104.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solcova</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uecker</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinike</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiratova</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of the support on the reducibility of high-loaded nickel catalysts</article-title><source>Appl. Catal. A Gen.</source><volume>94</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>160</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0330">Solcova, O., Uecker, D.C., Steinike, U., Jiratova, K.., 1993. Effect of the support on the reducibility of high-loaded nickel catalysts. Appl. Catal. A Gen. 94, 153-160.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref61"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sultan</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gra&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peeva</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebrahim</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Membrane fractionation of liquors from lignin-first biorefining</article-title><source>ChemSusChem</source><volume>12</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1203</fpage><lpage>1212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30673171</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0335">Sultan, Z., Gra&#x000e7;a, I., Li, Y., Lima, S., Peeva, L.G., Kim, D., Ebrahim, M.A., Rinaldi, R., Livingston, A.G.., 2019. Membrane fractionation of liquors from lignin-first biorefining. ChemSusChem 12, 1203-1212.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref62"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Various reactions catalyzed by niobium compounds and materials</article-title><source>Appl. Catal. A Gen.</source><volume>133</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>218</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0340">Tanabe, K., Okazaki, S.., 1995. Various reactions catalyzed by niobium compounds and materials. Appl. Catal. A Gen. 133, 191-218.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref63"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teles</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabelo-Neto</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukarakate</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orton</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Resasco</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noronha</surname><given-names>F.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catalytic upgrading of biomass pyrolysis vapors and model compounds using niobia supported Pd catalyst</article-title><source>Appl. Catal. B Environ.</source><volume>238</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0345">Teles, C.A., de Souza, P.M., Rabelo-Neto, R.C., Griffin, M.B., Mukarakate, C., Orton, K.A., Resasco, D.E., Noronha, F.B.., 2018. Catalytic upgrading of biomass pyrolysis vapors and model compounds using niobia supported Pd catalyst. Appl. Catal. B Environ. 238, 38-50.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref64"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thommes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neimark</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivier</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Reinoso</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouquerol</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sing</surname><given-names>K.S.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physisorption of gases, with&#x000a0;special reference to the evaluation of surface&#x000a0;area and pore size distribution (IUPAC Technical Report)</article-title><source>Pure Appl. Chem.</source><volume>87</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1051</fpage><lpage>1069</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0350">Thommes, M., Kaneko, K., Neimark, A.V., Olivier, J.P., Rodriguez-Reinoso, F., Rouquerol, J., Sing, K.S.W.., 2015. Physisorption of gases, with special reference to the evaluation of surface area and pore size distribution (IUPAC Technical Report). Pure Appl. Chem. 87, 1051-1069.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref65"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valencia-Balv&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Walton</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalpian</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osorio-Guill&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First-principles equation of state and phase stability of niobium pentoxide</article-title><source>Comput. Mater. Sci.</source><volume>81</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>140</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0355">Valencia-Balvin, C., Perez-Walton, S., Dalpian, G.M., Osorio-Guillen, J.M.., 2014. First-principles equation of state and phase stability of niobium pentoxide. Comput. Mater. Sci. 81, 133-140.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref66"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bifunctional Ni catalysts for the one-pot conversion of organosolv lignin into cycloalkanes</article-title><source>Catal. Today</source><volume>269</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>55</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0360">Wang, X., Rinaldi, R.., 2016. Bifunctional Ni catalysts for the one-pot conversion of organosolv lignin into cycloalkanes. Catal. Today 269, 48-55.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref67"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A route for lignin and bio-oil conversion: dehydroxylation of phenols into arenes by catalytic tandem reactions</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><volume>52</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>11499</fpage><lpage>11503</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0365">Wang, X., Rinaldi, R.., 2013. A route for lignin and bio-oil conversion: dehydroxylation of phenols into arenes by catalytic tandem reactions. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 52, 11499-11503.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref68"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solvent effects on the hydrogenolysis of diphenyl ether with Raney nickel and their implications for the conversion of lignin</article-title><source>ChemSusChem</source><volume>5</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>1455</fpage><lpage>1466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22549827</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0370">Wang, X., Rinaldi, R.., 2012. Solvent effects on the hydrogenolysis of diphenyl ether with raney nickel and their implications for the conversion of lignin. ChemSusChem 5, 1455-1466.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref69"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wojcieszak</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jasik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteverdi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziolek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettahar</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nickel niobia interaction in non-classical Ni/Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Mol. Catal. A Chem.</source><volume>256</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>233</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0375">Wojcieszak, R., Jasik, A., Monteverdi, S., Ziolek, M., Bettahar, M.M.., 2006. Nickel niobia interaction in non-classical Ni/Nb2O5 catalysts. J. Mol. Catal. A Chem. 256, 225-233.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref70"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kloekhorst</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venderbosch</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bykova</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khromova</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yakovlev</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heeres</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catalytic hydrotreatment of fast pyrolysis liquids in batch and continuous set-ups using a bimetallic Ni&#x02013;Cu catalyst with a high metal content</article-title><source>Catal. Sci. Technol.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>5899</fpage><lpage>5915</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0380">Yin, W., Kloekhorst, A., Venderbosch, R.H., Bykova, M.V., Khromova, S.A., Yakovlev, V.A., Heeres, H.J.., 2016. Catalytic hydrotreatment of fast pyrolysis liquids in batch and continuous set-ups using a bimetallic Ni-Cu catalyst with a high metal content. Catal. Sci. Technol. 6, 5899-5915.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref71"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Younker</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beste</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computational study of bond dissociation enthalpies for substituted &#x003b2;-O-4 lignin model compounds</article-title><source>ChemPhysChem</source><volume>12</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>3556</fpage><lpage>3565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22065478</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0385">Younker, J.M., Beste, A., Buchanan, A.C.., 2011. Computational study of bond dissociation enthalpies for substituted &#x003b2;-O-4 lignin model compounds. ChemPhysChem 12, 3556-3565.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref72"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemonidou</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lercher</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrodeoxygenation of bio-derived phenols to hydrocarbons using RANEY&#x000ae; Ni and Nafion/SiO<sub>2</sub> catalysts</article-title><source>Chem. Commun.</source><volume>46</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>412</fpage><lpage>414</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0390">Zhao, C., Kou, Y., Lemonidou, A.A., Li, X., Lercher, J.A.., 2010. Hydrodeoxygenation of bio-derived phenols to hydrocarbons using RANEY&#x000ae; Ni and Nafion/SiO2 catalysts. Chem. Commun. 46, 412-414.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref73"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemonidou</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lercher</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Highly selective catalytic conversion of phenolic bio-oil to alkanes</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><volume>48</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>3987</fpage><lpage>3990</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0395">Zhao, C., Kou, Y., Lemonidou, A.A., Li, X., Lercher, J.A.., 2009. Highly selective catalytic conversion of phenolic bio-oil to alkanes. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 48, 3987-3990.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref74"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Foord</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>S.C.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shape-dependent acidity and photocatalytic activity of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanocrystals with an active TT (001) surface</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><volume>51</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>3846</fpage><lpage>3849</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0400">Zhao, Y., Eley, C., Hu, J., Foord, J.S., Ye, L., He, H., Tsang, S.C.E.., 2012a. Shape-dependent acidity and photocatalytic activity of Nb2O5 nanocrystals with an active TT (001) surface. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 51, 3846-3849.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref75"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edman</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nanostructured Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> catalysts</article-title><source>Nano Rev.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0405">Zhao, Y., Zhou, X., Ye, L., Edman, S.C.., 2012b. Nanostructured Nb2O5 catalysts. Nano Rev. 3, 1-11.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref76"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fc;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation and spectroscopic properties of Nb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> nanorods</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Lumin.</source><volume>128</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>1369</fpage><lpage>1372</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0410">Zhou, Y., Qiu, Z., Lu, M., Zhang, A., Ma, Q.., 2008. Preparation and spectroscopic properties of Nb2O5nanorods. J. Lumin. 128, 1369-1372.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref77"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziolek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobczak</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of niobium component in heterogeneous catalysts</article-title><source>Catal. Today</source><volume>285</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>225</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0415">Ziolek, M., Sobczak, I.., 2017. The role of niobium component in heterogeneous catalysts. Catal. Today 285, 211-225.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec2" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplemental Information</title><p id="p0270"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>Document S1. Transparent Methods, Figures S1&#x02013;S4, and Tables S1&#x02013;S4</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>R.R. acknowledges the financial support provided by the <funding-source id="gs1">ERC</funding-source> Consolidator Grant LIGNINFIRST (Project Number: 725762). R.R. and A.A.S.C. thank FAPESP for the support provided (Process Number: 2016/50423-3). The authors are grateful to LNLS/CNPEM for the infrastructure (XPD beamline and chemistry laboratory), LNNano for the STEM infrastructure, the GPMMM laboratory (IQ-UNICAMP) for the quantitative FTIR of adsorbed pyridine analysis, CNPq for the PhD scholarship (Process Number: 165106/2014-0), and CAPES for the PDSE scholarship (Process Number: 88881.132245/2016-01). This study was financed in part by the <funding-source id="gs2">Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#x000ed;vel Superior</funding-source> - Brasil (CAPES) - Finance Code 001. Finally, the authors are thankful to CBMM for the ammonium niobium oxalate hydrate samples.</p><sec id="sec4"><title>Author Contributions</title><p id="p0255">Conceptualization, G.F.L, A.A.S.C., and R.R.; Methodology, G.F.L. and R.R.; Investigation, G.F.L., I.G., S.L., H.C., D.H.B., A.A.S.C., C.B.R., E.T.-N., and R.R.; Writing &#x02013; Original Draft, G.F.L.; Writing &#x02013; Review &#x00026; Editing, G.F.L., C.B.R, A.A.S.C., and R.R.; Funding Acquisition, C.B.R., A.A.S.C., and R.R.; Resources, C.B.R., A.A.S.C., and R.R; Supervision, C.B.R., A.A.S.C., and R.R.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Declaration of Interests</title><p id="p0260">The authors have no conflict of interests to declare.</p></sec></ack><fn-group><fn id="appsec1" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p id="p0265">Supplemental Information can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2019.05.007" id="intref0010">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2019.05.007</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>