<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Palestinian za’atar (
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic>) is not just a symbol of Palestine; it has also a great economic value. The economic value of growing and processing za’atar had become more viable in the last decade. The za’atar market has been greatly growing in recent years. Over 6000 dunams are planted with 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> in the northern West Bank, while only 500 dunams were planted in za’atar before 2010. The increasing demand by foreign companies has expanded the cultivated land of this herb. The za’atar market has a good profit; it regains its capital quickly, keeps producing for 7 years, has an average of harvesting every 40 days, and is resistant to pests and diseases. Palestinian za’atar farmers earn about 144 million New Israeli Shekel (NIS) annually. More than 85% of processed za’atar is sold in the local market, and the other 15% goes to the export market. The majority of produced za’atar is fresh-cut za’atar with an estimated 15,000 tons annually. The final marketed product of za’atar ranges from 20 to 29% (average 24%) compared with the freshly harvested biomass. Commercial production of za’atar is new in Palestine; it represented only 3% of the total exported herbs in 2013, but the production is growing and it more than doubled in both value and volume after two years, reaching 763 tons of dried za’atar and 329 tons of fresh za’atar in December 2016, according to the Palestinian Ministry of Agriculture. However, there is an export demand for other types of za’atar that are not known locally, but there are no research centers that can work on the hybridization and development of such kinds of za’atar. Palestinian 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> is not labeled by its scientific name; it is usually labeled as oregano or its Arabic name, za’atar. The end market of Palestinian za’atar is still dominated by about 42 cooperatives, hundreds of women’s groups, small-scale farmers, and about 16 processing industries. These processers are mainly located in Nablus and Jenin where most za’atar harvesting is carried out. A total of 200 workers produce za’atar and other kinds of herbs in these processers. A total of 70% of za’atar production in Palestine is done by commercial manufactures, while the other 30% is produced at homes and consumed locally. Some of the manufacturers buy fresh za’atar from farmers in big volumes during the peak of the season to reduce the costs. In Palestine, za’atar is commonly consumed in a dried form either alone or in za’atar mixes. Palestinians and people in regional countries prefer za’atar mixes for their strong, unique flavor. Only a small amount of za’atar from Jordan and Turkey is imported to Palestine each year, while Palestine exports za’atar to many countries including Jordan, Canada, Gulf countries, EU, and USA countries. About 70% of exported za’atar is in the dried form and most of it is exported in bulk to Jordan. Only some private-labeled packaged za’atar products are exported to Europe and the US. The Palestinian za’atar market is not big enough to reinforce an active industry. Therefore, za’atar producers and processors should concentrate on the export market to make a high-quality volume. To achieve this, local producers and processors will need to invest in developing export capabilities. Moving from exporting bulk raw za’atar to packaged branded products will significantly increase the Palestinian export value. Unfortunately, many challenges are facing the Palestinian za’atar market’s growth. It was found that Palestinian za’atar is re-exported from Israel to important markets as Israeli za’atar. Additionally, the cultivation of za’atar in Palestine is still difficult since its native areas are under occupation. Another challenge is the presence of competitor suppliers such as Jordan, Turkey, Lebanon, and Syria. These suppliers can compete on price, quality, and consistency of supply. Palestinian growers face difficulty in providing products with consistent quality, supply, and price. Manufacturers prefer other sources to buy raw materials, especially sumac and sesame, where they buy it from Turkey, Ethiopia, and Egypt. Other problems in Palestinian za’atar processing and production include: farmers are unorganized, the use of unsafe fertilizers, lack of equipment, lack of safety and standards certifications, some essential ingredients’ availability, quality and high cost, and very little production and processing of organic za’atar. Many factors need to be improved to solve these problems, including agriculture and propagation practices, research, processing and preservation technologies, quality control, marketing, legalization, and others [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
