<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Origanum</italic> can be generally characterized as several erect sub-shrubby Labiatae, and its stems are medium-sized, it has glandular punctate, and ovate leaves. 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> sub-terranean parts are mostly woody. Many species of 
 <italic>Origanum,</italic> especially the species grown in the East Mediterranean region, have woody, very thick roots. The stems in almost all Mediterranean species are woody as well. The length of stems varies among 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> species but most of them have stems with a length range of 30 to 60 cm. The leaves of 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> are petiolate in many species, and sessile or sub-sessile in several species. There is a big variation in the shape and size of leaf blades in 
 <italic>Origanum</italic>. Leaves’ length ranges from 2 to 40 mm, and their width ranges from 2 to 30 mm. The indumentum of leaves is similar to stems; however, the hairs on leaves are usually shorter. Two types of glands exist on the leaves: sessile and stalked glands. These also found on other parts of the 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> plant. Stems, corollas, bracts, and calyces also have glands on them. 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> verticillasters are arranged in dense spikes and have few sessile flowers and differentiated bracts. The inflorescences are mostly paniculate, the spikes are usually compact, and the bracts are imbricate. The number of bract pairs in a spike ranges from 2 to 40 with a mean of seven. The shape of bracts is often roundish, ovate, or obovate. Small bracts are similar to leaves in their texture, indumentum, and color, while large bracts are papery, partly purple or a yellowish-green color, and often are not hairy or just slightly hairy. Only two sessile flowers are found on a verticillaster in most 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> species. The nutlets of 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> species that have been seen are not different. They are brown and ovoid with 1–1.5 mm length, 0.5 mm width, and a base that is slightly acute to apiculate. Pollen grains of some species have been studied. They were suboblate, hexacoblate, or oblatespheroidal [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].
</p>
