<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our group prepared LO and silver nanoparticles (Ag NPs) incorporated with polyurethane (PU) nanofibers for wound-healing applications, as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-04017-f004">Figure 4</xref> [
 <xref rid="B107-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. The literature suggests that PU nanofibers provide several advantages, such as water insolubility, structural support to boost epithelization, noninvasiveness to human cells, and proper pore size for nutrient and gas transfer. However, PU nanofibers’ hydrophobic nature prevents their attachment with the wound, leading to low absorption of exudate and no release of the incorporated antibacterial agents. The addition of LO and Ag NPs (20% and 7%) significantly increased the hydrophilicity of the fiber mats, as illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-04017-f005">Figure 5</xref>A. At a high concentration of LO and Ag NPs, Ag salt decreases the PU solution’s viscosity and improves the dripping rate [
 <xref rid="B108-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. An MTT assay revealed that the viability of a chicken-embryo fibroblast was enhanced significantly with increasing Ag NPs and LO concentrations, up to the limiting concentration of 15% LO/5% Ag NPs, as illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-04017-f005">Figure 5</xref>B. The X-ray spectra of composites containing different LO and Ag NPs and pristine PU fibers are shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-04017-f005">Figure 5</xref>C. The spectrum of the virgin PU fibers was amorphous and did not show any apparent peaks. The diffraction peaks at 2θ of 38.58°, 44.63°, and 64.78°, which correspond to the (111), (200), and (202) crystal planes (hkl values) of Ag, were present in the spectra of the nanofibers that were incorporated with NPs. These results were in total agreement with the results in the literature on PU/Ag NP composites [
 <xref rid="B109-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. The results of a disk-diffusion assay indicated that nanofibers containing Ag NPs and LO were efficient in inhibiting the growth of 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus,</italic> and increased further as the concentration of LO and Ag NPs increased, as indicated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-04017-f006">Figure 6</xref> [
 <xref rid="B111-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>,
 <xref rid="B112-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,
 <xref rid="B113-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. Similarly, Pant et al. successfully established a green strategy to construct an Ag NP-assembled spiderweb-like PU nanofiber mat as a potential antibacterial medium [
 <xref rid="B114-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. Pant et al. also fabricated electrospun nylon6/Ag NP composite nanofibers, which showed antibacterial activity against both Gram-negative 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and Gram-positive 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>; therefore, they can be used in different areas such as wound dressing, water filters, etc. [
 <xref rid="B115-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. The outcome obtained from this study suggested that the nanofiber mats containing Ag NPs effectively controlled microbial growth, and could be a promising wound-dressing material.
</p>
