<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The applications of spectroscopy technique in agriculture are presented in 
 <xref rid="molecules-24-02025-t006" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 6</xref>. The spectroscopy technique is widely applied to inspect internal qualities that are externally invisible. A sizeable amount of research has performed spectroscopy in the UV-VIS-IR region to identify the internal constituents of agricultural products such as pigment compound in apple [
 <xref rid="B111-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>], moisture content in mushroom [
 <xref rid="B112-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>], protein and sugar in potato [
 <xref rid="B113-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>], and caffeine in coffee [
 <xref rid="B114-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>] among others. Within 400 to 1000 nm, 678 nm is sensitive to low chlorophyll content thus the reflectance at 678 ± 30 nm is suggested for the monitoring of the early stage of ripening and the pigment content change with a maximum correlation of closely 0.6 [
 <xref rid="B111-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>]. On the other hand, 590 to 700 nm is recommended for the maturity detection in early stage for yellow colour apple fruits with maximum correlation from 0.7 to 0.9. In the verification of moisture content in mushroom, the spectral region from 600 to 2200 nm gives the lowest standard deviation of cross validation as 0.644% and maximum correlation factor of 0.951 among the investigated wavelengths from 402 to 2490 nm [
 <xref rid="B112-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>]. A high experimental repeatability is presented by a standard deviation of 0.677% and a maximum correlation factor of 0.947 for a separate set of mushrooms of a similar type and treatment. In the protein and sugar content identification in potato, a modified PLS regression model is applied to calculate the relationship between the spectrum and chemical properties of the calibrated samples [
 <xref rid="B113-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>]. Based on the measurement, the standard deviations for crude protein, glucose, fructose, sucrose and red sugar for the 120 potato samples are 0.2%, 0.073%, 0.068%, 0.068%, and 0.122%, respectively. Correspondingly, the squared correlation coefficient for the above five parameters are deduced as 0.96, 0.70, 0.89, 0.62, and 0.82, respectively. In a total of 665 tea leaf samples, NIRS and liquid chromatography is coupled to a diode arrayed detector to determine its content of caffeine [
 <xref rid="B114-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>]. Among 375 calibration sets and 250 validation sets for caffeine in the tea leaf samples, a standard deviation of 8.6 and 8.9, as well as high squared correlation coefficients of 0.97 are acquired for both calibration and validation sets though regression model.
</p>
