<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concentration–mortality curves were estimated using probit analysis with the PROBIT procedure in the SAS statistical software package
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. The differential (essential oil and indoxacarb) susceptibility between lepidopteran species was estimated for each compound based on the estimated LC
  <sub>50</sub> (i.e., the lethal concentration capable of killing 50% of tested lepidopterans) for each compound and lepidopteran species, and the tolerance ratios (TR
  <sub>50</sub>) were estimated by dividing the LC
  <sub>50</sub> value obtained for 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gemmatalis</span> by the LC
  <sub>50</sub> value obtained for 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">frugiperda</span> strains
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. The 95% confidence limits of these toxicity rate estimates were considered to be significantly different (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05) if they did not include the value 1
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of egg viability, oviposition, foliar consumption and larval weight were subjected to univariate analysis of variance (ANOVA), or Kruskal-Wallis one-way ANOVA on ranks when the assumptions of normality and homoscedasticity were not satisfied. The results of walking behavior were submitted to multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) to secure an overall error level of 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05 with subsequent (univariate) analyses of variance of each trait, when appropriate (PROC GLM;
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>). The results of group activity were subjected to repeated measure analyses of variance to determine the effects of essential oil concentrations. Differences were recognized by Fisher’s exact test (PROC ANOVA;
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>).
 </p>
</sec>
