<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">Strength of phytotoxicity of 
 <italic>O. acanthium</italic> essential oils obtained from different plant parts along with the oil’s major components were investigated by performing bioassays against 
 <italic>Amaranthus retroflexus</italic> L. (dicot) and 
 <italic>Poa annua</italic> L. (monocot) using glyphosate (Roundup, Monsanto Co., St. Louis, MO, USA) being the positive control; these 2 species were chosen because they can be found growing alongside 
 <italic>O. acanthium</italic> in the same habitat. The essential oils’ major constituents including tricosane, tetracosane, pentacosane, hexacosane, heptacosane, octacosane, nonacosane, and β-eudesmol were purchased from Alfa Aesar
 <sup>®</sup> (Shanghai, China); purity of all compounds were 98%. Seeds of receiver species were surface sterilized with 2% sodium hypochlorite before use. The oils and the major components were first dissolved in DMSO (0.1% final concentration) and then diluted with distilled water containing Tween 80 (final concentration 0.02%) to give solutions at 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2.5, and 5 mg/mL for the assay (a preliminary experiment was conducted and results demonstrated that DMSO and Tween 80 at such concentrations did not affect seedling growth of 
 <italic>A. retroflexus</italic> and 
 <italic>P. annua</italic> significantly). Each petri dish (φ 5 cm) received 2 mL solutions (controls received 2 mL of distilled H
 <sub>2</sub>O containing 0.1% DMSO and 0.02% Tween 80) and 10 sterilized seeds of receiver species. Petri dishes were sealed with parafilm and kept in a growth cabinet at 25 °C with a 12-h photoperiod. 
 <italic>A. retroflexus</italic> and 
 <italic>P. annua</italic> seedlings were measured after 5 days and 7 days of incubation, respectively, due to relative slow development of 
 <italic>P. annua</italic> seedlings
 <italic>.</italic> Three replicates were performed for the assays (
 <italic>n</italic> = 30)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
