<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">A few species of 
 <italic>Millettia</italic> has evidence of values as a drug in the indigenous system of medicine for a number of ailments. In different countries of Asia, Africa and Australia such as India, Pakistan, Burma, China, Thailand, France, Kenya, etc in which 
 <italic>Millettia</italic> species are also grown naturally and used as ethnomedicine by local people (
 <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Dat et al., 2019</xref>). These species have been accessed for the treatment of various ailments. A number of studies have reported their use as traditional medicine by local people and have been widely used to treat the infected wounds, skin disorders, cough, rheumatoid pain, ulcer, menstrual disorder, inflammation, bronchititis, toothache, muscle ache, tuberculosis, hepatitis and bruises, etc presented in 
 <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The roots of 
 <italic>M. auriculata</italic> Brandis
 <italic>, M. racemosa</italic> (Roxb.) Benth.
 <italic>, M. pachycarpa</italic> Benth. and 
 <italic>M. piscidia</italic> (Roxb.) Wight were reported to have insect repellent, larvicidal activity, antitumor, anti-inflammatory, antiviral, and antibacterial and pest destroying activity. These are also used as a fish poison and applied to sores of cattle to kill vermin. A different community of Cameroon has used this 
 <italic>Millettia</italic> species for the treatment of intestinal parasites in case of children as a potent inhibitor (
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Rahman et al., 2015</xref>). In India, the Gujjar tribe follows the use of 
 <italic>M. extensa</italic> (Benth.) Baker barks paste for the treatment of wound (
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et al., 2013</xref>). The Bhilla tribe in Maharashtra, India also used its bark juice for the wound by applying it once a day for a time period of 4–5 days (
 <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Kamble et al., 2010</xref>). The tribal community of Odisha (Kalahandi District) used the root paste of 
 <italic>M. extensa</italic> (Benth.) Baker with liquor for the treatment of piles. They used this herbal formulation by applying it over the piles for 5 min in a time period of 2 days and also the root paste is used for the treatment of patient bitten by a mad dog (
 <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">Panda and Padhy, 2008</xref>). It is also used for the treatment of cough and skin infection (
 <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Padhi et al., 2017</xref>). The Tai Yai community in Northern Thailand used the leaves and stem of 
 <italic>M. auriculata</italic> Brandis by boiling it with water and used in the bath due to its tonic property (
 <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Khuankaew et al., 2014</xref>). 
 <italic>M. pachycarpa</italic> Benth. seeds are promptly used for the treatment of worm infection, pain and bruises (
 <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">Tu et al., 2019</xref>). As a rectal formulation the macerated twigs of 
 <italic>M. barteri</italic> (Benth.) Dunn is used to treating the purgative disorder. The stem bark (decoction) extract is taken for feverish aches, cough, and dysmenorrhea. Also, the decoction of bark root is taken to lower the cardiac pains (
 <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Havyarimana et al., 2012</xref>). In Congo, the aqueous decoction of 
 <italic>M. versicolor</italic> Baker leaves and stem bark is taken to treat intestinal parasitoses, feverish aches, kidney pains, cough, and female sterility. For the treatment of the syphilitic wounds, the infusion of stem bark is used on the bath. The trunk barks having potent anthelmintic property (
 <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Ongoka et al., 2008</xref>). 
 <italic>M. pinnata</italic> (L.) Panigrahi flower is used for the treatment of piles as well as bleeding disorders. Its fruits are meant for the treatment of abdominal ulcer and tumor. The leaf juice is meant for the treatment of cough, colds, leprosy, diarrhoea. The whole leaves are used as digestive, inflammation and also for wounds. Stem extract is used as sedative for CNS. The root juice is mixed with coconut milk and lime water for the treatment of gonorrhea (
 <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Pulipati et al., 2018</xref>). However, to the best of our knowledge, there are a number of traditional uses of the genus 
 <italic>Millettia</italic> are available in the literature as folkloric claims and these findings raised the possibility of researchers to undertake the exploration as well as scientific assessment of the activities.
</p>
