<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ability of the seeds to complete germination was tested in glass Petri dishes (ø = 5 cm). The seeds of each species were mixed before use to fulfil the randomization requirement. The seeds (25 per one Petri dish) were placed on double-layer filter paper and moistened with 3 ml of the tested solutions. To maintain stable and homogenous conditions all dishes were sealed with parafilm. The moisture level was monitored daily and the seeds were re-watered when any loss was observed. Germination test was conducted under 16/8 h photoperiod (light was supplied with white fluorescent tubes with a photon flux density of 52 μmol m
 <sup>−2</sup>·s
 <sup>−1</sup>) at 23°C. Close to natural photoperiod was used, due to the fact that the seeds of the species we studied complete germination only under sufficient light conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The temperature of 23°C was listed as optimal for completion of germination for many herbaceous plant species from the temperate region (including wild-living rangeland species [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] and species from dry acidic grasslands) and represents the mean temperatures at the Lodz Weather Station during June and July, when most seeds germinate in natural habitats. Furthermore, it allows direct comparisons of many species subjected to various chemical treatments [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Experiments were repeated four times (n = 4). Due to the fact that completion of germination of the studied species reached plateau after 12 days in the preliminary test, it was recorded daily for 14 days. The seeds that completed germination were removed from the Petri dishes. An emerged radicle was a sign of completed germination. Germination-related traits were determined on the basis of the number of viable seeds. Dead seeds (with soft and brown embryo) were not included in the calculations.
</p>
