<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The egg and, more precisely, the egg yolk, is a vitamin-rich food that contains all vitamins except vitamin C (ascorbic acid). The absence of vitamin C in the egg may result from the fact that birds are capable of satisfying their own vitamin C requirements, by de novo synthesis from glucose [
 <xref rid="B52-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. The ability to produce vitamin C has been lost during the process of evolution in several animal species including guinea pigs, monkeys, flying mammals, humans, and some evolved passerine birds [
 <xref rid="B52-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Consequently, these latter species, but not domestic birds, are dependent on dietary sources of vitamin C (fruits and vegetables). The egg yolk contains high amount of vitamin A, D, E, K, B1, B2, B5, B6, B9, and B12, while egg white possesses high amounts of vitamins B2, B3, and B5 but also significant amounts of vitamins B1, B6, B8, B9, and B12 (
 <xref rid="nutrients-11-00684-t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). Eating two eggs per day covers 10% to 30% of the vitamin requirements for humans. It is noteworthy that the content of liposoluble vitamins (vitamins A, D, E, K) in egg yolk is highly dependent on the hen’s diet (See 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec4dot2-nutrients-11-00684" class="xref">Section 4.2</xref>). In addition to these vitamins, eggs represent a major source of choline, which is essentially concentrated in the yolk (680 mg/100 g in the egg yolk versus 1 mg/100 g in the egg white) [
 <xref rid="B30-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. It has been reported that hard-boiled egg represents the second major source of choline after beef liver [
 <xref rid="B54-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] and the first source of choline in the US diet [
 <xref rid="B55-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. In foods, choline is found as both water-soluble (free choline, phosphocholine, and glycerophosphocholine) and lipid-soluble forms (phosphatidylcholine and sphingomyelin) and has important and diverse functions in both cellular maintenance and growth across all life stages. It plays some roles in neurotransmission, brain development, and bone integrity [
 <xref rid="B54-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>].
</p>
