<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">The plant consists of plenty of pharmaceutically important phytochemicals like xanthones, ursolic acid, flavonoids, terpenoids, iridoids, amarogentin, glycosides, secoiridoids and swertiamarin. Ophelic acid (C
 <sub>13</sub>H
 <sub>48</sub>O
 <sub>15</sub>) and chirantin (C
 <sub>26</sub>H
 <sub>48</sub>O
 <sub>15</sub>) are two major compounds present in such plant, are reasonable for developing bitter test. In terms of nature, ophelic acid is yellow in colour, non-crystalline, hygroscopic in characteristics and can be dissolved in water, ether or alcohol. Chirantin or Amarogentin binds with tannic acid to form insoluble compound. The compound is pale-yellow in colour, soluble in alcohol, ether, specifically in warm water. The compound splits into ophelic acid, water and 
 <italic>chiratogenin</italic> (C
 <sub>13</sub>H
 <sub>24</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>) when it is boiled with hydrochloric acid [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. It represents chemo-preventive and anti-leishmanial effects and possess properties like topoisomerase inhibition [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Presence of transparent monoterpene alkaloid like Gentianine is also proved in 
 <italic>S. chirayita</italic> extract. The compound belongs to the series of compounds which are recognized as pyranopyridines, polycyclic aromatic compounds containing pyran ring attached with a pyridine ring. In terms of nature, gentianine is soluble in aqueous solution and known for its anti-inflammatory, anaesthetic, antihistamine, anticonvulsant properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. It also poses other medicinal properties like antimalarial, antiamoebic, hypotensive, antipsychotic, and antibacterial properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Properties like bitter taste forms gentianine a potential biomarker for ingesting of such compound containing food product. Swertiamarin which is considered as a secoiridoid glycoside, present in the same plant extract, is known for its analgesic property. The compound was successfully used to treat diseases like arthritis, malaria, diabetes, hypertension, atherosclerosis and abdominal ulcers [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Such potential secoiridoid glycoside was successfully reported to control increased serum total cholesterol, triglycerides in high cholesterol induced rats. Swerchirin is one of the member classes of xanthones, isolated from 
 <italic>Swertia</italic> spp., possess similar medicinal properties like hypoglycemic, antimalarial and antihepatotoxic activity. Similarly like Swerchirin, presence of nine tetraoxygenated xanthones were also proved in 
 <italic>Swertia</italic> spp. Preliminary pharmacological screening clearly revealed the presence of such xanthones in the plant extract and it mainly signifies its therapeutic potential. Mangiferin, another potential bioactive constituent present in chirayita species, known for its antioxidant properties and other versatile therapeutic potentials [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. The compound also possess health endorsing antimicrobial, antiallergic, anticancer, hypocholesterolemic and immunomodulatory properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. The compound was proved to have inhibitory mechanism against various human cancers. Poor solubility, mucosal permeability and bioavailability of the compound mainly hinders its development as most successful clinical therapeutic agent and physicochemical modification is required to further extend its application. Lignan are the another type of fiber-associated polyphenolic substances normally isolated from the same plant origin. The compound is hepatoprotective in nature and basically obtained from a large variety of plant associated food products including seeds, grains, nuts, vegetables, legumes, fruit and drinks such as wine, tea or coffee. Existing researches in this field suggest that food rich in lignans are beneficial for health and cure diseases but additional investigations are required to justify the specific role of lignans. Along with such compounds, 
 <italic>chirayita</italic> also contains verities of triterpenoids including pichierenol, swertanone, gammacer-16-en-3β-ol, 21-a-H-hop-22(29)-en-3β-ol, taraxerol, swertenol, oleanolic acid, ursolic acid, episwertinol, swerta-7, 9(11)-dien-3β-ol [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Existence of some specific pentacyclic triterpenoids like β-amyrin, friedlin, chiratenol, kairatenol is also proved in this plant species. Present researches clearly reported the application of such naturally producing triterpenoids against several human health compilations which includes different cancers. Taraxerol as well as oleanolic acid are well known for their analgesic properties whereas ursolic acid was identified for its chemoprotective, anti-inflammatory and anti-microbial characteristics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Different types of experimental animal models have been already implemented to establish anticancer, anti-proliferative and pro-apoptotic properties of different triterpenoids present in the same plant species. Researchers like Basnet et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>] evaluated the hypoglycemic potential of bellidifolin, isolated from 
 <italic>Swertia japonica</italic> (another 
 <italic>Swertia</italic> species) on STZ-induced diabetic rats. The compound was highly effective to reduce glucose level in normal and diabetic rats when the compound was orally and intraperitoneally administrated. Previously Ghosal et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>] recognized the presence of nine tetraoxygenated xanthones in roots and aerial parts of 
 <italic>Swertia chirata</italic> and among those components, 1,5,8-trihydroxy-3- methoxyxanthone was identified with blood sugar lowering ability. Existence of anti-inflammatory xanthone derivative (1,5-dihydroxy-3,8-dimethoxyxanthone) was also recognized in the same plant species and activity level of the compound was evaluated by using sub-acute and chronic male albino rat experimental models [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Chemical structures of most specific and important therapeutically active phytochemicals obtained from S. 
 <italic>chirayita</italic> plant extract are represented in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.
</p>
