<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0095">Recent reports suggest that the development of bacterial drug resistance against various approved drugs is a big challenge (
 <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Högberg et al., 2010</xref>). Therefore, searching for more potent antimicrobial agents using plant-based products/extracts plays a crucial role in preventing the cellular kinetics of pathogens (
 <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Bag et al., 2012</xref>). Plant-based extracts have been reported to be effective against multidrug-resistant microorganisms. Among them, S. 
 <italic>aureus</italic> is one of the major challenging bacteria found in hospital-related infections with an approximate mortality rate of around 7–10% (
 <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Tatsimo et al., 2012</xref>). Previous reports revealed that owing to a high content of bioflavonoids and phenolic compounds, methanolic extracts of Hippophae 
 <italic>rhamnoides</italic> exhibited promising activity against Gram-positive S. 
 <italic>aureus</italic> and B. 
 <italic>subtilis</italic> (
 <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Jeong et al., 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2013</xref>)
 <italic>.</italic> Consistent with previous reports, all the four methanolic extracts of T. 
 <italic>articulata</italic> shows the significant antibacterial activity as revealed by the zone of inhibition against both Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria when compared to positive control ampicillin and gentamycin respectively. However, methanolic extract of dry leaves of T. 
 <italic>articulata</italic> exhibits maximum antibacterial activity against both Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria with zone of inhibition (20.1 ± 0.30 mm, 19.9 ± 0.18 mm, 18.1 ± 0.18 mm against P. 
 <italic>aeruginosa</italic>, K. 
 <italic>pneumonia</italic>, E. 
 <italic>coli</italic>) and Gram-positive bacteria (22.7 ± 0.23 mm, 25. 3 ± 0.34 mm, 19.4 ± 0.12 mm against S. 
 <italic>aureus</italic>, S. 
 <italic>epidermidis</italic>, S. 
 <italic>pneumonia</italic>) respectively. These results demonstrate that T. 
 <italic>articulata</italic> could be used as promising antibacterial agents in the future.
</p>
