<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Different types of cellulose with a well-defined and functionalized morphology with different active principles can be used to obtain advanced wound dressings with high performance for preventing wound infections and accelerated wound healing [
 <xref rid="B1-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Previous studies of wood-based nanofibrillated cellulose (NFC) have shown a high capacity to absorb liquids and form translucent films, suggesting the benefits of using cellulose fibers as a dressing. The property of maintaining a moist environment is necessary for the proper healing of chronic wounds, while translucency makes it possible to evaluate the wound progress without requiring the dressing removal [
 <xref rid="B3-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In addition, these nanomaterials can provide various drug delivery properties and other effects, depending on the raw materials they come from [
 <xref rid="B4-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] and can be used for the design of functional wound dressing or for topical drug delivery, offering several advantages over other administration pathways, including eliminating internal metabolism, minimizing pain, prolonging the drug release, and controlling drug absorption by removing skin bandage [
 <xref rid="B5-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. On the other side, Nie (2019) showed that the nanocellulose fibers (NF) have lower thermal stability compared with raw microcellulose fibers (MF) due to the reduced particle size, increased specific surface area, and increased exposed carbon and reactive group activity. The thermal degradation of NF generates low molecular weight segments and breakpoint defects. The same effect was produced after introducing the carboxylate group on the cellulose surface of the nano-sized fiber (prepared by oxidation of TEMPO ((2,2,6,6-tetramethyl-1-piperidinyl)oxidanyl) [
 <xref rid="B2-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Microcellulose fibers can be obtained from different plant species (including invasive ones), such as bamboo [
 <xref rid="B6-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], 
 <italic>Artemisia vulgaris</italic> [
 <xref rid="B2-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], and banana plant wastes [
 <xref rid="B7-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. 
</p>
