<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>PSF Experiment 1: To illustrate how mycorrhizal type associated with the specific soil microbial community determines PSF strengths, we conducted a pot experiment using germinated seedlings. We chose nine co-existing tree species in the first planting experiment as focal species, namely 3 AM plants (
 <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic>, 
 <italic>Pterospermum lanceaefolium</italic>, and 
 <italic>Schima superba</italic>), two EM plants (
 <italic>Castanopsis fissa</italic> and 
 <italic>Castanopsis chinensis</italic>), two NF plants (
 <italic>Albizia lebbeck</italic> and 
 <italic>Ormosia glaberrima</italic>), one NM plant (
 <italic>Helicia cochinchinensis</italic>), and one eucalypt (EU) plant (
 <italic>E. urophylla</italic>) (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). For each focal species, we selected six adult trees and collected two soil samples from the root zones of each individual (&lt;0.5 m from the base of the stem, 0–20 cm depth), and thoroughly pooled all samples for its species-specific soil. To avoid cross-contamination, we cleaned the shovels and sterilized them with 70% ethanol prior to the next sampling. In addition, we collected bulk soil from the field site, where those target tree species was not present within a radius of 50 m. To prepare the background soil, we mixed the bulk soil with sand (v 1:1) followed by sterilization with gamma radiation (25 kGy). We then thoroughly mixed the background soil with the species-specific soil (v 9:1) to prepare seven soil inocula treatment for each species: (i) conspecific sterilized soil, (ii) conspecific living soil, (iii) mixed soil of all species with the same mycorrhizal type to focus species and (iv)-(vii) the other four types of soil, respectively, mixed with their species-specific inocula (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Figure 2A</xref>). In particular, the NM and EU type with only one species, so 
 <italic>H. cochinchinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>E. urophylla</italic> seedlings both had only six inocula treatments without the mixed inocula of (iii). For each species, we filled plastic pots (13 cm in diameter, 15 cm in height) with one of 6 or 7 soil inocula in each pot. Thus, seedlings of the nine focal species were treated with 61 soil inocula treatment combinations and there were 549 pots in total (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Figure 2A</xref>), namely (7 species × 7 soil inocula + 2 species × 6 soil inocula) × 9 replicates.
</p>
