<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0175">Among the factors (excellent germplasm, cultivation area, water and fertilizer management, pest control, growth years, harvesting time, etc.) that affect the quality of Chinese medicinal materials, the post-harvest processing has a great impact on the content of medicinal active ingredients, which would further affect the clinical efficacy and stability of TCM (
 <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2018a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">2018b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2010</xref>). For 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>, the traditional post-harvest processing technology is to remove impurities after harvesting and to dry naturally in sun. Generally, it will not directly kill the enzymes in fresh roots of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> using steam. Instead, the dried roots will be softened by steam, and then cut to slices, and finally to be dried again. Previous studies have confirmed that steam treatment is better than water boiling treatment to soften the dried roots of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">Liao, 2006</xref>). The former has high temperature, strong penetration and good enzyme-killing effect, while the latter has the dried roots expose to water with slower softening speed so that some glycoside components will be dissolved in water (
 <xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">Qin et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">Liao et al., 2007</xref>). Therefore, the steam treatment is used to soften dried roots and to kill enzyme activity before cutting to slices, thereby preventing the content of glycosides from decreasing in traditional methods. In recent years, a series of new drugs including extracts, drop pills, formula particles and injection originated from 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> have been developed, leading to increasing demands for the raw medicinal materials of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>. Thus, it is bringing urgent needs that novel processing approaches should be proposed accordingly based on the traditional methods. To develop effective and reliable processing methods, a primary issue is that it remains unclear how the different treatments and processing technology affect the contents of medicinal active ingredients. In this study, we systematically designed six kinds of processing and technology according to several traditional treatments of post-harvest processing of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>. The total contents of the four main medicinal active ingredients in roots of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> using different processing treatments after harvest were shown as (from high to low): 
 <italic>D</italic> &gt; 
 <italic>C-D</italic> &gt; 
 <italic>C-S-D</italic> &gt; 
 <italic>D-S- C-D</italic> &gt; 
 <italic>S- C-D</italic> &gt; 
 <italic>D-S-C</italic> (
 <xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Among them, the total contents of four main active ingredients of 
 <italic>C-D</italic> treatment declined markedly compared with those of 
 <italic>D</italic> treatment, which may be related to the fact that baicalin and wogonoside can be transformed into baicalein and wogonin by the key enzyme UBGAT during the cutting process of fresh roots of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">Nagashima et al., 2000</xref>). Compared with other treatments of softening and slicing, the contents of active ingredients under 
 <italic>D</italic> treatment (drying and cutting directly) have the highest levels, indicating that this treatment could effectively reduce the loss of active ingredients during the processing process. For traditional methods, it is very difficult to cut the dried roots to slices following the 
 <italic>D</italic> treatment. Meanwhile, the cutting process of dried root is easy to form debris and irregular particles, which will not pass the quality control for use in medicine. However, for pharmaceutical enterprises, it is easy to cut the dried roots directly and then extract effective active ingredients including baicalin, wogonoside, and other ingredients. As a traditional processing method, the 
 <italic>D-S- C-D</italic> treatment typically softened the dried roots first and then cut to slices. The contents of active ingredients under such treatment is significantly higher than those of 
 <italic>D-S-C</italic> treatment (drying-softening-cutting) (
 <italic>P</italic> ≤  0.05). This result is related to the fact that moisture is often absorbed into dried roots during the process of steaming and wet roots that are not dried in time. Therefore, the baicalin in roots is susceptible to be hydrolyzed into other components in moisture conditions by steaming. To prevent the reduction and conversion of glycosides, the most effective treatment should be killing the enzyme activity by steaming. In the industrial production, the steam treatment and the drying treatment with high temperature can kill the enzyme in roots of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> to prevent the reduction or conversion of baicalin. For the efficiency of killing enzyme activity in fresh root slices of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>, the result showed that the contents of medicinal active ingredients with drying and cutting treatment (
 <italic>C-D</italic>) are higher than those of 
 <italic>C-S-D</italic> treatment (cutting-softening-drying). The most possible reason should be that the enzyme activity quickly lost under high temperature during the drying process, while the moisture could transform glycosides into aglycones in the process of steaming treatment. Meanwhile, the other active components are reduced and lost with the condensation and dissolution of water vapor. The contents of active ingredients of 
 <italic>C-S-D</italic> treatment are higher than those of 
 <italic>S- C-D</italic> treatment. This result may be related to that the enzyme inactivation is faster and more complete in 
 <italic>C-S-D</italic> treatment. Consequently, the dried slices can retain more active ingredients in roots of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>.
</p>
