<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <xref rid="foods-10-00106-t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref> summarises some important MAPs and their main volatile compounds. Regarding the data presented in this table, a different type of compound is responsible for the aromatic features of MAPs. For example, Lee et al. [
 <xref rid="B181-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>] identify a high content of linalool, methyl cinnamate, estragole, eugenol, and 1,8-cineole compounds in basil cultivars and reported that these compounds were responsible for the typical aroma of basil perceived by consumers. Similar results were presented by Shahwar et al. [
 <xref rid="B182-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>], who reported that the typical aroma of coriander is due to a mixture of different compounds in which decenal and related compounds (
 <xref rid="foods-10-00106-t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>) assume a high preponderance. Several other authors [
 <xref rid="B181-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>,
 <xref rid="B182-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>,
 <xref rid="B183-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>,
 <xref rid="B184-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>,
 <xref rid="B185-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>,
 <xref rid="B186-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>,
 <xref rid="B187-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">187</xref>,
 <xref rid="B188-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">188</xref>,
 <xref rid="B189-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">189</xref>,
 <xref rid="B190-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>,
 <xref rid="B191-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>] have reported that the typical aromatic features exhibited by MAPs are a result of a combined effect of several compounds rather than a single compound, as shown by Kizhakkayil and Sasikumar [
 <xref rid="B185-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>] for ginger. These authors reported that the typical “spicy” and “fresh” aromas exhibited by ginger is due to the simultaneous presence of different compounds such as zingiberene, 6-gingerol, 8-gingerol, 10-gingerol, 6-shogaol, 8-shogaol, geranial, and neral. These compounds, even in lower amounts, are critical for the consumer to perceive the typical aroma of ginger, all of them are important to define the ginger “bouquet”.
</p>
