<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Acceptability study</div>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During a one-month trial, the majority of the participants (52/60) applied the lotion correctly while 7 individuals applied the lotion sporadically: 5 individuals applied the lotion 3 times before sleeping, 40 applied it 2 times and 15 applied it only once. In general, most of the individuals (91.6%) apply lotions after a shower to keep skin hydrated while 5 men do not routinely apply lotions. Among the adolescents and adults (31 participants), most found the odor tolerable while 10 stated that it was strong smelling (pungent). The side effects (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>) included sneezing, feeling nauseous, and vomiting, but only 6 individuals reported these effects.
  <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Reported side effects.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Undesirable Effects</th>
      <th>Individuals, n = 60</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Sneezing</td>
      <td>3</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Nausea</td>
      <td>2</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Vomiting</td>
      <td>1</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Total</td>
      <td>6</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Almost everyone agreed that the lotion reduced how often they were bitten. Only one individual said that it was ineffective and that they were bitten as often with the repellent; 55 individuals said that they were not bitten after applying the lotion (Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>). Here we assign a value of 2 to individuals finding the essential oil effect effective and 1 to those who did not. Assuming the responses are normally distributed, the p-value was 0.001 for a null hypothesis that the essential oil was ineffective, which allows us to conclude that it was effective.
  <div id="Tab3" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Lotion effectiveness according to the survey.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Comments</th>
      <th>Individuals, n = 60</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Ineffective</td>
      <td>1</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Lotion reduces bites</td>
      <td>4</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>No bites after application</td>
      <td>55</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
