<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Steam distillation</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">KarireProducts cultivated 
   <span class="italic">N. cataria</span> in the Moso region in the province of RUTANA, Burundi, picked the leaves at full bloom, and air-dried them for 30 hours. In a 5 hour process, a stainless steel steam distillation system isolated essential oil from chopped dried plant material (20 to 25 kg/batch). We stored the essential oil in amber containers at low temperature (4 °C). A propane burner boiled water at the bottom of a tank and the steam it generated passed through a metal mesh that was supporting the weight of the leaves. The steam first heats the biomass. After one hour, both oil and water vapour broke through to the top of the distillation column and passed through a pipe at the top lead to a condenser. The condensed solution separated in a second vessel and we collected both the hydrosol and essential oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ultrasound extraction</div>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A Sonics Vibracell Ultrasound probe delivered 20 W (500 W nominal power) to 20 mL of water and ethanol in which we added 1 leaf (approximately 0.2 g) of catnip collected before the plant flowered. Sonication lasted 1 min. A thermocouple measured the temperature of the liquid. We collected all samples in 2 mL glass vials. The reference samples were stored in a 500 mL hermetically sealed dark brown glass bottle that we covered in aluminum foil and stored in a chemical cabinet maintained at ambient temperature.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Scanning electron microscopy</div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A field emission scanning electron microscope (FE-SEM-JEOL JSM-7600F) with a voltage of 2 kV imaged catmint leaves (LEI detector). The distance between sample and detector was 13 mm.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography</div>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">N. cataria</span> oil is a clear pale yellow liquid, with a refraction index of 1.4882 ± 0.0005 (23 °C). We diluted the samples in HPLC grade pentane (1:200). A gas chromatograph equipped with a flame ionisation detector (GC-FID) and another GC coupled to a mass spectrometer (GC-MS) quantified the main components of the essential oil. The GC-FID was equipped with a DB-5 column (30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 m; Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA), while the GC-MS had a Solgel-Wax column (30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 m; SGE Analytical Science, Austin, TX, USA). We set both GCs injection port and detector temperature at 220 °C and 260 °C, respectively. Helium carried analytes at a flow rate of 1.4 mL/minute. Temperature remained at 40 °C for 2 minutes, then increased to 210 °C at a rate of 2 °C/minute. The split ratio was 50:1 and the injection volume was 3 microlites. The mass spectrometer operated in electron-impact (EI) mode at 70 eV, with a scan range of 40–550 amu and a scan speed of 1458.6 amu/s. The temperature of the MS interface was 300 °C. We computed FID peak areas without a correction factor. The retention times of n-alkanes with an even number of hydrocarbons (C8–C24) injected using the same analytical conditions determined the retention indices of the essential oil constituents. We qualitatively identified all the compounds from the NIST library
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
   </span>. To identify the geometrical isomers we injected standards, purchased from Sigma Aldrich.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stability tests</div>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the light stability tests we exposed the samples to a UV-A lamp (Spectroline EA-160), while for the heat stability we placed the samples in an oven at 60 ± 3 °C. In the combined light and heat stability tests we placed the oil containing vials at the bottom of a thermic bath (ISOTEMP 205) at 60 ± 3 °C surmounted with the UV-A lamp.</p>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We applied ASTM-D5768 to measure the iodine value of the essential oil, which represents the degree of unsaturation: the iodine reacts with the double bonds, also known as the Wijs procedure.</p>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We reported the acid value as g of KOH required to neutralize 100 g of sample.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Acceptability study</div>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After meeting with presidential staff and ministers of health and agriculture, students in the faculty of medicine developed a strategy to assess the population’s acceptability of applying mosquito repellents daily. We produced a lotion that contained a mixture of 5% nepetalactone in vegetable oil, almond oil and citronella. In 2011 from March 3
   <span class="sup">rd</span> to April 3
   <span class="sup">rd</span>, the students followed 8 families in Kamenge (an urban neighborhood of Bujumbura) as selected by the non-governmental agency ALUMA respecting pre-established selection criteria and 4 families in the rural community of Cibitoke (selected by the local hospital). Both were hyper endemic malaria regions. Each family received 2 bottles with 100 mL of the lotion. The volunteers included one pregnant woman, 10 children younger than 5 y, 19 children from 5 to 11 y, 11 adolescents from 12 to 20 y, and 20 adults older than 20 y of which most of these were farmers (17). There were 32 males and 28 females in the study. Most individuals (45%) were in bed under impregnated mosquito nets by 21h00, while 32% were in bed by 22h00, and 10 children were in bed before 20h00.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data availability</div>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article (and its Supplementary Information files).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethics statement</div>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All participants and guardians were enrolled from March 3
   <span class="sup">rd</span> to April 3
   <span class="sup">rd</span> 2011 and provided written informed consent. Action de Lutte contre la Malaria au Burundi (ALUMA) and the hospital of Cibitoke selected the individuals. The hospital of Cibitoke and ALUMA approved the experimental protocol and it was carried out in accordance to all relevant guidelines and regulations.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
