<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
 <label>Figure 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Mechanisms of atherosclerosis induced by postprandial lipemia. (1) Endothelial function: TG increased after HFM, while serum nitrite/nitrate levels and FMD decreased, suggesting endothelium dysfunction. (2) Oxidative stress: In terms of oxidative stress, TBARS, leukocyte 
   <inline-formula>
    <math id="M1">
     <msubsup>
      <mrow>
       <mtext>O</mtext>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mn>2</mn>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mo>-</mo>
      </mrow>
     </msubsup>
    </math>
   </inline-formula>, and 8-PGF2 increased, and SOD, GSH-PX, and GSH decreased after HFM. ROS are produced in large quantities due to the increased levels of free fatty acids mediated by mitochondrial dissociation and β-oxidation. (3) Inflammation: ApoB100-containing lipoproteins enter into the arterial subendothelium, thus generating proinflammatory lipids, promoting the expression of adhesion factors such as, VCAM-1 and ICAM-1, which induce the augmentation of adhesion interaction with monocytes in turn, generating proinflammatory phenotypes and AS; TRL isolated from human plasma after HFM regulated TNF-α-induced VCAM-1 expression by regulating IRF-1-dependent transcription mechanism. The expression of CD11c on monocytes increased after a meal, and the purified monocytes internalized TRL isolated from postprandial blood through LDL receptor associated protein-1, which also caused the upregulation of CD11c. (4) Apoptosis: With the relation of cell cycle regulation and apoptosis, a group of genes of HUVEC differentially expressed in serum of postprandial hyperlipidemia after a meal, causing proliferation of HUVEC, significantly decreased and may be achieved by activating p53 network; the activities of pro-MMP-9, MPO, and caspase-3 increased significantly after a meal, showing apoptosis effect. (5) ER stress: The expansion of ER was significantly increased by HAEC treated with postprandial TRL, and the production of TRL increased the adhesion of VCAM-1-dependent monocytes to inflammatory endothelium, indicating ER stress plays a role in the regulation of VCAM-1 transcription in endothelial cells during the process of AS. (6) Mitochondrial dynamics: The binding rate of GDP increased by 85% after HFM, and the increase was the largest in early postprandial period. TG, triglyceride; HFM, high-fat meal; FMD, flow-mediated vasodilation; TBARS, thiobarbiturate reactants; 8-PGF2, 8-external prostaglandin F2; SOD, superoxide dismutase; GSH-PX, glutathione peroxidase; ROS, reactive oxygen species; VCAM-1, vascular cell adhesion molecule-1; ICAM-1, intercellular adhesion molecule-1; AS, atherosclerosis; TRL, TG-rich lipoprotein; LDL, low-density lipoprotein; HUVEC, human umbilical vein endothelial cell; ER, endoplasmic reticulum; HAEC, human aortic endothelial cell.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="fcvm-08-636947-g0001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
