<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In their studies, Fernandez et al. [
 <xref rid="B46-ijms-22-03671" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] investigated the efficacy of semisynthetic eugenol derivatives—such as 
 <italic>O</italic>-alkylated bearing the propyl chain with hydrogen, hydroxyl, ester, chlorine, and carboxylic acid as terminals and corresponding 
 <italic>O</italic>-alkylated oxiranes against the Sf9 (
 <italic>Spodoptera frugiperda</italic>) insect cell line. The insecticide activity of eugenol derivatives was also compared to a commercial synthetic insecticide, chlorpyrifos. Results showed that all eugenol derivatives that were formed by the alkylation reactions of the hydroxyl group possessed a propyl chain, with hydrogen, hydroxyl, ester, chlorine, and carboxylic acid terminals displaying higher toxicity than the pure form of eugenol. Among the oxiranes that arise from the epoxidation of alkylated derivatives, all compounds also showed higher toxic potential. The greatest efficacy was presented by two oxiranes—2-(4-(3-chloropropoxy)-3-methoxybenzyl)oxirane and ethyl 4-(2-methoxy-4-(oxiran-2-ylmethyl)phenoxy)butanoate, whose effects on the insects’ cells were nearly twofold stronger than the effect of the commercial insecticide. These two derivatives were further analyzed to investigate the effects on insects’ cells. Extended studies showed that both eugenol derivatives caused decrease in cell density compared with control cells, which corresponded with their impact on cell viability. Moreover, both derivatives exhibited changes in the chromatin structure—both chromatin condensation and nuclear fragmentation. In addition, an investigation of the impact on human cells was performed, as evaluation of potential toxic effect on humans is crucial for the development of new pesticides. Considering the usual routes of poisoning, human skin keratinocytes were chosen for the examination. Of these two derivatives, only ethyl 4-(2-methoxy-4-(oxiran-2-ylmethyl)phenoxy)butanoate showed no harmful effects on human cells while still demonstrating strong insecticidal activity, thus displaying a selective effect on insects’ cells.
</p>
