<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The liver is the centre of drug metabolism and it plays many critical functions such as cleansing toxins from the blood, producing immune agents to control infection, producing bile, and synthesizing proteins such as albumin and fibrinogen (Andreatos et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). It is well known that a substantial increase in steatosis and fibrosis usually leads to potentially lethal cirrhosis of the liver in humans (Turola et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The high global prevalence of hepatopathy places it among the most severe diseases (Araújo et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Although the pathogenesis of liver fibrosis is not entirely clear, there is no doubt that reactive oxygen species (ROS) play an essential role in pathological changes in the liver, particularly in cases of alcoholic and toxic liver diseases (Albano 
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Contreras-Zentella and Hernández-Muñoz 
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Biological membrane lipids are particularly prone to the ROS effect (Zadak et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). The peroxidation of unsaturated fatty acids in biological membranes leads to a decrease of membrane fluidity and to a disruption of membrane integrity and function, which is implicated in severe pathological changes (Erturk et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Yan et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Several endogenous protective mechanisms have been evolved to scavenge ROS and limit undesired cellular damage (Adams et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). However, since this protection may not be complete, or when the formation of ROS is excessive, additional protective mechanisms of dietary antioxidants may contribute to the health benefits (Ristow 
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Therefore, many natural and artificial agents possessing antioxidative properties have been proposed to prevent and treat hepatopathies induced by oxidative stress (Lee et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Kumarappan et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). There is increasing evidence for the hepatoprotective role of hydroxy- and polyhydroxy-organic substances, derived from fruits, vegetables, and some herbs (Bosek and Nakano 
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Moreover, different kinds of tea leaves are the most popular non-alcoholic beverages that contain a wide range of various natural antioxidants (Shi et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Busch et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).
</p>
