<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent animal studies demonstrated the broad-spectrum bioactivities of tricin, ranging from anti-obesity effect in high-fatdiet-induced obese mice [
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] to protection against UVB-induced wrinkle formation [
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Nevertheless, the anti-metastatic and/or immunomodulatory effects of tricin in colon cancer model have not yet been reported. Therefore, the present study aimed to verify the systemic efficacy of tricin in treating colorectal cancer using mouse model, of which the promising results might in turn translate to clinical uses. Here, a syngeneic orthotopic colon tumor-bearing mouse model using immune-competent mice was adopted to mimic the clinical pathological condition of metastatic CRC patients. Our results demonstrated apparent anti-tumor and anti-metastatic effects of tricin treatment at 37.5 mg/kg, which was comparable to the effects of chemotherapeutics FOLFOX treatment (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-03730-f004">Figure 4</xref>). The real-time monitoring of the tricin inhibitory effect on orthotopic colon tumor growth was reported here for the first time. This also provided evidence for demonstrating how oral dosage of tricin could gradually control colon tumor progression. Furthermore, in the immune-competent tumor-bearing mice, the ability of modulating tumor immunogenicity of tricin appeared to be stronger than that of FOLFOX since the populations of MDSC in spleens, regulatory T cells in lymph nodes, macrophages and tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes in tumors were altered after Tricin-H but not FOLFOX treatments. It is possible that the immunomodulatory efficacy of tricin was similar to that of its derivative, antartina (tricin 7-
 <italic>O</italic>-β-D glucopyranoside, isolated from grass 
 <italic>Deschampsia antarctica</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Intraperitoneal treatment with antartina for three weeks could inhibit colorectal carcinoma growth and liver metastasis in mice. The potent specific cytotoxic T-cell response against colorectal carcinoma and activation of dendritic cells induced by antartina were suggested to be responsible for the anti-tumor effect [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Nonetheless, antartina was administered by intraperitoneal injection while tricin was administered by oral gavage in the study. The oral bioavailability of tricin was reported [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and we showed the efficacy of ingested tricin in colon tumor-bearing mice. Hence, the feasibility to develop tricin as one of the health food ingredients for improving colon health is demonstrated here. Furthermore, based on the immunomodulatory properties of tricin, the potential benefit of combined use of tricin-containing food or medicinal herbs with chemotherapy and/or immunotherapy in colorectal cancer management is worth further investigation.
</p>
