<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0005">Exploring enhanced disease ameliorating therapeutic strategies against cognitive disorders like Alzheimer’s disease (AD) is a leading challenge of recent era. Cognitive impairment and neuropathological etiology is in consistent with cholinergic deficiency due to presence of neurofibrillary tangles and senile plaques besides the degeneration of cholinergic and cortical neurons in basal forebrain (
 <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Davies and Maloney, 1976</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">Varadarajan et al., 2000</xref>). World Health Organization (WHO) estimated approximately 71% of the dementia cases occur in developing countries (
 <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Ferri et al., 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Goverdhan et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Mathew and Subramanian, 2014</xref>). According to an estimate, by 2050, prevalence of dementia is expected to rise around 46.8 million people (
 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">Association, 2015</xref>). Therefore, cognitive disorders have become primary research areas due to their huge economic, social and healthcare impacts upon society. Financial burden along with social stigma linked with the loss of cognitive capabilities and lead to psychological sufferings in patients (
 <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Borsje et al., 2016</xref>). Loss of acetylcholine (ACh) neurotransmitter is critically important in causing dysfunction of cholinergic neurotransmission in aging or age-related disorders, responsible for cognitive deficits (
 <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">Vinutha et al., 2007</xref>). Acetylcholinesterase (AChE) is primarily responsible for ACh breakdown within cerebral cortex synapses (
 <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Bierer et al., 1995</xref>). Complex and multifaceted pathophysiology in neurodegeneration includes inflammation (
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Heneka et al., 2015</xref>), accretion of amyloid peptide (Aβ), highly phosphorylated tau protein, oxidative stress, mitochondrial dysfunction (
 <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Federico et al., 2012</xref>), neuronal apoptosis and cholinergic signaling deficit (
 <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Mufson et al., 2008</xref>). Strategies to improve cholinergic function include the cholinergic receptors activation or providing long term ACh availability to neuronal synaptic cleft via suppressing ACh hydrolysis by AChE (
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Palop and Mucke, 2016</xref>). Release of oxidative and inflammatory stress and ACh stimulation via inhibition of AChE seem imperative potential targets for neurodegeneration therapeutics. Commercially available AChE inhibitors for treatment of mild to moderate neurodegenerative disorders (NDs) include donepezil, tacrine, galanthamine, huperizine A, physostigmine (eserine) and rivastigmine. Synthetic drugs exhibit limited efficacy and significant side effects including gastrointestinal disturbances, hepatotoxicity, low bioavailability, short term biological activity (
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Chopra et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2011</xref>). These drugs also reported to temper only cholinergic symptoms, not to design for targeting specific mechanistic pathways involved in NDs pathogenesis (
 <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Lovell and Markesbery, 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">Nunomura et al., 2001</xref>). To counteract these side effects, natural therapeutic options are considered for enhancing NDs treatment efficiency (
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2014</xref>). Natural antioxidants and anti-inflammatory bioactive components possessed by medicinal plants extracts are reported to prevent cell damage and exhibit neuroprotective effects for the management of NDs (
 <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Aguiar and Borowski, 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2016</xref>)
 <italic>.</italic> Animal studies for improving cognitive functions using curcumin, a natural compound, indicated the recovery in memory, improved cholinergic function and reversal of stress-induced loss in neurogenesis (
 <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Poulose et al., 2017</xref>). Another study indicated the anti-cholinesterase activity of saffron ultimately modulating the cholinergic functions (
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Bukhari et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
