<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0090">This review delivers a comprehensive range of evidence on the utilization of polyphenols extracted from medicinal plants for the reserve of CoVs. The cases obviously demonstrate that the designs with specific components of polyphenols and/or herp extracts that have been established for centuries in traditional medicine can be useful as the basis of anti-SARS-CoV components in the treating and/or deterrence of COVID-19. Natural polyphenols can act as anti-enzymes, antioxidants, and through binding-blocking virus exterior protein receptors. Different plants can be utilized as a source of polyphenols with a wide range of biological activity. These components offer hope that polyphenol extracts accessible in this review may have antiviral activity, also against CoVs-family. The wide range of natural polyphenols presented in different sources, which are undervalued in conformist medicine, may establish a nearly infinite source of remedies. The latest tendencies in medicine and biotechnology have allowed the usage of polyphenols to a greater level, than in the earlier decades, mainly as nutritional complements and nutraceuticals. Their toxicity altogether with ingesting time is yet to be explored by aims of multidisciplinary tactics (proteomics, omics science-genomics, and metabolomics). New formulation technologies and processing might aid to improve the antiviral polyphenols solubility, delivery tactics, and therapeutic effects to adjust them as antiviral functional foods and remedies. The research achieved so far have added to the information of the chemical structure of antiviral polyphenols. Bioinformatic studies of the polyphenols-pharmacophores structures can chief to scheming new antiviral polyphenols drugs. The usage of plant extracts might deliver synergistic health useful effects i.e., anti-inflammation, antioxidant, antimutagenic, and antiviral among occurring polyphenol blends, which should be considered and must be intensely discovered.(
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Khalifa et al,2020</xref>),(
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Khalifa et al,2020</xref>),(
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Khalifa et al,2020</xref>),(
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Pekmezci, 2011</xref>) (
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Ryu et al, 2010</xref>)
</p>
