<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Keeping in view the medicinal use of 
 <italic>E. cardamomum</italic> in multiple gut-related disorders, the essential oils of EC-I (India) and EC-G (Guatemala) were evaluated and compared for their antidiarrheal and gut inhibitory activities through in vivo and in vitro assays. A castor oil-induced diarrhea model was used to study the antidiarrheal effect, whereas isolated rat ileum preparations were used in the in vitro experiments for elucidation of the detailed mechanism [
 <xref rid="B38-molecules-26-02546" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Diarrhea was induced in normal mice by using castor oil, which after hydrolysis into ricinoleic acid, led to evoked spasms in the gut [
 <xref rid="B39-molecules-26-02546" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Pre-administration of both 
 <italic>EC-I</italic> and 
 <italic>EC-G</italic> protected the mice from diarrhea in a dose-dependent manner; however, higher potency was observed with EC-I. After observing the antidiarrheal response, the method described by Palla et al. was followed to test and compare both the samples for antispasmodic effect in vitro in the isolated rat ileum [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-26-02546" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. For this purpose, 
 <italic>EC-I</italic> and 
 <italic>EC-G</italic> cumulative concentrations were added to organ bath after inducing sustained contractions with CCh and high K
 <sup>+</sup>. Interestingly, both samples demonstrated a dose-dependent complete inhibition of both types of contraction. A critical analysis of the pattern of the inhibitory CRCs of 
 <italic>EC-I</italic> and 
 <italic>EC-G</italic> against CCh and high K
 <sup>+</sup>-induced contractions indicated that 
 <italic>EC-I</italic> produces relaxation with significantly higher (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) potency than 
 <italic>EC-G</italic>. The mechanism supposed to be involved in the antispasmodic effect might be the inhibition of a phosphodiesterase (PDE) enzyme [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-02546" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and voltage-dependent Ca
 <sup>++</sup> channels, because both these mechanisms are involved in smooth muscles relaxation [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-26-02546" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-molecules-26-02546" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The antidiarrheal effect of EC-I is related to the inhibition of smooth muscle contraction and may be due to the presence of high concentration of the major compound α-terpinyl acetate and 1,8 cineole in this essential oil [
 <xref rid="B43-molecules-26-02546" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The present study elucidates an additional antispasmodic mechanism of cardamom not reported so far, namely the PDE enzyme inhibition. Gilani et al. reported Ca
 <sup>++</sup> channel blocking-like mechanisms; however, they did not test it against CCh-induced contractions, which are used to decipher the PDE inhibitory and/or cholinergic mechanisms (REF). Gilani et al. used aqueous methanolic extract, whereas we used essential oil of cardamom [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-02546" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. However, our results are also concurrent with those reported by Gilani et al., because they reported that the petroleum ether fraction of cardamom is the most potent in the CCB activity (inhibitory effect at 0.1 mg/mL). We explored the antispasmodic and antidiarrheal effects of cardamom essential oils for the first time, and our findings indicate that the activity of oils varies mainly due to the presence of 1,8 cineole [
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-26-02546" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Compound α-terpinyl acetate inhibited cytochrome P450 enzyme [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-26-02546" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]; inhibition of this enzyme may contribute to antidiarrheal effects [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-26-02546" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. In several studies, plants containing major compounds such as sesquiterpenes have also been reported for the biological effects including antimicrobials and antidiarrheal [
 <xref rid="B43-molecules-26-02546" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-26-02546" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], so not only the monoterpenes but sesquiterpenes may also contribute to the antidiarrheal effects.
</p>
