<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>At the peak of COVID19 pandemic which shudder the whole world through human to human transmission of SARS-CoV-2, devouring numerous lives, medical professionals and researchers all over the globe are in pursuit for the discovery of prophylactic or anaphylactic remedy to surmount the condition (Al-Khafaji et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Boopathi et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Pant et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Thus far, no specific vaccine or antiviral therapeutic has been either discovered or anticipated as a conventional medication for this viral infection (Zumla et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0091" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Current treatment strategy includes supportive care which is extended with supplementation of combination of broad-spectrum antibiotics, antivirals, cortecosteroids and convalescent plasma (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Habibzadeh &amp; Stoneman, 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). SARS-CoV-2 was found to be an enveloped single-stranded RNA-type beta coronavirus which shares 79.5% sequence similarity with its antecedent class SARS-CoV (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Wu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0082" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). During the previous outbreak of SARS crisis due to SARS-CoV, several research groups have conducted 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> analysis and randomized trials on use of natural herbal medicines to control the adverse effects of infection and evidenced their use as effective (Hsu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Jang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Kim et al., 2008; Lau et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">2005a</xref>, 2005b; Li et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Wen et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0081" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). As novel coronavirus is closely related to SARS coronavirus, it can be suggested that natural herbal medicine may have potential use in existing health crisis (Aanouz et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Elfiky, 
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">2020b</xref>; Islam et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Umesh et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0075" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Wahedi et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0078" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). In addition to this, for decades, natural herbal medicine has been expended for prevention and cure of numerous ailments concerning human wellbeing.
</p>
