<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this research, physical experiments and numerical simulations were completed with the primary goals of studying the effect of polymer degradation on polymer flooding in heterogeneous reservoirs and providing theoretical and technical guidance for its application in the development of these reservoirs. The physical experiment results showed that the viscosity of the polymer solution and polymer concentration had a good power law relationship with a high correlation coefficient square of 0.98. The viscosity of the polymer solution increased with increasing polymer concentration. However, the viscosity of the polymer solution decreased with increasing shear rate, demonstrating that the rheological property of the polymer solution presented shear thinning performance. Moreover, the viscosity of the polymer solution decreased with increasing time due to the polymer degradation. The plots of the polymer static and dynamic degradations showed excellent exponential relationships with high correlation coefficient squares of 0.93 and 0.94, and the first-order static and dynamic degradation rate constants were 0.0017 day
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> and 0.0022 day
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, respectively. The first-order dynamic degradation rate constant was greater than the first-order static degradation rate constant due to additional polymer chain ruptures, which were caused by the additional shear stress during the polymer solution flow through sands, resulting in supplemental polymer degradation. Furthermore, the new 3D two-phase polymer flooding simulator that evaluated the polymer static and dynamic degradation was designed and validated with high accuracy and reliability by comparing the obtained results with the simulation results run by the commercial software, as well as with the results obtained from the polymer flooding experiments. Additionally, the effect of polymer degradation on the production indicators were analyzed using the deigned simulator. According to the simulation results, the production indicators were significantly influenced by the polymer degradation. In the case that used a first-order dynamic degradation rate constant of 0.100 day
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, the oil recovery, after a cumulative injection volume of 1.67 PV, was 7.7% lower than in the case without considering polymer degradation. The larger amount of remaining oil in the reservoir and the faster polymer leading edge that occurred due to a reduction in the polymer solution viscosity, caused by the polymer degradation, led to an increase in the water-oil mobility ratio, resulting in unsatisfactory polymer flooding.
</p>
