<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The modulation of the activities of COX-1 and COX-2 is considered as one of the strategies to combat chronic inflammation. The anti-inflammatory action of the extracts and fractions were evaluated using a COX-inhibitor screening kit (Cayman Chemical, USA) following the manufacturer’s recommendation. The EIA kit used to determine the COX-1 and COX-2 inhibitory activity has been used in previous studies.
 <xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> The principle of the test kit is based on the inhibition of the biosynthesis of prostaglandins, thromboxanes, and prostacyclins from arachidonic acid by COX. The assay determines the production of prostaglandins (PGF
 <sub>2α</sub>) that is generated by stannous chloride (SnCl
 <sub>2</sub>), in the presence of PGH
 <sub>2</sub>. The initial reactions occurred in test tubes (initial reaction test tubes) at 37°C. In the background test-tubes, reaction buffer and heme were mixed together. Then, in the 100% activity test-tubes, reaction buffer, heme, enzyme (either COX-1 or −2) and the solvent used for dissolving the extract/fraction were added. In the sample test-tubes, reaction buffer, heme, inhibitor at different concentrations and enzymes were added. All test-tubes (initial reaction, 100% activity, background and samples) were incubated for 15 min at 37°C. Then, arachidonic acid (substrate) was added to all the tubes and incubated for 2 min. One molar hydrochloric acid (1 M HCl) was added to each test-tube to stop the reaction and thereafter, SnCl
 <sub>2</sub> was added to stabilize the reaction product. All the test-tubes were incubated for a further 5 min at room temperature. A 96-well microtitre plate coated with mouse anti-rabbit IgG was provided with the kits. In the 96-well microtitre plate, non-specific binding, maximum binding, standards, and the inhibitor dilutions from the test tubes were added with a tracer and antiserum. The 96-well microtitre plate was then incubated at room temperature for 18 h, washed 5 times with the wash buffer and developed with the Ellman’s reagent. The Ellman’s reagent is made up of acetylthiocholine and 5, 5ʹ-dithio-bis-(−2-nitrobenzoic acid) or DTNB. Hydrolysis of acetylthiocholine by acetylcholine esterase (tracer) cleaves thiocholine, which reacts with DTNB to yield 5-thio-2-nitrobenzoic acid or NTB, a yellow product that could be measured at 410 nm. Afterwards, the 96-well microtitre plate was placed on a microplate reader and read at 410 nm. The amounts of the product (yellow colour) are inversely proportional to the concentrations of the PG in the wells.
</p>
