<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Bioactivity of Plant EOs and Their Single Components</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bioactivity of EOs is the sum of its constituents which act either in a synergistic or in an antagonistic way [
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>, 
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>]. The term “bioactivity” could be used for all EOs as well as their main active constituents either stable or volatile such as monoterpenes, sesquiterpenoids, benzenoids, and phenylpropanoids which demonstrate a sort of biological activity on humans, animals, and plants.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The following part of the current review covers the following points: (i) mode of action of single components; (ii) factors affecting the single components bioactivity.</p>
 <sec id="sec4.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1. Mode of Action</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most antimicrobial activities of several plant EOs depend mainly on their bioactive single components which are able to inhibit the growth of microorganisms and/or completely suppress the pathogens [
   <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>, 
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>]. In fact, several studies have explained that the synergetic effect between two or more chemical constituents could have a distinctive role in the biological activity of EOs [
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The synergism between the aromatic plant components often plays an essential role in the effectiveness and reduction of the developing resistance of any pathogenic microorganism. Therefore, some constituents such as carvacrol, 
   <span class="italic">γ</span>-terpinene, and p-cymene are more effective when they are combining together [
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>]. This synergistic action is due to p-cymene which acts as a mediator for carvacrol transportation across cell wall components and the cytoplasmic membrane of pathogenic fungi. Furthermore, the enzymatic reactions within the EOs and the lipophilic properties of the individual bioactive constituents might play a role in degrading the microbe plasma membrane and hence lead to the lyses of the hypha wall as discussed by Soylu et al. (2010) [
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2. Factors Affecting the Bioactivity of EOs Composition</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The composition of each EO can vary depending on certain conditions such as plant variety, plant part, growth area, climatic changes, harvesting time, storage conditions, and the chemotype of each component [
   <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>]. Therefore, the composition of EOs cannot be expected to be similar every year even if they are extracted from the same area. For example, the minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) of four different chemotypes of thyme oil (linalool, thuyanol, carvacrol, and thymol type) against
   <span class="italic"> Staphylococcus aureus </span>Rosenbach ranged from 250 to 4000 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL depending on the presence of thymol [
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For improving the antimicrobial outfindings of many plant EOs, several factors either biological and experimental should be taken into consideration such as (i) appropriate and exact standardized microbiological test; (ii) available standard strains from different collections; (iii) assays including a variety of microorganisms either gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria, phytopathogens and human pathogens and yeasts; (iv) exact botanical identification of the plant EOs origin; (v) biochemical characterization of the extracted EOs as well as their production, storage conditions, and age. In addition, the distinctive water solubility and volatility of many EOs enable them to reveal a broadband spectrum of activity in various
   <span class="italic"> in vitro </span>tests such as agar well diffusion, serial dilutions, and volatile tests [
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several plant EOs demonstrated different antimicrobial activities according to the tests carried out, examiners themselves, or any other factors. For example, lemon EO showed to some extent a clear inhibition effect against
   <span class="italic"> Escherichia coli </span>Migula by using agar diffusion test as reported by Fisher and Phillips (2006) [
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>]. However, other researchers did not notice any inhibition activity from lemon oil against the same target organism using another nutrient media iso-sensitest agar [
   <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Möse and Lukas (1957) [
   <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>] have observed a clear inhibition activity from lemon oil against
   <span class="italic"> Klebsiella pneumonia</span> Schroeter in agar diffusion test, whereas Deans and Ritchie (1987) [
   <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>] reported that there is no antibacterial effect from lemon oil against this bacterium. The obtained results of MIC test showed diverse actions regarding the antibacterial activity of rosemary oil against
   <span class="italic"> S. aureus</span> ranging from 20 to 400 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL as reported by Panizzi et al. (1993) [
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>] due to differences in incubation period even at the same temperature.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand, Pellecuer et al. (1976) [
   <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>] reported the highest MIC value (1250 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL) regarding rosemary oil obtained in the dilution test against
   <span class="italic"> Bacillus subtilis</span> Ehrenberg, whereas Farag et al. (1989) [
   <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>] observed a moderate MIC value (750–800 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL). However, Panizzi et al. (1993) [
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>] reported the lowest MIC value of the same oil (10 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL) and these changes in estimated values could be due to the fluctuation of some experimental factors like temperature and incubation period.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
