<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although the coupling of amino acids onto CS has been extensively explored, in the last few years the incorporation of antimicrobial peptides has attracted more attention. Antimicrobial peptides (AMPs), both host defense peptides and their synthetic analogues, are promising candidates as antimicrobial agents due to their high efficiency and low probability to induce bacterial resistance [
 <xref rid="B53-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. Furthermore, the preparation of these cationic peptide-polysaccharides might enhance the selectivity towards bacteria in comparison with mammalian cells, as their structure mimics the peptidoglycans found in the bacterial membrane [
 <xref rid="B56-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. Cationic chitosan-
 <italic class="italic">graft</italic>-polylysine and chitosan-
 <italic class="italic">graft</italic>-poly(lysine-
 <italic class="italic">ran</italic>-phenylalanine) have been prepared by 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>-carboxyanhydride (NCA) ring-opening copolymerization of α-amino acids initiated from the amino groups of chitosan. The resulting derivatives showed outstanding broad spectrum antimicrobial properties against Gram-negative 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and Gram-positive 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> bacteria (MIC values between 5 and 20 μg/mL) and the fungi 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Fusarium solani</italic> (MIC values between 0.2 and 0.9 μM,) while maintaining very high selectivity over human RBCs. In another strategy, the antimicrobial peptide poly(lysine
 <sub class="sub">11</sub>-
 <italic class="italic">stat</italic>-phenylalanine
 <sub class="sub">10</sub>), prepared by NCA ring-opening copolymerization, was modified by hexamethylene diisocyanate and then statistically grafted onto the acid-functionalized chitosan [
 <xref rid="B57-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. In this approach, the residual −COOH groups had to be further esterified, as an important decrease in the antibacterial activity was observed that partially counteracted the positive charge.
</p>
