<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rosemary (
 <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L.) essential oil is commonly used for food and medicinal purposes due to its anti-inflammatory, anticancer, fungicidal, antioxidant, and antimicrobial activities, mainly owing to its flavonoid and terpene content. Alizadeh-Sani et al. prepared whey protein isolate/cellulose nanofiber/titanium dioxide/rosemary essential oil (WPI/CNFs/TiO
 <sub>2</sub>/REO) bio-nanocomposite film by the casting/evaporation method [
 <xref rid="B233-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">233</xref>]. The transparency value observed from 400 to 800 nm revealed that its transparency was reduced after encapsulating the TiO
 <sub>2</sub> and REO into WPI. Therefore, the highest clarity was of pure WPI [
 <xref rid="B234-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">234</xref>,
 <xref rid="B235-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">235</xref>]. Furthermore, the WPI/CNF film-transparency value was lowered slightly by REO, but it was not notable. The addition of a higher concentration of TiO
 <sub>2</sub> and CNFs to pure WPI enhanced WPI films’ thickness. After encapsulating a higher concentration of CNFs, the moisture absorption value increased, but TiO
 <sub>2</sub> and REO incorporation induced the opposite outcome [
 <xref rid="B235-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">235</xref>,
 <xref rid="B236-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">236</xref>]. To preserve consistency and minimize moisture transfer between the ambient atmosphere and the product, the packaging material’s water-vapor permeability should be minimal. It was observed that the encapsulation of CNFs, REO, and TiO
 <sub>2</sub> decreased the water content, water-vapor permeability, and water solubility of WPI films [
 <xref rid="B237-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>,
 <xref rid="B238-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">238</xref>]. WPI/CNF 7.5% films blended with TiO
 <sub>2</sub> nanoparticles and REO presented more considerable mechanical strength and antioxidant activity. The WPI/CNF 7.5%/TiO
 <sub>2</sub> 1% REO2% composite film showed the larger inhibition zone against 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes, Staphylococcus aureus, Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic>, and 
 <italic>Salmonella enteritidis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B239-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">239</xref>]. Because of the excellent distribution of the TiO
 <sub>2</sub> and REO into the WPI/CNFs matrix, the films prepared in this study showed better morphological features and good antioxidant and antibacterial activity. They enhanced physicomechanical properties, which are the significant properties needed for packaging applications.
</p>
