<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Curcumin (diferuloylmethane) is the main active curcuminoid and a water-insoluble pigment isolated from turmeric (curcuma), the dried rhizome of 
 <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L, (Zingiberaceae). It possesses multiple therapeutic properties and is considered a potential candidate for treating eye diseases (Radomska-Leśniewska et al., 2019). Several researchers (Wang et al., 2013; Pescosolido et al., 2014) have demonstrated the beneficial effects of curcumin on ocular diseases, such as chronic anterior uveitis, diabetic retinopathy, glaucoma, AMD, and dry eye syndrome, which make curcumin a potent therapeutic drug candidate for inflammatory and degenerative retinal eye diseases. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies suggest that curcumin has various mechanisms, which supports the concept of it interacting with multiple cellular signalling pathways and modulating numerous molecular targets. It exerts anti-inflammatory, anti-tumour, antioxidant and antiangiogenic properties through the modulation of numerous biochemical mediators (Hewlings et al., 2017; Peddada et al., 2019). Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-γ (PPAR-γ) ligands play an antiangiogenic role in AMD. Curcumin, a PPAR-γ agonist, may therefore play a role in mitigating AMD progression through the down-regulation of the proinflammatory functions of microglia. Recently, Saberi et al. (2019) reported that curcumin activates PPAR-γ that, in turn, down-regulates matrix metalloproteinases production. It is well-known that matrix metalloproteinase-9 causes extracellular matrix degradation and stimulates RPE cell migration to Bruch’s membrane, and thus contributes to AMD pathogenesis. It has also been shown that curcuma extract and its curcuminoids provide significant protection against photooxidative damage and apoptosis in human retinal pigment epithelial cells laded with A2E in a dose-dependent manner (Park et al., 2017). Other curcuminoids, such as 7-(3,4 dihydroxyphenyl)-5-hydroxy-1-phenyl-(1E)-1-heptene isolated from 
 <italic>Curcuma comosa</italic>, also protect human retinal pigment epithelial cells against oxidative stress, (H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>)-induced partly by enhancing several anti-oxidant defence mechanisms. The anti-oxidant activity (IC
 <sub>50</sub>) of this compound is similar to that of vitamin C (Jitsanong et al., 2011). Previously, Mandal et al. (2009) observed significant retinal neuroprotection in rats fed with diets supplemented with curcumin, which involved the inhibition of nuclear factor-κB activation and the down-regulation of cellular inflammatory genes. When tested on retina-derived cell lines (661W and ARPE-19), curcumin pre-treatment protected these cells from H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>-induced cell death by up-regulating cellular protective enzymes, such as HO-1, thioredoxin. Studies into curcumin’s efficacy have been limited mostly to animal studies. Moreover, the biomedical potential of curcumin is not easy to develop given its low solubility and oral bioavailability. Improving the pharmacological profile by reconstituting curcumin with non-curcuminoid components of turmeric has been found to substantially increase bioavailability (Antony et al., 2008). Curcumin is well tolerated and does not show any dose-limiting toxicity when administered at doses of up to 8 g/day for 3 months (Basnet and Skalko-Basnet, 2011).
</p>
