<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The diversity of techniques used makes it difficult to compare results from different groups of researchers. Several are the factors that influence the data found in published works related to this topic, namely, microbiological methods, techniques of EO extraction, plant part involved in the extraction, harvesting season, climatic and environmental conditions where the plants were cultivated, and others. Consequently, the differences observed between articles could not possibly reflect a real difference between EOs’ features. It has been found that there is no consensus about both the methodology for the evaluation of the antimicrobial activity of a natural product, and an acceptable value for the minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC). Deep discrepancies among researchers have been found when considering antibiotic-like concentrations or good antimicrobial potential, even when the EO activity consists in a weak inhibition. We consider that a comparison between the MIC values of EOs and commercial antibiotics is not applicable, because the former contain a mixture of compounds which can interact among them, whereas the latter are pure compounds. Aligiannis et al. [
 <xref rid="B78-molecules-23-00544" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>], for example, classified the antibacterial activity of plant extracts on the basis of MIC results, indicating as strong inhibition that corresponding to MIC up to 500 μg/mL, moderate inhibition that characterized by MIC between 600 μg/mL and 1500 μg/mL, and weak inhibition that observed with MIC above 1600 μg/mL. In contrast, Holetz et al. [
 <xref rid="B79-molecules-23-00544" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>] argued that MIC values lower than 0.1 mg/mL represent strong antimicrobial action, values between 0.1 mg/mL and 0.5 mg/mL indicate moderate antimicrobial activity, values between 0.5 and 1.0 mg/mL indicate weak action, while values above 1.0 mg/mL indicate inactive products. The analysis of the MIC values found in the studied EOs allows us to suggest that values less than or equal to 0.5 mg/mL represent strong activity, while those between 0.5 mg/mL and 1.0 mg/mL indicate moderate action. The values between 1.0 mg/mL and 2.0 mg/mL indicate weak action and those greater than 2.0 mg/mL should be considered as corresponding to lack of activity. This appreciation can be useful, since the previous work focused mainly on plant extracts and not on essential oils. 
 <xref rid="molecules-23-00544-t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref> presents studies on the antimicrobial activity of EOs from the Verbenaceae family against human pathogens, carried out in South America in the last two decades. It should be noted that the broth microdilution test is the most used method to determine the MIC. These data are detailed in the following paragraphs. 
</p>
