<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">In the current study, we employed GeNorm, NormFinder, BestKeeper, and RefFinder to rank the stability of candidate reference genes among diverse experimental groups and in total samples. Even though the stability rankings of GeNorm and NormFinder were not completely identical, two assessment tools consistently identified 
 <italic>ACT7</italic> as the most appropriate reference gene for hormone treatments and 
 <italic>β-TUB</italic> as the optimum reference gene in different tissue types, abiotic stresses and all tested samples (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Supplementary Table 3). The rankings generated by BestKeeper differ significantly from those provided by geNorm and NormFinder. In particular, the results of BestKeeper showed that 
 <italic>UBC</italic> was the most stable reference gene for hormone treatments, while 
 <italic>ACT7</italic>, the most stable reference gene recommended by geNorm and NormFinder, was only the fourth most stable reference gene by BestKeeper (Supplementary Table 4). We previously found that the results of GeNorm and NormFinder were mostly consistent, while the results of BestKeeper were quite different to those of GeNorm and NormFinder in 
 <italic>C. pilosula</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Recently, many studies have stated a preference for GeNorm and NormFinder for the evaluation of reference genes rather than BestKeeper to evaluate appropriate reference genes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. To evaluate the stability of these genes more reasonably, we utilized RefFinder to obtain the comprehensive ranking of these genes. As shown in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, the ranking of RefFinder is highly consistent with those from GeNorm and NormFinder. All three recommender softwares recommend that 
 <italic>β-TUB</italic> as the best reference gene for different tissue types, abiotic stresses and all tested samples, while 
 <italic>ACT7</italic> is recommended as the most stable gene for hormone treatments.
</p>
