<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0135">Bioactivity of plant extracts is the work of secondary metabolites produced for purposes of normal plant defenses; to deter, stun, poison or kill threatening species, but inadvertently inhibiting various physiological targets/processes required for growth, biosynthesis of macromolecules, metabolism, and virulence of microbial systems [
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. To characterize and identify the active compounds mediating activity against the tested organisms, we initially performed qualitative phytochemical screening in all extract solvent fractions (
 <xref rid="tbl6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>), and subsequent GC-MS analysis of the methanolic solvent extract fraction (
 <xref rid="tbl7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref> &amp; Figures 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). We qualitatively identified terpenoids, phenolics such as flavonoids and anthraquinones, and alkaloids in 
 <italic>A. pluriseta</italic> extracts, and thus speculated that they are the phytochemicals partly or wholly responsible of the antitubercular activity demonstrated by various extract fractions. Previous studies have also reported presence of terpenoids, alkaloid, flavonoids, anthraquinones and phenolic in 
 <italic>A. pluriseta</italic> aqueous extract [
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Terpenes were enriched in all fractions tested, and a broad range of terpenes identified in other studies have been associated with antitubercular activity, partly due to their lipophilicity that makes it easier for them to penetrate through MTB wall [
 <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Alkaloids, terpenoids, and flavonoids have been speculated to induce antitubercular activity by interfering with the MTB efflux pump, thus modulating in non-specific manner membrane proteins and receptors as well as inhibiting natural methods for MTB resistance development [
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>].
</p>
