<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The family Lamiaceae comprises approximately 224 genera and more than 5600 species distributed all over the world. One of these genera is 
 <italic class="italic">Lepechinia</italic> Willd., consisting of 43 species growing from Northern California, in Western USA, to Central Argentina, in South America [
 <xref rid="B1-pharmaceuticals-11-00033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-pharmaceuticals-11-00033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-pharmaceuticals-11-00033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-pharmaceuticals-11-00033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. The flora of Ecuador contains 21 genera of Lamiaceae, for a total number of 135 species, 33 of which are endemic. In particular, the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Lepechinia</italic> Willd. includes nine species, among which four are endemic to Ecuador [
 <xref rid="B2-pharmaceuticals-11-00033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-pharmaceuticals-11-00033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Lepechinia</italic> species are perennial herbs to shrubs, rarely gynodioecious or dioecious, often aromatic. Leaves are entire to toothed, often rugose; inflorescences are terminal and often axillary [
 <xref rid="B2-pharmaceuticals-11-00033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-pharmaceuticals-11-00033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Several 
 <italic class="italic">Lepechinia</italic> spp. are valued in the horticultural trade, and indigenous peoples of North and South America commonly use 
 <italic class="italic">Lepechinia</italic> plants for medicinal and antiseptic purposes. Plants of this genus are used in folk medicine for the treatment of uterine tumors, stomach ailments, diabetes mellitus control and diarrhea treatment. In particular, the leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">L. mutica</italic> are used to treat headache and nervous affections [
 <xref rid="B1-pharmaceuticals-11-00033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-pharmaceuticals-11-00033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-pharmaceuticals-11-00033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-pharmaceuticals-11-00033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>], whereas the 
 <italic class="italic">L. caulescens</italic> extract has been patented as a cosmetic constituent [
 <xref rid="B8-pharmaceuticals-11-00033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>].
</p>
