<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">When exposure to oil concentrations that killed 50% of the larvae (LC
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub>), the majority of eggs rafts from both garlic (73.1%) and asafoetida (55.8%) essential oil treatments did not hatch. In addition, larvae from 19 of the 23 egg rafts that hatched in asafoetida essential oil treatments and all the 14 egg rafts that hatched in garlic essential oil treatments died as first instars. Similar bioassays using allyl disulfide revealed its significant role towards inhibition of egg hatch: 96.2% of eggs exposed to this compound failed to hatch and larvae from the two egg rafts that hatched died as first instars. Diallyl trisulfide which was also a major component of garlic essential oil is also known to suppress egg hatch in some beetle species and may also have contributed to egg hatch inhibition by garlic essential oil (
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Huang et al. 2000</xref>). Because allyl disulfide (7.38%) and diallyl trisulfide (4.55%) were minor components of asafoetida essential oil, our results suggest that either only small amounts of allyl disulfide and diallyl trisulfide are required to inhibit egg hatch or that other components of asafoetida essential oil also contribute to egg hatch inhibition. Further studies are needed to determine the role of various components of asafoetida essential oil towards inhibition of egg hatch. The ovicidal properties of garlic essential oils have been demonstrated in diamondback moth 
 <italic class="italic">Plutella xylostella</italic> (L.) (
 <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sangha et al. 2017</xref>) and garlic extracts are also known to exhibit ovicidal effects against red spider mite, 
 <italic class="italic">Oligonychus coffeae</italic> (Nietner) (
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Roobakkumar et al. 2010</xref>) and mosquitoes (
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jarial 2001</xref>). In contrast, this is the first report of ovicidal effects of asafoetida essential oil against mosquitoes. We did not examine the mechanism(s) underlying the ovicidal properties of the two essential oils but previous studies suggest that garlic extracts inhibit egg hatch by interfering with the ability of mosquito embryos to break the egg shells (
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jarial 2001</xref>).
</p>
