<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>QS is a cell-to-cell communication used by many bacteria to coordinate common behaviors and regulate a diverse array of physiological activities through the sensing of cell-population densities. In this process, bacteria produce, release, and detect chemical signal molecules called ‘autoinducers’ (AI) that increase in concentration concomitantly with cell density [
 <xref rid="B32-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The reach of a minimal threshold stimulatory concentration leads to activation or induction of QS-dependent gene expression among a responding bacterial population. Depending on bacteria species, these processes may include symbiosis, virulence, competence, conjugation, antibiotic production, motility, sporulation, and/or biofilm formation [
 <xref rid="B35-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Basically, there are different types of QS systems based on the nature of AI and their detection mechanism. The best known and/or relevant systems are (i) the LuxI/R signaling systems, primarily exploited by different Gram-negative bacteria such as 
 <italic>Chromobacterium violaceum, Agrobacterium tumefasciens</italic>, and 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, based on 
 <italic>N</italic>-acyl homoserine lactones signal molecules (AHLs; also called autoinducer-1, AI-1) and known to promote the production of virulence factors (e.g., violacein, pyocyanin, elastases, and proteases), swarming/twitching motilities, biofilm formation, and other process such as transfer of tumor-inducing plasmid to host [
 <xref rid="B18-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]; (ii) the oligopeptide-two-component-type QS system, primarily exploited by Gram-positive bacteria such as 
 <italic>Bacillus cereus, Listeria monocytogenes, Streptococcus mutans, Enterococcus faecalis</italic>, and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, based on autoinducing peptides (AIP) as signal molecules and known to up-regulate the expression of several exoproteins genes (e.g., enterotoxins, listeriolysin O, α-, β-, and γ-hemolysins, as well as leucotoxins) and repress the transcription of particular genes encoding for cell wall-associated proteins (e.g., protein A, coagulase, and fibronectin binding protein) [
 <xref rid="B18-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]; (iii) the LuxS/AI-2 signaling system, based on (2R, 4S)-2-methyl-2,3,3,4-tetrahydroxytetrahydrofuran (Autoinducer-2, AI-2), exploited by 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> spp. and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> for interspecies communication, and reported to regulate the expression of over 400 genes associated to bacterial adhesion processes, motilities, and toxin production; (iv) the autoinducer-3/epinephrine/norepinephrine (AI-3/E/NE) signaling system based both on pyrazinones (AI-3), primarily exploited by 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> for interkingdom communications [
 <xref rid="B40-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], and on eukaryotic hormones epinephrine/norepinephrine that are reported to activate a virulence-associated type III secretion system (T3SS), causing characteristic histopathologic ‘attaching and effacing’ lesions on host cells (enterocytes), leading to loss of microvilli and intimate attachment of the bacterium to the host cell surface [
 <xref rid="B41-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]; and (v) the PhcBSR QS system, based on fatty acids (R)-methyl 3-hydroxymyristate (3-OH MAME) or (R)-methyl 3-hydroxypalmitate (3-OH PAME), employed by 
 <italic>Ralstonia solanacearum</italic> to regulate virulence factors, EPS, and endoglucanase production [
 <xref rid="B42-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].
</p>
