<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Somatic cells are not totipotent per se, and they need induction under appropriate conditions [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. During the induction phase, somatic cells acquire embryogenic competence and proliferate, while during the expression phase, embryogenic cells differentiate into somatic embryos [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. These two phases are thought to be mutually independent and influenced by different factors. Competent cells represent a transition from somatic to embryogenic state, which still requires exogenous stimuli, while the embryogenic cells have the ability to regenerate embryos without exogenous stimuli [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Inductive conditions, such as exogenously added PGRs and stress factors, lead to the dedifferentiation of plant cells and activation of the embryogenic pathway [
 <xref rid="B10-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. It is still unclear why and how differentiated plant cells become totipotent and acquire embryogenic potential and why this phenomenon occurs only in certain plant species, certain tissue types, or cells [
 <xref rid="B10-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Many genes are involved in the vegetative to embryogenic transition. These include phytohormone-responsive genes, such as auxin-related and ABA-inducible genes, genes involved in the cell cycle control, genes involved in growth and remodeling of the cell wall, as well as an array of transcription factors. The involvement of 
 <italic>LEC</italic> (leafy cotyledon), 
 <italic>BBM</italic> (baby boom), 
 <italic>WUS</italic> (wuschel), 
 <italic>CLV</italic> (clavata), 
 <italic>STM</italic> (shoot meristemless), 
 <italic>SHR</italic> (short root), 
 <italic>ABI3</italic> (abscisic acid-insensitive), 
 <italic>FUS3</italic> (fusca) and other transcription factorshave been confirmed in SE regulation [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Somatic Embryogenesis Receptor-Like Kinases (SERKs) are well-known SE-specific signaling components [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Although significant progress in identifying factors involved in induction, perception, and signal transduction during SE has been made, the results of these numerous studies are still fragmentary and insufficient to explain the events occurring during SE at the molecular level.
</p>
