<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par95">
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par96">
    <italic>Lipase assay buffer I</italic> (for diluting test samples and preparing the positive control orlistat, and the substrate) consisted of 13 mM Tris-HCl, 75 mM NaCl, 1.3 mM CaCl
    <sub>2</sub> (pH 8.0) and 2% DMSO.
   </p>
   <p id="Par97">Comments: DMSO was used to aid with the solubility of the extracts in the buffer [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>, 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. Preliminary testing confirmed that 2% DMSO (final concentration of 0.001% DMSO) had no significant effect on lipase activity in this assay.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par98">
    <italic>Lipase assay buffer II</italic> (for preparing porcine pancreatic lipase enzyme) consisted of 13 mM Tris-HCl, 75 mM NaCl and 1.3 mM CaCl
    <sub>2</sub> (pH 8.0).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par99">
    <italic>Test samples</italic> (20 mg herbal extract granules) were dissolved in 4 mL distilled water containing 2% DMSO to prepare stock solutions of 5 mg/mL and diluted in lipase assay buffer I to 0.4 mg/mL (final concentration of 0.1 mg/mL). Samples were freshly prepared before experiments and used immediately.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par100">
    <italic>Positive control orlistat</italic> (25 mg) was dissolved in lipase assay buffer I (5 mL) to obtain a 5 mg/mL stock solution and diluted in lipase assay buffer II to 0.4 mg/mL (final concentration of 0.1 mg/mL) immediately before experiments.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par101">
    <italic>Negative control</italic> (vehicle) was the lipase assay buffer I.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par102">
    <italic>Porcine pancreatic lipase enzyme</italic> powder was dissolved in lipase assay buffer II to obtain a stock solution 3.5 × 10
    <sup>4</sup> U/mL. Subsequently, the enzyme solution was serially diluted to obtain a working solution of 50 U/mL.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par103">
    <italic>4-MUO substrate solution</italic> was prepared by dissolving in lipase assay buffer I to obtain a working substrate solution of 0.1 mM.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
