<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Upon exposure to PUFAs (DHA and AA), α-syn acquires an α-helical secondary structure with a rapid equilibrium between its free and the lipid-bound form [
 <xref rid="B114-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">117</xref>]. This conformational transition is a function of PUFA concentration and follows a two-state model [
 <xref rid="B114-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>]. The study of this interaction is very challenging, since the protein and FAs mutually and dynamically affect their physical properties. It has been shown that for this interaction, a prerequisite is the presence of at least one double bond in the fatty acid. Palmitic and arachidic acids, for example, do not induce the formation of α-helical structure in α-syn, while oleic acid (OA), a MUFA, does [
 <xref rid="B114-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">117</xref>]. Two factors modulate the protein/PUFA interaction in vitro: (i) the self-assembly/aggregation state of the FA, regulated in turn by its critical aggregative concentration (CAC) in solution; and (ii) the molecular ratio between the FA and the protein. PUFAs exhibit a high tendency to self-assemble, in vitro, being composed of amphiphilic chains. This process strongly depends on PUFAs’ concentration, as well as on the media ionic strength, temperature and pH [
 <xref rid="B116-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">120</xref>]. More specifically, the PUFAs are present as a mixture of a neutral form and a negatively-charged form as a function of pH [
 <xref rid="B121-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">121</xref>]. In diluted solution and above a critical concentration, PUFAs can dynamically form micelles, vesicles and oil droplets as a function of the ratio between the ionized and non-ionized species (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-23-01531-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>a). Micelles are the dominant aggregation species at pH &gt; 9; oil droplets form above pH 8; whereas PUFAs preferentially form vesicles in the pH range of 8–9 [
 <xref rid="B119-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">119</xref>]. These lipid aggregates show dynamic nature, wide size variability and different surface characteristics, as seen by transmission electron (TEM) and cryo-transmission electronic microscopy (cryo-TEM) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-23-01531-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>b), strongly affecting the modality of interaction with proteins [
 <xref rid="B114-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B122-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">122</xref>,
 <xref rid="B123-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">123</xref>].
</p>
