<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A debated question is which type of interaction occurs between α-syn and FAs at the molecular level. The presence of the imperfect repeats at the α-syn N-terminus and some similarity with the amino acid sequences of fatty acid binding proteins (FABPs) have previously suggested that α-syn might be a member of the intracellular FABP family or might work as an FA transporter [
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B125-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">125</xref>]. Although α-syn is able to bind FA in a manner reminiscent of FABPs, by using a combined approach of NMR and TEM, Lücke et al. [
 <xref rid="B125-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">125</xref>] concluded that the protein does not likely act as an intracellular fatty acid carrier, and the ability to bind to negatively-charged membranes is one of its intrinsic, possibly physiological, properties [
 <xref rid="B116-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>]. Limited proteolysis experiments were shown to be a useful tool to map the α-syn/DHA complex at the molecular level, demonstrating that the N-terminal region is engaged in the presence of DHA [
 <xref rid="B114-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>]. At a DHA/protein molar ratio of 50, in which all α-syn molecules are bound to the FA, α-syn region 89–102 resulted in being flexible and proteases sensitive. The produced N-terminal 1–89 and then 1–72 fragments, resistant to further proteolysis, accumulated in the reaction mixture and retained α-helical structure, suggesting that these species derive from the digestion of the protein bound to DHA and are very important for the interaction (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-23-01531-f004" class="xref">Figure 4</xref>). We also analyzed the propensity of α-syn isolated fragments to interact with DHA, confirming that the interaction with the fatty acid is mediated by the N-terminal portion of α-syn [
 <xref rid="B126-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">126</xref>]. It has been also demonstrated that the α-syn N-terminal region from residues 2–60 is responsible and essential for the binding to PUFAs and for the FA-induced oligomerization of the protein [
 <xref rid="B127-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">127</xref>]. We showed that the peptide corresponding to the sequence 1–52 is able to trigger the binding of α-syn to DHA oil droplets and to exhibit the same ability of the full length protein to change the fatty acid aggregative properties [
 <xref rid="B126-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">126</xref>]. To reinforce these considerations, it is important to underline the general role of the α-syn N-terminus for its membrane-assisted binding and folding [
 <xref rid="B109-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">109</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">128</xref>]. It has been suggested that the short sequence comprising residues 1–25 is responsible for the nucleation of the cooperative coil/helix transition of the adjacent large protein domains in the presence of lipid [
 <xref rid="B109-molecules-23-01531" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">109</xref>].
</p>
