<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. EO Content and Chemical Composition</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The EOs from the aerial parts of
  <span class="italic"> M. suaveolens</span> subsp.
  <span class="italic"> timija</span> were found to be a yellow liquid with yields ranging from 0.82 ± 0.12% to 0.90 ± 0.08% (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab1" href="#tab1">Table 1</a>). These results demonstrated that cultivation of this species with N, P, and K fertilizer or VAM inoculation had no significant effect on the EO production. These findings are in line with what has been reported for other aromatic and medicinal species exposed to these treatments, such as
  <span class="italic"> Thymus maroccanus</span> and
  <span class="italic"> T. leptobotrys</span> [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>],
  <span class="italic"> Rosmarinus officinalis</span> [
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>], and
  <span class="italic"> Lippia citriodora</span> [
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemical analyses data of the volatile constituents of the different mint timija EOs (percentage content of each compound, elution order, retention index, and structural subclass) are summarized in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab1" href="#tab1">Table 1</a>. In total, 27 components were identified, which represented more than 99.9% of the total oils. Oxygenated monoterpenes (87.9–93.2%) constituted the principal compound class, followed by monoterpene hydrocarbons and sesquiterpene hydrocarbons. The predominant constituents were menthone (40.7–49.3%), followed by pulegone (31.3–36.5%), isomenthone (2.5–4.3%), 1,8-cineole (2.1–3.4%), borneol (2.3–2.7%), and
  <span class="italic"> E</span>-caryophyllene (1.6–1.9%). The results indicate that N, P, and K fertilization and VAM inoculation affected the chemical composition of mint timija EOs, especially the content of their major compounds menthone and pulegone. In fact, compared with the oil extracted from control plants, applying both treatments produced an increase in menthone content (11.1% for N, P, and K fertilization, and 21.1% for VAM inoculation), and a reduction in pulegone (14.2% for N, P, and K fertilizer, and 11.0% for VAM inoculation).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The variation in the content of the major compounds of the EOs in response to the application of mineral and/or biological treatments observed in this study is in agreement with what has been previously reported by many authors [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>, 
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>, 
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>–
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>]. In fact, it has been found that the addition of these treatments improved the physical and chemical properties of the soil through increases in the contents of mineral elements and organic matter and enhanced rhizosphere activity [
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>]. Enhancement of edaphic conditions is likely to lead to positive effects on plant growth, metabolic reactions, and enzyme activities, such as those of the terpenes biosynthesis pathways [
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>, 
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>]. In addition, many studies have shown that the application of mineral fertilizers and biological amendments plays a beneficial role in the tolerance of cultivated plants against many environmental stresses [
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>, 
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>–
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>]. It has been reported that cultivation of
  <span class="italic"> M. suaveolens</span> subsp.
  <span class="italic"> timija</span> in harsh environmental conditions such as an arid climate, low soil nutrient status, and salt stress produces an increase in pulegone content and consequent decrease in menthone content, in line with their known inverse accumulation trends [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>]. Based on the results of the present study, it seems that the use of mineral fertilizer and VAM inoculation during cultivation of mint timija minimizes the effect of the environmental stress. This may indeed explain the observed increase in menthone content and decrease in pulegone.
 </p>
</sec>
