<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6. Insecticidal Activity </div>
 <sec id="sec2.6.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.1. Insect Cultures</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We followed the methods of Kasrati et al. [
   <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>]. Colonies of the red flour beetle,
   <span class="italic"> Tribolium confusum</span> (du Val) (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae), were maintained in the laboratory without exposure to any insecticide. They were reared in glass containers (16 cm diameter × 22 cm height) covered by a fine mesh cloth for ventilation. Each container contained a mixture of wheat flour, wheat germ, and yeast extract (13 : 6 : 1 w/w/w). The cultures were maintained in a growth chamber at 26 ± 1°C, with a relative humidity (RH) of 70–85% and 16 : 8 h light : dark photoperiod. Only young adults (7–14 days old) were used for the tests. All experimental procedures were conducted under environmental conditions identical to those of the cultures. In all bioassays, insects where considered dead when no leg or antennal movements were observed. The bioassays were designed to assess median lethal concentrations (LC
   <sub>50</sub> and LC
   <sub>90</sub> values) (doses that killed 50% and 90% of the exposed insects, resp.).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.6.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.2. Contact Toxicity Bioassay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The contact insecticidal activity of EOs obtained from mint timija against
   <span class="italic"> T. confusum</span> adults was determined by assessing the toxicity using filter paper discs (Whatman number 1, 9 cm diameter) as described by Kasrati et al. [
   <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>]. Oils were dissolved in acetone at concentrations of 0.09, 0.16, 0.24, and 0.31 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>L/cm
   <span class="sup">2</span>. Several preliminary tests were conducted to select the doses to be used for each EO. One mL of each solution was dispensed on the surface of the filter paper that was then placed in a glass Petri dish. Control filter papers were treated with acetone only. After 10 min, once the solvent had been evaporated, 10 unsexed adults were deposited into each dish. Each EO and control treatment was replicated three times, repeating each assay twice. Mortality was recorded after 24 hours.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.6.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.3. Fumigant Toxicity Bioassay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fumigant toxicity of mint timija EOs was determined using the method described by Kasrati el al. [
   <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>]. 2 cm diameter filter papers (Whatman number 1) were impregnated with the different oil doses 1, 2, 3, and 4 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>L. The impregnated filter papers were then attached to the screw caps of 60 mL Plexiglas bottles to give calculated fumigant concentrations of, respectively, 16.66, 33.33, 50, and 66.66 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>L/L air. Caps were screwed tightly on the vials, each of which contained 10 unsexed adults. Each EO and control treatment was replicated three times, repeating each assay twice. Mortality was recorded after 24 h.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
