<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Experimental Site</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiment was carried out at the Faculty of Science Semlalia in Marrakech (31°37′N–08°02′W, 470 m above sea level). The experimental area is characterized by an arid climate with an average temperature in the warmest month of 38.3°C and of 4.5°C in the coldest one and a mean rainfall of 242 mm/year. The soil characteristics were as follows: sand (37.3%), silt (24.2%), clay (38.5%), pH (8.06), electrical conductivity (0.28 mS/cm), organic matter (2.9%), total N (0.65%), P (7.96 mg/100 g), K (40.58 mg/100 g), and Ca (18.22%).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Crop Experimental Design</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In February 2012, a total of 400 stem cuttings of
   <span class="italic"> M. suaveolens</span> subsp.
   <span class="italic"> timija</span> (vegetative stage) were randomly sampled from the natural population located in the Marrakech region, Ourika valley (31°23′N–7°42′W; altitude: 900 m). The species identification was done by one of the authors (A. Abbad) and a voucher specimen (MST05) was deposited at the Laboratory of Biotechnology, Protection and Valorization of Plant Resources, Faculty of Science Semlalia, Marrakech, Morocco. The prepared cuttings (length 20 cm) were immediately transplanted to the main field in a randomized complete block design. Twenty-five cuttings were transplanted in each block (2 m × 2 m) with plant to plant and row to row spacing of 40 cm. One meter alley was maintained between treatments to eliminate any influence of lateral water movement. At the time of transplantation, the treatments were applied. Each treatment was replicated three times. Two treatments consisting of application of a complete mineral fertilizer using the N, P, and K fertilizer (60 kg/ha of N, P
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>5</sub>, and K2O with 13 : 40 : 13 formulation) [
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>] and inoculation with 50 g/plant of
   <span class="italic"> Glomus </span>sp. soil were conducted. Culture of
   <span class="italic"> Glomus </span>sp. was kindly provided by Sfairi (high commissariat for water and forests and desertification in Morocco). Blocks containing the crop without any treatment were taken as control. For the first month (establishment phase), the crop was watered on alternate days. Thereafter, the irrigation was carried out as needed, depending on the rainfall. The plants were harvested at the beginning of flowering stage, 10 weeks after application of treatments. The mycorrhizal colonization of the randomized mint timija plants was determined by staining of colonized roots with trypan blue according to the method of Phillips and Hayman [
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. EO Extraction</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the EO extraction, we followed the methods described by Kasrati et al. [
   <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>]. The collected material was air-dried at room temperature (≈25°C) in the shade and subjected to hydrodistillation, using a Clevenger-type apparatus for 3 h until total recovery of oil. The extraction was performed on three different samples and the obtained oils were dried with anhydrous sodium sulphate, weighed, and stored at 4°C until use.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Gas Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry (GC/MS) Analyses of EOs</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The GC/MS analysis of EOs was performed in an Agilent GC-MSD system (Agilent Technologies 6890/5973) with helium (high purity) as the carrier gas at a constant linear velocity of 37 cm/s. The transfer, source, and quadrupole temperatures were 280°C, 230°C, and 150°C, respectively, operating at 70 eV ionisation energy and scanning the 
   <span class="italic">m</span>/
   <span class="italic">z</span> range 41–450. The column used was an Agilent DB5 ms capillary column (30.0 m × 0.25 mm ID × 0.25 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>m film thickness; model number: 122-5532) programmed from 60°C to 246°C at 3°C/min. EO samples (60 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>L) were diluted with acetone (2 mL). The injection volume was 1.0 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>L, the split ratio was 1 : 50, and the injector temperature was 260°C. Identification of the individual components was based on (i) comparison with the mass spectra of authentic reference compounds where possible and with reference to WILEY275, NBS75 K, and Adams terpene library [
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>] and (ii) comparison of their retention indices (RI) on a DB5 (apolar, 5% phenyl polysilphenylene-siloxane), calculated relative to the retention times of a series of C-9 to C-24
   <span class="italic"> n</span>-alkanes, with linear interpolation, with those of authentic compounds or literature data. For semiquantitative purposes, the normalized peak area of each compound was used without any correction factors to establish abundances.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Antioxidant Activity</div>
  <sec id="sec2.5.1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.1. DPPH Free Radical-Scavenging Activity</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ability of EOs to scavenge the 2,2′-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical was measured using the method described by Sahin et al. [
    <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>]. The sample concentration providing 50% inhibition (IC
    <sub>50</sub>) was calculated by plotting the inhibition percentages against the concentrations of the sample.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2.5.2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.2. Reducing Power Determination</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ferric reducing capacity of EOs was determined by using the potassium ferricyanide-ferric chloride method [
    <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>]. The sample concentration providing 0.5 of absorbance (IC
    <sub>50</sub>) was calculated by plotting absorbance at 700 nm against the corresponding sample concentration.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2.5.3" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.3. 
    <span class="italic">β</span>-Carotene/Linoleic Acid Bleaching Assay
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antioxidant activity of the EOs was evaluated by the 
    <span class="italic">β</span>-carotene/linoleic model system using the method of Miraliakbari and Shahidi [
    <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>]. The oil concentration providing 50% inhibition (IC
    <sub>50</sub>) was obtained plotting inhibition percentage versus oil solutions concentrations.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6. Insecticidal Activity </div>
  <sec id="sec2.6.1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.1. Insect Cultures</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We followed the methods of Kasrati et al. [
    <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>]. Colonies of the red flour beetle,
    <span class="italic"> Tribolium confusum</span> (du Val) (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae), were maintained in the laboratory without exposure to any insecticide. They were reared in glass containers (16 cm diameter × 22 cm height) covered by a fine mesh cloth for ventilation. Each container contained a mixture of wheat flour, wheat germ, and yeast extract (13 : 6 : 1 w/w/w). The cultures were maintained in a growth chamber at 26 ± 1°C, with a relative humidity (RH) of 70–85% and 16 : 8 h light : dark photoperiod. Only young adults (7–14 days old) were used for the tests. All experimental procedures were conducted under environmental conditions identical to those of the cultures. In all bioassays, insects where considered dead when no leg or antennal movements were observed. The bioassays were designed to assess median lethal concentrations (LC
    <sub>50</sub> and LC
    <sub>90</sub> values) (doses that killed 50% and 90% of the exposed insects, resp.).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2.6.2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.2. Contact Toxicity Bioassay</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The contact insecticidal activity of EOs obtained from mint timija against
    <span class="italic"> T. confusum</span> adults was determined by assessing the toxicity using filter paper discs (Whatman number 1, 9 cm diameter) as described by Kasrati et al. [
    <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>]. Oils were dissolved in acetone at concentrations of 0.09, 0.16, 0.24, and 0.31 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>L/cm
    <span class="sup">2</span>. Several preliminary tests were conducted to select the doses to be used for each EO. One mL of each solution was dispensed on the surface of the filter paper that was then placed in a glass Petri dish. Control filter papers were treated with acetone only. After 10 min, once the solvent had been evaporated, 10 unsexed adults were deposited into each dish. Each EO and control treatment was replicated three times, repeating each assay twice. Mortality was recorded after 24 hours.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2.6.3" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.3. Fumigant Toxicity Bioassay</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fumigant toxicity of mint timija EOs was determined using the method described by Kasrati el al. [
    <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>]. 2 cm diameter filter papers (Whatman number 1) were impregnated with the different oil doses 1, 2, 3, and 4 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>L. The impregnated filter papers were then attached to the screw caps of 60 mL Plexiglas bottles to give calculated fumigant concentrations of, respectively, 16.66, 33.33, 50, and 66.66 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>L/L air. Caps were screwed tightly on the vials, each of which contained 10 unsexed adults. Each EO and control treatment was replicated three times, repeating each assay twice. Mortality was recorded after 24 h.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7. Data Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of antioxidant activity of EOs were expressed as the mean of three replications ± standard deviation (±SD). Variance analysis of the data (one-way ANOVA) was performed using SPSS 12.0 software and means were separated according to Student–Newman-Keuls test at 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05. Probit analysis [
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>] was conducted on the corrected mortality data [
   <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>] to estimate lethal concentrations (LC
   <sub>50</sub> and LC
   <sub>90</sub>) with their 95% confidence intervals by SPSS 12.0 Statistical Software. LC values were considered significantly different when their respective 95% confidence intervals did not overlap.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
