<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Wang et al. [
 <xref rid="B94-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>] further evaluated the antidiabetic activity of genistein by observing insulin sensitivity in mice. Results of this study showed that genistein weakened glucose tolerance and reduced insulin sensitivity by inhibiting the insulin-induced phosphorylation of insulin receptor substrate-1 (IRS1) at tyrosine residues, leading to the inhibition of insulin-mediated GLUT4 translocation in adipocytes. Mac-CM, an inflammatory stimulus, induced glucose intolerance accompanied by impaired insulin sensitivity; genistein reversed these changes by restoring the disturbed IRS1 function, leading to an improvement in GLUT4 translocation. In addition, genistein increased AMPK activity under both normal and inflammatory conditions; this was shown to contribute to the anti-inflammatory effect of genistein, which led to an improvement in insulin signaling and the amelioration of insulin resistance. Hence, it was concluded that genistein showed the opposite effects on insulin sensitivity under normal and inflammatory conditions in adipose tissue and this action was derived from its negative or positive regulation of IRS1 function. Its upregulation of AMPK activity contributes to the inhibition of inflammation implicated in insulin resistance. This finding was found to be actually correlated with a study that was done earlier using non-diabetic mice in which genistein boosted insulin level and altered hepatic gluconeogenic and lipogenic enzyme activities [
 <xref rid="B95-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Liu et al. [
 <xref rid="B80-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] explained that genistein stimulates insulin secretion in a dose of 0.01–5 μM, thereby stimulates intracellular cAMP accumulation, which consequently activates protein kinase A (PKA) via protein tyrosine kinase (PTK) independent and estrogen receptor independent. Furthermore, genistein was also found to promote the insulin signaling pathway in the cerebral cortex of aged female rats [
 <xref rid="B96-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>].
</p>
