<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The liver is the main metabolic organ of the human body, and many factors, such as chemical drugs, pathogenic microorganisms, alcohol, and so on, can induce liver injury and cause liver cirrhosis, liver fibrosis, liver cancer, and other diseases (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Xin and Qing, 2018</xref>). 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> ethanol extract and total flavonoid extract have excellent hepatoprotective activity (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2019a</xref>). The ethanol extract of 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> has a certain protective effect on acute immune liver injury induced by ConA in mice, and can effectively reduce the liver injury caused by concomitant inflammation. The mechanism may be related to the regulation of Kupffer cell function and reducing the synthesis and release of inflammatory mediator TNF- α (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Wang, 2009</xref>). Total flavonoid extract of 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> can reduce the activities of ALT, AST, TBA, TBIL, and LDH in serum, increase the activities of SOD and GSH in liver, reduce the content of lipid peroxide MDA, and it is suggested that the total flavonoids of 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> can protect hepatocytes by inhibiting oxidative free radicals and improving the ability of antioxidation, and inhibit the lipid peroxidation induced by α-naphthalene isothiocyanate (ANIT) by reducing the content of lipid peroxidation product MDA in liver tissue (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2018</xref>). In the study of the protective effect of 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> on drug-induced liver injury induced by isoniazid and rifampicin in mice, it was found that under the intervention of total flavonoids of 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic>, the levels of TNF- α, IL-1β, and IL-6 in liver tissue of mice decreased, and the expression of Fas was significantly decreased by Western blotting assay, which had significant anti-drug-induced liver injury. The mechanism may be related to blocking Fas-mediated apoptosis pathway and inhibiting inflammatory response (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Xi et al., 2017</xref>). The study of 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al. (2019)</xref> found that the extract of total flavonoids of 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> could reduce the content of Hsp90, TNF- α, and IL-6 in the cells of mice with liver injury induced by carbon tetrachloride, increase the number of integrin β1, 5’- nucleotidase and positive antigen KI-67 cells in spleen, and reduce the pathological injury of liver; the mechanism may be through the inhibition of inflammatory stress reaction and apoptosis, inactivate Hsp90 in hepatocytes, and improve spleen immunity to protect liver. Total flavonoids of 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> also have protective effects on acute alcoholic liver injury. It can improve antioxidation by scavenging lipid peroxides, reduce the content of inflammatory factors IL-4, IL-6, and TNF- α, and inhibit liver inflammation, while improving the immune capacity of the damaged body (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2016</xref>). In addition, the ethanol extract of 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> not only alleviated the liver injury induced by carbon tetrachloride but also improved the structural damage of cardiomyocytes and glomeruli (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2019b</xref>).
</p>
