<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Parallel near infrared light illuminated the entire sample cell and the transmitted light was detected by sensors arranged linearly across the sample from top to bottom. Transmission was converted into extinction by log I/I0 and particle concentration could be calculated. The progression of the transmission profiles contained the complete information on the kinetics of any concentration changes due to creaming, sedimentation, flocculation, coalescence or phase separation [
 <xref rid="B26-pharmaceutics-11-00231" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. In addition to measuring stability directly and making shelf life prediction, a discrimination between flocculated and nonflocculated dispersions could be performed and particle size distributions could be measured using the highest industry norms and regulations (ISO 13318-2). The analysis was performed as follows: the fresh samples, without prior dilution, were placed in rectangular test-tubes (optical path of 10 mm) and exposed, at 25 °C, to different relative centrifugal forces (RCF): 500 rpm (300 × 30 profiles/s); 2000 rpm (400 × 30 profiles/s); 3000 (350 × 30 profiles/s); 4000 rpm (300 × 30 profiles/s). Such experiment allowed differentiating between various instability mechanisms, at an accelerated rate, in drastically shortened time, and extrapolated results were used to estimate dispersion shelf-life in minutes instead of months. Since instability phenomena, such as creaming or sedimentation, depend on the specificity gravities of the continuous and dispersed phases, which affect preferential particles migration upward or downward, they can be described by Stoke’s law, which allows determining the predictable theoretical value of the instability phenomenon velocity [
 <xref rid="B27-pharmaceutics-11-00231" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. For this reason, we compared the obtained results with the theoretical model based on Stoke’s law (Equation (2)):
 <disp-formula class="disp-formula">Vs = 
  <italic class="italic">g</italic> (
  <italic class="italic">ρp</italic> − 
  <italic class="italic">ρ</italic>) 
  <italic class="italic">dp</italic>
  <sup class="sup">2</sup>/18 
  <italic class="italic">η</italic>,
  <label class="label">(2)</label>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <italic class="italic">g</italic> is the gravitational acceleration constant, 
 <italic class="italic">ρp</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">ρ</italic> are respectively the densities of the particle and fluid, 
 <italic class="italic">dp</italic> is the particle size and 
 <italic class="italic">η</italic> is the fluid viscosity. As previously reported [
 <xref rid="B27-pharmaceutics-11-00231" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>], the closeness of the measured values of sedimentation/creaming velocities at different RCF to the predictable values based on Stoke’s law, can be exploited to describe the instability phenomena by Stoke’s law. Thus, the obtained data can be used to extrapolate the sedimentation velocity at regular gravity (1 RCF).
</p>
