<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Stereoselective fluorination is an emerging strategy for controlling the conformations of organic molecules. The highly polarized C–F bond tends to align in predictable ways with adjacent functional groups, due to a combination of hyperconjugative and/or dipolar interactions [
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. This knowledge led us to propose the hypothetical analog 
 <bold>2</bold> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) as a potential mimic of 
 <bold>1</bold>. The analog 
 <bold>2</bold> contains a saturated alkyl chain with two vicinal C–F bonds in the α/β positions relative to the amide moiety. The presence of a vicinal difluoride moiety within an alkyl chain is known to favour rotamers in which the C–F bonds align 
 <italic>gauche</italic> (I and II, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Separately, the presence of fluorine on the α-carbon of a tertiary amide is known to restrict the C
 <sub>α</sub>–C(O) bond to a small set of low-energy rotamers (III–V, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Intriguingly, studies of simple molecules containing either F–C–C–F or F–C–C=O motifs have shown that the rotamer populations can change, depending on the polarity of the solvent [
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The rotamers I and IV (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>, boxed) would appear to provide the closest structural match with compound 
 <bold>1</bold>, but in a highly polar medium the more polar rotamers II and V might predominate. Of course, the contiguous positioning of the F–C–C–F and F–C–C=O moieties within the same molecule (
 <bold>2</bold>) means that these moieties would not function independently, but rather would likely influence one another, adding another layer of complexity. Finally, it is interesting to consider whether the microenvironment of a protein binding site could also change the relative energies of the various F–C–C–F and F–C–C=O rotamers, offering the possibility that analog 
 <bold>2</bold> might be an effective conformational mimic of 
 <bold>1</bold> in some environments but not in others.
</p>
