<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Grains of rice treated with the geraniol and citral were respectively collected 0, 2, 4, 6, and 8 days after inoculation. Then, these grains were ground into powder and passed through 80 mesh sieves for the following measurements. Five grams of rice powder was dissolved at the rate 1:10 (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) in distilled water to record pH by precision digital pH meter (PB-10, Sartorius Stedim Biotech, Goettingen, Germany). Fatty acid contents of the grains were assessed by referring to standard methods [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>], and test results were expressed as sodium hydroxide equivalents. The MDA was measured using a published method [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>] with some slight modifications. Briefly, 1 g of ground sample was extracted with 4 mL 10% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) trichloroacetic acid (TCA), and then the sample extract was centrifuged at 6000 g at 4 °C for 10 min. The supernatant was added to 4 mL thiobarbituric acid (TBA). The mixture was heated in a boiled water bath for 15 min and was cooled with running water. The supernatant was collected by centrifugation at 1000 g for 10 min and was measured at 532 nm of absorbance by using a microplate multimode spectrophotometer (SpectraMax M5, Molecular Devices, San Francisco, CA, USA). The MDA content was calculated and normalized to micromole per gram (μmol/g). For the detection of colony number, 5 g of sample was aseptically transferred to an autoclaved Erlenmeyer flask containing 45 mL of sterile distilled water and homogenized in a Stomacher blender (Ultra-Turrax T25, IKA Laboratory Technology, Staufen, Germany) for 5 min. Afterwards, the homogenate was diluted serially 10-fold in sterile distilled water and a 200 μL aliquot of diluent was mixed with 15 mL of 40 °C PCA medium on a sterilized Petri dish. After the liquid medium of the dish had solidified, the plates were incubated at 28 ± 2 °C for 36–48 h to observe and count visible microbial colonies.
</p>
