<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Besides tomography another convenient technology is gamma densitometry. Gamma densitometry uses a radioactive source to obtain measurements of the multi-phase flow. Gamma is preferred because of its ability to measure spacial distribution based on the atomic number and density of a material [
 <xref rid="B111-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>,
 <xref rid="B113-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>]. When gamma-rays are radiated from the source to the detector, the ray will attenuate depending on the absorption of radiation of the flow within the pipe [
 <xref rid="B115-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>]. Depending on the detected gamma quanta at the detector, the sensor is able to measure even small changes in the density differences of the fluid, and can hereby obtain accurate measurements of the fraction of each phases [
 <xref rid="B116-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>]. To measure both the phase volume fraction and velocities, and not only the average fluid density, the gamma densitometer is often installed together with an equipment such as e.g., a venturi meter or an orifice plate. In [
 <xref rid="B117-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">117</xref>] researchers presents a single clamp-on gamma densitometer unit, which is able to determine both phase volume fractions and velocities to predict the individual phase flow rates of vertically upward multi-phase flows. The method yield promising improvements on the accuracy, but still needs more investigation as the densitometer is flow dependent. Gamma densitometry has also been tested and evaluated in [
 <xref rid="B118-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">120</xref>]. A disadvantage with gamma-rays is the salinity content in the water. Saltwater has a higher attenuation coefficient than freshwater, which will cause errors in the measurements if the salinity content changes [
 <xref rid="B98-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">98</xref>]. To avoid these errors additional equipment is needed. A single-beam gamma densitometer with an accuracy of 0.97% (phase fraction measurements) is presented in [
 <xref rid="B121-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">121</xref>]. The applied gamma source is Am-241, with radiation energy of 59.5 keV. The accuracy of the desitometer is increased by increasing the measuring time and the location of the radioactive source with respect to the pipe. With increased measuring time and the radioactive source at the center of the pipe, an accuracy of the phase fraction measurements on 0.53% can be achieved. Another method for detecting the flow regime and void fraction by the use of a gamma source is presented in [
 <xref rid="B122-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">122</xref>,
 <xref rid="B123-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">123</xref>]. The method is based on dual modality densitometry using artificial neural network (ANN) and presents error less than 1% between estimated and simulated values.
</p>
