<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Baicalin belongs to Class IV of the Biopharmaceutical Classification System (BCS) due to the extremely low water solubility (0.054 mg/mL) and lipophilicity (P
 <sub class="sub">app</sub> = 0.037 × 10
 <sup class="sup">−6</sup> cm/s, logP = 1.29) [
 <xref rid="B5-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. It is a weak acidic compound, with pKa values of 7.6 and 10.1 [
 <xref rid="B6-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. It can be seen from the chemical structure that both the glucuronide and flavone parts form intramolecular H-bonds, which can be responsible for the extremely poor water solubility and high melting point [
 <xref rid="B7-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. The stability of baicalin was evaluated in buffered aqueous solutions at different pHs (2.0, 3.0, 4.5, 6.8, 7.4, and 9.0) and temperatures (4, 25, and 40 °C). An acidic environment and low temperature were protective factors for the long term stability of this compound [
 <xref rid="B8-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. The absolute bioavailability of baicalin was 2.2 ± 0.2% after intravenous and oral administration to intact rats. It undergoes extensive intestinal glucuronidation and the fraction of baicalin and its conjugated metabolites excreted in urine appear to be negligible compared with the biliary excretion [
 <xref rid="B9-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Different ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporters were identified, which interfere in the enterohepatic recirculation of baicalin [
 <xref rid="B10-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Various formulations were developed to counterbalance the low oral bioavailability of the drug. Solid dispersions, cyclodextrins, nanoemulsions, liposomes, and PEGylated lipid nanoparticles have already been investigated [
 <xref rid="B11-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. A baicalin-loaded nanohydrogel formulation showed promising performances in the topical treatment of skin wounds [
 <xref rid="B12-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. 
</p>
