<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">SEDDS can form colloidal micro/nanoemulsions (r &lt; 100 nm) after dilution in the gastrointestinal tract (GIT) [
 <xref rid="B16-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. It is important to accurately specify the kind of colloidal dispersion used in a study, because this influences the physicochemical and functional properties. There are a lot of similarities between micro- and nanoemulsions (e.g., composition, fabrication, structure), but some differences can help distinguish between them [
 <xref rid="B17-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. The most significant difference between nanoemulsions and microemulsions is in terms of their thermodynamic stabilities. From a thermodynamic point of view, nanoemulsions are thermodynamically unstable, whereas microemulsions are thermodynamically stable systems [
 <xref rid="B18-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. There are numerous physicochemical phenomena which can lead to the breakdown of a nanoemulsion (e.g., creaming, flocculation, Ostwald ripening) [
 <xref rid="B19-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. By incorporating substances known as stabilizers, such as surfactants, texture modifiers, weighting agents, or ripening retarders, the long-term stability of nanoemulsions can be enhanced [
 <xref rid="B20-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Although the physicochemical characterization of SEDDS and nanodroplets are well-known considering particle size distribution, zeta-potential, polydispersity index (PDI), turbidity, dilution robustness, and drug release, atomic force microscopy (AFM) had not yet been used for the morphological imaging of drug loaded nanodroplets [
 <xref rid="B21-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. We developed and optimized baicalin loaded self-nanoemulsifying drug delivery systems (BSNEDDS), which can overcome the limitations of conventional nanoemulsions, such as low patient compliance (poor palatability), unsuitability for delivery through hard or soft gelatine capsules (high water content), larger volume, and ambiguous long-term storage. SNEDDS provide easy manufacture and ability to scale, improved physical and chemical stability, and better patient compliance [
 <xref rid="B23-pharmaceutics-10-00275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. 
</p>
