<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The effects of 
 <italic class="italic">Valeriana wallichii</italic> DC. (patchouli alcohol chemotype) were tested in the mouse FST after acute and 14-days administration [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. The acute treatment with this essential oil reduced, in a dose-dependent manner, the immobility time of mice in the FST; the antidepressant doses in this assay were 20 mg/kg and 40 mg/kg [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. However, after repeated administration, the 
 <italic class="italic">V. wallichii</italic> DC. oil reduced immobility time only at 20 mg/kg [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. Chronic administration increased norepinephrine and 5-HT levels in the mouse brain [
 <xref rid="B61-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>]. More evidence suggests the participation of nitric oxide signaling pathway in the acute antidepressant-like effect of 
 <italic class="italic">V. wallichii</italic> DC. essential oil. The pretreatment with 
 <sc class="sc">l</sc>-arginine (NO precursor) and sildenafil (phosphodiesterase 5 inhibitor) prevented the antidepressant effect, while it was potentiated with L-NAME (NOS inhibitor), and methylene blue (inhibitor of soluble guanylate cyclase) [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. These findings are in accordance with previous studies that showed reduction of NO levels within the brain inducing antidepressant-like effects [
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. Classical antidepressant drugs induce behavioral effects in the FST via blockade of nitregic system pathway [
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>]. The 
 <italic class="italic">V. wallichii</italic> DC. oil constituents were identified by gas chromatography-mass spectroscopy. The oil contains patchouli alcohol (40%) as the major constituent followed by the presence of δ-guaiene (10%), seychellene (8%), 8-acetoxyl patchouli alcohol (4%) and virdiflorol (5%). These isolated compounds have not still tested on experimental depression. Further studies, aimed at investigating the effects of these isolated compounds as well as the effects of 
 <italic class="italic">V. wallichii</italic> DC. essential oil on depression in rodents, are needed [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>].
</p>
