<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par71">The structures of polyamides used in chromatography contain both acryl and amide groups. Hydrophobic and/or hydrogen bond interaction will occur in polyamide column chromatography depending on the composition of the mobile phase. When polar solvents such as aqueous solvents are used as the mobile phase, the polyamides act as the non-polar stationary phase and the chromatography behavior is similar to reversed-phase chromatography. In the contrast, the polyamides act as the polar stationary phase and the chromatography behavior is similar to normal phase chromatography. Polyamide column chromatography is a conventional tool for the separation of natural polyphenols including anthraquinones, phenolic acids and flavonoids, whose mechanisms are ascribed to hydrogen bond formation between polyamide absorbents, mobile phase and target compounds. Gao et al. studied the chromatography behavior of polyphenols including phenolic acids and flavonoids on polyamide column. It was found that the polyamide functioned as a hydrogen bond acceptor, and the numbers of phenolic hydroxyls and their positions in the molecule affected the strength of adsorption [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. In addition to polyphenols, the separation of other types of natural products by polyamide column chromatography were also reported. The total saponins of Kuqingcha can be enriched by polyamide column chromatography, which significantly reduced the systolic pressure of SHR rat [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Using a mixture of dichloromethane and methanol in a gradient as the eluent, the seven major isoquinoline alkaloids in Coptidis Rhizoma including berberine (
 <bold>39</bold>), coptisine (
 <bold>40</bold>), palmatine (
 <bold>41</bold>), jatrorrhizine (
 <bold>42</bold>), columbamine (
 <bold>78</bold>), groenlandicine (
 <bold>79</bold>) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), and magnoflorine (
 <bold>80</bold>, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>) were separated in one-step polyamide column chromatography [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>].
</p>
