<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The chief aim of this review was to provide a comprehensive review of the literature regarding the isoflavonoids as well as to establish a critical review of the current evidence in relation to the anti-diabetic potential of plant based isoflavonoids. Hence, this review provides an analysis of the therapeutic potential of isoflavonoids for the slowdown in the progression of DM and possible mechanism of actions. The development of alternatives for insulin secretion control in vitro or in vivo represents an important aspect to be thoroughly explored. In this regard, natural products including isoflavonoids have been progressively explored with this aim. In particular, isoflavonoids, mainly biochanin A, genistein, daidzein, glycitein, and formononetin, have been suggested as potential candidates to act as insulin secretagogue. The information pertaining to antidiabetic potential of the aforementioned isoflavonoids were obtained from different databases and platforms that mainly included PubMed, Scopus, ISI Web of Knowledge, SciELO, Google Scholar, LILACS, Wiley Online Library, Springer Link, Web of Science, and Science Direct. Moreover, abstract proceedings, published books as well as non-indexed and non-impact journals were also taken into deep consideration to gather key information as well as to further ensure that no well documented key information with regard to the antidiabetic potential of the aforementioned isoflavonoids was left out. In this respect, a total of 134 articles from 1992 to 2020 focused on antidiabetic activity was identified. After thorough study and investigations of all searched articles, 116 manuscripts were finally selected based on the exclusion and inclusion criteria to accomplish this review. More precisely, for this review, the inclusion criteria thoroughly consisted of research articles published in indexed as well as non-indexed journals, year of publication, and in vitro and in vivo antidiabetic investigations (antihyperglycemic and hypoglycemic). Exclusion criteria comprised the repetition of similar effect with the same compound, insignificant results with poor statistical analysis, poorly written articles, article published twice in different journals with duplicate content, weakly orchestrated research work as well as research manuscripts that did not fulfil the aforementioned inclusion criteria.</p>
