<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="abs0010">
 <p>Antimicrobial resistance to antibiotics is a serious health problem worldwide, for this reason, the search for natural agents with antimicrobial power against pathogenic microorganisms is of current importance. The objective of this work was to evaluate the antioxidant capacity (ABTS+ and DPPH), antimicrobial activity, and polyphenol compounds of methanolic and aqueous extracts of 
  <italic>Jacaranda mimosifolia</italic> flowers. The antimicrobial activity against 
  <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> ATCC 10876
  <italic>, Bacillus subtilis</italic> ATCC 6633
  <italic>, Enterococcus faecalis</italic> ATCC 51299
  <italic>, Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC 25922
  <italic>, Listeria monocytogenes</italic> ATCC 19115
  <italic>, Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATCC 27853
  <italic>, Salmonella typhimurium</italic> ATCC 14028, 
  <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 25923, and 
  <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> ATCC 25175, was determined using the Kirby Bauer technique. The results of polyphenolic compounds showed a high amount of total flavonoids in the methanolic and aqueous extracts (503.3 ± 86.5 and 245. 7 ± 27.8 mg Rutin Equivalents/g DW, respectively). Quercetin, gallic acid, caffeic acid, and rutin were identified by the HPLC-DAD technique, while in the GC-MS analysis, esters, fatty acids, organic compounds, as well as monosaccharides were identified. Higher antioxidant capacity was detected by the ABTS technique (94.9% and 62.6%) compared to DPPH values (52.5% and 52.7 %) for methanolic and aqueous extracts, respectively. The methanolic extract showed a greater inhibitory effect on gram-positive bacteria, with a predominant higher inhibition percentage on 
  <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> and 
  <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> (86% for both). In conclusion, 
  <italic>Jacaranda</italic> flower extracts could be a natural antimicrobial and antioxidant alternative due to the considerable amount of polyphenolic compounds, and serve as a sustainable alternative for the isolation of active ingredients that could help in agriculture, aquaculture, livestock, pharmaceutics, and other industrial sectors, to remediate problems such as oxidative stress and antimicrobial abuse.
 </p>
</abstract>
