<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Early Hum Dev</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Early Hum Dev</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Early Human Development</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0378-3782</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1872-6232</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier B.V.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7528971</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0378-3782(20)30700-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.earlhumdev.2020.105216</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">105216</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Some health effects of global warming</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name><surname>Grech</surname><given-names>Victor</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name><surname>Cuschieri</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><aff id="af0005"><label>a</label>Mater Dei Hospital, Malta</aff><aff id="af0010"><label>b</label>University of Malta, Malta</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cr0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><elocation-id>105216</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0005">The world continues in the grip of the COVID-19 pandemic but it is hoped that a vaccine will be available within the next 12&#x000a0;months and that this particular global issue will then be partially or completely resolved in the not too distant future. However, there are wider and far more serious and pressing issues that threaten the world and our species (and indeed, many other species), one of which is global warming. During the unprecedent times of COVID-19, the enforced and voluntary restrictions to travel resulted in a global reduction in both air pollutants and greenhouse gases (GHGs) which are the pinnacle contributors of the &#x02018;Anthropocene Epoch&#x02019; [<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>]. The rapid and careless exploitation the Earth's resources by mankind dating back to the Industrial Revolution of the 1800s led to a significant impact on the planet's ecosystem and climate [<xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Climate change rapidly become a prominent dilemma experienced across the globe, but the onset of COVID-19 pandemic tipped the scales back, releasing the grips of mankind on the environment and resulting in temporarily favourable climate outcomes. Nonetheless, this is a temporarily situation as when global economies return to previous norms after COVID-19 is dealt with, global warming will have to be tackled with urgency lest a tipping point is reached that leads a runaway increase in global temperatures [<xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This set of Best Practice Guidelines in <italic>Early Human Development</italic> will focus on some health issues particularly pertaining to global warming.</p><p id="p0010">One of the papers will explore the link between global warming, air pollution and two of the most common and debilitating neurological conditions, stroke and neurodegenerative disorders. A link has been shown between accumulated levels of air pollutants (especially particulates), and the incidence of ischemic strokes and dementia and this will be amplified in Zammit et al. &#x0201c;Neurological disorders vis-&#x000e0;-vis global warming.&#x0201d;</p><p id="p0015">Another, more general topic is that of heat stress induced by global warming, particularly in the elderly, in infants and in individuals with co-morbid cardiovascular and/or respiratory conditions. All of these may have impaired thermoregulation that may be affected by extreme cold or warmth, with increased mortality as discussed by Calleja-Agius et al. in &#x0201c;The effect of global warming on mortality&#x0201d;.</p><p id="p0020">An equally general and little discussed topic is that of the footprint created on the surrounding environment by the increasing production of medications for human and veterinary use. One of the papers in this collection will outline the various measures that have been introduced to promote green manufacturing and practices. Sammut Bartolo et al. in their article &#x0201c;Pharmaceuticals and the environment&#x0201d; will also discuss the reduction of wastage both on the supply side and the patient side who may hoard unnecessarily and inefficiently.</p><p id="p0025">Gestational diabetes (GDM) is explored by Pace et al. in this collection's article &#x0201c;Gestational diabetes and environmental temperature &#x02013; from epidemiological evidence to physiological mechanisms&#x0201d; as there is a complex association between this condition and environmental temperature. Indeed, studies have shown a relationship between rising environmental temperatures and the risk of both GDM and impaired beta cell function including the seasonal trends with a higher prevalence in summer months.</p><p id="p0030">Type 2 diabetes is also surveyed by means of a review article by Cuschieri et al. that indicates both direct and indirect links of this condition with climate change in &#x0201c;The interaction between diabetes and climate change &#x02013; A review on the dual global phenomena&#x0201d;. It is noted that temperature changes may trigger a person's susceptibility to develop diabetes and also exacerbate the effects of extant diabetes.</p><p id="p0035">It is hoped that this BPG collection with some unusual facets on the topic of climate change may provide interested readers with reading matter that lies outside the box.</p></body><back><ref-list id="bi0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bb0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brasseur</surname><given-names>G.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The response in air quality to the reduction of Chinese economic activities during the COVID-19 outbreak</article-title><source>Geophys. Res. Lett.</source><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2020GL088070</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2020GL088070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bauwens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Compernolle</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stavrakou</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>J.-F.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Gent</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eskes</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levelt</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der A</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veefkind</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vlietinck</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zehner</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of coronavirus outbreak on NO2 pollution assessed using TROPOMI and OMI observations</article-title><source>Geophys. Res. Lett.</source><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2020GL087978</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2020GL087978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0015"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crutzen</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoermer</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Anthropocene</article-title><source>Glob. Chang. Newsl.</source><volume>17&#x02013;18</volume><year>2000</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crutzen</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geology of mankind</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>415</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>23</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/415023a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11780095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenton</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rockstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaffney</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahmstorf</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schellnhuber</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate tipping points &#x02014; too risky to bet against</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>575</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/d41586-019-03595-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31776487</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>