<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ticks belong to a group of exclusively blood-feeding ectoparasites (Elmhalli et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">2009</a>). From the medical point of view, ticks are the second most important group of disease vectors after mosquitoes. The pathogenic agents transmitted by ticks affect the public health and cause economic losses in livestock sector (Svehlova et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2014</a>). The Mediterranean region offers suitable environment for a wide range of tick species (Maia et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">2014</a>). The geographical distribution of ticks has continued to increase over the past three decades (Tabanca et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2013</a>; Svehlova et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2014</a>). This distribution might be modified by future climate and environmental changes (Jore et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The common tick, 
  <span class="italic">Ixodes ricinus</span> (L.) (Acari: Ixodidae), is a triphasic tick that parasitizes a large number of vertebrates including small, medium to large mammals; birds and lizards (Becker et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">2009</a>). The abundance of 
  <span class="italic">I</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ricinus</span> on different vegetation types in a wooded area of Southern Italy was determined by Dantas-Torres and Otranto (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">2013</a>). They found that the abundance of 
  <span class="italic">I</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ricinus</span> larvae on the ground-level vegetation was generally higher than on the higher vegetation whereas both nymphs and adult stages were more abundant on higher vegetation. The questing behavior of 
  <span class="italic">I</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ricinus</span> consists of climbing the low vegetation to a point from where it can attach to the passing hosts. The host-seeking activity of the castor-bean tick indicated that this tick has a bimodal seasonal activity with a dominant peak during spring whereas a minor peak during autumn (Schulz et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2014</a>). The immature stages (larvae and nymphs) feed on woodland birds and small to medium-sized mammals while the adult female feeds on large mammals. Each life stage (larva, nymph, adult) of this tick feeds once on different host for continuous period lasting several days (Heylen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Ixodes</span>
  <span class="italic">ricinus</span> is a potential vector of different pathogens. The cattle parasite, 
  <span class="italic">Babesia divergens</span> (the causative agent of human’s babesiosis) is transmitted to human by 
  <span class="italic">I</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ricinus</span> (Zintl et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2014</a>). Spirochete, 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span>
  <span class="italic">burgdorferi</span> sensu lato (the causative agent of Lyme disease) is considered diderm (double-membrane) bacteria with a worldwide distribution. 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia burgdorferi</span> is mostly associated with 
  <span class="italic">I</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ricinus</span> complex in Northern Hemisphere. The density of questing 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> in Northern Norway was determined for the first time by Hvidstena et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2015</a>). They found that the overall prevalence of nymphs and adult ticks infected by 
  <span class="italic">B. burgdorferi</span> s.l. was 21 and 46%, respectively. The high incidence rate of reported Lyme borreliosis in Bonnoy region can be explained by the high 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span>-infection prevalence in ticks (Hvidstena et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2015</a>). The encephalitis virus is transmitted to humans by 
  <span class="italic">I</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ricinus</span> nymphs and adults. The infection prevalence of tick-born-encephalitis virus (TBE) was significantly lower in 
  <span class="italic">I</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ricinus</span> nymphs (0.51%) than adults (4.48%) stage (Pettersson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2014</a>). Due to the role of 
  <span class="italic">I</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ricinus</span> tick in the transmitting of many serous pathogens, personal protection against bites of the infected stages of 
  <span class="italic">I</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ricinus</span> is essential.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite recent advances in tick control strategies, large-scale reduction of tick populations has not been achieved (Tabanca et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2013</a>). The synthetic repellents are commonly accepted means of personal protection against tick bites (Iori et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2005</a>). However, the use of such commercial synthetic acaricides leads to resistance, residual effects and potentially can harm the environment (Elmhalli et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">2009</a>). There is a direct need to establish alternative substances for tick control which are safer, available, cheaper and more effective (Frances and Wirtz 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2005</a>). Many essential oils (extracted from medicinal plants) considered as promising repellent agents against 
  <span class="italic">I</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ricinus</span>. The repellency of the oils appears to be largely associated with the presence of volatile terpenoid constituents.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a part of our ongoing studies of bioactive constituents from plants commonly used in folk medicine (El-Seedi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2012</a>; Al-Henhen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2014</a>; Boldbaatar et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2014</a>
  <span class="bold">)</span> with potential use in chemical ecology research, we here present results from 11 medicinal and culinary plants originating from Egypt. We isolated the essential oils and evaluated their bioactivity against the common tick 
  <span class="italic">I</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ricinus</span> and identified the main chemical constituents of these essential oils using gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC–MS).
 </p>
</sec>
