<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par102">
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par103">To establish a state strategy respecting narcotic and psychotropic substances to develop the one-for-all approaches to regulating the turnover of these substances, including cannabis and cannabinoids in Ukraine. In its formation, it is advisable to target on both the international human rights conventions providing the right to life, the highest attainable standard of physical and mental health, be free from discrimination and mental health and social and economic rights (International Drug Policy Consortium 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2016</xref>), and the information reported by Global Commission on Drug Policy (GCDP). For instance, the reports mentioned focus on the regulations-change paradigm for narcotic and psychotropic substances: both the ‘total ban’ and the absence of adequate regulation facilitate development of the illicit drug market (Global Commission on Drug Policy 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2019</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par104">In accordance with Art.16 of the Law of Ukraine “On Narcotic Drugs, Psychotropic Substances and Precursors”, to set the course of development of new narcotic and psychotropic preparations, including those containing cannabis and cannabinoids by means of regulatory by-laws (Law of Ukraine 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1995</xref>). Attention should be paid to conflicts of laws: for instance, illicit drugs seized by law enforcement authorities cannot be used later for the production of legal medicinal products. According to Ukrainian legislation they must be utilized. It does not just help improve access to narcotic and psychotropic substances for Ukrainian patients and refine income deficiency for pharmaceutical companies, it also leads to additional state expenses on imported raw materials and utilization of the illicit substances.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par105">In accordance with the approved state strategy concerning narcotic drugs, to develop a new law on cannabis or introduce relevant amendments to the Law of Ukraine “On Narcotic Drugs, Psychotropic Substances and Precursors”. This is believed to contribute to legal activity related to cannabis and cannabinoids use for medical and scientific purposes (Law of Ukraine 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1995</xref>). This law must consider the requirements of Art. 23 and Art. 28 of the Single Convention on Narcotic Drugs (1961), in particular, the foundation of a state cannabis agency with specified functions. This includes stating the soil lots for cannabis cultivation for the production of narcotic drugs, granting licenses, crop purchasing and its further distribution, liability for export and import, needs estimation, submission of statistic information to INCB and other functions (United Nations 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">1961</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par106">Ukraine already has efficient mechanisms to implement the requirements of international conventions on drugs control. Thus, the State Service of Ukraine on Medicines and Drugs Control can perform as a cannabis control agency. More particularly, it refers to its structural branch. The Directorate of state regulation and control deals with circulation of narcotic drugs, psychotropic substances and precursors and counters their illicit turnover. This branch is responsible for lisensing and quoting the cultivation of narcotic drug-containing plants, identifying needs in narcotic substances, collection of statistics and its submission to international structures/bodies and others. Besides, the Center for mental health and drugs and alcohol monitoring at the MHU has been functioning in Ukraine since 2009. Its functions cover both the monitoring of drugs and collecting information on use of narcotic products (Institute of Analysis and Advocacy 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2018</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par107">To introduce changes into the Decree of CMU №770 in May 6, 2000 “On the Approval of the Schedule of Narcotic Drugs, Psychotropic Substances and Precursors” (Decree of CMU 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2000</xref>) in accordance with recommendations approved at the ECDD WHO 41st session (WHO 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2018</xref>). And specifically, to exclude cannabis, cannabis resin, extracts and tincture of cannabis from Table I, Schedule 1 “Especially dangerous narcotic drugs, with the circulation to be prohibited” and to include cannabis and cannabis resin into Table II, Schedule 1 “Narcotic drugs, with the circulation to be limited”, and to include extracts and tinctures of cannabis into Table III, Schedule 1 “Narcotic drugs, with the circulation to be limited; in relation to these substances the exceptions to some control measures shall be allowed”. Besides, to exclude THC (isomers and their stereochemical variants) from Table I, Schedule 2 “Especially dangerous psychotropic substances, with the circulation to be prohibited”, as well as dronabinol and its stereoisomers (Δ9-THC) from Table II, Schedule 2 “Psychotropic substances, with the circulation to be limited” and to include them into Table II, Schedule 1.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par108">To exclude from the Schedules of narcotic drugs, psychotropic substances and precursors of the Decree of CMU № 770, May 6, 2000, cannabis with the total THC content not exceeding 1.0% and CBD with admixed THC not exceeding 1.0%, because there is no psychotropic effect and the risk of drug addiction development (the case of Switzerland and Uruguay). CBD preparations with THC content of 1.0% have a far stronger therapeutic effect for medical use than a ‘pure’ CBD (entourage effect) (Russo 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2018</xref>). To obtain official interpretation or advisement from the state bodies of Ukraine (MHU) regarding that preparations containing pure CBD are not subject to control under Conventions regulating the traffic of narcotic drugs.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par109">To approve necessary subordinate acts allowing policy implementation for medical cannabis turnover: Decrees of CMU, Orders of MHU, etc. To develop relevant monographs on cannabis plant and cannabinoids in SPhU, treatment protocols, clinical guidelines and other regulating documents. With the help of HTA tools to substantiate the importance of medical cannabis application for treating certain symptoms or diseases, in particular through budget funds or health insurance.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par110">To provide a comprehensive framework for conducting research on cannabis and cannabinoids by scientific research and higher education institutions of all types of ownership without licenses and quotas (for a definite number of plants). Considering requirements of the national legislation on medicinal products to allow research and higher educational institutions to cultivate cannabis, to develop medicinal substances and products based on cannabis and cannabinoids, to carry out preclinical and clinical trials.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par111">To introduce changes to the Criminal Code and the Code of Administrative Offences of Ukraine to decriminalize the possession and storing of cannabis in a limited quantity without intention to sell it, taking into consideration information provided in Art. 3, p. 2 of the UN Convention on countering illicit turnover of narcotic drugs and psychotropic substances (1988) (United Nations 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1988</xref>), materials laid in the GCDP reports (Global Commission on Drug Policy 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2018</xref>, 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2019</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
