<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The increases in occurrence and abundance of 
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>multiflora</italic> and 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>thunbergii</italic> in plots with a history of agriculture were similar in magnitude to the impacts of mining. Plots with a history of agriculture also contained significantly more invasive plant species than plots that had remained forested since 1939. 
 <italic>Berberis thunbergii</italic> is a known post-agricultural specialist and a history of agriculture has been found to increase abundance and occurrence of many other invasive species including 
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>multiflora</italic>, 
 <italic>L</italic>. 
 <italic>morrowii</italic>, 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>petiolata</italic>, and 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>orbiculata</italic>, in addition to increasing the total number of invasive species found at a site [
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] [
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Agricultural abandonment creates an invasion opportunity, as with mining, by clearing native vegetation. As some invasive plant species were once planted in hedgerows or to prevent erosion, they are ideally located to take advantage of abandoned fields [
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Further, agriculture often results in persistent changes in soil chemistry, as fertilizer application increases nitrogen and phosphorus concentrations for decades after the farmland is abandoned [
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. These highly fertile sites have been shown to increase growth of invasive species relative to forested areas [
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Our results suggest that the disturbance and removal of the native plant community as a result of historic agriculture allowed for the initial invasion of 
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>multiflora</italic> and 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>thunbergii</italic>, and thus resulted in a greater probability of invasive occurrence even after the forest regrew in those plots. However, historic agriculture is unique among our land-use history categories in that it increased the abundance of both invasive focal species as well. These results suggest that a history of agriculture continues to enhance invasive species performance for decades after abandonment perhaps due to long-term increases in soil fertility. Further, our findings highlight the importance of re-establishing a native plant community quickly after farming is discontinued to limit invasive species introduction and spread.
</p>
