<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The latter 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> study, which was performed in mice feed with HFD, suggested that the weight loss effect was less dependent on tymoquinone, while other phenolic compounds may affect (
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr">Mahmoudi et al., 2018</xref>). Alternatively, studies on female C57BL/6 mice, which were also subjected to HFD and supplemented with thymoquinone (10–20%), showed that this compound ameliorated obesity-induced metabolic dysfunction and impaired positive effects on ovarian and mammary gland metabolic functions (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">Harphoush et al., 2019</xref>). In another context, obesity markers were significantly down-regulated while momentous control over obesity-induced changes in biochemical profile of the body by thymol (13) treatment. It also modified fat and glucose metabolism in such a way to favor the control over obesity in mice partly via hypolipidemic, hypoglycemic, hypo-insulinemic, hypoleptinemic, and pancreatic lipase inhibition action (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Haque and Ansari, 2018</xref>). This compound has also been endorsed to possess anti-obesity properties by controlling obesity markers in HFD induced obese male Wistar rats. They recorded significant reduction in body and liver weights, visceral fat pad weight, food intake, leptin and inhibition of pancreatic lipase (
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">Haque et al., 2014</xref>). Among molecular mechanisms, 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al. (2017)</xref> assessed the role of thymol (13) in 3T3-L1 white adipocytes via promoting mitochondrial biogenesis, enhancing expression of a core set of brown fat-specific markers as well as enhancing the protein levels of PPARγ, PPARδ, pAMPK, pACC, HSL, PLIN, CPT1, ACO, PGC-1α, and UCP1. It also augmented lipolysis, thermogenesis and fat oxidation. In the case of carvacrol (12), it can act by reduction of autophagy (essential for adipocyte maturation) and on carbohydrate-responsive element-binding protein ChREBP activity, reducing adipogenic differentiation (
 <xref rid="B191" ref-type="bibr">Spalletta et al., 2018</xref>). The supplementation of this compound in the diet (0.1%) may prevent diet-induced obesity by modulating gene expressions involved and protein associated with the signaling cascades in adipogenesis, as well as inflammation (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Cho et al., 2012</xref>). Overall, it seems that 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> has an interesting profile of phytochemicals, which can act in different ways and require attention.
</p>
