<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It is composed of amylose and amylopectin polymers (α-d-glucose monomers), containing hydroxyl groups (–OH). These groups show strong intermolecular interactions, which give, on the basis of tighter arrangement, increased crystallinity and melting temperatures. As a consequence, starch molecules are thermally affected, which strongly limits their application as a packaging material (
 <xref rid="materials-12-00471-t003" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B134-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">134</xref>,
 <xref rid="B135-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">135</xref>]. Alternatively, the presence of hydroxyl groups supports the break of hydrogen bonds that induce the disintegration into small fragments. Starch products are food sources for microorganisms in determined environment conditions, as elevated humidity (~55–60% RH), in the presence of satisfactory oxygen feedstock, and suitable temperatures to make the biodegradation easy [
 <xref rid="B136-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">136</xref>,
 <xref rid="B137-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">137</xref>]. In addition, starch hydrophilicity creates materials with a poor water barrier [
 <xref rid="B138-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">138</xref>]. At a modest or elevated relative humidity, starch-based substances tend to soak up moisture from the environment. Firstly, this behavior will induce swelling of the matrix, with disruption of hydrogen bonds, after that the increase of free volume spaces will also enhance the chain mobility. Therefore, moisture and gas barriers are negatively influenced and, consequently, are drastically compromised. According to this, starch may not be adequate to realize packages for dry and oxygen-sensitive foods. Other than low barrier properties, starch materials have the inclination to show reduced mechanical characteristics, reducing, consequently, again their utilization [
 <xref rid="B139-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">139</xref>]. Furthermore, even if starch price is relatively low, adaptation of its performances may improve the final cost of different materials. Numerous parameters should be considered for the design of starch food packages. 
</p>
