<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="order" class="list">
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Use an X-ray microtomography scanner to acquire the three-dimensional X-ray scans at the micron scale of the reservoir rock saturated with oil and brine at subsurface conditions.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Find the most effective phase contrast between oil, brine, and rock by doping the brine phase, using KI to be the intermediate phase in terms of X-ray adsorption. To achieve a good contrast between oil (lowest sorption, black), brine (intermediate, dark gray) and rock (most sorbing phase, light gray), as shown in 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" class="xref">Figure 4</xref>, prepare mini-containers with a different weight percent of KI brine, and perform the scanning. The histogram of the gray-scale value should show 3 separate phases (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" class="xref">Figure 4</xref>
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>). 
   <list list-type="order" class="list">
    <list-item class="list-item">
     <p class="p">To prepare a contrast sample, half-fill a small cylindrical glass container (1 mL) with both oil and KI brine phases. Then, fill the other half of the container with crushed pieces of rock and mix them rigorously. Use a clean cylindrical metal to compact the mixture, avoiding any grain movement while scanning. Wear complete PPE and perform the mixing of the crude oil and the KI brine in a fume cupboard.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Use a relatively long carbon fiber core holder with a small diameter to allow the X-ray source to be brought as close as possible to the sample. Do not use a very long core holder, which could increase the sample movement due to rotation during the scan acquisition.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Use the 4X objective to acquire X-ray images at a high resolution (
   <italic class="italic">i.e.</italic>, 2 µm/voxel) sufficient to measure the effective 
   <italic class="italic">in situ</italic> contact angle.Use flexible PEEK tubing as injection lines to allow a smooth 360° rotation of the core holder assembly during the scan acquisition.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">For thin or low-density samples, use an X-ray source voltage and power of 80 kV and 7 W, respectively. For thick or high-density samples, use an X-ray source voltage and power of 140 kV and 10 W, respectively. NOTE: In this case, an X-ray source voltage of 80 kV and a power of 7 W were used.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">To acquire the 2 µm/voxel scans, use the 4X objective with an exposure time (
   <italic class="italic">i.e.</italic>, 1.5 s or more) sufficient to obtain an X-ray radiation intensity of greater than 5,000 counts/s.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Use a high number of projections (at least 3,200 projections) depending on time constraints. NOTE: X-ray microtomography involves an ionizing radiation risk. Hence, an appropriate risk assessment is required to ensure a safe working environment.</p>
 </list-item>
</list>
