<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The pomegranate fruit is a rich source of sugars. The level of the sugars in pomegranate juice is highly correlated with the level of total soluble solids (TSS). Shwartz et al. (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>) and Dafny-Yalin et al. (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>) calculated a value of 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.89, 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.01. The TSS level in the juice ranges from 4.2 to 8.5 g/100 g depending on cultivars, climatic conditions, and cultural techniques (reviewed by Kalaycioglu and Erim (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>); Amir et al. (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>)). Pomegranate juice contains a high amount of polyphenols such as flavonoids, ellgitannins, and the color molecules anthocyanins. A substantial fraction of these molecules are known to be conjugated to sugars, mostly glucose. The taste of arils from various pomegranate varieties is significantly variable, ranging from sour to sweet (Holland et al., 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Amir et al., 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>). Sugar content is an important parameter influencing taste, although it is highly influenced by organic acid content as well. Many studies examined the sugars in the pomegranate fruit, mainly in the juice, revealing glucose, and fructose as the main component of the juice sugars (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>). Sugars found in the fruit peel were in some controversy among studies from different countries. It should be noted that those studies were done for different purposes and therefore followed different procedures of extraction and detection that might explain this disagreement. Some of the studies indicated glucose and fructose as the main sugars while others found that xylose and arabinose are the main sugars (Hasnaoui et al., 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
