<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phenolic compounds are plant secondary metabolites with a strong antioxidant effect, being known to initiate numerous processes involved in the wound healing process [
 <xref rid="B21-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In this study, we aimed to extract the cellulosic material from the 
 <italic>G. triacanthos</italic> pods, which was further multi-functionalized with a leaf extract of the same species, showing a significantly highphenolic compound content that in a first stage could exhibit both antimicrobial and antioxidant activities, contributing to skin regeneration. Data regarding UHPLC-DAD-ESI/MS analysis of PA and flavonoids from 
 <italic>G. triachantos</italic> leaf extract have not been previously reported. However, Mohammed (2014) isolated and identified eight flavone glycosides and two flavone aglycones such as luteolin-7-O-β-glucopyranosid, luteolin-7-O-β-galactopyranoside, apigenin-7-O-β-glucopyranoside, luteolin, and apigenin from the aqueous ethanol extract of 
 <italic>G. triacanthos</italic> L. leaves. Vitexin, luteolin, isovitexin, and quercetin have also been previously identified in this plant extract [
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In addition, some identified compounds from the alcoholic extract of 
 <italic>G. triachantos</italic>, such as syringic acid [
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], gallic acid [
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], p-coumaric acid [
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], apigenin [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], quercetin [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], and myricetin [
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], were reported to exhibit anti-inflammatory effects. Thus, PAs promise to be multivalent, bioinspired molecules that either alone or in the form of biomaterials additives can be very useful to prevent and treat medical device-associated and drug-resistant infections [
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-22-00033" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].
</p>
