<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Two years late, the same group evaluated jatamanvaltrates P-Y, nardostachin, and ten new valepotriates, but this time, the compounds were isolated from the whole plants and found cytotoxic activity against PC-3M cells [
 <xref rid="B104-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. They also examined the structure-activity relationship of these valepotriates and the results reveal a crucial 10-chlorine in the oxirane ring and the bond C3–C4. The compound valtrate was able to avoid migration of human breast cancer cells and induce apoptosis, both in vitro and in vivo. In another experiment, they discover that valtrals (A, B, and C), which are by-products of valepotriates resulting from a degradation reaction during the separation methodology from the ethanol extract prepared with the entire plant, showed selective cytotoxicity against colon cancer (HCT-8) cell lines and metastatic prostate cancer (PC-3M) [
 <xref rid="B104-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. Other tests performed with three new minor valepotriate isomers, jatamanvaltrates, all of them isolated from the entire plants of 
 <italic>V. jatamansi,</italic> evidenced moderate cytotoxicity in the two cell lines cited above and also hepatoma (Bel7402) [
 <xref rid="B105-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Jatamanvaltrate P, an iridoid ester, can inhibit the proliferation and growth, in a concentration-dependent manner, of MDA-MB-231, MDA-MB-453, and MDA-MB-468 (this last three lines corresponding to the triple-negative breast cancer) and MCF-7 cell lines. As the author’s highlight, this molecule exhibited an antitumor effect in MDA-MB-231 xenografts without noticeable toxicity, suggesting that it could be used in research for a future potential therapeutic drug against breast cancer [
 <xref rid="B105-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. A specific fraction obtained from 
 <italic>V. jatamansi</italic> (no data provided about the parts of the plant) significantly inhibited the growth of breast cancer cells in a concentration-dependent manner by inducing apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B106-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. Among its therapeutic effects on insomnia and seizures the valeric acid, which is another active compound in valerian, has been reported to improve immunity against cancer [
 <xref rid="B107-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Promising data also involve other compounds, in this case, fatty acids naturally occurring in seed oils such as conjugated linolenic acids (CLNs) which are likewise present in 
 <italic>C. ruber</italic> and 
 <italic>V. officinalis)</italic> [
 <xref rid="B108-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>].
</p>
