<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Heterogeneous soil had no effects on most growth traits except shoot numbers in the one-plant density treatment (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). In addition, plants accumulated less biomass when soil nutrient availability was heterogeneous at high density (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Few studies have found that clonal plants grew more biomass in the heterogeneous than in the homogeneous soil treatment (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Hutchings and Wijesinghe, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">You et al., 2014</xref>). However, the positive effect of soil nutrient heterogeneity on the growth performance of plants may gradually decrease because the soil nutrients become limited in high-density populations (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Day et al., 2003a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Dong et al., 2015</xref>). For example, soil nutrient heterogeneity has a short-term effect on the growth cycle of 
 <italic>Cardamine hirsuta</italic>, and it does not have a long-term impact (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Day et al., 2003a</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). Furthermore, the long-term response of 
 <italic>Holcus lanatus</italic> was to produce far less shoot biomass in the heterogeneous treatment than expected under the homogeneity treatment (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Fransen and Kroon, 2001</xref>). In addition, the growth performance of clonal plants in heterogeneous soil conditions may be correlated with the spatial scale of heterogeneity (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Wijesinghe and Hutchings, 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2016</xref>). For example, the growth of 
 <italic>Glechoma hederacea</italic> was dependent on the spatial scale of soil nutrient heterogeneity (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Wijesinghe and Hutchings, 1997</xref>), but 
 <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> displayed generally similar, scale-independent performance in most traits under different scales of soil nutrient heterogeneity (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2016</xref>). We speculate that the benefits of environmental heterogeneity to clonal plants may be correlated with spatial or temporal scale.
</p>
