<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="order">
 <list-item>
  <p>Pyridine (190.23 mmol) and 4-nitrophenyl chloroformate (104.62 mmol) were added to a stirred solution of alkyl 2-amino-4,5-dialkylthiophene-3-carboxylate (
   <bold>1</bold>, 95.11 mmol) in anhydrous CH
   <sub>2</sub>Cl
   <sub>2</sub> at 0 °C. The reaction mixture was warmed to room temperature and stirred for 2 h. After the reaction was completed, the reaction mixture was quenched with H
   <sub>2</sub>O and extracted using CH
   <sub>2</sub>Cl
   <sub>2</sub>. The organic layer was dried over anhydrous MgSO
   <sub>4</sub>, filtered, and concentrated. The crude product was precipitated by adding diethyl ether and kept at 4 °C for few hours to complete the precipitation. The precipitate was filtered and washed with diethyl ether and dried in vacuum to produce a 4-nitrophenoxycarbonylamino derivative (
   <bold>2</bold>) as a yellow solid.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>A solution of the above intermediate (
   <bold>2</bold>, 56 mmol), 
   <italic>tert</italic>-butyl 3-(aminomethyl)-2-
   <italic>R</italic>-substituted-4,7-dihydrothieno[2,3-
   <italic>c</italic>]pyridine-6(5
   <italic>H</italic>)-carboxylate (
   <bold>3</bold>, 62 mmol), and triethylamine (113 mmol) in CH
   <sub>2</sub>Cl
   <sub>2</sub> was stirred overnight at room temperature. The organic solution was washed with H
   <sub>2</sub>O, dried over anhydrous MgSO
   <sub>4</sub>, and concentrated under reduced pressure. The solid product was filtered and washed with diethyl ether to obtain a pure compound (
   <bold>4</bold>) as a pale yellow solid.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Trifluoroacetic acid (155.9 mmol) was added to a stirred solution of the above intermediate (
   <bold>4</bold>, 19.4 mmol) in CH
   <sub>2</sub>Cl
   <sub>2</sub> at 0 °C. The reaction mixture was stirred at room temperature for 5 h. After the reaction was complete, the mixture was diluted with CH
   <sub>2</sub>Cl
   <sub>2</sub> and washed with brine (br). Next, 2N NaOH (aq.) was slowly added to the separated organic solution at 10 °C, and then the suspension was stirred for 1.5 h. The precipitate was filtered and agitated with methyl 
   <italic>tert</italic>-butyl ether for 2 h. The solid was filtered and washed with diethyl ether and dried under vacuum to obtain the product (
   <bold>5</bold>) as a white powder. The final product (6) could be obtained as an organic or inorganic salt by further process to get more stable solid state.
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
