<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mushroom polysaccharides, especially glucans, are known to exert anticancer activity through immunostimulatory potential, which involves the activation of the innate immune system as well as the acceleration of the host’s defense mechanisms [
 <xref rid="B1-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In addition to the anticancer potential, mushroom polysaccharides possess a vast spectrum of biological activities, including antimicrobial, antiviral, antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, or prebiotic properties [
 <xref rid="B6-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The major glucans isolated from the fungal species used in the treatment of cancer in Asian countries are β-glucans, e.g., lentinan from 
 <italic>Lentinus edodes</italic>, schizophyllan from 
 <italic>Schizophyllum commune</italic>, krestin from 
 <italic>Trametes versicolor</italic>, and grifolan from 
 <italic>Grifola frondosa</italic> [
 <xref rid="B11-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Colon cancer is believed to be preventable with the use of natural chemopreventive agents. The strategy of chemoprevention assumes reversing, suppressing, or preventing carcinogenic progression [
 <xref rid="B15-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. With their multidirectional activity, mushroom polysaccharides are able to act at different steps in the carcinogenic process, with the overall goal of reducing cancer incidence. Moreover, there are some already known strategies based on the use of mushroom β-glucans not only to inhibit tumor growth but also induce synergistic effects with chemotherapeutic agents or other immune stimulators. An innovative approach assumes that β-glucans may be used to deliver nanoparticles containing chemotherapeutic agents to the colon cancer site to improve their therapeutic efficacy [
 <xref rid="B16-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
</p>
