<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The 18:3 PUFAs, especially GLA, can be the dietary supplementation to improve dry skin and dermatitis. PGE1 and 15-hydroxyeicosatrienoic acid converted from GLA via dihomo-GLA possess anti-inflammatory characteristics. GLA supplementation was investigated to reverse epidermal hyperproliferation [
 <xref rid="B89-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>]. The consumption of GLA-rich borage oil modified fatty acid metabolism and increased the skin barrier function [
 <xref rid="B90-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>]. In the previous report [
 <xref rid="B91-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>], GLA-rich oil was incorporated into the food for oral consumption in 130 subjects with mild atopic dermatitis. After 4 weeks, the GLA group revealed lower TEWL and a higher stratum corneum index compared to the control. No significant side effects were found after GLA administration. The mechanism of skin barrier recovery has been associated with the possible generation of anti-inflammatory metabolites from GLA. The dihomo-GLA concentration in the serum of atopic dermatitis patients was lower than that of the healthy control [
 <xref rid="B92-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>]. Dihomo-GLA is one of the active metabolites of GLA. Since GLA is sometimes not effectively converted into dihomo-GLA in dermatitis patients, Kawashima et al. [
 <xref rid="B93-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>] examined whether oral delivery of dihomo-GLA prevented dermatitis-like lesions in NC/Nga mice. The clinical severity score and scratching behavior manifested lower levels in the mice fed dihomo-GLA. The total plasma immunoglobulin (IgE) was significantly lower in the dihomo-GLA group (15.6 μg/mL) than in the control (64.2 μg/mL). In another study utilizing NC/Tnd mice as the animal model [
 <xref rid="B94-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>], dietary dihomo-GLA but not AA and EPA suppressed the development of dermatitis-like lesions. The application of dihomo-GLA upregulated prostaglandin D1 (PGD1), resulting in the subsequent suppression of IgE-mediated degranulation. The amount and duration of scratching were lessened by dihomo-GLA supplementation. The description of the fatty acids existed in fish oils for preventing or treating dermatitis is shown in 
 <xref rid="marinedrugs-16-00256-t003" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>.
</p>
