<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cancer is a major health problem. Radiotherapy, chemotherapy and surgical removal are the current treatment methods. However, these methods have varied disadvantages such as drug resistance and toxic effects on nontargeted tissues. Therefore, researchers are searching for naturally available plant-based bioactive compounds for cancer therapy [
 <xref rid="B62-plants-10-00032" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Among the plant-based bioactive compounds, saponins and phytosterols have significant importance in reducing the risk of cancer [
 <xref rid="B63-plants-10-00032" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-plants-10-00032" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Various steroidal saponins isolated from various tissues of 
 <italic>B. aegyptiaca</italic> are reported to display anticancer activities. For example, a mixture of balanitin-6 and balanitin-7 (28:72) isolated from kernels show growth inhibition in human cancer cell lines in vitro [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-10-00032" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Balanitin-6/balanitin-7 exhibited higher antiproliferative activity than well-known natural cancer therapeutic agents, such as etoposide and oxaliplatin. Balanitin-6/balanitin-7 displayed its highest activity against A549 nonsmall cell lung cancer (IC
 <sub>50</sub>, 0.3 µM) and U373 glioblastoma (IC
 <sub>50</sub>, 0.5 µM) cell lines. Balanitoside extracted from the fruit also showed anticancer activity against Ehrlich ascites carcinoma (EAC)-bearing Swiss albino mice [
 <xref rid="B36-plants-10-00032" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Mice injected intraperitoneally with balanitoside (10 mg/kg body weight) displayed decreases in liver and serum enzyme levels. Issa et al. [
 <xref rid="B65-plants-10-00032" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] studied an aqueous extract of pulp on the development and growth of EAC and metastasis to the liver and spleen. Treatment with the extract (400 mg/kg) inhibited tumor growth and proliferation in ascetic fluid, inducing a significant decrease in tumor volume, total cell volume and viable cell count and prolonged mouse survival. The authors also recorded significant decreases in levels of lipid peroxidation and increased superoxide dismutase and catalase activity and P53 (a tumor suppressor protein) expression. The saponin, balanitin-7 isolated from seed kernels, showed antiproliferative activity [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-10-00032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. These agents showed potent antiproliferative activity against MCF-7 human breast cancer cells and HT-29 human colon cancer cells, with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 2.4 and 3.3 µM, respectively.
</p>
