<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the present study, the discrete and combinational inhibitory effects of HSEO and radiation treatments on growth, production of DON and ZEA by 
 <italic class="italic">F. graminearum</italic> in maize grains were assessed under laboratory set-ups. The GC-MS analysis of HSEO revealed the presence of 48 compounds constituting to 96.84% of total weight and major compounds were 1,8-cineole, linalool, and β-pinene. The simple linear regression analysis showed that HSEO and radiation treatments were discretely inhibited the fungal growth, DON, and ZEA content in maize grains by the dose-dependent way, and complete inhibition were noticed at 3.15 mg/g of HSEO and 6 kGy of radiation. The combinational inhibitory action of HSEO and radiation treatments on growth, production of DON and ZEA by 
 <italic class="italic">F. graminearum</italic> in maize grains was studied by CCD of RSM statistical program. The fungal growth, DON, and ZEA content were not detected at combinational treatment of 1.89 mg/g of HSEO and 4.12 kGy of radiation. The results revealed that combination of HSEO and radiation treatments could reduce the fungal growth, DON, and ZEA content at much lower concentration than their discrete inhibitory dose. The quadratic model was found well appropriate for reductions of fungal growth (log CFU), DON, and ZEA content in maize grains. The optimized design was found statistically significant (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) with larger 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>-value and adequate precision, and a smaller 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-value. The actual data points were close to the straight line and presented good correlation regression coefficients (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">
  <italic class="italic">2</italic>
 </sup>) for the responses. In addition, diagnostic and correlation plots, i.e., correlation matrix, normal plot residuals, Box-Cox, and actual vs. predicted plots were confirmed that optimized design was accurate and appropriate. The study concluded that optimized design could adequately represent the real interdependence of factors chosen (HSEO and radiation) for reductions of fungal growth, DON, and ZEA content. The present study suggests that combinational treatment of essential oil and radiation could be a novel promising approach for improving the shelf-life and safety of food and feed matrices. As well, study accomplishes that usage of natural antifungal agents with the combination of food-processing techniques is an appropriate and innovative strategy to improve decontamination efficiency of food-processing techniques.
</p>
