<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The application of 
 <italic class="italic">Lemna</italic> spp. as potential aqua-feed ingredients requires continuous production. Sustainable production of this plant requires an understanding of its nutritional and environmental requirements. The nutritional value of a plant also depends on the culture medium. The growth rate of duckweed clones in different natural (Rejmankova, 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1975</xref>) and laboratory (Landolt, 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1957</xref>) conditions varied. Many studies showed the production of 
 <italic class="italic">Lemna</italic> spp. in domestic waste water (Zirschky and Reed, 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1988</xref>), septage-fed ponds (Edwards et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1990</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1992</xref>), and effluent water (Vroon and Weller, 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1995</xref>). The production of 
 <italic class="italic">Lemna</italic> spp. in clean water with a known manuring schedule is required for commercial aqua-feed production. Few studies have been conducted to find the best balance of nutrients that may provide maximum growth of duckweed (FAO, 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1989</xref>), especially for 
 <italic class="italic">Lemna</italic> spp. The requirement to fertilize duckweeds depends on the source of the water. Rainwater collected in ponds may need a balanced NPK application. In Bangladesh, inorganic fertilizers (IFs, urea, triple superphosphate, and potash) were used for the production of duckweeds (DWRP, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1998</xref>). Hassan and Chakrabarti (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>) suggested a wide range of organic waste materials 
 <italic class="italic">viz</italic>. animal manure, kitchen wastes, wastes from a wide range of food processing plants, biogas effluents, etc. for the production of duckweeds. A periodic supply of nutrients helped to avoid nutrient deficiency in the culture systems (Sutton and Ornes, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1975</xref>; Said et al., 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1979</xref>). A direct relationship was found between the crude protein content of duckweed and the nitrogen content of the culture system. Although many species survive at extreme temperature, warm and sunny conditions are preferable for faster growth of the plants (Skillicorn et al., 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1993</xref>). The distribution of various members of duckweed has been influenced by the microclimatic factors such as light intensity, salinity, and regional temperature (Landolt, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1986</xref>). The growth of duckweed is largely a function of environmental temperature and light, nutrient status of the culture medium and the degree of crowding of the plants (Hassan and Chakrabarti, 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>).
</p>
