<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In Cameroon, 
 <italic class="italic">P. capense</italic> is reported to be used for treating cancer [
 <xref rid="B123-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">123</xref>,
 <xref rid="B124-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">124</xref>], while the aerial part of 
 <italic class="italic">P. capense</italic> is traditionally used in Comoro Islands for diarrhea and cough [
 <xref rid="B115-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B125-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">125</xref>]. Other reports have cited the traditional uses of 
 <italic class="italic">P. capense</italic> in the treatment of abdominal pain, diarrhea, and cough [
 <xref rid="B126-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">126</xref>]. An extensive discussion on traditional usages of 
 <italic class="italic">P. capense</italic> can be found on the Useful Tropical Plants Database website [
 <xref rid="B127-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">127</xref>]. According to the author’s report, the fruit is considered to be carminative, diuretic, stimulant and stomachic and vermifuge, and when prepared as infusion can be taken to treat stomach problems, including indigestion, flatulence and colic; heart and kidney problems; and as a cough medicine. Moreover, the leaf preparations are used to treat including abdominal disorders; bilious fever; kwashiorkor; hematuria; bacterial skin infections; epileptic attacks; and polio. On the other hand, the root is said to be anthelmintic, the sweetened root infusion or seed extract is consumed to alleviate cough, the raw or cooked root is eaten as an aphrodisiac tonic while the root is applied to the soles of the feet to treat paralysis of patients suffering from cerebral bleeding. Further, the macerated bark is drunk to treat sore mouth and throat; chest complaints; and venereal diseases, the infused bark is used to treat sterility while the pulverized bark is applied on wounds and against vaginal discharge.
</p>
