<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Furanodienone is a sesquiterpene with a structure characterized by a cyclodecane ring, substituted with two methyl groups and an isopropyl group. It is also considered as a promising anticancer agent. The influence of furanodienone on human breast (MCF-7, MDA-MBA-231, and T47D) cells was investigated by Li et al. Their studies showed marked decrease in cell growth in a dose-dependent manner, by inhibiting estrogen receptor α signals and mRNA expression levels without effecting ER beta. It also blocked 17β-estraiol (E2)-stimulated MCF-7 cell proliferation and E2-stimulated estrogen response element driven plasmid activity and removed E2 targeted gene expression (Cyclin D1, Bcl-2, and c-myelocytomatosis (MYC)) which inhibited cell proliferation with induction of apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B86-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>]. Furanodienone also inhibited signaling pathway of epithelial growth factor (EGFR)/human epithelial growth factor receptor (HER2) of HER 2-overexpression of human breast cells (BT474 and SKBR3) by G1 cell cycle arrest and apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B87-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>]. Recently, Jiang et al. explained that when colorectal carcinoma cells were treated with furanodinone, it induced apoptosis with the help of reactive oxygen species. Furanodinone showed an upregulation of p21cip1 which caused decrease in cyclin D1, cyclin E, cdk4/6, and cdk 2 and this ultimately resulted cell cycle arrest at G0/G1 phase. In addition to this, the activation of ROS was enhanced by N-acetyl cysteine (NAC), increasing the phosphorylation of JNK, p38, and decreased ERK. This is further explained by caspase-dependent intrinsic and extrinsic mitochondrial pathway, stimulated by MAPK which facilitated the reduction of Bcl-2 and increased Bax with induction apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B88-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biomolecules-09-00013-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>d). Therefore, the outcome of these studies conducted on breast and colorectal cancers suggests that furanodinone is an effective anticancer agent.
</p>
