<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">In Sukumaland, North-Western part of Tanzania 
 <italic>ngitili</italic> has been proven as one of the successfully traditional management systems for rangeland management and forestry restoration (Kamwenda 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2002</xref>). The system is farmer-lead Initiatives evolved from traditional grazing management used by pastoralists and agro-pastoralist as drought coping mechanisms. It involve reserving pasture as standing hay during rainy season and allowed for grazing during the peak of dry season when forage resources are scarce. Historically, 
 <italic>ngitili</italic> evolved in 1980s’ as pastoralists’ initiatives in response to acute shortage of forages occurred as a result of increased human population pressure (Barrow and Shah 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>; Selemani et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2013</xref>). These ngitili have been practiced for many years as drought coping strategy among sukuma people before abandoned in 1970s’ as results of ujamaa villagization programme (Pye-Smith 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2010</xref>). Ujamaa villagization scheme forced pastoralists to settle in ujamaa villages and abandon their traditional pastoral practices including ngitili management. Disrupting pastoral systems by increasing sedentarisation drives a population boom which strains the fragile ecosystem. In 1980s’ ngitili practice was revived in response to acute shortage of forage resources (Barrow and Mlenge 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2003</xref>). According to Kamwenda (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2002</xref>) two key powerful institutions are used in management of 
 <italic>ngitili</italic> namely; traditional village guards (
 <italic>sungusungu</italic>) and village assemblies (
 <italic>dagashida</italic>). In 1986, the tradition 
 <italic>ngitili</italic> management was reinforced by the government initiative named “Hifadhi Ardhi Shinyanga” (HASHI), the project funded by Norwegian government (Pye-Smith 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2010</xref>) which enabled restoration of approximately 400,000 ha of 
 <italic>ngitili</italic> by 2002 (Barrow and Shah 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>). In addition to forage improvement and forestry restoration, 
 <italic>ngitili</italic> in Sukuma land plays significant role in soil conservation and reduction of soil erosion.
</p>
