<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-medicines-04-00029" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-medicines-04-00029" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Plant Sample</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The leaf, stem, seed, rhizome, and pod of 
   <span class="italic">A. danielli</span> were collected from mature plants cultivated in Uyo Local Government Area of Akwa Ibom State, Nigeria, in the month of March, 2016. The sample was identified by a taxonomist in the Department of Botany and Ecological Studies, University of Uyo, where the voucher specimen was deposited. The essential oils were obtained by hydro-distillation (4 h) of the fresh plant parts using a Clevenger-type apparatus (Garg Process Glass, India Pvt. Ltd., Mumbai, India) in accordance with the British Pharmacopoeia [
   <a rid="B17-medicines-04-00029" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-medicines-04-00029">17</a>]. The oils were dried over sodium sulfate (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) and stored in refrigeration (4 °C) after the estimation of percentage yield.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-medicines-04-00029" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry (GC-MS)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The volatile oils were subjected to GC-MS analysis on an Agilent system consisting of a model 7890N gas chromatograph, a model mass detector Triple Quad 7000A in electron impact (EI) mode at 70 eV (
   <span class="italic">m</span>/
   <span class="italic">z</span> range 40–600 amu) (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA), and an Agilent ChemStation data system (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA). The GC column (Crawford Scientific Ltd, Scotland, UK) was an HP-5ms fused silica capillary with a (5% phenyl)-methyl polysiloxane stationary phase (30 m × 250 μm × 0.25 μm). The carrier gas was helium with a column head pressure of 9.7853 psi and a flow rate of 1.2 mL/min. Inlet temperature and mass selective detector (MDS) temperature was 250 °C. The GC oven temperature program was used as follows: 50 °C initial temperature, held for 5 min; increased at 6 °C/min to 190 °C for 20 min; increased at 7 °C/min to 290 °C for 15 min; increased at 7 °C/min to 300 °C for 10 min. The sample was dissolved in dichloromethane, and 2 µL was injected (split ratio 10:1; split flow 12 mL/min).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The components were identified by comparison of their mass spectra with NIST 1998 library data of the GC-MS system as well as by comparison of their retention indices (RI) with the relevant literature data [
   <a rid="B18-medicines-04-00029" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-medicines-04-00029">18</a>]. The relative amount of each individual component of the essential oil was expressed as the percentage of the peak area relative to the total peak area. The RI value of each component was determined relative to the retention times of a homologous 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-alkane series with linear interpolation on the HP-5ms column.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-medicines-04-00029" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Antioxidant Activity</div>
  <sec id="sec2dot3dot1-medicines-04-00029" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.1. DPPH Radical Scavenging Activity</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The DPPH free radical scavenging of the 
    <span class="italic">A. danielli</span> essential oils and ascorbic acid prepared in methanol at various concentrations (20–100 µg/mL) were evaluated according to the method of Shekhar and Anju [
    <a rid="B19-medicines-04-00029" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-medicines-04-00029">19</a>]. One millilitre of 0.1 mM DPPH solution in methanol was added to 3 mL the solutions prepared with the oils and standard, and stirred for 1 min. Each mixture was kept in the dark at room temperature for 30 min and the absorbance was recorded against a blank at 517 nm. The assays were carried out in triplicate and the results were expressed as mean values ± standard deviation. Lower absorbance of the reaction mixture indicated higher free radical activity. Percentage scavenging activity was calculated using the expression: 
    <div id="FD1-medicines-04-00029" class="disp-formula">
     <span class="label">(1)</span>
     <div id="mm1" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mo">%</span>
        <span class="mi">Scavenging</span>
        <span class="mtext"> </span>
        <span class="mi">activity</span>
        <span class="mo">=</span>
        <span class="mo"> </span>
        <div class="mfrac">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">Absorbance</span>
          <span class="mtext"> </span>
          <span class="mi">of</span>
          <span class="mtext"> </span>
          <span class="mi">Control</span>
          <span class="mo">−</span>
          <span class="mi">Absorbance</span>
          <span class="mtext"> </span>
          <span class="mi">of</span>
          <span class="mtext"> </span>
          <span class="mi">Sample</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">Absorbance</span>
          <span class="mtext"> </span>
          <span class="mi">of</span>
          <span class="mtext"> </span>
          <span class="mi">Control</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mo"> </span>
        <span class="mo">×</span>
        <span class="mo"> </span>
        <span class="mn">100</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot3dot2-medicines-04-00029" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.2. FRAP Assay</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reducing power of the essential oils was determined according to the method of Oyaizu [
    <a rid="B20-medicines-04-00029" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-medicines-04-00029">20</a>]. Various concentrations (20, 40, 60, 80 and 100 µg/mL) of essential oils and ascorbic acid were mixed with phosphate buffer (2.5 mL, 0.2 M, pH 6.6) and 1% (
    <span class="italic">w</span>/
    <span class="italic">v</span>) of potassium ferricyanide water solution (2.5 mL). The mixture was incubated at 50 °C for 20 min. Aliquots of trichloroacetic acid (2.5 mL, 10%, aqueous solution (
    <span class="italic">w</span>/
    <span class="italic">v</span>)) were added to the mixture and centrifuged at 3000 rpm for 10 min. The supernatant (2.5 mL) was mixed with distilled water (2.5 mL) and a freshly prepared ferric chloride solution (0.5 mL, 0.1% (
    <span class="italic">w</span>/
    <span class="italic">v</span>)). After 30 min of incubation at room temperature in the dark, the absorbance of the solution was measured at 700 nm. The experiment was performed in triplicate and the average absorbance was noted for each measurement. Higher absorbance indicated higher reducing power. The ferric-reducing capacity of the essential oils and standard compound were expressed graphically by plotting the absorbance against concentration.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
