<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cholinesterase refers to the family of enzymes that speed up the hydrolysis of the acetylcholine (ACh) neurotransmitter into choline and acetic acid, a reaction necessary to allow a cholinergic neuron to return to its resting state after activation [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Anticholinesterases or AChE inhibitors inhibit the enzyme cholinesterase from hydrolyzing ACh, increasing both the level and duration of the neurotransmitter action [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Decrease in cholinesterase activities was observed in fishes that were exposed to arsenic only. There is slight difference in cholinesterase inhibition between fishes that were treated with crude extract only and the fishes that were treated with crude extract followed by exposure to arsenic (Figures 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6</xref>
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7"/>–
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">8</xref>). Slight decrease in cholinesterase activity in fishes that were treated with crude extract followed by exposure to arsenic may be due to the effect of arsenic. Several studies reported the effect of arsenic in inhibiting cholinesterase activities. Chandravanshi et al. in an experimental study, reported the ability of arsenic to cause significant decrease in serum acetylcholinesterase activities in in a dose-dependent manner [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. This result is also in agreement with the previous studies that demonstrated a decreased activity of acetylcholinesterase in neuroblastoma cells of mice [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], in arsenic induced rat whole brain [
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], and in two models of fish [
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Increase of cholinesterase activities in fishes treated with crude extract followed by administration of arsenic may be due to the neutralizing effect of the phenolic compounds present in the crude extract. Several bioactive compounds were reported to reverse the effect of cholinesterase reduced activities. Alkaloid is among the phenolic compounds that act by selective, competitive, and rapidly reversible AChE inhibition that interacts with the anionic subsite, as well as with the aromatic gorge [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The compound is also an allosteric ligand at nicotinic cholinergic receptors inducing their modulation. Alkaloid interacts with the nicotinic receptor at binding sites separate from those for ACh and nicotinic agonists and acts specifically to enhance the activity (sensitize) of nicotinic receptors in the presence of ACh [
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].
</p>
