<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It was reported that SBP is rich with cycloartane compounds in high enough levels to produce high antioxidant activity, which resulted in inhibitory activity against yeast α-glucosidase [
 <xref rid="B87-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. In addition to the antioxidant properties shown by inhibition of inflammatory enzymes [
 <xref rid="B87-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>], SBP also decreased the mutagenesis in yeast cells (
 <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B96-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. In the same study, SBP extracts were more effective against gram-positive bacteria than gram-negative bacteria [
 <xref rid="B96-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Furthermore, extracts of SBP demonstrated antibiofilm and antibacterial activities, by inhibiting reduced 
 <italic>S. mutans</italic> growth and adherence [
 <xref rid="B97-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. Another study found that one of the extracted components from SBP is α-mangostin [
 <xref rid="B97-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. The α-mangostin (likely collected from Mangosteen) exhibited a strong antibacterial effect against both gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria, with 
 <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> being the most sensitive [
 <xref rid="B100-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. Similarly, the high concentrations of diterpenic acids in one extract of SBP were associated with cytotoxic activity against 
 <italic>Staphylococcal aureus</italic>, but not against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> or 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> [
 <xref rid="B93-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>,
 <xref rid="B106-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Another study has shown that cinnamoyloxy-mammeisin isolated from SBP has antimicrobial, anti-adherence and anti-biofilm activity against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B85-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>].
</p>
