<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005">
 <label>Table 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Melissopalynologicala analysis of the honey samples.</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>
     <bold>Floral origin</bold>
    </th>
    <th>
     <bold>Quantitative mel</bold>
     <bold>is</bold>
     <bold>s</bold>
     <bold>opaly</bold>
     <bold>nological result of the honey samples</bold>
    </th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <italic>Schefflera abyssinica</italic>
    </td>
    <td>
     <italic>S. abyssinica</italic> honey samples were characterized by the low pollen representation, that range between 25 and 30% with the presence of other species pollen also. But the honey samples were authenticated based on sensorial and physico-chemical analysis and its distinctive harvesting season and regions.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <italic>Eucalyptus globules</italic>
    </td>
    <td>
     <italic>Eucalyptus globules</italic> honey samples were characterized by relatively high pollen content accounting for ≥ 45% of the typical pollen grains of the respective species.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <italic>Guizotia scabra</italic>
    </td>
    <td>
     <italic>G. scabra</italic> honey samples were characterized by predominant ≥ 45% content of the typical 
     <italic>G. scabra</italic> pollen grains.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <italic>Vernonia amygdalina</italic>
    </td>
    <td>
     <italic>V. amygdalina</italic> honey samples were characterized by low pollen representation, that ranges between 25 and 30% of the 
     <italic>V. amygdalina</italic> pollen grains with the presence of other species pollen.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <italic>Croton macrostachyus</italic>
    </td>
    <td>
     <italic>C. macrostachyus</italic> honey samples were characterized by low pollen representation between 25 and 30% with the presence of other species pollen, but the honey samples were authenticated based on sensorial and physicochemical analysis,
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <italic>Becium grandiflorum</italic>
    </td>
    <td>
     <italic>B. grandiflorum</italic> honey samples were characterized by under representation (≤ 25%) of its pollen, because of the flower morphology (long filament that keeps the dehiscence of anther faraway from its nectar location, which limits the direct contamination of the nectar by its pollen. The honey samples were further confirmed based on sensorial and physico-chemical analysis and its distinctive harvesting season and geographical origins.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <italic>Multi-floral honey</italic>
    </td>
    <td>The multi-floral honeys were characterized by the presence of very diverse pollen grains from various cultivated oil crops pulses and annual weeds.</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn>
   <p>*The mono-floral honeys considered in this study, besides their pollen analysis, distinctiveness in geographical location and harvesting seasons, it has been easily differentiated by experts familiar with the honeys, by assessing their peculiar tastes, aroma, color, structure of their crystals.</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
