<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The timing of data acquisition is crucial for aerial photograph analysis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29-sensors-09-04869">29</xref>] since the acquisition is usually made by request; the data may only be useful if collected when the targeted alien plant is distinct from its background and neighboring areas. This issue can be resolved by utilizing multi-spectral high spatial resolution satellite images. Fuller [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30-sensors-09-04869">30</xref>] utilized 4-m multispectral IKONOS imagery (GeoEye, Dulles, Virginia, USA) to map an Australian tree 
 <italic>Melaleuca quinquenervia</italic> in south Florida, USA using a back-propagation neural network classifier. Coupling the classification with a landscape fragmentation analysis technique, he found that the spatial pattern of 
 <italic>Melaleuca</italic> was highly aggregated and regularly shaped comparing to the nearby patches of woody plants, which were likely associated with infrastructural development. However, the analysis pointed out that the 4-m GSI of IKONOS multi-spectral bands was insufficient to identify the alien tree at low cover levels (&lt; 50%). Sanchez-Flores 
 <italic>et al.</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31-sensors-09-04869">31</xref>] used pan-sharpened 1-m IKONOS imagery in concert with a genetic algorithm to predict the existence of African grasses 
 <italic>Schismus arabicus</italic> and 
 <italic>Brassica tournefortii</italic> in the Sonoran Desert of Mexico. Laba 
 <italic>et al.</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32-sensors-09-04869">32</xref>] applied a maximum-likelihood classification on QuickBird, another multi-spectral satellite system (DigitalGlobe, Longmont, Colorado, USA) with even finer spatial resolution (2.4 m), to estimate the presence of multiple alien plants (
 <italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic>, 
 <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> and 
 <italic>Trapa natans</italic>) in diverse tidal wetlands of the Hudson River National Estuarine Research Reserve, USA. They demonstrated that QuickBird was a relatively reliable data source for wetland non-native plant mapping (accuracy assessment ≥ 65%). QuickBird data also proved highly accurate (accuracy assessment ≥ 86%) in delineating an Indian grass 
 <italic>Arundo donax</italic> along a riparian zone in Texas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33-sensors-09-04869">33</xref>].
</p>
