<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Nanofood are those food products in which a nanoparticle or any nanostructured material is used at any stage of food development process (cultivation, production, processing and packaging). In other words, food developed by the addition of a nanomaterial or food that has been cultured, produced, processed or packaged using a nano-technological system is known as “nanofood” [
 <xref rid="B59-bioengineering-06-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. The concept of nanofood is developing day by day, as it has potential to fulfil essential requirements of food products; for example, it can enhance food safety, increase nutritional value, enhance flavour and reduce cost. Nanofood includes additives which help to achieve a longer shelf life, promote health or introduce a variety of new flavours. Antimicrobial agents packed in starch colloid are coated in such a way that if there is any microbial growth on the packed food, the antimicrobial agents will be released [
 <xref rid="B60-bioengineering-06-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. The presence of nano-sensors in food for the detection of pathogens makes the process quick, susceptible and effortless. Some food products also have nano-sized transport systems for the addition of nutrients and supplements, such as antioxidants, vitamins, minerals, flavours, colour and preservatives [
 <xref rid="B59-bioengineering-06-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. The nanocarrier system is added to protect the additives and ingredients during the processing of the food product. However, the Food and Drug Administration (FDA)issued a warning regarding nanofood products, as they have modifications in their physical and chemical properties. These nanofood products differ from the properties of the macroparticles of the same elements and may cause toxicity on interaction with a biological system [
 <xref rid="B61-bioengineering-06-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>]. Some examples of nanofoods are fortified fruit juices (High Vive, USA), NanoSlim beverage, tomato carotenoid in synthetic form, benzoic acid, ascorbic acid, nanoceutical slim shakes (assorted flavours, RBC Lifesciences, Irving, TX, USA), isoflavanones, omega 3 fatty acid, supplements such as vitamins A and E, coenzyme-Q10, lutein, ß-carotene, oat nutritional drinks (assorted flavours, Toddler Health, Los Angeles, CA, USA) and many more [
 <xref rid="B59-bioengineering-06-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. A listing of nano-related food and beverages are provided by the Nanotech Project in its Nanotechnology Consumer Products Inventory (
 <xref rid="bioengineering-06-00026-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>).
</p>
