<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Some synthetic insecticides can kill nontarget organisms, such as aquatic species, parasitoid, pollinator, and predator insects, besides soil decomposers.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr1-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr2-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
  <xref rid="bibr3-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
  <xref rid="bibr4-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr5-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>
 </sup> Some natural insecticides are as effective as synthetics in pest control and more selective in terms of mortality to nontargets.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr6-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr7-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
  <xref rid="bibr8-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr9-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup> Commercial insecticides, based on plant compounds, generally have natural or synthetic synergistics in their formulation, such as lead (II) oxide (or lead monoxide). This is an inorganic with the molecular formula PbO
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr10-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup> and component of some botanicals, such as Schultz Insecticide, Houseplant &amp; Indoor Garden Insect Spray.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr11-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup> This product, with a broad-spectrum action, is recommended to control pests on plants in indoor and outdoor environments, including edible vegetables.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr12-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup> The mortality of the cabbage looper, 
 <italic class="italic">Trichoplusia ni</italic> Hübner (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) caterpillars treated by topical application was 4 times higher with PbO at 0.20% + pyrethrin at 0.02% than with pyrethrin at 0.02% alone.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr12-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup> The high mortality of cabbage looper caterpillars by insecticides with PbO is attributed to the inhibition activity of this synergist on the detoxifying enzymes of this pest, including cytochrome P450 monooxygenases (CYP).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr13-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
