<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">However, the global distribution pattern of CVD incidence varies considerably between individual countries, and local dietary habits may play a role in this heterogeneity. Numerous observational cohort studies indicate that plant-derived dietary patterns strongly correlate with lower CVD incidence and mortality (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>–
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>). In particular, the incidence of cardiovascular problems in European Mediterranean countries is relatively low (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>). A considerable amount of data supports the evidence that by inhibiting oxidative stress, a Mediterranean diet potentially helps to prevent and treat CVD (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>). The Mediterranean dietary pattern is abundant in olive oil, vegetables, fruit, red wine, nuts, seeds, legumes, but is low in red meat and dairy products. This diet is likely to be cardioprotective because of its high concentration of bioactive compounds, including unsaturated fatty acids, polyphenols, fiber, phytosterols, vitamins, and minerals that exhibit potent anti-inflammatory, anti-oxidant and anti-thrombotic effects alleviating endothelial dysfunction, atherosclerosis, and, in turn, CVD (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>). The foremost benefits of the Mediterranean diet have been traditionally attributed to its olive oil content (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>). In that regard, clinical and experimental evidence suggests that the impact from metabolic cardiovascular risk factors, such as hypertension, dyslipidaemia, hyperglycaemia/insulin resistance, and/or overweight/obesity can be diminished by the regular consumption of bioactive compounds and sources of natural antioxidants, including olive oil (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>). Moreover, recent studies have demonstrated that regular olive oil consumption shows similar or even more powerful anti-hypertensive, lipid-lowering, hypoglycaemic, anti-thrombotic, and anti-inflammatory effects compared to accessible pharmacological therapies (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>). These findings indicated that timely dietary correction and regular olive oil intake can contribute to the prevention of CVD and premature cardiovascular deaths.
</p>
