<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The extraction of feijoa essential oil was optimized using SD and HD and the volatile and aroma active compounds the essential oils from four New Zealand grown cultivars were characterized by GC-MS and HS-SPME-GC-O-MS, and aroma profiles of feijoa essential oils, with a comparison of the four cultivars, were established. HD, with a material to water ratio of 1:4 and an extraction time of 90 min, was the optimized extraction method for feijoa essential oil. The Wiki Tu cultivar produced the highest essential oil yield among the four selected cultivars, which could potentially be applied in commercial feijoa essential oil production. A total of 160 compounds were detected, among which 90 compounds, novel to feijoa essential oils, were reported. Significant differences were observed in the concentrations of the detected compounds, as well as the aroma intensity of the aroma active compounds, both of which could potentially serve as bio-markers to differentiate feijoa cultivars. PCA results revealed that the essential oils from the Opal Star and Unique cultivars varied from the Wiki Tu and Apollo essential oils, with regards to their correlations to aroma active compounds. Terpenes and esters were dominant compounds in feijoa essential oil composition and were also major contributors to feijoa essential oil aroma. Five aroma attributes, ‘fruity and honey-like’, ‘herbal and woody’, ‘sweet and floral’, ‘metallic and pungent’, and ‘grassy and minty’, were selected to generate the aroma profile of feijoa essential oils, among which, the ‘fruity and honey-like’ note had the largest impact on the overall aroma of feijoa essential oils. Among the four essential oils, differences were observed in the strength of each aroma attribute. This study is the first to provide evidence on the yield of essential oils, compositional difference, and aroma profile diversity of feijoa essential oils from different cultivars. However, further exploration would be required to reveal the unknown compounds detected in the essential oils and additional feijoa cultivars could be tested for commercial production of essential oils.</p>
