<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">
 <italic>Sphagneticola trilobata</italic> (L.) Pruski (Asteraceae), a creeping perennial herb, is native to South America. In the 1970s, 
 <italic>S. trilobata</italic> was introduced into China as a groundcover plant and quickly escaped into the wild. Now it has become the most common weed in southern China, crowding out native plant 
 <italic>Sphagneticola calendulacea</italic> (L.) Pruski and forming a single excellent community
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>S. trilobata</italic> has been recognized as one of the 100 most harmful invasive species in the world
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. At present, there is a broad understanding of the invasion biology of exotic plants, indicating that the factors affecting plant invasion mainly include the invasiveness of communities of exotic plants and their native congeners
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. Various factors in an ecosystem may affect the productivity of native and invasive species, including changes in the external environment
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>, the inherent biodiversity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>, and competitive intra- and interspecies relationships
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>, such as rapid reproduction capacity, extensive ecological adaptability and strong allelopathy. However, research on these characteristics has mainly focused on leaves
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup>. As the most important organs for photosynthesis, leaves are sensitive to changes in the external environment during evolution
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. Previous studies have shown that the leaves of 
 <italic>S. trilobata</italic> have a higher CO
 <sub>2</sub> fixation capacity, wider photosynthetic effective radiation range and higher light quantum utilization efficiency than 
 <italic>S. calendulacea</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. The construction cost of its leaves is significantly lower than that of 
 <italic>S. calendulacea</italic>, but its distribution is easily limited by water
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. These results indicate that photosynthesis is of great significance in the successful invasion of 
 <italic>S. trilobata</italic>. However, research on the invasion mechanisms of 
 <italic>S. trilobata</italic> mainly focuses on the physiological and ecological aspects of leaves, while research at the photosynthetic transcriptional level is rarely reported
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
