<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Positive effects of proteolytic enzymes have been claimed in several studies. Papadopoulos (
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1986</xref>) reported positive effect on IVPD of proteolytic enzyme treatment (Maxatase, Gist-Brodcades NV, Delft) of feathers hydrolyzed by pressure-thermic treatment. However, adding NH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> to maintain pH at 8.5 may have confounded the effects of the enzyme in that study. Mokrejs et al. (
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>) found that increasing enzyme (Savinase, EC 3.4.21. 62, Ultra 16 L, Novozymes A/S Bagsvaerd, Denmark) concentration from 1 to 5% in a 2-stage hydrolysis of degreased feathers, using 0.3% potassium hydroxide and enzyme treatment (62°C for 4 h), increased feather solubilization from about 705 to 785 g/kg. Kim et al. (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>) found that INSTA-PRO enzyme (INSTA-PRO International, Des Moines, IA 50,322) treatment for 24 h after NaOH treatment (1.0 N for 2 h at 37°C) increased N solubility, but not IVPD. This enzyme product includes 
 <italic class="italic">B. subtilis</italic> fermentation extract and Na
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>SO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> that may both have contributed to the observed solubilization. In other studies, supernatants from keratinolytic bacteria or bacteria cultures have been used, which may contain mixture of several enzymes. Grazziotin et al. (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>) used supernatants or whole culture of the keratinolytic bacterium 
 <italic class="italic">Vibrio</italic> sp. strain kr2 to hydrolyze autoclaved and hammer milled feathers. After cultivation, the whole culture and the supernatants were autoclaved. Supernatant culture hydrolysate (985 g/kg) had higher IVPD than whole culture hydrolysate (834 g/kg) and a commercial feather meal (578 g/kg). It is not clear if the autoclaving after cultivation had a confounding effect on digestibility. Tiwary and Gupta (
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) studied the effects of different enzyme concentrations produced by 
 <italic class="italic">B. licheniformis</italic> ER-15 on solubilization and IVPD of pressure-thermic treated chicken feathers. Increasing the enzyme concentration to 20 μkat degraded the feathers completely within 12 h (at 50°C, pH = 8), but IVPD increased only from 670 to 734 g/kg of protein. In summary, these studies show varying effects of keratinolytic enzymes.
</p>
