<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Under the same population densities of 
 <italic>A. sinensis</italic>, more leaves of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> were consumed than 
 <italic>A. sessilis</italic>. Therefore, more leaf biomass (hence the population biomass) and a larger leaf area for photosynthesis were reduced when compared to 
 <italic>A. sessilis</italic>. Furthermore, Zangerl et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0083619-Zangerl1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> proposed that the indirect impact of reduced photosynthesis (due to herbivory pressure) on the loss of plant population biomass was greater than the direct impact of herbivores on the loss of biomass. This study found that caterpillar feeding remarkably decreased photosynthesis of the remaining, intact leaf tissue, as measured by both gas exchange and fluorescence imaging. Consistent with previous studies 
 <xref rid="pone.0083619-Zangerl1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0083619-Marlina1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, we also found that compared with controls, P
 <sub>max</sub> of the remaining, intact leaves of the two species decreased significantly. However, Fv/Fm of the remaining, intact leaves decreased significantly only in 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>. Moreover, our data reveal that the photosynthetic capacity of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> was more intensely suppressed than that of 
 <italic>A. sessilis</italic> in the presence of the grasshopper, which may explain why the population biomass of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> was reduced more than 
 <italic>A. sessilis</italic> when herbivores were present. The leaf N concentration of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> decreased significantly at severe herbivore load, but leaf N concentration of 
 <italic>A. sessilis</italic> was not affected by herbivory. Because proteins participate in the Calvin cycle and represent the majority of the leaf nitrogen content, leaf photosynthesis correlates positively with protein content, hence the leaf nitrogen content 
 <xref rid="pone.0083619-Evans1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Although lower nitrogen concentrations can decrease photosynthetic ability and relative growth rate, it is also associated with low palatability and has been suggested as one anti-herbivore strategy for plants 
 <xref rid="pone.0083619-Feeny1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0083619-Goecker1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>.
</p>
