<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec5-ijms-19-00686" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5. Valuable Properties of Other Plant Polyphenols</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Except from the European olive, known as 
  <span class="italic">Olea europea</span>, there are many other plants rich in invaluable polyphenols. Epigallocatechin and genistein, present in tea and soy, contribute to the DNA hypomethylation, and thus reactivation of the previously suppressed suppressor genes such as 
  <span class="italic">p16</span>, 
  <span class="italic">RARbeta</span>, 
  <span class="italic">MGMT</span>, resulting in the inhibition of cancer induction or growth [
  <a rid="B103-ijms-19-00686" ref-type="bibr" href="#B103-ijms-19-00686">103</a>]. Anthocyanins of black raspberries decrease DNA methyltransferase (DNMT1) activity, and also lead to the activation of the suppressor genes via promoter demethylation mechanism [
  <a rid="B104-ijms-19-00686" ref-type="bibr" href="#B104-ijms-19-00686">104</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other kinds of polyphenols, also classified as phytoestrogens, such as resveratrol and genistein, interact with estrogen receptors and influence the regulation of estrogen-dependent gene expression of 
  <span class="italic">P21</span> gene [
  <a rid="B105-ijms-19-00686" ref-type="bibr" href="#B105-ijms-19-00686">105</a>,
  <a rid="B106-ijms-19-00686" ref-type="bibr" href="#B106-ijms-19-00686">106</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Resveratrol, as observed in animal models with chemically induced tumor lesions, showed anti-tumor and anti-atherogenic properties. On the other hand, in human tumor cell line models, resveratrol inhibited cell proliferation (cell cycle blockage) with no apoptosis induction [
  <a rid="B107-ijms-19-00686" ref-type="bibr" href="#B107-ijms-19-00686">107</a>]. The hydroxytyrosol-rich extracts that are available from different plants induce inhibition of breast cancer cell growth [
  <a rid="B108-ijms-19-00686" ref-type="bibr" href="#B108-ijms-19-00686">108</a>]. Interestingly, many studies reported ginger (
  <span class="italic">Zingiber officinale Roscoe</span>) to contain numerous chemical constituents of potential health benefits. According to some, pulp and peel of ginger rhizomes exhibit in vitro antiproliferative activity against colon cancer cells. They also show anti-inflammatory properties due to inhibition of cellular nitric oxide production. The anticancer activity of ginger rhizome against colorectal carcinoma is attributed to the main compound of the extract—α-zingiberene and its derivatives [
  <a rid="B109-ijms-19-00686" ref-type="bibr" href="#B109-ijms-19-00686">109</a>]. In addition to that, 6-shogaol, another phenolic constituent of ginger, decreased metastatic potential of lung and breast cancer in mice. Studies confirm that 6-shogaol exerts significant anticancer activity both in vivo and in vitro, and at present is concerned as an efficacious immunotherapeutic agent for cancer treatment [
  <a rid="B110-ijms-19-00686" ref-type="bibr" href="#B110-ijms-19-00686">110</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other noteworthy polyphenols are chlorogenic and caffeic acids that are found in coffee and other plants. They are both powerful antioxidants as observed in vitro and they effectively inhibit 
  <span class="italic">N</span>-nitrosation reaction, as observed in vivo. Furthermore, chlorogenic acid can inhibit DNA damage as observed in vitro since it inhibits lipid peroxidation and suppresses reactive oxygen species-mediated nuclear factor NF-κB [
  <a rid="B111-ijms-19-00686" ref-type="bibr" href="#B111-ijms-19-00686">111</a>,
  <a rid="B112-ijms-19-00686" ref-type="bibr" href="#B112-ijms-19-00686">112</a>,
  <a rid="B113-ijms-19-00686" ref-type="bibr" href="#B113-ijms-19-00686">113</a>]. Interestingly, recent studies have demonstrated a reciprocal relationship between coffee intake and the risk of colon, liver, breast, or endometrial cancer. It was found that the consumption of at least one cup of coffee per day lowered the risk of upper gastrointestinal cancer in the Japanese population by 49% [
  <a rid="B111-ijms-19-00686" ref-type="bibr" href="#B111-ijms-19-00686">111</a>,
  <a rid="B114-ijms-19-00686" ref-type="bibr" href="#B114-ijms-19-00686">114</a>]. There are, without doubt, plants containing numerous chemicals invaluable for human health that are still waiting to be discovered. 
 </p>
</sec>
