<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We target optimising reactive eradication of small-scale outbreaks of an invading plant pathogen [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] occurring in regions extending from 1-10km. We concentrate on how cryptic infection (i.e. infectivity without symptoms), the inherent stochasticity of epidemics, and uncertainties in the parameters controlling disease spread affect the performance of control via local removal of plant hosts in the vicinity of detected infection. Effectively controlling in this fashion is extremely challenging, requiring an estimate of how far the epidemic has spread ahead of visibly infected regions. Nevertheless, recent modelling studies of a number of plant pathogens have shown how, in principle, control by local removal of susceptible hosts can be effective in managing plant disease [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], even when disease spreads non-locally via complex contact networks [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. A consensus has begun to emerge that this type of control can be successful, albeit with the beguilingly simple proviso that there is a need to “match the scale of control with the intrinsic scale of the epidemic” [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The obvious problem is that the appropriate scale is very difficult to define, and depends in a complex fashion on the interplay between the epidemiology of the plant-pathogen interaction, the spatial distribution of susceptible hosts, the implementation and logistics of detection and control, and the current state of the epidemic. The quantitative detail of how these factors affect the nature of the optimal control strategy and how effectively it performs is extremely complex, and general principles remain ill-understood. However, identifying such general principles is clearly relevant to the control of all plant diseases.
</p>
