<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the issues we investigate are generic, we illustrate our work in the context of an economically important system for which eradication by reactive culling was attempted: citrus canker (caused by the bacterium 
 <italic>Xanthomonas citri</italic> pv. 
 <italic>citri</italic>) on commercial and residential citrus in Florida. The United States government spent over one billion dollars on survey, control and compensation costs during an eradication campaign that ran from 1996 to 2006 [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] (see 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Text</xref> for further details). Aside from the attraction of choosing a prominent and controversial real-world example to frame our analyses, a major motivation for using this system as our case-study is an extremely detailed data set on disease spread in five uncontrolled sites in the Miami region, originally collected by the United States Department of Agriculture [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. These data have allowed parsimonious, stochastic, spatially-explicit, epidemiological models to be fitted to the spread of citrus canker that track the disease status of individual host plants [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], and here we use a flexible extension of these models to analyse the effectiveness of the control scenarios we consider. We also take advantage of recent work fitting this type of model to huanglongbing disease (also known as HLB or citrus greening) [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004211.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], a disease of citrus vectored by psyllids and that is caused by 
 <italic>Candidatus</italic> Liberibacter spp. bacteria, in order to demonstrate the flexibility of our methods and the generality of the underlying principles.
</p>
