<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Solvent methanol/water (1:5, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) was selected as the stationary phase for polarity-stepwise elution CCC, while five mobile phases were selected to sequentially elute the compounds from the extract with polarities from low to high, including solvents 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane/ethyl acetate (3:5, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>), 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane/ethyl acetate (2:5, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>), 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane/ethyl acetate (1:5, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>), ethyl acetate, and ethyl acetate/
 <italic>n</italic>-butanol (4:1, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>). The selection of the polarity gradient solvent systems mainly depended on the suitable partition coefficients (
 <italic>K</italic> value) and settling times the solvent systems offered. The 
 <italic>K</italic> values were calculated as previously described [
 <xref rid="B59-molecules-26-00224" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Each solvent system was paired with equal volumes of solvent methanol/water (1:5, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) and individual 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane/ethyl acetate (3:5, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>), 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane/ethyl acetate (2:5, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>), 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane/ethyl acetate (1:5, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>), ethyl acetate, and ethyl acetate/
 <italic>n</italic>-butanol (4:1, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) was partitioned to the upper layer and lower layer. Then, a proper amount of sample (1–2 mg, in 1.5 mL tube) was dissolved by equal volumes of the upper and lower phases (each 500 µL) assisted by vortex mixing. After settling, the upper layer and lower layer sample solutions were individually separated (each 200 µL) and then evaporated to dryness by nitrogen gas. Then, the residue was re-dissolved using 200 µL of methanol and subjected to HPLC assay. The 
 <italic>K</italic> value was calculated as 
 <italic>K</italic> = 
 <italic>A
  <sub>upper</sub>
 </italic>/
 <italic>A
  <sub>lower</sub>
 </italic>, where 
 <italic>A
  <sub>upper</sub>
 </italic> and 
 <italic>A
  <sub>lower</sub>
 </italic> were the HPLC peak areas of the compound tested in the upper and lower layers, respectively.
</p>
