<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Kaempferol is a flavonoid naturally occurring in green leafy vegetables such as spinach, kale, and herbs, dills, chives, tarragon, wild leeks, and ramps (
 <xref rid="ijms-22-04180-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B68-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. It has been found to be a weak SIRT6 activator in immunoblotting assay, whereas it was identified as a potent activator in the fluorogenic-based assay. A pharmacophore modeling revealed that kaempferol activates SIRT6 by binding to the SIRT6-specific acyl binding channel [
 <xref rid="B61-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. To determine the influence of kaempferol on the deacetylation activity of SIRT6, H3 peptide sequence was used as a substrate that simulated the biological deacetylation site of H3K56 in a fluorogenic assay. In contrast, core histone with full-length H3 peptide has been employed as a substrate in an immunoblotting assay. Therefore, the deacetylation activity of SIRT6 is substrate specific [
 <xref rid="B13-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Several studies have reported on the different biological activities of kaempferol such as neuroprotective, antioxidant, anticancer, anti-inflammatory, and antidiabetic activity. Antioxidant capacity of kaempferol attributes to its ROS scavenging potential [
 <xref rid="B69-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Neuroprotective effect in AD involves induction of anti-apoptotic activity in Aβ-induced SH-SY5Y neuronal cells [
 <xref rid="B70-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Scavenging superoxide anions and hydroxyl radicals decreased peroxynitrile levels; inhibition of xanthine oxidase are responsible for its antioxidant effect [
 <xref rid="B69-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Kaempferol exerts its anticancer effect through apoptosis, cell cycle arrest at the G2/M phase, downregulation of epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT)-related markers, and phosphoinositide 3-kinase/protein kinase B signaling pathways [
 <xref rid="B69-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Kaempferol has also been reported to produce anti-inflammatory action by inhibiting the activity of of NF-κB and activator protein-1 (AP-1), and reducing gene expression of TNF-α, IL-1, and IL-8inhibiting activity as well [
 <xref rid="B68-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].
</p>
