<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We must, therefore, look at less direct sources of evidence to evaluate the potential longevity of 
 <italic>G. tinctoria</italic> seeds. 
 <italic>G. tinctoria</italic> seeds are very small and spherical (1–1.5 mm diameter) (Williams et al. 
 <xref rid="b58" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Gioria and Osborne 
 <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). It has been observed that small-seeded families generally have the highest proportion of long-term seed persistence records (Thompson et al. 
 <xref rid="b50" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>), and small, nearly spherical seeds tend to be the most persistent of all (Bakker et al. 
 <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Schwienbacher et al. 
 <xref rid="b46" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Viable 
 <italic>G. tinctoria</italic> seeds have been found buried deep in soils, down to 20 cm, at many locations with different soil types and conditions (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1</xref>; see also Hickey 
 <xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Based on 
 <sup>210</sup>Pb and 
 <sup>137</sup>Cs dating, the soil at these depths has been estimated to be nearly a century old and consistent with records for the earliest occurrence of naturalized material (Gioria and Osborne 
 <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). A previous study carried out in the same area showed that 
 <italic>G. tinctoria</italic> seeds found in deep soils are highly viable (up to 68% viability) (Hickey 
 <xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). The patterns of 
 <sup>210</sup>Pb and 
 <sup>137</sup>Cs distribution in soils from Sraheens also indicate that the soil is largely undisturbed. Because seed movement in soil is slow (Bekker et al. 
 <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>), it is generally true that deeper seeds are older, except in severely disturbed soils (Harper 
 <xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">1977</xref>; Leck et al. 
 <xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>; Thompson et al. 
 <xref rid="b50" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>; Espinar et al. 
 <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). There is also a strong correlation between species where viable seeds are found at some depth in the soil and extended seed longevity (Baker 
 <xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>; Thompson et al. 
 <xref rid="b50" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>; Bekker et al. 
 <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>). 
 <italic>G. tinctoria</italic> also produces large persistent seed banks (Gioria and Osborne 
 <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), which would not be possible if its seeds were not relatively long-lived.
</p>
