<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Regarding the different chemical profile, compared to the one previously described, most of the essential oils of the genus 
 <italic>Clinopodium</italic> present in the literature can be divided into three main categories: (i) EOs based on oxygenated monoterpenoids, (ii) EOs based on sesquiterpenes and sesquiterpenoids, and (iii) EOs based on both classes of metabolites. The first group is absolutely dominant, and it can be considered typical for the composition of 
 <italic>Clinopodium</italic> essential oils. It is characterized by a fresh and minty aroma, sometimes phenolic. Pulegone, isopulegone, piperitone, piperitenone, piperitenone oxide, menthone, isomenthone and menthol are the main constituents. 1,8-Cineole, menthofuran, carvacrol, thymol, linalool and their derivatives can also seldom be found [
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. The second group is decidedly less common, and includes species like 
 <italic>Clinopodium umbrosum</italic> (M.Bieb.) Kuntze and 
 <italic>Clinopodium gracile</italic> (Benth) Matsum, whose EO major components are (
 <italic>E</italic>)-
 <italic>β</italic>-caryophyllene, germacrene D, spathulenol, 
 <italic>β</italic>-elemene, 
 <italic>α</italic>-bergamotene and 
 <italic>cis</italic>-
 <italic>β</italic>-farnesene, among others [
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The third type of EO is very rare and it is characterized by the presence of major compounds of both monoterpene and sesquiterpene. This is the case for 
 <italic>Clinopodium chinense</italic> (Benth.) Kuntze, whose volatile fraction contains, most prevalently, piperitone, (
 <italic>E</italic>)-
 <italic>β</italic>-caryophyllene and spathulenol [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. According to this classification, the chemical composition of the volatile fraction described in this study clearly fits with the second EO profile, since (
 <italic>E</italic>)-
 <italic>β</italic>-caryophyllene (17.8–14.5%), 
 <italic>α</italic>-copaene (10.5–8.0%), 
 <italic>β</italic>-bourbonene (9.9–8.2%), 
 <italic>δ</italic>-cadinene (6.6–5.4%), 
 <italic>cis</italic>-cadina-1(6),4-diene (6.4–0.2%) and germacrene D (4.9–4.9%) are the most abundant constituents. Nevertheless, the EO described in 2018 for 
 <italic>C. taxifolium</italic> belongs to the first group [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Therefore, two quite different chemical profiles of 
 <italic>C. taxifolium</italic> EO can be hypothesized, with the one described here probably being rarer.
</p>
