<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemical compositions of the essential oil</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The light yellow essential oil was obtained by hydrodistillation of dried 
  <span class="italic">C. rotundus</span> rhizomes with a yield of 0.83% (v/w). The chemical compositions of essential oil were analyzed by GC-MS and the result was presented in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="t1" href="#t1">Table 1</a>. In total, 30 components were identified, representing 94.7% of the total amount. The α-cyperone (38.46%), cyperene (12.84%) and α-selinene (11.66%) was found to be the major components in the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">C. rotundus</span> rhizomes, followed by β-caryophyllene oxide (4.33%), (d)-limonene (3.62%), α-calacorene (3.14%), and γ-muurolene (3.13%), besides, other components (0.13–1.58%) were found to be lower content in the essential oil in the present study (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="t1" href="#t1">Table 1</a>). The profile obtained in the present study was very similar to the previous results reported by Liu 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. who found that α-cyperone (29.38%), cyperene (13.97%), caryophyllene oxide (6.71%) and β-selinene (6.47%) were the major compounds in the essential oil from Zhejiang province in China
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>. Aghassi 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. reported that cyperene (37.9%) and cyperotundone (11.2%) were the major components from oil of 
  <span class="italic">C. rotundus</span> grown in Iran
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">16</a>. The rhizome oils of 
  <span class="italic">C. rotundus</span> from Tunisia were reported to have cyperotundone (19.7%), cyperene (15.2%), mustakone (5.8%), caryophyllene oxide (2.6%), rotundene (3.6%) and eudesma 5-en-11-α-ol (2.6%)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" href="#b18">18</a>. Lawal and Oyedeji reported that there was an obvious difference in components of essential oil between two different locations both in the Kwa-Zulu Natal Province of South Africa
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" href="#b15">15</a>. These differences in components and its content of essential oil from 
  <span class="italic">C. rotundus</span> rhizome may be concerned in the chemotypes
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" href="#b15">15</a>, geographical region
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">16</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">23</a>, extracts methods
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">24</a> and analysis methods
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" href="#b6">6</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" href="#b17">17</a> of essential oil. According to previous research results that the volatile compounds of 
  <span class="italic">C. rotundus</span> has been divided into four types four chemotypes (H-, K-, M-, O-types)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" href="#b15">15</a>, the essential oil in the present study should belong to the M-type because it mainly contained α-cyperone, cyperene, caryophyllene oxide, and β-selinene.
 </p>
</sec>
