<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Three features of these enhanced secondary metabolites became prominent. First, the molecular structure of the secondary metabolites dictated the biological effect based on the number and sites of the phenolic hydroxyl groups in flavonoids. Flavonoids are a series of compounds containing two benzene rings connected by 3 carbon atoms, and phenolic hydroxyls are a regular moiety on them, as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0238927.g006">Fig 6</xref>. It has been proven that the number of hydroxyl groups on the B ring directly impacts the activity, which is also markedly enhanced when a double bond is introduced into the C ring [
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The hydroxyl group at positions C-5 and C-7 together in the A ring, as well as the C-3', C-4' and C-5' sites on the B ring, can all increase the activities obviously [
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. A hydroxyl group can also be located in another position, such as C-6 [
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. It has been proven that baicalein is 2~5 times more antibiotically active than baicalin and 1~3 times better than baicalin at inhibiting IL-1β and converting enzymes [
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Second, except for baicalin and wogonoside, the other flavonoids were free flavonoids without sugar moieties. The biosynthesis of flavonoids is performed in the endoplasmic reticulum, and it is difficult for flavonoid glycosides with hydrophilic sugar moieties to freely pass through biomembranes with a lipophilic phospholipid bilayer. The biomembranes of animals and plants are the same; therefore, the biological effect of glycosides would be limited in animals and plants unless the sugar moieties were removed. A study showed that the activities of flavanone disappear when a sugar moiety is introduced into the A ring [
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and another study showed that baicalein is more than 7 times more bioavailable than baicalin due to hydrophilic variations [
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Flavonoid glycosides therefore are regarded as superfluous flavonoids; when required, they work mainly after their conversion into free flavonoids [
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Third, the contents of some components with methoxy groups increased under high levels of ROS. The methoxy groups on flavonoids have the ability to donate electrons and exhibit a weak antioxidant capacity in their natural state, but their power is remarkably enhanced with the help of peroxidase (POD) [
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The activity and biosynthesis of POD, an adversity-resistant antioxidase, are induced by ecological stress. Only when the POD activity was high under stress can the components with methoxy groups exert a strong power. These components are usually located at the downstream or terminus of biosynthesised flavonoids and are stable. Therefore, the activities of the components with methoxy groups constantly changed due to ROS formed from ecological stress.
</p>
