<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to the existing reports, it can be seen that there are other chemical components in TDG, among which polysaccharide is regarded as necessary active one because of its various biological activities. 
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">Rao et al. (2016)</xref> determine the contents of fucose, rhamnose, arabinose, mannose, glucose, and galactose in the polysaccharide by ion chromatography. And 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">Shao et al. (2011)</xref> use response surface methodology to optimize the extraction process of polysaccharides from three different factors of TDG from. These studies have laid the foundation for the subsequent research on polysaccharides from TDG. In addition to polysaccharides, 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Fu et al. (2012)</xref> conduct inductively coupled plasma optical emission spectrometry (ICP-OES) research and find that there are many trace elements in TDG, and the higher contents are Mg, Fe, Mn, Zn and Ba, and so on, in turn. In the follow-up studies, they discover selenium (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Fu J. et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Cai et al. (2013)</xref> result in the existence of amino acids and cardiac glycosides through the characteristic identification reaction, but there are few related researches. Besides, there are other substances in TDG, for example, mannitol (92), emodin (93), emodin-8-O-β-D-glucopyranoside (94), physcione-8-O-β-D-glucopyranoside (95), 4-hydroxy-3-methoxybenzaldehyde (96), 5-hydroxymethyl furfural (97) (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">Liu, 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr">Zeng, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Ding et al., 2015b</xref>). With the continuous development of science and technology, 
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al. (2015)</xref> extracts a new phenolic glycoside from TDG tuber, designs it as hemsleyanumoide (98), and determines its specific structure through various methods. 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al. (2018)</xref> first discover a new polyunsaturated fatty acid glyceride in TDG, namely (9R)-Hydroxy-(10 E, 12Z, 15Z)-octadecatrienoic-2, 3-dihydroxypropyl ester (99). Separation of the EtOAc-soluble fraction of the methanolic extract of the aerial parts of TDG result in the isolation of ten alkaloids. Then, 
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. (2018a)</xref> also discover that with the spectral data in the current literature, and the alkaloids are identified as indole (100), indole-3-carboxylic acid (101), indole-3-propanoic acid (102), 5-hydroxy-indole-3-carboxaldehyde (103), 5-hydroxy-indole-3-carboxylic acid (104), 6-hydroxy-3,4-dihydro-1-oxo-β-carboline (105), hippophamide (106), 4-hydroxycinnamide (107), pyrrole-3-propanoic acid (108) and S-(-)-trolline (109). In addition, three new compounds are isolated from the ethyl acetate fraction of the 90% EtOH extract of TDG aerial parts, which are 1-O-trans-p-hydroxycinnamoyl-2’-O-trans-caffeoyl gentiobiose (110), 2S-hydroxy-4-(4-hydroxy-phenethoxy)-4-oxobutanoic acid (111), and (3R, 4S, 5R) -3, 4-dihydroxy-5-((R) -1-hydroxyeicosyl) dihydrofuran-2 (3H)-one (112). Their structures are elucidated by UV, IR, one- and two-dimensional nuclear magnetic resonance, high-resolution mass spectrometry data, and other methods. The preliminary researches have shown that compounds (110, 111) have a weak inhibitory activity against soluble epoxide hydrolase, while compound (112) shows moderate cytotoxicity against the HCT116 cell line (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018b</xref>) (structure can be seen in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">
  <bold>Figure 6</bold>
 </xref> and the names of the compounds are listed in 
 <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">
  <bold>Table 5</bold>
 </xref>).
</p>
