<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Protein fractions were extracted from defatted locust meal (DLM) using an adapted alkali isoelectric precipitation method outlined by Amza [
 <xref rid="B27-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] and Tirgar et al. [
 <xref rid="B28-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="insects-09-00020-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref> below shows a basic schematic diagram of the various fractions extracted. DLM (11 g) was mixed with deionized water (EMD Millipore Corporation, Milli-Q Advantage A10 Water System, Merck, Billerica, MA, USA) at 5% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) and stirred using an overhead stirrer (IKA, RW20, Total Lab Systems, Auckland, New Zealand). The pH was adjusted to 10.0 [
 <xref rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] using 1 M NaOH (VWR International, LLC, Global Science Ltd.,Auckland, New Zealand) and stirred at 900 rpm for 1.5 h. The solution was centrifuged at 15,300 g for 30 min at 4 °C (Beckman JA-14 M/E, Beckman Coulter Ltd., Palo Alto, CA, USA). This was repeated once more, ultimately forming two fractions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="insects-09-00020-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>); solid residue referred to as the insoluble locust fraction (ILF), and the upper liquid layer (pooled supernatant). The supernatant’s pH was adjusted to 4.0 using 1 M HCl and stirred at 900 rpm for 1 h. pH 4 and 10 were chosen following similar methods conducted by Bußler et al. [
 <xref rid="B15-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. After centrifugation at the same conditions as above, the residual precipitated protein was re-suspended twice in acidified water (pH 4) and centrifuged at similar conditions for 30 min. This formed two fractions; precipitated locust protein referred to as soluble locust fraction (SLF) and the supernatant fraction (SF). SLF was adjusted to pH 7 using 1 M NaOH. The resulting three fractions; ILF, SLF and SF, were freeze dried and stored in a desiccator at room temperature for further analysis. Protein and fat contents were identified using the same methods as proximate analysis. Yield of each fraction is based on dry weight basis compared to total initial weight. Results are also presented as a percentage of protein recovery in which the protein content of each fraction is divided by the initial total protein content of the sample tested (after defatting).
</p>
