<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HSV is a member of Herpesviridae, which is a large family of enveloped double-stranded DNA viruses that causes diseases in both human and animals [
 <xref rid="B104-molecules-25-04878" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. Even though Herpesviridae viruses vary in tissue tropism and host interaction mechanisms, they have a much-conserved tool by which they replicate their DNA in infection. Among the members of this family, HSV has been much exploited to study its mechanism of replication. It is well understood that other viruses of this family follow similar replication pathways, but they differ in the pace of activity [
 <xref rid="B105-molecules-25-04878" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Initially, the host cell attachment happens with the HSV virus. This attachment occurs at the heparan sulfate moieties of cellular proteoglycans with the glycoprotein present in the virus envelope, where they bind with the secondary cellular receptors. After the attachment, the viral envelope is released into the cytosol. This will facilitate the movement of capsid toward the nuclear pore, where the viral DNA will be released via the capsid portal. Once in the nucleus, viral DNA transcription leads to mRNA by cellular RNA polymerase II. This viral gene expression is tightly regulated, which is comprised of three kinetic expressions such as early, intermittent, and late mRNA formation. All mRNA transcripts are translated into proteins and travel into the nucleus from the cytoplasm. Capsid proteins assemble in the nucleus to form empty capsids. Then, the newly formed capsids are released from the nucleus to the cytoplasm, where they form its final vesicles [
 <xref rid="B106-molecules-25-04878" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>,
 <xref rid="B107-molecules-25-04878" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Then, the formed virus accumulates in the endoplasmic reticulum and is subsequently released by exocytosis (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-04878-f002">Figure 2</xref>).
</p>
