<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Investigation to study the medicinal potential of over 600 wild and domesticated 
 <italic>Dioscorea</italic> species requires a multidisciplinary dimension involving indigenous natives who have a thorough grasp of these plants while adopting a well thought out strategy that puts into context society, health, conservation and sustainable use of species biodiversity. Numerous synthetic contraceptives and steroid related hormonal medications are made of dioscin. Unfortunately, the global need of dioscin is around 8000 tons but present production status puts it at 3000 tons [
 <xref rid="B336-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">336</xref>]. The increasing pressure from pharmaceutical industries is laying a high demand burden thus making this vital resource a scarce commodity looking into the future. Another perspective to this problem is the ineffectiveness of methods for extracting bioactive compounds. It has been reported that the rate of extraction and separation are generally low, with only the extraction of diosgenin accorded priority [
 <xref rid="B337-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">337</xref>]. It is imperative that efficient strategies that concentrate diosgenin from its natural sources are optimized [
 <xref rid="B144-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>] putting into consideration other compounds and eliminating waste. It is however important to develop carrier systems like nanoparticles for targeted delivery of yam bioactive extracts and compounds, thus improving efficacy while reducing side effects [
 <xref rid="B144-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. The need to standardize analytical protocols toward achieving optimal extraction should not be overlooked. Although extraction methods, such as soxhlet, maceration and hydrodistillation, have been extensively applied in the extraction of bioactive compounds, with newly developed methods shown to be much cleaner, higher yielding and efficient, such as thein situ pressurized biphase acid hydrolysis extraction reported by Yang et al. [
 <xref rid="B338-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">338</xref>] should be explored. The recent technological advancement in chromatographic techniques such as liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry (LC-MS) and high-resolution mass spectrometry (HR-MS) should be utilized for identifying and quantifying the various compounds in yam species. In addition, sophisticated instrumentation such as HR-MS should be applied to unravel possible beneficial unknown compounds in yam crop.
</p>
