<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Type 2 diabetes is a chronic and complex metabolic disease characterized mainly by hyperglycemia, insulin resistance, and insufficient insulin secretion [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. When carbohydrates are swallowed, dietary polysaccharides are absorbed by the hydrolysis effects of enteral 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase to obtain free monosaccharides [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Free monosaccharides assimilated in the blood can lead to hyperglycemia caused by type 2 diabetes [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. One of the diabetes treatments is to inhibit the enzyme activity of 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase to minimize the formation of blood glucose. 
 <italic>α</italic>-Glucosidase inhibitors extend the overall carbohydrate digestion time and decrease the absorption of glucose, which slow postprandial glucose elevation [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Several drugs, 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase inhibitors, such as voglibose, acarbose, and miglitol, are now available to treat the patients who suffer from postprandial hyperglycemia. However, a long-term use of these inhibitors has been associated with severe side effects, such as diarrhea and vomiting [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Hyperglycemia-induced oxidative stress is implicated in the onset and progression of diabetes and, if left untreated, can lead to severe complications [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Free radicals and reactive oxygen species are products of normal cellular metabolism and are extremely reactive and potentially damaging transient chemical species [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Numerous studies showed that over generation of free radicals and reactive oxygen species could be harmful to human health and trigger many diseases, such as cancer, arteriosclerosis, inflammatory disorders, and aging processes [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Therefore, the development of high-efficiency and low-toxicity antioxidant and 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase inhibitors from natural resources has become one research hotspot.
</p>
