<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Dwindling fossil resources and climate change drive the development of sustainable bio-based processes for generation of chemicals, pharmaceuticals, and biofuels, such as biodiesel (Chisti, 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>; Tai and Stephanopoulos, 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). With regard to biofuel products, current biodiesel is derived from plant-oils, which are associated with limited renewability due to utilization of agricultural land mass and fresh water resources as well as application of chemical fertilizers and pesticides. Therefore, this first-generation biofuel merely offers a partial solution with respect to sustainability and drives the socioeconomic food vs. fuel debate, which has limited the industrial roll out of biofuel processes (Hill et al., 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>). In that regard, current arable lands are not sufficient to meet the global-demand for plant derived biofuels (Smith et al., 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). Furthermore, rising demands for biodiesel lead to increasing prices of conventional plant oils. This situation lead to 2-fold price increase for rapeseed, peanut, and sunflower oils between 2007 and 2008 (Papanikolaou and Aggelis, 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Assuming a consistent pricing trend, 2020 price projection for the average vegetable oils are expected to exceed 2$.kg
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, which does not alleviate current economic or ecological pressures for biodiesel production (Koutinas et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). While algae based oils (3rd generation biodiesel) present an ecological alternative to plant oils, their photoautotrophic production is still associated with significant cost (5.6–21.0 $.kg
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) and technological barriers, including slow growth rate and difficulty in maintaining high-density cultures (Papanikolaou and Aggelis, 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Consequently, the development of new biofuel processes that utilize biomass waste without impacting agricultural activity are in demand to ensure global food security and address requirements for sustainable energy and oleochemical supply.
</p>
