<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To meet economic boundary conditions for industrial implementation of the technology, process costs have to be significantly reduced. In that regard, innovative fermenter designs, recycling/valorization of process residues streams and low energy oil recovery and purification methods are key to the commercialization of microbial oil production technology (Koutinas et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; Karlsson et al., 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). In the same manner, the feedstock materials represent a considerable fraction of the overall fermentation-based production costs (Singh et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). To that end, several strategies could be implemented to significantly improve the techno-economic boundary conditions of microbial oil production. These include the utilization of various biogenic waste materials as low or negative cost feedstocks, including as raw glycerol (biodiesel residue stream) and lignocellulosic hydrolysates (Zhao et al., 
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Co-fermentation of lignocellulosic-derived carbohydrates containing a mixture of pentoses (e.g., xylose) and hexoses (e.g., glucose) could also alleviate process costs (Stephanopoulos, 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>). Beyond the use of low cost hydrolysates, the design of zero waste yeast oil processes, that valorize all process streams lead to a significant economic and ecological enhancement in the overall process viability. In that regard, our group has recently reported a zero waste yeast oil production process based on marine macroalgae hydrolysates, where feedstock residues have been utilized as biological absorbents for recovery/recycling of industrially relevant metals (Ce
 <sup class="sup">+3</sup>, Cu
 <sup class="sup">+2</sup>, and Ni
 <sup class="sup">+2</sup>) from oil refining processes or for the removal of heavy metals (Pb
 <sup class="sup">+2</sup>) from waste water streams. Additionally, due to its unique sugar composition, the spent 
 <italic class="italic">C. oleaginosus</italic> cell wall after oil extraction was proposed as a performance animal feed additive to improve the techno-economic viability of the overall process (Masri et al., 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>). Another strategy to increase the economic viability of the yeast oil process, involves genetically engineering oleaginous yeast strains to improve substrate uptake and direct the metabolic flux into lipogenic pathways, thereby improving lipid productivity and tailor process specific FA profiles (Mlickova et al., 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>). Despite the high cost of manufacture (COM), microbial production of specialty lipids can achieve higher market prices and therefore rapid market viability. To that end, production of cocoa butter substitutes (CBS) from oleaginous yeast strains has been demonstrated at a technical scale since 1980s. However, recent records anticipate generalized market penetration of CBS in food industry following indications of future disappearance of cocoa plant (Davies and Holdsworth, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1992</xref>; Smit et al., 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1992</xref>; Hassan et al., 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1994b</xref>; Papanikolaou and Aggelis, 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). In a specific genetic engineering approach, a Δ9 fatty acid desaturase from 
 <italic class="italic">C. oleaginosus</italic> has been cloned and characterized for the production of CBS-SCOs (Papanikolaou and Aggelis, 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Beyond the production of cocoa butter, genetic engineering approaches to generate high value cosmetic fats, such as shea butter and sal fat has been explored as cocoa butter equivalents (CBE) (Koutinas et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Prior to technical implementation of any of these strategies, assessment and optimization of cultivation media components is essential to determine which factors influence biomass and lipid formation (Singh et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
