<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Identifying and designing optimal fermentation conditions plays a major role in the development of bioconversion systems, as the cultivation medium composition dictates product yield and volumetric productivity (Singh et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). In that respect, the carbon source is regarded as the most crucial element in the medium; as it represents the main energy source for growth, biomass formation, and subsequent lipid yield (Willis et al., 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). In addition to the carbon source, the source of nitrogen is thought to be another essential factor determining formation of yeast biomass and lipids. In fact, selected nitrogen sources can elevate biomass productivity, while others may prevent the synthesis of certain metabolites (Singh et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). The biochemical basis of lipid accumulation in oleaginous yeasts is believed to be an adaptive response under a carbon-rich and nutrient-limited (mainly nitrogen) conditions, where excess carbon is incorporated into intracellular lipids (TAGs) as a form of energy storage (Willis et al., 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Furthermore, fatty acid composition differs greatly depending on the type and concentration of the carbon and nitrogen sources. Lipid yield and type, in addition to biomass formation, are likewise influenced by the carbon to nitrogen ratio (C: N) in addition to media components like carbon and nitrogen-sources as well as vitamins and minerals (Granger et al., 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1993</xref>; Ratledge and Wynn, 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>). Enhancing strain genetics and improving media parameters are usually concomitant. 
 <italic class="italic">C. oleaginosus</italic> ability to produce high amounts of intracellular lipids from a variety of substrates has previously been reported (Evans and Ratledge, 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1983</xref>; Gujjari et al., 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Willis et al., 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). However, genetically engineering this particular yeast remains a challenge. With many genes lacking functional annotations and absence of proteomic data, these engineering efforts only rely on recently reported transcriptomic sequences (Kourist et al., 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Recently methods that enable genetic accessibility of 
 <italic class="italic">C. oleaginosus</italic> have been reported. These methods allowed an increase in total lipid yields as well as the generation of tailor-made, non-native fatty acid, such as polyunsaturated very long chain fatty acids eicosatrienoic and eicosadienoic acid and (E-10, Z-12) conjugated linoleic acid (Gorner et al., 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Based on the available data, this study will focus on a systematic, multi-factorial analysis of how carbon and nitrogen sources affect 
 <italic class="italic">C. oleaginosus</italic> biomass and lipid formation.
</p>
