<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>From the aromatic features perspective, the actual challenges in research are multifold: (a) overcome the crop defects; (b) refinement of aroma deviations; (c) modulate volatile and nonvolatile compounds’ biosyntheses to produce high-potency aromatic features; (d) increase the accuracy of aromatic features signature; (e) understand how preharvest and postharvest factors can affect vegetable and MAP aromatic features or tastes. The flavour is the result of a complex metabolic network that can be influenced by several factors, such as genetics, environment, agricultural practices, and postharvest handling and storage. However, recent findings show that the biosynthesis of the compounds can be remarkably influenced by other factors, such as enzyme specificity of gene adaptation [
 <xref rid="B192-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>,
 <xref rid="B193-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>] leading to the research of new steps. Until recently, the research focus was to understand how agriculture practices affect plant composition and interfere in the consumer´s perception of aromatic features [
 <xref rid="B126-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>,
 <xref rid="B194-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>], but the latest research studies are shifting from yield to quality factors. Nowadays, the trends in consumption are mostly defined by consumer’s preferences (sustainability, nutrition, aromatic features, novelty) and not exclusively by the producer’s priorities [
 <xref rid="B194-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>]. Genomic and metabolomic analysis with clarification of the fundamental metabolism of volatile compounds with aromatic features and their biosynthetic mechanisms, regulations, and localisation is a hot topic [
 <xref rid="B194-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>]. So, linkages of the biosynthesis of aromatic features with enzymatic endogenous processes will provide new insights into the flavour control mechanism. Moreover, the association of genome and metabolome analysis with identification of key enzymatic changes occurred in physiological processes would address new opportunities to increase the contents of specific compounds, particularly those with importance for consumer acceptance. This approach will open the possibility to produce vegetables and MAP species with an enhanced content of a specific volatile or nonvolatile compound, with greater biological properties. Additionally, it will speed up the discovery of new or unknown chemosensory-active molecules and understanding of their biochemical interactions with main food matrix constituents. Likewise, it will open ways of direct improvement of foods by adapting processing parameters that can help to overcome taste defects or undesirable aromatic features, without the addition of any artificial ingredients.
</p>
