<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since important similarities exist between the sequences of ACE and ACE2 (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Guy et al., 2005</xref>), molecules with inhibitory effects toward ACE may exert the same effect toward ACE2 and thus lead to reduce the viral entry. However, further studies should be undertaken to evaluate this hypothesis. 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Patten et al. (2016)</xref> reviewed the medicinal plants for their inhibitory effects on ACE2. They reported 141 medicinal species belonging to 73 families and 49 purified natural compounds with documented ACE inhibitory potential. Moreover, 16 medicinal species (16 families) were found to be able to block the angiotensin type 1A receptor 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. 
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">Sharifi et al. (2013)</xref> identified four Iranian medicinal species able to inhibit more than 80% of ACE activity 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. These active species were: 
 <italic>Berberis integerrima</italic> Bunge., 
 <italic>Crataegus laevigata</italic> (Poir.) DC., 
 <italic>Onopordum acanthium</italic> L., and 
 <italic>Quercus infectoria</italic> G. Olivier. At 330 µg/ml, Q
 <italic>uercus infectoria</italic> G. Olivier. was found to be the most active and caused 94% ACE inhibition. This important inhibitory activity might be attributed to its higher phenolic content and enhanced antioxidant potential. In spite of the important ACE inhibition and antioxidant activities exhibited by 
 <italic>Q. Infectoria</italic> extract, the presence of condensed tannins compromised its usefulness due to their interference in the functions of ACE. On the other hand, 
 <italic>B. integerrima, C. microphylla</italic> and 
 <italic>O. acanthium</italic> were found to have both important ACE inhibitory activities and enhanced antioxidant potential without the presence of tannins (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">Sharifi et al., 2013</xref>
 <italic>)</italic>. These species could be promising sources of antiviral molecules. Indeed, viral infections are accompanied by oxidative stress which in turn promotes virus replication. Antioxidant species decrease the ROS production in infected cells and target different oxidative stress-related signalling pathways resulting in reduction of viral spread (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Fedoreyev et al., 2018</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">Walls et al. (2020)</xref> demonstrated that SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV bind with similar affinities to ACE2. In another study, 25 Chinese herbal families were found to significantly inhibit the interaction SARS-CoV – ACE2. Among them, species belonging to Polygonaceae, Labiatae, Oleaceae, Magnoliaceae, Lauraceae, and Nelumbonaceae exhibited the most important inhibitory effects. These inhibitory effects were attributed to emodin (1,3,8-trihydroxy-6-methylanthraquinone) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">
  <bold>Figure 2</bold>
 </xref>) produced in high levels in in genus Rheum and Polygonum. Emodin blocked the interaction SARS-CoV S protein and ACE2 in a dose-dependent manner with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 200 µM (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Ho et al., 2007</xref>).
</p>
