<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Abstract</title>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Context:</bold> Orange Jessamine [
  <italic class="italic">Murraya paniculata</italic> L. (Rutaceae)] has been used worldwide in folk medicine as an anti-inflammatory, antibiotic and analgesic.
 </p>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Objective:</bold> The objective of this study is to investigate the 
  <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> antioxidant, cytotoxic, antibacterial and antifungal activity and the time-kill curve studies of orange jessamine essential oil and β-caryophyllene, as well as the chemical composition of the essential oil.
 </p>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Material and methods:</bold> The cytotoxic activity of 
  <italic class="italic">M. paniculata</italic> and β-caryophyllene (7.8–500 μg/mL) was evaluated using the MTT assay on normal fibroblasts and hepatoma cells. The minimal inhibitory concentration and time–kill curves (24 h) were evaluated against those of Staphylococcus 
  <italic class="italic">aureus</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Salmonella typhimurium</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Enterococcus faecallis</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Aspergillus</italic> (
  <italic class="italic">niger</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">fumigates</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">parasiticum</italic>) and 
  <italic class="italic">F. solani</italic> by the broth microdilution method. The antioxidant activity was measured by the DPPH and ABTS assays. Chemical composition was evaluated by GC/MS analyses.
 </p>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Results:</bold> GC/MS analyses identified 13 compounds, with β-caryophyllene as the major compound. The oil exhibited moderate antibacterial activity (MIC &lt;1.0 mg/mL) and strong antifungal activity. Time–kill curve studies showed that either the essential oil or β-caryophyllene presented rapid bacterial killing (4 h for 
  <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic>) and fungicidal effect (2-4 h for 
  <italic class="italic">F. solani</italic>); however, both displayed weak free radical scavenger capacity. The cytotoxic activity exhibited a prominent selective effect against hepatoma cancer cells (IC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> value =63.7 μg/mL) compared with normal fibroblasts (IC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> value =195.0 μg/mL), whereas the β-caryophyllene showed low cytotoxicity.
 </p>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Discussion and conclusion:</bold> The experimental data suggest that the activities of 
  <italic class="italic">M. paniculata</italic> essential oil are due to the synergistic action among its components.
 </p>
</abstract>
