<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many studies exploring the bioactivity of EOs have mainly attributed their antioxidant capacity to terpenoids with phenolic groups such as carvacrol, methyl chavicol, thymol, and eugenol, as they can donate hydrogen atoms to free radicals and transform them into more stable products [
 <xref rid="B162-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>,
 <xref rid="B164-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>]. For example, about 80% of oregano EOs are constituted by carvacrol and thymol, mainly responsible for its antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B165-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>,
 <xref rid="B166-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>]. Similarly, EOs from other aromatic plant species, like lemon balm, basil, thyme, and sage, have also been established as rich sources of antioxidants [
 <xref rid="B162-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>]. The study conducted by Viuda-Martos and co-workers demonstrated the ability EOs from oregano (
 <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic>), rosemary (
 <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic>), and sage (
 <italic>Salvia officinalis</italic>) to chelate Fe
 <sup>2+</sup>, with rosemary EO displaying the highest effect (76.06%). Moreover, oregano EO showed the most increased antioxidant activity in the Rancimat test [
 <xref rid="B167-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>]. Tunisian 
 <italic>Thymus capitatus</italic> EO’s antioxidant activity, mainly composed of carvacrol, 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene, and γ-terpinene, was compared with butylated hydroxyanisole (BHA) and Butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) by DPPH and thiobarbituric acid-reactive species (TBARS) methods, evidencing better antioxidant properties [
 <xref rid="B168-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>]. On the other hand, Kulisic et al. revealed that the antioxidant activity of 
 <italic>O. vulgare</italic> EO was less effective than ascorbic acid (AA), but comparable with the α-tocopherol and BHT, based on the BCB test, DPPH radical scavenging method, and thiobarbituric acid-reactive species (TBARS) assay [
 <xref rid="B169-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>]. Furthermore, in vivo experiments carried out in pigs fed with diets containing 
 <italic>O. vulgare</italic> crude herbal drug promoted significantly improved stability and lower cholesterol oxide content in raw belly bacon than controls after 34 weeks of storage [
 <xref rid="B170-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>]. In line with these findings, Botsoglou et al. demonstrated that laying hens fed with a 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic>-enriched diet (3% ground herb) led to an increased storage time (over 60 days) in the refrigerator, mostly due to reduced oxidation of liquid yolk [
 <xref rid="B171-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>]. Additionally, higher enzyme levels of the antioxidative enzymes, namely superoxide dismutase (SOD) and glutathione peroxidase (GPx), were found in ageing rats dietary supplemented with thyme oil or thymol [
 <xref rid="B172-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>]. Studies conducted in White pigs demonstrated that rosemary EO (150 mg/kg) significantly reduced the generation of TBARS and hexanal, and carbonyls, indicators of lipid and protein oxidation, respectively [
 <xref rid="B165-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>,
 <xref rid="B173-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>]. A study developed by Takayama et al. showed that pre-treatment of rats with 
 <italic>R. officinalis</italic> EO (50 mg/kg) protected against the gastric injury induced by ethanol, probably by modulating the activities of SOD and GPx, and increasing or maintaining the levels of glutathione (GSH) [
 <xref rid="B174-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>]. In vitro experiments dealing with the DPPH scavenging activity of 
 <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> EO revealed that its potent antioxidant activity (The half maximal inhibitory concentration (IC
 <sub>50</sub>) = 19 µg/mL) could be attributed to the presence of oxygenated monoterpenes such as thymol and thymoquinone [
 <xref rid="B175-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>]. Furthermore, 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> EO strongly inhibited tert-Butyl hydroperoxide (
 <italic>t</italic>-BuOOH) induced 2′,7′-dichlorofluorescin diacetate (DCFH) oxidation with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 1.0 μg/mL in WS-1 cells, indicating its ability to inhibit reactive oxygen species (ROS) production [
 <xref rid="B176-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">176</xref>]. In vivo assays demonstrated that 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> EO holds the potential to significantly improve the oxidant status of normal rats by enhancing the activity of several antioxidant enzymes, namely glutathione reductase and glutathione transferase [
 <xref rid="B177-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>]. Singh et al. also showed the strong antioxidant effect of 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> EO in the rapeseed oil system, evidencing comparable results to BHA and BHT effects at the 6 mg levels [
 <xref rid="B158-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>].
</p>
