<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">The SEM micrographs indicated that the mycelia shrank and became applanate, exuvial and blistery after treatment with cinnamon bark oil and cinnamon oil. Soylu 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. found that 
 <italic class="italic">Origanum</italic> essential oil caused the hyphal morphology of 
 <italic class="italic">B</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">cinerea</italic> to degenerate, resulting in cytoplasmic coagulation, vacuolations, hyphal shriveling and protoplast leakage
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup>, and Xu 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. also reported that 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-cinnamaldehyde induced the hyphae collapse and fracture of 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alternata</italic>
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>. As shown in the SEM graphs, cinnamon bark oil was more toxic than cinnamon oil, which might be related to the contents of camphene, eucalyptol, and o-cymene, since different chemical compounds stimulated or inhibited the mycelial growth alone or together
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup>. The most serious disruption to the hyphae caused by 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-cinnamaldehyde indicated that it was the primary active compound in the cinnamon bark and cinnamon oils. Different abnormal phenomena might be responsible for the different treatments. As the previous study, fumigation impacts of PEOs on fungal structures might reflect effects of the volatiles emitted by oils on surface mycelial development and/or the perception/transduction of signals involved in the switch from vegetative to reproductive development
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup>. The contact activity of PEOs may be impacted by interactions with the matrix components, which resulted in mycelial injury
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>. This result further confirmed that cinnamon bark oil, cinnamon oil and 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-cinnamaldehyde inhibited mycelial growth by destroying the surface structure of the mycelia and provided some reference and a basis to further explore the action mechanism of PEOs against 
 <italic class="italic">V</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">virens</italic>. The specific mechanism on gene expressions and protein activities of cinnamon bark oil, cinnamon oil and 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-cinnamaldehyde against hyphae surface morphological alterations of 
 <italic class="italic">V</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">virens</italic> remained unclear and needs to be studied.
</p>
