<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6117356</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5877</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-05877-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Reprogramming of the antimycin NRPS-PKS assembly lines inspired by gene evolution</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Awakawa</surname><given-names>Takayoshi</given-names></name><address><email>awakawa@mol.f.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>Takuma</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Lihan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hoshino</surname><given-names>Shotaro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Zhijuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>Junko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kozone</surname><given-names>Ikuko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>Haruo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Shin-Ya</surname><given-names>Kazuo</given-names></name><address><email>k-shinya@aist.go.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Wen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3640-888X</contrib-id><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>Ikuro</given-names></name><address><email>abei@mol.f.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2151 536X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.26999.3d</institution-id><institution>Graduate School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, </institution><institution>The University of Tokyo, </institution></institution-wrap>7-3-1 Hongo, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo, 113-0033 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2151 536X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.26999.3d</institution-id><institution>Collaborative Research Institute for Innovative Microbiology, </institution><institution>The University of Tokyo, </institution></institution-wrap>Yayoi 1-1-1, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo, 113-8657 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0404 8570</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.420249.9</institution-id><institution>Japan Biological Informatics Consortium, </institution></institution-wrap>2-4-7 Aomi, Koto-ku, Tokyo, 135-8073 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9206 2938</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410786.c</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Microbial Engineering, Kitasato Institute for Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Kitasato University, </institution></institution-wrap>Kanagawa, 252-0373 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2230 7538</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.208504.b</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology (AIST), </institution></institution-wrap>2-4-7 Aomi, Koto-ku, Tokyo, 135 0064 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000119573309</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9227.e</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory of Bio-Organic &#x00026; Natural Products Chemistry, Shanghai Institute of Organic Chemistry, </institution><institution>Chinese Academy of Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Lingling Road 345, 200032 Shanghai, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>3534</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Reprogramming of the NRPS/PKS assembly line is an attractive method for the production of new bioactive molecules. However, it is usually hampered by the loss of intimate domain/module interactions required for the precise control of chain transfer and elongation reactions. In this study, we first establish heterologous expression systems of the unique antimycin-type cyclic depsipeptides: JBIR-06 (tri-lactone) and neoantimycin (tetra-lactone), and engineer their biosyntheses by taking advantage of bioinformatic analyses and evolutionary insights. As a result, we successfully accomplish three manipulations: (i) ring contraction of neoantimycin (from tetra-lactone to tri-lactone), (ii) ring expansion of JBIR-06 (from tri-lactone to tetra-lactone), and (iii) alkyl chain diversification of JBIR-06 by the incorporation of various alkylmalonyl-CoA extender units, to generate a set of unnatural derivatives in practical yields. This study presents a useful strategy for engineering NRPS-PKS module enzymes, based on nature&#x02019;s diversification of the domain and module organizations.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">Modifying the non-ribosomal peptide synthase (NRPS)/polyketide synthase (PKS) pathway to generate novel non-ribosomal peptides often results in a loss of productivity. Here the authors use evolutionary alignments of NRPS/PKS gene clusters to guide rational design of complexes that can produce novel lactones.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100001700</institution-id><institution>Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology (MEXT)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>JP15H01836, JP16H06443, JP16K13084, and JP17H04763</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>Ikuro</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Polyketides and non-ribosomal peptide hybrids are an important class of natural products, and include a variety of bioactive compounds, exemplified by the anti-cancer agents, bleomycin, epothilone, and calyculin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. They are built up by a complex system composed of polyketide synthases (PKSs) and non-ribosomal peptide synthetases (NRPSs)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, which are thiotemplate module enzymes consisting of several catalytic domains. In the PKS system, the ketosynthase (KS) domain catalyzes decarboxylative Claisen condensation between a starter acyl group and an extender unit thioesterified to an acyl carrier protein (ACP) via the action of an acyltransferase (AT), during a single polyketide extension cycle. In the NRPS system, the amino acid building blocks are activated as adenylates and thioesterified to the thiolation (T) domain by the adenylation (A) domain. The condensation (C) domain forms a peptide bond between two acylated T domains during a single peptide extension cycle. In both systems, if the termination domain is a thioesterase (TE), then chain release typically occurs by hydrolysis or macrocyclization. A set of domain complexes responsible for one cycle of chain extension is called a module. The amino acid sequences within subunits that join domains and modules covalently are referred to as a linker, and those which are located on distinct subunits and mediate communication between modules are referred to as a docking domain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. In the NRPS&#x02013;PKS complex systems, the product of the NRPS module is transferred onto the KS domain of PKS module and condensed with a polyketide extender unit by PKS, or the product of PKS module is condensed with an amino acid to form a peptide bond by NRPS. The substrate specificities of the KS and C domains are usually rigid, thus contributing to the maintenance of the precise chain transfer order. Several reports have clarified the reaction mechanism of each module and domain in the NRPS and PKS systems in terms of the protein structure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>; however, the engineering of these systems usually accompanies significant loss of productivity due to the strict regulation of the module enzymes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">To overcome such problems, the optimal joint connections for each catalytic domain and module should be identified. Recently, Bode and co-workers reported a new strategy for the manipulation of NRPSs by using exchange units that are sets of A-T-C domains that can be transplanted into active chimeric modules<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. However, this strategy may not be necessarily applied to hybrid NRPS-PKS systems because the quaternary organization of NRPS-PKS is likely different from that of pure NRPS system. In fact, the quaternary structure of NRPS module is defined as a monomer in the early chromatographic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> and X-ray crystallographic studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, but we cannot exclude that it works as a dimer in the NRPS-PKS system, as the docking domain from tubulysin system forms a homodimer in the solution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. It has thus remained challenging to establish a general rule for rational reconstruction of module assembly lines, and scientists still rely on trial-and-error strategies. One possible solution is to learn how nature diversifies the domain and module organizations by taking advantage of bioinformatics analyses, through comparisons of closely related enzymes. In nature, various module enzymes have evolved through horizontal gene transfer, gene deletion, mutation, and so on<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> to form functional sets of modules. Thus, for <italic>cis</italic>-AT PKSs, the predominant evolutionary model is a repeated cycle of duplication of ancestral modules coupled with domain exchanges<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, while for the distinct class of <italic>trans</italic>-AT PKSs, it is rather horizontal gene transfer that appears to dominate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. However, the specific evolutionary history of hybrid <italic>cis</italic>-AT PKS/NRPS system has yet to be rigorously investigated. It is a promising way to modify the module compositions according to the evolutionary course, because this method is effective to maintain the connectivity between multiple modules while minimizing the change of the overall structure and the protein&#x02013;protein interactions which underlie their function. The knowledge on the constraint for NRPS-PKS engineering should be accumulated more to understand how this system has been evolved and can be manipulated. This could lead to computational platforms which clearly predict domain/linker/docking-domain boundaries as the one established in <italic>cis</italic>-PKS system for designing chimeric modules<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Antimycins (<bold>1</bold>) are a group of di-lactone depsipeptides with various important biological properties, including anti-fungal, insecticidal, anti-cancer, and anti-inflammatory activities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. They are biosynthesized by the NRPS-PKS system from substrates including a unique 3-formamidosalicylate (3-FSA) starter unit, L-threonine, pyruvate, and alkylmalonyl-CoA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Their structures are characterized by the depsipeptides constructed by two NRPS modules (AntC), including one module with an unusual ketoreductase (KR)-domain, one PKS (AntD) that generates alkyl group variations at C-9 by the incorporation of a broad range of extender substrates provided by a crotonyl-CoA reductase/carboxylase (CCR)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> (AntE), and a reductase (AntM). Zhang&#x02019;s group and we have created ~100 antimycin derivatives, by employing the biosynthetic enzymes with the tolerant substrate specificities in the antimycin systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Interestingly, in nature, there are tri-lactone, tetra-lactone, and penta-lactone antimycin-type depsipeptides that also utilize 3-FSA as a common starter unit<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, including the tri-lactone JBIR-06 (<bold>2</bold>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> and the tetra-lactone neoantimycin A (<bold>3a</bold>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), known downregulators of GRP78, a molecular chaperone related to resistance to chemotherapy and hypoglycemic stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. In 2013, Magarvey&#x02019;s group reported two NRPS-PKS gene clusters based on bioinformatic analyses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, and proposed that they are involved in the biosyntheses of <bold>2</bold> and <bold>3a</bold>, respectively; however, their proposal has not been validated experimentally and the sequence information has not been deposited in GenBank. The NRPS-PKS assembly line organizations involved in the biosyntheses of <bold>1</bold>, <bold>2</bold>, and <bold>3a</bold> are very similar, and the conservation of the two modules that incorporate 3-FSA and L-threonine in these biosynthetic systems implies that they are generated from the same ancestor. Very recently, Zhang&#x02019;s group also reported the neoantimycin gene cluster and showed the extender substrate of its PKS module was malonyl-CoA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Here, we control the size of lactone rings of JBIR-06 and neoantimycin, and introduce diverse alkyl groups into the JBIR-06 scaffold, by rationally modifying their assembly lines with the aid of the information how they are diversified, to yield various bioactive antimycin-type depsipeptides.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Organization of modular enzymes involved in the biosynthesis of antimycin-type depsipeptides. C condensation, A adenylation, T thiolation, KR ketoreductase, KS ketosynthase, AT acyltransferase, ACP acyl carrier protein, MT methyltransferase, TE thioesterase, CCR crotonyl-CoA reductase/carboxylase, R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> various alkyl groups, R<sub>starter</sub> the acyl moiety of 3-FSA. The module and domain organizations of the starter, the module 1, and the module 2 are identical among the all three systems. The starter and the module 1 uptake 3-FSA and L-threonine, respectively, common to all pathways, but the module 2 uptake pyruvate (AntC), isoleucic acid (SmlB), and valic acid (NatB), respectively. JBIR-06 and neoantimycin systems include an additional NRPS modules (module 3) after the module 2 in the same ORF. The module 3 in SmlB uptakes phenylpyruvic acid, and the module 3 in NatB uptakes leucic acid. The PKS modules of JBIR-06 and neoantimycin systems (module 4) contain MT domain between AT and ACP, and accept malonyl-CoA as an extender unit, to yield dimethyl group at the &#x003b1;-position of polyketide moiety, differently from antimycin system. Furthermore, neoantimycin system includes an extra NRPS module (module 5 as NatD) which uptakes isoleucic acid or valic acid</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_5877_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e529"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>JBIR-06 and neoantimycin biosynthetic gene clusters</title><p id="Par6">In this work, we independently identified the biosynthetic gene clusters of the tri-lactone JBIR-06 and the tetra-lactone neoantimycin (the <italic>sml</italic> and <italic>nat</italic> clusters) from each producing strain (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>), and heterologously expressed them in <italic>Streptomyces lividans</italic> TK21 to identify their products. The JBIR-06 and neoantimycin gene clusters were each cloned into pKU518<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, a bacteriophage-based BAC vector, resulting in pKU518J06 and pKU518nant, respectively (Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>, Supplementary Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>). From the sequence data of these two vectors, we confirmed that the assembly line organizations of JBIR-06 and neoantimycin NRPS-PKSs were identical with those in the previous report<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, except for NatD (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In contrast to the Magarvey&#x02019;s report, where <italic>natD</italic> and <italic>natE</italic> encode A-KR and T-TE domains, respectively, <italic>natD</italic> encodes a whole single module consisted of C-A-KR-T-TE domains in our sequence data. As Zhang&#x02019;s group also reported the same NatD domain organization as ours<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, the current module organization of neoantimycin is more plausible. HPLC analyses of the culture extracts of the recombinants revealed that <italic>S. lividans</italic>/pKU518J06 and <italic>S. lividans</italic>/pKU518nant yielded <bold>2</bold> and <bold>3a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>3b</bold>, respectively (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>). Through NMR and MS analyses, <bold>2</bold>, <bold>3a</bold>, and <bold>3b</bold> were identified as JBIR-06, neoantimycin A, and neoantimycin F (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>, Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>), by comparisons with data in the literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. These results linked <bold>2</bold> to the product of <italic>sml</italic> cluster, and <bold>3a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>3b</bold> to those of <italic>nat</italic> cluster, and provided the platform for the engineered biosynthesis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Bioinformatic analyses of the NRPS-PKS module structures</title><p id="Par7">Sequence analyses revealed that <italic>sml</italic> and <italic>nat</italic> NRPS/PKS gene clusters encode four and five modules, respectively, to build up the molecular scaffold of the tri-lactone JBIR-06 and the tetra-lactone neoantimycin (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). We conducted the DNA sequence alignment for A, C, T, and KR domains from <italic>ant</italic>, <italic>sml</italic>, and <italic>nat</italic> system, respectively, and calculated their identities (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref>). Due to the high amino acid sequence identities (i.e., the PKS modules AntD and SmlC share 51% amino acid sequence identity, while AntD and NatC share 53%), we could precisely identify functional domain boundaries, and thus intervening linkers or adjacent docking domains (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">9</xref>). It is critical to retain the intimate domain/module interactions that are required for precise control of the chain transfer and elongation reactions for successful engineering of the NRPS/PKS assembly lines. As a result, as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>, we annotated region 1 (1301&#x02013;1371 in SmlC and 1320&#x02013;1390 in NatC) as the ACP domain of PKS module, region 2 (1393&#x02013;1647 in SmlC), which is only conserved in AntD and SmlC, as the TE domain, and the region surrounded by ACP and TE (1372&#x02013;1392 in SmlC) as an interdomain linker (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Homology modeling (SWISS-MODEL server, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://swissmodel.expasy.org">https://swissmodel.expasy.org</ext-link>) supports the hypothesis on its structure including region 1 forms four &#x003b1;-helices and two loops, which are involved in the interactions with the KS-AT domains<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">10</xref>). The C-terminal region of NatC (1391&#x02013;1411) was predicted to be a docking domain between PKS and NRPS modules, as the one previously reported for the epothilone NRPS-PKS system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Therefore, with the bioinformatic information in our hands, we anticipated that the deletion of the NatD NRPS module from the tetra-lactone neoantimycin assembly line would lead to ring contraction (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>), whereas the addition of the NatD module to the tri-lactone JBIR-06 system would expand the ring structure (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). Furthermore, in order to maintain the intimate domain/module interactions, we employed the TE domain of the SmlC PKS module (TE<sub>SmlC</sub>), as well as the predicted interdomain linker between the ACP and TE domains of SmlC, for the ring contraction, while the docking domain between the NatC PKS module and the NatD NRPS module was kept for the ring expansion experiment. We therefore took advantage of this information to redesign the chimeric NRPS-PKS assembly lines for the ring contraction and expansion, as described below.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Bioinformatic analyses of the antimycin PKS modules. <bold>a</bold> Alignment of the PKS modules, AntD, SmlC, and NatC. We annotated SmlC<sub>1301&#x02013;1371</sub> as an ACP domain (region 1), SmlC<sub>1372&#x02013;1392</sub> as an interdomain linker, SmlC<sub>1393&#x02013;1647</sub> as a TE domain (region 2), and NatC<sub>1391&#x02013;1411</sub> as a docking domain. <bold>b</bold> A homology model of ACP<sub>NatC</sub> (1320&#x02013;1411), based on the reported crystal structure of the surfactin synthase ACP subunit (PBD: 2VSQ) as the template. <bold>c</bold> A homology model of the ACP<sub>NatC-</sub>TE<sub>SmlC</sub> domains, the NRPS module from <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (NCBI PBD ID 4ZXH_A, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/4ZXH_A">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/4ZXH_A</ext-link>) was used as the template</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_5877_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e775"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Ring contraction of neoantimycin A. <bold>a</bold> The reconstructed module structure for ring contraction. <bold>b</bold> HPLC analyses of the metabolites from transformants harboring (i) pKU518nant and (ii) pKU518nant&#x00394;<italic>natD</italic>::<italic>smlCTE</italic>. The chromatogram represents the UV absorbance at 320&#x02009;nm. * and ** indicate unidentified analogs with <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> values that were 14 and 28 less than <bold>3b</bold>, respectively. <bold>c</bold> Engineering scheme and structure of <bold>4</bold></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_5877_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e811"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Ring expansion of JBIR-06. <bold>a</bold> The reconstructed module structure for ring expansion. <bold>b</bold> HPLC analyses of the metabolites from transformants harboring (i) pKU518J06 and (ii) pKU518J06&#x00394;smlCTE/pZH2-NatD. The chromatogram represents the UV absorbance at 320&#x02009;nm. *** indicates a mixture of analogs with <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> values that are 14 less than <bold>5</bold>. <bold>c</bold> Engineering scheme and structure of <bold>5</bold> and <bold>6</bold></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_5877_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e844"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">Notably, our sequence analysis of the C-terminal region of NatC revealed that NatC<sub>1391&#x02013;1411</sub> contains several positively charged residues while other C-terminal docking domains that interact with NRPS subunits contain a run of negatively charged residues (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">11A</xref>). Further, the three &#x003b1;-helices and two &#x003b2;-turns, annotated as a docking domain in the EpoB NRPS structure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, are uniquely replaced with a shorter 9 amino acid sequences in NatD (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">11B</xref>). This suggests that the docking between NatC and NatD is fundamentally different from other interfaces. Despite these dissimilarities, our engineering strategy with the docking domain of NatC worked (see the section of ring expansion).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Ring contraction of neoantimycin A</title><p id="Par9">We first conducted the ring contraction of the tetra-lactone neoantimycin A (<bold>3a</bold>), by deleting the NatD NRPS module from <italic>nat</italic> cluster and connecting the linker-TE<sub>SmlC</sub> domain right after the C-terminus of NatC, to form a NatC-SmlC chimeric PKS (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>,&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>). TE domains usually exhibit tolerant substrate specificities, as exemplified by the early studies where the TE domain from erythromycin system was shown to accept polyketide chains of diverse lengths<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, and recognize the functional group at the acyl terminus and adjacent to the attacking nucleophile<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Therefore, we expected that TE<sub>SmlC</sub> domain, which recognizes the acyl group derived from polyketide and the hydroxyl group of threonine as a nucleophile, would accept the intermediate from the new construct and catalyze macrocyclization. The interdomain linker of SmlC was also employed, to connect the ACP<sub>NatC</sub> domain to the TE<sub>SmlC</sub> domain (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). The <italic>S. lividans</italic> strain harboring pKU518nant&#x00394;<italic>natD</italic>::<italic>smlCTE</italic>, accordingly engineered with the Red/ET system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup> (Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>, Supplementary Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>), was incubated in A3M medium, and the extract of the transformant was analyzed by HPLC. As expected, the production of <bold>3a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>3b</bold> was completely abolished, and <bold>4</bold> newly appeared (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>). LC-MS analyses showed that the <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> of <bold>4</bold> was 581, which is 116 less than <bold>3a</bold>, and its UV max was around 315&#x02009;nm, characteristic of the antimycin starter unit (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">12</xref>, Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>), suggesting that <bold>4</bold> was generated from the ring contraction of <bold>3a</bold>. The <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR data defined the structure of the side chain, and the HMBC correlations from H-28, H-29, and H-30 to C-8 (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">18</xref>, Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>) clearly showed that the hydroxyl group of the L-threonine moiety was esterified with the carboxyl group of the polyketide moiety, indicating that <bold>4</bold> is a trilactone generated by the loss of isoleucic acid from <bold>3a</bold> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>). <bold>4</bold> bears a keto group at C-1, indicating that the ketoreduction unexpectedly did not work in the recombinant strain. It might be caused by the polar effect on the expression of <italic>natF</italic>, a ketoreductase gene located downstream of <italic>natD</italic>, though we cannot eliminate the possibility that NatF no longer recognizes the substrate. The yield of <bold>4</bold> (3.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7&#x02009;mg/L) was 3-fold reduced relative to that of <bold>3a</bold> (12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0&#x02009;mg/L) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), but it did not drop significantly, verifying the accuracy of our domain structure prediction.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The yields of isolated products</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Product</th><th>Yields<sup>a</sup> (mg/L)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<bold>3a</bold>
</td><td>12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>3b</bold>
</td><td>6.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>4</bold>
</td><td>3.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>2</bold>
<sup>b</sup>
</td><td>5.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>5</bold>
</td><td>5.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>6</bold>
</td><td>9.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>2</bold>
<sup>c</sup>
</td><td>5.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>7a</bold>
<sup>c</sup>
</td><td>1.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>7b</bold>
<sup>c</sup>
</td><td>0.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>7c</bold>
<sup>c</sup>
</td><td>0.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.17</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>7d</bold>
<sup>c</sup>
</td><td>0.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>7e</bold>
<sup>c</sup>
</td><td>0.39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>7f</bold>
<sup>c</sup>
</td><td>1.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>2</bold>
<sup>d</sup>
</td><td>4.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>7a</bold>
<sup>d</sup>
</td><td>0.53&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>7b</bold>
<sup>d</sup>
</td><td>0.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>7c</bold>
<sup>d</sup>
</td><td>0.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>7d</bold>
<sup>d</sup>
</td><td>0.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>7e</bold>
<sup>d</sup>
</td><td>0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>7f</bold>
<sup>d</sup>
</td><td>0.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>The quantification was done based on the standard curve using <bold>6</bold> (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3, mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM)</p><p><sup>b</sup>From <italic>S. lividans</italic> harboring pKU518J06</p><p><sup>c</sup>From <italic>S. lividans</italic> harboring pKU518J06&#x00394;SmlC/pZH2-SmlCAT<sub>ant</sub>-AntEV350G</p><p><sup>d</sup>From <italic>S. lividans</italic> harboring pKU518J06&#x00394;SmlC/pZH2-AntEV350G</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Ring expansion of JBIR-06</title><p id="Par10">We next enlarged the lactone size of the tri-lactone JBIR-06 (<bold>2</bold>) by creating an <italic>sml/nat</italic> chimera. To this end, we appended the NatD NRPS module to <italic>sml</italic> cluster and replaced the linker and TE domain in the SmlC PKS module with the docking domain of NatC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6A</xref>), to maintain the module/module interactions to yield the tetra-lactone product. The accordingly engineered BAC, pKU518J06&#x00394;smlCTE (Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>, Supplementary Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>), was introduced into <italic>S. lividans</italic> with the <italic>natD</italic> expression vector, based on the &#x003d5;C31 phage integration system (pZH2-NatD) (Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">19</xref>). As a result, the original product <bold>2</bold> disappeared completely, and <bold>5</bold> and <bold>6</bold> newly appeared in the transformant (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). The planar structure of <bold>5</bold> was determined as the tetra-lactone, which contains one threonine, two isoleucic acids, and one leucic acid (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>), through a comparison of the 1D NMR data with the literature (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">23</xref>, Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. The HMBC correlations between H-9 and C-8/-10, and H-7 and C-8 and MS data indicated that the additional isoleucic acid was introduced into the C-terminus of the depsipeptide chain of <bold>2</bold>, and lactonized with the hydroxyl group of threonine to yield <bold>5</bold> (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">18</xref>, and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">24</xref>, Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>). The stereochemistry of each building block was identified as L-threonine, L-isoleucic acid, and L-leucic acid with the chiral GC-MS analyses of the acid-hydrolyzed fragments of <bold>5</bold> and <bold>6</bold>, and the linear depsipeptide consisted of 3-FSA starter unit, threonine, isoleucic acid, and leucic acid (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">30</xref>, Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>). The yield of <bold>5</bold> (5.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6&#x02009;mg/L) was almost the same as that of <bold>2</bold> (5.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7&#x02009;mg/L, from <italic>S. lividans</italic>/ pKU518J06) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), indicating that NatD accepted the intermediate from SmlC efficiently and esterified one more L-isoleucic acid with the intermediate, to produce the tetra-lactone <bold>5</bold>. The unexpected accumulation of the acyclic <bold>6</bold> (9.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8&#x02009;mg/L) might have been caused by the extended residence time of the intermediate on SmlB relative to the native system, leading to its spontaneous hydrolysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Alkyl chain diversification of JBIR-06</title><p id="Par11">As described above, both SmlC and NatC PKS modules include an additional methyltransferase (MT) domain, which is not present in the antimycin system (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In addition, the <italic>sml</italic> and <italic>nat</italic> clusters both lack the CCR enzyme<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, which supplies various alkylmalonyl-CoA extender substrates to generate the alkyl group variations. Unlike the antimycin system, the JBIR-06 and neoantimycin systems lost the alkyl chain variations and only form the dimethyl group at C-9 in JBIR-06 and at C-11 in the neoantimycins, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Therefore, in order to increase the structural variations of the medicinally important JBIR-06, we planned to utilize the previously reported engineered CCR, the structure-based mutant of AntE that can supply a wide range of longer and bulkier alkylmalonyl-CoAs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, which is not straightforward by organic synthesis. Importantly, the long-chain alkyl group in the antimycin-type depsipeptide scaffold is reportedly essential for the Bcl2/Bcl-xL inhibitory activity, which leads to cancer cell death<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. At the same time, we also engineered SmlC PKS module by introducing mutations into the AT domain in order to broaden its substrate specificity toward that of the antimycin system (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>), so that the engineered PKS can process the unnatural extender units. Thus, we introduced SmlCAT<sub>ant</sub>, in which the substrate recognition motif &#x0201c;LRIAPH&#x0201d; was substituted with MPAAAH from AntD (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">9</xref>, Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>, Supplementary Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>), into <italic>S. lividans</italic> harboring pKU518J06&#x00394;SmlC, with <italic>smlC</italic> deleted (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>, Supplementary Note&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>). We focused on this motif since it has been reported that the mutation of this site VDYASH in the AT domain of the erythromycin PKS altered the substrate preference<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Alkyl chain diversification of JBIR-06. <bold>a</bold> The reconstituted module structure for alkyl chain diversification. <bold>b</bold> HPLC analysis of the metabolites from transformants harboring (i) pKU518J06 and (ii) pKU518J06&#x00394;SmlC/pZH2-SmlCAT<sub>ant</sub>-AntEV350G. The chromatogram represents the UV absorbance at 320&#x02009;nm. <bold>c</bold> Engineering scheme and structure of the representative product <bold>7f</bold></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_5877_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1539"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">The introduction of AntEV350G and SmlCAT<sub>ant</sub> gave rise to the production of <bold>7a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>7f</bold>, with <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> values that are 28 (<bold>7a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>b</bold>), 42 (<bold>7c</bold>&#x02013;<bold>e</bold>), and 56 (<bold>7f</bold>) higher than <bold>2</bold> (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>), suggesting that they possess longer alkyl chains (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). Using NMR and HR-MS data, we characterized <bold>7a</bold>, <bold>7c</bold>, and <bold>7f</bold> as JBIR06-type tri-lactone depsipeptides with butyl (<bold>7a</bold>), pentyl (<bold>7c</bold>), and hexyl (<bold>7f</bold>) chains at the C-9 position (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>, Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">45</xref>, Supplementary Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">9</xref>). Compounds <bold>7b</bold>, <bold>7d</bold>, and <bold>7e</bold> were also identified as their minor derivatives (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">51</xref>, Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">10</xref>). Small amounts of <bold>7a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>7f</bold> were observed in the strain harboring pKU518J06 with AntEV350G, but these yields were 2&#x02013;3 times lower than that of the AT<sub>SmlC</sub>-mutated construct (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). These data suggested that the mutation into AT<sub>SmlC</sub> broadens the substrate specificity to accept a variety of extender substrates supplied by AntEV350G. Notably, the C-9 di-substituted pattern of <bold>2</bold> changed into a mono-substitution, suggesting that the MT domain of SmlC does not work when the longer alkyl chain has been incorporated. However, it should be noted that the yield of the native product <bold>2</bold> is still dominant (5.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7&#x02009;mg/L) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), indicating further optimization is required. Nonetheless, it was remarkable that the total yield of the newly obtained JBIR-06 derivatives with different alkyl chain structures, <bold>7a</bold>, <bold>7c</bold>, <bold>7e</bold>, and <bold>7f</bold> (3.8&#x02009;mg/L), is almost comparable with that of <bold>2</bold>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par13">In this study, we accomplished three manipulations of the antimycin-type NRPS-PKS assembly lines and obtained nine depsipeptides (<bold>4</bold>, <bold>5</bold>, <bold>6</bold>, <bold>7a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>f</bold>) with different lactone ring sizes in substantial yields. It is quite remarkable that the yields of the compounds which we obtained in the engineered NRPS-PKS system are 5&#x02013;10 times higher than those in the reported module assembly line engineering<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. For the ring reduction approach, the linker between the ACP and TE domains smoothly connected the TE<sub>SmlC</sub> domain to the ACP<sub>NatC</sub>, resulting in the production of the tri-lactone <bold>4</bold> without significant drop of yield. Since TE<sub>SmlC</sub> macrocyclizes a tri-lactone compound which shares the same structures around the carboxyl and attacking hydroxyl groups as the original substrate, we anticipated that TE<sub>SmlC</sub> would work efficiently in the engineered system. In this approach, we reversely traced the evolutionary flow from the Sml to Nat modules, which facilitated the efficient reconstruction without large changes in the intermediate structures.</p><p id="Par14">In the ring expansion approach, the intersubunit docking domain at the C-terminus of the NatC module was added onto the SmlC domain, instead of the TE domain. Remarkably, the yield of the ring-expanded compound <bold>5</bold> was same degree as that of original products <bold>2</bold>. This data demonstrated that our strategy was effective to newly generate the module interactions. The interactions between NatC and NatD are likely to be different from the known systems, because the N-terminus of NatD lacks a predicted secondary structure consistent with the crystal structure of the docking domain from the EpoB NRPS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. The interactions between PKS and NRPS modules are still elusive, and need to be clarified by X-ray crystallization or cryo-EM analyses for future engineering studies.</p><p id="Par15">In our alkyl chain diversification approach, we introduced the broad substrate specificity of AntD into SmlC by mutating the AT substrate definition sequence. The substrate definition sequence &#x0201c;M<sub>701</sub>PAAAH<sub>706</sub>&#x0201d; in AntD is exceptionally simple, and it likely causes the expansion of substrate binding cavity. In fact, the two alanines corresponding to A<sub>703</sub> and A<sub>705</sub> were recently shown to be the residues that influence substrate specificity of SpnD-AT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. In the case of the systems with relaxed substrate specificity for acyl-CoAs, the CCR enzyme family<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> could be used to diversify product structures in future. The butyl-, 3-methylbutyl, and hexylmalonyl-CoAs provided by AntEV350G for <bold>7a</bold>, <bold>7c</bold>, and <bold>7f</bold> production were likely synthesized from 2,3-hexenoyl, 5-methyl-2,3-hexenoyl, and 2,3-octenoyl-CoAs. This side chain pattern was also observed in our previous engineering studies for <bold>1</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, implying the wide distribution of 2,3-alkenoyl-CoA in <italic>Streptomyces</italic>. As the original product (<bold>2</bold>) was still dominant in our system, the expansion of extender unit specificity of KS domain should be effective to increase the yields. With expecting the higher yield, we also tested several chimeric PKS module constructs such as KS<sub>SmlC</sub>-AT<sub>AntD</sub>-MT ACP TE<sub>SmlC</sub> with domain swapping strategy (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">52</xref>); however, none of them afforded any detectable products (data not shown). Further adoption of the recently identified &#x0201c;optimal&#x0201d; fusion junctions for AT-domain swaping<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup> may improve the product yields.</p><p id="Par16">Consequently, this study paves the way for the rational engineering of NRPS-PKS assembly machineries, by following the evolution of enzymes in nature. Through sequence comparisons, we can learn how nature cut and paste module structures. In addition, by employing the enzymes to give the various functional groups, we can further increase the diversity of products, as we have done previously with CCR enzymes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. The <italic>Escherichia</italic>-<italic>Streptomyces</italic> shuttle BAC genetic platform that we used is also an important factor to readily build artificial biosynthetic modules. The productivity of the engineered modules would be improved by optimizing the interactions betwen domains and modules based on the structural analysis of the whole module complex, even though it still remains a technically challenging endeavor. This study confirmed that the strategies applied to pure PKS and NRPS systems can be productively used for hybrid PKS/NRPS system. Furthermore, this study serves as an exemplar for bioengineering productive biosynthetic assembly lines that produce unnatural polyketide-non-ribosomal peptides.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>General experimental procedures</title><p id="Par17">Solvents and chemicals were purchased from Wako Chemicals Ltd. (Tokyo, Japan) or Kanto Chemical Co., Inc. (Tokyo, Japan), unless noted otherwise. Oligonucleotide primers were purchased from Eurofins Genetics (Tokyo, Japan) and Sigma-Aldrich Japan (Tokyo, Japan). PCR was performed using a TaKaRa PCR Thermal Cycler Dice<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Gradient (TaKaRa), with Prime Star Max (Takara). Sequence analyses were performed by Eurofins Genetics (Tokyo). Analytical and preparative HPLC were performed on a Shimadzu Prominence system. Silica gel column chromatography was performed using Wakogel C-200. NMR spectra were obtained at 500&#x02009;MHz (<sup>1</sup>H) and 125&#x02009;MHz (<sup>13</sup>C) with a JEOL ECX-500 or ECZ-500 spectrometer, and chemical shifts were recorded with reference to solvent signals (<sup>1</sup>H NMR: CDCl<sub>3</sub> 7.26&#x02009;ppm; <sup>13</sup>C NMR: CDCl<sub>3</sub> 77.0&#x02009;ppm). All NMR spectra were measured by using CDCl<sub>3</sub> as solvent. Samples for LC-MS analysis were injected into an Shimadzu Prominence system HPLC-MicroTOF mass spectrometer (Bruker Daltonics), using electrospray ionization with a COSMOSIL 2.5C<sub>18</sub>-MS-II column (2.0 i.d.&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;75&#x02009;mm; Nacalai Tesque, Inc.).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Genome sequencing</title><p id="Par18">The complete genome sequence of <italic>Streptomyces</italic> sp. ML55 and <italic>Streptomyces orinoci</italic> NBRC13466 was determined by using a Miseq (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA) and a PacBio RS II (Pacific Biosciences, Menlo Park, CA, USA). End sequencing was carried out using the BigDye terminator ver3.1 kit (Applied Biosystems). The obtained sequence data were assembled using HGAP2 (Pacific Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Analytical conditions</title><p id="Par19"><italic>S. lividans</italic> transformants were cultured at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 4 days in 500&#x02009;mL flasks containing 100&#x02009;mL A3M medium (Glucose 0.5%, Glycerol 2%, Soluble Starch 2%, Pharmamedia 1.5%, Yeast extract 0.3%, HP20 1%, pH&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.0). After filtering, the mycelia were lyophilized to dryness. Dried mycelia were extracted by MeOH:CHCl<sub>3</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2:1. The extraction solution was concentrated in vacuo to remove the solvent. Products from <italic>S. lividans</italic> TK21 transformant were analyzed by HPLC equipped with a STAR Separar C18G 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;m column (4.6 i.d.&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;250&#x02009;mm, Rikaken Co. Ltd., Nagoya, Japan), with a solvent system of 0.1% formic acid (solvent A) and acetonitrile containing 0.1% formic acid (solvent B), at a flow rate of 1.0&#x02009;mL/min and a column temperature of 40&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Separation was performed with solvent B/solvent A (50:50), a linear gradient from 50:50 to 80:20 within the following 5&#x02009;min, an isocratic elution with 80:20 within the following 25&#x02009;min.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Isolation of the metabolites from <italic>S. lividans</italic> TK21</title><p id="Par20"><italic>S. lividans/</italic>pKU518nant&#x00394;<italic>natD</italic>::<italic>smlCTE</italic> was cultured at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 4 days in 30&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;500&#x02009;mL flasks containing 100&#x02009;mL A3M medium (Glucose 0.5%, Glycerol 2%, Soluble Starch 2%, Pharmamedia 1.5%, Yeast extract 0.3%, HP20 1%, pH&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.0). After filtering, the mycelia were lyophilized to dryness. Dried mycelia were extracted by MeOH:CHCl<sub>3</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2:1. The extraction solution was concentrated in vacuo to remove the solvent. The extract was subjected to silica-gel column chromatography and eluted using chloroform 100%. <italic>S. lividans/</italic>pKU518J06&#x00394;<italic>smlCTE</italic>/pZH2-NatD was cultured at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 4 days in 5.0&#x02009;L A3M medium, and <italic>S. lividans/</italic>pKU518J06&#x00394;<italic>smlC</italic>/pZH2-SmlCAT<sub>ant</sub> was cultured at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 4 days in 12&#x02009;L A3M medium. The compounds were extracted and purified by silica-gel as described above.</p><p id="Par21">Fractions containing <bold>4</bold> was further purified by reverse-phase preparative HPLC equipped with an 5C18-MS-II column (Nacalai Tesque, Kyoto, Japan, 5 &#x00394;m, 10&#x02009;mm i.d.&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;250&#x02009;mm). Separation was performed with solvent B (CH<sub>3</sub>CN)/solvent A (0.05% formic acid) (70:30), a linear gradient from 70:30 to 85:15 within the following 10&#x02009;min, a linear gradient from 85:15 to 100:0 within the following 0.5&#x02009;min, 100:0 for 4.0 additional min, to yield <bold>4</bold> (1.1&#x02009;mg). Fractions containing <bold>5</bold> and <bold>6</bold> were further purified by preparative HPLC equipped with an YMC-Triant C18 column (YMC, Kyoto, Japan, 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;m, 10&#x02009;mm i.d.&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;250&#x02009;mm) using acetonitrile-0.05% formic acid (80:20) as the eluting solvent (flow rate 1.0&#x02009;mL/min), to yield <bold>5</bold> (2.1&#x02009;mg) and <bold>6</bold> (2.2&#x02009;mg). Fractions containing <bold>7a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>f</bold> were further purified by preparative HPLC equipped with an YMC-Triant C18 column (YMC, Kyoto, Japan, 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;m, 10&#x02009;mm i.d.&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;250&#x02009;mm) using acetonitrile-0.1% formic acid (80:20) as the eluting solvent (flow rate 3.0&#x02009;mL/min), and further purified by preparative HPLC equipped with an X-select HSS T3 column (Waters, MA, USA, 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;m, 10&#x02009;mm i.d.&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;250&#x02009;mm) using acetonitrile-0.1% formic acid (70:30) as the eluting solvent (flow rate 3.0&#x02009;mL/min) to yield <bold>7a</bold> (2.4&#x02009;mg), <bold>7b</bold> (0.6&#x02009;mg), acetonitrile-0.1% formic acid (72.5:27.5) to yield <bold>7c</bold> (1.0&#x02009;mg), <bold>7d</bold> (0.2&#x02009;mg), <bold>7e</bold> (0.3&#x02009;mg), and acetonitrile-0.1% formic acid (75:25) to yield <bold>7f</bold> (2.9&#x02009;mg).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Chemical synthesis of isoleucic/leucic acids</title><p id="Par22">L-isoleucine (100&#x02009;mg) was dissolved in 1.25&#x02009;M H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> (5&#x02009;mL) and stirred on ice, and ice-cold aqueous solution of NaNO<sub>2</sub> (0.2&#x02009;g/mL, 4&#x02009;mL) was slowly added and stirred for 2&#x02009;h on ice. Then, the reaction mixture was moved to room temperature, and further stirred for 15&#x02009;h at room temperature. Finally, the reaction mixture was directly extracted with diethyl ether (5&#x02009;mL&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2), and organic layer was dried with Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. The organic solvent was removed under reduced pressure and L-isoleucic acid was obtained as colorless oil (56&#x02009;mg). Other isoleucic/leucic acids were also prepared from corresponding amino acids by diazotization except for L-leucic acid (Wako Pure Chemical Industries, Ltd.).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Methyl esterification of isoleucic/leucic acids</title><p id="Par23">A methanol solution of L-isoleucic acid (50&#x02009;mg/10&#x02009;mL) in eggplant flask was stirred at room temperature. Then, thionyl chloride (1.2&#x02009;mL) was slowly added to the solution. The mixture was further stirred for 2&#x02009;h at 100&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (in reflux), and cooled to room temperature. The solvent was removed under reduced pressure and the residue was suspended in diethyl ether (10&#x02009;mL). The suspension was washed with saturated sodium hydrogen carbonate (10&#x02009;mL&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2), and the organic layer was dried with Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. Finally, the ether was removed by evaporation and the L-leucic acid methyl ester was obtained as colorless oil (42&#x02009;mg). For other isoleucic/leucic acid methyl esters were also prepared in the same procedure.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Preparation of N-TFA-threonine methyl esters</title><p id="Par24">L-threonine (1&#x02009;mg) was dissolved in hydrogen chloride-methanol reagent (5&#x02013;10%) (0.5&#x02009;mL, purchased from Tokyo Chemical Industry Co., Ltd.), and the mixture was incubated for 30&#x02009;min at 100&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (in reflux). The solvent was removed under reduced pressure. To the residue, a 1:1 mixture of trifluoroacetic anhydride (TFAA)/dichloromethane (0.5&#x02009;mL) was added and the mixture was incubated for 30&#x02009;min at 100&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (in reflux). After the reaction, the solvents were removed by argon gas injection. Finally, the residue was dissolved in acetone (0.5&#x02009;mL) and subjected to GC-MS analysis as a standard. The other stereoisomers of threonine were also derivatized in the same procedure and subjected to GC-MS analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Hydrolysis of <bold>5</bold> and <bold>6</bold></title><p id="Par25">Compound <bold>5</bold> (0.1&#x02009;mg) was added to 6&#x02009;M hydrochloric acid (0.5&#x02009;mL) and stirred for 24&#x02009;h at 110&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (in reflux). After the reaction, the mixture was cooled on ice to room temperature, and the solvent was removed by lyophilization. The resulting residue was used for further chemical derivatization as noted below. Compound <bold>6</bold> was also hydrolyzed by the same procedure.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Chemical derivatization of hydrolysates of <bold>5</bold> and <bold>6</bold></title><p id="Par26">The hydrolysate of <bold>5</bold> (from 0.1&#x02009;mg) was in hydrogen chloride-methanol reagent (5&#x02013;10%) (0.5&#x02009;mL), and the mixture was incubated for 30&#x02009;min at 100&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (in reflux). The reaction mixture was divided in two equal parts, and the solvent was removed under reduced pressure. The half part of the residue was dissolved in acetone (0.5&#x02009;mL) and subjected GC-MS to analyze isoleucine/leucine acids as methyl ester. The remaining half part of the residue was dissolved in the mixture of TFAA/dichloromethane (0.5&#x02009;mL), and the mixture was incubated for 30&#x02009;min at 100&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (in reflux). The solvents were removed by argon and the residue was dissolved in acetone (0.5&#x02009;mL), which was subject to the GC-MS to analyze threonine moiety as the N-TFA methyl ester. The hydrolysate of <bold>6</bold> (from 0.1&#x02009;mg) was also derivatized and subjected to the GC-MS analysis in the same procedure.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>GC-MS analysis condition</title><p id="Par27">CP-Chirasil Dex-CB column (Alltech, 0.25&#x02009;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;25&#x02009;m; He as the carrier gas; program rate: 50&#x02013;150&#x02009;&#x000b0;C at 5&#x02009;&#x000b0;C/min, 150&#x02013;200&#x02009;&#x000b0;C at 50&#x02009;&#x000b0;C/min).</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>GC-MS for threonine derivatives</title><p id="Par28">CP-Chirasil Dex-CB column (Alltech, 0.25&#x02009;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;25&#x02009;m; He as the carrier gas; program rate: 50&#x02013;200&#x02009;&#x000b0;C at 6&#x02009;&#x000b0;C/min).</p></sec><sec id="Sec120"><title>Data availability</title><p id="Par30">The DNA sequences of JBIR-06 and neoantimycin biosynthetic gene clusters were registered as <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/LC375135.1">LC375135</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/LC375136">LC375136</ext-link> in DDBJ, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec23"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41467_2018_5877_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41467_2018_5877_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Peer Review File</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary Information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41467-018-05877-z.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by a Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology, Japan (JSPS KAKENHI Grant Number JP15H01836, JP16H06443, JP16K13084, and JP17H04763), JST/NSFC Strategic International Collaborative Research Program Japan-China, Kobayashi International Scholarship Foundation, and National Natural Science Foundation of China Grants (21520102004). We also thank Prof. Hiroyasu Onaka for providing genetic tools.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>T.A., L.Z., W.L., K.S. and I.A. designed the experiments. T.A., T.F., L.Z., S.H., Z.H., J.H., I.K. and H.I. performed the experiments. T.A., T.F., L.Z. and I.A. analyzed the data. T.A., K.S. and I.A. wrote the paper.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polyketide and nonribosomal peptide antibiotics: modularity and versatility</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2004</year><volume>303</volume><fpage>1805</fpage><lpage>1810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1094318</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15031493?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15031493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polyketide-nonribosomal peptide epothilone antitumor agents: the EpoA, B, C subunits</article-title><source>J. Ind. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10295-003-0044-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12707798?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12707798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wakimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Calyculin biogenesis from a pyrophosphate protoxin produced by a sponge symbiont</article-title><source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>648</fpage><lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.1573</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24974231?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24974231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wakimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Egami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calyculin: nature&#x02019;s way of making the sponge-derived cytotoxin</article-title><source>Nat. Prod. Rep.</source><year>2016</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5NP00123D</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26923942?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26923942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sattely</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischbach</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Total biosynthesis: in vitro reconstitution of polyketide and nonribosomal peptide pathways</article-title><source>Nat. Prod. Rep.</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>757</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b801747f</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18663394?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18663394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structural biology of biosynthetic megaenzymes</article-title><source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>660</fpage><lpage>670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.1883</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26284673?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26284673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundaram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hertweck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On-line enzymatic tailoring of polyketides and peptides in thiotemplate systems</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbpa.2016.01.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26859622?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26859622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nietlispach</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Broadhurst</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multienzyme docking in hybrid megasynthetases</article-title><source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.2007.61</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18066054?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18066054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dowling</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural elements of an NRPS cyclization domain and its intermodule docking domain</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2016</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>12432</fpage><lpage>12437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1608615113</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27791103?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27791103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Engineering polyketide synthases and nonribosomal peptide synthetases</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sbi.2013.06.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23838175?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23838175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bozh&#x000fc;y&#x000fc;k</surname><given-names>KAJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>De novo design and engineering of non-ribosomal peptide synthetases</article-title><source>Nat. Chem.</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchem.2890</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29461518?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29461518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sieber</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evidence for a monomeric structure of nonribosomal peptide synthetases</article-title><source>Chem. Biol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1074-5521(02)00214-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12323374?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12323374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarry</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmeing</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Piecing together nonribosomal peptide synthesis</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sbi.2018.01.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29444491?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29444491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenke-Kodama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dittmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary implications of bacterial polyketide synthases</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2027</fpage><lpage>2039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msi193</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15958783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15958783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ridley</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Khosla</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of polyketide synthases in bacteria</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>4595</fpage><lpage>4600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0710107105</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18250311?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18250311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exploiting the mosaic structure of trans-acyltransferase polyketide synthases for natural product discovery and pathway dissection</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt1379</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18223641?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18223641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medema</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cimermancic</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischbach</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systematic computational analysis of biosynthetic gene cluster evolution: lessons for engineering biosynthesis</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e1004016</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25474254?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25474254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ClusterCAD: a computational platform for type I modular polyketide synthase design</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>D509</fpage><lpage>D515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx893</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29040649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29040649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimycin-type depsipeptides: discovery, biosynthesis, chemical synthesis, and bioactivities</article-title><source>Nat. Prod. Rep.</source><year>2016</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1146</fpage><lpage>1165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C6NP00004E</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27307039?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27307039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beyond ethylmalonyl-CoA: the functional role of crotonyl-CoA carboxylase/reductase homologs in expanding polyketide diversity</article-title><source>Nat. Prod. Rep.</source><year>2012</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C1NP00082A</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22124767?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22124767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent advances in the biosynthesis of unusual polyketide synthase substrates</article-title><source>Nat. Prod. Rep.</source><year>2016</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5NP00112A</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26571143?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26571143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Screening and engineering the synthetic potential of carboxylating reductases from central metabolism and polyketide biosynthesis</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><year>2015</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>13457</fpage><lpage>13461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201505282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rational control of polyketide extender units by structure-based engineering of a crotonyl-CoA carboxylase/reductase in antimycin biosynthesis</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><year>2015</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>13664</fpage><lpage>13667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ange.201506899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rui</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enzymatic synthesis of dilactone scaffold of antimycins</article-title><source>ACS Chem. Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1956</fpage><lpage>1961</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cb300416w</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22971101?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22971101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biosynthetic pathway for high structural diversity of a common dilactone core in antimycin production</article-title><source>Org. Lett.</source><year>2012</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>4142</fpage><lpage>4145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ol301785x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22861048?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22861048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>De novo biosynthesis of terminal alkyne-labeled natural products</article-title><source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.1718</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25531891?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25531891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multiplexing of combinatorial chemistry in antimycin biosynthesis: expansion of molecular diversity and utility</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><year>2013</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>12308</fpage><lpage>12312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201305569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ueda, J. Y. et al. A novel antimycin-like compound, JBIR-06, from <italic>Streptomyces</italic> sp. ML55. <italic>J. Antibiot</italic>. <bold>61</bold>, 241&#x02013;244 (2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cassinelli, G., Grein, A., Orezzi, P., Pennella, P. &#x00026; Sanfilippo, A. New antibiotics produced by <italic>Streptoverticillium orinoci</italic>, n.sp. <italic>Arch. Mikrobiol</italic>. <bold>55</bold>, 358&#x02013;368 (1967).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glucose-regulated proteins in cancer: molecular mechanisms and therapeutic potential</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Cancer</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrc3701</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24658275?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24658275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect on tumor cells of blocking survival response to glucose deprivation</article-title><source>J. Natl. Can. Inst.</source><year>2004</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>1300</fpage><lpage>1310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djh243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanner</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemical and biosynthetic evolution of the antimycin-type depsipeptides</article-title><source>Mol. Biosyst.</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2712</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c3mb70219g</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23989727?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23989727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skyrud</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of the 15-membered ring depsipeptide neoantimycin</article-title><source>ACS Chem. Biol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1398</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acschembio.8b00298</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29693372?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29693372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Omura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cane</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-minimized Streptomyces host for the heterologous expression of secondary metabolism</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>2646</fpage><lpage>2651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0914833107</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20133795?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20133795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Engineered Streptomyces avermitilis host for heterologous expression of biosynthetic gene cluster for secondary metabolites</article-title><source>ACS Synth. Biol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/sb3001003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23654282?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23654282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nuclear magnetic resonance and biosynthetic studies of neoantimycin and structure elucidation of isoneoantimycin, a minor metabolite related to neoantimycin</article-title><source>J. Nat. Prod.</source><year>1998</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>978</fpage><lpage>981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/np9800194</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9722479?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9722479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zvanych</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanner</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Magarvey</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical variation from the neoantimycin depsipeptide assembly line</article-title><source>Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett.</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>5123</fpage><lpage>5127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bmcl.2013.07.031</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23932359?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23932359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cane</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Khosla</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular recognition between ketosynthase and acyl carrier protein domains of the 6-deoxyerythronolide B synthase</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>22066</fpage><lpage>22071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1014081107</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21127271?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21127271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure of a modular polyketide synthase</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2014</year><volume>510</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature13423</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24965652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24965652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of epothilone intermediates with alternate starter units: engineering polyketide-nonribosomal interfaces</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><year>2003</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>3917</fpage><lpage>3921</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.200352077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Engineering a polyketide with a longer chain by insertion of an extra module into the erythromycin-producing polyketide synthase</article-title><source>Chem. Biol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1074-5521(01)00024-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11358694?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11358694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of the macrocycle-forming thioesterase domain of the erythromycin polyketide synthase: Versatility from a unique substrate channel</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>14808</fpage><lpage>14813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.011399198</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11752428?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang, Y., Buchholz, F., Muyrers, J. P. P., &#x00026; Stewart, A.F. New technology. A new logic for DNA engineering using recombination in <italic>Escherichia coli. Nat. Genet.</italic><bold>20</bold>, 123&#x02013;128 (1998).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bodur</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Basaga</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bcl-2 inhibitors: emerging drugs in cancer therapy</article-title><source>Curr. Med. Chem.</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1804</fpage><lpage>1820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/092986712800099839</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22414090?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22414090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alteration of the substrate specificity of a modular polyketide synthase acyltransferase domain through site-specific mutations</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2001</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>15464</fpage><lpage>15470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi015864r</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11747421?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11747421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Del Vecchio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Active-site residue, domain and module swaps in modular polyketide synthases</article-title><source>J. Ind. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10295-003-0062-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12811585?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12811585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundermann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enzyme-directed mutasynthesis: a combined experimental and theoretical approach to substrate recognition of a polyketide synthase</article-title><source>ACS Chem. Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/cb300505w</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23181268?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23181268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koryakina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inversion of extender unit selectivity in the erythromycin polyketide synthase by acyltransferase domain engineering</article-title><source>ACS Chem. Biol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acschembio.6b00732</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28103677?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28103677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hertweck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rational design of modular polyketide synthases: morphing the aureothin pathway into a luteoreticulin assembly line</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><year>2014</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1560</fpage><lpage>1564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201308176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Freedom and constraint in engineered noncolinear polyketide assembly lines</article-title><source>Chem. Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chembiol.2014.12.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25660274?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25660274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wlodek, A. et al. Diversity oriented biosynthesis via accelerated evolution of modular gene clusters. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 1206 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li, Y. et al. Structural basis of a broadly selective acyltransferase from the polyketide synthase of splenocin. <italic>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed</italic>. 10.1002/anie.201802805 (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuzawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive in vitro analysis of acyltransferase domain exchanges in modular polyketide synthases and its application for short-chain ketone production</article-title><source>ACS Synth. Biol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acssynbio.6b00176</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27548700?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27548700</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>