<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An obvious question then is whether it was in fact the increase in deer populations, rather than abundance of non-native plants and non-native earthworms, that is responsible for the now widespread depauperate plant communities at our sites? Such negative effects of high deer populations on local plant and animal diversity, abundance, and cover have been described for many other locations and regions using long-term datasets (
 <xref rid="plx026-B14" ref-type="bibr">Côté 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2004
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="plx026-B97" ref-type="bibr">Wiegmann and Waller 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="plx026-B75" ref-type="bibr">Rogers 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2009
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="plx026-B32" ref-type="bibr">Goetsch 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2011
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="plx026-B55" ref-type="bibr">Martin 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2011
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="plx026-B31" ref-type="bibr">Frerker 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="plx026-B11" ref-type="bibr">Chips 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2015
 </xref>) and our sites have likely undergone similar “sorting” processes. While we lack detailed historic records from our study locations, we documented that protecting individuals of preferred browse species such as 
 <italic>T. recurvatum</italic>, 
 <italic>E. divaricata</italic>, 
 <italic>M. racemosum</italic> and 
 <italic>P. pubescens</italic> from deer browse by fencing, or lowering deer browse pressure by culling, had beneficial effects on growth and reproductive output (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plx026-F4">Figs. 4</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plx026-F8">8–</xref>
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plx026-F10">10</xref>), two important factors that may ultimately contribute to positive population growth rates (
 <xref rid="plx026-B94" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Mopper 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="plx026-B46" ref-type="bibr">Knight 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2009a
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="plx026-B43" ref-type="bibr">Kalisz 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2014
 </xref>). This benefit accrued despite the remaining potential threats of biotic influences (invasive plants and introduced earthworms) or other regional factors such as climate change, changes in nutrient deposition or previous land use history that were not affected by deer culling or fencing. Thus, we find support for our third hypothesis. Together, this provides clear and compelling evidence that deer are the responsible driver (
 <xref rid="plx026-B53" ref-type="bibr">MacDougall and Turkington 2005</xref>) for demise of native species, and that the rise of at least the three non-native invasive plant species we investigated is but a symptom of other underlying stressors (see also Blossey et al, this issue). Thus, these three non-native species can be considered passengers rather than drivers of change in plant community composition (
 <xref rid="plx026-B53" ref-type="bibr">MacDougall and Turkington 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="plx026-B19" ref-type="bibr">Dávalos 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2015b
 </xref>).
</p>
