<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the case of walnut leaves, a mixture of various organic solvents and water as a useful extraction system for obtaining and analyzing the antioxidant content of the prepared extracts has been considered. In this way, different ratios of water and other solvents were employed by different authors. For example, the microwave-assisted extraction (MAE) method was compared with three others for the extraction and determination of TPC and TFC in walnut leaves. It was found that TPC and TFC for the prepared extracts of walnut leaves in MAE method was 4 min, higher than that when using maceration extraction (ME), UAE, and SE for 24 h, 15 min, and 6 h, respectively. Compared with other extraction methods, MAE reduced the extraction time. It was found that blanching had no significant effect on the TPC of walnut leaves. Different methanol concentrations (20, 40, 60, 80, 99.8% 
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) were tested and the highest TPC was obtained using 60% methanol [
 <xref rid="B187-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">187</xref>]. The hydroethanolic leaf extract of walnut (20–70% 
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) was prepared to evaluate their antidiarrheal and antinociceptive effects in rats [
 <xref rid="B170-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">170</xref>]. The effect of 50% ethanolic extract prepared from walnut green husk and leaf on cutaneous Leishmaniasis caused by Leishmania major in BALB/c mice were also reported by Sharafi Chegeni, et al. [
 <xref rid="B162-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">162</xref>]. In a double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial study reported by Rabiei, et al. [
 <xref rid="B173-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">173</xref>], a hydroalcoholic extract (70%) of walnut leaves was used to evaluate its effects on blood glucose levels in type 2 diabetic patients and the major cardiovascular risk factors.
</p>
