<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In an investigation by Vieira, et al. [
 <xref rid="B172-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">172</xref>], they tried to compare the ME and MAE methods for enhancing the extraction of valuable compounds from walnut leaves. For optimizing time, temperature and ethanol–water proportion as the main variables of the ME and MAE systems, an experimental design assisted by RSM was developed. The achieved optimum conditions have been reported as 112.5 min, 61.3 °C and 50.4% of ethanol for the ME method; and 3.0 min, 107.5 °C and 67.9% of ethanol for MAE method. Authors reported the highest TPC and total flavonol content (TFOC) for the MAE method. The hydroethanolic leaf extract was obtained by HAE (50.4%, 
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>; 30 g/mL at 61.3 °C for 116 min) at the same optimized conditions for the analysis of phenolic compounds [
 <xref rid="B206-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">206</xref>]. For the qualitative and quantitative analysis of flavonoids from 
 <italic class="italic">J. regia</italic> L. leaves using high-performance liquid chromatography coupled tandem mass spectrometry with electrospray ionization and negative ion detection (HPLC-ESI-MS/MS), Zhao, et al. [
 <xref rid="B167-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">167</xref>] used 60% ethanolic solution as the extraction solvent. The effect of walnut leaf extract on cerebrum malformation in the fetuses of diabetic rats was studied using ethanol as the extraction solvent. In these studies, the powdered leaves were then allowed to soak in 70% ethanol and, at room temperature, re-extracted three times with fresh 96% ethanol [
 <xref rid="B168-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">168</xref>,
 <xref rid="B169-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">169</xref>]. The ethanol extract (80%) of Iranian walnut leaves was examined for its antibacterial activities on 
 <italic class="italic">Streptococcus mutans (S. mutans), Streptococcus salivarius (S. salivarius), Streptococcus sanguis (S. sanguinis), and Actinomyces viscosus (A. viscosus)</italic> using the microdilution method. It has been reported that Iranian walnut leaves had antibacterial effects on the examined bacteria and may be a suitable alternative remedy for the protection and treatment of dental plaque due to these microorganisms [
 <xref rid="B164-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">164</xref>]. Salimi, et al. [
 <xref rid="B165-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">165</xref>] tried to assess the cytotoxicity effects of various 
 <italic class="italic">J. regia</italic> L. leaf extracts in human cancer cell lines. They prepared total extracts with ethanol:water (80:20) at room temperature. Also, the leaf powder was extracted sequentially by solvents with different polarities, including hexane, chloroform, ethyl acetate, and methanol using the ME method. They observed that the yield of extraction for aqueous ethanol was 21.66%, while the yields for the obtained fractions of hexane, chloroform, ethyl acetate, and methanol were 8.66, 2.13, 2.68 and 12.01%, respectively.
</p>
