<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study was designed to investigate the effects of previously identified RAP polysaccharides [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-25-06045" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] on some of the biochemical, antioxidant, inflammatory biomarkers, and histological alterations in an animal model of inflammation. The results indicate that oral administrations of RAP with doses of 100 and 200 mg/kg before LPS administration reduced the levels of total inflammatory cytokines and markers. In the therapeutic approaches for organ injury after LPS administration, additional antioxidant compounds capable of preventing this damage is necessary. This research sheds light on the therapeutic efficacy of RAP extract against the systemic inflammatory response induced by LPS in rats. The current results showed that LPS administration encouraged an increase in plasma AST, ALT, and LDH activity, which could be due to an increase in hepatic cell membrane fluidity that led to the rerelease of the enzymes into the circulation. Pretreatment with RAP (100 and 200 mg/kg) significantly reduces the plasma concentration of AST, ALT, and LDH in inflammatory animals, which indicates the maintenance of hepatic cell function and structure. Such an increase in enzyme activity may be due to the antioxidant properties of the RAP to free radicals, thus protecting the integrity of the cell membranes from oxidative damage caused by LPS. Results of the current investigation showed that after administration of LPS, total bilirubin in inflammatory rats increased significantly. LPS administration causes several changes that lead to intrahepatic cholestasis-related hyperbilirubinemia, the severity of which depends on the degree of impairment of bile formation [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-06045" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-06045" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-25-06045" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. RAP (100 and 200 mg/kg) pretreatment resulted in a significant decrease in BIL in a dose-dependent manner. Following LPS administration, this study found a significant increase in CK, Cr, and BUN. These findings are consistent with the findings of Wali et al., 2020 [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-25-06045" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The results obtained indicate that, compared to normal groups, oral administration of RAP significantly reduced CK, Cr, and BUN activities. The loss of renal function is associated with an organ failure, which leads to the accumulation of a number of compounds during kidney disease development [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-25-06045" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In this study, changes in tissues and organs caused by oxidative stress were biochemically examined through experimentally inflicted systemic inflammation in rats by LPS. SOD and CAT are enzymes; SOD catalyzes hydrogen peroxide and oxygen degradation of superoxide, while CAT catalyzes the reduction of hydrogen peroxide reaction and thus prevents oxidative damage in cells [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-25-06045" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. These act equally as supportive antioxidant enzymes that offer protection against ROS [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-25-06045" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-25-06045" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. This study showed significant reductions in the liver and brains of LPS treated animals in these enzymes. In the present study, however, treatment with RAP (100 and 200 mg/kg) restored these activities. The present results observed a significant reduction in the albumin concentration following LPS administration. The decrease in albumin levels in the current investigation might be due to severe damage to the liver leading to a reduction in the albumin synthesizing capacity [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-25-06045" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-25-06045" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Pretreatment with RAP has restored the albumin concentration in a dose-dependent manner.
</p>
