<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Zilla spinosa</italic> (L.) Prantl., locally named shibrim or silla, is a perennial, spiny shrub belonging to the family Brassicaceae (Cruciferae), which comprises 321 genera and 3660 species distributed worldwide [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. It is widespread throughout the Asir region and is familiar to local inhabitants due to its prevalence in traditional medicine. The 
 <italic>Z. spinosa</italic> has been widely employed in traditional medicine for treating several illnesses, including gastrointestinal disorders and diabetes [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], urinary tract pains [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], diarrhea, gall bladder, kidney stones, liver and pancreas pain, respiratory ailments [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and rheumatism [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The plant is also found to have antimicrobial activity [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and anti-inflammatory, analgesic, and anticancer properties [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. A previous study [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] has investigated the hepatoprotective effect of 
 <italic>Z. spinosa</italic> extract against carbon tetrachloride-induced acute hepatotoxicity in rats and concluded that the hepatoprotective effect of the extract is attributed to the combined action of flavonoids. Similarly, El-Sharabasy and Mohamed [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] investigated the chemical constituents and biological activity of chloroform extract of 
 <italic>Z. spinosa</italic> aerial parts. They isolated and identified different compounds including three coumarin compounds, bergapten, psoralene, and umbleferone, and two triterpenes, 
 <italic>β</italic>-amyrin and friedelene, in addition to four phytosterols, campesterol, spinasterol, 
 <italic>β</italic>-sitosterol, and stigmasterol, and examined their anti-inflammatory, analgesic, and antimicrobial activities. The obtained results showed significant anti-inflammatory and antimicrobial effects of 
 <italic>Z. spinosa</italic> extract. Moreover, previous phytochemical studies of 
 <italic>Z. spinosa</italic> revealed various classes of phytochemicals including flavonoids, alkaloids, tannins, anthraquinones, saponins, sterols, and triterpenes [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Furthermore, Sekkoum et al. [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] analyzed the essential oil obtained from the aerial parts of 
 <italic>Zilla macroptera</italic>, a species collected from Algeria. They identified 72 compounds, with carvone oxide as the main compound.
</p>
