<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Food Sci Nutr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Food Sci Nutr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2048-7177</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">FSN3</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Food Science &#x00026; Nutrition</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2048-7177</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6475806</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.1000</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">FSN31000</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Efficiency of Tragacanth gum coating enriched with two different essential oils for deceleration of enzymatic browning and senescence of button mushroom (<italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic>)</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">NASIRI et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="fsn31000-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nasiri</surname><given-names>Mahshid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn31000-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="fsn31000-cr-0002" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Barzegar</surname><given-names>Mohsen</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6811-5566</contrib-id><address><email>mbb@modares.ac.ir</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn31000-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="fsn31000-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sahari</surname><given-names>Mohammad Ali</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8783-0530</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn31000-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="fsn31000-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Niakousari</surname><given-names>Mehrdad</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4557-9031</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn31000-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="fsn31000-aff-0001">
<label><sup>1</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Faculty of Agriculture, Department of Food Science and Technology</named-content>
<institution>Tarbiat Modares University</institution>
<named-content content-type="city">Tehran</named-content>
<country country="IR">Iran</country>
</aff><aff id="fsn31000-aff-0002">
<label><sup>2</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Faculty of Agriculture, Department of Food Science and Technology</named-content>
<institution>Shiraz University</institution>
<named-content content-type="city">Shiraz</named-content>
<country country="IR">Iran</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold><break/>
Mohsen Barzegar, Faculty of Agriculture, Department of Food Science and Technology, Tarbiat Modares University, Tehran, Iran.<break/>
Email: <email>mbb@modares.ac.ir</email><break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.2019.7.issue-4</issue-id><fpage>1520</fpage><lpage>1528</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> &#x000a9; 2019 Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. <copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2019 The Authors. <italic>Food Science &#x00026; Nutrition</italic> published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:FSN3-7-1520.pdf"/><abstract id="fsn31000-abs-0001"><title>Abstract</title><p>The effect of Tragacanth gum (T) coating containing (100, 500, and 1,000&#x000a0;mg/L) <italic>Satureja khuzistanica</italic> essential oil (S), <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss. essential oil (Z), and (1,000&#x000a0;mg/L) sodium metabisulfite (M) on mushroom (<italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic>) enzymatic browning and postharvest quality was examined throughout 16&#x000a0;days of cold storage. Mushroom respiration rate, soluble solids content (SSC), percentage of open caps, and sensory quality as well as factors related to browning such polyphenol oxidase (PPO), phenylalanine ammonia lyase (PAL), and peroxidase (POD) activities were figured out. The significant decrease in respiration rate, cap opening delay, and SSC enhancement was observed after treating mushrooms with TZ and TS. Moreover, TZ&#x02010; and TS&#x02010;treated mushrooms prevented enzymatic browning through inhibiting PPO and POD activities and increasing activity of PAL over the storing term. Additionally, the influence of TZ5 and TS5 (containing 500&#x000a0;mg/L essential oil) coatings was validated by sensory evaluation through protecting the overall quality of button mushrooms over the storage. Thus, Tragacanth coating enriched with essential oils might be an encouraging nomination for improving the modality of button mushroom and expanding its shelf life.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="fsn31000-kwd-0001">button mushroom</kwd><kwd id="fsn31000-kwd-0002">natural coating</kwd><kwd id="fsn31000-kwd-0003"><italic>Satureja khuzistanica</italic></kwd><kwd id="fsn31000-kwd-0004">shelf life</kwd><kwd id="fsn31000-kwd-0005"><italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Tarbiat Modares University</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="6473"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>component-id</meta-name><meta-value>fsn31000</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>April 2019</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:5.6.2.1 mode:remove_FC converted:22.04.2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="self-citation">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-1001">
<string-name>
<surname>Nasiri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Barzegar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sahari</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Niakousari</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Efficiency of Tragacanth gum coating enriched with two different essential oils for deceleration of enzymatic browning and senescence of button mushroom (<italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic>)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Sci Nutr</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1520</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1528</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.1000</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</p></notes></front><body><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0001"><label>1</label><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>
<italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic> Imbach (white button mushroom), with the first reports on the cultivation date from 1707, from France, produces about 32% of total edible mushroom in the world, extensively recognized for its nutritional, medicinal, and organoleptic attributes (Gao, Feng, &#x00026; Jiang, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Khan et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Rzymski, Mleczek, Niedzielski, Siwulskid, &#x00026; Asecka, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). <italic>A.&#x000a0;bisporus</italic> is a perishable food product that its shelf life may be limited by bacterial spoilage or enzymatic browning, depending on handling and storage conditions (Sapers, Miller, Pilizota, &#x00026; Kamp, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>).</p><p>A substitutable way for postponing ripening and alleviating postharvest decay of fruit is achieved by application of natural products (Tripathi &#x00026; Dubey, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). Edible coatings can provide an additional protective layer for fresh products and can also give the same effect as modified atmosphere storage in amending internal gas composition (Park, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>). Application of semi&#x02010;permeable obstacle versus O<sub>2</sub>, CO<sub>2</sub>, moisture, and solute movement has been revealed to expand the postharvest life of fruit and vegetables, increase the water barrier, inhibit microbial contamination, maintain flavor, reduce the degree of shrinkage distortion, and retard fat oxidation (Ali, Maqbool, Ramachandran, &#x00026; Alderson, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Jiang, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Jiang, Feng, Zheng, &#x00026; Li, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Polysaccharides, proteins, and lipids are different sources for production of edible films and coatings with particular characteristics (Raeisi, Tajik, Aliakbarlu, Mirhosseini, &#x00026; Hosseini, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Fruit quality protection has been achieved using several edible coatings, such as chitosan in fresh&#x02010;cut strawberry (Campaniello, Bevilacqua, Sinigaglia, &#x00026; Corbo, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>), gum Cordia in Chilgoza (Haq, Alam, &#x00026; Hasnain, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), and gum Arabic in mango fruit (Khaliq, Mohamed, Ali, Ding, &#x00026; Ghazalic, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>).</p><p>Tragacanth gum (T) is one of the three major exudate gums, which possesses a unique range of functionalities (Verbeken, Dierckx, &#x00026; Dewettinck, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). This natural and acidic polysaccharide secretes spontaneously or with a scrape on the different species of <italic>Astragalus</italic> plant. This gum composed of 30%&#x02013;40% Tragacanthin (water&#x02010;soluble and extremely branched) and 60%&#x02013;70% bassorin (insoluble but water&#x02010;swellable fraction)<italic>.</italic> Forms and structures of these two constituents are different. The ratio of Tragacanthin and bassorin strongly depends on variety (Azarikia &#x00026; Abbasi, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>).</p><p>Safety aspects of chemical additives caused increasing interest of application of natural preservative coatings with antimicrobial agents (Jiang, Feng, &#x00026; Zheng, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>), such as gum Arabic, aloe vera, chitosan containing thyme essential oil (Bill, Sivakumar, Korsten, &#x00026; Thompson, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>), chitosan coating augmented with thyme oil (Jiang et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>), and carboxymethyl cellulose&#x02010;based coatings containing <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss. essential oil and grape seed extract (Raeisi et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). These researches have revealed that essential oils (EOs) and extracts of various herbs and spices could be used as natural food preservers due to their antimicrobial acting. Like other biopolymers, Tragacanth gum is known as an appropriate carrier for natural antimicrobial and antioxidant complexes (Taban, Rahimi, Saharkhiz, Hadian, &#x00026; Zomorodian, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>).</p><p>
<italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss (Labiatae) is an herbal plant with several thin, hard, and highly ramified stems from family which found naturally in Iran, Pakistan, and Afghanistan. This plant with traditional title of Avishan Shirazi (in Iran) has been used as antiseptic, anesthetic, antispasmodic, and flavor composition in broad range of foods in Iran. The essential oil of <italic>Z.&#x000a0;multiflora</italic> Boiss. contains compounds with important pharmaceutical, antimicrobial, and antioxidant effects (Fathi, Sahari, Zangiabadi, &#x00026; Barzegar, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Kordsardouei, Barzegar, Sahari, &#x00026; Ebrahimipour, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Phenolic compounds, such as carvacrol and thymol, are the major components of the <italic>Z.&#x000a0;multiflora Boiss</italic>. essential oil (Z) (Dashipour et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>).</p><p>Another plant that is separated through southern part of Iran including Ilam, Lorestan, and Khuzestan provinces is <italic>Satureja khuzistanica</italic> Jamzad (Lamiaceae). It is a small shrub with branched stem approximately 30&#x000a0;cm high, densely leafy, covered with short white hairs (Moazeni, Saharkhiz, Hoseini, &#x00026; Mootabi Alavi, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Analgesic and an antiseptic characteristic of plant are considered by the people in southern region of Iran. A main component of wild <italic>S.&#x000a0;khuzistanica</italic> (&#x02264;90%) is monoterpene carvacrol (Hashemi, Niakousari, Saharkhiz, &#x00026; Eskandari, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>).</p><p>The purpose of this study was to investigate the effect of Tragacanth gum coating, individually and/or in combination with <italic>Z.&#x000a0;multiflora Boiss</italic>. essential oil (S) and <italic>S.&#x000a0;khuzistanica</italic> essential oil (Z) and sodium metabisulfite (M) as a chemical preservative (which widely used in the mushroom processing industry), on mushroom tissue browning, some physicochemical, and as well as sensorial changes during 16&#x000a0;days of storage in refrigerator (4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1&#x000b0;C).</p></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0002"><label>2</label><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0003"><label>2.1</label><title>Plant material</title><p>Button mushrooms were gathered from a local farm in Shiraz, Iran. Mushrooms were selected from the similar flower and zone of the shed so as to reduce probable alteration affected by cultivation and environment. During one hour of harvesting, the mushrooms were conveyed to the test center and then kept in dimness at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1&#x000b0;C and 90% relative humidity (RH). Mushrooms having good physical shape without any damage were selected to be used in the experiments.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0004"><label>2.2</label><title>
<italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss. and <italic>Satureja khuzistanica</italic> essential oils</title><p>Two essential oils (EOs) were acquired from Giah Essans (Gorgan, Iran). Their characteristics sheets indicate 98% pureness.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0005"><label>2.3</label><title>Tragacanth gum and coating treatments</title><p>The best kind of gum was obtained from a local shop, washed, dried, milled, and determined the optimum concentration of gum solution (0.6%), and ten different treatments were prepared based on Nasiri, Barzegar, Sahari, &#x00026; Niakousari, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>: (a) control (C, water washed, without coating); (b) Tragacanth gum coating (T); (c) gum coatings containing 100&#x000a0;mg/L S (TS1), (d) 500&#x000a0;mg/L S (TS5), (e) 1,000&#x000a0;mg/L S (TS10); (f) gum coatings containing 100&#x000a0;mg/L Z (TZ1), (g) 500&#x000a0;mg/L Z (TZ5), (h) 1,000&#x000a0;mg/L Z (TZ10); (i) 1,000&#x000a0;mg/L sodium metabisulfite (M); and (j) gum coating containing 1,000&#x000a0;mg/L metabisulfite (TM). They were placed in polyethylene (HDPE) containers and were kept for 16&#x000a0;days at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1&#x000b0;C and 95% RH pending further analysis, and every 4&#x000a0;days, three replicates from each treatment group were analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0006"><label>2.4</label><title>Respiration rate</title><p>Respiration rate of samples was measured using method described by Li, Zhang, and Yu (<xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0007"><label>2.5</label><title>Soluble solids content</title><p>Mushrooms were crushed in a pounder. The juice was pressed and analyzed for the soluble solids content (SSC). The measurement was carried out in a CARL Zeiss refractometer model 78969 (Germany) at 25&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0008"><label>2.6</label><title>Percent open caps and overall acceptability</title><p>The principles of evaluating the percentage of open caps were in accordance with development of the umbrella&#x02010;like form of the cap followed by detachment of veil. The percent open caps were measured using known number of mushrooms based on Equation (<xref rid="fsn31000-disp-0001" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>):<disp-formula id="fsn31000-disp-0001"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="nlm-math-1"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mtext>Open</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mtext>caps</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>oc</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>N</italic>
<sub>oc</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;number of opened cap mushrooms; <italic>N</italic>
<sub>t</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;total number of mushrooms.</p><p>The consumer acceptance of the product was studied using 10 panelists with age ranging from 25 to 40&#x000a0;years. Panelists were trained based on the method described by Ares, Parentelli, G&#x000e1;mbaro, Lareo, and Lema (<xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>). Mushrooms were served in closed, odorless plastic containers at room temperature. After opening polyethylene bags, evaluations were performed within 2&#x000a0;hr in order to avoid loss of off&#x02010;odors. The overall acceptability based on color, texture, and percent opened caps were done by round&#x02010;table basis using four&#x02010;point scale where 1&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;poor, 2&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;fair, 3&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;good, and 4&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;excellent (Jiang et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0009"><label>2.7</label><title>Determination of protein content and PPO, PAL, and POD activities</title><p>Enzymatic activity determined as explained by Gao et al. (<xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). The protein content determination was carried out as the method of Bradford (<xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">1976</xref>), with application of bovine serum albumin as a standard.</p><p>Polyphenol oxidase (EC 1.10.3.2) activity was investigated using incubating 0.5&#x000a0;ml of enzyme extract in 2.5&#x000a0;ml of buffered substrate (100&#x000a0;mM sodium phosphate, pH&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6.4, and 50&#x000a0;mM catechol), then detecting the change of absorbance at 398&#x000a0;nm. The quantity of enzyme caused 0.01 increases in absorbance per minute under the specified conditions defines one unit of PPO activity. The specific PPO activity was represented as U/mg protein.</p><p>Phenylalanine ammonia lyase (EC 4.3.1.5) measured spectrophotometrically using the substrate trans&#x02010;cinnamic acid at 290&#x000a0;nm. Three ml of the reaction mixture, containing 0.8&#x000a0;ml supernatant and 50&#x000a0;mM <sc>l</sc>&#x02010;phenylalanine in sodium borate buffer (200&#x000a0;mM, pH&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8.8), was incubated at 37&#x000b0;C; after 90&#x000a0;min, the reaction was interrupted by ice water. The amount of enzyme caused 0.01 absorbance rise in 1&#x000a0;hr under the assay conditions defined as one unit of PAL activity. The specific PAL activity was expressed as U/mg protein.</p><p>Peroxidase (EC 1.11.1.7) activity was analyzed by determining the absorbance of guaiacol. 50&#x000a0;mM sodium phosphate buffer (pH&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6.0), 5&#x000a0;mM guaiacol, 5&#x000a0;mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, and 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of tissue extract constructed the reaction mixture. One unit of POD activity was distinguished as the quantity of enzyme that leads to change of 0.01 absorbance per minute at 470&#x000a0;nm under the specified conditions. The specific POD activity was defined as U/mg protein.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0010"><label>2.8</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Experiments were conducted in triplicates. Data were analyzed using SPSS (version 16; IBM, USA). Analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Duncan's multiple range test was used to distinguish the treatments at <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0011"><label>3</label><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0012"><label>3.1</label><title>Effect of gum coating containing EOs on respiration rate</title><p>Figure <xref rid="fsn31000-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref> demonstrated the respiration rates of button mushrooms over 16&#x000a0;days of storage. The primary respiratory rate defined as CO<sub>2</sub> accumulation of mushrooms at first day was around 117.33&#x000a0;mg CO<sub>2</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;hr<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. During storage, significant reduction in respiration rate was found, which could be attributed to mushroom deterioration (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). At the end of storage time, the respiration rates of the control (92.4&#x000a0;mg CO<sub>2</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;hr<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and M (84.8&#x000a0;mg CO<sub>2</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;hr<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) samples were higher than TZ1 (75.6&#x000a0;mg CO<sub>2</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;hr<sup>&#x02212;1)</sup>, TZ5 (73.9&#x000a0;mg CO<sub>2</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;hr<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), TZ10 (71.9&#x000a0;mg CO<sub>2</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;hr<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), TS1 (78.8&#x000a0;mg CO<sub>2</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;hr<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), TS5 (76.0&#x000a0;mg CO<sub>2</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;hr<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), TS10 (74.2&#x000a0;mg CO<sub>2</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;hr<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), TM (77.8&#x000a0;mg CO<sub>2</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;hr<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), and T (79.0&#x000a0;mg CO<sub>2</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;hr<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) samples. Samples treated with TZ10 displayed a considerably inferior respiration rate than other treated or untreated samples. The respiration rate of mushrooms treated with gum contained EOs did not reveal substantial variation. The process by which cells obtain chemical energy by the consumption of oxygen and the release of carbon dioxide is known as respiration (Xu, Tian, Mab, Liu, &#x00026; Zhang, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Earlier investigation indicated that essential oil treatments had the effective role in falling the respiration rate of nectarine fruits (Abd El Wahab, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>), Tabarzeh grape (Abdolahi, Hassani, Ghosta, Bernousi, &#x00026; Meshkatalsadat, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>), and Crimson seedless grape (Abd El Wahab, Abd El Wahab, &#x00026; Kamel, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Furthermore, respiration rate reduction was observed in apple piece coated by alginate (Wong, Tillin, Hudson, &#x00026; Pavlath, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">1994</xref>) and mushrooms treated with alginate coating (Jiang, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Internal gas atmosphere modification, affected by TG coating, reduced CO<sub>2</sub> production and respiration rate. The permselectivity, gas obstacle specifications, and affiliation with relative humidity temperature of the edible coating applied to surface will appearance a crucial role in the variations in interior O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> levels. Obviously, the extreme limitation of gas exchange can cause anaerobiosis and the development of off&#x02010;flavor (Jiang et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Contrariwise, scientists have discovered that the essential oils isolated from Satureja could display antifungal specification (Farzaneh, Kiani, Sharifi, Reisi, &#x00026; Hadian, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Taban et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>) and the antimicrobial effects of ZEO applied in different coatings such as chitosan (Moradi, Tajik, Razavi Rohani, &#x00026; Oromiehie, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>), carboxy methyl cellulose (Dashipour et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>), and zein (Moradi, Tajik, Razavi Rohani, &#x00026; Mahmoudian, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>) have been reported. Consequently, interaction of gum and EOs could decrease respiration rate without increment of off&#x02010;flavor.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31000-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Effect of essential oil&#x02010;incorporated gum coating on respiration rate of button mushrooms stored at 4&#x000b0;C for 16&#x000a0;days. Vertical bars represent standard errors of means. C: control (without coating); M: 1,000&#x000a0;mg/L sodium metabisulfite; T: coating with Tragacanth gum (TG); TM: TG coating containing 1,000&#x000a0;mg/L metabisulfite; TS1: TG coating containing 100&#x000a0;mg/L of <italic>Satureja khuzistanica</italic> essential oil (S); TS5: 500&#x000a0;mg/L S; TS10: 1,000&#x000a0;mg/L S; TZ1: TG coating containing 100&#x000a0;mg/L <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss. essential oil (Z); TZ5: 500&#x000a0;mg/L Z; TZ10: 1,000&#x000a0;mg/L Z</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="FSN3-7-1520-g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0013"><label>3.2</label><title>Effect of gum coating containing essential oils on SSC</title><p>Soluble solids content enhancement was gradual during storage time (Figure <xref rid="fsn31000-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The control and MS samples exposed the highest SSC; it extended 7.80 and 7.47&#x000b0;Brix, compared with 5.80, 5.71, 5.53, 5.75, 5.69, 5.46, 5.82, and 5.58&#x000b0;Brix in TZ1&#x02010;, TZ5&#x02010;, TZ10&#x02010;, TS1&#x02010;, TS5&#x02010;, TS10&#x02010;, TM, and gum&#x02010;coated mushrooms (T), respectively. The observed surge in SSC is a sign of high respiration rate and retarding the senescence process (Jafri, Jha, Bunkar, &#x00026; Ram, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Another factor contributed to SSC increase in aged mushroom might be the cell wall polysaccharides and hemicellulose solubilization (Jiang et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). The increase in SSC of TZ10 and TS10 samples was slower and more gradual than the other samples. The coatings provided a promising semi&#x02010;permeable film on the surface of the fruit, adjusting the interior atmosphere by decreasing O<sub>2</sub> and/or enhancing CO<sub>2</sub> and suppressing production of ethylene. The synthesis and use of metabolites consequences lower SSC, due to the slower hydrolysis of carbohydrates to sugars, decelerated by decreased respiration rates (Ali et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Rohani, Zaipun, &#x00026; Norhayati, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>). The same effects were found by Khaliq et al. (<xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) presented a slow increase in SSC concerning mango coated with Arabic gum.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31000-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effect of essential oil&#x02010;incorporated TG coating on soluble solids content of button mushrooms stored at 4&#x000b0;C for 16&#x000a0;days. Vertical bars represent standard errors of means. For abbreviations see Figure <xref rid="fsn31000-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="FSN3-7-1520-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0014"><label>3.3</label><title>Effect of gum coating containing essential oils on percentage of open caps and overall acceptability</title><p>After 16&#x02010;day storage, the proportion of opened caps mushrooms increased in all samples (Table <xref rid="fsn31000-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Control (C) and M&#x02010;treated samples had higher opened caps mushrooms, 82.2% and 80.0%, respectively. Over the same period, the percentage of opened caps mushrooms coated with TZs, TSs, and T were in the range 66.7%&#x02013;75.6%. According to Jiang (<xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), mushroom cap opening leads to increased water loss, which in turn leads to mushroom dryness. Cohesive forces of water and other hydrophilic molecules, such as proteins responsible for the well position of the caps and veil in mushrooms, diminished over the storage, as a result of water loss increment. TG coating alone and in combination with each of the essential oils attenuated water loss, the cap opening of mushrooms was lower, and the least changes (66.7%) were related to mushrooms coated with TZ10.</p><table-wrap id="fsn31000-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Effect of Tragacanth gum coating containing two essential oils on percentage of open caps of samples</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Treatment</th><th align="left" colspan="4" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1">Time (day)</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TS1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.4<sup>Ad</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.4<sup>ABCDc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.3<sup>ABCb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.4<sup>CDa</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TS5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.2<sup>Ad</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.2<sup>CDc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.0<sup>Cb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.0<sup>EFa</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TS10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.8<sup>Ad</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.9<sup>CDc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.9<sup>Cb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.8<sup>Fa</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TZ1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.5<sup>Ad</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.7<sup>BCDc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.2<sup>BCb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.0<sup>DEa</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TZ5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.6<sup>Ad</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.4<sup>CDac</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.3<sup>Cb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.7<sup>Fa</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TZ10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.1<sup>Ad</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.8<sup>Dc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.8<sup>Cb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.7<sup>Fa</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.0<sup>Ad</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.9<sup>ABc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.9<sup>ABCb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.2<sup>CDa</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.7<sup>Ad</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.0<sup>Bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.9<sup>ABb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.3<sup>ABa</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.1<sup>Ad</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.5<sup>ABCc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.6<sup>ABCb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.6<sup>BCa</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.6<sup>Ad</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.9<sup>Ac</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.9<sup>Ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.9<sup>Aa</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fsn31000-note-0001"><p>
<sup>a</sup>Mean of three replications&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard deviation. Means in the same row with different small letters are significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). Means in the same column with different capital letters are significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). C: control (without coating); M: 1,000&#x000a0;mg/L sodium metabisulfite; T: coating with Tragacanth gum; TM: TG coating containing 1,000&#x000a0;mg/L metabisulfite; TS1: TG coating containing 100&#x000a0;mg/L of <italic>Satureja khuzistanica</italic> essential oil (S); TS5: 500&#x000a0;mg/L S; TS10: 1,000&#x000a0;mg/L S; TZ1: TG coating containing 100&#x000a0;mg/L <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss. essential oil (Z); TZ5: 500&#x000a0;mg/L Z; TZ10: 1,000&#x000a0;mg/L Z.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>Overall acceptability (based on color, texture, and percentage samples opened caps) reduced during storage (Table <xref rid="fsn31000-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Based on the assessment given by the sensory panel members, the control and MS failed to be acceptable following 16&#x000a0;days of storage. Over the same period of storage, mushrooms coated with Tragacanth gum and essential oils did not display any unsuitable characteristics and received an overall acceptability of about 2.17 from the panelists. These results demonstrate the effectiveness of the TZ5 and TS5 in delaying mushroom appearance deterioration. Jiang et al. (<xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>) reported the reaction of polyphenol oxidase (PPO) enzyme and the action of bacteria and mold on the mushroom tissue result in browning of mushrooms. As Tragacanth gum and gum containing essential oils coatings could lower the activity of spoilage organisms, such as <italic>Pseudomonas</italic>, undertaking for phenolic compounds oxidation to form brown&#x02010;colored melanins, improving the appearance and color.</p><table-wrap id="fsn31000-tbl-0002" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effect of Tragacanth gum coating containing two essential oils on overall acceptability of samples</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">
Treatment
</th><th align="left" colspan="4" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1">Time (day)</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TS1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>ABCa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>Aab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>ABb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2<sup>Ac</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TS5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>ABa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>Aab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.1<sup>Aab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>Ab</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TS10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2<sup>ABCa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2<sup>Ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4<sup>ABc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>Ac</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TZ1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.0<sup>ABCa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>Aab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.6<sup>ABbc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>Ac</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TZ5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2<sup>Aa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2<sup>Aa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4<sup>ABb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.0<sup>Ac</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TZ10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2<sup>ABCa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>Aab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.5<sup>ABbc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.0<sup>Ac</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2<sup>ABCa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2<sup>ABa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.5<sup>ABb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2<sup>Ab</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.3<sup>ABCa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>Bb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>ABc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>Bc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TM</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.6<sup>BCa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>Aa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4<sup>ABab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2<sup>Ab</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>Ca</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>Cb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2<sup>Bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1<sup>Cd</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fsn31000-note-0002"><p>
<sup>a</sup>Mean of three replications&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard deviation. Means in the same row with different small letters are significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). Means in the same column with different capital letters are significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). For abbreviations see Table <xref rid="fsn31000-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0015"><label>3.4</label><title>Effect of gum coating containing EOs on PPO activity</title><p>The activity of PPO increased during the storage period. PPO activity of control mushrooms increased swiftly without peaks and was considerably greater than samples coated with TG and TG containing essential oils (Figure <xref rid="fsn31000-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). TG coatings might be slightly permeable especially to oxygen, thus preventing PPO to access to oxygen. Browning has been studied in other fruits, and discoloration correlated well with PPO activity. The inhibition of the PPO activity by coating fruits and vegetables was reported by numerous investigators: chitosan coating on litchi fruit (Jiang, Li, &#x00026; Jiang, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>), carrageenan coating on fresh&#x02010;cut banana (Bico, Raposo, Morais, &#x00026; Morais, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), and different edible coatings on fresh&#x02010;cut &#x0201c;Royal Gala&#x0201d; apple (Bertrand, Raposo, Morais, &#x00026; Morais, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). In the present study, a high activity of PPO leads to a dark and unpleasant appearance of mushrooms. This result is in a good agreement with those reported by the above researchers. Here, there exist associations among the PPO activity and the color parameters in mushrooms; enhancing the PPO activity leads to the decrease in L* values and the increase in BI, indicating the dependency of enzymatic browning reactions to the PPO. In general, PPO acceleration the monophenols (monophenolase) hydroxylation and the oxidation of <italic>o</italic>&#x02010;diphenols into <italic>o</italic>&#x02010;quinones (diphenolase). Therefore, in the presence of oxygen, polymerization and creation of the unwanted brown pigments took place (Amin, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). In general, treatments with essential oils prompt a decrease in the activity of PPO. The studies conducted by Amin (<xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>) who sprayed celery, basil, and peppermint essential oils on Anna apple and Gao et al. (<xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) in fumigation of button mushroom with clove, cinnamaldehyde, and thyme essential oils show similar trends observed in our studies and those reported by several previous investigators. Compared to the control and M samples, those treated by TG containing essential oils preserved more ascorbic acid content (Data not shown). This may be attributed to the pH lowering action of ascorbic acid particularly at high concentration, which decreases the pH below the optimum value in turn inhibiting the catalytic action of PPO (Sapers, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">1993</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31000-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Effect of essential oil&#x02010;incorporated TG coating on PPO activities of button mushrooms stored at 4&#x000b0;C for 16&#x000a0;days. Vertical bars represent standard errors of means. For abbreviations see Figure <xref rid="fsn31000-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="FSN3-7-1520-g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0016"><label>3.5</label><title>Effect of gum coating containing essential oils on POD activity</title><p>In all treatments, pattern of POD activity was similar during 16&#x000a0;days of storage, reaching a peak and then declined. The POD activities in TZ&#x02010; and TS&#x02010;coated mushrooms were significantly lower than that in C (Figure <xref rid="fsn31000-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Unpleasant quality alterations, such as discoloration, off&#x02010;flavor, and nutritional destruction through handling, transportation, packaging, processing, and storage of fruit and vegetables, are consequences of enzymatic browning. These reactions resulted mostly from enzymes such as peroxidase (Mousavizadeh, Sedaghathoor, &#x00026; Khorami, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). The POD association with enzymatic browning and antioxidant defense has been revealed by former investigation (Lin et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). The increase in peroxidase is a sign of fruit quality deterioration and is relevant to the enzymatic browning process because <italic>o</italic>&#x02010;phenols could encourage fruit and vegetable products to be darkened over the processing and preservation and could display reducing function in the enzyme reaction (Amin, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). The quality features and mushroom decay may be affected by different enzymatic changes in chemical constituents. Also, POD could affect odor and taste and deteriorate eating and nutritional qualities of mushrooms (Baardseth, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">1979</xref>; Fasidi &#x00026; Kadiri, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">1991</xref>). For that reason, it is required to inactivate the peroxidase enzyme to minimize deterioration.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31000-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Effect of essential oil&#x02010;incorporated TG coating on POD activities of button mushrooms stored at 4&#x000b0;C for 16&#x000a0;days. Vertical bars represent standard errors of means. For abbreviations see Figure <xref rid="fsn31000-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="FSN3-7-1520-g004"/></fig><p>It is acceptable that edible coatings practice as protective barrier on the surface of fresh product, diminish oxygen supply, slow down ripening and senescence, and, subsequently, postpone browning of fruits and vegetables. Several preservation methods, based on chitosan coating (Eissa, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>) and alginate coating (Jiang, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), restricted activities of POD. In addition, application of essential oils resulted in the decrease in the peroxidase enzyme activity, which may account for the inhibition of the mushroom browning. Alikhani, Sharifani, Azizi, Hemati, and Mousavizadeh. (<xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>) reported the value of natural essential oils in the decrease in activity of the peroxidase enzyme of fruits and vegetables. Mousavizadeh et al. (<xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>) demonstrated that antioxidative properties of essential oils can lead to peroxidase activity reduction in white and red cabbage. In this study, gum coating&#x02010;impregnated EOs reduced POD activity of samples. Thus, it appears that coating influence on browning inhibition is through extenuating oxygen supply and inhibitory properties on POD activity.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0017"><label>3.6</label><title>Effect of gum coating containing EOs on PAL</title><p>Despite PPO, PAL activities of all samples decreased continuously during storage (Figure <xref rid="fsn31000-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). PAL is the major enzyme in the biosynthesis of varieties of phenylpropanoid compounds, such as simple phenols, anthocyanin, flavonoid, and lignin (Hiratsuka et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Ju, Yuan, Lieu, &#x00026; Xin, <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>). It is stated that the accumulation of phenols and anthocyanins equated the PAL activity enhancement in some fruits (Wang et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Thus, PAL activity was studied in this paper to examine the possible response to TG coating containing EOs. Unlike, Eissa (<xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>) who reported cationic charge of chitosan caused protein binding and chitosan coating&#x02010;treated fresh&#x02010;cut mushroom inhibited the increase in PAL activity. Gum coating containing EOs induced increasing in PAL activity compared to control and M samples. It is conceivable that essential oils exhibit positive influence on plant secondary metabolites and motivating biosynthesis of phenolic and anthocyanin compounds by promoting PAL activity (Gao et al., <xref rid="fsn31000-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). TZ10, TZ5, TS10, and TS5 were more effective than other treatments in enhancing PAL activity.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31000-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Effect of essential oil&#x02010;incorporated TG coating on PAL activities of button mushrooms stored at 4&#x000b0;C for 16&#x000a0;days. Vertical bars represent standard errors of means. For abbreviations see Figure <xref rid="fsn31000-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="FSN3-7-1520-g005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0018"><label>4</label><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>Inhibition of enzymatic browning is the most important concern in the mushroom's industry. As the food industry tends to decrease the use of chemical preservatives in food products, TG coating contained each essential oils could be considered as a potential source for shelf&#x02010;life extension of cold&#x02010;stored mushroom. TZ and TS treatments slowed down respiration rate, postponed cap opening, and SSC addition compared with gum&#x02010;coated, M&#x02010;treated, and control mushrooms. Furthermore, TS5 showed greater influence to inhibit discoloration of button mushrooms. Consequently, these natural products have promising effect to protect the quality and safety of button mushroom. TZ and TS coatings could prevent enzymatic browning through inhibition the activities of PPO and POD, increasing PAL activity during the storage time.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="fsn31000-sec-0020"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31000-sec-0021"><title>ETHICAL STATEMENT</title><p>Study's protocols and procedures were ethically reviewed and approved by Tarbiat Modares Research Council. Ethics approval and consent to participate are not applicable to this manuscript, since it does not report on or involve the use of any animal or human data or tissues.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="fsn31000-sec-0019"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</title><p>The authors acknowledge the financial support provided by the Tarbiat Modares University Research Council.</p></ack><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="fsn31000-bibl-0001"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Abd El Wahab</surname>, <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Maintain postharvest quality of nectarine fruits by using some essential oils</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Middle East Journal of Applied Sciences</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>855</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>868</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Abd El Wahab</surname>, <given-names>W. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Abd El Wahab</surname>, <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Kamel</surname>, <given-names>O. T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Using safe alternatives for controlling postharvest decay, maintaining quality of Crimson seedless grape</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">World Applied Sciences Journal</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>1345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1357</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Abdolahi</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hassani</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ghosta</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bernousi</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Meshkatalsadat</surname>, <given-names>M. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Study on the potential use of essential oils for decay control and quality preservation of Tabarzeh table grape</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Plant Protection Research</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/v10045-010-0008-2</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Ali</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Maqbool</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ramachandran</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Alderson</surname>, <given-names>P. G.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Gum Arabic as a novel edible coating for enhancing shelf&#x02010;life and improving postharvest quality of tomato (<italic>Solanumly copersicum</italic> L.) fruit</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Postharvest Biology and Technology</source>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>42</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2010.05.005</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Alikhani</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sharifani</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Azizi</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hemati</surname>, <given-names>K. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Mousavizadeh</surname>, <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The effect of some natural compounds in shelf&#x02010;life and quality of pear fruit (<italic>Esfahan Shah Mive</italic> cultivar)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>158</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>171</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Amin</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Determination of some essential oils effects on the quality traits of the Egyptian Anna apple fruit during its shelf life</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Horticultural Science and Ornamental Plants</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Ares</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Parentelli</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>G&#x000e1;mbaro</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lareo</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Lema</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Sensory shelf life of shiitake mushrooms stored under passive modified atmosphere</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Postharvest Biology and Technology</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>197</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2006.03.013</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Azarikia</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Abbasi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Mechanism of soluble complex formation of milk proteins with native gums (Tragacanth and Persian gum)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Hydrocolloids</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodhyd.2015.10.018</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Baardseth</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Enzymatically induced quality changes in fresh and frozen carrot</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Acta Horticulture</source>, <volume>93</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17660/ActaHortic.1979.93.8</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Bertrand</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Raposo</surname>, <given-names>M. F. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Morais</surname>, <given-names>R. M. S. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Morais</surname>, <given-names>A. M. M. B.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Effects of different edible coatings on polyphenol oxidase activity and color of fresh&#x02010;cut apple during cold storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">International Journal of Postharvest Technology and Innovation</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Bico</surname>, <given-names>S. L. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Raposo</surname>, <given-names>M. F. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Morais</surname>, <given-names>R. M. S. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Morais</surname>, <given-names>A. M. M. B.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Combined effects of chemical dip and/or carrageenan coating and/or controlled atmosphere on quality of fresh cut banana</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Control</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>508</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>514</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2008.07.017</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Bill</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sivakumar</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Korsten</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>, <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The efficacy of combined application of edible coatings and thyme oil in inducing resistance components in avocado (<italic>Persea americana</italic> Mill.) against anthracnose during postharvest storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Crop Protection</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>167</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cropro.2014.06.015</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Bradford</surname>, <given-names>M. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1976</year>). <article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilising the principle of protein&#x02010;dye binding</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Analytical Biochemistry</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>248</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>254</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Campaniello</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bevilacqua</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sinigaglia</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Corbo</surname>, <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Chitosan: Antimicrobial activity and potential applications for preserving minimally processed strawberries</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Microbiology</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>992</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1000</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2008.06.009</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18954735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Dashipour</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Razavilar</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hosseini</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shojaee&#x02010;Aliabadi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>German</surname>, <given-names>J. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ghanati</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x02026; <string-name>
<surname>Khaksar</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant and antimicrobial carboxymethyl cellulose films containing <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> essential oil</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">International Journal of Biological Macromolecules</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>606</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>613</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2014.09.006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25220790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Eissa</surname>, <given-names>H. A. A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Effect of chitosan coating on shelf life and quality of fresh&#x02010;cut mushroom</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Quality</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>623</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>645</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1745-4557.2007.00147.x</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Farzaneh</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kiani</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sharifi</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Reisi</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Hadian</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Chemical composition and antifungal effects of three species of <italic>Satureja</italic> (<italic>S. hortensis</italic>,<italic> S. spicigera</italic>, and <italic>S. khuzistanica</italic>) essential oils on the main pathogens of strawberry fruit</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Postharvest Biology and Technology</source>, <volume>109</volume>, <fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>151</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2015.06.014</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Fasidi</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Kadiri</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Changes in enzyme activities of <italic>Termitomyces robustus</italic> (Beeli) Heim and <italic>Lentinus subnudus</italic> Berk during sporophore development</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Fathi</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sahari</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zangiabadi</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Barzegar</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Application of <italic>Satureja hortensis</italic> L. and <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss. essential oils as two natural antioxidants in soybean oil during microwave heating</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Medicinal Plants</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>12</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Gao</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Feng</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Browning inhibition and quality preservation of button mushroom (<italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic>) by essential oils fumigation treatment</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>149</volume>, <fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2013.10.073</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24295683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Haq</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Alam</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Hasnain</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Gum Cordia: A novel edible coating to increase the shelf life of Chilgoza (<italic>Pinus gerardiana</italic>)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">LWT &#x02013; Food Science and Technology</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>306</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>311</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2012.05.008</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Hashemi</surname>, <given-names>M. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Niakousari</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Saharkhiz</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Eskandari</surname>, <given-names>M. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Effect of <italic>Satureja khuzestanica</italic> essential oil on oxidative stability of sunflower oil during accelerated storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Natural Product Research</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>1458</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1463</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21819311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Hiratsuka</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Onodera</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kawai</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kubo</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Itoh</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Wada</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Enzyme activity changes during anthocyanin synthesis in &#x02018;<italic>Olympia</italic>&#x02019; grape berries</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Scientia Horticulturae</source>, <volume>90</volume>, <fpage>255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>264</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-4238(00)00266-1</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Jafri</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jha</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bunkar</surname>, <given-names>D. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ram</surname>, <given-names>R. C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Quality retention of oyster mushrooms (<italic>Pleurotus florida</italic>) by a combination of chemical treatments and modified atmosphere packaging</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Postharvest Biology and Technology</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>118</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2012.10.002</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Effect of alginate coating on physicochemical and sensory qualities of button mushrooms (<italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic>) under a high oxygen modified atmosphere</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Postharvest Biology and Technology</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2012.09.005</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Feng</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Effect of chitosan coating enriched with thyme oil on postharvest quality and shelf life of shiitake mushroom (<italic>Lentinus edodes</italic>)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22136665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Feng</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Physicochemical responses and microbial characteristics of shiitake mushroom (<italic>Lentinus edodes</italic>) to gum Arabic coating enriched with natamycin during storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>138</volume>, <fpage>1992</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1997</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2012.11.043</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23411335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jing</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cai</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ying</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Integrated application of nitric oxide and modified atmosphere packaging to improve quality retention of button mushroom (<italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic>)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>126</volume>, <fpage>1693</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1699</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25213946</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Effects of chitosan coating on shelf life of cold&#x02010;stored litchi fruit at ambient temperature</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">LWT &#x02013; Food Science and Technology</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>757</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>761</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2004.09.004</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Ju</surname>, <given-names>Z. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yuan</surname>, <given-names>Y. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lieu</surname>, <given-names>C. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Xin</surname>, <given-names>C. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Relationships among phenylalanine ammonia&#x02010;lyase activity, simple phenol concentrations and anthocyanin accumulation in apple</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Scientia Horticulturae</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>226</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0032">
<string-name>
<surname>Khaliq</surname>, <given-names>G. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mohamed</surname>, <given-names>M. T. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ali</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ding</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ghazalic</surname>, <given-names>H. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Effect of gum Arabic coating combined with calcium chloride on physicochemical and qualitative properties of mango (<italic>Mangiferaindica</italic> L.) fruit during low temperature storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Scientia Horticulturae</source>, <volume>190</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>194</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2015.04.020</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0033">
<string-name>
<surname>Khan</surname>, <given-names>Z. U.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Aisikaer</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Khan</surname>, <given-names>R. U.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bu</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ni</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ying</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Effects of composite chemical pretreatment on maintaining quality in button mushrooms (<italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic>) during postharvest storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Postharvest Biology and Technology</source>, <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2014.04.001</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0034">
<string-name>
<surname>Kordsardouei</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Barzegar</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sahari</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ebrahimipour</surname>, <given-names>S. Y.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Influence of different temperatures and times on antiradical properties of <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss. and <italic>Cinnamon zeylanicum</italic> essential oils by using DPPH method</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Agriculture Technology and Biological Sciences</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>447</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0035">
<string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>W. X.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Yu</surname>, <given-names>H. Q.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Study on hypobaric storage of green asparagus</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Engineering</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>230</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0036">
<string-name>
<surname>Lin</surname>, <given-names>Q.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lu</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Guan</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Effects of high CO<sub>2</sub> in&#x02010;package treatment on flavour, quality and antioxidant activity of button mushroom (<italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic>) during postharvest storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Postharvest Biology and Technology</source>, <volume>123</volume>, <fpage>112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>118</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0037">
<string-name>
<surname>Moazeni</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Saharkhiz</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hoseini</surname>, <given-names>A. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Mootabi Alavi</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>In vitro scolicidal effect of <italic>Satureja khuzistanica</italic> (Jamzad) essential oil</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Asian Pacific Journal of Tropical Biomedicine</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>616</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>620</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23569981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0038">
<string-name>
<surname>Moradi</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tajik</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Razavi Rohani</surname>, <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Mahmoudian</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant and antimicrobial effects of zein edible film impregnated with <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss. essential oil and monolaurin</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Science and Technology</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0039">
<string-name>
<surname>Moradi</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tajik</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Razavi Rohani</surname>, <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Oromiehie</surname>, <given-names>A. R.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Effectiveness of <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss. essential oil and grape seed extract impregnated chitosan film on ready&#x02010;to&#x02010;eat mortadella&#x02010;type sausages during refrigerated storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture</source>, <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>2850</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2857</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21796636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0040">
<string-name>
<surname>Mousavizadeh</surname>, <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sedaghathoor</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Khorami</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Essential oils as reducing agents of cabbage peroxidase</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Scientia Horticulturae</source>, <volume>128</volume>, <fpage>388</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>392</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2011.01.027</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0041">
<string-name>
<surname>Nasiri</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Barzegar</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sahari</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Niakousari</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Tragacanth gum containing <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss. essential oil as a natural preservative for storage of button mushrooms (<italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic>)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Hydrocolloids</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>209</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodhyd.2017.05.045</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0042">
<string-name>
<surname>Park</surname>, <given-names>H. J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Development of advanced edible coatings for fruits</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Trends in Food Science and Technology</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>254</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>260</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0924-2244(00)00003-0</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0043">
<string-name>
<surname>Raeisi</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tajik</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Aliakbarlu</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mirhosseini</surname>, <given-names>S. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Hosseini</surname>, <given-names>S. M. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Effect of carboxymethyl cellulose&#x02010;based coatings incorporated with <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss. essential oil and grape seed extract on the shelf life of rainbow trout fillets</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">LWT &#x02013; Food Science and Technology</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>898</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>904</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2015.06.010</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0044">
<string-name>
<surname>Rohani</surname>, <given-names>M. Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zaipun</surname>, <given-names>M. Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Norhayati</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Effect of modified atmosphere on the storage life and quality of <italic>Eksotika</italic> papaya</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Tropical Agriculture and Food Science</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0045">
<string-name>
<surname>Rzymski</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mleczek</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Niedzielski</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Siwulskid</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Asecka</surname>, <given-names>M. G.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Cultivation of <italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic> enriched with selenium, zinc and copper</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Science of Food and Agriculture</source>, <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>923</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>928</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0046">
<string-name>
<surname>Sapers</surname>, <given-names>G. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Browning of foods: Control by sulfites, antioxidants, and other means</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Technology</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0047">
<string-name>
<surname>Sapers</surname>, <given-names>G. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Miller</surname>, <given-names>R. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pilizota</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Kamp</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Shelf&#x02010;life extension of fresh mushrooms (<italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic>) by application of hydrogen peroxide and browning inhibitors</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Science</source>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>362</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>366</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2621.2001.tb11347.x</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0048">
<string-name>
<surname>Taban</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rahimi</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Saharkhiz</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hadian</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Zomorodian</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The efficacy of <italic>Satureja khuzistanica</italic> essential oil treatment in reducing <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7 load on alfalfa seeds prior to sprouting</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Safety</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>127</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0049">
<string-name>
<surname>Tripathi</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Dubey</surname>, <given-names>N. K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Exploitation of natural products as an alternative strategy to control postharvest fungal rotting of fruit and vegetables</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Postharvest Biology and Technology</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>245</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2003.11.005</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0050">
<string-name>
<surname>Verbeken</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dierckx</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Dewettinck</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Exudate gums: Occurrence, production, and applications</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-003-1354-z</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12802529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0051">
<string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>K. T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jin</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cao</surname>, <given-names>S. F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shang</surname>, <given-names>H. T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yang</surname>, <given-names>Z. F.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>, <given-names>Y. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Methyl jasmonate reduces decay and enhances antioxidant capacity in Chinese bayberries</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>5809</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5815</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf900914a</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19522511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0052">
<string-name>
<surname>Wong</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tillin</surname>, <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hudson</surname>, <given-names>J. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Pavlath</surname>, <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Gas exchange in cut apples with bilayer coatings</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>2278</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2285</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf00046a037</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31000-bib-0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31000-cit-0053">
<string-name>
<surname>Xu</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tian</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mab</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>, <given-names>Q.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Effect of plasma activated water on the postharvest quality of button mushrooms, <italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic>
</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>197</volume>, <fpage>436</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>444</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.10.144</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26616972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>