<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The aim of this study was to determine the functional composition and biological activities of some date fruit varieties that are unknown to the general public, but highly appreciated by the local populations of oases these varieties are locally known as 
 <italic>Boufgous, Bouskri, Bousrdon, Bousthammi, Jihl</italic> and 
 <italic>Majhoul</italic>. Sucrose was the main sugar in 
 <italic>Bouskri</italic> unlike other varieties which contain fructose and glucose in high amount. 
 <italic>Bouskri</italic> contains the highest amount of pyridoxine and 
 <italic>Majhoul</italic> possesses the highest amount niacin and riboflavin. Among analyzed cultivars, 
 <italic>Bousthammi</italic> contains the highest amount of magnesium and manganese and has iron seven times more than 
 <italic>Jihl</italic> cultivars, which contains a high amount of calcium and copper. The highest amount of zinc was found in 
 <italic>Najda</italic> while the highest amount of potassium was detected in 
 <italic>Bouskri</italic>. Significant difference in antioxidant activity was observed between analyzed varieties. The highest antioxidant activity was observed in both 
 <italic>Bousrdoun</italic> and 
 <italic>Jihl</italic> which contained the highest amount of phenolic and flavonoids content. Gallic, Ferulic, Caffeic acids and Rutin were the most dominant among analysed polyphenolic compounds and the highest amount of these compounds were observed in 
 <italic>Jihl</italic> and 
 <italic>Bousrdoun.</italic> Regarding the anti-inflammatory activity and based on the results of three in vitro assays and two in vivo assays, 
 <italic>Bousrdoun</italic> and 
 <italic>Jihl</italic> exhibited the highest anti-inflammatory effect. Moderate antibacterial activity was observed in all studied varieties except Bouskri and Majhoul which didn’t show no antibacterial effect against the six bacterial strains. 
 <italic>Bousrdon</italic> and 
 <italic>Jihl</italic> were found to be more potent against these bacterial strains. These differences in chemical composition and biological activity suggest that date fruit is an extensive domain hence the size should not be the only character that should be used to choose the variety but also its composition and their biological activities. 
</p>
