<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot8-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.8. Preparation of Trimethylsilyl Ether Derivatives and HRGC-FID Analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The silylation reaction was carried out as described by Lombardi et al. [
  <a rid="B29-foods-07-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-foods-07-00030">29</a>] with slight modifications. In brief, BSTFA and acetone were added to the sterol fraction and the reaction was carried out at 40 °C for 20 min to obtain trimethylsilyl ether (TMSE) derivatives. Sterols and alcohols, as TMSE derivatives, were analyzed using a DANI GC1000 DPC gas chromatograph equipped with a split-splitless injector and FID. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Separation of TMSE sterols and alcohols was obtained using the AT-1701 fused silica capillary column (25 m × 0.25 mm i.d., 0.2 μm f.t.; Alltech, Milan, Italy). </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For analysis of TMSE sterols, the following chromatographic conditions were used: injector and detector temperature was 300 °C; oven temperature of 260 °C was held for 4 min, then increased to 300 °C at 1.5 °C/min, and the final temperature was held for 30 min; carrier gas (He) flow rate was 1.2 mL/min. </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For analysis of TMSE alcohols, the following chromatographic conditions were used: injector and detector temperature was 290 °C; oven temperature was held at 180 °C for 3 min, raised to 260 °C at 6 °C/min for 15 min, then raised to 280 °C at 2 °C/min for 30 min. </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chromatograms were acquired and processed using Clarity integration software. The percentage of each sterol was calculated by using the peak area of the samples corrected with the correction factor equal to 1 as reported by Laakso [
  <a rid="B30-foods-07-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-foods-07-00030">30</a>]. TMSE sterols were also analyzed by HRGC coupled with mass spectrometry (MS) detector as described in 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot9-foods-07-00030" href="#sec2dot9-foods-07-00030">Section 2.9</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
