<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As described previously (
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Niu et al., 2015</xref>), the red blood cells (iRBC) infected by 
 <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> (NF54 strain from MR4, Manassas, VA) were cultured in RPMI-1640 medium (Life Tech, Grand Island, NY) supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated (56 °C for 45 min) human AB+ serum (Interstate blood bank, Memphis, TN), 12.5 µg/mL hypoxanthine and 4% hematocrit (O+ human blood) in a candle jar at 37 °C for 15-17 days. The medium was replaced every day to provide sufficient nutrients. Blood smears stained with Giemsa (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) were used to examine parasitemia or gametocytemia every other day under a light microscope. Then, the cells were collected and washed three times with RPMI-1640 at 300 × g for 4 m. The cell pellets were re-suspended in PBST (PBS containing 0.2% Tween-20) and homogenized by ultra-sonication with six cycles of 10 s pulse and 50 s resting on ice for each period. The lysates were centrifuged at 8,000 g for 2 min to remove insoluble materials and cellular debris. With the iRBC lysate and insect cell-expressed recombinant FREP1, the ELISA assay was used to screen the fungal extract library to block FREP1-parasite interaction (
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Niu et al., 2015</xref>). A 96-well ELISA plate was coated with 50 µL iRBC lysate (2 mg/mL protein) and incubated overnight at 4 °C. After coating, the plate was blocked with 100 µL of PBS plus 0.2% bovine serum albumin (BSA) per well for 1.5 hr at RT. After removal of the blocking solution, FREP1 (10 µg/mL) in blocking buffer (PBS plus 0.2% BSA) was added to each well, and 1 µL fungal extract was taken from a 96-well plate containing 2 mg/mL crude extract dissolved in DMSO in each well with a multiple-channel pipette and transferred to the ELISA plate, then incubated for 1 hr at RT with gentle shaking. After washing three times with PBST, 50 µL rabbit anti-FREP1 polyclonal antibody (
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Niu et al., 2015</xref>) (diluted 1: 5,000 in blocking buffer, 1 µg/mL) was added to each well and incubated for 1 hr at RT. About 50 µL alkaline phosphatase-conjugated anti-rabbit IgG (diluted 1: 20,000 in blocking buffer) was added to each well and incubated for 45 min at RT. The wells were washed three times with PBST between incubations. After washing, each well was developed with 50 µL pNPP substrate (Sigma-Aldrich) until the colors were visible, and absorbance at 405 nm was measured. The functional FREP1 supplemented with 1 µL solvent (DMSO) was used as non-inhibition control, and the heat-inactivated FREP1 (65 °C for 15 min) was used as a 100% inhibition control.
</p>
