<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0130">The traditional-based approach of preparing the extracts using water yielded very low antitubercular and antimicrobial activities, while the crude methanolic extract exhibited a broad-spectrum antimicrobial activity against acid-fast, Gram-positive, Gram-negative, and fungi. This could point to a possible implication of differential solubility of various plant compounds in solvents of different polarities. It is established that solvent polarity affects the qualitative and quantitative composition of bioactive compounds enriched in various solvents, and that methanol is a better and more powerful extractant compared to water [
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. With methanolic crude extract giving a robust antitubercular activity, the next question we asked ourselves was whether solvent fractionation would give us more fractions with potent activity, and at a lower concentration (from 1 g/mL to between 50-6.25 μg/mL; Tables 
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Compared to the positive control, the concentration of the crude methanolic extract was 10
 <sup>4</sup>-fold higher. We reasoned that the active compound(s) in the crude methanolic extract comprised only a small fraction of the crude extract and if purified and isolated, might work at a lower concentration, or even more potently than the standard antibiotic used. To test this assumption, we fractionated the plant sample by organic solvents of increasing concentration. Interestingly, all solvent extract fractions had a strong antitubercular activity with MIC ranging between 25 and 6.25 μg/mL that yielded similar inhibitory capacity (0 GU) to the commercially available antimycobacterial drugs, streptomycin, isoniazid, rifampicin, and ethambutol (SIRE) (
 <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). These findings are consistent with other studies that have demonstrated that plants are an excellent potential source of active antitubercular compounds [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. However, solvent fractionation yielded relatively lower general antimicrobial activity against Gram-positive, Gram-negative, and fungi compared to the crude extract (Tables 
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). This phenomenon suggests a possible synergistic and/or additive effect of the active molecules in the crude extract, an effect that was possibly lost by fractionation [
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Furthermore, the fact that fractions demonstrated a robust antitubercular activity, and low general activity against Gram-positive, Gram-negative, and fungi allude to a possible selective activity against MTB, which is an essential feature in search of novel selective antitubercular leads [
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>].
</p>
