<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For the species cited in at least nine studies (one third taken as an arbitrary threshold value) a comprehensive literature review of pharmacological data was conducted based on a literature search with the online databases Medline (PubMed), Scopus, and the Cochrane Library (
 <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">
  <bold>Table 3</bold>
 </xref>). Preclinical and clinical data obtained with botanical drugs derived from the 98 medicinal plant species cited in at least nine studies are reported in correspondence to the predominant traditional uses (use-records). As an arbitrary threshold value predominant uses are defined here as those recorded in the same ICPC category by at least seven independent studies or alternatively, those most frequently recorded in an ICPC category in case no category was recorded in at least seven studies. A use-record is defined as a reported use per taxon and ICPC category in one study. Studies lacking methodological transparency or using doses unrealistically high from a therapeutic perspective were excluded from this review. We evaluated the available pharmacological and preclinical data in order to extrapolate on the safety and efficacy of clinical applications. We took the mode of application into account and considered the importance of cultural factors for the perceived effectiveness, which is to be distinguished from efficacy (
 <xref rid="B348" ref-type="bibr">Ortiz de Montellano, 1975</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B273" ref-type="bibr">Last et al., 2001</xref>, p. 57-58; 
 <xref rid="B321" ref-type="bibr">Moerman and Jonas, 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B483" ref-type="bibr">Witt, 2013</xref>). Therefore, we evaluated as potentially safe and effective also applications of herbal drugs for which no negative toxicological reports were available. Despite the human influence on the current distribution of plant taxa is not always exactly known we categorized the 98 species into natives and exotics, judging those species native which, due to their cultural importance, obtained a wide distribution range over South and MA prior to European conquest and colonization (e.g., 
 <italic>Bixa orellana</italic> and 
 <italic>Petiveria alliacea</italic>) as well as the pantropic species (e.g., 
 <italic>Cissampelos pareira</italic> and 
 <italic>Cocos nucifera</italic>).
</p>
