<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Parasites &#x00026; Vectors</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1756-3305</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6186027</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3096</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-018-3096-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Functional analysis of a novel parasitic nematode-specific protein of <italic>Setaria digitata</italic> larvae in <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> by siRNA mediated RNA interference</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Somarathne</surname><given-names>Magalla Bastian Chalitha Lakmal</given-names></name><address><email>chalithasomarathne@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gunawardene</surname><given-names>Yasanthi Illika Nilmini Silva</given-names></name><address><email>nilminisg@kln.ac.lk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chandrasekharan</surname><given-names>Naduvilath Vishvanath</given-names></name><address><email>nchandra@chem.cmb.ac.lk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ellepola</surname><given-names>Arjuna Nisantha Bandara</given-names></name><address><email>arjuna@hsc.edu.kw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Dassanayake</surname><given-names>Ranil Samantha</given-names></name><address><email>rsdassanayake@chem.cmb.ac.lk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000121828067</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8065.b</institution-id><institution>Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Science, </institution><institution>University of Colombo, </institution></institution-wrap>Colombo 03, 00300 Sri Lanka </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8631 5388</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.45202.31</institution-id><institution>Molecular Medicine Unit, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>University of Kelaniya, </institution></institution-wrap>Ragama, 11010 Sri Lanka </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1240 3921</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411196.a</institution-id><institution>Department of Bioclinical Sciences, Faculty of Dentistry, Health Sciences Center, </institution><institution>University of Kuwait, </institution></institution-wrap>Kuwait City, Kuwait </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>541</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Functional analysis of animal parasitic nematode genes is often quite challenging due to the unavailability of standardised <italic>in vitro</italic> culture conditions and lack of adequate tools to manipulate these genes. Therefore, this study was undertaken to investigate the suitability of <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>, as an <italic>in vivo</italic> culture platform for <italic>Setaria digitata</italic> larvae and RNA interference (RNAi), as a post-transcriptional gene silencing tool to study the roles of a vital gene that encodes a novel parasitic nematode-specific protein (<italic>SDNP</italic>).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">The red colour fluorescence detected following RNAi injection to the thorax of <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic> indicated the uptake of dsRNA by <italic>S. digitata</italic> larvae. The reduction of <italic>SDNP</italic> transcripts in siRNA treated larvae compared to non-treated larvae, as determined by qPCR, indicated that the siRNA pathway is operational in <italic>S. digitata</italic> larvae. The observation of motility reductions and deformities during the development indicated the association of <italic>SDNP</italic> in larvae locomotion and development processes, respectively. The irregularities in the migration of larvae in mosquitoes and elevated survival rates of mosquitoes compared to their untreated counterparts indicated reduced parasitism of <italic>S. digitata</italic> larvae in mosquitoes upon targeted downregulation of <italic>SDNP</italic> by siRNA treatment.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par3">SDNP plays vital roles in muscle contraction, locomotion, development processes, larval development and parasitism of <italic>S. digitata</italic>. Its ubiquitous presence in parasitic nematodes and its absence in their hosts provide a tantalising prospect of the possibility of targeting SDNP for future development of anthelmintic drugs. The susceptibility of the larval stages of <italic>S. digitata</italic> for RNAi in <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> was also demonstrated for the first time in this study.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Setaria digitata</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>SDNP</italic></kwd><kwd>RNAi</kwd><kwd><italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></kwd><kwd>Gene knockdown</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100009826</institution-id><institution>University of Colombo</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>AP/3/2011/CG/03</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par14">Nematodes are the most abundant metazoans, capable of inhabiting both terrestrial and aquatic habitats. This facilitates their ability to cause both human and animal health problems, as well as to impair crop production worldwide. Gastrointestinal nematodes infect 3.5 billion humans annually worldwide, and cause around 125,000 deaths per year, whereas filarial nematodes infect 120 million people in the globe annually, disabling around 40 million of them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Additionally, plant-parasitic nematodes destroy approximately 12.3% of the annual crop yield, and animal parasitic nematodes kill millions of livestock animals. This contributes to a loss of billions of US dollars annually and necessitates the allocation of additional billions of US dollars for anthelminthic drugs for livestock [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Strategies for controlling this problem have mainly focused on chemical treatments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. However, due to the limited efficiency and high toxicity of the available drugs, adverse effects on the environment, and emergence of drug resistance in parasites, these chemical treatment methods have become somewhat ineffective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Hence, global interest has recently arisen in developing more effective controlling strategies for parasitic nematodes. In this context, screening of the nematode genome will enable us to gain a comprehensive knowledge of the molecular mechanisms associated with the development of the nematode, which may facilitate the control of parasitic nematodes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par15">RNA mediated gene silencing has become a promising and unbiased tool in genetic screening [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. RNA interference (RNAi) is a double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) induced post-transcriptional, homology-dependent gene silencing mechanism, naturally occurring in organisms, assumed to be involved in defence against virus attacks, heterochromatinisation and retrotransposon silencing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. RNAi was initially utilised in the genetic screening of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>, and after that, this technique was expanded to other invertebrates (nematodes, insects, molluscs), vertebrates (fish, mice, humans), plants, fungi and algae [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. RNAi allows the temporary shut-down of gene expression more specifically and rapidly and gives an insight into gene function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p><p id="Par16"><italic>Setaria digitata</italic> is a parasitic nematode that naturally resides in the peritoneum and mesentery of cattle, zebu and water buffalo. Under normal circumstances, the nematode does not show any pathogenicity towards the natural hosts. The microfilariae produced by the adult female worm travel into the bloodstream of the cattle and are transmitted into new hosts <italic>via</italic> mosquito bites. However, when the larvae are transfected into non-permissive hosts such as goats, sheep and horses, they invade the brain, spinal cord, and eyes, causing cerebrospinal setariosis, conjunctivitis, and filariasis oculi, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Intriguingly, studies on <italic>S. digitata</italic> have revealed that it has a high resemblance to the human parasitic nematode <italic>Wuchereria bancrofti</italic> with regard to its morphology, antigenicity and histology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Hence <italic>S. digitata</italic> has been recommended as a model organism for studying <italic>W. bancrofti</italic> and <italic>Brugia malayi</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]<italic>.</italic></p><p id="Par17">Unveiling the biology of the parasitic nematodes genes, which are specific and functionally crucial for their survival, is crucial in identifying targets to control the nematode population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. <italic>SDNP</italic> is such a gene found in <italic>S. digitata</italic>. Intriguingly, this gene has demonstrated high sequence similarities with putative proteins of <italic>W. bancrofti</italic> (79%), <italic>Brugia malayi</italic> (77%) and <italic>Loa loa</italic> (81%). Moreover, bioinformatics studies of <italic>SDNP</italic> revealed that this protein contains a nuclear localisation signal, an RNAP_Rpb7_N_like domain, and an inter-domain linker of muscle-specific twitchin kinase similar to that of <italic>C. elegans</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Considering the background, our study focused on the functional characterisation of <italic>SDNP</italic>.</p><p id="Par18">Commonly, RNAi protocols are practised by isolation of the nematodes from their natural hosts and maintaining them in artificial liquid cultures (<italic>in vitro</italic>). These <italic>in vitro</italic> protocols reduce the efficiency of RNAi due to several shortcomings such as difficulty in maintaining the worms&#x02019; viability in the culture, poor RNAi trigger delivery, and compatibility issues of the culture medium with different life stages of the worm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. To overcome these drawbacks of <italic>in vitro</italic> protocols, in our study an <italic>in vivo</italic> approach was developed, where <italic>S. digitata</italic> larval stages were cultured in its intermediate host, <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>, and the RNAi trigger (siRNA) was directly injected into the mosquito [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], and the possibility of using the mosquito as a better siRNA delivery platform examined. Furthermore, we focused on developing an effective RNAi protocol to specifically shut down the gene of interest to study its function and explore the gene&#x02019;s potential as a likely drug target.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Mosquito colony establishment</title><p id="Par19"><italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> were collected from a cattle trap and maintained at 27 &#x000b0;C with 80% relative humidity, with cycles of 16 h of light and 8 h of darkness, in 12 &#x000d7; 12 &#x000d7; 12-inch cages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. The eggs obtained from these mosquitoes were hatched in cups containing pre-boiled water, and the larvae which emerged from the eggs were fed with a larval diet (brewer yeast, bovine liver powder, tuna meal) until pupae appeared. The pupae were then separated from the larvae and placed in containers with fresh water in separate cages for 36 h until adult mosquitoes emerged. These were then fed with 10% sucrose solution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. They were used as an <italic>in vivo</italic> culturing medium for <italic>S. digitata</italic> microfilariae.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Mosquito infection with <italic>S. digitata</italic></title><p id="Par20">Adult female worms obtained from a cattle slaughterhouse in Welisara, Ragama, Sri Lanka were cut into small pieces after washing three times with mosquito physiological saline (MPS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] to release microfilariae (MF) into a tube containing 300 &#x003bc;l MPS. This was vortexed and centrifuged at 1500&#x000d7; <italic>rpm</italic> for 30 s, and the supernatant recovered was then re-centrifuged at 1500&#x000d7; <italic>rpm</italic> for 3 min to obtain a pellet containing MF, which was then re-suspended in MPS to achieve a microfilariae (MF) concentration of 40 MF/&#x003bc;l.</p><p id="Par21">The thorax of anaesthetized adult mosquitoes (aged 3 days) on ice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] was injected with a volume of 0.5 &#x003bc;l of microfilariae suspension using a pre-pulled borosilicate glass capillary attached to a manual injector [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. The injected mosquitoes were kept in paper cups covered with a net while providing them with cotton pads soaked with the sucrose solution.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>siRNA synthesis, Cy3 labelling and RNAi treatment</title><p id="Par22">The entire coding sequence of <italic>SDNP</italic> was divided into four overlapping regions<italic>,</italic> and each of them was amplified by separate PCR reactions using four separate primer sets containing T7 promoter sequence at 5' ends (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) to enrich the total yield of the template and PCR products of overlapping regions were used to synthesize siRNA. The PCR conditions used for the amplification were initial denaturation at 94 &#x000b0;C for 2 min, followed by 40 cycles of denaturation at 94 &#x000b0;C for 30 s, annealing at 55 &#x000b0;C for the primer sets SDNP-1-F/R, SDNP-2-F/R and SDNP-3-F/R and 45 &#x000b0;C for the primer set SDNP-4-F/R, and extension at 72 &#x000b0;C for 30 s with a final extension of 10 min at 72 &#x000b0;C (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Primer sets used for the synthesis of dsRNA. The positions of the primers with respect to <italic>SDNP</italic> sequence (GenBank: GU222920), sequence corresponding to T7 promoter region of primers (underlined), the size of the PCR products, and the optimized annealing temperatures of primer sets are given</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Primer</th><th>Position</th><th>Sequence (5'-3')</th><th>Product size (bp)</th><th>Annealing T (&#x000b0;C)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>SDNP-1-F</td><td>1</td><td><underline>TAATACGACTCACTATAG</underline>GGCGACGAGGGTTCCATTGAGTGA</td><td rowspan="2">154</td><td rowspan="2">55</td></tr><tr><td>SDNP-1-R</td><td>134</td><td><underline>TAATACGACTCACTATAG</underline>GGGCTTCCTGACAAGCCAAACAT</td></tr><tr><td>SDNP-2-F</td><td>155</td><td><underline>TAATACGACTCACTATAG</underline>GGCGACGAGGGTTCCATTGAGTGA</td><td rowspan="2">150</td><td rowspan="2">55</td></tr><tr><td>SDNP-2-R</td><td>282</td><td><underline>TAATACGACTCACTATAG</underline>GGTTGGAATATAAACATGCGGTATA</td></tr><tr><td>SDNP-3-F</td><td>305</td><td><underline>TAATACGACTCACTATAG</underline>GGCTACCGGTATCAGAACTCAGAA</td><td rowspan="2">157</td><td rowspan="2">55</td></tr><tr><td>SDNP-3-R</td><td>462</td><td><underline>TAATACGACTCACTATAG</underline>GGTAGCGCTGGACCGAATTCTTTT</td></tr><tr><td>SDNP-4-F</td><td>463</td><td><underline>TAATACGACTCACTATAG</underline>GGGGAAATGGAACTTGTGAAATAA</td><td rowspan="2">155</td><td rowspan="2">45</td></tr><tr><td>SDNP-4-R</td><td>618</td><td><underline>TAATACGACTCACTATAG</underline>GGTCAGTAATTAATCAAATT</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Abbreviation</italic>: <italic>T</italic> temperature</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par23">The resulting PCR fragments were transcribed separately <italic>in vitro</italic> by T7 RNA polymerase (New England Biolabs, Hitchin, UK) using slightly modified manufacturer&#x02019;s protocols, to yield a high amount of dsRNA. Briefly, the <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription reaction was carried out overnight at 37 &#x000b0;C in a 120 &#x003bc;l reaction mix containing 81.5 &#x003bc;l of nuclease-free H<sub>2</sub>O, 12.0 &#x003bc;l of 10&#x000d7; T7 buffer, 3.0 &#x003bc;l of DTT (100 mM), 10 &#x003bc;l (2 &#x003bc;g) of PCR product, 12 &#x003bc;l of rNTP mix (80 mM), 1.5 &#x003bc;l of T7 RNA polymerase (18 U/&#x003bc;l). The RNA products of <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed DNA were first treated with DNase 1 (New England BioLabs) to remove DNA templates and then incubated at 75 &#x000b0;C for 5 min before cooling them down to room temperature for the complementary strands of synthesized RNA to anneal to make dsRNA. The dsRNA (assessed by gel electrophoresis) was digested with RNase III (New England Biolabs) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol to produce 21&#x02013;23 mer siRNA. They were analyzed by polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis before labelling with Cy3 fluorescent dye using a Silencer&#x000ae; siRNA Labeling Kit - Cy&#x02122;3 dye (Ambion, Life Technologies, California, USA) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par24">The ds-RNA synthesized from the gene encoding for the green fluorescent protein (GFP) of <italic>Aequorea victoria</italic> was also used as the non-specific siRNA control as this gene neither has any homologous sequences in <italic>S. digitata</italic> nor mosquito. pCRII TOPO vector (pCRII TOPO-<italic>GFP</italic>) containing <italic>GFP</italic> was used in the synthesis of GFP dsRNA. The vector was digested with <italic>Kpn</italic> I [7.5 &#x003bc;l nuclease free H<sub>2</sub>O, 2.0 &#x003bc;l 10&#x000d7; buffer, 0.5 &#x003bc;l <italic>Kpn</italic> I (15 U/&#x003bc;l)<italic>,</italic> 10 &#x003bc;l DNA (200 ng/&#x003bc;l); incubated 1 h at 37 &#x000b0;C] and <italic>Xho</italic> I [10 &#x003bc;l nuclease free H<sub>2</sub>O, 3.0 &#x003bc;l 10&#x000d7; buffer, 0.3 &#x003bc;l BSA, 0.5 &#x003bc;l <italic>Xho</italic> I (20 U/&#x003bc;l), 16.2 &#x003bc;l DNA (200 ng/&#x003bc;l); incubated 3 h at 37 &#x000b0;C] separately. The <italic>Kpn</italic> I digested vector was <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed by T7 RNA polymerase using the same protocol indicated above. The <italic>Xho</italic> I digested vector was <italic>in-vitro</italic> transcribed by Sp6 RNA polymerase using the following reaction; 60 &#x003bc;l of nuclease-free H<sub>2</sub>O, 8.0 &#x003bc;l of 10x Sp6 buffer, 2 &#x003bc;g (10 &#x003bc;l) of pCR II-TOPO vector, 8 &#x003bc;l of rNTP mix (80 mM), 2 &#x003bc;l of Sp6 RNA polymerase (20 U/&#x003bc;l), incubated at 40&#x000b0;C for 4 h. The separately <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed RNA was mixed and incubated at 75 &#x000b0;C for 5 min and cooled down to room temperature for the complementary strands of synthesised RNA to anneal to make dsRNA.</p><p id="Par25">The <italic>S. digitata</italic> infected mosquitoes were initially injected with 150 ng of Cy3 labelled <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA mix into their thorax at 12 h post infection (hpi) to monitor the uptake of siRNA by larvae. To target the L2 to L3 larvae transformation, non-labelled siRNA mix was injected at eight days post infection (dpi). The <italic>GFP</italic> siRNA (150 ng) was injected as a negative control.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Mosquito dissection</title><p id="Par26">The mosquitoes infected with <italic>S. digitata</italic> and injected with <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA, non-injected, <italic>GFP</italic> siRNA-injected and buffer-injected were dissected at different time intervals (24 hpi, 8&#x02013;14 dpi) under a dissection microscope. In this process, the bodies of cold anaesthetized mosquitoes were separated into the thorax, midgut, and head, and each of these body parts was further dissected to release the larvae on to glass slides. The MF obtained from the smeared content on the slides at 24 hpi were visualized under the fluorescent microscope using Cy3 filter set (excitation: 550 nm, emission: 570 nm) to detect the uptake of siRNA. The transformation of L2 larvae to L3 was recorded from the mosquitoes dissected at 8 to 14 dpi, and the following data were recorded only from the mosquitoes dissected at 14 dpi: (i) larvae length and width (Image J software was utilized in obtaining the measurements); (ii) larvae location in the mosquito (larvae in the head, thorax and abdomen of the mosquito; (iii) larvae motility (motility of the RNAi treated and control worms were compared according to a previously used pre-fashioned 5-point scheme based on Song et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]). The scoring scheme was as follows: 1, immobile, dead; 2, compromised motility; 3, partial movement of the body; 4, slightly reduced motion in the body; and 5, all parts of the body are vigorously twisting. Values in between 5 and 1 in the scale were assigned according to the decreasing motility blindly by an independent evaluator; (iv) at 14 dpi, mosquito survival rate was also measured by counting the live mosquitoes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Relative quantification of SDNP mRNA level</title><p id="Par27">Total RNA was extracted at two dpi and 14 dpi from non-injected, <italic>GFP</italic> siRNA injected, <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected and buffer-injected mosquitoes infected with S<italic>. digitata</italic> using a GenoSpin R<sup>TM</sup> Total RNA Extraction Kit (CEYGEN Biotech, Colombo, Sri Lanka) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Five mosquitoes were used from each batch. DNA contamination in extracted RNA was removed by treating with DNase I and heat inactivating the DNase I at 75 &#x000b0;C for 5 min. cDNA synthesis was carried out using RNA (2 &#x003bc;g) purified using an RNeasy Plus Mini Kit (Qiagen, California, USA) in a 20 &#x003bc;l reaction mix containing 5.0 &#x003bc;l of M-MLV transcription buffer, 1.0 &#x003bc;l of oligo dT primers (5 nM), 1.25 &#x003bc;l of dNTP mix (10 nM), 1.0 &#x003bc;l RNase inhibitor (20 U), 1.0 &#x003bc;l M-MLV reverse transcriptase (200 U, Promega, California, USA), RNA (2 &#x003bc;g), and RNase free water according to the vendor&#x02019;s protocol.</p><p id="Par28">Relative quantification of <italic>SDNP</italic> mRNA levels was carried out by quantitative real-time PCR [CFX96 RealTime PCR System (Bio-Rad)] using SYBR green as the DNA binding dye. qPCR conditions were initial denaturation at 95 &#x000b0;C for 2 min, followed by 40 cycles of denaturation at 95 &#x000b0;C for 30 s annealing at 60 &#x000b0;C for SDNP primers and 55 &#x000b0;C for actin primers for 45 s (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), and with an extension at 72 &#x000b0;C for 30 s. In qPCR, the actin gene (GenBank: AF079359.1) was used as the internal amplification control in a separate tube for each qPCR reaction. In calculating the relative mRNA expression level, the 2<sup>-&#x02206;&#x02206;CT</sup> method was used as mentioned in qPCR Application Guide (BioRad). The data obtained were presented as the mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (SD). A <italic>P</italic> value &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Primers used for qPCR. The primer sequences of the target (SDNP) and internal control (Actin) are given</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Primer</th><th>Sequence (5'-3')</th><th>Position</th><th>Product size (bp)</th><th>Annealing T (&#x000b0;C)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5">SDNP amplification</td></tr><tr><td>SDNP-RTPCR-FP</td><td>AAGACTTGCAACTCCATCTCGAT</td><td>219</td><td rowspan="2">170</td><td rowspan="2">60</td></tr><tr><td>SDNP-RTPCR-RP</td><td>ATTTTCTCGCTGACCACCACAACT</td><td>366</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><italic>S. digitata</italic> actin amplification (reference gene)</td></tr><tr><td>SDACT-RTPCR-FP</td><td>CGCTCGAGAAATCTTACGAATTGC</td><td>707</td><td rowspan="2">147</td><td rowspan="2">55</td></tr><tr><td>SDACT-RTPCR-RP</td><td>TCCTTTCTGATATCGATATCACATT</td><td>854</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Abbreviation</italic>: <italic>T</italic> temperature</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>siRNA uptake by <italic>S. digitata</italic> microfilariae in the mosquito host</title><p id="Par29">A previous study demonstrated the possibility of <italic>in vivo</italic> suppression of the cathepsin L-like cysteine protease gene of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>malayi</italic> using RNAi in <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Therefore, in this study, the possibility of using <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic> as an <italic>in vivo</italic> siRNA delivery platform for developing <italic>S. digitata</italic> larvae was tested, where the transformation of MF to L3 larvae of the latter organism has been observed. Since the previously stated study revealed the dissemination of siRNA to the MF of <italic>B. malayi</italic> through the mosquito, in the current study the uptake of the Cy3 labeled RNAi trigger by MF was investigated by, comparing the internal fluorescence of the MF with the mosquito physiological saline (MPS) injected control under a fluorescent microscope (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). A dispersion of the fluorescent signal was observed throughout the body of the tested MF at 24 hpi (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>) indicating that uptake of Cy3 labelled siRNA by MF is occurring in the mosquitoes. Although the mechanism of siRNA uptake is unclear at this point, it is possible that this would occur <italic>via</italic> feeding or through the cuticle of MF. Therefore, here, it was possible to recreate the <italic>in vitro</italic> siRNA soaking conditions for <italic>S. digitata</italic> larvae <italic>in vivo</italic>, and the possibility of utilizing the mosquito as a siRNA delivering platform for parasitic nematodes hosted by the mosquito was affirmed.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Uptake and distribution of Cy3 labelled <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA by microfilariae at 24 hpi. <bold>a</bold> Fluorescent image of microfilariae from siRNA non-injected mosquitoes (position indicated by a red square). <bold>b</bold> Bright field image of microfilariae from siRNA non-injected mosquitoes. <bold>c</bold> Fluorescent image of microfilariae from Cy3 labelled <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected mosquitoes (arrow indicates the dispersion of Cy3 labelled siRNA). <bold>d</bold> Bright field image of microfilariae from Cy3 labelled <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected mosquitoes. Fluorescence was visualised using Olympus BX53 using Cy3 filter. Magnification 400&#x000d7;. <italic>Scale-bars:</italic>
<bold>a-d</bold>, 20 &#x003bc;m</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2018_3096_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>The effect of siRNA on SDNP mRNA level of MF</title><p id="Par30">Several recent studies involving RNAi on nematodes showed that genes could be specifically suppressed by soaking the nematode in <italic>in vitro</italic> culture media consisting of RNAi triggers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. In this study, instead of using the <italic>in vitro</italic> culture conditions, we recreated the soaking conditions <italic>in vivo</italic> by injecting the mosquitoes harbouring nematode larvae with siRNA. The RNAi effect on <italic>SDNP</italic> transcript level was assessed two dpi, and 14 dpi of siRNA using qPCR and the knockdown of the gene was determined by comparing the transcript levels of the worms derived from non-injected, buffer-injected and <italic>GFP</italic> siRNA-injected mosquitoes. A significant suppression of the target gene expression was observed in this study, and the transcript abundance of the <italic>SDNP</italic> was reduced by 93% (unpaired two-tailed t-test, <italic>t</italic><sub>44</sub>
<italic>=</italic> 15.8716, <italic>P</italic> = 0.05) and 87.4 % (unpaired two-tailed t-test, <italic>t</italic><sub>44</sub>
<italic>=</italic> 15.2220, <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.05) in the worms from <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected mosquitoes, compared to the non-injected at 2 dpi and 14 dpi, respectively, compared to worms from non-injected mosquitoes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a, b</xref>). Worms from the buffer-injected, and <italic>GFP</italic> siRNA-injected mosquitoes displayed no significant changes in the <italic>SDNP</italic> transcript levels (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a, b</xref>). The qPCR results obtained proved the worms&#x02019; susceptibility to specific RNAi while showing the effectiveness of the new siRNA delivery platform developed in this study and the capability of siRNA to knockdown the targeted gene specifically in this parasitic nematode.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Relative mRNA expression changes owing to the RNAi. <bold>a</bold> Relative mRNA levels of <italic>SDNP</italic> at two dpi. <bold>b</bold> Relative mRNA levels of <italic>SDNP</italic> at 14 dpi. Changes of <italic>SDNP</italic> specific transcript levels were analysed by qPCR, and the 2<sup>-&#x02206;&#x02206;CT</sup> method was used in evaluating the results. For the reference gene, <italic>S. digitata</italic> actin gene was used. <italic>GFP</italic> was used as the non-specific control. <italic>SDNP</italic> transcript level was presented as relative to that of non-treated worms. Each experiment was performed in triplicate. Bars display mean &#x000b1; SD. Statistical analysis was performed using Student&#x02019;s t-test (<italic>P &#x0003c;</italic> 0.05). Significant differences are represented by different lowercase letters</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2018_3096_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Changes in developmental phenotypes and motility of larvae because of RNAi</title><p id="Par31">To study the phenotypic changes, if any, associated with the transformation of L2 to L3 in the <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected group in comparison to the control mosquito groups, the infected mosquitoes were dissected to recover the larval stages at eight dpi to 14 dpi following the RNAi trigger. A significant reduction in body length and width together with deformities in the body structure was observed in the larvae from <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected mosquitoes at 14 dpi (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b, e</xref>) compared to the non- injected, buffer-injected and <italic>GFP</italic> siRNA-injected counterparts (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a, c-e</xref>). In addition, aberrations, with larval lethality was also observed in <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA treated larvae compared to its control groups, and with ~96% of L2 to L3 transformation in non-treated, ~95% in buffer-treated and ~93% in <italic>GFP</italic> siRNA treated compared to ~18% of such transformation in treated at 14 dpi (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The L2 and L3 larvae were differentiated based on their length of the body. No significant developmental changes were observed in the worms from <italic>GFP</italic> siRNA-injected mosquitoes suggesting the phenotypic changes are specific to <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA and not due to the injection of non-specific siRNA. Therefore, it is reasonable to assume these phenotypic changes are most likely due to the downregulation of <italic>SDNP</italic> transcripts, which in turn affects the larval development. The previous finding reported by us, i.e., the ubiquitous expression of <italic>SDNP</italic> in all life stages of <italic>S. digitata</italic> and also its predominant expression in longitudinal muscle, reproductive systems, and developing embryos [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], together with the findings of the present study, i.e. association of <italic>SDNP</italic> downregulation with irregularities in the larvae development, transformation arrest, changes in phenotypes, etc. in larvae can be used to further strengthen our previous suggestion regarding the involvement of <italic>SDNP</italic> in growth and development of nematodes.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Larvae development in <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic> mosquitoes at 14 dpi. <bold>a</bold> Larvae in siRNA non-injected mosquito. <bold>b</bold> Larvae in <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected mosquito. <bold>c</bold> Larvae in <italic>GFP</italic> siRNA-injected mosquito. <bold>d</bold> Larvae in buffer-injected mosquito (magnification 400&#x000d7;). <bold>e</bold> Mean length and width of larvae form <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected, non-injected, buffer-injected and <italic>GFP</italic> siRNA-injected mosquitoes. To target L2 to L3, siRNA injections were made at 8 dpi. Triplicates were performed for each experiment. Bars represent mean &#x000b1; SD. Significant differences at <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 are represented by different lowercase letters. <italic>Scale-bars</italic>: <bold>a</bold>-<bold>d</bold>, 400 &#x003bc;m</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2018_3096_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Percentage of larval development to L3 stage out of total larvae inside the mosquito. <italic>S. digitata</italic> larvae from non-injected, <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected, <italic>GFP</italic> siRNA-injected and buffer-injected <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic> are represented by four different patterns in the graph. To target L2 to L3, siRNA injections were made at 8 dpi. Triplicates were performed for each experiment. Bars represent mean &#x000b1; SD. Significant differences at <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 are indicated by *</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2018_3096_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par32">In the motility changes monitored at 14 dpi of the control worms and worms from <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected mosquitoes, the former displayed a vigorously convoluting body movement (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a, c, d</xref>) of 4 and 5 in the motility scale (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a, c, d</xref>) while the <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-treated showed a significantly depressed body movement, feeble body twitching, and total body paralysis (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>, <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>). Also, the worms from <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected worms and monitored at 14 dpi displayed irregular migration patterns in the mosquitoes compared to the controls (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Worms from the control mosquitoes were predominantly found in the head (non-injected: ~91%; GFP siRNA-injected: ~85%; buffer-injected: ~87%) of the mosquito, while <italic>SDNP</italic>-suppressed worms were mainly found either in the thorax (~85%) or abdomen (~10%) indicating that motility irregularities of larvae are associated with the migration within the mosquito. It has been previously revealed that <italic>SDNP</italic> had homology with the inter-domain linkers of the muscle-specific twitchin kinase of <italic>C. elegans</italic> and was expressed in the longitudinal muscles of the adult worm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Hence, the downregulation of the <italic>SDNP</italic> could affect the muscle movement of the developing worm, which in turn reduces the migration of the parasite in the mosquito. The increased mosquito survival rate was seen in the <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected mosquito group compared to the control groups (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). This observation suggests that the compromised motility and development of the larvae induced by the <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA treatment could reduce the parasitic burden on the mosquito, thereby increasing its survival.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Motility comparison of larvae at 14 dpi in, <bold>a</bold> non-injected, <bold>b</bold>
<italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected, <bold>c</bold>
<italic>GFP</italic> siRNA-injected, <bold>d</bold> buffer-injected mosquitoes (Magnification 40&#x000d7;) <italic>Scale-bars</italic>: <bold>a</bold>-<bold>d</bold>, 400 &#x003bc;m</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2018_3096_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Frequency distribution for motility of <italic>S. digitata</italic> larvae at 14 dpi in, <bold>a</bold> siRNA non-injected, <bold>b</bold>
<italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected, <bold>c</bold>
<italic>GFP</italic> siRNA-injected and <bold>d</bold> buffer-injected mosquitoes. The scoring scheme was: 1, immobile or dead; 2, compromised motility; 3, partial movement of the body; 4, slightly reduced motion in the body; 5, all parts of the body are vigorously twisting. Values in between 5 and 1 in the scale were assigned according to the decreasing motility blindly by an independent evaluator. Five replicates were performed for each experiment. Bars represent mean &#x000b1; SD</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2018_3096_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig><fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Frequency distribution of <italic>S. digitata</italic> larvae in <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic> head, thorax, or abdomen. Migration of the larvae was monitored at 14 dpi in non-injected, <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected, <italic>GFP</italic> siRNA-injected and buffer-injected mosquitoes. Mosquitoes were dissected into head, thorax and abdomen and larvae in each part was counted. Five replicates were performed for each experiment. Bars represent mean &#x000b1; SD. Statistical analysis was performed using Student&#x02019;s t-test (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Significant differences at <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 are indicated by *</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2018_3096_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig><fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Mosquito survival rate. Survivability of the non-injected, <italic>SDNP</italic> siRNA-injected, <italic>GFP</italic> siRNA-injected and buffer-injected mosquitoes at 14 dpi was measured. Five replicates were performed for each experiment. Bars represent mean &#x000b1; SD. Significant differences at <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 are indicated with different lowercase letters</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2018_3096_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par33">In this study, we demonstrated the successful usage of the RNAi approach to turn off the expression of <italic>SDNP</italic> in the larval stages of <italic>S. digitata</italic> in their natural milieu, <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic>, and the possibility of using this host as an <italic>in vivo</italic> culture platform in the absence of proper culture conditions to study the biological functions of the genes that the <italic>S. digitata</italic> genome encodes<italic>.</italic> Further, we showed that the specific silencing of <italic>SDNP</italic> is associated with developmental deformities and motility changes in the developing larvae of <italic>S. digitata</italic>, in addition to the reduction of migration of the larvae to the head of the mosquito. Therefore, by taking the outcomes of present and our previous studies into consideration, it can be concluded that <italic>SDNP</italic> plays a vital role in the movement and development of larvae. Hence, it can be suggested that the <italic>SDNP</italic> may be utilised as a candidate anthelminthic drug target.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>RNAi</term><def><p id="Par4">RNA interference</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SDNP</term><def><p id="Par5">Setaria digitata novel protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qPCR</term><def><p id="Par6">Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>siRNA</term><def><p id="Par7">Small interfering RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>dsRNA</term><def><p id="Par8">Double stranded RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MPS</term><def><p id="Par9">Mosquito physiological saline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MF</term><def><p id="Par10">Microfilariae</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>hpi</term><def><p id="Par11">Hour post infection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>dpi</term><def><p id="Par12">Days post-infection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GFP</term><def><p id="Par13">Green fluorescent protein.</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgement</title><p>The corresponding author wishes to acknowledge Professor Mark Taylor and his team for providing him training in RNA interference at his laboratories in Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine, Liverpool under the Commonwealth Fellowship Programme in 2012.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par34">The research was funded by a grant (AP/3/2011/CG/03) awarded to Professor R.S. Dassanayake by the University of Colombo, Sri Lanka, to promote collaborative research. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par35">The data supporting the conclusions of this study are included within the article. Clones and raw data are available from the authors upon request.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>MBCLS carried out research work, collected samples, analysed data, and wrote the manuscript. YINSG supervised research work, analysed research data and wrote the manuscript. NVC supervised research work data and corrected the manuscript. ANBE analysed research data and corrected the manuscript. RSD designed and supervised the study and corrected the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhadury</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Austen</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilton</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambshead</surname><given-names>PJD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Smerdon</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and evaluation of a DNA-barcoding approach for the rapid identification of nematodes</article-title><source>Mar Ecol Prog Ser</source><year>2006</year><volume>320</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/meps320001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stepek</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Buttle</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Duce</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Behnke</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human gastrointestinal nematode infections: are new control methods required?</article-title><source>Int J Exp Pathol</source><year>2006</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2613.2006.00495.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16965561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Global Programme to Eliminate Lymphatic Filariasis</collab></person-group><source>Progress report on mass drug administration 2010</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Switzerland</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nematodes: a threat to sustainability of agriculture</article-title><source>Procedia Environ Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.proenv.2015.07.270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roeber</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jex</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasser</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of gastrointestinal parasitic nematodes of sheep, and the role of advanced molecular tools for exploring epidemiology and drug resistance - an Australian perspective</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>153</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-6-153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23711194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilleard</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding anthelmintic resistance: the need for genomics and genetics</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2006</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1227</fpage><lpage>1239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2006.06.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16889782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug resistance in nematodes of veterinary importance: a status report</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol</source><year>2004</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2004.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15363441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richard-Lenoble</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandenier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaxotte</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ivermectin and filariasis</article-title><source>Fundam Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1472-8206.2003.00170.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12667230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berriman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lustigman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarter</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomics and emerging drug discovery technologies</article-title><source>Expert Opin Drug Discov</source><year>2007</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>S83</fpage><lpage>S89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/17460441.2.S1.S83</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23489036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlow</surname><given-names>CKS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mining nematode genome data for novel drug targets</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2004.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15734654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuwabara</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNAi - prospects for a general technique for determining gene function</article-title><source>Parasitol Today</source><year>2000</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-4758(00)01677-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10900483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allshire</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retraction. Hairpin RNAs and retrotransposon LTRs effect RNAi and chromatin-based gene silencing</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>310</volume><fpage>49</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.310.5745.49b</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shankaranarayana</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Noma</surname><given-names>K-I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayoub</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>SIS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Establishment and maintenance of a heterochromatin domain</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>2232</fpage><lpage>2237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1076466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12215653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behm</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bendig</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarter</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sluder</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNAi-based discovery and validation of new drug targets in filarial nematodes</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2004.12.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15734653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fire</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Albertson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Moerman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of antisense RNA leads to effective and specific inhibition of gene expression in <italic>C. elegans</italic> muscle</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1991</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>514</lpage><?supplied-pmid 1782862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1782862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name><name><surname>Behm</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Target identification and validation for anthelmintic discovery</article-title><source>Expert Opin Drug Discov</source><year>2007</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>S91</fpage><lpage>S98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/17460441.2.S1.S91</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23489038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfarr</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Heider</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoerauf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNAi mediated silencing of actin expression in adult <italic>Litomosoides sigmodontis</italic> is specific, persistent and results in a phenotype</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2006</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2006.01.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16546192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamath</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahringer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide RNAi screening in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2003</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1046-2023(03)00050-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12828945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallup</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartholomay</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimber</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of an <italic>in vivo</italic> RNAi protocol to investigate gene function in the filarial nematode, <italic>Brugia malayi</italic></article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e1001239</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1001239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21203489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jinkichi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Soichi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Toshio</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tetsuo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ken</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tadashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heterotopic parasitism of <italic>Setaria digitata</italic> (Linstow, 1906) in the heart of a cattle</article-title><source>Japanese J Vet Sci</source><year>1985</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>999</fpage><lpage>1002</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms1939.47.999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antigenicity of a filarial protease from <italic>Setaria digitata</italic> in <italic>Wuchereria bancrofti</italic> infection</article-title><source>Ann Trop Med Parasitol</source><year>1999</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00034983.1999.11813424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10562830</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decruse</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Raj</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histological studies on female <italic>Setaria digitata</italic> (von Linstow 1906), a filaria of bovine, <italic>Bos indicus</italic></article-title><source>Proc Anim Sci</source><year>1990</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03186378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Hawking F &#x00026; World Health Organization</collab></person-group><source>Diethylcarbamazine: a review of the literature with special reference to its pharmacodynamics, toxicity, and use in the therapy of onchocerciasis and other filarial infections</source><year>1978</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>WWP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dassanayake</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Voronin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel parasitic nematode-specific protein of <italic>Setaria digitata</italic> largely localized in longitudinal muscles, reproductive systems and developing embryos</article-title><source>Exp Parasitol</source><year>2014</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exppara.2014.03.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24632187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lendner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Doligalska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucius</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Attempts to establish RNA interference in the parasitic nematode <italic>Heligmosomoides polygyrus</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>2008</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molbiopara.2008.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18606194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tung</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Demonstration of vector competence of <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae) for <italic>Setaria digitata</italic></article-title><source>Vet Parasitol</source><year>2004</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2004.07.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15325055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerberg</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Manual for mosquito rearing and experimental techniques</article-title><source>Bull Am Mosq Control Assoc</source><year>1970</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>109</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of a physiological saline solution for <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (L.)</article-title><source>J Econ Entomol</source><year>1953</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>624</fpage><lpage>627</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jee/46.4.624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Benedict M, Howell P. 3.8 Mosquito Anesthesia. In: Methods in <italic>Anopheles</italic> Research. 2nd ed. Atlanta: bei RESOURCES; 2010. p. 1&#x02013;4.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garver</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protocol for RNAi assays in adult mosquitoes (<italic>A. gambiae</italic>)</article-title><source>J Vis Exp</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>230</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Juhn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Injection of dsRNA into female <italic>A. aegypti</italic> mosquitoes</article-title><source>J Vis Exp</source><year>2007</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>224</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashmi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuhrman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oksov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of the cathepsin-like cysteine protease genes in adult <italic>Brugia malayi</italic> using RNA interference</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e377</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19190745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of the cellulase gene of the pine wood nematode, <italic>Bursaphelenchus xylophilus</italic>, using RNA interference</article-title><source>Genet Mol Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1931</fpage><lpage>1941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4238/vol10-3gmr1367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21948755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aboobaker</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaxter</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of RNA interference to investigate gene function in the human filarial nematode parasite <italic>Brugia malayi</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>2003</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-6851(03)00092-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12798505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lustigman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Oksov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashmi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA interference targeting cathepsin L and Z-like cysteine proteases of <italic>Onchocerca volvulus</italic> confirmed their essential function during L3 molting</article-title><source>Mol Biochem Parasitol</source><year>2004</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molbiopara.2004.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15555728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dassanayake</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>WWP</given-names></name><name><surname>Karunanayake</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Weerasena</surname><given-names>OVDSJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrasekharan</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A putative nuclear growth factor-like globular nematode-specific protein</article-title><source>Bioinformation</source><year>2009</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6026/97320630003370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19759810</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>