<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Three factors give information on the properties of the analyzed sample material, properties that are compared to those of the reference material, which is considered to be ideal. Values close to 1 for the three factors point out that the analyzed material has properties that are very close to those of the reference material. A decrease in the values of the three factors indicates the presence of manufacture defects or that the analyzed material is different from the reference material. A value of less than 1 of the resistance factor shows that there are areas in the material where the mechanical properties are inferior to those of the reference material. In the case of composite materials, it indicates that there are areas where either the reinforcement volume proportion is lower than necessary, or the reinforcement orientation does not coincide with that of the reference material. A value less than 1 of the elasticity factor may give information on the dimensions of the area where the mechanical properties are inferior to those of the reference material. The lower the elasticity factor, the larger the faulty area dimensions. If the elasticity factor is 1 and the resistance factor is less than 1, there is a concentrated defect in the analyzed material. The uniformity factor characterizes the uniformity of the analyzed material. Decreased values of this factor point out the existence in the material of certain areas where the mechanical properties differ very much. There might be a case when the resistance factor and the elasticity factor have values less than 1, be very close, or a case in which the uniformity factor is near to the value 1. This shows that the analyzed material is uniform and so different from the reference material that it is actually a different material and not the faulty reference material. In the case of composites, this situation may indicate that the analyzed material has reinforcing material proportions, resin specifically, different from those of the reference material.</p>
