<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.3.2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.2. Determination of Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC), Minimum Bactericidal Concentration (MBC), and Minimum Fungicidal Concentration (MFC)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) of HR and SGR essential oils was evaluated by means of the twofold serial microdilution assay [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>]. The essential oils dissolved in DMSO were diluted at concentrations ranging from 500 to 0.48 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL, with Mueller-Hinton broth medium for bacteria and 5000 to 4.88 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL with Sabouraud medium for yeasts. The antimicrobial activity of the solvent DMSO was also evaluated. Vancomycin (for Gram-positive bacteria), norfloxacin (for Gram-negative bacteria), and amphotericin B (for yeasts) were used as controls. The MIC values, presented in 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL, were considered as the lowest concentration of the essential oils that inhibited the growth of the microorganisms, after 24 h of incubation at 37°C. The microbial growth was measured with an Absorbance Microplate Reader set to 620 nm (Thermo Scientific Multiskan FC). Assays for each tested microorganism were carried out in triplicate.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Minimum Bactericidal Concentration (MBC) or Minimum Fungicidal Concentration (MFC) were evaluated for each set of wells. For the MIC evaluation, a loopful of broth was collected from those wells where any growth was observed and then was further inoculated on sterile Mueller-Hinton medium broth for bacteria and Sabouraud medium for yeasts by streaking. The plates were then inoculated with microorganism and were incubated at 37°C for 24 h. After incubation, the lowest concentration was considered as MBC (for bacteria) and MFC (for yeasts) and presented in 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL, at which no visible growth was observed.
 </p>
</sec>
