<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The thirty seven samples from Greece (22 traditional mixtures and single ingredients and 15 packed industrial samples), were acquired in different traditional herb stores of Greece: Rethymno and Heraklion in Crete, Naxos, Santorini, Thessaloniki, and 
 <italic>Varvakeion</italic> market in Athens between 2016 and 2019 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). The six traditional samples from Syria, were acquired in herbalist local stores of Damascus in 1999 and the four industrial, throughout online commerce since 2011 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). In Lebanon, “
 <italic>zhoura</italic>t”, a renowned herbal blend was studied, six samples of traditional formulations were analyzed three were prepared by three independent informants in Kfarhamam (in Southern Lebanon). One sample was blended in the “
 <italic>Dabbous</italic>” specialist shop of herbs and spices, in Tripoli (Northern Lebanon). The other two traditional mixtures, which are prepared in Beirut (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>), were acquired from a Lebanese food store in Paris (Les Délices D'Orient). On-line commerce industrial “
 <italic>zhourat</italic>” samples include Abido Libanesischer Kräutertee, Abido Mills Herbal Tea and London Tea (Lebanon), Al Rayan Zhourat, Zhourat Shamia, Syrian Natural Products Zhourat tea, and Alattar Zhourat Lebnania (Syria). A traditional mixture made by the Assyrian of Tur-Abdin (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abdalla 2004</xref>) was also included. Two traditional mixtures from Iran and four from Turkey were obtained from herbalists at Tehran and Istanbul respectively. Industrial samples from Iran (fifteen) and Turkey (five) were obtained at the World’s Expo Food Fair of Milan (Italy), in 2015 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>), and from different on-line commerce sites in 2020. The outgroup of spices mixtures include: Arabian Spice mixture, Bahrat, Hawayil (Yemen), Berebere and Zahtar (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Ellen’s Kitchen, 2020</xref>), Laebriq, Ras el Hanut and Tjalaet (Morocco) (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">González et al., 2010</xref>), Ras el Hanout (Morocco) (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Bellakhdar, 1997</xref>) and Arba'in (Palestine) (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Crowfoot and Baldensperger 1932</xref>).
</p>
