<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The quest for novel drugs in the clinical treatment of diabetic complications such as peripheral neuropathy has led to the discovery of DA-9801, an ethanol extract of 
 <italic>D. japonica</italic>, 
 <italic>D. rhizoma</italic> and 
 <italic>D. nipponica</italic>, as a potential therapeutic agent [
 <xref rid="B294-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">294</xref>,
 <xref rid="B295-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">295</xref>]. Peripheral neuropathy is a common disorder among diabetic patients, a result of the malfunctioning of the peripheral nerves. Peripheral neuropathy is characterized by symptoms such as pain, numbness and chronic aberrant sensations, which often disrupt sleep and can lead to depression, thus affecting the quality of life [
 <xref rid="B238-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">238</xref>]. An investigation conducted by Song et al. [
 <xref rid="B296-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">296</xref>] on the inhibitory effects of DA-9801 on transport activities of clinically important transporters showed that inhibitory effects in vitro did not translate into in vivo herb drug interaction in rats. Interestingly, Jin et al. [
 <xref rid="B297-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">297</xref>] and Moon et al. [
 <xref rid="B238-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">238</xref>] further buttressed the potential therapeutic applications of DA-9801 for the treatment of diabetic peripheral neuropathy. These studies show that DA-9801 reduced blood glucose levels and increased the response latency to noxious thermal stimuli. It is anticipated that DA-9801 can be used as a botanical drug for the treatment of diabetic neuropathy. Transporters are critical in the absorption, distribution and elimination of drugs, thus modulating efficacy and toxicity [
 <xref rid="B296-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">296</xref>]. This prediction of interaction is vital in clinical studies and the drug development process. Sato et al. [
 <xref rid="B298-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">298</xref>] demonstrated that the natural product diosgenin remains a candidate for use in acute improvement of blood glucose level in type I diabetes mellitus. Also, Omoruyi [
 <xref rid="B299-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">299</xref>] supports the use of 
 <italic>D. polygonoides</italic> extracts in clinical management of metabolic disorders such as diabetes.
</p>
