<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">Plants are the repository of variable number of valuable secondary metabolites that bears pharmacognostic and pharmacological implications having potentiality to emerge as super drugs in future. In-vivo production of these metabolites is influenced by the biotic and abiotic stresses resulting in continuous accumulation of diverse phytochemicals and their derivatives that can be useful in designing and developing potential drugs for future. The aim of the present study is to review the existence of medicinally important secondary metabolites and possible pharmacological and pharmacognostic importance of under-explored weed plant species 
   <italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> (L.) Poit., to explore the potentiality of the plant for developing and designing the drugs for future.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Main body of the abstract</title>
  <p id="Par2">
   <italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> belonging to family Lamiaceae is the rich source of medicinally important phytochemicals like essential oils, tannins, saponins, phenols, flavonoids, terpenoids, alkaloids, and sterols. One or many of these compounds have antioxidative, anti-inflammatory, antispasmodic, anti-septic, anti-cancer, anti-ulcer, antimicrobial, antibacterial, antiviral, antifungal, anti-diabetic, anti-fertility, diaphoretics, anticutaneous, anticatarrhal, antirheumatic, anti-ulcer, gastroprotective, immunomodulatory, analgesic, and antiviral activity.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Short conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par3">
   <italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> contains unique terpenoid metabolites like suaveolic acid, suaveolol, methyl suaveolate, beta-sitosterol, ursolic acid, and phenolic compound like rosamarinic acid, methyl rosamarinate that have potentiality to substitute the traditional drugs as therapeutic agent against the resistant and newly emerged bacterial and viral pathogens. Pentacyclic triterpenoid, ursolic acid have been reported to have effective antiviral response against the SARS-CoV2 responsible for the present COVID-19 pandemic and HIV virus for which no effective vaccines are available till date. Ursolic acid has the ability to modulate the activity of main protease (M
   <sup>pro</sup>) that is essential for processing of SARS-CoV2 replicase-transcriptase machinery needed for viral replication and particle assembly.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
