<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <italic>Camellia</italic> genus of the family Theaceae is among the most traditional and famous plants in Asia [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], especially in China and Japan. Different species and cultivars are prevalent in many countries across the world, including in Portugal. Some species belonging to 
 <italic>Camellia</italic> genus have a high economic value due to their subproducts such as tea, oil seed, iconic flowering shrubs and ornamental plants [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The high abundance and economic value has boosted interest in the biological properties of this plant genus and several studies were undertaken to evaluate its antioxidant, antimicrobial and antitumor activity. Most of the studies on the 
 <italic>Camellia</italic> genus were focused in three species; namely, 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> (the tea plant), 
 <italic>C. oleifera</italic> (used to obtain edible oil) and 
 <italic>C. japonica</italic> (ornamental flowers). Tea is the second most consumed beverage worldwide, just after water [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and is most consumed as black, green or oolong tea, being also found as white, pu’erh or red tea [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Black tea is preferred in Western countries (78%), followed by green tea (20%) and oolong tea (approximately 2%) [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Despite being from the same plant, 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> or 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> var 
 <italic>assamica</italic> leaves, the different types of teas are obtained according to the fermentation process used. The edaphoclimatic conditions and the agricultural practices strongly impact the composition and properties these plants [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Tea leaves are mainly composed by alkaloids, steroids, terpenoids, and polyphenols [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], including catechins [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. 
 <italic>Camellia</italic> oil is obtained from 
 <italic>C. oleifera</italic> seeds and is one of the four edible tree oils (palm oil, olive oil and coconut oil). It is mainly composed by neutral lipids (88.2%), especially oleic acid (86.3%—
 <italic>C. japonica;</italic> 67.7–76.7%—
 <italic>C. oleifera</italic>). and is commonly named as “Asian olive oil” because of the high oleic acid concentration, very similar to that of olive oil [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. After oil extraction, 
 <italic>C. oleifera</italic> seeds still are of interest (the so called 
 <italic>Camellia</italic> seed cake) and have been used over the years as a material for washing hair, for itching and pain relief and to produce cosmetics and food supplements [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Over the years a huge amount of works was published demonstrating that these species are an enormous source of antioxidant compounds with proven biological activity against bacteria, fungi and virus as well as antitumor potential [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. This review aimed to summarize all of these works giving a global and critical perspective of the properties of such an important genus. The antioxidant activity is discussed firstly (
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2-molecules-26-02178">Section 2</xref>. Antioxidant Properties) and, due to the large amount of available data, the most relevant antioxidant parameters quantified in the literature were summarized in a table (
 <xref rid="molecules-26-02178-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The next section is dedicated to the antimicrobial activity and includes antibacterial, antifungal and antiviral properties. The antitumor activity is explored in 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec4-molecules-26-02178">Section 4</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec5-molecules-26-02178">Section 5</xref> is dedicated to other benefits on health and diseases. Finally, a concluding remarks section was added to stress that despite the large amount of published literature, further additional works still are of relevance, particularly if focused on 
 <italic>Camellia</italic> species other than 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic>, 
 <italic>C. japonica</italic> and 
 <italic>C. oleifera</italic>.
</p>
