<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RosA is a natural, water-soluble phenolic acid compound that can be isolated from 
 <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L. (Labiatae). Due to its widespread distribution, it is particularly found in plants of Lamiaceae and Boraginaceae in large amounts. RosA also serves as an effective active ingredient of 
 <italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic> Bge., 
 <italic>Perilla frutescens</italic> (L.) Britt., 
 <italic>Prunella vulgaris</italic> L. and other Chinese herbal medicines (Cai et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Moreover, it possesses oxidation resistance (Zych et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), anti-inflammation (Fan et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>), immune regulation (Cao et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) and anti-thrombosis (Zou et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>) activities and other biological functions. Studies have found that RosA can help prevent cell damage caused by free radicals due to its strong antioxidant activity, which is related to its structure (Fujimoto et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The catechol hydroxyl eliminates free radical activity, while its C-3 conjugated double bond has a synergistic effect (Imai et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). According to numerous investigations, oxidative stress is the most serious and long-lasting factor that leads to myocardial I/R injury (Gonzalez-Montero et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Therefore, it is believed that RosA is a likely drug candidate for preventing and treating heart and cerebrovascular diseases. Previous studies have also reported that RosA has protective effects against acute ischaemic injury (Ramalho et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and hypoxia/reoxygenation myocardial cell injury in rats (Zhang et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Furthermore, recent studies have shown that RosA has strong anti-apoptotic ability and can protect cells from hydrogen peroxide-induced DNA damage and apoptosis (Salimei et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). In light of the above studies, this investigation assumed that RosA possesses protective effects in myocardial ischaemia/reperfusion injury.
</p>
