<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition, there is a large body of evidence showing that oxidative stress is primarily induced by hyperglycemia and is associated with a key process in the initiation and progression of diabetic complications [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-26-00317" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-molecules-26-00317" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]; however, the precise mechanisms by which oxidative stress accelerates the development of diabetic complications are only partly known [
 <xref rid="B43-molecules-26-00317" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-26-00317" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Inflammatory mediators are generated, and these are stimulated by hyperglycemia-induced oxidative stress, which leads to the production of free radical species [
 <xref rid="B42-molecules-26-00317" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-26-00317" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Free radicals are an unstable species of molecule that pair up their odd free electrons by attacking healthy cells, causing loss of cell structure and/or function [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-26-00317" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. These damaged cells contribute greatly to degenerative diseases such as cancer, inflammation, immune system weakening, liver disease, brain dysfunction, cardiovascular conditions, diabetic renal failure, and others [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-26-00317" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Plant antioxidants are free radical-scavenging agents that can control the detrimental effect of these unstable species on the human body [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-26-00317" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and may be useful in treating some diabetic complications. This work aimed to perform a large-scale screening of plant extracts that exhibit both inhibitory effects on α-amylase and free radical-scavenging properties with minimal side effects. To this end, 41 extracts from plants widely used by people in the Middle East as food and medication were screened for such activities. Once a plant extract that can act as both an antidiabetic and antioxidant is identified, it can be further studied to isolate its bioactive compounds.
</p>
