<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phytochemicals are compounds that help plants to defend against microbes, insects, and other animals. When these phytochemicals are subjected to isolation from medicinal plants and then used in the form of plant extracts, they can have a lot of therapeutic importance [
 <xref rid="B1-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The primary active compounds of the plant extracts include antioxidants and antimicrobials. However, the antimicrobial attributes of plant extracts are of significant interest nowadays [
 <xref rid="B4-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The uncontrolled and massive utilization of synthetic compounds, such as antibiotics in cosmetics, medicine, pharmaceutics, and the food industry, is causing environmental concerns [
 <xref rid="B7-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Interestingly, plant extracts have been largely used to treat microbial infections due to their inherent ability to treat synthetic antibiotic-resistant infections [
 <xref rid="B10-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The efficient extraction and delivery of phyto-compounds (e.g., essential oils) to patients from medicinal plants is a great challenge for researchers with regard to use them as antimicrobial agents. The antimicrobial agents, e.g., essential oils, have an exclusive position to treat various diseases. However, the polymer matrix also performs a critical function in delivering the same. To achieve this goal, various polymers are used to provide a suitable vehicle system to deliver essential oils. These polymers are used primarily in the form of nanomaterials with different dimensions (e.g., 0-D, 1-D, 2-D, and 3-D). However, the nanomaterials in the form of 1-D structures; for instance, the polymeric nanofibers, are vigorously used due to their large surface-to-volume ratio compared to other nanostructures. In this regard, various techniques were previously put forward for manufacturing these nanofibers, such as freeze-drying [
 <xref rid="B15-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], self-assembly [
 <xref rid="B17-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], phase separation [
 <xref rid="B19-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], template synthesis [
 <xref rid="B19-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and spinneret-based engineered parameters [
 <xref rid="B16-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. However, electrospinning is the most widely utilized technique for applications in tissue engineering [
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], wound dressing [
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], and drug release [
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. This method has drawn tremendous interest in the scientific community due to its low price, flexibility to tune the fiber morphology, and high yield, which make this technique industrially applicable. It produces fibers within the diameter range of few microns to the nanometer scale using high electric fields [
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Moreover, essential oils, because of their antioxidant [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], antiparasitic [
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], insecticidal [
 <xref rid="B31-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], antidepressant [
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], food preservative [
 <xref rid="B36-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], analgesic, and anti-inflammatory [
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] properties, are recently gaining popularity. Therefore, the latest research paid enormous attention to nanofibers’ application with antimicrobial agents that will be used in tissue engineering, drug delivery, food, cosmetics, and wound healing. Pant et al. prepared salicylic acid/polyurethane nanofibers, showing good mechanical qualities, excellent biocompatibility, and antibacterial action, thus having considerable promise for various future health applications, including tissue engineering, injury treatment, and medicines [
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Similarly, they also fabricated electrospun carbon nanofibers loaded with titanium dioxide/ zinc oxide nanoparticles (TiO
 <sub>2</sub>/ZnO NPs), which demonstrated a strong photocatalytic activity for the decomposition of methylene blue under UV irradiation, and showed good antibacterial properties as well [
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. However, this review article will discuss the application of several essential oils, such as lavender, thyme, cinnamon, peppermint, tea tree, etc., encapsulating composite fibers, and mainly electrospun fibers.
</p>
