<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The properties of gelatin nanoparticles (GNPs) can be maximized by applying a particular extraction procedure. GNPs can be extracted by applying: (i) two-step desolvation, the method is characterized by the presence of a desolvating agent in an aqueous gelatin solution, resulting in conformational modification from triple helical coiled macromolecular arrangement to nanoparticles. Kumari and co-authors organized GNPs in a size range of 110–257 nm by this procedure [
 <xref rid="B91-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>]. (ii) Simple coacervation: Mohanty and co-authors [
 <xref rid="B92-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>] successfully obtained stable spherical nanoparticles (45 ± 5 nm) by measured presence of ethanol to aqueous gelatin solution. (iii) Solvent evaporation: this methodology is characterized by a single emulsion, oil-in-water (w/o), or double-emulsion, (water-in-oil)-in-water (w/o)/w, procedure. Water solutions that contain drug and gelatin are incorporated with ultrasonic treatment or high-speed homogenization with the oil phase. The water-in-water mixture method is utilized to produce insulin-loaded GNPs (250 nm) in mild conditions for the activity of insulin [
 <xref rid="B93-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>]. (iv) Microemulsion: It is a new and successful procedure used to prepare gelatin particles. In this process, gelatin in aqueous solution is combined to the solution of surfactant [sodium bis (2-ethylhexyl) sulfosuccinate (AOT)] in n-hexane and then glutaraldehyde (GA) to cross-link the nanostructures, followed by evaporation of n-hexane for recovery of GNPs [
 <xref rid="B94-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>]. The nanostructures had dimensions ranging 5–50 nm. (v) Nanoprecipitation: Implies the precipitation of pre-formed GNPs from an organic solution and the dispersion of the organic solvent in the water solution with prevalence of a surfactant [
 <xref rid="B95-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">97</xref>].
</p>
