<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Buckwheat belongs to the family of Polygonaceae. 
 <italic class="italic">Fagopyrum esculentum</italic> (Common buckwheat) has been a crop of secondary importance in many countries, and the main producers are the Russian Federation, China, Ukraine and Kazakhstan [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-23-00182" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-23-00182" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Fagopyrum tataricum</italic> (Tartary buckwheat) is a popular edible and medicinal coarse cereal, mainly cultivated in the southwest of China, northern India, Bhutan and Nepal [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-23-00182" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-23-00182" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Both 
 <italic class="italic">F. esculentum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">F. tataricum</italic> are rich in proteins, amino acids, dietary fiber, vitamins and trace elements. Nowadays, there are a lot of buckwheat-based food products available on the market such as buckwheat flour, noodles, bread, tea, vinegar and sprouts [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-23-00182" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-23-00182" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-23-00182" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Fagopyrum cymosum</italic> is a famous medicinal plant mainly distributed in China, Nepal, India, Bhudan and Thailand. Its rhizome was regarded as folk medicine for clearing away heat and toxic materials, removing blood stasis and expelling pus, which has been widely used for the treatment of lung diseases, rheumatism, inflammation, snakebite and traumatic injuries [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-23-00182" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-23-00182" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. The major bioactive compounds of the three buckwheat species (
 <italic class="italic">F. esculentum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">F. tataricum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">F. cymosum</italic>) have demonstrated to be phenolics, flavonoids (such as rutin, quercetin, kampferol, orientin, and vitexin etc.), terpenoids, steroids, 
 <sc class="sc">d</sc>-chiro-inositol, 
 <sc class="sc">d</sc>-fagomine, and emodin, etc. Recent studies have revealed that these bioactive compounds had notable antioxidant, hypocholesterolemic, antidiabetic, antimicrobial, and antitumor activities, and were beneficial for human health [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-23-00182" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-23-00182" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>].
</p>
