<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par60">Valles et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>] using an expressed sequence tag (EST) library from 
 <italic>S. invicta</italic>, detected a short sequence (approximately 750 nt, GenBank access: EF409991) related to plant tenuiviruses. Further identity analysis showed that sequence is 99.8% identical to SINV14 RNA4. They suggested that the sequence would be likely a contamination due to the ant diet feeding either plant or infected insect. Tenuiviruses are typical plant viruses that replicate in the insect vector [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], and the high abundance of SINV-14 compared to housekeeping genes is strong evidence of active replication in 
 <italic>S. invicta</italic>. Furthermore, the highest virus abundance was found in a sample prepared from a dissected ant brain, which rules out the possibility of contamination due to feeding on plants or association with insect vectors infected with a tenuivirus. The Maize stripe virus (MSpV), a typical plant tenuivirus, was detected in the brain of its vector 
 <italic>Peregrinus maidis</italic>, providing evidence of replication of tenuiviruses in this tissue [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Tenuiviruses replicate in diverse tissues of their insect vectors and are transovarially transmitted between generations suggesting that SINV-14, and other tenui-like viruses, could be sustained through vertical transmission in their insect host [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Additionally, significant asymmetric abundance sequences of different components of SINV-14 suggest a very specific and active interaction. Asymmetric accumulation in multipartite viruses has been shown and seems to be common trait, shared by RNA and DNA multipartite viruses infecting plants and animals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]; this has been suggested to be involved in control of gene expression allowing fast virus adaptation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Although this has not yet been shown for any phenuivirus and may be host dependent [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>], our results suggest that this may occur, at least for SINV-14, and more experiments will be necessary to confirm.
</p>
