<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> (Martius) Grisebach (Amaranthaceae), commonly known as alligator weed, is a perennial herbaceous plant that is both stoloniferous and amphibious. It can grow prostrate along the ground or across the water surface, rooting at the nodes, anchoring to the shore, and forming tangled mats. The native range of this species is thought to be the Parana River region of southern Brazil, Paraguay, and Argentina. It can also be found in coastal Brazil and northern areas of South America 
 <xref rid="pone.0083619-Sainty1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Currently, 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> has invaded the USA, China, Australia, New Zealand, Indonesia, India, and Thailand 
 <xref rid="pone.0083619-Schooler1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref> and has caused economic and ecological problems in these regions. In China, 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> was first introduced into suburban Shanghai from Japan as a forage crop in the late 1930s. It was then spread intentionally to eastern and southern China between the 1950s and the 1970s, has now invaded large areas south of the Yellow River Basin, and can be found sporadically in northern China. 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> has been listed as one of the 12 most harmful alien, invasive species in China 
 <xref rid="pone.0083619-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. In its native range, 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> has many parasitic natural enemies. These enemies, especially specialists feeding on different organs and tissues of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>, regulate its population 
 <xref rid="pone.0083619-Coulson1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0083619-Sosa1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. In China, more than ten generalist insects feed on 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>
 <xref rid="pone.0083619-Li2" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0083619-Li3" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. However, no literature was found discussing either the preference of these generalist insects for 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> versus native plants or the defense mechanisms of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> and native plants against these generalists.
</p>
