<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In line with previous findings (Ramachandran &amp; Saravanan, 
 <xref rid="fsn32090-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), our results showed that STZ injection markedly induced oxidative stress in liver tissues as we showed a significant increase of MDA levels and a significant decrease in anti‐oxidative markers including total thiol content and SOD and CAT activities. While STZ mainly causes damage to pancreatic tissue, it also has direct toxic effects on other tissues such as the liver and kidney (Ghasemi et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn32090-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Single STZ injection has been reported to induce tissue damage and lipid peroxidation in mouse liver before hyperglycemia induction (Kume et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn32090-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). Furthermore, hyperglycemia generates ROS in the enzymatic and nonenzymatic path, which in turn causes lipid peroxidation and hepatocyte damage (Asmat et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn32090-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Therefore, oxidative damage to the liver tissue could be induced by either the toxic effect of STZ or hyperglycemia or a combination of both or elucidated indirectly by other consequences of hyperglycemia such as tissue inflammation. However, we cannot exclusively determine the liver damages observed in this study arise from STZ direct toxicity, hyperglycemia, or other related factors. Nonetheless, extensive data are showing that high blood glucose induces liver damage in other diabetic models such as genetically modified diabetic animals, as well as in diabetic patients (Cordero‐Herrera et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn32090-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Garcia‐Compean et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn32090-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Mukai et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn32090-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>). Treatment with both fennel (400 mg/kg) and TA and metformin was able to significantly reduce lipid peroxidation compared to the diabetic group and restore the thiol content and CAT activity to normal levels. In line with these results, in STZ‐induced diabetes and chlorpyrifos‐induced liver injury models, treatment with fennel essential oil has been reported to exert anti‐oxidative effects in kidney and liver tissues (El‐Soud et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn32090-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Mansour et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn32090-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). The antioxidant effects of fennel could be attributed to the hypoglycemic or presence of antioxidants, such as vitamins and phenolic compounds (Barros et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn32090-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Furthermore, oxidative stress in diabetic condition also can be triggered in liver by other mechanisms such as hyperglycemia‐induced tissue inflammation. Therefore, the anti‐oxidative effects of fennel could be applied through indirect pathways such as reducing inflammation, which is required more investigation in future studies.
</p>
