<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the present study, we report, for the first time to our knowledge, the neuroprotection of LR extracts against glutamate-induced oxidative stress in HT22 cells and neurotoxicity in 
 <italic>C. elegans</italic>. In this cell line, we induced oxidative stress by using 5 mM glutamate which has been reported to reduce approximately 50% of the cells [
 <xref rid="B19-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Interestingly, we found that only LRE prevented cells from undergoing apoptosis after cotreatment by using Annexin V/PI straining that interacts strongly and specifically with exposed phosphatidylserine (PS), the marker of apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B44-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The protective effect of LRE correlated with increasing MMP, antioxidant gene expressions (CAT, SOD1, SOD2 and GPx) and decreasing intracellular ROS accumulation. Studies on the chemical constituents of LR indicated that bioactive compounds from ethanol extracts performed better than aqueous extractions because the ethanol extract contained high levels of phenolic compounds and phospholipids such as linoleic, oleic and palmitic acid which acted as the antioxidants, whereas aqueous extracts contained a high proportion of polysaccharides, β-glucan and water-soluble components [
 <xref rid="B45-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Some findings reported that aqueous extracts of LR showed antioxidant properties in vitro including DPPH and ABTS scavenging assay and contained phenolic compounds [
 <xref rid="B9-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. However, several findings found that mushroom β-glucan from the aqueous extract is involved in modulating the immune system and in anti-inflammatory, anti-cancer and antiviral activity [
 <xref rid="B49-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Unlike β-glucan in mushrooms, β-glucan in barley showed a higher free radical scavenging property than in oats and yeast [
 <xref rid="B52-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. In addition, β-glucan in oats exert indirect antioxidant effects on immune cells [
 <xref rid="B53-biology-10-00030" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Therefore, it could be possible that glucan in LRC and LRH are unlikely to be the major component that was responsible for protecting HT22 cells from glutamate-induced oxidative stress. Moreover, another possibility was the difference in yields of the extracts in our study. The yield of the LRE was 10 times lower than that of the LRC and LRH despite all extracts being applied at a similar concentration. Thus, the active ingredients in aqueous extracts may be lower than those in ethanolic extracts.
</p>
