<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In summary, antioxidant and 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase inhibitory activities of the extract, fractions, and isolated compounds from mango seed kernel were first documented. The petroleum ether, dichloromethane, ethyl acetate, and 
 <italic>n</italic>-butanol fractions exhibited different degrees of antioxidant and 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase inhibitory activity. In order to further clarify the chemical basis, a total of 23 ingredients were identified by efficient and fast GC-MS analysis from the petroleum ether fraction. As far as we know, it was the first report on the detailed compounds of the petroleum ether fraction of mango seed kernel. Among all the identified components, (
 <italic>Z</italic>)-3-(Heptadec-10-en-1-yl) phenol, eicosane, 9-octadecenoic acid methyl ester, and 9-hexadecenoic acid methyl ester had never been reported before. In addition, 17 compounds were isolated and identified from other active fractions of mango seed kernel. 1, 2, 3, 4, 6-penta-
 <italic>O</italic>-galloyl-
 <italic>α</italic>-D-glucoside (
 <bold>2</bold>), 1-glycerol gallate (
 <bold>9</bold>), gallocatechin (
 <bold>15</bold>), and hexyl-
 <italic>β</italic>-D-glucoside (
 <bold>17</bold>) were isolated from 
 <italic>Mangifera</italic> for the first time. Among isolated components, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6-penta-
 <italic>O</italic>-galloyl-
 <italic>β</italic>-D-glucoside (
 <bold>1</bold>) and 1, 2, 3, 4, 6-penta-
 <italic>O</italic>-galloyl-
 <italic>α</italic>-D-glucoside (
 <bold>2</bold>) showed stronger DPPH radical scavenging and 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase inhibitory capacities than others. The structure-activity relationship has been discussed. According to the kinetic research, 
 <bold>2</bold> inhibited 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase in a competitive manner, whereas 
 <bold>1</bold> acted in a noncompetitive manner. Molecular docking studies showed that compound 
 <bold>1</bold> accommodated well in the allosteric site of the 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase interacting with a number of crucial amino residues. Compound 
 <bold>2</bold> reached deeper the active site pocket of 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase than acarbose. The stability of binding was enhanced by 
 <italic>π</italic>-
 <italic>π</italic> T-shaped, 
 <italic>π</italic>-alkyl, hydrogen bond, and electrostatic interactions. These results might be useful to investigate the pharmacological activity in this fruit. Meanwhile, our study provided a chemical basis for the further development and utilization of mango seed kernel in the food and medicine fields.
</p>
