<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In another study, pigs were allocated into six different dietary treatments during the weaning (21 days post-weaning until 35 kg of live weight) and finishing (up to 105 kg of live weight) periods [
 <xref rid="B24-antioxidants-10-00780" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. More specifically, the control group was fed a high energy diet without grass meal (GM) in both periods, while the other groups were fed as follow: (i) GM105: pigs fed low-energy diets with GM (100 g GM/kg—weaner, 200 g GM/kg—finisher) from weaning to slaughter; (ii) GM50: pigs fed low-energy diets with GM up to 50 kg of live weight and then a high energy diet from 50 kg to slaughter; (iii) GM80: pigs fed concentrate diet with GM up to 80 kg of live weight and a high nutrient dense finisher diet from 80 kg to slaughter; (iv) VitE: pigs fed concentrate diets with GM up to 80 kg of live weight and then a VitE enriched diet (200 mg/kg) with rapeseed oil (50 g/kg) from 80 kg to slaughter; (v) GTC (green tea catechins), pigs fed concentrate diets with GM up to 80 kg of live weight and then a GTC enriched diet (200 mg tea extracts/kg) with rapeseed oil (50 g/kg) from 80 kg to slaughter. Significant effects were reported on some slaughter traits. The kill-out (carcass weight/slaughter weight) was lower in GTC group than the control (by 1.0%), but higher compared to the GM105 group (by 1.1%), whereas no differences were found compared to the other groups. In addition, the GTC fed animals had higher kill-out (by 10.4%) in comparison with the GM105 ones. The pH 24 h post-mortem of GTC carcasses was lower (by 4.9%) than the GM50 one, whereas fat depth in the shoulder and ham was higher in GTC than GM80 group (by 38.0% and 58.3%, respectively). The chemical composition of the 
 <italic>Longissimus dorsi</italic> (LD) muscle was unaffected by dietary treatments. In GTC-fed animals, a greater ash (by 14.8%) and a lower alpha-tocopherol (by 29.0%) content compared with those consuming GM50 and VitE, respectively, were found. Lipid oxidation of LD muscle was not affected at all under anaerobic conditions. However, lower TBARS values on LD muscle of GTC compared with GM105-fed animals (by 76.9%) were found in modified atmosphere packaging (MAP) after 2 days of storage, and compared with GM105 (by 41.2%) and GM50 (by 44.4%) after 4 days of storage. Nevertheless, neither GTC nor VitE was able to delay lipid oxidation of the LD muscle of pigs after 10 days of storage [
 <xref rid="B24-antioxidants-10-00780" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The meat fatty acid profile (saturated fatty acids, SFA; monounsaturated fatty acid, MUFA; polyunsaturated fatty acids, PUFA) of LD meat was not modified by GTC and VitE dietary inclusion [
 <xref rid="B24-antioxidants-10-00780" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Regarding the color, lightness was increased by the dietary inclusion of GTC (on average by 4.7%) but only compared with GM105 and VitE groups and after 2 days of aerobic packaging [
 <xref rid="B24-antioxidants-10-00780" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] (
 <xref rid="antioxidants-10-00780-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).
</p>
