<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It should be highlighted here that great attention is devoted from consumers to the fatty acid composition of meat for its implications in human health. In fact, a reduction in SFA and an increase in PUFA consumption is of great interest; in particular, the n-3 series exerts beneficial effects in atherosclerosis and other diseases [
 <xref rid="B25-antioxidants-10-00780" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. An increase of n-3 PUFA content in pork meat can be achieved by the dietary supplementation with marine lipid sources such as fish oil, which is rich in eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA), or plant lipid sources such as linseed meal/oil, which are rich in α-linolenic acid [
 <xref rid="B26-antioxidants-10-00780" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-antioxidants-10-00780" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Olive leaves (OL, 0.5% and 1% of the diet) when added in linseed oil-enriched diets affected the fatty acid profile of LD muscle in pigs, only compared with a sunflower oil-rich ration [
 <xref rid="B28-antioxidants-10-00780" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The OL supplementation in a linseed oil-enriched diet, compared with a sunflower oil-enriched diet, increased the proportion of SFA (on average by 6.8%), but that increase was not observed when compared with a linseed oil VitE-enriched ration. On the other hand, the proportions of MUFA were decreased in the LD muscle of OL compared with sunflower oil-fed pigs (from 3.2% to 2.4%). A decrease n-6:n-3 ratio (by an average value of 84.5%) was observed in the OL compared with sunflower oil-fed animals. Moreover, effects were observed on the fatty acid composition between OL and VitE groups. Due to the high content of linseed oil in n-3 fatty acid, the authors also investigated its impact on meat lipid peroxidation throughout 9 days of storage. Feeding OL led to a decrease in MDA content in LD muscle, both in comparison with sunflower and linseed oil-fed animals, whereas VitE supplementation was more effective than OL in delaying lipid oxidation. Conversely, protein oxidation was affected neither in raw nor cooked meat of pigs fed with linseed oil. Positive effects were also found in OL and VitE groups regarding sensory meat qualities [
 <xref rid="B28-antioxidants-10-00780" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] (
 <xref rid="antioxidants-10-00780-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).
</p>
