<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this study, a statistically significant variation in the unshelled and shelled seed of different 
 <italic class="italic">P. cembroides</italic> provenances has been observed regarding morphology (
 <xref rid="molecules-24-02057-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Population variability with respect to pine nut morphometry analysis has been reported earlier in some 
 <italic class="italic">P. cembroides</italic> communities. A study of the length, diameter, and weight of seed collected from Cadereyta in the state of Querétaro, Mexico, showed values similar to those found in our study [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-02057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Also, seeds production in the cones of 
 <italic class="italic">P. cembroides</italic> presented variations in the number of seeds per cone, percentage of developed and aborted seeds, and percentage of germination associated with the year of harvest from Santa María Las Cuevas, Altzayanca, Tlaxcala, Mexico [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-24-02057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Our results showed that populations from Hidalgo State had the most prominent pine nut values associated with size and weight, while the population of Chihuahua State had the smallest ones. Some studies have previously indicated that bigger seed could be a desirable characteristic and a good indicator of success of planted forest trees in reforestation programs. Size correlates with increased higher root, shoot ratios, and seedling growth, which could improve the seedling performance by developing and maintaining a deep and extensive root system that can capture water from deep within the soil profile [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-24-02057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-24-02057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. In this context, SMCH and JCZH populations of Hidalgo State can be considered the best source of seeds for a reproduction program in these zones.
</p>
