<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2dot3-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.3. 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus Brasiliensis</span> ATCC 16404
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus brasiliensis</span> is a black mold that can spoil food products, especially fruits and vegetables [
  <a rid="B48-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-materials-10-00045">48</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inhibition rate of the tested essential oils (thyme oil, clove oil, rosemary oil, tea tree oil) against 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus brasiliensis</span> ATCC 16404 is presented in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f007" href="#materials-10-00045-f007">Figure 7</a>. The results presented evidenced that thyme oil was effective against 
  <span class="italic">A. brasiliensis</span> ATCC 16404 at a volume of 5 µL (
  <span class="italic">IR</span> = 97.43%), while clove oil shows antifungal activity at a volume of 30 µL (
  <span class="italic">IR</span> = 82.64%). The strong antifungal activity of thyme oil is attributed to phenolic compounds carvacrol (2.75%) and thymol (43.1%), while the antimicrobial effectiveness of clove oil is associated with the activity of eugenol (85.7%), β-caryophyllene (4.5%), and eugenol acetate (7.9%). Similar studies were conducted by Abbaszadeh et al. [
  <a rid="B46-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-materials-10-00045">46</a>], who tested the antifungal efficiency of thymol, carvacrol, eugenol, and menthol on growth inhibition of some important food-borne pathogens. The results showed that thymol and carvacrol inhibited the fungal growth of 
  <span class="italic">Cladosporium</span> spp., 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus</span> spp., 
  <span class="italic">Fusarium oxysporum</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Botrytis cinerea</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Penicillium</span> spp., 
  <span class="italic">Alternaria alternata</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Rhizopus oryzae</span>, and the inhibition growth was dependent on the concentration used.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil of rosemary showed an inhibition rate of 14.22% for the volume of 60 µL. Jiang et al. [
  <a rid="B37-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-materials-10-00045">37</a>] tested the antimicrobial activity of rosemary essential oil and its main components, α-pinene and 1.8-cineole, against Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria and fungi (
  <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus niger</span>). This study showed that the antimicrobial activity of rosemary essential oil was superior to its active compounds, and the essential oil is more active against all the bacteria used in this research compared to the tested fungi, concluding that the synergism between its compounds determine the antifungal activity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tea tree essential oil inhibited the growth of the tested fungus with an inhibition rate of 88.90% for a volume of 35 µL.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparing antifungal activity results of the studied essential oils, the following decreasing order of activity is evident: thyme oil &gt; clove oil &gt; tea tree oil &gt;&gt; rosemary oil. Concerning the sensitivity to various fungi, the thyme oil and tea tree oil are very effective in the inhibition of the 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus brasiliensis,</span> as is clove oil in the inhibition of the 
  <span class="italic">Penicillium corylophilum.</span> The rosemary oil is less effective as an antifungal agent but shows some activity against 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus brasiliensis.</span> However, other studies have evidenced that high-quality rosemary oil has antitumor, antifungal, and antiparasitic effects [
  <a rid="B49-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-materials-10-00045">49</a>]. It has also analgesic, anticancer, anticatarrhal, anti-infection, anti-inflammatory, and expectorant properties and stimulates the circulatory system [
  <a rid="B50-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-materials-10-00045">50</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
