<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot9-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.9. Determination of the Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) of Bacteria</div>
 <sec id="sec3dot9dot1-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.9.1. Agar MIC Testing</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The preparation of agar, broth, and bacteria were carried out as described in 
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot7-materials-10-00045" href="#sec3dot7-materials-10-00045">Section 3.7</a>. MICs was determined for thyme, clove, and tea tree against 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">E. coli</span> according to the method used by Zhang and Mith [
   <a rid="B53-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-materials-10-00045">53</a>,
   <a rid="B54-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-materials-10-00045">54</a>] with some minor modifications. The original solution of each EO was dissolved in Tween-20 (0.5%), dimethyl sulfoxide (DSMO, 5%), or ethanol (100%) in a 1:1 ratio to make serial 2-fold dilutions, yielding solutions with a gradient from 100% oil to 0.2% oil (
   <span class="italic">v</span>/
   <span class="italic">v</span>). A volume of 10 µL of each oil dilution was added to the 6 mm paper disc and then placed on MH agar plates with a 100 µL bacterial concentration containing a 10
   <span class="sup">4</span>–10
   <span class="sup">5</span> CFU/mL suspension of each tested bacterium. DSMO without bacteria was used as a control.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot9dot2-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.9.2. Broth Microdilution MIC Testing</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similar dilutions in either Tween-20 (0.5%), dimethyl sulfoxide (DSMO, 5%), or ethanol (100%) were transferred to sterile microtiter plates (honeycomb plates with 100 wells). Three parallel dilution series were used with 100 µL in each well. The microtiter plates were mounted in a Bioscreen C (Oy Growth Curves Ab Ltd., Helsinki, Finland), an automated growth curve analysis system, programmed to measure absorbance at 600 nm (abs 600 nm) at regular time intervals at 37 ± 0.1 °C. Prior to each measurement, the plates were shaken for 10 s (default setting). Growth curves of both strains were recorded. Time-to-detection (TTD) were defined as 
   <span class="italic">ABS</span>
   <sub>600nm</sub> = 0.2. Lack of absorbance above 0.2 were defined as growth inhibition.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
