<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In one of the studies, the aerial parts of 
 <italic>Gastrocotyle hispida</italic> were air dried and used for extraction. The extract showed a flavonoid content of 178 mg/g QE. The in vitro assay of extract was performed for evaluation of its anticancer activity against kidney, liver and breast cancer cell lines [
 <xref rid="B39-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Some reports suggest the flavonoid anticancer activity is because it inhibits protein kinases, which are responsible for regulating cellular pathways [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Prenylated chalcone and flavonoids are structurally related and are often considered analogs of each other. Prenylflavonoids were investigated for their potential anticancer activities in vitro [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Recently, four prenylated flavonoids isolated from the fruits of 
 <italic>Sinopodophyllum hexandrum</italic> were tested for their cytotoxicity against the human breast cancer cell line T47D. The isolated compounds were spectroscopically analyzed, and structures were elucidated (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05243-f002">Figure 2</xref>). The percent growth inhibition determined showed an IC
 <sub>50</sub> values to be less than 10 μmol·L
 <sup>−1</sup> [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Apple is rich in many flavonoids which are directly related to improved cardiovascular health [
 <xref rid="B42-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] and reduces the risk of asthma and Alzheimer’s disease [
 <xref rid="B43-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Flavonoids present in apple are reported to reduce the risk of colorectal cancer. Studies have shown that consumption of one apple per day reduces the chance of cancer up to 50% [
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Flavonoids extracted from female hop cones have great pharmaceutical importance including anti-carcinogenic and anti-microbial effects [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].
</p>
