<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <bold class="bold">Antigenotoxic evidence for rosemary and its phytochemicals:</bold> All the previously mentioned facts have motivated the analysis and research of a large number of scientific contributions that provide extensive information on rosemary, beyond its culinary and ornamental uses. In order to confirm its genoprotector potential, Darina Slamenova and her team from the Institute of Cancer in the Slovak Republic, in 2002, started a research focused on the antigenotoxic evaluation (using single cell gel electrophoresis) of an ethanol extract of rosemary (EER) against oxidative DNA damage induced by H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>- and visible light-excited Methylene Blue in colon cancer cells CaCo-2 and hamster lung cells V79. Their findings showed that EER reduced the genotoxic activity of both agents after a long-term (24 h; 0.3 μg/mL) or short-term (2 h; 30 μg/mL) pre-incubation of cells; they suggested that the extract evidences a protective effect against the oxidative damage to DNA because of both OH radicals and singlet oxygen scavenging (
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) [
 <xref rid="B171-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">171</xref>]. Some years later, Aherne et al. [
 <xref rid="B172-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">172</xref>] explored the cytoprotective and genoprotective effects of some aqueous extracts of plants (rosemary (
 <italic class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L.), oregano (
 <italic class="italic">Origanum vulgare</italic> L.), sage (
 <italic class="italic">Salvia officinalis</italic> L.), and echinacea (
 <italic class="italic">Echinacea purpurea</italic> L.)) against the damage induced by H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> in Caco-2 cells. Once the cells were pre-treated with each extract for 24 h and exposed to the H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, the cellular viability by the neutral red uptake assay (NRUA) and DNA damage were assessed by the so-called comet assay. The results indicated that all extracts induced cell injury, with echinacea the least toxic; however, rosemary, sage, and oregano protected against H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-induced DNA damage (olive tail moment and percentage tail DNA were reduced) [
 <xref rid="B172-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">172</xref>].
</p>
