<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The oil sample was analyzed after converting the fatty acids to methyl esters, using the AOAC procedure 965.49 [
 <xref rid="B9-antioxidants-10-00465" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], with some modifications. A fatty oil sample (45–55 mg) was measured into dry flask, and mixed with a methanol-sulfuric acid mixture, the mixture is carefully heated for 2 h under reflux to enable moderate boiling. After the reaction is complete, the balloon is cooled in a mixture of water and ice. The mixture was washed twice with 50 mL of petroleum ether and once again with 20 mL of distilled water. Afterwards, petrol ether fraction was dried by passing through the anhydrous Na
 <sub>2</sub>SO
 <sub>4</sub>. The dried solution is carefully filtered through filter paper to remove the desiccant, transferred to a dry and clean Erlenmeyer flask, and the solvent was evaporated on a vacuum evaporator. The oily residue obtained was weighed, dissolved in methylene chloride, and the samples thus prepared were further analyzed using gas chromatography. The chemical composition of the fatty oil was analyzed using GC and GC/MS technique. GC/MS analyses were performed on a Shimadzu GCMSQP2010 ultra mass spectrometer fitted with a flame ionic detector and coupled with a GC2010 gas chromatograph. The InertCap5 capillary column (60.0 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 µm) was used for separation. Helium (He), at a split ratio of 1:5 and a linear velocity of 35.2 cm/s was used as a carrier gas. The ion source temperature was 200 °C, injector temperature was 250 °C, detector temperature 300 °C, while column temperature was linearly programmed from 40 to 260 °C (at rate of 4 °C/min), from 260 to 310 (at rate 10 °C/min) and after reaching 310 °C, kept isothermally for 10 min. The derivatized samples were dissolved in the methylene chloride a and consecutively injected always in amount of 1 µL. The content of different compounds was determined on the basis of area of chromatograms and defined as content according to the GC area (the mean of three determinations). The identification of the constituents was performed by comparing their mass spectra and retention indices (RIs) with those obtained from authentic samples and/or listed in the NIST/Wiley mass-spectra libraries, using different types of search (PBM/NIST/AMDIS) and available literature data [
 <xref rid="B10-antioxidants-10-00465" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-antioxidants-10-00465" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. 
</p>
