<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Adult tiger beetles were collected through opportunistic sampling from tree trunks, branches, and leaves using entomological hand net from 9 April to 4 August 2019 in the municipality of Masiu, Saguiran, and Marawi City, Lanao del Sur Province, Mindanao, Philippines. A total of 10 sampling sites were established in these areas (Table 
 <xref rid="ece37149-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Some sampling sites were visited several times, while others surveyed once due to time constraints and availability. During every visit in every sampling site, all specimens of every tree species present in particular areas were checked (Table 
 <xref rid="ece37149-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Sampling sites were located in human‐disturbed habitat close to human settlements or even in the villages. In total, over 10 tree and large, tree‐like perennial species have been checked, including three taxa alien and/or invasive for the Philippines (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece37149-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>): 
 <italic>Spathodea campanulata</italic> P. Beauv. (native to Africa, one of the most invasive tree species in the world), 
 <italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L. (native to continental south‐east Asia), and 
 <italic>Acacia mangium</italic> Willd. (native to Australia, Papua, and Moluccas). Moreover seven native taxa, 
 <italic>Erythrina fusca</italic> Lour., 
 <italic>Hibiscus tiliaceus</italic> L., 
 <italic>Artocarpus heterophyllus</italic> Lam., 
 <italic>A. odoratissimus</italic> Blanco, 
 <italic>Cocos nucifera</italic> L., 
 <italic>Musa</italic> spp., and 
 <italic>Bambusa</italic> spp., have been checked as well. According to literature (Elias &amp; Prance, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">1978</xref>; Feinsinger &amp; Swarm, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">1978</xref>; Peng, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Savage et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Seibert, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">1948</xref>; Sugiura et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Zimmermann, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">1932</xref>), all invasive species and first two of the mentioned native taxa can be characterized by presence of extrafloral nectaries.
</p>
