<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Neuropathic pain is known as pain caused by a disease or lesion of the central or peripheral nervous system by features like hyperalgesia and allodynia (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>). Recently, it has been reported that pro-inflammatory cytokines including interleukin-1b (IL-1b) produced by immune cells, microglia, and astroglia, in the spinal cord have important roles in the pathogenesis of neuropathic pain (
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>). These agents can initiate a cascade of neuro-inflammation-related events that might keep up and worsen the original injury that finally leads to pain and chronicity (
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>). Moreover, inflammation induces cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) expression and results in the generation of prostaglandins (PGE) (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>). PGE2 is a pain-inducing factor. It is able to sensitize primary sensory neurons and leads to central sensitization and also facilitate the release of pain-related neuropeptides (
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>). Metalloproteinases (MMPs) are mostly involved in tissue remodeling and inflammation associated with some neurodegenerative disorders (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). These agents have important roles in nociception and hyperalgesia in the chronic phase of neuropathic pain (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>). Studies in these fields demonstrated that hydroalcoholic extract of rosemary (10-50 mg/kg, IP) and carnosol (0.5-2 mg/kg, IP) inhibit formalin-induced pain and inflammation in mice (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>). In a previous study, it was reported that different triterpenes (micromeric, oleanolic, and ursolic acids) in 
 <italic>R. officinalis</italic> revealed anti-inflammatory and antinociceptive properties in experimental models of pain including acetic acid-induced writhing test, formalin test, and a model of arthritic pain in mice. Moreover, each of the mentioned triterpenes revealed a similar capability to that observed with ketorolac (10 mg/kg, IP), a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory medicine and a typical clinic analgesic (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>). González-Trujano and colleagues, 2007, studied the antinociceptive effect of ethanol extract of rosemary aerial parts. They compared the antinociceptive property of this herb with either tramadol (3.16-50 mg/kg, IP in mice, and 1.0-31.62 mg/kg, IP in rats) or acetylsalicylic acid (31.62-562.32 mg/kg, PO). The achieved data indicate that aerial parts of rosemary have antinociceptive and anti-inflammatory properties, and consolidate the use of it in folk medicine (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). In this regard, Ghasemzadeh 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 2016, conducted a research to investigate the potential anti-inflammatory properties of ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>R. officinalis</italic> (100, 200, and 400 mg/kg, IP) and rosmarinic acid (10, 20, and 40 mg/kg, IP) in a rat model of sciatic nerve chronic constriction injury (CCI)-induced neuropathic pain. In this study, the effects of 14 days, intraperitoneal prescription of ethanolic extract of rosemary and rosmarinic acid on the lumbar spinal cord expression of oxidative stress and inflammatory markers including PGE-2, IL-1b, COX2, NO, and MMP2 were assessed (
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>). Histological analysis of the sciatic nerve revealed that terpenoid-enriched rosemary extract prevented axon and myelin derangement, edema, and inflammatory infiltrate (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>). The obtained data reinforced the traditional use of rosemary as an effective treatment for inflammatory disorders and pain relief. These data also suggest that the ethanolic extract of rosemary and rosmarinic acid might be potential candidates in treating neurological disorders accompanied by inflammation and neuropathic pain by modulating neuro-inflammation. According to the data, it could be suggested that the extract and rosmarinic acid might have an important role against oxidative and inflammatory markers including IL-1b, PGE-2, NO, COX-2, and MMP2.
</p>
