<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the extrapyramidal system of the brain, dopamine is a precursor to norepinephrine and epinephrine and it has an important role in behavior regulation (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). So, regulating the amount of dopamine and dopaminergic pathways is an important goal in controlling depression. It was also revealed that ursolic acid, a pentacyclic triterpenoid derived from rosemary could reduce the immobility time both in tail suspension test and forced swimming test in mice. Pretreatment with SCH23390 (0.05 mg/kg, SC, a dopamine D(1) receptor antagonist) and sulpiride (50 mg/kg, IP, a dopamine D(2) receptor antagonist) prevented the ursolic acid effects (0.001–10 mg/kg, PO) in the tail suspension test. Moreover, administrating the sub-effective dose of ursolic acid in addition to the sub-effective doses of SKF38393 (0.1 mg/kg, SC, a dopamine D(1) receptor agonist), apomorphine (0.5 μg/kg, IP, a preferential dopamine D(2) receptor agonist) or bupropion (1 mg/kg, IP, a dual dopamine/ noradrenaline reuptake inhibitor) decreased the immobility time in the tail suspension test compared with each of the drugs alone. These results show that the antidepressant effect of ursolic acid in the tail suspension test could be because of an interaction with the dopaminergic pathway and through activation of dopamine D
 <sub>1</sub> and D
 <sub>2</sub> receptors (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). This team also assessed the antidepressant-like property of different fractions of rosemary including, hexane (0.1-10 mg/kg, PO), ethanolic, ethyl acetate 1 and 2, and essential oil-free (0.1-100 mg/kg, PO), and some isolated compounds such as betulinic acid (10 mg/kg, PO), and carnosol (0.01-0.1 mg/kg, PO) in the tail suspension, a predictive test to investigate the antidepressant activity, in mice. Results showed that all of the fractions and prescribed constituents produced a significant antidepressant-like effect (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). This finding could be further evaluated by molecular and biochemical tests to determine the exact mechanisms involved in their antidepressant like properties.
</p>
