<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The analyses described in this report were performed on samples collected during a previously reported companion study [
 <xref rid="B13-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>], which was conducted at the South Dakota State University (SDSU) Animal Research Wing (ARW; Brookings, SD), with all procedures approved by the SDSU Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee before the start of the trial. For the purpose of the microbiome study presented in this report, rumen fluid was sampled from a subset of 10 of the animals fed milk replacer supplemented with EO (3.75g/feeding, mixed with the milk replacer), and from 10 of the animals fed milk replacer without supplementation. The commercial supplement, manufactured by Ralco, Inc. (Stay Strong for Dairy Calves; Marshall, MN), was a blend of EO (carvacrol, caryophyllene, p-cymene, cineole, terpinene, and thymol) that also included arabinogalactans, a type of hemicellulose known to enhance immune function [
 <xref rid="B14-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. All calves were housed individually, fed milk replacer (24%:20% crude protein:fat; as-fed basis), and had ad libitum access to water and pelleted calf starter during the trial (see 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-microorganisms-07-00120" class="xref">Supplementary Table S1</xref> for calf starter ingredient composition). Calves were fed colostrum for the first two days after birth. Milk replacer (with or without EO supplementation, according to treatment group) was then offered by bucket feeding twice every day from d3 until d35, then reduced to once every day starting at d36 to facilitate weaning at d42. From week 1 until week 6, calf starter intake increased from approximately 2% of total dry matter intake (DMI) to approximately 70%; the average daily DMI in the week prior to sampling was 1.38 kg/d for control calves and 1.45 kg/d for EO-fed calves (
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> &gt; 0.05) [
 <xref rid="B13-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. The amount of EO supplemented per feeding remained constant during the trial, and it was not adjusted as a function of calf growth or increased DMI. Rumen samples were collected one day after weaning (day 43) from each animal by stomach tubing, with rinsing of the sampling equipment with warm water between each collection. Separate samples (50 mL/sample) were collected for microbiome and SCFA analysis, with the latter supplemented with 25% metaphosphoric acid (W/V) at a ratio of 4:1 before freezing. All samples were stored at –20 °C until analyzed.
</p>
