<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Dose Response</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Dose Response</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DOS</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Dose-Response</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1559-3258</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7493261</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1559325820959563</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1559325820959563</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Therapeutic Response of <italic>Epimedium gandiflorum&#x02019;s</italic> Different Doses to Restore the Antioxidant Potential and Reproductive Hormones in Male Albino Rats</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0380-1332</contrib-id><name><surname>Munir</surname><given-names>Naveed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1559325820959563">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1559325820959563"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>Zahed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1559325820959563">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yameen</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1559325820959563">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>Ghulam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1559325820959563">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-1559325820959563">
<label>1</label>Department of Biochemistry, Government College University Faisalabad, Punjab, Pakistan</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-1559325820959563">Naveed Munir, Department of Biochemistry, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="Ringgold">72594</institution-id><institution content-type="university">Government College University Faisalabad</institution></institution-wrap>, Faisalabad, Punjab 34000, Pakistan. Email: <email>naveedmunir215@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jul-Sep</season><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>1559325820959563</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Current study was planned to explore the therapeutic response of different doses of hydroethanolic extract of <italic>Epimedium grandiflorum</italic> leaves in male albino rats. Phytochemical analysis, HPLC and FTIR spectroscopy results revealed the presence of wide range of phenolic compounds and functional groups, respectively. Further, extract not induced significant hemolysis (7.56 &#x000b1; 1.297%) against PBS (3.65 &#x000b1; 0.35%) as negative control; while have significant clot lysis (44 &#x000b1; 5.2%) potential, exhibited DPPH (78.87 &#x000b1; 5.427%) scavenging, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (31.82 &#x000b1; 3.491%) scavenging, antioxidant and reducing power activities. <italic>In vivo</italic> experimentation in albino male rats&#x02019; revealed that administration of different doses (50, 100, 200 mg/Kg b.w.) of extract orally for 42 days after CCl<sub>4</sub> intoxication significantly (P &#x0003c; 0.05) restore the selected parameters including liver enzymes, renal profiles, and stress markers and significantly (P &#x0003c; 0.05) increased reproductive hormones like testosterone, luteinizing hormone, follicle stimulating hormone and prolactin while significantly (P &#x0003c; 0.05) decreased progesterone and estradiol toward normal in dose dependent manner. Significant (P &#x0003c; 0.05) improvement in the structural architecture of testicular tissue particularly in high dose group (200 mg/Kg b.w.) was also observed. Results revealed <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> has significant therapeutic response to address the healthcare problems particularly of impotency.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>phytoconstituents</kwd><kwd>doses</kwd><kwd>therapeutic response</kwd><kwd>antioxidant potential</kwd><kwd>reproduction</kwd><kwd>diseases</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>July-September 2020</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts3</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-1559325820959563"><title>Introduction</title><p>
<italic>Epimedium</italic> belongs to Berberidaceae family containing about 52 species, with multiple common names like Horny Goat Weed, Rowdy Lamb Herb, Xianlinpi, Bishop&#x02019;s Hat, Fairy Wings, Barrenwort, and Yangheye or Yin Yang Huo.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>
<italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> and <italic>Epimedium sagittatum</italic> are the most important <italic>Epimedium</italic> species used to enhance sexual performance. Due to aphrodisiac properties induction in Chinese goat, <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> is commonly known as horny goat weed. Icariin, a flavonol glycoside as active ingredient of this plant induce the nitric oxide (NO) synthesis in penis,<sup><xref rid="bibr2-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> cavernosal smooth muscle where NO acts as inhibitor of cGMP-specific phosphodiesterase type 5 (PDE5),<sup><xref rid="bibr3-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> and boost the proliferation of smooth muscle, and reduce the formation of advanced glycation end product<sup><xref rid="bibr4-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> and caricaturist endogenous androgens.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> These beneficial effects of <italic>Epimedium</italic> species are due to the presence of various phytochemical constituents; and about over 260 including alkaloids, flavonoids, proteins, glycosides, bioactive peptides, waxes, amino acids, phyto-hormones are responsible for beneficiary activities, have been isolated. The active compounds of <italic>Epimedium</italic> possess a wide range of pharmacological actions including the regulation of hormones, strengthening yang, to cure osteoporosis, boosting immunological function, hepatoprotective, anti-cancer, anti-oxidation, anti-lipidemic, anti-aging, and anti-depressant activities. Further, various <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> studies have been done to screen the pharmacological activities due to effective monomeric compounds or active parts present in <italic>Epimedium</italic>.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>
</p><p>Infertility can also be referred as biological failure of an individual to contribute to conception which might be due to male or female. It is becoming one of the major problems of our society and about 13-18% married couples&#x02019; i.e 1 in 6 couples are affected by infertility.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> It was reported by WHO that infertility in worldwide affects about 60-80 million couples at reproductive age.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Both in male and female dysregulation of reproductive hormones or anatomical anomalies might be the major causes of infertility.<sup><xref rid="bibr8-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Hypothalamus-pituitary-gonadal axis and various factors like behavioral, environmental, genotoxic and genetic factors compromise the spermatogenesis in male.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Phytotherapeutic approaches to treat infertility motivated to explore numerous plants and polyherbal preparations because modern drugs development is expensive and time consuming with many side effects. So in developing countries, traditional medicine plays major role in healthcare community<sup><xref rid="bibr10-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> and different selected parts like fruits, seeds, leaves, roots, etc or their extract powders are used to treat various diseases of humans, animals and plants.<sup><xref rid="bibr11-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> In addition medicinal plants used as traditional medicine are easily consumable, easily available and cheaper with simple preparation strategies to mediate beneficial effects.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bibr13-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Moreover, it was reported that 80% population worldwide and more than 30% of pharmaceutical formulations are dependent upon medicinal plants, reported by WHO.<sup><xref rid="bibr14-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> The current study was planned with the main objectives to determine the phytochemical constituents of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> leaves aqueous hydroethanolic extract, therapeutic response by determining the antioxidant parameters and reproductive hormones as well as structure of testicular tissue in CCl<sub>4</sub> intoxicated male albino rats.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="section2-1559325820959563"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="section3-1559325820959563"><title>Selection and Collection of Plant Material</title><p>
<italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> leaves were purchased from local market of Faisalabad-Pakistan and were taxonomically identified and confirmed from Department of Botany, Government College University, Faisalabad-Pakistan. It was well reported that ethanol and methanol act as effective solvents for the extraction of antioxidant phenolic compounds.<sup><xref rid="bibr15-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> So aqueous Ethanolic (30:70) plant extract was prepared and dry leaves were sonicated twice with 10 time&#x02019;s higher volume of hydro alcohol for 48 hours at room temperature. Then the solution was filtered by Whatman filter paper number 1 and evaporated using rotary evaporator under reduced pressure.</p></sec><sec id="section4-1559325820959563"><title>Phytochemical Analysis</title><sec id="section5-1559325820959563"><title>Qualitative analysis</title><p>Various phytochemicals including alkaloids, flavonoids, tannins, saponins, glycosides, steroids and triterpenoids were investigated in the hydroethanolic <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> extract by standard methods.<sup><xref rid="bibr16-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">16</xref><xref rid="bibr17-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr18-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr19-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="section6-1559325820959563"><title>Quantitative Estimation of Phytochemicals</title><sec id="section7-1559325820959563"><title>Total phenolic contents (TPC) and Total flavonoids contents (TFC)</title><p>Folin-Ciocalteu method was used to quantify the TPC present in hydroethanolic extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> according the procedure described by Jain et al., and gallic acid as standard was used.<sup><xref rid="bibr16-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> The contents of total phenolics in plant extract were quantified as milligram (mg) gallic acid equilant (GAE) per milliliter (mL) of plant hydroethanolic extract. While TFC was measured using the method explained by Pranuthi et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> Catechin as standard was used and TFC represented as &#x000b5;g CE/g (microgram Catechin per gram) of dried plants material.</p></sec><sec id="section8-1559325820959563"><title>High performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) analysis</title><p>HPLC was used to determine the phenolic compounds following the method with some modifications described by Xie et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr20-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> C<sub>18</sub> column (250 &#x000d7; 4.6 mm internal diameter), having 5 &#x000b5;m film thickness, accompanying an oven set at 30&#x000b0;C was used in Liquid chromatography. Chromera HPLC system (Perkin Elmer, USA.) attached with Flexer Binary LC pump, UV/Vis LC Detector (Shelton CT, 06484 USA) controlled by software V. 4.2. 6410 used to analyze the data. Two solutions including solvent A consisted of acetonitrile: methanol (70:30) and solvent B composed of double distilled water with 0.5% glacial acetic acid were used as the mobile phase. UV spectra were recorded at 275 nm. Different phytocompounds were identified using 275 nm wavelength by comparing the retention times and spiking samples with standards.</p></sec><sec id="section9-1559325820959563"><title>Fourier-transform infrared (FTIR) spectroscopy</title><p>
<italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> extract was milled with potassium bromide (KBr) powder and pellets were prepared by pressing. After making the pellets FTIR spectrometer (Model Bruker Platinum ATR with accessories A225/Q Platinum ATR Multiple Crystals CRY diamond and having Interferogram Size of 10550 points) in the frequency range of 400-4,000/cm was used to analyze for the identification of functional groups as representative of wide range of important phytoconstituents.</p></sec></sec><sec id="section10-1559325820959563"><title>Antioxidant Profiling</title><sec id="section11-1559325820959563"><title>Total antioxidant capacity (TAC) by phosphomolybdenum method</title><p>Phosphomolybdenum method to determine the total antioxidant capacity (TAC) of the hydroethanolic extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> was used, following the procedure described by Prieto et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr21-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Different concentrations of ascorbic acid were mixed in absolute methanol to make standard solutions (1000, 500, 250, 125, 62.5 and 31.25 &#x003bc;g/mL). The total antioxidant activity is expressed as the number of gram equivalent of ascorbic acid.</p></sec><sec id="section12-1559325820959563"><title>DPPH radical scavenging potential</title><p>To evaluate the antioxidants potential of plant extract the 2, 2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical scavenging assay was used as described by Shahid et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr22-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> The percent DPPH inhibition was calculated using the following formula</p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1559325820959563"><alternatives><mml:math id="mml-disp1-1559325820959563"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>DPPH inhibition</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext></mml:mfenced><mml:mtext>=</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>- A</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/A</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>0</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mtext>&#x000d7; 100</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-eq1.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></alternatives></disp-formula><p>Where A<sub>S</sub> = Absorbance of Sample, A<sub>0</sub> = Absorbance of Blank.</p></sec><sec id="section13-1559325820959563"><title>Measurement of reducing power by FRAP method</title><p>Fe3+ (CN)6 reduction into Fe2+ (CN)6 was used to measure the reducing potential of hydroethanolic extract according to Yadav et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr23-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> The absorbance at 700 nm wavelength represented the reductive potential of sample.</p></sec><sec id="section14-1559325820959563"><title>Hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) scavenging capacity</title><p>The H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> scavenging capacity of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> hydroethanolic extract was measured following the protocol described by Ruch et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr24-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Ascorbic acid used as standard and % age H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> scavenging activities were calculated as</p><disp-formula id="disp-formula2-1559325820959563"><alternatives><mml:math id="mml-disp2-1559325820959563"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>% Scavenged</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mtext>=</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>- A</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>/A</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mtext>&#x000d7; 100</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-eq2.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></alternatives></disp-formula><p>Where A<sub>C</sub> = absorbance of the control, A<sub>S</sub>= absorbance in the presence of the sample of extract or standards.</p></sec></sec><sec id="section15-1559325820959563"><title>Hemolytic Assay to Determine Cytotoxic Potential of Plants Extract</title><p>
<italic>In vitro</italic> the cytotoxic potential of hydroethanolic plant extract, 10 mg/mL was dissolved in 20% DMSO (Dimethyl sulfoxide), was determined through hemolytic assay performed by spectrophotometric method against Human erythrocytes.Triton-x-100 as positive control and phosphate buffer saline (PBS) as negative control were used.<sup><xref rid="bibr25-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>-
<xref rid="bibr26-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> % age hemolysis was calculated as:</p><disp-formula id="disp-formula3-1559325820959563"><alternatives><mml:math id="mml-disp3-1559325820959563"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>% Hemolysis =</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>- A</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mtext>/</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>- A</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mtext>&#x000d7; 100</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-eq3.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></alternatives></disp-formula><p>Here: A<sub>t</sub> = Test sample absorbance, A<sub>n</sub> = Saline control absorbance, A<sub>c</sub> = The DMSO control absorbance.</p></sec><sec id="section16-1559325820959563"><title>Clot Lysis Assay to Determine Thrombolytic Activity of Plant Extract</title><p>Clot lysis method was used to evaluate the <italic>in vitro</italic> thrombolytic potential of hydroethanolic extract following the procedure of Rahman et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr27-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> Streptokinase and PBS were used as positive and negative controls, respectively. The % age clot lysis activity was calculated as:</p><p>Clot lysis (%) = (clot weight before lysis &#x02212; clot weight after lysis) / clot weight before lysis &#x000d7; 100</p></sec><sec id="section17-1559325820959563"><title>
<italic>In Vivo</italic> Experimentation</title><sec id="section18-1559325820959563"><title>Animal grouping and different dosage plan</title><p>The male albino rats weighing about 160 gram to 190 gram of 8-10 weeks of age were used as animal model for <italic>in vivo</italic> experimentation and all the animals (n = 35) were divided into different groups with 5 animals (n = 5) in each group as follow Group 1 (GM-1): Healthy Control (Normal diet and water administered only); Group 2 (GMT-2): Intoxicated control (20% CCl<sub>4</sub> 0.5 mL/Kg body weight (b.w) intraperitoneally (i.p.) twice a week); Group 3A (GMT-3A): Positive control (20% CCl4 0.5 mL/ Kg b.w i.p. twice a week and Injected Testosterone enanthate 2.5 mg/Kg b.w intra muscular (i.m) twice a week); Group 3B (GMT-3B): Positive control (20% CCl4 0.5 mL/ Kg b.w i.p. twice a week and given Laboob-e-Kabeer (Polyherbal preparation) 200mg/kg orally twice a week); Group 4A (GMT-4A): 20% CCl4 0.5 mL/ Kg b.w i.p. twice a week and hydroethanolic plant extract (50mg/Kg b.w. as low dose) orally daily; Group 4B (GMT-4B): 20% CCl4 0.5 mL/ Kg b.w i.p. twice a week and hydroethanolic plant extract (100mg/Kg b.w. as intermediate dose) orally daily; and Group 4C (GMT-4C): 20% CCl4 0.5 mL/ Kg b.w i.p. twice a week and hydroethanolic plant extract (200mg/Kg b.w. as high dose) orally daily. All experimental animal groups were kept at normal diet and 12 hours light/dark cycle with normal husbandry environment for 6 weeks in the animal house, Department of Physiology, Government College University, Faisalabad-Pakistan after institutional ethical review committee.</p></sec></sec><sec id="section19-1559325820959563"><title>Cytotoxic Studies</title><p>To evaluate the toxicity of hydroetaholic extract in rats&#x02019; cytotoxic studies were carried out by increasing the dose from 500 mg/kg b.w. to 750 mg/kg b.w. to 1000 mg/kg b.w. It was reported that at the dose of 1000 mg/kg toxic clinical features appeared in 12 hours of drug administration. Therefore, highest dose was selected as less than one fourth (200mg/kg b.w.) of toxic level drug to run the trial.</p><sec id="section20-1559325820959563"><title>Change in body weight and collection of blood samples</title><p>At the final day of experiment to determine the therapeutic response of plant extract, rats of each group were weighed to evaluate the change in body weight. Gain in body weight (grams) was evaluated by subtracting the pre-clinical trial body weight from post-clinical trial body weight of each group. For the determination of selected antioxidant and biochemical parameters heart puncture technique after 42 days was performed to collect blood samples. Serum from non-anti-coagulated blood was separated after centrifugation and frozen at -20 &#x000b0;C until analysis.</p></sec><sec id="section21-1559325820959563"><title>Stress markers and biochemical parameters estimation</title><p>Serum stress markers including total antioxidant status (TAS), total oxidant status (TOS), Malondialdehyde (MDA) by Sahreen et al<sup><xref rid="bibr28-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>; Superoxide dismutase (SOD) by Kakkar et al,<sup><xref rid="bibr29-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> and Catalase (CAT) by Chance and Maehly<sup><xref rid="bibr30-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> were determined. To evaluate the safety concerns of hydroethanolic plant extract liver enzymes like transaminases (ALT and AST) by Bergmeyer et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr31-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) and alkaline phosphatase (ALP) were determined colorimetrically as described by Thomas,<sup><xref rid="bibr32-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> total protein, albumin, globulin by Koller et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr33-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> and renal profile including urea by Burtis and Ashwood,<sup><xref rid="bibr34-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> creatinine and uric acid by Swanson et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr35-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> were determined using automated photometric methods. The reproductive hormones including testosterone by Chen et al., (1991),<sup><xref rid="bibr36-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> Luteinizing hormone (LH) by Frank et al., (1996),<sup><xref rid="bibr37-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> Follicle Stimulating hormone (FSH) by Qiu et al., (1998),<sup><xref rid="bibr38-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> Prolactin by Vanderpump et al., (1998),<sup><xref rid="bibr39-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> progesterone by Radwanska et al., (1978)<sup><xref rid="bibr40-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> and estradiol by Tsang et al., (1980)<sup><xref rid="bibr41-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> were measured using standard Enzyme Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) based kit method.</p></sec><sec id="section22-1559325820959563"><title>Histological examination of testicular tissue</title><p>Tissue samples were collected in buffered formalin (neutral) container after dissecting the animals for histological examination. After the fixation sections were taken in labeled tissue cassettes and processed to embed in paraffin wax adopting the protocol described by Bancroft and Gamble.<sup><xref rid="bibr42-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> After embedding the tissue in paraffin wax, microtomy was performed to take thin sections and after deparaffinization, sections were stained using Hematoxylin and Eosin (H &#x00026; E) stain according to the standard procedure of Bancroft and Gamble,<sup><xref rid="bibr42-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> and observed under microscope.</p></sec></sec><sec id="section23-1559325820959563"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The obtained results were represented as Mean &#x000b1; SEM and further interpreted through applying 1 way ANOVA test and to determine the difference between groups pairwise study was determined by Tukey&#x02019;s test using Minitab 17 statistical software (trial version).<sup><xref rid="bibr43-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup>
</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section24-1559325820959563"><title>Results</title><sec id="section25-1559325820959563"><title>Phytochemical Constituents and Antioxidant Potential</title><p>Results of qualitative analysis explored different phytochemical constituents like alkaloids, flavonoids, tannins, saponins, glycosides, steroids and triterpenoids in the hydroethanolic extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> leaves extract (<xref rid="table1-1559325820959563" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The results of quantitative analysis revealed the total flavonoid (241.8 &#x000b1; 11.18 &#x000b5;g CE/g dry plants material) and phenolic contents (1010.72 &#x000b1; 12.49 mg GAE/g dry plants material) in current study and the mean &#x000b1; SE (Standard error of mean) are given in <xref rid="table2-1559325820959563" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Free radical scavenging potentials determinations are very important parameters to evaluate the antioxidant capacity of medicinal plants. Ferric Reducing Antioxidant Power (FRAP) Assay, Phosphomolybdenum, DPPH (1,1-diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl) and hydrogen peroxide scavenging assays were used to evaluate the antioxidant potential of hydroethanolic plant extract and the results represented in <xref rid="table2-1559325820959563" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1559325820959563">Figure 1A and B</xref>. The results revealed significant (p &#x0003c; 0.05) increase in radical scavenging and reducing activity directly correlated with the plant extracts concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1559325820959563">Figure 1A and B</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="table1-1559325820959563" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Qualitative Phytochemical Screening of Ethanolic Extract of E. grandiflorum.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-table1"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plants/phytochemicals</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Epimedium grandiflorum</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkaloids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavonoids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tannins</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saponins</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycosides</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Steroids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triterpenoids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-1559325820959563"><p>(+) indicates the presence of phytoconstituents, (-) indicates no phytoconstituents present</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table2-1559325820959563" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Total Phenolic, Total Flavonoid Contents, and Antioxidant Activities of Ethanolic Extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> (Mean &#x000b1; SEM).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-table2"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plants/phytochemicals</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Epimedium grandiflorum</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPC (mg GAE/g dry plants material)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1010.72 &#x000b1; 12.49</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TFC (&#x000b5;g CE/g dry plants material)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">241.8 &#x000b1; 11.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPPH Scavenging activity (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.87 &#x000b1; 5.427</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> Scavenging activity (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.82 &#x000b1; 3.491</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><fig id="fig1-1559325820959563" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>(A) Reducing potential of hydroethanolic extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> using different concentrations by FRAP method, (B) Total antioxidant capacity of hydroethanolic extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> by Phosphomolybdate assay (C) Thrombolytic activity of hydroethanolic extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> measured against streptokinase as positive control and Phosphate buffer saline (PBS) as negative control (D) Hemolytic activity of hydroethanolic extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> measured against Triton-X as positive control and PBS as negative control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-fig1"/></fig></sec><sec id="section26-1559325820959563"><title>HPLC and FTIR Spectroscopy</title><p>In the present study, HPLC-UV was used to analyze the hydroethanolic extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> leaves qualitatively. The results revealed the presence of different phenolic compounds might be responsible for strong antioxidant potential of <italic>E. genadiflorum</italic> includes Gallic Acid (Rt = 2.808), Catechin (Rt = 3.257), Chlorogenic acid (Rt = 5.366), HB acid (Rt = 6.893), Caffeic acid (Rt = 7.969), Sinapic acid (Rt = 12.954) and Ferulic acid (Rt = 13.416). The results of HPLC also revealed some peaks with different retention time could not be identified; however, based on their chromatographic behaviors and UV spectra, they may correspond to unknown flavonoids compounds as presented in respective chromatogram (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1559325820959563">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig id="fig2-1559325820959563" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Chromatogram of hydroethanolic extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> obtained from HPLC analysis representing the presence of different phenolic molecules.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-fig2"/></fig><p>According to infrared spectroscopy in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1559325820959563">Figure 3</xref>, there were absorption peaks at 3,500-4,000/cm, 2,918/cm, 2,360/cm, 2,341/cm, 1,726/cm, 1,586/cm, 1,494/cm, 1,462/cm, 1,426/cm, 1,428/cm, 1,296/cm, 1,259/cm, 1,179/cm, 1,120/cm, 1,023/cm, 836/cm, 726/cm, 694/cm, 563/cm and 439/cm. The absorption peaks at range 3,500 to 4,000/cm was associated with the stretching vibration of O-H, which meant that there were hydrogen bonds in intramolecules and intermolecules. The absorption peak at 2,918/cm was attributed to the asymmetrically stretching vibration of C-H. The peak at 2,360/cm and 2,341/cm might be related to stretching vibration of C-H. The absorption peak at 1,726/cm was attributed to the symmetrically stretching vibration of C=O. The absorption peaks at 1,586/cm might be related to the stretching vibration of C=N and C=C. The peaks at 1400 to 1500/cm (1,494/cm, 1,462/cm, 1,426/cm and 1,428/cm) might be attributed with strong to medium vibration of C=C and N=O functional groups. The absorption peaks at 1,296/cm and 1,259 was due to the stretching vibration of C-O. The peaks at 1,179/cm and 1,120/cm were attributed to the asymmetrically stretching vibration of C-O-C. The absorbance peak at 563/cm might be represented of aliphatic C-I stretching while the peak at 439/cm might be related to S-S stretching vibration.</p><fig id="fig3-1559325820959563" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Infrared spectra of the hydroethanolic extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> leaves revealing the presence of wide range of functional groups.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-fig3"/></fig></sec><sec id="section27-1559325820959563"><title>Hemolytic and Thrombolytic Activities</title><p>Results of hemolytic assay revealed that the %age (percentage) hemolysis of plant extract is significantly negligible as compare to positive control (Triton-X) shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1559325820959563">Figure 1C</xref>. To evaluate the blood and semen thinning effect of hydroethanolic extract clot lysis activity was measured using human clotted blood. Results revealed that Streptokinase (SK; 100 &#x000b5;L) incubation with clot for 90 min at 37&#x000ba;C dissolve the 73.6 &#x000b1; 7.7% clot while on the other hand only 3.65 &#x000b1; 0.35% clot lysis was observed in clots treated with phosphate buffer saline (PBS) and significant (p &#x0003c; 0.001) thrombolytic activity of hydroethanolic extract of plant (44 &#x000b1; 5.2%) was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1559325820959563">Figure 1D</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="section28-1559325820959563"><title>
<italic>In Vivo</italic> Hydroethanolic Extract&#x02019; Therapeutic Response</title><sec id="section29-1559325820959563"><title>Hepatoprotective and renoprotective activities of E. grandiflorum extract</title><p>Evaluation of drugs toxicity is one of the major concerns in drug development<sup><xref rid="bibr44-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> because most of the herbal preparations have a wide range of health benefits so hepatoprotective and renoprotective aspects were also evaluated. The statistical analysis revealed that there was a significant (P &#x0003c; 0.01) increased in total bilirubin and liver enzymes on intoxication with CCl<sub>4</sub> while serum proteins significantly (P &#x0003c; 0.05) decreased. On the other hands, Significant (P &#x0003c; 0.05) improvement was reported after administration of different doses of hydroethanolic extract of plant and this improvement in liver enzymes and proteins was in dose dependent manner. Although, the concentration of globulin also increases with increased in concentration of extract amount but a significant (P &#x0003c; 0.05) difference was reported on administration of 200 mg per Kg bw extract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1559325820959563">Figures 4A-C</xref>). The intoxication with CCl<sub>4</sub> administration significantly (P &#x0003c; 0.05) affects the kidney function evaluated by measuring blood urea, creatinine and uric acid level as compared to normal animal group while administration of hydroethanolic extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> significantly (P &#x0003c; 0.05) restore these renal parameters on dose dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1559325820959563">Figure 4D</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4-1559325820959563" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>(A) Concentration of Serum Total Bilirubin (B) Activities of liver enzymes including alanine transaminase (ALT), aspartate transaminase (AST), alkaline phosphatase (ALKP) and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) (C) Concentration of serum proteins like Total proteins, albumin and globulin and (D) Concentration of blood urea, creatinine and uric acid in the blood samples collected from different experimental groups at the end of trial. Values are Mean &#x000b1; SEM (standard error of Mean) of the study groups. Colum share the same alphabets indicate non-significant (P &#x0003e; 0.05) differences.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-fig4"/></fig></sec><sec id="section30-1559325820959563"><title>Total oxidant (TOS), antioxidant status (TAS) and stress markers in rats&#x02019; blood</title><p>It was noted that induction of CCl<sub>4</sub> significantly (P &#x0003c; 0.01) decreased the TAS and increased the TOS in rats while the administration of plant extracts orally on daily basis revert significantly (P &#x0003c; 0.01) TAS and TOS (<xref rid="table3-1559325820959563" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The results revealed a significant (P &#x0003c; 0.05) high MDA level in CCl<sub>4</sub> intoxicated rats as compare to other studied animals. MDA level returned to near normal after administration of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> extract in rats (<xref rid="table3-1559325820959563" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Moreover, SOD (Superoxide dismutase) and CAT (Catalase) as enzymatic antioxidant and decreased in both enzymes activities was also noted on intoxication with CCl4 while in plants extract and positive drugs treated rats, both SOD and CAT significantly (P &#x0003c; 0.05) improves in dose dependent manner (<xref rid="table3-1559325820959563" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="table3-1559325820959563" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Effect of Selected Ethanolic <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> Extract and Control Drugs on Stress Markers in Male Albino Rats.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-table3"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GM-1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMT-2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMT-3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMT-4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMT-5A</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMT-5B</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMT-5C</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.823 &#x000b1; 0.051<sup>CD</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.504 &#x000b1; 0.038<sup>F</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.718 &#x000b1; 0.051<sup>E</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.737 &#x000b1; 0.044<sup>DE</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.906 &#x000b1; 0.026<sup>C</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.473 &#x000b1; 0.073<sup>B</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.402 &#x000b1; 0.037<sup>A</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.758 &#x000b1; 2.055<sup>BC</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.748 &#x000b1; 2.317<sup>A</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.672 &#x000b1; 2.320<sup>A</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.940 &#x000b1; 2.336<sup>A</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.544 &#x000b1; 1.547<sup>B</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.905 &#x000b1; 1.132<sup>BC</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.089 &#x000b1; 1.278<sup>C</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.51 &#x000b1; 1.55<sup>C</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.28 &#x000b1; 1.54<sup>A</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.75 &#x000b1; 1.27<sup>AB</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.08 &#x000b1; 1.17<sup>B</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.33 &#x000b1; 1.10<sup>C</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.77 &#x000b1; 0.85<sup>CD</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.13 &#x000b1; 1.31<sup>D</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.85 &#x000b1; 2.74<sup>CD</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.92 &#x000b1; 1.95<sup>E</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.86 &#x000b1; 2.58<sup>D</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.20 &#x000b1; 2.69<sup>CD</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.53 &#x000b1; 2.00<sup>C</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.65 &#x000b1; 2.37<sup>B</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.68 &#x000b1; 3.06<sup>A</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.74 &#x000b1; 2.07<sup>CD</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.62 &#x000b1; 1.59<sup>E</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.32 &#x000b1; 1.60<sup>DE</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.54 &#x000b1; 1.56<sup>C</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.22 &#x000b1; 1.60<sup>CD</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.92 &#x000b1; 2.23<sup>B</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.85 &#x000b1; 2.94<sup>A</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn2-1559325820959563"><p>GM-1; normal control male rats given only diet, GMT-2; toxic group male rats intoxicated with 0.5 mL 20% CCl<sub>4</sub>, GMT-3; Positive control group male rats given 0.5 mL 20% CCl<sub>4</sub> + 2.5 mg/Kg bw testosterone injection, GMT-4; Positive control group male rats given 0.5 mL 20% CCl<sub>4</sub> + 200 mg/Kg bw Laboob e Kabir (Polyherbal Preparation) orally, GMT-5A, GMT-5B, GMT-5B; Test group male rats intoxicated with 0.5 mL 20 % CCl<sub>4</sub> and administered with ethanolic extract E. grandiflorum in dose concentrations of 50, 100 &#x00026; 200 mg per Kg bw, orally daily respectively TAS (Total antioxidant status), TOS (Total oxidant status), MDA (Malondialdehyde), SOD (Superoxide dismutase), CAT (Catalase) Values are mean &#x000b1; SE (standard error) of means of the study groups. Different letters in superscripts in same row indicate significant group mean differences. The p &#x0003c; 0.05 considered statistically significant while p &#x0003c; 0.01 indicates highly significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="section31-1559325820959563"><title>Change in body, testis weight and reproductive hormones</title><p>The changes in the results, as mean &#x000b1; SEM, of body weight (g), testis weight (g), relative gain in testis (g) and reproductive hormones in male rats have been given in <xref rid="table4-1559325820959563" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1559325820959563">Figure 5</xref>. The results of statistical test revealed that CCl<sub>4</sub> exposure significantly (P &#x0003c; 0.01) decreased the body weight and reproductive hormones including testosterone, LH, FSH and prolactin while progesterone and estradiol increased significantly (P &#x0003c; 0.05) in rats in comparison with the normal rats (<xref rid="table4-1559325820959563" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1559325820959563">Figure 5</xref>). On the administration of different doses of hydroethanolic extracts significant (P &#x0003c; 0.01) restoration of these hormones in comparison of positive control animals administered testosterone injecction and Laboob-e-Kabir have been reported (<xref rid="table4-1559325820959563" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1559325820959563">Figure 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="table4-1559325820959563" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Effect of Ethanolic Plant Extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> and Control Drugs on Body Weight (g) and Testis Weight in Male Albino Rats.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-table4"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GM-1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMT-2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMT-3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMT-4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMT-5A</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMT-5B</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMT-5C</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial body weight (g)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160.6 &#x000b1; 6.95B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">170 &#x000b1; 6.44B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">170.8 &#x000b1; 8.25B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165 &#x000b1; 5.79B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">187 &#x000b1; 6.52A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">174.8 &#x000b1; 9.68AB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">166.2 &#x000b1; 8.87B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final body weight (g)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">248 &#x000b1; 9.083BC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">237.4 &#x000b1; 9.274C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">264 &#x000b1; 7.176AB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250 &#x000b1; 8.916BC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">277.8 &#x000b1; 6.325A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">270 &#x000b1; 8.396A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">271 &#x000b1; 8.276A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body weight gain (g)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.4 &#x000b1; 3.962BC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.4 &#x000b1; 4.159D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.8 &#x000b1; 4.324B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 &#x000b1; 3.050C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.8 &#x000b1; 4.324B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.2 &#x000b1; 4.637A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.8 &#x000b1; 3.317A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Testis Weight Gain (g)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.472 &#x000b1; 0.145C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.442 &#x000b1; 0.178E</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.588 &#x000b1; 0.131C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.104 &#x000b1; 0.073D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.058 &#x000b1; 0.106B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.762 &#x000b1; 0.183A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.034 &#x000b1; 0.126A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative weight gain in Testis (g)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.804 &#x000b1; 0.044BC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.455 &#x000b1; 0.108D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.740 &#x000b1; 0.095BC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.644 &#x000b1; 0.073C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.827 &#x000b1; 0.047B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.136 &#x000b1; 0.100A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.229 &#x000b1; 0.101A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn3-1559325820959563"><p>GM-1; normal control male rats given only diet, GMT-2; toxic group male rats intoxicated with 0.5 mL 20% CCl<sub>4</sub>, GMT-3; Positive control group male rats given 0.5 mL 20% CCl<sub>4</sub> + 2.5 mg/Kg bw testosterone injection, GMT-4; Positive control group male rats given 0.5 mL 20% CCl<sub>4</sub> + 200 mg/Kg bw Laboob e Kabir (Polyherbal Preparation) orally, GMT-5A, GMT-5B, GMT-5B; Test group male rats intoxicated with 0.5 mL 20 % CCl<sub>4</sub> and administered with ethanolic extract E. grandiflorum in dose concentrations of 50, 100 &#x00026; 200 mg per Kg bw, orally daily respectively Values are Mean &#x000b1; SE (standard error) of means of the study groups. Different alphabetic letters in same row specify the significant differences in group means. The level of significance was considered at p &#x0003c; 0.05 while p &#x0003c; 0.01 indicates highly significant.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig5-1559325820959563" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Concentration of reproductive hormones including testosterone, prolactin, FSH, LH, progesterone and estradiol in the blood samples collected from different experimental groups at the end of trial. Values are mean &#x000b1; SE (standard error) of means of the study groups. Colum share the same alphabets indicate non-significant (p &#x0003e; 0.05) differences.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-fig5"/></fig></sec><sec id="section32-1559325820959563"><title>Histological examination of testicular tissue</title><p>The histological examination of testicular tissues revealed that CCl<sub>4</sub> intoxication of rats significantly damaged the spermatogenic cells in the seminiferous tubules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1559325820959563">Figure 6B</xref>) as compared to normal control group, as normal testis are composed of multiple seminiferous tubular cells with germinal epithelium (4-6 layers) at various spermatogenic stages with mature spermatozoa in the central lumen. The other cells including sertoli cells and leydig cells are also present in adequate number in normal testis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1559325820959563">Figure 6A</xref>). The sections from both positive controls and rats administrated hydroethanolic plant extract showed noticeable improvement in the histo-architecture after CCl<sub>4</sub> intoxication (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1559325820959563">Figure 6C-E</xref>).</p><fig id="fig6-1559325820959563" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Histological Sections taken from Testicular tissues of different experimental male rats and stained with H &#x00026; E stain (A) GM-1 (B) GMT-2 (C) GMT-3 (C) GMT-4 (D) GMT-5B. The alphabets (a-f) indicates different histological features of testis as (a) represent the lumen of seminiferous tubule (b) shows mature spermatozoa (c) indicates primary spermatocyte (d) highlight the spermatogonium (e) marks the seminiferous tubules basement membrane and (f) represent the leydig cells present between seminiferous tubules spaces.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-fig6"/></fig></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section33-1559325820959563"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="section34-1559325820959563"><title>Phytochemical Constituents and Antioxidant Potential</title><p>A wide range of medicinal plants are being used with several therapeutic potentials due to the presence of phytochemical constituents including alkaloids, flavonoids, steroids, glycosides, tannins and saponins.<sup><xref rid="bibr45-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> Natural alkaloid as well as their synthetic derivatives have proven to have wide range of pharmacological activities including antimicrobial, analgesic and antispasmodic<sup><xref rid="bibr46-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> and it was reported that the antioxidant potential of herbal preparations is due to the presence of phenolic compounds.<sup><xref rid="bibr47-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> Moreover, it was well reported that ethanol and methanol act as effective solvents for the extraction of antioxidant phenolic compounds<sup><xref rid="bibr15-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> and most important groups of natural products include flavonoids are the widespread class of natural phenolic constituents. It was reported that quenching of active oxygen species is due to several flavonoids present in extract.<sup><xref rid="bibr48-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>
</p><p>Defect in the natural antioxidant defense system might create oxidative stress which might be associated with different types of disorders and other healthcare problems<sup><xref rid="bibr49-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup> and to prevent these oxidant associated disorders natural antioxidants including flavonoids, carotenoids as well as vitamins like A, C and E with food supplements are used.<sup><xref rid="bibr50-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup>
</p><p>It was reported that <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> has good antioxidant potential, and could act as natural antioxidants in pharmaceutical preparations, foods and cosmetics, and our results are in agreement with the findings of Yang et al.,<sup><xref rid="bibr51-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> who also found the good radical scavenging activity of Epimedium species. Moreover, results also explored that the increase in the reductive capacity is directly proportional to the concentration of plant extracts. In addition, it was also reported that the hydroethanolic extract of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> contains phyto compounds responsible for reducing potential, a significant indicator of its antioxidant capacity.<sup><xref rid="bibr52-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="bibr53-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></sup>
</p></sec><sec id="section35-1559325820959563"><title>Hemolytic and Thrombolytic Activities</title><p>Evaluation of drugs toxicity is one of the major concerns in drug development<sup><xref rid="bibr44-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> because most of the herbal preparations have a wide range of health benefits. Very high viscosity of semen is also a cause of infertility because this significantly affects the motility of spermatozoa. Although, a wide range of thrombolytic medicines are available but many of them have severe side effects which might lead to bleeding and embolism.<sup><xref rid="bibr54-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup> In the previous studies, it was reported that secondary metabolites present in the plant extract might be responsible for the thrombolytic activity. Fuentes et al<sup><xref rid="bibr55-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup> determined that flavonoids and saponins are the phytochemicals responsible for the thrombolytic activity of plants and these compounds have ability to dissolve the fibrin clot.</p></sec><sec id="section36-1559325820959563"><title>
<italic>In Vivo</italic> Hydroethanolic Extract&#x02019; Therapeutic Response</title><sec id="section37-1559325820959563"><title>Hepatoprotective and renoprotective activities of E. grandiflorum extract</title><p>Liver as a chief organ in body plays vital roles in the body like synthetic, detoxification, storage, excretion as well as secretion; and the failure of any these metabolic process might associated with liver abnormalities leading to increased serum liver enzymes levels in blood circulation.<sup><xref rid="bibr56-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup> The improvement in liver enzymes of plants treated rats suggests the extract has hepatoprotective potential of Epimedium.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> It was also found that Epimedium species have potential to restore the transaminases reported by Lee et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr57-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup>
</p><p>In Chinese Traditional Medicine, the kidney is alleged to be crucial for sexual and bone health. To tonify the renal functions and stimulate the yang, epimedium species are under in clinical practice and latest <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> pharmacological studies demonstrated that epimedium plants have a wide range of therapeutic applications including renoprotective activities.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Intragastric administration of 5 g/kg b.w daily of Epimedium to male rats, it was reported that kidney functions are restored by recovering the injured Kidney cell which also up regulate the bone formation by increasing the expression of renal hormone genes.<sup><xref rid="bibr58-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup>
</p></sec><sec id="section38-1559325820959563"><title>Total oxidant (TOS), antioxidant status (TAS) and stress markers in rats&#x02019; blood</title><p>Antioxidant systems both enzymatic and non-enzymatic act the natural body defense mechanism to neutralize the oxidant molecules. Total antioxidant status in the body often revealed the dynamic equilibrium between the body&#x02019;s antioxidant defense and pro-oxidants.<sup><xref rid="bibr59-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> Physiologically, body have capacity to generate enough antioxidants or are taken as food supplements for the detoxification of free radical species produced<sup><xref rid="bibr60-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup> and in addition, oxygen free radicals to provide the energy source produced due to the enzymatic reduction of oxygen.<sup><xref rid="bibr61-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup> Our results are coherent with the finding of Yang et al,<sup><xref rid="bibr62-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></sup> who also reported the antioxidant potentials of Epimedium species in experimental rats. As <italic>in vitro</italic> analysis of <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> for antioxidant parameters including reducing as well as scavenging potential revealed good antioxidant activities which might be due to the presence of high contents of flavonoids and phenolic compounds as their active secondary metabolites, therefore these compounds also provide good antioxidant defense system in animals after intoxication with CCl<sub>4</sub>.<sup><xref rid="bibr63-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup>
</p></sec><sec id="section39-1559325820959563"><title>Change in body, testis weight, reproductive hormones and histo-architecture of testis</title><p>Epimedium plants not only used as medicines in Chinese Traditional medicine for the treatment of disease but also have importance to prevent disease and strengthen the body as supplement.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Reproductive hormones including gonadotrophins, testosterone and prolactin influence erectile processes in males.<sup><xref rid="bibr64-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,<xref rid="bibr65-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></sup> The reproduction is tightly regulated by hypothalamo-pituitary gonadal axis and Gonadotrophin releasing hormone (GnRH) from hypothalamus influence the secretion of gonadotrophins; FSH and LH from the anterior pituitary. FSH stimulate the spermatogenesis while LH have role in the production and release of testosterone, male reproductive hormone, from the leydig cells essential for spermatogenesis and for reproductive system development like testis and prostate.<sup><xref rid="bibr66-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></sup> It also regulate the expression of secondary sexual characteristic in males like increased muscle mass, bone mass, the endocrine system and growth of body-hair.<sup><xref rid="bibr67-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></sup> FSH function is to stimulate the process of spermatogenesis while LH play role in stimulating the testosterone synthesis and release. Increased blood flow is influenced by testosterone which in turn stimulates the growth of the target tissues. The current study is in agreement with findings of Khan and Ahmed,<sup><xref rid="bibr68-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></sup> who also reported that CCl<sub>4</sub> induced testicular toxicity in rats and described that administration of CCl<sub>4</sub> caused the atrophy of testicular tissue, germinal layer degeneration, lowered the serum level of gonadotropins (FSH and LH) and testosterone in male rat.<sup><xref rid="bibr68-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></sup> The impairment in reproductive hormones might be due to the direct impact of CCl<sub>4</sub> on leydig cells and make them unresponsive to FSH and LH, leads to decreased secretion of testosterone. In addition, it was also reported that many hormonal fluctuations like lower level of serum cortisol, testosterone, FSH, and insulin and impairment of prolactin secretion are associated with liver disorders in males.<sup><xref rid="bibr63-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,<xref rid="bibr65-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></sup> Moreover, it could be suggested that CYP17A1 enzyme action is inhibited by the action of CCl<sub>4</sub> during intoxication phase and in the leydig cells progesterone produced could not be metabolized to androgen which ultimately leads the decreased concentration of testosterone and increased level of progesterone. Hence the decreased level of progesterone and increased level of testosterone in treated animal groups revealed the effects of plants extract are to counter this inhibitory effect of CCl<sub>4</sub>.<sup><xref rid="bibr69-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></sup>
</p><p>Moreover, it was also find that Epimedium extracts possess a male-hormone-like effect and the administration of epimedium extract (2.0 mg/kg body weight (bw) for 2 week (14 days) orally daily significantly increased the sexual function, weight of attached genitals and improved the testosterone level in the plasma in rats.<sup><xref rid="bibr70-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup> Furthermore, Luo,<sup><xref rid="bibr71-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></sup> investigated that glycosides from <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> 5 g/kg for 8 weeks to guinea pigs significantly improved the body weight, testicular growth, spermatozoa parameters including density, viability in the epididymis and vice-testis and also increased the of the testicles, epididymis, adenohypophysis and seminal vesicles. The improvement in the sexual arousal was also reported on administration of plant extract that might be due to improvement in the reproductive hormones.<sup><xref rid="bibr71-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></sup> Our finding are also coherent in the findings of She et al., who on administration of the total flavonoids from <italic>E. brevicornum</italic> (150.0 mg/kg bw for 7 days) to the rats, observed significantly raised the level of reproductive hormones including testosterone, estradiol and luteinizing hormone levels as well as increased the weight of the anterior pituitary gland, epididymis and seminal vesicles in juvenile rats. Such finding revealed the Epimedium plants improving impact on both structural male reproductive system and reproductive endocrine activities.<sup><xref rid="bibr72-1559325820959563" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></sup>
</p><p>It could be concluded that <italic>E. grandiflorum</italic> contained a wide range of phytochemical constituents, their significant <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> antioxidant potential, significant hepatoprotective, renoprotective and reproductive hormones restoring capacity in male albino rats as therapeutic response directly proportional to doses of hydroethanolic extract administered. However, more research is required to isolate the novel compounds from this therapeutic plant to address the problems particularly of impotency.</p></sec></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors acknowledged the technical supervision and providing the space in Clinical Biochemistry Laboratory, Department of Biochemistry, Government College University Faisalabad&#x02013;Pakistan to complete this research work.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn1-1559325820959563"><p><bold>Declaration of Conflicting Interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1559325820959563"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1559325820959563"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Naveed Munir <inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1559325820959563-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0380-1332">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0380-1332</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-1559325820959563"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The genus Epimedium: an ethnopharmacological and phytochemical review</article-title>. <source>J Ethnopharmacol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>519</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>541</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21215308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-1559325820959563"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shindel</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>ZC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Erectogenic and neurotrophic effects of icariin, a purified extract of horny goat weed (Epimedium spp.) in vitro and in vivo</article-title>. <source>J Sex Med</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1518</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1528</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20141584</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-1559325820959563"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>ZC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Banie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lue</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of icariin on phosphodiesterase-5 activity in vitro and cyclic guanosine monophosphate level in cavernous smooth muscle cells</article-title>. <source>Urology</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1350</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1354</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17169663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-1559325820959563"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>BX</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Effect of icarisid II on diabetic rats with erectile dysfunction and its potential mechanism via assessment of AGEs, autophagy, mTOR and the NO&#x02013;cGMP pathway</article-title>. <source>Asian J Androl</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>143</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22728670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-1559325820959563"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZB</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>QT</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The testosterone mimetic properties of icariin</article-title>. <source>Asian J Androl</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>601</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>605</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16751992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-1559325820959563"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayernia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaroszynski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Stem cell based therapeutical approach of male infertility by teratocarcinoma derived germ cells</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1451</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1460</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15163638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-1559325820959563"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tournaye</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohlen</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Management of male-factor infertility</article-title>. <source>Best Pract Res Cl Ob</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>769</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>775</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-1559325820959563"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Speroff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). (<year>2005</year>). <source>Clinical Gynecologic Endocrinology and Infertility</source>
<publisher-name>. Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-1559325820959563"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toshimori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Maekawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Toyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki-Toyota</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Impairment of spermatogenesis leading to infertility</article-title>. <source>Anat Sci Int</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>111</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15453611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-1559325820959563"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ipomoea littoralis (Convolvulaceae)&#x02014;taxonomy, distribution, and ethnobotany</article-title>. <source>Econ Bot</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>256</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-1559325820959563"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazl-i-Hadi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>An ethnobotanical study of Medicinal Plants in high mountainous region of Chail valley (District Swat-Pakistan)</article-title>. <source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24739524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-1559325820959563"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Liserre</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Acerola nectar with added microencapsulated probiotic</article-title>. <source>Lwt-Food Sci Technol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-1559325820959563"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chhokar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evaluation of root and leaf extracts of Glycrriza glabra for antimicrobial activity</article-title>. <source>J Med Biol Eng</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-1559325820959563"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taid</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajkhowa</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalita</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A study on the medicinal plants used by the local traditional healers of Dhemaji district, Assam, India for curing reproductive health related disorders</article-title>. <source>Adv Appl Sci Res</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>296</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-1559325820959563"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esmaeili</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Coad</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gholamifard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Teimory</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Annotated checklist of the freshwater fishes of Iran</article-title>. <source>Zoosyst Ross</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>361</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>386</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-1559325820959563"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaidya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Preliminary phytochemical, pharmacognostical and physico-chemical evaluation of Cedrus deodara heartwood</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacogn Phytochem</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-1559325820959563"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pranuthi</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Narendra</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Swathi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Qualitative assessment of bioactive compounds from a very rare medicinal plant Ficus dalhousiae Miq</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacogn Phytochem</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-1559325820959563"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Phytochemical analysis of some medicinal plants</article-title>. <source>J Phytol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-1559325820959563"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Junaid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Phenolic contents, antioxidant and anticholinesterase potentials of crude extract, subsequent fractions and crude saponins from Polygonum hydropiper L</article-title>. <source>Bmc Complem Altern M</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>145</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-1559325820959563"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jian-Fei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Simultaneous determination of nine phenolic acids in dendranthema morifolium (Ramat) Tzvel. cv. Chuju samples by high performance liquid chromatography</article-title>. <source>Chin J Anal Chem</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>388</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-1559325820959563"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pineda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anguilar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Spectrophotometric quantitation of antioxidant capacity through the formation of a P hosphomolybdenum C omplex: specific application to the determination of vitamin E</article-title>. <source>Anal. Biochem</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>269</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>341</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10222007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-1559325820959563"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shahid Chatha</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Asad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Majeed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aslam</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Bioactive components and antioxidant properties of Terminalia arjuna L. extracts</article-title>. <source>J Food Process Technol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>298</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-1559325820959563"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>In vitro antioxidant activity and total phenolic content of endophytic fungi isolated from Eugenia jambolana Lam</article-title>. <source>Asian Pac J Trop Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>256</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>261</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-1559325820959563"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruch</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Klaunig</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Prevention of cytotoxicity and inhibition of intracellular communication by antioxidant catechins isolated from Chinese green tea</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1003</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1008</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2470525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-1559325820959563"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Catranis</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Maynard</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Design of self-processing antimicrobial peptides for plant protection</article-title>. <source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>168</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10972721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-1559325820959563"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Karthik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hemolytic activity of Indian medicinal plants towards human erythrocytes: an in vitro study</article-title>. <source>Elixir Applied Botany</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>5534</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5537</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-1559325820959563"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Emran</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Effects of organic extracts of six Bangladeshi plants on in vitro thrombolysis and cytotoxicity</article-title>. <source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>25</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23363538</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-1559325820959563"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahreen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of Carissa opaca leaves extract on lipid peroxidation, antioxidant activity and reproductive hormones in male rats</article-title>. <source>Lipids Health Dis</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>90</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23786717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-1559325820959563"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kakkar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Viswanathan</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A modified spectrophotomateric assay of superoxide dismutase</article-title>. <source>Indian J Biochem Bio</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>132</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-1559325820959563"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chance</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Maehly</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Assay of catalase and peroxidases</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol</source>
<year>1955</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>764</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>775</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-1559325820959563"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergmeyer</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><name><surname>Horder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rej</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>IFCC methods for the measurement of catalytic concentration of enzymes. Part 2. IFCC method for aspartate and alanine aminotransferases</article-title>. <source>J Clin Chem Clin Biochem</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>481</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>495</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3734711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-1559325820959563"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Clinical Laboratory Diagnostics</source>. <edition>1st ed</edition>
<publisher-name>TH-Books Verlagsgesellschaft</publisher-name>
<year>1998</year>;<fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-1559325820959563"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pesce</surname><given-names>AJ.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <source>Total Serum Protein, Clinical Chemistry, Theory, Analysis and Correlation</source>. <publisher-name>Mosby Company</publisher-name>; <comment>1984</comment>:<fpage>1316</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1319</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-1559325820959563"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burtis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashwood</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Tietz Textbook of Clinical Chemistry</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>
<publisher-name>Saunders</publisher-name>; <year>1994</year>:<fpage>625</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>888</lpage>, <comment>928&#x02013;1081, 1513&#x02013;1568</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-1559325820959563"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Swartzentruber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolen</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sine</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Multicenter evaluation of the boehringer Mannheim compensated, rate-blanked creatinine/jaffe application on BM/Hitachi systems. Advances in clinical diagnostics</article-title>. <source>Boehringer Mannheim Corporation</source>. <year>1993</year>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-1559325820959563"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bookstein</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Meldrum</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Diagnosis of a testosterone-secreting adrenal adenoma by selective venous catheterization</article-title>. <source>Fertil Steril</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>1202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1828044</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-1559325820959563"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Faix</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermos</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Thyroid function in very low birth weight infants: effects on neonatal hypothyroidism screening</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>128</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>548</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>554</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8618191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-1559325820959563"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Enzyme immunoassay method for total urinary follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) beta subunit and its application for measurement of total urinary FSH</article-title>. <source>Fertil Steril</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>278</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>285</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9496342</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr39-1559325820959563"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanderpump</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Appleton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tunbridge</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kendall-Taylor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The prevalence of hyperprolactinaemia and association with markers of autoimmune thyroid disease in survivors of the Whickham Survey cohort</article-title>. <source>Clin Endocrinol (Oxf)</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9509066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr40-1559325820959563"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radwanska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Frankenberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Plasma progesterone levels in normal and abnormal early human pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Fertil Steril</source>. <year>1978</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>398</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>402</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">710610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr41-1559325820959563"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Steroid biosynthesis by isolated human ovarian follicular cells in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1407</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1411</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6255006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr42-1559325820959563"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bancroft</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamble</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Theory and practice of histological techniques</article-title>. <source>Elsevier Health Sci</source>. <year>2008</year>;<fpage>625</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>725</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr43-1559325820959563"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Design and Analysis of Experiments</source>. <edition>7th ed</edition>
<publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr44-1559325820959563"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fowles</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mootoo</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramsewak</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Toxicity&#x02013;structure activity evaluation of limonoids from Swietenia species on Artemia salina</article-title>. <source>Pharma Biol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>264</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>267</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr45-1559325820959563"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edeoga</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><name><surname>Okwu</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mbaebie</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Phytochemical constituents of some Nigerian medicinal plants</article-title>. <source>Afr J Biotechnol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>685</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>688</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr46-1559325820959563"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okwu</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Okwu</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Chemical composition of Spondias mombin Linn Plant parts</article-title>. <source>J Sustain Agric Environ</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>147</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr47-1559325820959563"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Micro-wave-assisted extraction and antioxidant activity of total phenolic compounds from pomegranate peel</article-title>. <source>J Med Plants Res</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1004</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1011</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr48-1559325820959563"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leake</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Is diversity of ectomycorrhizal fungi important for ecosystem function?</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>152</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr49-1559325820959563"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smolskait&#x00117;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Venskutonis</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Talou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Comprehensive evaluation of antioxidant and antimicrobial properties of different mushroom species</article-title>. <source>LWT-Food Sci Technol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>462</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>471</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr50-1559325820959563"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jayakumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chennazhi</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Furuike</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Chitin scaffolds in tissue engineering</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1876</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1887</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21673928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr51-1559325820959563"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Enzymatic water extraction of polysaccharides from Epimedium brevicornu and their antioxidant activity and protective effect against DNA damage</article-title>. <source>J Food Biochem</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e12298</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr52-1559325820959563"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>QS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Anti-oxidation on total flavones of Epimedium in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Nanchang Univ(Natural Science)</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr53-1559325820959563"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Optimization of ultrasonic extraction of phenolic compounds from Epimedium brevicornum maxim using response surface methodology and evaluation of its antioxidant activities in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Anal Methods Chem</source>. <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr54-1559325820959563"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capstick</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy of thrombolytic agents in the treatment of pulmonary embolism</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>864</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>874</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16264048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr55-1559325820959563"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Guzm&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Alarc&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Palomo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Thrombolytic/fibrinolytic mechanism of natural products</article-title>. <source>Fibrinolysis Thrombolysis</source>. <year>2014</year>:<fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr56-1559325820959563"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nweze</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mustapha</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alkali</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Aqueous leaf extracts of Tobacco plant (Nicotiana tabaccum) causes hepatotoxicity in male Wistar albino rats</article-title>. <source>Asian J Pharmacol Toxicol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>07</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr57-1559325820959563"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Antihepatotoxic activity of Icariin, a major constituent of Epimedium koreanum</article-title>. <source>Planta Medica</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>526</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8824946</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr58-1559325820959563"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The effects of Epimedium on the expressions of renal and femoral bone morphogenetic protein-7 in male rats with kidney-YANG insufficiency</article-title>. <source>Chin J Osteoporosis</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>90</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr59-1559325820959563"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghiselli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Serafini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Natella</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Scaccin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Total antioxidant capacity as a tool to assess redox status: critical view and experimental data</article-title>. <source>Free Radical Biol Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1114</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11121717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr60-1559325820959563"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Targarona</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thayer</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattner</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brugge</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Warshaw</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Incidental pancreatic cysts: clinicopathologic characteristics and comparison with symptomatic patients</article-title>. <source>Arch Surg</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>427</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>434</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12686529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr61-1559325820959563"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leibfritz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moncol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Telser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Free radicals and antioxidants in normal physiological functions and human disease</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>44</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16978905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr62-1559325820959563"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Extract from Epimedium brevicornum Maxim. Against injury to function of human sperm membrane in vitro</article-title>. <source>Chin J Clin Pharmacol Therapeutics</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>667</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr63-1559325820959563"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>MUQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Lipid peroxidation and antioxidant enzymes in relation to semen quality</article-title>. <source>Oxid Commun</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>4-I</issue>): <fpage>2990</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2998</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr64-1559325820959563"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Sexual dysfunction in hypertensive men, a critical review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Hypertension</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3294176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr65-1559325820959563"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evaluation of antioxidant and fertility effects of Digera muricata in male rats</article-title>. <source>Afr J Pharm Pharmacol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>688</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>699</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr66-1559325820959563"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Calandra</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Peripheral and central mechanisms involved in the hormonal control of male and female reproduction</article-title>. <source>J Neuroendocrinol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>28</volume>:doi:<comment>10.1111/jne.12405</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr67-1559325820959563"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Famili</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Towards multidimensional genome annotation</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>141</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16418748</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr68-1559325820959563"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Protective effects of Digera muricata (L.) mart. on testis against oxidative stress of carbon tetrachloride in rat</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1393</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1399</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19327381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr69-1559325820959563"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Conley</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathewson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Expression of steroidogenic enzymes during equine testicular development</article-title>. <source>Reproduction</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>141</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>841</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>848</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21300693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr70-1559325820959563"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of administration of herba Epimedium at the optimal time levels on sexual hormones</article-title>. <source>J Tradit Chin Med</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>619</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>621</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr71-1559325820959563"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of herba epimediim on growth of guinea pig</article-title>. <source>Chin WildvPlant Resources</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>38</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr72-1559325820959563"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>She</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>She</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effeets of flavonoids from Herba Epimediim on the reproduetive system in male rats</article-title>. <source>Chin J Androl</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>294</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>296</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>