<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Most cellular activities involve complex signaling pathways, including apoptotic pathways and mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathways. In intrinsic apoptotic signaling pathways, tumor suppressors such as p53 induce apoptosis via regulation of proapoptotic proteins (BIM, PUMA, NOXA, and BAX) and antiapoptotic proteins (BCL-2, MCL-1, and BCL-XL) [
 <xref rid="B92-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. MAPKs are composed of a cascade of several kinases to transmit cellular signals to diverse types of transcription factors [
 <xref rid="B93-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. As MAPK signaling pathways can activate or inactivate cell metabolisms, such as cell proliferation and apoptosis, MAPKs are one of major targets for cancer treatment. The demonstrated anticancer effects of UNA, which were consistent with various scientific investigations, imply that UNA may be able to regulate cancer-related signaling pathways, including apoptotic and MAPK pathways. Unfortunately, detailed mechanisms of UNA’s pharmacological potential have not yet been sufficiently explained. Two publications previously explained the signaling pathways of cancer cells regulated by UNA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biomolecules-10-01505-f004">Figure 4</xref>). In MGC-803 human gastric cancer cells, UNA increased the protein levels of p53, cell death effector BAX, and activated caspase-3 and caspase-9, which execute apoptosis of cells [
 <xref rid="B35-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. In A549 and H1299 human lung cancer cells, UNA inactivated phosphorylation extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK) and transcription factor cAMP response element-binding protein (CREB), which are highly associated with the expression of MMPs and metastases [
 <xref rid="B59-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B94-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B95-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. In HaCaT keratinocytes, UNA inhibited ERK and the c-fos signaling pathway and repressed the expression of collagenase MMP-1, which is a principal enzyme responsible for skin aging [
 <xref rid="B59-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. Several research studies further showed that UNA exerted strong pharmaceutical effects in diverse types of cells; further research may unveil additional antitumour, as well as other, therapeutic mechanisms exerted by UNA. Particularly, it is expected that UNA may strongly affect signaling pathways in some contexts, such as cytotoxicity in HCT15 colon cancer cells (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 1.23 μM) and attenuated NO production in RAW264.7 macrophages (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 4.94 µM) [
 <xref rid="B22-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Furthermore, previous in silico assays predicted that UNA could display inhibitory activity against the transcription factor NF-κB, with a probability of activation value of 54% [
 <xref rid="B98-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. This implies that UNA may be involved in regulation of NF-κB signaling pathways, which are responsible for proinflammatory responses [
 <xref rid="B98-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>].
</p>
