<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par54" class="p">Since the last, comprehensive review of natural products with activity against parasitic nematodes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>], there have been partial revisions on the parasiticidal activities of plant extracts, essential oils and some individual compounds therein [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127" class="xref">127</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129" class="xref">129</xref>], sometimes focusing on specific parasites [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130" class="xref">130</xref>] or on a particular compound class [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131" class="xref">131</xref>]. Here, we critically appraised the scientific and patent literature for all pure natural compounds active against any parasitic nematode of animals, or against the model nematode 
 <italic class="italic">C. elegans</italic>, from 2010 to 2018, to gain a perspective on the abundance of natural chemical starting points available for anthelmintic drug discovery. The findings are somewhat disappointing, considering that natural products are a main source of novel drug scaffolds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>], especially for anti-parasitics and antimicrobials. Only one new chemical class has emerged from the scientific literature in the review period, namely that of the open nemadectin analogues [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" class="xref">103</xref>], and very limited effort seems to have been devoted to exploring the SARs of previously described compounds, with the exception of the jietacins [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" class="xref">117</xref>]. Most publications analysed are rather preliminary reports of compounds with low to moderate activity from sources not explored before for anthelmintic activity, but yielding in the end already known chemical structures. Compounding the problem, most reviewed compound structures fall within classes with promiscuous activity and dubbed “Pan Assay INterference compoundS” (PAINS) or “Invalid Metabolic Panaceas” (IMPs) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132" class="xref">132</xref>], because they keep being rediscovered as hit compounds in unrelated biological assays. This may be due to easy chemical reactivity, optical properties or to a capacity for non-specifically binding and aggregating macromolecules, especially when compounds are assayed at hundreds of micromolar or millimolar levels. Such unwanted properties should be investigated as part of the hit characterisation process for compounds with structural alerts [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133" class="xref">133</xref>], something that, admittedly, may be difficult to do without a biologically relevant target-based assay. An intriguing conclusion from this review has been that plants are the sources for most compounds discussed herein. The only reported compound of fungal origin was β-sitosterol, also present in plants, while, arguably, the most interesting compounds, the open nemadectins (Macrocycles subsection) and the jietacins (Miscellaneous compounds subsection), were both isolated from cultures of 
 <italic class="italic">Streptomyces</italic> species (bacteria). The overwhelming focus on plants seems to relate to ready accessibility, ethnobotanical considerations and the possibility of directly using plant material to treat helminthiases of animals. However, as discussed in the Background section, plants often present issues of irregular yields of active compounds and of sustainable supplies. Additionally, re-discovery rates seem to indicate that most major classes of plant products have already been described. Minor components of plant extracts with potent biological activity are probably still waiting to be isolated, but we appear to have reached a situation in which diminishing returns demand increased analytical efforts. The apparent rareness of screening activity using compounds from animal sources can be justified by the difficulties and costs associated with accessing their sources, but it is more difficult to explain why microbial extracts are not more widely reported in anthelmintic screens. Of the four novel anthelmintic classes introduced into general use since 2000, three originated from bacterial products (macrocyclic lactones, cyclooctadepsipeptides and paraherquamides), and only one is a fully synthetic class, the aminonitriles (monepantel). From a theoretical perspective as well, the genetic diversity, and, consequently, the metabolic capabilities of microbes far exceed those of metazoans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134" class="xref">134</xref>], and there is a plethora of well-curated collections of pre-fractionated microbial extracts and pure compounds available for screening (cf. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>]), with far fewer reproducibility and sustainability issues than plant extracts. Therefore, the published literature leads to the conclusion that most research activity in this area is biased towards plant compounds primarily for reasons other than past or theoretical success rates. It may be that extracting plant material requires less infrastructure and know-how than isolating and culturing microorganism, and there is also the issue of research funding. Accessing well-curated natural products libraries involves some costs and compound screening is often derided as a “fishing expedition” and usually dismissed by research funding agencies, while the same work is considered too preliminary and risky for industry funding, thus limiting anthelmintic research to low-cost activities. It would help academic initiatives in this area if freely accessible high-throughput phenotypic assays were made widely available, as it has been done for antimicrobials [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135" class="xref">135</xref>]. Hopefully, the recognition of key helminthiases as neglected tropical diseases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136" class="xref">136</xref>] should provide a much-needed boost to the field, before drug resistance renders current control activities ineffective for human patients as well as for livestock animals.
</p>
