<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Trace element concentrations in fillets were lower than in the diets (
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.t008" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 8</xref>), except for no change in selenium, suggesting these trace elements may be excreted by Nile tilapia. Aluminum (Al) and iron (Fe), for example, have been examined in a few dietary toxicity studies in tilapia [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>]. We found that fillet concentrations, compared to diet concentrations, declined to below detection for Al and declined by an order of magnitude for Fe. Prior investigators reported that the Al and Fe taken up by tilapia were not accumulated in the body and subsequently excreted in the feces [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. Feeding 
 <italic class="italic">Spirulina</italic> containing high dietary level of Al (&gt;2816 mg kg
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> diet) and Fe (&gt;7573 mg kg
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> diet) as a sole protein source compromised the growth of juvenile tilapia [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>]; but these dietary Al and Fe levels were an order of magnitude higher than in all our diets (Al &lt;94.9 mg kg
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> diet, iron &lt;133.6 mg kg
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> diet). Also, a clear advantage of using the 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oculata</italic> co-product over whole cells in aquafeeds is that Al and Fe levels were an order of magnitude less in co-product than in whole cells (
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.t005" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 5</xref>). In another study, Hussein et al. (2014) [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref072" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>] found no negative effect of high concentration of dietary Al (1792 mg kg
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> diet) and iron (3059 mg kg
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> diet) on growth and body composition of Nile tilapia in diet containing 38% algae; again, these levels were higher than in all our diets. Studies in other fish species also found no toxic effects of dietary Al concentrations of 100 to 2000 mg kg-1 [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref073" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref074" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>]. We found low or non-detectable levels of other trace elements such as lead, mercury, and arsenic in the co-product, feeds, and fillet. We detected a low concentration of arsenic levels in the 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oculata</italic> co-product (0.2 mg kg
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup>), lower than in whole cells (5.9 mg kg
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup>), and arsenic levels were non-detectable in the experimental diets and fillets. We also detected a low concentration of lead (0.1 mg kg
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup>) in the 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oculata</italic> co-product and all diets containing the co-product. Lead is a highly toxic metal that causes health problems in many parts of the world; and the US Center for Disease Control considers lead poisoning to be the leading environmental health threat to children at 10μg/dL concentration in blood [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref075" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>]. We found non-detectable levels of lead concentrations in fish fillets across all diets; thus, fish fed the fishmeal free diet, with 8% 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oculata</italic> co-product inclusion by weight, yielded a fillet which is safe eating for human health.
</p>
