<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our findings highlight the need to better understand how anti-nutrients in microalgal co-product limit inclusion rates in aquafeeds and to identify practical steps to improve nutrient digestibility to achieve higher replacement levels. The observed reduction in nutrient digestibility could be due to the high content of complex indigestible cell wall non-starch polysaccharides (NSPs) in the microalga [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Nannochloropsis</italic> sp. cell walls are known to include complex polysaccharides [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. Complex non-starch polysaccharides, such as cellulose, gums, pectins and hemicelluloses, are undesirable in aquafeed because they depress nutrient absorption [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref056" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. Lipid extraction from 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oculata</italic> whole cells seems to elevate anti-nutrient levels including NSP in 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oculata</italic> co-product biomass, which might explain our results on 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oculata</italic> co-product digestibility and growth effects. Specifically, anti-nutrient analysis (
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.t004" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 4</xref>) showed that 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oculata</italic> co-product contains higher levels of crude fiber (3.7%) than whole cells (0.8%), higher hemicellulose level (43.3 ugmg
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) than whole cells (28.8 ugmg
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>), higher level of trypsin inhibitor (2145.0 TIU/g) than whole cells (1000TIU/g), and higher level of lectin (240.0 HU/mg) than whole cells (19.0 HU/mg). Finally, composition analysis indicated that neither 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oculata</italic> whole cells nor co-product contain pectin, which provides an advantage to formulate aquaculture feed with co-product. Pectin is a polysaccharide characterized by relatively high extractability using acid or chelators and a high content of D-galacturonic acid (GalUA) units as the backbone, connected in chains through a glycosidic linkage [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. These uronic acids have carboxyl groups which, in the presence of divalent cations (usually calcium), have considerable effects on viscosity, solubility, and gelation formation [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>].
</p>
