<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our results fit with several prior studies that revealed that NSPs have a negative influence on digestion and absorption by modulating digesta viscosity and rate of passage, and by altering fish gut physiology and morphology [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>]. The presence of digestive enzymes that can hydrolyze the β-glycosidic bonds of NSP seems to be very low or nonexistent in monogastric animals including tilapia [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. Thus, highly concentrated amounts of complex NSPs, and trypsin inhibitor content in 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oculata</italic> co-product could have inhibited nutrient digestibility in tilapia in our experiment. In our previous study, we also found depressed digestibility of fatty acids and amino acids in 
 <italic class="italic">Chlorella sp</italic>. whole cells, likely due to their complex cell wall structure [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Similarly, Skrede et al. (2011) [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>] revealed that the complex cell wall structure of algae may affect digestibility of inherent algae lipids and other lipids in the diets. As the digestive tracts of tilapia lack any appreciable NSP enzyme activity [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>], adding NSP enzymes to feed could enhance digestibility and utilization of nutrients supplied by 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oculata</italic> co-product [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref063" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. Also, extrusion processing of feeds containing 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oculata</italic> co-product would break down trypsin inhibitors and thus could improve the digestibility and retention of protein and lipids, and feed conversion in fish. Similarly, previous studies on plant protein have revealed that extrusion could enhance the utilization of protein, starch and NSPs [
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201315.ref067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>]. We did not extrude the feeds used in our experiments and recommend doing so in future work with 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oculata</italic> co-product.
</p>
