<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0230">Dust air pollution affects an area of more than 1.4 million square km and over 800 million people in the world (
 <xref rid="bib127" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2016</xref>). Most of these people live in developing countries experiencing the detrimental effects of COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Loayza, 2020</xref>). Haloculture has a good potential to generate vegetation and reduce wind and water erosion, and thus can stabilize airborne dust centers. Agricultural production in saline conditions requires more leaching to control the salinity of the root zone; in addition to increasing the entry of salts into the deeper soil layers, this also causes more soil erosion, leading to the production of dust. Cultivating halophytes in haloculture systems reduces the need for water and the need for leaching. This is especially important in areas such as the Middle East, where dust and drainage are a pervasive crisis. The important point is that in the most significant centers of fine dust production, the COVID-19 situation is in a critical state. It is believed that the coronavirus can spread by airborne dust particles (
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">Qu et al., 2020</xref>). Scientists believe that some diseases could spread through the population by airborne pathogen transmission. Some developing countries are struggling with air pollution, since dust particles may transmit COVID-19 and accelerate the infection rate (
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">Qu et al., 2020</xref>). Notably, it has been stated that soil particles can contain microorganisms such as the coronavirus, and this is exacerbated when sewage sludge enters the soil (
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Conde-Cid et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">Núñez-Delgado, 2020</xref>). Therefore, haloculture reduces the production of fine dust and stabilizes the centers of fine dust by creating vegetation and reducing erosion (wind and water), which in turn can reduce the prevalence of COVID-19 and other pathogenic microorganisms proliferated in saline soils. Indeed, in addition to the coronavirus, there are some other pathogens that can be spread by saline and/or sodic soil particles, some examples of which are listed in 
 <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref> .
</p>
