<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Diabetes mellitus, characterized by abnormal hyperglycemia, affects 463 million patients globally [
 <xref rid="B1-foods-10-00538" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], of which 60% have one or more complications, such as diabetic retinopathy, nephropathy, and neuropathy [
 <xref rid="B2-foods-10-00538" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The results of epidemiological and clinical research show that effective blood glucose control postpones the occurrence of diabetic complications; however, its development in patients with diabetes is certain to happen [
 <xref rid="B3-foods-10-00538" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-foods-10-00538" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Furthermore, changes in diet or medication of patients with diabetes often results in nutritional deficiencies, dramatically damaging the health and lowering quality of life [
 <xref rid="B5-foods-10-00538" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Thus, the health management of patients with diabetes should be concerned with the control of hyperglycemia, prevention of complications, and supplementation of nutrition. α-Glucosidases are a group of intestinal enzymes involved in carbohydrate digestion and are critical targets for the amelioration of postprandial hyperglycemia [
 <xref rid="B6-foods-10-00538" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Aldose reductase is a pivotal target for preventing the onset and progression of diabetic complications [
 <xref rid="B7-foods-10-00538" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Moreover, oxidative stress is strongly related to the onset of diabetes and exacerbation of complications [
 <xref rid="B8-foods-10-00538" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Currently, the increasingly mindful attitudes of consumers to their diet and health has led to the development of new trends, including the widespread use of functional foods. Hence, there is growing interest in developing functional food ingredients that possess effective inhibitory activities against α-glucosidase, aldose reductase, and free radicals, particularly those with nutritional supplementation that may be useful for promoting the health of patients with diabetes.
</p>
