<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>BP modified drug delivery systems targeted both healthy and destructed bones no matter whether cancer metastasis happened. Adding the targets of delivery systems is an effective way to improve the accuracy of targeting. For instance, designed NPs may contain two types of target ligands that target bone and tumor cells respectively. Dual-targeted or even multi-targeted drug delivery systems rely on the discovery of cells’ special expression or special molecular structure in the osteolytic microenvironment. It was found that bone metastatic cancer cells overexpress folate receptor (FR), cluster of differentiation 44 (CD44) and integrin αVβ3. Human cells express and depend on FR to uptake exogenous folate. FR is widely expressed in normal and tumor cells but more in quantity and activity in tumor cells. In tumor cells, FR loses polarity and becomes easier for drugs in circulation to approach. Folate is a target ligand for FR and is often used to modify the targeted NPs synergistically with BP to target metastatic bone lesions (Assaraf et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Au et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Shih-Hong Chen et al. designed an NPs-based dual-targeted delivery system comprising hydrophobic PLGA core and ALN-modified, folic acid-conjugated D-a-tocopheryl polyethylene glycol succinate (TPGS) coat to deliver PTX. PTX-loaded dual-targeted NPs evidently accumulated in bone metastases after intravenous injection and exhibited the highest efficiency of inhibiting 4T1 tumor growth. It retarded bone destruction of the tumor-bearing mice appreciably with significant improvement of the survival rate of treated mice (median survival &gt;50 d, but &lt;35 d in other groups; Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). In another work, aspartate which possesses affinity to the bone because of the similar HA-binding domain of osteopontin and osteocalcin, and folate were used to conjugate onto the surface of DOX-loaded liposomes. Fluorescent images (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>) demonstrated that dual-targeted liposomes optimized the liposome accumulation in cancer metastatic bone (Ke et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). CD44 is one kind of transmembrane glycoprotein that binds with extracellular matrix hyaluronic acid to mediate intracellular signaling. It is overexpressed in tumor cells and plays an important role in tumor metastasis and invasion. Hyaluronic acid, as a specific ligand for CD44 receptor, was used in many targeted delivery systems (Dosio et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Bai et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Kaili Wang et al. fabricated CD44 and bone dual-targeted nano micelles via a series of esterification reactions, with oligosaccharides of hyaluronan targeting CD44 and ALN targeting bone. 
 <italic>In vivo</italic> distribution experience, dual-targeted micelles group had higher distribution to the bone than other groups (Wang, Guo, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0127" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Another work about DOX-loaded bone and CD44-dual-targeted delivery system showed that the signals of dual-targeting group peaked at 2 h after injection, quicker than the CD44-single-targeting group (6 h). The median survival time was extended to 67 d from 30 d for the untreated group (Feng et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). These results showed that dual-targeted delivery systems have a stronger ability to target metastatic bone, further optimized the distribution of drugs. Integrin αVβ3 is expressed rarely in normal cells but highly in tumor cells and neoplastic neovascular endothelial cells. It can activate matrix metalloproteinase 2 (MMP-2) and accelerate tumor cells secreting cell adherence molecule which contributes to tumor metastasis and neoplastic neovascular formation. ITGβ3 (a subunit of integrin αVβ3) is over-expressed in bone metastatic cancer cells compared to cancer cells from other metastatic organs such as liver, lymph nodes (Ross et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0098" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Gdowski et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). ITGβ3 is a critical factor that contributes to the ability of cancer cells to specifically home and bind to endothelial cells in bone (Kwakwa &amp; Sterling, 
 <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). This targeting bone function of integrin was exploited to engineer a programmable-bioinspired NPs (P-BiNP) to target bone and increase uptake in homotypic tumor cells (Gdowski et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Researchers employed chemokine factor motif chemokine ligand 12 (CXCL12) to stimulate cancer cells to express more integrin, and purified cancer cell membranes to carry PLGA NPs. 
 <italic>In vivo</italic> bone homing experiment, P-BiNP had an increased affinity to the bone and decreased affinity to other organs compared to the BiNPs (Gdowski et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). On the other hand, integrin αVβ3 can be a target and recognized by tripeptide Arg − Gly − Asp (RGD) and quinolone nonpeptide specifically (Wang, Cai, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0126" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Michael H. Ross et al. used quinolone nonpeptide to decorate phospholipid/polysorbate-80 micelle NPs which loaded DOX and demonstrated a stronger accumulation in bone metastases than nontargeted NPs through immunofluorescent analysis 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> (Ross et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0098" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Well-design and mature technology are required for linking two kinds of ligands to nanocarriers. And whether dual-targeted systems could have better biodistribution still needs to be experimented.
</p>
