<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060" class="p">
 <italic class="italic">N. sativa</italic> as a medicinal plant is well-known for its potent anti-oxidative effects.
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">33</sup>
 </xref> It has been reported that 
 <italic class="italic">N. sativa</italic> have protective effects on the renal damage.
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">34</sup>
 </xref>
 <italic class="italic">N. sativa</italic> seeds could significantly ameliorate the spatial cognitive deficits caused by chronic cerebral hypo perfusion in rats.
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">35</sup>
 </xref> Furthermore, 
 <italic class="italic">N. sativa</italic> improved scopolamine – induced learning and memory impairment as well as reduced the AChE activity and oxidative stress of the rats brain.
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">36</sup>
 </xref> Antioxidant effects of 
 <italic class="italic">N. sativa</italic> oil on the patients with rheumatoid arthritis (RA) showed 
 <italic class="italic">N. Sativa</italic> reduced the serum level of IL-10, MDA and NO. 
 <italic class="italic">N. sativa</italic> also improved inflammatory responses and reduced oxidative stress in patients with RA.
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">37</sup>
 </xref> In the other clinical trial, 40 healthy volunteers were divided into the treatment with capsules of 
 <italic class="italic">N. sativa</italic> (500 mg) and placebo (500 mg) twice daily for 9 weeks. 
 <italic class="italic">N. sativa</italic> enhanced memory, attention and cognition compared to the placebo group.
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">38</sup>
 </xref>
 <italic class="italic">N. sativa</italic> (500 mg) also decrease anxiety, to stabilize mood and to modulate cognition in the human model after 4 weeks.
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">39</sup>
 </xref> Neuroprotective effects of 
 <italic class="italic">N.</italic> sativa and thymoquinone (TQ) (its major components) on various nervous system disorders such as Alzheimer disease, epilepsy and neurotoxicity have been reviewed.
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">40</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
