<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CCl
 <sub>4</sub> brings an increase in plasma glucose levels in rats treated with CCl
 <sub>4</sub> alone in comparison with the normal control group. This elevation may be due to the destruction of liver cells or disruption of glycogen storage due to the degradation of glycogen to glucose in hepatocytes after treatment with CCl
 <sub>4</sub>, which leads to increased plasma glucose concentration [
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. However, rats treated with AECe + CCl
 <sub>4</sub> showed a significant reduction in plasma glucose concentration in comparison with the CCl
 <sub>4</sub>-treated group. In our investigation, AECe could enhance insulin secretion and stimulate the storage of glucose by the peripheral glucose uptake [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. For the lipid profile, the serum levels of triglyceride and VLDL-c showed remarkable increases in CCl
 <sub>4</sub>-treated rats. Previous studies have indicated that increased VLDL is the result of disturbance of lipid metabolism induced by CCl
 <sub>4</sub> intoxication. Triglycerides accumulation in the cytoplasm of hepatocytes leads to hepatic steatosis [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. However, treatment with AECe corrected this elevation. This effect indicates that the extract improved metabolic function by restoring serum triglycerides (TG) and VLDL levels to normal values compared to the CCl
 <sub>4</sub>-treated group. The other lesion of hepatic injury was hepatomegaly. While liver index was an objective indicator to reflect hepatomegaly, eliminating individual variation led to the difference of liver weights. In the present study, the liver index significantly enlarged in the CCl
 <sub>4</sub>-treated group, which indicated that CCl
 <sub>4</sub> caused the hepatic damage and hepatomegaly. However, the treatment with AECe (250 mg/kg) restored the liver weight and the liver index to the condition almost like in the normal group. On the other hand, the study revealed that the biochemical parameters of the kidney did not show any variation (not significant) when compared to the normal control group. These results showed that CE has a significant hepatoprotective effect against carbon tetrachloride (CCl
 <sub>4</sub>). Free-radical production plays a key role in the mechanism pathway of CCl
 <sub>4</sub>-induced acute liver injury. Hence, the scavenging of free radicals is one of the major antioxidation mechanisms to inhibit the hepatotoxicity of CCl
 <sub>4</sub> and reduce liver damage [
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The characteristic phytochemical constituents in Caralluma species are glycosides, flavone glycoside, triterpenoids, flavonoids, tannins, alkaloids, and saponins. The phytoconstituents such as flavonoids, glycosides, triterpenoids, alkaloids, and saponins are known to possess hepatoprotective activity. Flavonoids have been known for their antioxidant and antiperoxidant properties leading to hepatoprotective activities [
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Consequently, we suggest that the hepatoprotective activity of CE may be due to the presence of some of these components and/or other phytochemical compounds. However, further studies are required before we could conclude on the exact mechanism(s) involved in the hepatoprotective activity of the CE, and phytochemical studies are needed to isolate active compounds responsible for this activity.
</p>
