<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Material and Methods</div>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The commercial samples of whole unpearled (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 1) and pearled (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 1) quinoa seed, whole lupin seed (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 2), rapeseed press cake (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 2), dehulled buckwheat seed (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 3), buckwheat bran (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 1), whole faba bean (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 3), hulled and grinded faba bean (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 1), whole flaxseed (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 3), whole oil hemp seed (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 4), and hulls of oil hemp (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 3) were purchased from local grocery stores or directly from farmers/producers. The sample size varied 500-1000 g. Pearled quinoa seeds were pre-processed by the farmer using abrasive milling (i.e. pearling) to remove the saponin-rich outer layer of the seed. Buckwheat samples were dehulled and rapeseed press cakes were produced from cold-pressing processes by the manufacturers. All unmilled or coarse samples were milled before analyses using a KT-120 hammer mill with a ø1mm sieve (Koneteollisuus Oy, Klaukkala, Finland). All milled samples were stored in a freezer at −20 °C before being analyzed.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Luke laboratories (T024) comply with standard EN ISO/IEC 17025 and are accredited by the FINAS Finnish Accreditation Service (Helsinki, Finland). All methods except fiber are accredited.</p>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The moisture content was determined by drying the samples at 105 °C overnight (17 h).</p>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The nitrogen contents were determined with an in-house Kjeldahl method using a Kjeltec TM8400 analyzer according to the Association of Official Analytical Chemists (AOAC) method 2001.11.</p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The total fat content was determined using the SoxCap TM 2047 in combination with the Soxtec TM 2050 extraction system with a preparatory acid hydrolysis step and diethyl ether extraction (Foss A/B, Hillerød, Denmark) according to ISO 6492. (Animal feeding stuffs – Determination of fat content. 2011).</p>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The total carbohydrates content was calculated with the following formula: total carbohydrates (% FW) = 100 − moisture (%) − protein content (%FW) − crude fat (%FW) − ash (%FW). The results show total carbohydrates as g/100 g FW.</p>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ash content was measured by burning the samples at 500 °C overnight (17 h).</p>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The energy content was calculated with the following factors: protein 4 kcal/g, fat 9 kcal/g, and carbohydrates 4 kcal/g.</p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis of AA tot (peptide bound and free) was done according to the Community methods of analysis for the determination of amino acids, crude oils and fats, and olaquindox in feeding stuffs and amending Directive 71/393/EEC [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>]. AA tot was determinated by MassTrak UPLC (Waters, Milford, USA), using the UPLC Amino Acid Analysis Solution® application.
  </p>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PER on the basis of interactions between leucine - tyrosine was calculated using the modified regression equations as described by Alsmeyer et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. PER = −0.468 + 0.454 leucine – 0.105 tyrosine where leucine and tyrosine are concentrations of these AA expressed in g/16 gN.
  </p>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sugars (fructose, glucose, maltose, raffinose, lactose and sucrose) were determined according to the method of the Nordic Committee on Food Analysis (No 148/1993) by HPLC-RI. The analytical column used was Luna NH2 150 mm*3 mm, particle size 5 μm (Phenomenex, Torrance, CA) and acetonitrile-water (75:25) was used as a mobile phase.</p>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Total, soluble and insoluble dietary fiber was determined according to AOAC official method 991.43. Total, soluble, and insoluble dietary fiber in foods.</p>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mineral and trace elements were determined by ICP-OES and cadmium by ETAAS method. For the elemental composition, samples were digested in concentrated nitric acid in a block digestor (Tecator Dig40AUTO with scrubber).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical Analyses</div>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All analyses were performed at least duplicated or triplicated. The results of the samples obtained from various sample suppliers are expressed as means and SD. One-way analysis of variance was fitted to the data. LSD was calculated for pairwise comparisons. If the difference between two samples is higher than LSD, the difference is statistically significant at 5% level. Because of imbalance of sample sizes, LSD will vary between comparisons. Median LSD was reported (=typically LSD for comparison where sample with 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 1 was compared to sample where 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 3). SAS 9.3. was used to fit the model (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, USA).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
