<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High animal protein intake has been linked to increased risk of type 2 diabetes, cardiovascular disease, colorectal cancer and early deaths, whereas plant proteins have shown significant protective effects [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>]. A major source of gas emissions is ruminant-based animal production. It has been estimated that in the European Union, the livestock sector accounts for between 12 and 61% of the total anthropogenic greenhouse gas emissions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. There is therefore an urgent need to shift towards a more plant-based diet, for both environmental and public health reasons.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Faba bean (
  <span class="italic">Vicia faba</span>), lupin (
  <span class="italic">Lupinus angustifolius</span>), rapeseed (
  <span class="italic">Brassica rapa/napus</span> subsp. 
  <span class="italic">Oleifera</span>), flaxseed (
  <span class="italic">Linum usitatissimum</span>), oil hemp (
  <span class="italic">Cannabis sativa</span>), buckwheat (
  <span class="italic">Fagopyrum esculentum</span>), and quinoa (
  <span class="italic">Chenopodium quinoa</span>) may offer good alternatives to soybean, and contribute to enhancing diversity as well as the environmental and economic sustainability of local agricultural production. They are also a rich source of energy, fiber, high quality protein, macro- and micronutrients, as are good sources of bioactive non-nutrient compounds [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From a nutritional point of view, the most important aspects of a protein source are its AA and EAA content, composition and digestibility. As mentioned above, plant protein sources can also offer other nutrients and bioactive compounds.</p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is still insufficient knowledge of the compositional data of faba bean, lupin, rapeseed press cake, flaxseed, oil hemp, buckwheat, and quinoa, as well as the effect of processing. The goal of the present study was to determine the various nutrients in the commercial products of these crops.</p>
</sec>
