<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several studies have reported in vitro activities of essential oils and plant extracts against fungal and bacterial plant pathogens [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. However, few have focused on in vivo activities of essential oils against seedborne fungi [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, with many pathogens managed using fungicides, some of them have developed resistance to various fungicides that were previously very effective [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. 
 <italic>Stagonosporopsis</italic> spp. are devastating fungal pathogens of cucurbits and can lead to severe yield losses. These pathogens are major seedborne fungi of pumpkin and the dominant fungal cause of pumpkin seedling gummy stem blight [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. No commercial cultivars with resistance to gummy stem blight are available, and so this disease has been frequently managed by fungicides application. As a result, several fungicides have lost their effectiveness against this disease following the development of resistance by 
 <italic>S. cucurbitacearum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-26-02354" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Therefore, the development of alternative strategies to the use of synthetic fungicides for seed treatments is essential for both integrated pest management and organic agriculture. 
</p>
