<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Cancer is a group of diseases that endanger human life and currently it has become the first leading cause of death in the world. There were an estimated 14.1 million new cases of cancer and 8.2 million deaths from cancer in 2012 [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-22-01391" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Cancer cells have characteristics of uncontrolled growth and invasion, thus effective inhibition of cancer proliferation is a method for cancer therapy [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-22-01391" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Chemoprevention is the hot spot and the leading edge of cancer prevention. It is a method to prevent or slow the development of cancer by using chemical or biological substances, thereby reducing the incidence and mortality of cancer [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-22-01391" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Previous studies have revealed that oxidative stress played a key role in the etiology of a wide array of human diseases, including cancer [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-22-01391" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Natural or synthetic antioxidants have been studied with respect to their protective effect against free radical damage that may be the cause of cancer. Natural products, such as paclitaxel, camptothecin, vinblastine, and matrine, have been used as chemoprophylactic drugs and proved to be effective in the treatment of cancer [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-22-01391" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-22-01391" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-22-01391" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. So far, the anticancer activities of essential oils from extraction of plants have attracted much interest. Essential oils are a diverse group of natural products that are composed of terpene hydrocarbons, alcohols, aldehydes, ketones, and esters [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-22-01391" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-22-01391" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Monoterpenes are the major components of essential oils in the extracts from many plants.
</p>
