<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Samples of milk (250 mL) were collected on days 0, 28, and 84 of the trial period for the determination of selenium and vitamin E concentrations. After collection, the samples were sent to the Laboratory of Minerals of the Faculty of Animal Science and Food Engineering of the University of São Paulo, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine/USP and stored in a freezer at −20 °C in black plastic bags to protect them from light for subsequent analyses. For the analysis of selenium, wet digestion was performed with a nitric-perchloric mixture of samples, and subsequent reading by fluorometric analysis was performed according to sensitization by diaminonaphthalene [
 <xref rid="B10-nutrients-11-01218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. For the determination of the values of vitamin E, milk samples were prepared for analysis by means of high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC). Vitamin E was determined by liquid chromatography according to the methods of Liu et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-nutrients-11-01218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. One gram of whey of milk was weighed into a test tube with 7.3 mL of the saponification solution (11% 
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic> KOH, 45% 
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic> H 2 O, 55% 
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic> ETOH and 0.25 g Vitamin C/sample). The samples were vortexed and the tubes were capped before being heated in a 78 °C water bath for 7 min. The samples were then vortexed again and placed in the water bath for an additional 7 min. For extraction, the samples were vortexed again and cooled in cold water. Four milliliters of isooctane was added to each sample, and after being capped with stoppers, the tubes were vortexed for 2 min to extract vitamin E. The tubes were rested to separate the isooctane from the water, which was transferred to a vial for HPLC and stored at room temperature until the samples were analyzed with HPLC. Calculations were performed using the following formula: LV (ppm) = μg/mL isooctane × 4 mL/g of blood/milk. Blood collections from children used syringes with volumes of 10 mL, held also at 0, 28, and 84 days. Samples were centrifuged at 2000× 
 <italic class="italic">g</italic> for 15 min. For the analysis of glucose, total cholesterol, triglycerides, high density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol, low density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol, urea, and creatinine, Laborlab commercial kits (Laborlab
 <sup class="sup">®</sup>, Guarulhos, São Paulo, Brazil) were used with a Jaffe
 <sup class="sup">®</sup> automatic analyzer. Erythrograms and hemograms were determined using a Scatter Laser
 <sup class="sup">®</sup> analyzer.
</p>
