<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Celastrol (
 <bold>81</bold>) is a triterpene isolated from the plant family Celastraceae and these plants have been used in traditional Chinese medicine for their anti-inflammatory property [
 <xref rid="B250-antioxidants-09-01191" ref-type="bibr">250</xref>]. Yu et al. investigated the ability of celastrol (
 <bold>81</bold>) to attenuate hypertension-induced inflammation and oxidative stress in VSMCs via HO-1 induction [
 <xref rid="B251-antioxidants-09-01191" ref-type="bibr">251</xref>]. The celastrol-mediated HO-1 expression may reduce HIV-1 Tat-induced neuroinflammatory responses [
 <xref rid="B252-antioxidants-09-01191" ref-type="bibr">252</xref>], HCV replication [
 <xref rid="B253-antioxidants-09-01191" ref-type="bibr">253</xref>] and macrophage M1 polarization [
 <xref rid="B254-antioxidants-09-01191" ref-type="bibr">254</xref>]. Jeong et al. discovered an anti-inflammatory phytochemical, an ursane-type triterpene, 23-hydroxyursolic acid (
 <bold>82</bold>, 3β, 23-dihydroxyurs-12-en-28-oic acid) from flowered fruit-spike of 
 <italic>Prunella vulgaris</italic>, which increased the expression of HO-1 in a dose-dependent manner in human liver-derived HepG2 cells [
 <xref rid="B255-antioxidants-09-01191" ref-type="bibr">255</xref>]. Another ursane-type triterpene from 
 <italic>Cucurbita pepo</italic> was also found as an inducer of HO-1 expression [
 <xref rid="B256-antioxidants-09-01191" ref-type="bibr">256</xref>]. The fruiting bodies of 
 <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> (commonly known as the Reishi mushroom) are widely used in China, Japan and Korea as a valuable crude drug, especially in the treatment of chronic hepatitis, nephritis, hepatopathy, neurasthenia, arthritis, bronchitis, asthma, gastric ulcer and insomnia [
 <xref rid="B257-antioxidants-09-01191" ref-type="bibr">257</xref>]. Lanostane-type (tetracyclic) triterpenes were identified as phytochemicals responsible for the anti-inflammatory activity inducing HO-1 expression [
 <xref rid="B258-antioxidants-09-01191" ref-type="bibr">258</xref>]. Glycyrrhizin (
 <bold>83</bold>) is a triterpene glycoside, which is responsible for sweet taste and pharmacological activity of 
 <italic>Glycyrrhiza glabra</italic> (licorice) [
 <xref rid="B259-antioxidants-09-01191" ref-type="bibr">259</xref>]. Kim et al. proposed that glycyrrhizin (
 <bold>83</bold>) reduces high mobility group box 1 (HMGB1) secretion by p38/Nrf2-dependent induction of HO-1, which may prevent sepsis [
 <xref rid="B259-antioxidants-09-01191" ref-type="bibr">259</xref>]. Mou et al. demonstrate that glycyrrhizin (
 <bold>83</bold>) protects human melanocytes from H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative damage via the Nrf2-dependent induction of HO-1, providing evidence for the application of glycyrrhizin (
 <bold>83</bold>) in the treatment of vitiligo [
 <xref rid="B260-antioxidants-09-01191" ref-type="bibr">260</xref>]. Another triterpene glycoside chiisanoside (
 <bold>84</bold>) isolated from 
 <italic>Acanthopanax sessiliflorus</italic> showed a hepatoprotective effect via an antioxidative effect and inflammatory suppression in NF-κB and activation of Nrf2/HO-1 signaling [
 <xref rid="B261-antioxidants-09-01191" ref-type="bibr">261</xref>]. Structures of the triterpenes (
 <bold>81</bold>–
 <bold>84</bold>) are presented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="antioxidants-09-01191-f014">Figure 14</xref>.
</p>
