<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29" class="p">The dose-mortality response bioassays of EOs were carried out against adult female 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. aegypti</italic>, MCM-S and PMD-R strains, by using the topical application method modified from the standard protocol of WHO susceptibility test [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>]. The EO of each plant was diluted serially in a suitable solvent such as ethanol or acetone in order to prepare a graded series of 4–6 concentrations. The mosquitoes were weighed individually after being anaesthetized with carbon dioxide (CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>). The anaesthetized mosquitoes were subsequently kept immobile over dry filter paper on a custom cold plate standing under a stereomicroscope for preventing reanimation during manipulations. For each treatment, a 0.1 μl volume of EO solution was applied to the upper part of the female’s pronotum by using a handheld Hamilton microdispenser (700 series Microliter™, Hamilton Company, Reno, NE, USA). A group of 25 individual females was treated at each concentration, with at least 4 different concentrations covering the range of mortality from 10 to 95%. The solvent-treated mosquitoes served as the control group. In order to prevent contamination among the test samples, the filter paper was replaced with a new one for each EO tested. The dosages used in these bioassays were expressed in μg of EO per mg of body weight of a live female. The adulticidal activity of PBO, which was used in a synergism experiment as the positive control, was also evaluated in a manner similar to that for the EOs. The treated mosquitoes in all the groups were transferred into plastic cups and provided with 10% sucrose plus 10% multivitamin syrup. All bioassays were carried out at 25 ± 2 °C and 80 ± 10% RH, and replicated four times together with the control. Mortality at a 24 h holding period was checked and confirmed by the lack of mosquito response to mechanical stimuli, and then reported from the average of four replicates. Four experimental treatments were repeated for each test sample by using different batches of mosquitoes. The results obtained were pooled for calculating the mortality percentages used in the determination of 24 h lethal dosages by the Probit analysis.
</p>
