<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, MPE was found to be effective in inhibiting the growth of 
 <italic>F. sporotrichioides</italic>. In MPE rich in menthol, l-menthone, pulegone, piperitone, caryophyllene, and menthol acetate, these are the major compounds which are reported in many articles.[
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>
 <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] In addition, δ-cadinene, copaene, eugenol, methyl pivalate, menthomenthene, thujopsene, caryophyllene oxide also some of the compound identified in MPE and demonstrated antifungal activity and antibacterial activity.[
 <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>
 <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>
 <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>
 <xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>
 <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>
 <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] Further, the anti-inflammatory, cytotoxic effects were reported by Sun 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 2014.[
 <xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] The MIC values of MPE obtained in this study were 500 µg/mL and 1000 µg/mL at this particular concentration; the fungal growth was minimum as compared to untreated fungal cells. The potential mechanisms of volatile compounds as reported could damage the cell and disturb the cellular metabolism.[
 <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] The previous report concluded that volatile compounds act as H 
 <sup>+</sup> carriers and depletion of adenosine triphosphate takes place and disturb the cellular membrane, by reacting with the active sites of cellular enzymes.[
 <xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>
 <xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] The present study clearly demonstrates that the antifungal activity of MPE supported by SEM images of MPE showing morphological changes in the fungal hyphae due to the leakage of ions, leakage of molecular substances, and lesions as well as discrepancies in cell metabolism.
</p>
