<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0105">Apoptosis induction in cancer cells has been documented as a major mode of cellular death provoked by cytotoxic drugs including botanicals and phytochemicals [
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In the present study, it was found that ASL induced apoptosis in CCRF-CEM cells and provoked cycle arrest in the G0/G1 phase (
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>) and this was later confirmed by the annexin V/PI results (
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). ASL did not activate neither intrinsic caspase 3/7 and 9 nor the extrinsic caspase 8 (
 <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>), suggesting a poor involvement of intrinsic and extrinsic pathways in the apoptotic process induced by this botanical. The increase production of ROS has also been reported in the apoptotic process induced by various botanicals and phytochemicals in cancer cells [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Treatment of CCRF-CEM cells with the crude extract, ASL, led to important increased in ROS level (
 <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>). This suggests that ROS production contributes to ASL-induced cell death. Finally, the present study shows that ASL extract induces apoptosis and increases the production of ROS, which is closely related to apoptosis, but is not caspase-dependent. Such phenomenon have peviously been identified for several botanicals [
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Caspase-independent pathways have also been reported in cadmium-induced apoptosis renal in proximal tubule (RPT) cells [
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]; In effect, caspase-independent apoptotic pathway, known as the apoptosis-inducing factor (AIF)/Endo G pathway has earlier been discussed. Caspase-independent apoptosis is activated by Bcl-2/adenovirus E1B 19-kDa interacting protein 3 (BNIP-3), which induces mitochondrial AIF release; Endo G acts as a modulator. Forced BNIP-3 expression by plasmid transfection results in mitochondrial Endo G release and nuclear translocation, leading to cell death [
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].
</p>
