<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To determine the lipid concentration, the lipids were extracted by a rapid ultrasonication-microwave treatment described by Patel et al (2018) with minor modifications. Briefly, 50 mL of culture broth were transferred to Teflon-capped Pyrex tubes (16 × 100 mm), centrifuged at 10,000 rpm for 10 min and the supernatant was discarded. The pellet was washed several times with distilled water to remove the media components. The cells were then dried in an oven at 55 °C and mixed with 10 mL of chloroform: methanol (2:1; 
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>), then sonicated at 40 Hz for 2 min followed by microwave treatment for 2 min at 800 W. The slurry was stirred for 30 min and filtered through a sintered glass funnel, followed by the addition of 5 mL 0.034% MgCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and centrifugation at 3000 rpm for 5 min. The upper aqueous layer was aspirated, and the bottom chloroform layer was transferred to a new screw cap test tube. The concentration of the lipids was then determined gravimetrically after solvent evaporation and expressed as gram per liter (g/L). The extracted lipids were analyzed for their lipid components by thin layer chromatography (TLC) with a protocol described by Patel et al (2018) [
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>] and transesterified into fatty acid methyl esters by using acid catalysts as reported in the protocol of Laurens et al. (2012) [
 <xref rid="B59-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. The composition of fatty acids was analyzed by GC-FID (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA) equipped with the capillary column (Select FAME; dimensions 50 m × 0.25 mm ID and 0.25 μm film thickness). The biodiesel properties of the corresponding FAMEs were analyzed with the help of derived empirical formulas as described before [
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>].
</p>
