<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0215" class="p">Langmuir-Blodgett deposition technique is very simple but very powerful tool towards formation of nano dimensional ultrathin films with desired properties/architectures. Here each film is built from multiple monolayers. Accordingly the thickness and molecular arrangement is controllable at the molecular level. Using LB technique, it is possible to create complex yet precise artificial molecular arrays with predesigned physical and chemical properties. Already the potential of this versatile technique has been tested towards realization of optoelectronic devices. However, LB films have yet to be utilized in today's commercial products. The technique is still expected to be a vital part of future fabrication methods in molecular electronics. Unique dynamic nature of LB technique where Langmuir monolayer (typically one molecule thick) with large lateral dimension (2D) and molecular level control give us an opportunity for macroscopic action at molecular scale. This technique has the potential to build functional molecular system in a controlled manner at air-water interface and onto solid support, where they can be manipulated electrically or optically. This will open a new door to design solid state artificial molecular machines and devices 
 <xref rid="bib183" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[183]</xref>. Therefore, when molecular electronic and bio-electronic devices will become available, LB films will definitely play a vital role in their realization. However, commercial application of LB film is still lacking. Although extensive research work on various aspects of LB films are going on. Therefore main challenge to the researchers is demonstration of the commercial use of LB films. This need multidisciplinary outlook and collaborative efforts from almost all branches of science ranging from basic science to engineering Therefore it is highly appropriate to make a great stride in these important and promising areas of research, which can provide a conceptual understanding with wide opportunity of technological applications.
</p>
