<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One Biosecurity provides a unified framework to address the many biosecurity risks that transcend the traditional boundaries of animal health, plant health, human health, and the environment (
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). There are many examples where an alien species has impacts across multiple sectors including the environment and human health. The raccoon dog (
 <italic>Nyctereutes procyonoides</italic>) originates in the Far East but is now a widespread invasive canid species in Northern, Eastern, and Central Europe, where it not only competes successfully with native predatory mammals but is also a vector of wildlife, livestock, and human diseases [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Similarly, the wild boar (
 <italic>Sus scrofa</italic>) has been introduced to the Americas and Oceania where it destroys crops, is associated with declines in threatened and endangered species, and contributes to the transmission of a wide variety of parasites, viruses, and bacteria that can infect humans and domestic livestock [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Cross-sectorial impacts are not limited to vertebrates, invertebrates can also have impacts across human and livestock health. The giant African snail (
 <italic>Achatina fulica</italic>) has been introduced widely throughout the tropics where its feeding leads to considerable crop losses which are exacerbated by its role as a vector of plant pathogens (
 <italic>Phytophthora</italic> spp.), it outcompetes native gastropods and is also an intermediate host playing a role in the transmission of 
 <italic>Angiostrongulus</italic> spp. the causative agents of eosinophilic meningoencephalitis in livestock and humans [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Invasive alien vectors of disease can also have wider impacts. The Asian tiger mosquito (
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>) is able to transmit at least 22 arboviruses to wild and domesticated animals as well as humans and thus can impact the population viability of wildlife as well as facilitate the spread of zoonotic diseases, such as Rift Valley virus from livestock to people [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. However, while the role that invasive alien plants, invertebrates and vertebrates play in human health has become increasingly recognised [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C39" ref-type="bibr">39–41</xref>], with the exception of alien mosquitoes, current understanding of the role of alien species in the transmission of zoonotic diseases between livestock and humans remains limited.
</p>
