<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Though superhydrophobic 3D PMs have certain advantages (e.g., large adsorption capacity, high efficiency, recyclable) in oil/water separation from oceans, rivers and lakes, oil easily adheres to the skeleton leading to surface contamination, reduction of hydrophobicity and even loss oil/water separation property [
 <xref rid="B197-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">197</xref>]. Superhydrophilic-underwater superoleophobic 3D porous materials were developed to overcome oil adhesion by the formed density water film. Oil was prevented to contact with the 3D PMs by the water film thereby keeping the surface clean [
 <xref rid="B198-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">198</xref>,
 <xref rid="B199-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">199</xref>]. Moreover, the multi-level interactive three-dimensional porous structures show high efficiency in separating stratified oil/water mixture and oil-in-water emulsion avoiding the secondary pollution which was caused by the utilization of demulsification surfactants. Lv et al. [
 <xref rid="B113-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>] dip-coated different amount of SiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> nanofibers onto melamine formaldehyde (PMF) sponge to adjust the pore size, resulting in the formation of hierarchical pore structures (such as major pores: 100~200 µm, nanoscrolls: 30 nm~2 µm). The obtained sponge with hierarchical pore structure shows highly efficiency (the oil rejection rate is around 99.46%) on demulsification of 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hexane emulsions. Superhydrophilicity-underwater superoleophobicity (OCA: 162.57°) of PMF composite sponge are tuned via the in-situ growth of hydroxide by depositing polydopamine (PDA) and polyethyleneimine (PEI). Water droplets quickly wet the sponge within 25 ms while the underwater oil contact angle (1,2-dichloroethane) is measured of 162.57°. The superhydrophilicity-underwater superoleophobicity enables the quick separation of light oil from water surface and oil from oil-in-water emulsions under gravity driven. However, the double-layered hydroxide (LDH) is positively charged which is not suitable for the separation of negatively charged emulsion due to the neutralization reaction between positive surfaces and negative liquid causing oil contamination and the reduction of flux, and the preparation process is complicated. To solve this problem, Wang et al. [
 <xref rid="B89-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>] mixed cellulose powder with pore-forming agent (Na
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>SO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>·10H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O) and then regenerated the fibers to fabricate superhydrophilic-underwater superoleophobic cellulose sponge via foaming and freeze drying. The cellulose sponge has excellent demulsification performances by gravity driven (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="polymers-11-00806-f014" class="xref">Figure 14</xref>a) and maintains high-flux (91 L m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> h
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) and separation efficiency (99.94%) after more than six cycles. The FTIR (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="polymers-11-00806-f014" class="xref">Figure 14</xref>b
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>) and UV-VIS analyses (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="polymers-11-00806-f014" class="xref">Figure 14</xref>b
 <sub class="sub">5</sub>) illustrate that the oil was removed completely after the emulsion passing through the sponge (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="polymers-11-00806-f014" class="xref">Figure 14</xref>b). Due to the strong hydrogen bonding affinity between water molecules and cellulose sponges, oil is replaced by the strong competitive adsorbed water showing excellent self-cleaning and anti-pollution ability when the oil-contaminated sponge was immersed into water (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="polymers-11-00806-f014" class="xref">Figure 14</xref>c).
</p>
