<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>GLs are a rich source of essential oils (
 <xref rid="foods-10-00752-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The major constituent of GL essential oil includes 1,8-cineole and 
 <italic>trans</italic>-caryophyllene [
 <xref rid="B27-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Chen et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] identified 50 compounds in GL essential oil using gas chromatography (GC) and gas chromatography/mass spectrometry (GC–MS), where they found β-caryophyllene, α-pinene, and 1,8-cineole to be the major ones. GL essential oil from the Philippines was found to contain a different profile, with limonene, α-pinene, β-caryophyllene, and longicyclene as major compounds [
 <xref rid="B28-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Ecuadorian GL essential oil contained a higher content of monoterpenes (limonene and α-pinene) whereas Tunisian guava leaf oil displayed a higher content of veridiflorol and 
 <italic>trans</italic>-caryophyllene [
 <xref rid="B29-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Soliman et al. [
 <xref rid="B31-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] reported a larger amount of monoterpenes, contrary to the other studies, where sesquiterpenes constituted the major compound in GL essential oil. El-Ahmady et al. [
 <xref rid="B32-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] reported 4 α-selin-7(11)-enol, α-selinene, β-caryophyllene, and β-caryophyllene oxide as the major constituents of GL essential oil. In another study, sixty-four different compounds were determined in essential oil extracted from GLs by gas chromatography–mass spectrometry (GC–MS). Among them, caryophyllene (24.97%) was found to be predominantly present, which acts as an antioxidant, anticancer, anti-inflammatory, and antimicrobial agent [
 <xref rid="B21-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. This study reported the concentration of non-oxygenated sesquiterpenes, oxygenated sesquiterpenes, and monoterpenes as 73.67, 12.94, and 8.55%, respectively.
</p>
