<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Qualitative tests were done for the leaves extract of 
 <italic>Acanthus polystachyus</italic> for the presence of phytoconstituents such as flavonoids, steroidal compounds, terpenes, alkaloids, saponins, tannins, and phenolic compounds, as described in a standard procedure. Test for alkaloids: extract (0.2 g) was dissolved in dilute hydrochloric acid. The solution was filtered and a few drops of Dragendroff’s reagent added. The treated solutions were observed for any precipitation. Similarly, to a portion of filtered solution, a few drops of Mayer’s reagent were added. The treated solutions were observed for any precipitation; test for flavonoids: five mL of ethyl acetate was added to a solution of 0.5 g of the extract in water. The mixture was shaken, allowed to settle and inspected for the production of yellow color in the organic layer which is taken as positive for free flavonoids; test for saponins: the hydro-alcoholic extract (0.5 g) was dissolved in 10 mL of distilled water in a test tube. The test tube was corked and shaken vigorously for about 30 sec. The test tube was allowed to stand vertically and observed over a 30-min period of time. If froth above the surface persists after 30 min the sample is suspected to contain saponins; test for tannins: a portion of the alcoholic extract was dissolved in water. The solution was clarified by filtration. 10% ferric chloride solution was added to the clear filtrate. This was observed for a change in color to bluish black; test for glycosides: 0.5 g of crude extracts was dissolved separately in 5 mL of methanol. 10 mL of 50% HCl was added to 2 mL of each extract in test tubes. The mixtures were heated in a boiling water bath for 30 min. 5 mL of Fehling’s solution was added and the mixtures were boiled for 5 min to give a brick red precipitate as an indication for the presence of glycosides; test for Phenols: 0.5 g of each of crude extracts were put in a different test tube and treated with a few drops of 2% of FeCl3; bluish green or black coloration were indicated the presence of phenols; test for steroids: 0.5 g of each crude extracts were dissolved in 5 mL of methanol. 1 mL of the extract was treated with 0.5 mL of acetic acid anhydride and cooled in ice. This mixed with 0.5 mL of chloroform and 1 mL of concentrated sulphuric acid was then added carefully by means of a pipette. At the separations level of the two liquids, reddish-brown rings were formed, as indication of the presence of steroids; test for terpenoids: 0.5 g of each crude powders were separately dissolved in 5 mL of methanol. 2 mL of the extract was treated with 1 mL of 2,4-dinitrophenyl hydrazine were dissolved in 100 mL of 2M HCl. Yellow-orange colorations were observed as an indication of Terpenoids; and test for anthraquinones: the extract of the plant material (equivalent to 100 mg) was shaken vigorously with 10 mL of benzene, filtered and 5 mL of 10% ammonia solution added to the filtrate. The mixture was shaken and observed for the presence of a pink, red or violet color in the ammonia (lower) phase that indicates the presence of free anthraquinones.
 <xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22–24</xref>
</p>
