<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Considering the literature reports, this leads us to the following question: What is the future of medicinal plants from Mexico, in the field of pain managment? To understand the problem with translational pain research in the field of Mexican plants and their derivates it is necessary to understand the multidisciplinary factors that historically have not allowed traditional medicine to cross from preclinical to clinical research [
 <xref rid="B207-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">207</xref>]. Thus, it is important highlight the fact that most of the studies listed in our review lack description of the mechanisms of action underlying these plants’ antinociceptive effects, as well as lacking toxicological tests or assays related to these plants’ side effects (
 <xref rid="plants-10-00865-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Relatedly, less than half of the studies attributed the plants’ antinociceptive effects to bio-compounds present in the plant, which suggests that most of the studies of the plants used extracts developed using methanol, ethanol, chloroform or other chemicals. Some of these extracts are not candidates for research addressed toward clinical studies. Several studies were performed with commercial compounds and were not necessarily isolated from the medicinal plant studied. Thus the characterization of the phytochemical composition of these plants is urgent, along with the linking of the plants’ effects to these compounds. The development of a commercial product for human use is based on standardized extracts, but it is important to understand their composition in order to define a marker compound for quality control. On the other hand, preclinical assays of Mexican plants and their antinociceptive properties mostly evaluated these plants using the formalin test, carrageenan-induced paw edema, acid acetic-induced writhing and thermal nociception tests, whereas only six studies focused on neuropathy models (
 <xref rid="plants-10-00865-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). We consider that these points must be resolved in order to advance the study of pain treatment using Mexican medicinal plants. Finally, in agreement with other authors, we suggest the adoption of new models to evaluate inflammatory and neuropathic pain conditions, to provide effective and predictive behavioral animal models for future clinical trials [
 <xref rid="B208-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">208</xref>,
 <xref rid="B209-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">209</xref>].
</p>
