<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="order">
 <list-item>
  <p>Dissolve hydrazide and aldehyde functionalized polymers separately in 10 mM phosphate buffered saline (PBS), or any desired aqueous buffer, to create solutions of desired concentrations. Note: Mass concentrations between 5-40 wt% are typically used, with gelation at lower concentrations possible if higher functional group fractions are present on the polymers.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Using a single barrel syringe to transfer the solutions, load each precursor solution (~1 mL each) into separate barrels of a double barrel syringe (2.5 mL volume, 1:1 ratio syringe) attached to a static mixer (1.5" length) and (optionally) a syringe (typically 18 G, 1.5” length for in vitro studies) and (optionally) a syringe (typically 18 G, 1.5” length for in vitro studies).</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Prepare molds of desired thickness, shape, and diameter by punching holes into a silicone rubber sheet. Note: In a typical experiment, a standard punch set is used to punch a 7 mm diameter cylindrical hole inside a 1/16" thick silicone rubber sheet (total volume of reservoir ~300 µL).</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Mount the silicone mold on a standard glass microscope slide such that the holes punched in the mold are completely backed by glass.  A 0.1 M HCl wash of the glass is recommended but not required prior to mounting of the silicone mold.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Co-extrude the double barrel syringe contents through the static mixer to completely fill (or slightly overfill, with a meniscus at the top) the silicone mold. Note: Multiple samples can be prepared during one extrusion sample provided the gelation time is on the same order of magnitude or longer than the total time required to fill multiple molds.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Place another standard glass microscope slide on top of the mold and wait for the gelation to complete. Note: The standard recipes described in the synthesis section gel within &lt;1 minute; slower gelation times (and thus longer required wait times) are observed at lower functional group densities, lower polymer concentrations and/or higher fractions of OEGMA
   <sub>475</sub> relative to M(EO)
   <sub>2</sub>MA (for POEGMA hydrogels).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Remove the top microscope slide and use a spatula to push the hydrogel away from the silicone rubber mold.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Lift the mold from lower microscope slide to recover the hydrogels for further testing.</p>
 </list-item>
</list>
