<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The phagocyte NOX2 complex is a multicomponent enzyme composed of membrane-bound subunits (Nox2 protein and p22phox) and cytosolic subunits (p47phox, p67phox, and Rac) [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-23-01857" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. The Nox2 protein acts as the catalytic subunit of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-23-01857" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. NOX2 is highly expressed in phagocytes and in the RAW264.7 cells [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-23-01857" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-23-01857" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. The NOX2 in the phagocytes constitutes the primary source of ROS during an oxidative burst [
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-23-01857" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. The signal transduction and inflammatory response induced by LPS are related to the activity of NOX2 in a number of cells [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-23-01857" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-23-01857" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Previous results reported that LPS-induced superoxide formation and inflammatory are inhibited by silencing the Nox2 protein in human pulmonary microvascular endothelial cells [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-23-01857" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. In conjunction with our Nox2 protein silencing data, the NOX2-siRNA knockdown of the Nox2 protein inhibited not only the LPS-induced generation of ROS, but also its protective effect against oxidative stress-induced inflammation in the RAW264.7 cells. These results supported the role of Nox2-induced ROS production in LPS-mediated pro-inflammation expression. Therefore, the inhibition of ROS production using inhibitors against the NADPH oxidase is proposed as an alternative approach to conventional antioxidant therapies against inflammation. We examined the effect of OEO on the activation of NADPH oxidase in the RAW264.7 cells induced by LPS. The results showed that the OEO inhibited the ROS production in the RAW264.7 cells by reducing the NADPH oxidase activity. These data are consistent with previous observations that 
 <italic class="italic">Z. multiflora</italic> essential oil, thymol, and carvacrol (1–100 ng/mL) significantly reduce the NADPH oxidase activity in the LPS-stimulated murine macrophage cells [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-23-01857" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>].
</p>
