<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<notes id="NT1" class="notes">
 <title class="title">Notes</title>
 <p class="p">MP holds a new investigator salary award from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research and Fonds de recherche Québec-Santé. KS holds a Canada Research Chair in Nutritional Lipidomics and receives salary support from the Canada Research Chairs program. This work was supported (in part) by travel grants from the North American branch of the International Life Sciences Institute (ILSI NA). ILSI NA is a public, nonprofit foundation that provides a forum to advance understanding of scientific issues related to the nutritional quality and safety of the food supply by sponsoring research programs, educational seminars and workshops, and publications. It receives support primarily from its industry membership. ILSI NA had no role in the scope, drafting, review, or final approval of the manuscript. The opinions expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the views of ILSI.</p>
 <p class="p">Supplemental Tables 1–3 are available from the “Supplementary data” link in the online posting of the article and from the same link in the online table of contents at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/ajcn/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://academic.oup.com/ajcn/</ext-link>.
 </p>
 <p class="p">Abbreviations used: BHT, butylated hydroxytoluene; FAME, fatty acid methyl esters; FAQAP, fatty acid quality assurance program; FID, flame ionization detector; GC, gas chromatography; HUFA, highly unsaturated fatty acid (≥3 carbon-carbon double bonds); IS, internal standards; ITT, intent-to-treat; LC, liquid chromatography; MS, mass spectrometer; NEFA, nonesterified fatty acid; NIST, National Institute of Standards and Technology; PL, phospholipid; PP, per protocol; QC, quality control; RBC, red blood cell; RCT, randomized controlled trial; SRM, standard reference material; TG, triacylglycerol, also known as triglyceride; TL, total lipid.</p>
</notes>
