<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Organometallic mono-, di-, and tetranuclear 
 <italic>C^N^S</italic>-coordinated Pd(II) complexes based on the TSC scaffold were synthesized and studied for their antiplasmodial activity against CQS 3D7 and CQR K1 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> strains to ascertain the influence of coordination with palladium and the effects of having multiple metallic centres on the activity of the ligands [
 <xref rid="B88-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Tetranuclear complexes 
 <bold>85a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold> were assembled by coordination of previously tested antiplasmodial TSC ligands with potassium tetrachloropalladate(II), forming a product with a Pd
 <sub>4</sub>S
 <sub>4</sub> core due to the palladium-sulfur bridging bonds (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05276-f022">Figure 22</xref>). Cleavage of the Pd
 <sub>4</sub>S
 <sub>4</sub> bridges in these complexes with PPh
 <sub>3</sub> and diphosphino ligands yielded mono- and binuclear cyclopalladated complexes (
 <bold>86a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold> and 
 <bold>87</bold>), respectively. The biological assessment of the obtained compounds revealed that incorporation of the Pd(II) centre increased the inhibitory activity of the complexes as the tetranuclear (
 <bold>85a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold>) and mononuclear (
 <bold>86a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold>) compounds were more potent than their respective TSC ligands against CQS 3D7 and CQR K1 strains, with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values below 6 μM. The mononuclear complexes emerged as the most active in the study particularly against the sensitive strain, suggesting the presence of multiple Pd(II) centres had no marked effects on biological activity. Intriguingly, only the complexes containing the 1,1’-bis(diphenylphosphino)ferrocene linkage (
 <bold>87a</bold> and 
 <bold>88a</bold>) were active, while the non-ferrocenyl ethylene and benzene counterparts were inactive within the binuclear series. This highlights the beneficial pharmacological effects of ferrocene [
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>].
</p>
