<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Biogeography also explains a significant amount of variation in the relative richness of naturalized and invasive plants, with the island–mainland differentiation being by far the most important factor included in our analysis. However, the importance of explanatory variables differs between RRN and RRI, and also between mainland and island regions. Islands harbour disproportionally more alien plants with deleterious impacts on the environment and which ultimately pose a major threat to native species survival (
 <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Sax and Gaines 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">McGeoch 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>). Island floras are thus not only hotspots of anthropogenic mixing and subsequent homogenization of regional species pools (
 <xref rid="CIT0079" ref-type="bibr">Winter 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">Rosenblad and Sax 2017</xref>), but also hotspots of alien species with negative environmental impacts (i.e. invasive aliens). While it has been repeatedly shown that islands are more affected by naturalized species (e.g. 
 <xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">Vitousek 1988</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr">Vitousek 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 1997
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Lonsdale 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Kueffer 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref> for plants; 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Dyer 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2017
 </xref> for birds; 
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Capinha 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2017
 </xref> for amphibians and reptiles; 
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Dawson 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2017
 </xref> for several taxonomic groups) than mainland regions, the precise nature and extent of these differences on a global scale for vascular plants was unknown, nor had it been tested whether islands and mainland regions differ in invasive alien species richness. We find that, on average, islands harbour ~6-fold relative richness of naturalized species, and &gt;3-fold relative richness of invasive species compared to mainland regions. With more than a quarter of all islands in our analysis having accumulated more naturalized alien plant species than are native to the same island, we find that the magnitude of anthropogenic permanent additions to the regional species pool—and the relative richness of alien species with environmental impacts—have become pervasive for many islands.
</p>
