<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the herbivore exclosure experiment, native herbivores were shown to successfully limit the population expansion of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> as the exclosure treatment improved the aboveground performance (higher shoot biomass and total shoot length) of the plant. Studies have suggested that native herbivores have a significant and strong negative effect on the establishment and individual performance of invasive species; however, they can only effectively limit the spread of an introduced plant when its density is low
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">44</xref>. Herbivory pressure from native generalist herbivores is not sufficient to limit the spread of exotics after they cross a density threshold; therefore, native herbivores fail to completely repel exotic plants
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">44</xref>. The evolution of increased competitive ability hypothesis proposes that, in invaded ranges, invasive plants will reduce their protection against specialists but improve their growth and reproduction as well as increase their resistance and tolerance to generalist herbivores
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">45</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref>. Therefore, the effects of native generalist herbivores on invasive plants will be reduced. In contrast, Hull-Sanders and colleagues found that invasive plants lose their defence against generalist herbivores in invaded ranges
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">47</xref>. In our study, the herbivory pressure from native herbivores was considerable, and the defoliation of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> increased to 25%. Studies have found that native herbivores can successfully deter the invasion of exotic plants or weak invaders
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>, although for the pernicious invasive plant 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>, native generalist herbivores can also reduce the population performance and adverse effects of this species after its successful establishment.
</p>
