<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The dual culture assay showed that all forty-three endophytic fungi were inhibitory against one or more pathogens (
 <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp. (ND17), and 
 <italic>A. niger</italic> (ND15) exhibited a broad spectrum of activity for all six pathogens. 
 <italic>A. fumigatus</italic> isolates, GG13, ND02, and ND14, exhibited similar activity pattern against the same pathogens (
 <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Diversity data show that 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> genus attributed to 43%, followed by 
 <italic>Fusaria</italic> with 29%, then we have 14% 
 <italic>M. circinelloides</italic> and 
 <italic>Neurospora</italic> respectively. 
 <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> with 37%, followed by 
 <italic>Borytis cinerea</italic> 17%, then we had 
 <italic>Fusarium</italic> sp. at 14% and 
 <italic>F. graminearum</italic> with 10% was the least inhibited. 
 <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> represents the antifungal effect of the selected endophytic fungi using filtrate culture assay. From a total of forty-three (
 <italic>n</italic> = 43) tested endophytic fungi, 77% showed inhibition activity against one or more pathogens (
 <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Culture filtrates of the endophytic fungi DR08 exhibited a broad range of antifungal activity against all the pathogens. Least activity was displayed by DR04, DR18, DR14.1, and DR20. The greatest antifungal activity in dual culture was displayed by the isolate GG09, however, that was not the case in the culture filtrate where it showed almost no activity for pathogen 
 <italic>Fusarium</italic> 2929 while showing complete inhibition for 
 <italic>B. cinerea</italic> 10139 (D), 
 <italic>F. graminearum</italic> 12517 (E), and 
 <italic>Colletotrichum gleosporioides</italic> (F). Additionally, the results revealed that majority of the endophytic fungi extracts from the medicinal plant have partial antifungal activity. None of the isolates tested were able to control all six pathogenic fungi. From the diversity of the antifungal activity, 
 <italic>Fusaria</italic> was dominate with 32%, followed by 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> genus with 21% and 
 <italic>Alternaria</italic> with 11% (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1(A)</xref>). Endophytic fungi (DR08, 
 <italic>Fusarium</italic> sp.) showed the most activity followed 
 <italic>Fusarium</italic> sp. (DR24). 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp. (ND9) showed the least activity against the pathogens. Among all the six pathogens, 
 <italic>F. graminearum</italic> (G) and 
 <italic>Colletotrichum gleosporioides</italic> (H) were less resistant. 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp. which was isolated from maize was the most resistant pathogen. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1(B,C)</xref> illustrates the activity that occurred between the six pathogens and the filtrates tested against. 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> was the most resistant pathogen out of the six tested with 50% and 
 <italic>F graminearum</italic> was the most inhibited pathogen with 35%. From a total of forty-three (
 <italic>n</italic> = 43) tested endophytic fungi, all (100%) exhibited inhibitory activity against one or more pathogens using dual diffusion assay. 
 <italic>Fusarium</italic> and 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> were the dominate genus that showed significate antifungal effect. Seventy-seven (77%) displayed inhibition activity against one or more pathogens. Endophytic fungi (DR08, 
 <italic>Fusarium</italic> sp.) was the most effective and 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp. (ND9) was the least activity.
</p>
