<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Current global trend is moving toward a more sustainable, improved, safer and eco-friendly alternatives to the conventional resistant antimicrobial drugs on the market. Medicinal plants have shown to possess several biological activities that has tremendous health benefits. This set a tone in the investigation of significantly important microbial community that has a symbiotic interactions with plants [
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. 
 <italic>S. tortuosum</italic> L. commonly known as kougoed is a native medicinal plant that has been used in indigenous tribes for stress relief, depression, as a painkiller, alleviate hunger and overall mood-enhancer [
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Hence, 
 <italic>S. tortuosum</italic> L. was selected in the current study for the screening of endophytic fungi that exhibit antifungal activity against fungal pathogens. Fungal pathogens cause diseases that pose serious concern in the agricultural sector. Subsequently leading to pathogenic fungi infects agricultural crop resulting in considerable losses of yield and economic losses which will have an impact on the global crop prices. Recent fungicide used for agricultural commodities are posing more shortcomings such as causing cancer, toxicity, and resistant [
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Hence, more and more people are questioning the utilization of the current fungicide on the market and are looking for a more health benefit and eco-friendly approach. It was reported that approximately 12% of endophytic fungi have shown to exhibit antifungal activity against four plant fungal pathogens (
 <italic>B. cinerea, Sclerotinia sclerotiorum, Rhizoctonia solani</italic> and 
 <italic>F. oxysporum</italic>) using dual-culture method. In the same study, 
 <italic>Penicillium</italic> sp. and 
 <italic>A. oryzae</italic> demonstrated to be the most effective [
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In the current study, 100% of the endophytic fungi displayed inhibitory activity against one or more pathogens. 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> strains were dominate in the antifungal bioassay using dual method. 
 <italic>Fusaria</italic> genus was predominate followed by 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> genus. It is not surprising, 
 <italic>Fusaria</italic> genus are considered as an enormous group inhibiting plants, animals and humans as saprophytic, opportunistic and even symbiotic association [
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Several studies have demonstrated that endophytic fungi producing a wealth of bioactive compounds have the potential to be an outstanding antifungal agent and fungicide [
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11–13</xref>].
</p>
