<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Solid dispersion (SD) preparation process is relatively simple, which is one of the means to improve the dissolution and bioavailability of drugs. Commonly used carriers for solid dispersions include povidone (pvp) [
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>], cross-linked povidone (pvpp) [
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], and nano calcium carbonate [
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Some researchers chose PVPk30-Soluplus composite carrier to prepare oleanolic acid solid dispersion, which can obviously increase the dissolve and dissolution rate of this component and improve its dissolution effect [
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Gao et al. [
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>] developed the amorphous solid dispersions of OA (OA-PVP) by the hot-melt extrusion, which avoided the organic solvent use, so it was safe and green [
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. The evaluation in vitro and in vivo showed a remarkable improvement of OA-PVP compared with commercial tablet. Especially, pharmacokinetic analysis in rats showed that the bioavailability of OA-PVP was about 2.4 times that of OA tablets. As for instance, Wang et al. [
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] designed oleanolic acid-polyvinylpolypyrrolidone (OA-PVPP-SD) by a simple solvent evaporation method. Dissolution test showed that approximately 50%-75% of OA was dissolved from SDs within the first 10 min, which is about 10-15 times of free OA. In vivo pharmacokinetic studies showed that OA-PVPP-SD has a shorter 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>max</sub> (
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and an increased 
 <italic>C</italic>
 <sub>max</sub> (
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) compared to direct oral administration of OA, and its relative bioavailability is 183.07%. In summary, OA-SD made of composite carrier can significantly improve the OA dissolution rate in vitro, but the bioavailability needs further study.
</p>
