<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0145">Terpenes are structurally made when different isoprene units (5-carbon-base; C5) coupled together, they may have oxygen or not i.e. terpenoids and terpenes. The main classes of terpenoid are diterpenes (C20), hemiterpenes (C5), monoterpenes (C10), sesquiterpenes (C15), tetraterpenes (C40), triterpenes (C30). Essential oils are heterogenous mixtures of both terpenes and terpenoids in addition to other aromatic and straight chain constituents. They are mostly found in aromatic plants. Terpenes displayed several biological activities through synergistic and antagonistic ways (
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Aharoni et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Ntalli and Caboni, 2012</xref>). Ursolic acid (
 <bold>24</bold>), cadinene, caryophyllene (
 <bold>17</bold>), Stigmasterol (
 <bold>20</bold>), guaiene (
 <bold>22</bold>) and β-amyrin (
 <bold>23</bold>) are terpenes isolated and identified from 
 <italic>B. verticillata.</italic> Terpenes or aromatic plant species have been renowned to possess antinemic activity, many authors have reported that nematicidal activity is one of the activity displayed by this type of plant species beside antimicrobial effect (
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Ntalli et al., 2011</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Begum et al. (2008)</xref> isolated some pentacyclic triterpenoids from the aerial parts of 
 <italic>Lantana camara</italic>. They further confirmed that lantanolic acid, lantoic acid and pomolic acid displayed 100% mortality at 1 mg/ml concentration after a day of application and camarin, camarinin, ursolic (
 <bold>24)</bold> and lantacin acid exhibited 100% mortality at 1 mg/ml concentration after two days of application. The result was as the discovery of the conventional nematicide used “Furdan” (
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Begum et al., 2008</xref>). Some authors isolated three terpenoids from 
 <italic>Curtisia dentata</italic> extracts, betulinic acid lupeol and ursolic acid (
 <bold>24</bold>). These compounds were evaluated on 
 <italic>Haemonchus contortus, Trichostrongylus colubriformis</italic> and 
 <italic>C. elegans</italic>. Betulinic acid and Lupeol were active only on 
 <italic>Trichostrongylus colubriformis</italic> and 
 <italic>Haemonchus contortus</italic> but at high concentrations (200 and 1,000 μg/mL). All three compounds were active against 
 <italic>C. elegans</italic> with an LC50 of 2, 12 and 79 μg/mL, respectively (
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Shai et al., 2009</xref>). Iridoids are classes of organic compounds that belongs to terpenes groups, their antinemic activity is reported by numerous authors (
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">Sultana et al., 2013</xref>). Sweroside, an iridoid was isolated from methanol extract of 
 <italic>Alstonia scholaris</italic>, after the extract gave a significant antinemic activity against 
 <italic>M. incognito</italic>. This compound exerts good nematicidal activity as reported by the authors (
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">Sultana et al., 2013</xref>). This plant is interesting for further research.
</p>
