<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">An approximation of the secondary and tertiary structure of plant acyl-ACP thioesterases was first achieved through their homology to bacterial thioesterases, the structure of which was determined by XR diffraction (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lawson et al., 1994</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Li et al., 2000</xref>). These modeling studies showed these enzymes to have two Helix/4-Stranded Sheet hot dog fold domains in the N-terminal end that determined their specificity (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mayer and Shanklin, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Serrano-Vega et al., 2005</xref>), consistent with earlier biochemical studies (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Salas and Ohlrogge, 2002</xref>). Highly conserved catalytic amino acids were also present in the C-terminal domain of the protein. These models were applied to both the FatA and Fat B thioesterases, allowing amino acids involved in the enzyme-substrate interactions to be identified and making it possible to design thioesterase alleles with improved catalytic properties (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mayer and Shanklin, 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moreno-Pérez et al., 2014</xref>). More recent studies determined the crystal structure of FatB1 from 
 <italic class="italic">Umbellularia californica</italic> (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Feng et al., 2017</xref>), a thioesterase that specifically acts on C12 substrates. This thioesterase acts as a dimer, its monomers establishing two tandem hot dog folds that are joined by a flexible linker, one close to the C-terminal domain and other close to the N-terminal one. The N-terminal hot dog domain defines the substrate binding pocket, which can be engineered to change the substrate specificity of the enzyme (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Feng et al., 2018</xref>). This 
 <italic class="italic">Uc</italic>FatB1 is more closely related to other plant thioesterases than to any bacterial isoforms and thus, the structure of this enzyme is likely to be a better reference to model FatA and FatB2 enzymes.
</p>
