<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">To assess AM fungal abundance in roots of M+ plants, DNA was extracted from frozen roots (70–80 g per sample) by the glass milk method with the CTAB extraction buffer as described in Gryndler et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>
 </sup> with minor modifications (the samples were frozen in the CTAB buffer before homogenization, a wash buffer was applied twice, the samples were incubate 5 min in 65 °C during elution). An internal standard was added to the samples before DNA extraction to correct subsequent real-time PCR (qPCR) analyses for DNA loses upon extraction and for PCR inhibition
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>
 </sup>. To this end, 2 × 10
 <sup>10</sup> copies of the linearized plasmid carrying fragment of cassava mosaic virus DNA (GenBank accession number AJ427910) were used, and recovery after the extraction was quantified by qPCR. The DNA recovery rates of the internal standard for each individual DNA sample (15.2 ± 0.9 in this study) were used to correct the qPCR results obtained with the AM fungal taxa‐specific markers, as described in von Felten et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>
 </sup>. The qPCR was further used to assess abundance of the three AM fungal taxa in roots using taxon-specific primers and hydrolysis (TaqMan) probes targeting the nuclear large ribosomal subunit (nLSU) gene (
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>
 </sup>, Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>), HOT FIREPol Probe qPCR Mix Plus(ROX) chemistry (Solis BioDyne, Tartu, Estonia) and StepOnePlus qPCR Cycler (Applied Biosystems, now Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, Massachusetts). The DNA extracts were diluted 10 × before the qPCR. The reaction conditions and calculations followed Janoušková et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>
 </sup>. Only M+ samples were analyzed, two DNA extracts from M− pots were used as a negative control.
</p>
