<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Protein-based nanostructures are one of the most used systems to encapsulate different types of bioactive compounds (hydrophilic or lipophilic compounds with different molecular weight, solubility, etc.) [
 <xref rid="B5-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. These nano-systems present a high surface area which increases the possibility to uptake active compounds and improve their absorption and bioavailability [
 <xref rid="B85-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>]. Numerous works have been published indicating the influence of environmental conditions on protein-based nanostructures and evaluating the release profile of active compounds encapsulated in this type of system. An improvement of bioavailability and a controlled release of encapsulated compounds were observed when protein-based nanostructures were employed, which is an important step to create new solutions for delivery of bioactive compounds at a specific target. In addition, protein-based nanostructures allow some drawbacks related with other nanostructures to be overcome such as the production protocol and the low loading capacity. They can be produced in an isolated way (i.e., without the interference of the bioactive compounds) and designed to spontaneously load bioactive molecules through electrostatic, van der Waals, and/or hydrophobic interactions between the bioactive compounds and the polymer matrix, during the gel folding process. All these aspects contribute to the formation of stable nanostructures. Moreover, the ability of these nanostructures to produce a response (e.g., swelling) to environmental stimuli (e.g., temperature, pH, ionic strength, or enzymatic conditions) makes them very interesting systems to deliver bioactive compounds locally to specific sites and at a particular time in the GI tract, which allows the inherent instability of this complex route and the low permeability of the intestinal mucosa to be overcome [
 <xref rid="B86-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>]. On the other hand, these structures may present limitations, particularly if produced by physical gelation, as the nanohydrogels contain labile bonds in the polymer networks which are susceptible to being disrupted under physiological conditions in the GI tract [
 <xref rid="B34-gels-05-00009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. Protein-based nanostructures can be prepared from several proteins (whey proteins, zein, collagen) with different techniques, the gelation process being the most commonly used method. It is possible to find in the literature different works reporting the ability of protein nanohydrogels to incorporate and release hydrophilic and lipophilic bioactive compounds such as drugs, unsaturated fatty acids, vitamins, as well as peptides—see 
 <xref rid="gels-05-00009-t003" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>.
</p>
