<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The research team led by Kang [
 <xref rid="B76-molecules-25-04125" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>] found that thymol inhibits cell growth and induces apoptosis in gastric adenocarcinoma cells. The cytotoxic, dose-dependent thymol effect on tumor cells decreased their viability from 89.56 ± 0.84% to 50.75 ± 2.4% after 24 h of exposure to this monoterpene. It was observed that thymol induced significant morphological changes such as lower cell density, fragmentation of cell nuclei, and chromatin condensation. The use of thymol caused an increase in the number of cells in the sub-G1 phase, when the DNA is cleaved, which is a characteristic feature of apoptosis. Another mechanism of thymol cytotoxic activity is the induction of reactive oxygen species (ROS). It caused depolarization of mitochondrial membranes by activating the Bax protein, responsible for the formations of pores in the membrane, and thus the outflow of cytochrome c. Thymol activated caspase degrading protein and led to the activation of poly-ADP-ribose polymerase (PARP), which plays a role in DNA damage detection and its repair, gene stability, and cell death. Also, Günes-Bayir and co-workers [
 <xref rid="B77-molecules-25-04125" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>] confirmed the cytotoxic, genotoxic, and proapoptotic effects of thymol on gastric adenocarcinoma cells. These cell lines were treated with thymol in concentrations of 10, 20, 30, 50, 100, 200, and 400 μM, prepared from a stock solution of 600 μM of thymol in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO), and after 24 h of incubation, a dose-dependent decrease in cell survival was observed compared to the control group. Simultaneous measurements of reactive oxygen species (ROS) and glutathione (GSH) levels were performed. ROS induction was also dose-dependent and correlated negatively with cell survival. A reduced amount of GSH was observed in exposed cancer cells at a concentration of 50 μM. Investigation of the effect of thymol at a concentration of 10 to 100 μM on gastric adenocarcinoma cells confirmed its antitumor effect, manifested by apoptosis induction: cell nucleus shrinkage and chromatin condensation. This mechanism is associated with a decrease in the level of Bcl-2 protein and an increase in the level of Bax protein, caspase-3, and caspase-9. A significant proapoptotic effect of thymol was found at a dose of 50 μM. Genotoxicity tests have shown that thymol concentration from 20 to 100 μM induced DNA damage in a dose-dependent manner compared to control cells. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-04125-f007">Figure 7</xref> presents a summary of thymol antineoplastic activity pathways.
</p>
