<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While inflammation is responsible for numerous diseases, including arthritis, diabetes, multiple sclerosis, Alzheimer’s disease, and Parkinson’s disease, it is also highly associated with cancer progression [
 <xref rid="B6-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B79-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Anti-inflammatory effects of triterpenoids from medicinal plants are well reported [
 <xref rid="B6-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Nitric oxide (NO) is a molecule which is highly linked with immunity and inflammation [
 <xref rid="B80-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. In a recent study, UNA remarkably inhibited production of NO in lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-induced RAW264.7 murine macrophage cells in the low micromolar range (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 4.94 µM), whereas ULA showed no repressive action [
 <xref rid="B22-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Notably, the keto group of UNA at the C-3 position led to significantly different anti-inflammatory activity. Also, UNA effectively inhibited human platelet aggregation induced by arachidonic acid (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.26 mM) and exerted an anti-inflammatory effect in rat paw edema induced by carrageenan (53% of inhibition at dose of 50 mg/kg) [
 <xref rid="B36-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. These inhibitory effects of UNA were comparable with quercetin (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 4.41 µM) and aspirin (28–71% of inhibition at 150–300 mg/kg), which are well-known anti-inflammatory molecules [
 <xref rid="B22-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Although ULA is well-known for its anti-inflammatory effects, it can also exert proinflammatory activities [
 <xref rid="B9-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-biomolecules-10-01505" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], indicating that UNA may be used as an alternative drug for the amelioration of inflammatory diseases.
</p>
