<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0120">Researchers from Hungary investigated the pharmacoactive effects of β-cyclodextrin against the toxic effects of the xenoestrogenic mycotoxin, ZEN, in Tg (vtg1:mCherry) zebrafish embryos and HeLa cells. The results revealed that ZEN was able to form stable complexes with methyl-, sulfobutyl-, and succinyl-methyl-substituted β-cyclodextrins at pH 7.4 (K = 1.4–4.7 × 104 L/mol). The resultant complexes (
 <italic>i.e</italic>., modified cyclodextrins) strongly reduced or eliminated ZEN-induced mortality in zebrafish embryos and loss of cell viability in HeLa cells. Co-treatment with β-cyclodextrins further alleviated the sub-lethal effects of ZEN (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Faisal et al., 2020</xref>). A study by 
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Fliszar-Nyul et al. (2019)</xref> investigated association of alternariol toxin with γ- and β-CDs using molecular and fluorescence spectroscopy techniques. They also examined the extraction of the mycotoxin alternariol from water-based (aqueous) solutions using β-CD bead polymer (BBP) that is insoluble. The results demonstrated that natural γ-CD at pH 7.4 firmly increased the fluorescence of alternariol, which formed most stable complexes with natural γ-CD and quaternary ammonium derivatives under acidic/physiological pH and at pH of 10.0. Furthermore, BBP successfully extracted alternariol toxin from aqueous medium. The alternariol-binding capacity of BBP and β-CD polymers were strongly increased because of the β-CD content of the polymer. The effect of selective encapsulation of star anise essential oil (SAEO) by hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin (HPCD) on its composition, stability, volatility, and antibacterial activity was investigated and results showed that encapsulation significantly decreased the irritating odour of SAEO and also improved the inhibitory effect of SAEO on 
 <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae, Rhizopus stolonoifer,</italic> and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> and its antibacterial stability in 24 h (
 <xref rid="bib168" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
