<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chemical composition of the EO extracted from 
  <span class="italic">D. moldavica</span> harvested in Urmia, Iran, was dominated by geranial, neral, geraniol and geranyl acetate, respectively. These chemical compositions were similar to the chemical composition of the oils from Egypt
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>
  </span>
  <span class="sup">,</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>
  </span> and Hungary.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>
  </span> The results also showed that 
  <span class="italic">M. officinalis</span> EO was characterized by the presence of four dominating components: Citronellal, Thymol, Citral and β-caryophyllene, respectively. In a study in which EOs obtained from aerial parts of 
  <span class="italic">M. officinalis</span> grown in Turkey were analyzed by GC-MS, citronellal (36.62 to 43.78%), citral (10.10 to 17.43%), thymol (0.40 to 11.94%), and β-caryophyllene (5.91 to 7.27%) were recorded as the major components,
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>
  </span> which they were completely consistent with the results of the present study. However, the variations in the essential oil composition may be due to the region’s climate, plant species, distillation conditions and maturity stage and some other factors.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The advantage of essential oils and their biological properties have driven recent researches to the direct evaluation of antioxidant and antimicrobial activity of plant EOs 
  <span class="italic">in vitro </span>and also in food models.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>
  </span>
  <span class="sup">,</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>
  </span> Disk diffusion agar and micro-dilution tests are known assays to identify antibacterial properties of the EOs.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>
  </span> The results of this study revealed that gram-positive bacteria were more sensitive than gram-negative bacteria to the tested EOs. This finding was completely consistent with the literature data.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>
  </span>
  <span class="sup">-</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>
  </span> Divalent cations and polysaccharide part of lipopolysaccharides in the outer cell membrane of gram-negative bacteria obtains hydrophilic qualities that impede the contact of the hydrophobic constituents (such as EOs) with the bacterial cell, resulting in a higher resistance of gram-negative bacteria to the antibacterial properties of the EOs.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>
  </span>
  <span class="sup">,</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>
  </span>
  <span class="sup">,</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>
  </span>
  <span class="sup">,</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>
  </span>
  <span class="sup">,</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the disk diffusion agar assay and micro-dilution method, it can be concluded that 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> had the highest sensitivity to 
  <span class="italic">M. officinalis </span>and
  <span class="italic"> D. moldavica</span> EOs. Several studies have shown that 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> is the most sensitive bacteria against essential oils.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>
  </span> However, there have been few studies regarding antibacterial effects of 
  <span class="italic">M. officinalis </span>and 
  <span class="italic">D. moldavica </span>EOs.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>
  </span> In a study carried out on several gram positive and gram negative bacteria, 
  <span class="italic">E.</span>
  <span class="italic">coli </span>and the multi-resistant strain of 
  <span class="italic">Shigella sonei </span>have shown the highest sensitivity to the antibacterial effect of 
  <span class="italic">M. officinalis </span>EO. In another study,
  <span class="italic"> M. officinalis </span>EO revealed strong antimicrobial activity against 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S. enterica.</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>
  </span> This variation can be due to the differences in major and/or minor components of the EOs. Various factors can affect EOs chemical composition such as climate, seasonal and geographic conditions.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>
  </span>
  <span class="sup">,</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Nowadays consumers prefer to use EOs and plant extracts instead of chemical preservatives in order to prevent microbial growth and oil oxidation.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>
  </span> Using DPPH and ABST assays for evaluating antioxidant activity of the EOs in the present study revealed that both EOs were weaker than ascorbic acid and BHT. Although, BCBT indicated a higher activity of 
  <span class="italic">M. officinalis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">D. moldavica </span>EO than ascorbic acid. These results were in agreement with those reported in former studies.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>
  </span>
  <span class="sup">-</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">37</a>
  </span> There are some other studies indicating the both of these EOs can be used as antioxidant as well.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">37</a>
  </span>
  <span class="sup">-</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>
  </span> There is a direct correlation between the free radical scavenging and antioxidant activity of the essential oils and the concentration. Also, a linear trend has been observed between polyphenolic concentration and radical scavenging activity of different plants.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>
  </span> The antioxidant potency of both EOs may be due to the presence of different bioactive EOs compounds which are identified by GC-MS analysis such as flavonoids, geraniol, thymol, geranial, citronellal and citral.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusions, the present study revealed a significant antimicrobial effect of 
  <span class="italic">M. officinalis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">D. moldavica </span>against 
  <span class="italic">S. typhimorium, E. coli, L. monocytogenes </span>and
  <span class="italic"> S. aureus</span>. Although 
  <span class="italic">M. officinalis</span> EO showed better antimicrobial properties than 
  <span class="italic">D. moldavica</span> EO. On the other hand, a remarkable potency was identified in antioxidant activity of both EOs using different assays, therefore, they can be used as natural remedies in infectious diseases as well as natural preservatives in food industries.
 </p>
</sec>
