<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. MPEO Regulates Profibrogenic Protein Expression in CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-Induced Fibrosis
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">α</span>-SMA and desmin immunoreactivity appeared to be cytoplasmic and stained brown in colour. 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-SMA expression was seen in smooth muscle cells of the blood vessels in the normal control and the MPOE control (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">4(a)</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">4(d)</a>). In the liver fibrosis control group, 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-SMA staining located in the myofibroblast cells along collagenous septa bridging portal areas and central areas and desmin immunostaining was observed in perisinusoidal cells and interstitial myofibroblasts. 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-SMA and desmin protein expression were significantly elevated in liver fibrosis control group than in the normal control (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">4</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">5</a>). Group 3 (MPOE-treated) showed a significant reduction of 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-SMA and desmin protein expression compared to the liver fibrosis control group (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">4</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">5</a>). TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 was a cytoplasmic immunostaining, and it was observed in periductal cells in the portal tract of the normal control and MPOE control groups (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6(a)</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6(d)</a>). SMAD3 expression was nuclear and cytoplasmic immunostaining. The fibrotic control group showed TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 immunoreactivity in the periductal cells in the portal tract, in perisinusoidal cells, around the blood vessels, in sinusoidal lining cells, in inflammatory cells, and in the network around the necrotic hepatocytes; and a small amount was observed in necrotic hepatocytes. TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 and SMAD3 protein expression were significantly increased in the liver fibrosis control group than in the normal control (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig7" href="#fig7">7</a>). Group 3 (MPOE-treated) showed a sustained reduction of TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 and SMAD3 protein expression compared to the liver fibrosis control group (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig7" href="#fig7">7</a>, resp.). No significant difference was recorded between the normal control and MPOE control groups.
 </p>
</sec>
