<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fibrogenesis is a multicellular wound healing process that occurs as a frequent consequence of many chronic liver injuries [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>]. Regardless of its etiology, hepatic fibrosis is generally characterized by oxidative tissue damage, inflammatory cells infiltration, HSCs activation, and excessive collagen deposition [
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>, 
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>]. Accumulating clinical and experimental evidences have shown that the halting of the fibrogenic process may allow the reversal of liver fibrosis. Indeed, resolution of liver fibrosis or even cirrhosis may occur upon eradication of the causative insult [
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>, 
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>]. Oxidative stress has been proposed as a conjoint pathological mechanism in the initiation and progression of fibrosis [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>]. Thereby, inhibition of ROS-mediated fibrogenesis might yield great potential therapeutic benefits. In this context, attention is progressively shifting towards herbal products and their antioxidant constituents [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>, 
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> has been known for its great multipharmaceutical benefits [
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>, 
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>]. The active phytocompounds of MPEO contribute to many of its profound therapeutic actions. Although the hepatoprotective effect of MPOE was previously demonstrated [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>], its antifibrogenic influence against hepatic fibrosis has not been investigated yet. The present study aimed to evaluate the potential of MPOE to ameliorate CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-induced hepatic fibrosis in rats and to elucidate some aspects of its underlying molecular mechanisms.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MPEO was reported to have a wide range of components, including menthol, menthone, menthofuran, and methyl acetate, and other pharmacologically active compounds such as flavonoids, tannins, and caffeic acid [
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">37</a>]. In the current study, the chemical profile of MPEO, as presented in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>, is characterized by the dominant presence of the oxygenated monoterpenes menthol (46.7%) and menthone (18.3%). A high percentage of carvone (15%) was observed compared to that of the composition previously reported by Sun et al. [
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">38</a>]. Different chemotypes of 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> were reported in other countries in which the major constituent in MPEO is linalool as in 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> collected from Brazil [
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">39</a>] or limonene as in 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> collected from India [
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>]. This diversity in the chemical composition may be attributed to geographical and soil condition, biosynthetic factors, and collection time [
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">38</a>]. However, the composition of MPEO presented in the current study still maintains a certain level of chemosimilarity with some previously reported MPEO compositions [
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">38</a>]. Mentha species are known for their ability to exhibit strong antioxidant and radical scavenging activities owing to the presence of valuable secondary metabolites in the essential oil and phenolic substances [
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>]. Previous studies showed that the radical scavenging activity of essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> species is attributed to the presence of menthone and menthol, with the presence of the hydroxyl radical (
  <span class="sup">•</span>OH). The vast majority of these antioxidants (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1</a>) have the ability to trap the free radicals and interrupt the chain reaction due to the presence of at least one aromatic ring in their structures [
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">42</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-induced fibrosis has been extensively used as an 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span> model for the study of liver damage [
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>, 
  <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">43</a>, 
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>]. CCl
  <sub>4</sub> toxicity represents a multifactorial process involving its detoxification by CYP450 into the highly reactive CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-derived free radicals, covalent binding to macromolecules, stimulation of inflammatory cytokines, oxidative damage with subsequent necrosis of hepatocytes, and activation of HSCs [
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fibrogenesis is mediated by a complex interplay of signaling pathways. Of particular note, TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1/SMAD is one of the core mechanisms of fibrogenesis [
  <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">45</a>]. Recently, much information has emerged concerning the central role of TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 as the principal driver of excessive scarring and tissue fibrosis. TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1, in HSCs, acts by stimulating collagen I expression and inhibiting ECM degradation [
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>, 
  <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">46</a>]. Excessive TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 release by necrotic hepatocytes is considered as one of the first signals to adjacent quiescent HSCs to be activated by transdifferentiation into myofibroblasts-like cells [
  <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">47</a>]. Upon activation, TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 binds to its cell-surface receptor complexes and initiates an intracellular signaling cascade resulting in phosphorylation of SMAD2 and SMAD3. Subsequently, the activated SMAD2 and SMAD3 form stable oligomer complexes with SMAD4. These complexes actively shuttle into the nucleus to regulate the transcription of target genes [
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">48</a>, 
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">49</a>]. It has been demonstrated that SMAD3 is a key element in TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1–induced fibrosis [
  <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">50</a>]. A number of fibrogenic genes (e.g., collagens) and markers (e.g., 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-SMA) are SMAD3-dependent as SMAD3 directly binds to the DNA regulatory sequences of these target genes [
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>, 
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">52</a>]. Moreover, SMAD3 inhibits matrix metalloprotease 1 activity in fibroblasts and activates tissue inhibitor of metalloproteases and thus inhibits ECM degradation [
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">53</a>]. Considering this major role of TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 signaling in the pathobiology of liver fibrosis, TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 or its downstream mediators may provide important targets for the new therapeutic strategies of liver fibrosis [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study, eight weeks of CCl
  <sub>4</sub> administration was sufficient to induce severe hepatotoxic changes detected by the considerably elevated activities of serum ALT and AST markers (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>). Increased release of these cytosolic enzymes in the serum reflects hepatocyte damage and leakage and provides important diagnostic biomarkers for hepatic diseases [
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">54</a>]. Moreover, high AST and ALT levels are associated with an increased risk of fibrosis progression [
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">55</a>]. MPEO administration reversed the elevated levels of ALT and AST compared to those of the CCl
  <sub>4</sub> group. These findings are consistent with those of previous studies [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">LPO is thought to be the initiation step of CCl
  <sub>4</sub> hepatotoxicity [
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">56</a>]. Lipid hydroperoxides are unstable and so degrade rapidly into a variety of secondary metabolites such as MDA, 4-hydroxynonenal (4-HNE), and other conjugated dienes [
  <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">57</a>]. MDA serves as a main biomarker to assess the level of lipoperoxidative tissue damage [
  <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">58</a>]. In accordance with previous studies [
  <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">59</a>, 
  <a rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60">60</a>], a significant increase in liver MDA content was observed in the CCl
  <sub>4</sub> group, suggesting an enhanced LPO (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-intoxicated rats showed a significant increase in the liver NO (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>). This elevated NO indicates the stimulation of inflammatory cells and release of inflammatory cytokines [
  <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">61</a>]. NO participates in the induction of fibrosis through its reaction with superoxide anions forming highly reactive peroxynitrite radicals, which induce HSCs activation and accelerate the progression of liver fibrosis [
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">56</a>]. The obtained results closely agreed with those mentioned by Sagor et al. [
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">62</a>] and Abdel Salam et al. [
  <a rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63">63</a>], who suggested the correlation between the hepatic NO content and the degree of liver fibrosis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand, a significant decline in the liver antioxidant capacity was detected in the CCl
  <sub>4</sub> group evidenced by the decreased SOD and CAT activities and the depletion in GSH content (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>). This disturbance in the prooxidants/antioxidants balance was further verified by the low TAC (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Histopathological analysis of liver sections provided an initial evidence of CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-induced liver hepatocellular damage and fibrosis (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab5" href="#tab5">Table 5</a>). Degenerative changes including fatty degeneration, congestion, and cytoplasmic vacuolization were observed in the liver fibrosis control group (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2(b)</a>). These findings were in agreement with those obtained by Ogaly et al. [
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>] and Yacout et al. [
  <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">64</a>]. Additionally, MT staining revealed clear fibrotic bridging in the liver sections of group 2 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3(b)</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Immunohistochemical analysis of desmin, a hallmark of both quiescent and activated HSCs, revealed a significant elevation in desmin-immunopositive cells in the livers of CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-injured group 2 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Figure 5(b)</a>). In accordance with Fujii et al. [
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>], this finding implicates increased numbers of HSCs in the livers of CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-treated animals, as expression of desmin together with the stellate-shaped morphology is the main characteristic feature of HSCs [
  <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">66</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another important evidence for the activation of HSCs and progression of fibrosis was the significantly increased number of 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-SMA-immunopositive cells in the CCl
  <sub>4</sub> fibrosis group (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4(b)</a>), as compared to the control group (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4(a)</a>). 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-SMA is a reliable hallmark for HSCs activation into the myofibroblastic phenotype and considered as an important myogenic marker that plays a significant role in collagen I deposition by activated HSCs [
  <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">67</a>]. These obtained findings, in accordance with Rockey et al. [
  <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">68</a>], indicate that CCl
  <sub>4</sub> stimulated HSCs activation and transdifferentiation. Moreover, it was found that SMAD3 increases 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-SMA production and stimulates its organization into stress fibers [
  <a rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69">69</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the current study, the livers of group 2 showed an augmented expression of TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 and SMAD3 proteins as detected by the increased immunoreactivity compared to those of the control group (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig7" href="#fig7">7</a>). Similar findings were previously reported in rats [
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MPOE at the investigated dose (50 mg/kg) significantly improved the liver indices, antioxidant profile, and histological picture of liver tissue. MPOE significantly reduced serum ALT and AST, indicating a preserved liver integrity and improved function (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>). MPOE treatment markedly increased the liver antioxidant capacity by restraining the LPO byproduct (MDA) and simultaneously enhancing the activities of SOD, catalase, and regeneration of GSH (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>). Our data come in line with previous studies that reported the hepatoprotective effect of 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>] or its oil [
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>]. It was suggested that several active components of Mentha have antioxidant and antiperoxidant activities that provoke the capacity of endogenous antioxidant systems and protect against toxic hepatic damages [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>, 
  <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">70</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coadministration of MPOE with CCl
  <sub>4</sub> significantly improved the liver histopathology (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a>) and reduced the fibrotic changes (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3</a>, 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab5" href="#tab5">Table 5</a>). Furthermore, the MPOE-treated group showed a marked reduction in both 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-SMA- and desmin-immunopositive cells (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">4(c)</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">5(c)</a>). These data reflect the efficacy of MPOE to reduce the hepatocellular toxic effects of CCl
  <sub>4</sub> and to suppress HSCs activation and proliferation as well.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the same context, MPOE-treated group 3 showed marked reductions in TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 and SMAD3 proteins expression (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6(c)</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig7" href="#fig7">7(c)</a>) compared to the CCl
  <sub>4</sub> fibrosis group (Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6(b)</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig7" href="#fig7">7(b)</a>). According to Kanzler et al. [
  <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">47</a>] and Chen et al. [
  <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">71</a>], the observed suppression in TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 protein expression and the subsequent downregulation of SMAD3 in the livers of group 3 could explain the observed reduction of 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-SMA-positive cells (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4(c)</a>), collagen deposition (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3(c)</a>), and fibrosis % (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3(e)</a>) and the reduced fibrosis scores (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab5" href="#tab5">Table 5</a>) in this group in comparison with the liver fibrosis control group. These findings support the antifibrogenic potential of MPOE against CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-induced liver fibrosis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">p53 is a tumor-suppressor protein that regulates the transcription of a plethora of target proteins involved in the cell cycle, differentiation, and apoptosis [
  <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">72</a>]. In normal redox state, p53 expression and degradation are tightly regulated by a variety of proteins to maintain a low level of p53 [
  <a rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73">73</a>]. Different stress signals including ROS, hypoxia, and oncogene activation induce p53 that becomes transcriptionally active, leading to cell cycle arrest, DNA repair, and apoptosis [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>, 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>]. It was reported that hepatocyte p53 activation resulted in spontaneous liver fibrosis and induced hepatocyte apoptosis, in addition to upregulation of connective tissue growth factor (CTGF) [
  <a rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74">74</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">In vitro</span> study showed that p53 induces CTGF in hepatocytes that occur via regulation of microRNA [
  <a rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75">75</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent studies highlighted the possible involvement of p53 in fibrogenesis as a profibrotic mediator [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>, 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>, 
  <a rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74">74</a>]. p53 has been implicated as an inducer of several profibrotic effectors such as TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1, CTGF, 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-SMA, and fibronectin [
  <a rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" href="#B76">76</a>]. During the fibrogenic process, a crosstalk between p53 and TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 has been suggested to stimulate transcription of the fibrogenic target genes [
  <a rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" href="#B77">77</a>, 
  <a rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78">78</a>]. Under oxidative stress, excessive ROS induces various transcription factors such as p53, activator protein-1 (AP-1), and NF-
  <span class="italic">κ</span>B by altering the DNA binding sites or by oxidizing the cysteine residues of such proteins resulting in conformational change of their tertiary structure with subsequent protein degradation activation or inhibition. Activated p53 plays a crucial role in inducing apoptosis to prevent the propagation of DNA damage [
  <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">72</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Few reports on the role of p53 and TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 and their interplay in the mechanism of fibrogenesis have arisen [
  <a rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75">75</a>–
  <a rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78">78</a>]. This encouraged our team to study the possible role of p53 and TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 in MPEO antifibrogenic mechanism. In the current investigation, Tp53 mRNA level showed a significant increase in response to CCl
  <sub>4</sub> fibrosis (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig8" href="#fig8">Figure 8(a)</a>). Consequently, a considerable level of p53 protein was detected in the livers of the fibrosis group (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig9" href="#fig9">Figure 9</a>). These findings agreed with those of previous studies that reported that p53 expression increases following the onset of liver injury [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>, 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>]. In the MPOE-treated group, both Tp53 mRNA (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig8" href="#fig8">Figure 8(a)</a>) and p53 protein expression (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig9" href="#fig9">Figure 9(c)</a>) were significantly suppressed. This p53 downregulation might have contributed to the reduced hepatic fibrosis in this group.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pharmacological p53 inhibitors have been proposed as a therapeutic application to alleviate tissue fibrosis [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis of CYP2E1 gene expression aimed to evaluate for the detoxifying capacity of the liver. CCl
  <sub>4</sub> intoxication resulted in a significant suppression in CYP2E1 mRNA (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig8" href="#fig8">Figure 8(b)</a>). This specific CYP2E1 downregulation in CCl
  <sub>4</sub> hepatic fibrosis was previously reported [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>] and may have contributed to a direct attack of CYP2E1 transcript by the reactive CCl
  <sub>4</sub> metabolites leading to its degradation. Besides, the inflammatory response associated with fibrosis could exert a suppressive effect on CYP2E1 expression [
  <a rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" href="#B79">79</a>]. Interestingly, MPOE treatment counteracted this CYP2E1 downregulation (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig8" href="#fig8">Figure 8</a>). This preservation of CYP2E1 expression could be one of the MPOE hepatoprotective and antifibrogenic actions [
  <a rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" href="#B80">80</a>]. These findings are consistent with those of previous studies [
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">62</a>] that reported the ability of peppermint to modulate both phase I and phase II liver drug-metabolizing enzymes. Besides, eugenol, an active component of MPOE (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>), has been previously shown to induce detoxification enzymes [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
