<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045" class="p">Besides semiconductor QDs, magnetic NPs have also been functionalized for bioapplications based on surfactant-assisted self-assembly. For example, Kim and co-workers use this approach to prepare discrete, monodisperse, and size-controllable core-shell mesoporous silica NPs by using Fe
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> nanocrystals as the core for simultaneous magnetic resonance (MR) and fluorescence imaging, and for drug delivery (
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kim et al., 2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kim et al., 2008</xref>). In their procedure, cetyl trimethylammonium bromide (CTAB) serves both as the stabilizing surfactant for transferring hydrophobic Fe
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> NPs to aqueous phase and as the organic template for the formation of mesopores in the sol-gel reaction. The surface of the NPs was modified with PEG to render them biocompatible by preventing the nonspecific adsorption of proteins to the NPs. The acquired Fe
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>@mSiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> particles are monodisperse and with diameters ranging from 45–105 nm. Worm-like mesopores with diameters of around 2–3 nm were observed in the silica shells and provide the potential ability for drug delivery. The products maintained the superparamagnetic property characterized by field-dependent magnetization at room temperature, which is a desirable characteristic for MR contrast agents (
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lee and Hyeon, 2012</xref>). The NPs can be spontaneously internalized into MCF-7 cells by endocytosis, and their uptake was clearly observed within 30 min. The core-shell nanostructures were also maintained after endocytosis. NPs with different compositions and shapes such as MnO and silver NPs have been demonstrated for preparing biocompatible NP-micelles for applications as MR imaging contrast agent or antimicrobial agents, respectively (
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Na et al., 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liong et al., 2009b</xref>). In addition, FeMnO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> and FePt NP-micelles have been prepared by using surfactant-assisted self-assembly (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fan et al., 2005a</xref>).
</p>
