<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another interesting and little studied in the group of 1,2,4-triazines condensed with a five-membered heterocycle is the pyrazolo[4,3-
 <italic>e</italic>][1,2,4]triazine ring system. Its derivatives are the least known in the group of condensed pyrazolotriazines and were less studied compared to pyrrolotriazines. Some synthesised derivatives of this system were evaluated for their anticancer activity against five type tumour cell lines (CEM, CEM-DNR, K-562, K-562-tax, and A549) and they showed antiproliferative activity against A549 cell line in the micromolar range
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref>. Bernat et al. reported that pyrazolo triazine derivates show increased antiproliferative and apoptotic effects in cancerous cell lines, as compared to normal tissue
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref>. Another group is pyrazolo[4,3-
 <italic>e</italic>][1,2,4]triazine sulphonamides prepared as inhibitors of carbonic anhydrase hCA IX and XII with antitumor activity
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref>. Moreover, some previously described pyrazolotriazine sulphonamides were found to have dose-dependent antiproliferative effects against two Bcr-Abl positive cancer cell lines, K562 and BV173. Therefore, they were tested against Abl kinase
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref>. On the other hand, our earlier study showed that tricyclic derivatives of the pyrazolo[4,3-
 <italic>e</italic>][1,2,4]triazines condensed with triazole or tetrazole were the most active against cancer cell lines
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref>. Replacement of triazole with a tetrazole ring results in increase of the anticancer activity.
</p>
