<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Intake of drugs and production of metabolic toxins in the body can pave the way for the production and release of ROS [
 <xref rid="B38-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], cytokines, and other inflammatory factors. This activates the Kupffer cells within the liver, thereby resulting in the destruction of hepatocytes [
 <xref rid="B110-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>,
 <xref rid="B112-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. Hepatic stellate cells (HSCs), which play a role in the formation of basement membranes by producing small amounts of extracellular matrix components like collagen type IV and laminin, when exposed to factors released from the stimulated Kupffer cells, lose their lipid level and then go through phenotypic alterations, proliferate, and produce excess amounts of extracellular matrix, thus resulting in liver fibrosis [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B113-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. Naringenin has shown hepatoprotective and anti-fibrotic effects against dimethylnitrosamine (DMN)-mediated liver injury in rats, while oral consumption of naringenin has resulted in reduction of AST, ALT, and ALP and bilirubin levels. Furthermore, staining of liver tissue sections with Sirius red stain has revealed a reduction in collagen accumulation in the naringenin-treated rats. Naringenin has also been reported to reduce the activation of hepatic stellate cells [
 <xref rid="B103-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. The effect of naringenin on inflammatory changes in the liver triggered by high dietary cholesterol has been extensively studied and has been found to significantly decrease the release of pro-inflammatory mediators and downregulate the expression of TNF-α and MMP-2 and MMP-9, which contributes to reduced macrophage infiltration [
 <xref rid="B115-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. It also modulates the levels of necrotic inflammation by degrading extracellular matrix [
 <xref rid="B117-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. Additionally, naringenin has been shown to alleviate inflammation induced by hyperglycemia in streptozotocin-nicotinamide-induced diabetes mellitus in rats [
 <xref rid="B117-plants-09-01784" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>].
</p>
