<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The molecular architecture of TRF1–DNA complexes requires both protein–protein interactions and protein–DNA interactions (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>). We have stretched a single compacted telomere to reveal looped structures mediated by protein–protein interactions when TRF1 forms homodimers to condense DNA. On the other hand, the direct interactions between TRF1 and DNA play a pivotal role in TTAGGG repeat-associated replication, averting TRF2-dependent telomeric R loops, and telomere breakages (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>). The TTAGGG repeats of telomeres challenge the DNA replication machinery, resulting in replication-dependent defects (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>). Gene deletion assays and single-molecule fluorescence experiments of replicating telomeres reveal that TRF1 is essential for efficient replication of mammalian telomeres by preventing fork stalling (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). We examined the dynamics of TRF1 at a telomeric DNA fork using single-molecule strand-separation assays. We found that TRF1 can modulate the forward and backward steps of DNA fork movements by 2–9 s at a critical force of 
 <italic>F</italic>
 <sub>1/2</sub>, generating an overall effect of maintaining the telomeric fork at an open state. Considering that DNA replication usually happens at a rate of &gt;100 bp/s (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>), our results from the telomeric fork assay provide insights into the kinetics of how TRF1 facilitated the efficient replication of a telomere. The experimental methods we developed here could be potentially used for further investigation on telomere replication. Our methods and results will also help future research on TRF1 as a drug target (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78–80</xref>).
</p>
