<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plant essential oils are possible sources of new antimicrobial agents. Different antibacterial properties of essential oils depend on their chemical composition. Variation in the chemical profile of essential oils in different plant species and even within the same species could be different depending on geographic region, harvest time, age of the plant, growing conditions, drying and extraction method.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup> Therefore, despite the various studies on the antimicrobial effect and chemical composition of the essential oils, it was important to determine the chemical composition of the essential oils to correlate with their antimicrobial activities.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
 </sup> The chemical profiles of the studied essential oils almost were in agreement with previous researches.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 </sup> For example, in chemical analysis of the original fresh leaf of 
 <italic>M. longifolia</italic> oil by Asekun
 <italic> et al</italic>., pulegone (35.00%) was the major compound.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
 </sup> Also in research, cumin aldehyde has been reported as the major compound (29.02%) in 
 <italic>C. cyminum </italic>essential oil, and in a study by Snoussi 
 <italic>et al</italic>., the main components of 
 <italic>M. spicata</italic> essential oil were carvone (40.80%) and limonene (20.80%).
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 </sup> In this study, mono-terpenes in 
 <italic>C. cyminum</italic> and oxygenated monoterpenes in 
 <italic>M. spicata</italic> and 
 <italic>M. longifolia</italic> essential oils were the main compounds. The lipophilic character of monoterpenes causes membrane fluidity and permeability, disturbance of membrane-embedded proteins, and alteration of ion transport processes. The results of previous studies have established that these compounds have a degree of antibacterial activity. Kotan 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, in the evaluation of inhibitory effects of 21 pure oxygenated monoterpenes on the growth of 63 bacterial strains showed that alcohol derivatives of oxygenated monoterpenes were more active than their acetate derivatives.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup> Antibacterial activity could be influenced by terpene, however, other components can contribute to this activity as well.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
 </sup> It seems pulegone and cumin aldehyde, the main component of the 
 <italic>M. longifolia </italic>and 
 <italic>C. cyminum</italic>, respectively, are predominantly responsible for most of their antibacterial activity and pharmacological effects.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
 </sup> The antimicrobial activity of the 
 <italic>M. spicata </italic>essential oil could be associated with the presence of carvone and limonene. Although other compounds in essential oils that are not abundant can contribute to this activity. The mechanism of carvone is related to the destabilization of the phospholipid bilayer structure, interaction with enzymes and proteins of the membrane, and its act as a proton exchanger reducing the pH among the membrane.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
 </sup> Antibacterial activities of some medicinal plants such as 
 <italic>Althaea officinalis</italic>, 
 <italic>M. longifolia</italic> and 
 <italic>C. cyminum </italic>extracts against methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>S. aureus </italic>have been reported.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
 </sup> Furthermore, Bokaeian
 <italic> et al</italic>. have reported that 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>cyminum </italic>essential oil has a strong antimicrobial effect against multidrug-resistant
 <italic> Escherichia coli </italic>strains.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 </sup> Due to undesirable flavor changes of essential oils which these preservatives cause in food and oral drugs, their application is currently limited. Food and drug preservation by multiple preservatives in small amounts are better than preservation by a large amount of a single preservative for secure microbial stability, safety, and maintaining of the sensory properties.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
 </sup> Nowadays, extensive efforts have been performed to use less concentrations of essential oils with other antimicrobial agents to receive stronger synergistic effects. The synergistic effect between essential oils and other antimicrobial contents has been conclusively demonstrated.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
 </sup> For example in a study, the synergistic effect of 
 <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> essential oil with nisin on 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>S. typhimurium</italic> was observed.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
 </sup> In this research, we found the significant inhibitory effect of the combined use of the essential oils with sodium benzoate on the studied bacteria. There is evidence that gram-positive bacteria more than gram-negative bacteria are vulnerable to plant oils and extracts.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup> Based on our results, 
 <italic>Y. enterocolitica </italic>was more sensitive in the presence of studied essential oils individually and combined with sodium benzoate, therefore, it could be concluded that the essential oils did not have selective antimicrobial activity based on the cell-wall differences of the bacteria as reported previously. Previous studies have also shown that these essential oils were active against different gram-negative bacteria.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>-</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>
 </sup> Therefore, the sensitivity of a microorganism to essential oils not only depends on the properties of essential oil but also on the nature of the microorganism (morphology, structure, metabolic type, nutritional, pathogenicity).
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>
 </sup> The results of this study demonstrated that the antimicrobial effect of sodium benzoate was higher when used in combination with the essential oils. A high concentration of sodium benzoate leads to the accumulation of toxic products and side effects.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>
 </sup> Thus, for a significant effect on these bacteria, a combination of sodium benzoate with other antimicrobial agents such as essential oils is recommended to reduce sodium benzoate concentration.
</p>
