<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Biofilm formation was evaluated as previously described (Marini et al., 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Briefly, bacteria were grown overnight in TSB containing 1% glucose at 30°C. Overnight bacterial suspensions were prepared to yield final inocula of ~1 × 10
 <sup class="sup">8</sup> colony-forming units (CFU)/mL; then 200 μL aliquots of the bacterial suspension were inoculated into 96-well microtitre plates at least in triplicate. After 24-h incubation, wells were washed 3 times in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), dried for 1 h at 60°C, and stained with Hucker's crystal violet. After three washes in sterile water, wells were inoculated with 100 μL of 95% EtOH and shaken for 10 min. Biofilm formation was quantified by measuring absorbance at 690 nm with a Multiscan Ascent apparatus (Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). The optical density (OD) cut-off (ODc) was defined as 3 standard deviations above the mean OD of the negative control, represented by non-inoculated wells containing TSB (Stepanovic et al., 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>). Strains were classified as non-producers (OD ≤ ODc), weak producers (ODc &lt; OD ≤ 2 × ODc), moderate producers (2 × ODc &lt; OD ≤ 4 × ODc), or strong producers (OD &gt; 4 × ODc). The biofilm-forming strain 
 <italic class="italic">S. epidermidis</italic> ATCC 35984 was used as a positive control (Christensen et al., 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1985</xref>). In some assays, biofilm formation was evaluated in presence of the 
 <italic class="italic">C. sativa</italic> EO. Briefly, overnight bacterial suspensions were prepared to yield final inocula of ~2 × 10
 <sup class="sup">8</sup> CFU/mL. Then, 100 μL of bacterial culture and 100 μL of different EO concentrations were added to each well of a 96-well microplate. Wells containing 100 μL of the bacterial suspension and 100 μL TSB without EO were the positive controls. After incubation, biofilm formation was evaluated as described above. All experiments were performed in triplicate.
</p>
