<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coronaviruses are single-stranded RNA viruses known to cause human respiratory tract or animal intestinal infection [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-05905" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-05905" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-05905" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05905-f002">Figure 2</xref>A). Primarily, there are four main types, including α-coronavirus, β-coronavirus, δ-coronavirus, and γ-coronavirus [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-05905" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Six coronaviruses, including SARS-CoV (Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome CoV) and MERS-CoV (Middle East Respiratory Syndrome CoV), were reported to cause illness in humans prior to SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-05905" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Similar to SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, SARS-CoV-2 belongs to β-coronavirus. SARS-CoV-2 and SARS have a genome sequence homology of approximately 79% and is more closely related to SARS-like bat coronaviruses than SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-05905" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The spike protein recognizes and binds to the receptor and invades the host cell 
 <italic>via</italic> clathrin-mediated endocytosis [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-25-05905" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. After internalization, the virus manipulates the cells’ reproductive machinery to produce more copies to infect other cells. SARS-CoV-2 also utilizes the cofactors, Furin and transmembrane proteases, serine 2 (TMPRSS2), protein cleaving enzymes, to cleave viral S-protein and further facilitate the virus-cell fusion [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-25-05905" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-05905" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. As revealed in structure model analysis, SARS-CoV-2 binds to Angiotensin I Converting Enzyme 2 (ACE2), a host receptor, with more than a 10-fold higher affinity as compared to SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-25-05905" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05905-f002">Figure 2</xref>B). These findings explain the greater propagation capacity of SARS-CoV-2 in humans relative to SARS-CoV and the higher number of reported cases of COVID-19 relative to SARS-CoV infection [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-25-05905" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The precise mechanism by which SARS-CoV-2 influences humans 
 <italic>via</italic> S-protein binding to ACE2, the association intensity for the danger of human transmission, and how SARS-CoV-2 causes organ damage remains unclear, and further studies are required. 
</p>
