<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Independent of their structural diversity, this type of compounds shows an intrinsic “in vitro” antioxidant activity all possessing the aforementioned phenolic moiety. Each phenolic substituent will be able (in theory) to act as antioxidant due to its inherent low redox potential and hence its electron/proton donor capacity [
 <xref rid="B100-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. Therefore, metabolites with more than one hydroxyl group (polyphenols) can show more than one redox potential, varying in magnitude depending on the pH of the medium. Consequently, one could deduce that for a single compound more phenol substituents mean more antioxidant capacity, but evidently there are some limitations to this “rule”. Substituents adjacent to the phenolic moiety as well as the level of conjugation of the total structure can increase/decrease the reactivity of this group. First, phenols are irreversibly oxidized with the transfer of one electron and one proton into a phenoxy radical, which is more stable when another hydroxyl substituent is located in 
 <italic>ortho</italic> and 
 <italic>para</italic> positions. The 
 <italic>ortho</italic> substitution pattern is more common, generating catechol groups which confer high antioxidant activity to the compounds with these characteristics. Secondly, substituents that contribute to the delocalization of the electrons through the resonant structures formed after the electron/proton transfer, also contribute to the in vitro effectiveness of polyphenols as antioxidants. Other chemical modifications that alter the redox reactivity of phenols are hydrophilic substituents like sugars that enhance the molecular solubility and promote the hydroxyl hydration in aqueous media, shifting the phenolic groups’ oxidation to more negative redox potentials. Bulky non-electroactive substituents may cause an unfavorable effect on the antioxidant activity due to the steric hindrance effect. A detailed explanation about phenol moiety oxidation mechanisms and factors that affect it can be obtained from the review recently published by Chiorcea-Paquim and collaborators (2020) [
 <xref rid="B100-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>].
</p>
