<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The extract was obtained from 250 g of dried leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">L. mutica</italic>, using EtOAc as the extraction solvent. The process was carried out statically, at room temperature, for three consecutive times, one hour each. After solvent evaporation, 24.1 g of the EtOAc extract were obtained (yield: 9.6%). The extract underwent subsequent removal of chlorophylls by filtration through a C-18 SPE column; elution was done with MeOH-H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O, 9:1 
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>, followed by 100% acetone. After chlorophyll removal and solvent evaporation chlorophyll, a free EtOAc extract (13.8 g) was obtained. In addition, 1 g of this extract was fractionated by medium-pressure flash chromatography on a C-18 cartridge, containing 100 g of stationary phase, with an elution gradient from methanol/water (2:1) to 100% methanol. The eluent flow was set at 30 mL/min, giving 19 main fractions. Fraction #11 (511.5 mg) was subjected to normal phase (silica gel) column chromatography. Elution with a mixture of hexane/EtOAc (97:3) gave 38.5 mg of carnosol (
 <bold class="bold">1</bold>). Fraction #12 and fraction #13 (58.6 mg) were collected together and submitted to silica gel column chromatography. From the elution with a mixture of hexane/EtOAc (95:5), 10.0 mg of viridiflorol (
 <bold class="bold">2</bold>) was obtained. Fraction #18 (79.9 mg) was submitted to C-18 reversed phase column chromatography. Elution with a mixture of MeOH/H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O (95:5) afforded 14.2 mg of ursolic acid (
 <bold class="bold">3</bold>), and 23.5 mg of oleanolic acid (
 <bold class="bold">4</bold>). A second amount of the EtOAc chlorophyll-free extract (11 g) was fractionated by preparative column chromatography on silica gel in order to get larger amounts of metabolites from 
 <italic class="italic">L. mutica</italic>. Elution with an increasing polarity gradient of a hexane/EtOAc mixture afforded 16 main fractions. Fraction #11 (4.9 g) was subjected to silica gel column chromatography. Elution with an increasing polarity gradient of a hexane/EtOAc mixture gave 11.9 mg of 5-hydroxy-4′,7-dimethoxy flavone (
 <bold class="bold">5</bold>), and 127.7 mg of carnosol (
 <bold class="bold">1</bold>). Collected fractions #13 and #14 (2.4 g) were submitted to silica gel column chromatography. Elution with an increasing polarity gradient of a hexane/EtOAc mixture gave 11 main fractions (F38-F49). Fraction #44 (158.3 mg) was also submitted to silica gel column chromatography. Elution with an increasing polarity gradient of a dichloromethane/EtOAc mixture afforded 77.7 mg of isolated chrysothol (
 <bold class="bold">6</bold>).
</p>
