<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Quite a number of works have reported using coconut shell AC to treat POME. Azmi and Yunos [
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-15-02200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>] investigated the performance of coconut shell AC to alleviate turbidity and TSS from POME. Over 71.26% removal was reported after 35.94 min contact time with a steady agitation speed of 39.82 rpm. Also, Amosa et al. [
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-15-02200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>] study the performance of high surface area adsorbent to reduce turbidity and TSS, and they reported 89.1 and 91.4% removal efficiency, respectively. In addition, Mohammed and Chong [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-15-02200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>] used palm kernel shell activated carbon to decolourize POME under variable contact time, pH and adsorbent dosage. From their report, 100% decolourization was achieved at a pH of 2. Equally, Alkhatib et al. [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-15-02200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] optimize colour removal from POME by granular activated carbon using the response surface method (RSM) and 89.95% decolourization was reported at 4.05 pH. In overview, it can be deduced that the studies using coconut shell biosorbent are rather limited and it has been scarcely applied for POME decolourization despite its impressive potential. More so, the previous reports on the application of CSAC biosorbents for POME decolourization anonymously confirmed that significant colour removal is only attained at an acidic pH [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-15-02200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-15-02200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-15-02200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijerph-15-02200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. Thus, discharging such partially treated effluent would also also hazardous to the environment because of its acidic pH. It can be deduced from these literatures that the sorbents provide adequate active sites for efficient removal of the colour pigments only if the pH is within the extreme acidic range [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-15-02200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>].
</p>
