<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Epoxidized soybean oil (ESO) is a collection of organic compounds obtained from the epoxidation of soybean oil that have been widely used as plasticizers and heat stabilizers of PVC materials. The chemical structure of ESO is shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="polymers-10-01303-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>. Ferrer et al. found that formulations based on PVC with different amounts of ESO (from 30 to 50 wt %) increased compatibility and improved thermal stability [
 <xref rid="B15-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Park et al. investigated the performances of epoxy resins plasticized with ESO [
 <xref rid="B16-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. They found that the thermal stability and glass transition temperature of epoxy resins reduced with the addition of ESO. This phenomenon occurs due to the decreased density of the epoxy network. The addition of ESO causes the increase of stress intensity factor along with the flexural strength. Zhao et al. investigated the plasticizing effect of ESO on polybutylene succinate (PBS) [
 <xref rid="B17-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. The results show that ESO efficiently improves elongation at break of PBS. The elongation at break reaches a maximum value when the content of ESO is 5 wt % of PBS, 15 times more than the elongation of pure PBS. Moreover, ESO enhances the elongation at break of poly(lactic acid) (PLA) by 63%. Xu et al. studied the performances of PLA plasticized with ESO [
 <xref rid="B18-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. The results show that 9 wt % ESO increased the elongation at break of PLA by about 63%. PLA blends containing 6 wt % ESO show maximum tensile strength and melt strength. Zhu et al. added maleic anhydride (MA) to enhance PLA’s reactivity with ESO, obtaining an elongation at break of about 140% [
 <xref rid="B19-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. This can be explained by the grafting content of MA, which determines the properties of the blends. Xu et al. investigated the effect of ESO on melt rheological properties such as shear viscosity and melt strength of PLA blends [
 <xref rid="B20-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. They chose melt flow index (MFI) as measuring rule. The results show that PLA/ESO blends possess more MFI than pure PLA. Under the temperature range of 160–180 °C, PLA blends with 6 wt % ESO achieve the maximum melt strength. 
</p>
