<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Anim Sci Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Anim Sci Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Animal Science and Biotechnology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1674-9782</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2049-1891</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6582608</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">358</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40104-019-0358-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae as a potential dietary protein source altered the microbiota and modulated mucosal immune status in the colon of finishing pigs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Miao</given-names></name><address><email>ymiao5656@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Zhenming</given-names></name><address><email>lzm900120@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Weidong</given-names></name><address><email>2846660425@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>Ting</given-names></name><address><email>blueskyrt@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Gang</given-names></name><address><email>wgw92004@yahoo.com.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5712-2573</contrib-id><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Xianyong</given-names></name><address><email>maxianyong@gdaas.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.488217.0</institution-id><institution>Institute of Animal Science, Guangdong Academy of Agricultural Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Guangzhou, 510640 Guangdong People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>State Key Laboratory of Livestock and Poultry Breeding, Guangzhou, 510640 Guangdong People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0369 6250</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418524.e</institution-id><institution>Key Laboratory of Animal Nutrition and Feed Science in South China, Ministry of Agriculture; Guangdong Public Laboratory of Animal Breeding and Nutrition, </institution></institution-wrap>Guangzhou, 510640 Guangdong People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Guangdong Engineering Technology Research Center of animal Meat quality and Safety Control and Evaluation, Guangzhou, 510640 Guangdong People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>50</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Insects, such as <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae, are rich in chitin and proteins, and represent a suitable feed ingredient replacement for animals. However, little is known about the effect of administering <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae on intestinal microbiota, bacterial metabolite profiles, and mucosal immune status in animals. This study aimed to investigate the effects of administering <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae on colonic microbiota and bacterial metabolites production in finishing pigs. Seventy-two crossbred (Duroc &#x000d7; Landrace &#x000d7; Large White) female pigs (initial body weight, 76.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.52&#x02009;kg) were randomly allocated to three different dietary treatments: a control diet (Control group) and two diets corresponding to 4% (H1 group) and 8% (H2 group) <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae inclusion levels, respectively. Each treatment consisted of eight pens (replicates), with three pigs per pen. After 46&#x02009;days of feeding, eight pigs per treatment (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8) were slaughtered, and the colonic digesta and mucosa were collected for microbial composition and microbial fermentation products, and genes expression analyses.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">The results showed that the H1 diet significantly increased the abundance of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic>Pseudobutyrivibrio</italic>, <italic>Roseburia</italic>, and <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic> compared with those in the control group (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), with a decrease in the abundance of <italic>Streptococcus</italic>. The numbers of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic>Roseburia</italic>, and <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa were significantly greater in the H1 group than in the control group (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Meanwhile, H2 diet increased the number of <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa compared with the control group (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). For colonic metabolites, total short chain fatty acids, butyrate, and isobutyrate concentrations were significantly higher in the H1 group than those in the control group (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05); the H1 treatment caused a striking decrease in protein fermentation compared with the control group, as the concentrations of total amines, cadaverine, tryptamine, phenol, <italic>p</italic>-cresol, and skatole were significantly lower (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Additionally, H2 diet also increased butyrate concentration compared with control group (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), while decreased the concentrations of phenol, <italic>p</italic>-cresol, and skatole (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Pigs in the H1 group down-regulated the expression of <italic>TLR</italic>-4 and pro-inflammatory cytokines (<italic>IFN-&#x003b3;</italic>) compared with pigs in the control group (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), and up-regulated anti-inflammatory cytokine (<italic>IL-10</italic>) and intestinal barrier genes (<italic>ZO-1</italic>, <italic>occludin</italic>, and <italic>mucin-1</italic>). H2 diet up-regulated the expression of <italic>ZO-1</italic> compared with control group (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Furthermore, the changes in the colonic mucosal gene expression were associated with changes in the bacterial composition and their metabolites.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">Collectively, dietary inclusion of <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae may enhance mucosal immune homeostasis of pigs via altering bacterial composition and their metabolites. These findings provide a new perspective on insect meal as a sustainable protein source rich in nutrient ingredients for swine.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s40104-019-0358-1) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Colon</kwd><kwd>Finishing pigs</kwd><kwd><italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae</kwd><kwd>Immune status</kwd><kwd>Microbial metabolites</kwd><kwd>Microbiota</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Presidential Foundation of the Guangdong Academy of Agricultural Sciences</institution></funding-source><award-id>201802B</award-id><award-id>201621</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Miao</given-names></name><name><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>Ting</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Guangdong Modern Agro-industry Technology Research System</institution></funding-source><award-id>2016LM1080, 2017LM1080</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Xianyong</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par15">The global population will exceed 9 billion in 2050, so the demand for meat is expected to be 58% higher in 2050 than its 2010 level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In parallel, this affects the demand for livestock feeds, and places heavy pressure on the already overexploited resources, especially protein sources. Therefore, more and more researchers are interested in finding new alternative and sustainable protein sources for livestock feed. Several insect species, such as the <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic>, as a sustainable food alternative and the feed ingredients are an interesting natural resource when considering their many environmental and health benefits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae provide a high nutritive value feedstuff as they are rich in protein (40&#x02013;44%) with a similar or even more balanced amino acid (AA) composition than soybean meal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. As the feed ingredients of a complete diet, <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae have been found to modulate growth performance, nutrient digestibility, and blood profiles of chickens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Additionally, dietary including 4% and 8% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae in weaning piglets had no negative effects on the growth performance and nutrient digestibility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Thus, these results demonstrate that <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae can be used in the diet of monogastric animals as a potential valuable feed ingredient.</p><p id="Par16">In addition, <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae also contain bacteriostatic substances, such as chitin, which is a naturally occurring polysaccharide of the arthropod&#x02019;s exoskeleton and considered to be one of the most abundant biopolymers in nature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Chitin resists the digestion and absorption in the small intestine of monogastric animals, and enters the large intestine for use by the microbiota as a fermentable substrate. A previous study in piglets indicated that chitin derivatives (such as chitosan) administered can potentially reduce or inhibit the proliferation of pathogenic bacteria causing post weaning diarrhea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Indeed, the effects of <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae as a feed ingredient on the gut microbiota [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] and microbial metabolites (such as short-chain fatty acids, SCFAs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] have been described in the cecal digesta of laying hens or broiler chickens, suggesting an evident effect of <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae on the gut microbiota and metabolism. However, it remains unclear whether the <italic>H. illucens larvae</italic> meal as a dietary protein source has evident effect on the gut microbiota and its metabolism in the colon of finishing pigs.</p><p id="Par17">As the first of innate immune response, the gastrointestinal epithelium represents a physical and an immunological barrier, and plays a significant role in maintenance and regulation of gastrointestinal health. Alteration of the bacterial community and their metabolite profile could affect intestinal immune function. Accumulating evidence has indicated that bacterial products resulting from carbohydrate fermentation, such as SCFAs exert many beneficial effects on physiological function of the intestine as they not only provide energy for epithelial cells, stimulate epithelial proliferation and tight junction formation, but also inhibit potential pathogen growth, inflammation and genotoxicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], while bacterial metabolites from protein fermentation, such as amines, ammonia, indolic and phenolic compounds are considered to exert negative effects on the intestinal mucosa by interfering with its inflammatory responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The previous study has indicated that <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae as an alternative feed additive increased frequency of CD4+ lymphocyte in broiler chicks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], which indicated that <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae may have the potential to positively affect immune homeostasis. However, whether the <italic>H. illucens larvae</italic> as a dietary protein source would benefit mucosal immune responses in the gut remains limited and requires further investigation.</p><p id="Par18">In the present study, we hypothesized that <italic>H. illucens larvae</italic> as a dietary protein source would change the bacterial community and its metabolites, and that these alterations can modulate the immune response in pigs. Therefore, the present study aimed to investigate the effects of <italic>H. illucens larvae</italic> as a dietary protein source on the microbiota, microbial fermentation profile, and mucosal immune responses in the colon of finishing pigs.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Preparation of <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae meal</title><p id="Par19"><italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae were purchased from Guangzhou AnRuiJie Protection Technology Co., Ltd., (Guangzhou, Guangdong, China). The prepupae were dried at 80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;min and air dried. Finally, the dried prepupae were crushed to powder through a 1.0-mm opening of a screen and was then used as <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae meal, and then kept in a well-closed and light-resistant place. The chemical composition, energy content, and amino acid concentration of the <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Analyzed chemical characteristics (% as fed), gross energy (MJ/kg), and amino acid concentration (% as fed) of the <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae meal used in the present study with finishing pigs</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Items</th><th><italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2">Analyzed composition</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;DM, %</td><td>92.22</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Gross energy, MJ/kg</td><td>21.80</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;CP, %</td><td>34.97</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Ether extract, %</td><td>35.49</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Ash, %</td><td>6.46</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ADF, %</td><td>6.71</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ADF-linked protein, %</td><td>5.59</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Chitin, %</td><td>4.65</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Mineral composition, %</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Total P</td><td>0.83</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Ca</td><td>4.39</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Essential amino acids</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Lysine</td><td>2.10</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Methionine</td><td>0.50</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Methionine + Cystine</td><td>0.62</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Isoleucine</td><td>1.36</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Leucine</td><td>2.12</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Tryptophan</td><td>0.60</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Valine</td><td>1.86</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Threonine</td><td>1.17</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Arginine</td><td>2.30</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Phenylalanine</td><td>1.18</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Histidine</td><td>0.80</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Non-essential amino acids</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Alanine</td><td>2.55</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Aspartate</td><td>2.67</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Glutamate</td><td>4.11</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Glycine</td><td>1.61</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Serine</td><td>1.16</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Tyrosine</td><td>1.63</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Animals, diets, and sampling</title><p id="Par20">A total of 72 crossbred (Duroc &#x000d7; Landrace &#x000d7; Large White) female pigs were randomly allocated to three different experimental diets based on their body weights (BW, 76.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.52&#x02009;kg). Pigs in the three treatments received increasing levels of <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae meal (0, 4% and 8%; Control, H1, and H2 group, respectively). Each treatment consisted of eight pens (replicates), with three pigs per pen. All of the experimental diets were formulated to meet or exceed the nutrient recommendations of the National Research Council (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. All pigs were provided the diet and water ad libitum during the 46-day experiment. The feed consumption per pen was recorded every day to calculate average daily feed intake (ADFI). The BWs of all pigs were recorded at the beginning and the end of the study period to determine average daily gain (ADG).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Feed ingredient and nutrient composition of experimental diets (as-fed basis)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Items</th><th colspan="3">Treatment<sup>a</sup></th></tr><tr><th>Control</th><th>H1</th><th>H2</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4">Ingredient, %</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Corn</td><td>71.00</td><td>71.20</td><td>71.76</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Soybean meal</td><td>16.98</td><td>13.86</td><td>10.75</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Wheat bran</td><td>6.00</td><td>6.00</td><td>6.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> L.</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>4.00</td><td>8.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Soybean oil</td><td>2.50</td><td>1.70</td><td>0.50</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Vitamin-mineral premix<sup>b</sup></td><td>1.00</td><td>1.00</td><td>1.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Dicalcium phosphate</td><td>0.95</td><td>0.95</td><td>1.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Limestone</td><td>0.75</td><td>0.40</td><td>0.03</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;NaCl</td><td>0.30</td><td>0.30</td><td>0.30</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>L</italic>-Lysine&#x000a0;HCl(98%)</td><td>0.38</td><td>0.40</td><td>0.42</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>DL</italic>-Methionine</td><td>0.06</td><td>0.07</td><td>0.09</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>L</italic>-Threonine</td><td>0.06</td><td>0.11</td><td>0.15</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;<italic>L</italic>-Tryptophan</td><td>0.02</td><td>0.01</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Total</td><td>100.00</td><td>100.00</td><td>100.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">Calculated content<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ME<sup>d</sup>, MJ/kg</td><td>14.37</td><td>14.38</td><td>14.38</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">&#x02003;Standard ileal digestible amino acid, %</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x02003;Lysine</td><td>0.73</td><td>0.73</td><td>0.73</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x02003;Threonine</td><td>0.46</td><td>0.46</td><td>0.46</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x02003;Methionine + Cysteine</td><td>0.42</td><td>0.42</td><td>0.42</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x02003;Tryptophan</td><td>0.14</td><td>0.14</td><td>0.14</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">Analyzed nutrient composition<sup>e</sup></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Dry matter, %</td><td>89.22</td><td>89.16</td><td>89.23</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Crude protein, %</td><td>14.53</td><td>14.53</td><td>14.54</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Ether extract, %</td><td>5.10</td><td>5.10</td><td>5.10</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Crude ash, %</td><td>4.36</td><td>4.39</td><td>4.50</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ADF, %</td><td>3.51</td><td>4.50</td><td>4.92</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ADF-linked protein, %</td><td>0.85</td><td>1.58</td><td>2.89</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Chitin, %</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.90</td><td>1.90</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>diets H1 and H2 contained 4% and 8% <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae in an amount providing similar nitrogen to the diet as control diet, respectively</p><p><sup>b</sup>Provided per kilogram of complete diet: vitamin A, 15,000&#x02009;IU; vitamin D<sub>3</sub>, 3,000&#x02009;IU; vitamin E, 150&#x02009;mg; vitamin K<sub>3</sub>, 3&#x02009;mg; vitamin B<sub>1</sub>, 3&#x02009;mg; vitamin B<sub>2</sub>, 6&#x02009;mg; vitamin B<sub>6</sub>, 5&#x02009;mg; vitamin B<sub>12</sub>, 0.03&#x02009;mg; niacin, 45&#x02009;mg; vitamin C, 250&#x02009;mg; calcium pantothenate, 9&#x02009;mg; folic acid, 1&#x02009;mg; biotin, 0.3&#x02009;mg; choline chloride, 500&#x02009;mg; Fe (FeSO<sub>4</sub>.H<sub>2</sub>O), 170&#x02009;mg; Cu (CuSO<sub>4</sub>.5H<sub>2</sub>O), 150&#x02009;mg; I (KI), 0.90&#x02009;mg; Se (Na<sub>2</sub>SeO<sub>3</sub>),0.2&#x02009;mg; Zn (ZnSO<sub>4</sub>.H<sub>2</sub>O), 150&#x02009;mg; Mg (MgO), 68&#x02009;mg; Mn (MnSO<sub>4</sub>.H<sub>2</sub>O), 80&#x02009;mg; Co (CoCl<sub>2</sub>), 0.3&#x02009;mg</p><p><sup>c</sup>Values were based on the chemical analysis</p><p><sup>d</sup>ME&#x02009;=&#x02009;metabolized energy</p><p><sup>e</sup>Analytical results obtained according to AOAC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par21">At the end of the feeding period (day 46), one pig from each pen was randomly selected and euthanized by electrical stunning and exsanguination after fasting approximately 12&#x02009;h. The digesta of the colon were collected, homogenized, and stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for later determination of the bacterial communities using Illumina MiSeq sequencing and microbial metabolites analyses. A sterile glass microscope slide was used to scrape mucosa as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen for later gene expression.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Chemical composition analysis</title><p id="Par22">The common nutritional components (dry matter, DM; crude protein, CP; crude fat; ash; and acid detergent fiber, ADF) in the experimental diets and <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae were analyzed according to the Association of Official Analytical Chemists (AOAC) procedures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. To determine the amino acid concentrations in <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae meal (except methionine and tryptophan), approximately 1.0&#x02009;g of each sample was digested in 10&#x02009;mL of 6&#x02009;mol/L HCl at 110&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x02009;h; the methionine concentration was measured after oxidation with performic acid, and tryptophan concentrations were determined after alkaline hydrolysis according to the AOAC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The protein linked to ADF in the experimental diets and <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae were determined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], and used to estimate the amount of chitin according to previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p><p id="Par23">Colonic SCFAs concentrations were determined by gas chromatography (GC) according to a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Lactate concentration in the colonic digesta was measured using a commercial assay kit (Nanjing Jiancheng Biological Engineering Institute, Nanjing, China) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Ammonia concentration in the colonic digesta was measured using UV spectrophotometer according to a previous method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The biogenic amines concentrations in the colonic digesta were analyzed using high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) with precolumn dansylation according to a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The concentrations of phenolic and indolic compounds were analyzed by HPLC, as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], with slight modifications. Briefly, 0.1&#x02009;g of the colonic digesta was mixed with 1.0&#x02009;mL acetonitrile. The mixture was vortexed and stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;min and then centrifuged at 3,000&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic> for 10&#x02009;min at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The supernatant was filtered through a 0.22-&#x003bc;m membrane and then analyzed on a Waters Alliance system (Alliance HPLC System e2695 separation module; Waters, Milford, MA, USA) with a multi &#x003bb; fluorescence detector (Waters 2475). Gradient elution of two mobile phases was used: mobile phase A consisted of HPLC grade water, and mobile phase B was acetonitrile. The gradient program was: 82% A initially, 55% A at 12&#x02009;min, 10% A at 22&#x02009;min, and 100% B at 23&#x02009;min. The flow rate was 1.0&#x02009;mL/min, and column temperature was 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>DNA extraction, Illumina MiSeq sequencing, and data processing</title><p id="Par24">Total genomic DNA in the colonic digesta was extracted using the QIAamp PowerFecal DNA Kit (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany), according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. DNA concentrations of all samples were quantified with the Nanodrop 1000 spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Wilmington, DE, USA). The V3-V4 regions of all bacterial 16S rRNA genes were amplified by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using the 338F universal forward primer (5&#x02032;-ACTCCTRCGGGAGGCAGCAG-3&#x02032;) and the 806R universal reverse primer (5&#x02032;-GGACTACCVGGGTATCTAAT-3&#x02032;) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The PCR products were purified using the AxyPrep DNA Gel Extraction Kit (Axygen Biosciences, Union City, CA, USA), according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The purified amplicons were pooled in equimolar concentrations from each sample and paired-end sequenced (2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;250) on an Illumina MiSeq platform (Majorbio, Shanghai, China) according to standard protocols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p><p id="Par25">The raw sequence data generated from 16S rRNA MiSeq sequencing were demultiplexed and quality-filtered using the QIIME (version 1.17) software package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Gaps in each sequence were discarded from all samples to decrease noise by screening, filtering, and pre-clustering processes as described by a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Operational taxonomic units (OTUs) were clustered with a cut-off of value 97% similarity using UPARSE (version 7.1, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://drive5.com/uparse/">http://drive5.com/uparse/</ext-link>), and chimeric sequences were identified and removed using UCHIME [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The representative sequence of each OTU was analyzed with the Ribosomal Database Project Classifier (RRID: SCR_006633) against the Silva (SSU119) 16S rRNA database at a confidence level of 90%.</p><p id="Par26">Bacterial diversity, including a rarefaction analysis, richness estimators (Chao 1 and ACE), and diversity indices (Shannon and Simpson) were calculated using MOTHUR software (version 1.35.1, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mothur.org">http://www.mothur.org</ext-link>), according to previous instructions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) was performed based on the Bray&#x02212;Curtis distance, and analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) was performed to compare the dissimilarities among the specimens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p><p id="Par27">The 16S sequencing data in this study were deposited in the National Center of Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Sequence Read Archive (SRA) database under accession number PRJNA504488.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Quantitative real-time PCR</title><p id="Par28">The quantities of total bacteria, Firmicutes, <italic>Ruminococcus, Bacteroides-Prevotella</italic>, <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster IV, <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa, <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic>, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> from each sample of colonic digesta (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8) were quantified by real-time quantitative PCR (qPCR) using specific primers (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). qPCR was performed on the CFX96 Real-Time PCR Detection System (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA) with TB Green&#x02122; Premix Ex Taq&#x02122; (Takara Biotechnology, Dalian, China). The reaction mixtures and qPCR conditions were set according to a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Mucosal RNA extraction of colon and real-time PCR</title><p id="Par29">Total RNA was extracted from the colonic mucosa with the TRIzol reagent (Takara Biotechnology, Dalian, China) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The RNA quality of every sample was quantified by Nanodrop 1000 spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Wiington, DE, USA), and the ratio (OD<sub>260</sub>: OD<sub>280</sub>) ranged from 1.8 to 2.0. Thereafter, 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g total RNA was reverse-transcribed to cDNA using a Synthesis Kit (Takara Biotechnology, Dalian, China) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Primers used for selected genes were presented in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2 in the supplemental material. Real-time PCR of the target genes and &#x003b2;-actin was performed on CFX96 Real-Time PCR Detection System (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA) with TB Green&#x02122; Premix Ex Taq&#x02122; (Takara Biotechnology, Dalian, China). The reaction mixtures and real-time PCR conditions were set according to a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The housekeeping gene &#x003b2;-actin was used to normalize the expression levels of each target gene, and according to the following formula 2<sup>&#x02212;(&#x02206;&#x02206;Ct)</sup>, where &#x02206;&#x02206;Ct&#x02009;=&#x02009;(Ct<sub>target</sub>&#x02013; Ct<sub>&#x003b2;-actin</sub>)<sub>treatment</sub> &#x02013; (Ct<sub>target</sub>&#x02013; Ct<sub>&#x003b2;-actin</sub>)<sub>control</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par30">All experimental data were analyzed using the SPSS software package (SPSS v. 20.0, SPSS Inc., Chicago IL, USA). The normality of the data distribution was confirmed by the Shapiro&#x02212;Wilk test before assessing differences between the groups. The Kruskal&#x02212;Wallis One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with the Benjamini&#x02212;Hochberg false discovery rate (FDR) multiple-testing correction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] was used to analyze non-normally distributed variables (some taxa richness data). Bacterial abundance data (at the phylum, genus, and species levels) are expressed as medians; a <italic>P-</italic>value &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was regarded as significant.</p><p id="Par31">The bacterial gene copy, metabolite concentration (lactate, SCFAs, ammonia, amines, and phenol and indole compounds), and gene expression data that were normally distributed were analyzed by One-way ANOVA with a Tukey&#x02019;s <italic>post&#x02009;hoc</italic> test. Data are expressed as means &#x000b1; standard error of mean (SEM), and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05 was regarded as significant. Correlations between mucosal gene expression and significantly changed bacterial abundances (at the genus level and qPCR, <italic>q</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) and fermentation end-products by dietary treatment were analyzed by Spearman&#x02019;s correlation analysis using GraphPad Prim version 5.0 (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA, USA). A correlation was considered significant when the absolute Spearman&#x02019;s correlation coefficient was &#x0003e;&#x02009;0.5 and significant at <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Growth performance</title><p id="Par32">During the whole trial, the pigs were considered healthy and no mortality has been observed. In this study, the H1 diet significantly increased (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) the ADG of pigs (means &#x000b1; SEM: 0.89&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03&#x02009;kg/d, 0.98&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03&#x02009;kg/d, 0.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02&#x02009;kg/d in control, H1, and H2 group, respectively) and decreased (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) the feed conversion rate (F:G) (3.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06, 2.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.12, 3.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05 in control, H1, and H2 group, respectively) compared with control and H2 diets. However, no difference in the ADFI (One-way ANOVA, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.466) was observed between the control group (means &#x000b1; SEM: 2.83&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;kg/d), H1 group (means &#x000b1; SEM: 2.77&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03&#x02009;kg/d), and H2 group (means &#x000b1; SEM: 2.87&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04&#x02009;kg/d).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Microbiota composition of the colonic digesta</title><p id="Par33">The microbial composition of the colonic digesta following the <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae treatment was revealed by 16S rRNA Illumina MiSeq sequencing. In the present study, a total of 1,031,156&#x02009;V3-V4 16S rRNA effective sequences from the 24 samples, with an average 42,954 sequences per sample, were used for subsequent analysis. The flattened rarefaction curves showed that the sampling in each group provided sufficient OTU coverage (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S1). No significant differences in species richness (as reflected by the ACE and Chao1 indices) or diversity (as reflected by Shannon and Simpson indices) were observed in the colonic digesta bacteria at the taxonomic level (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). However, the PCoA with the Bray&#x02212;Curtis distance results showed that the H1 group was separated from the control group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). AMOVA analysis also showed significant dissimilarities between the H1 and control groups (<italic>F</italic>s&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.25, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, among control, H1, and H2 groups; <italic>F</italic>s&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.63, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, H1 vs. H2; <italic>F</italic>s&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.45, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, control vs. H1; <italic>F</italic>s&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.61, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.069, control vs. H2).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> Diversity and richness of colonic digesta microbial community at the 3% dissimilarity level. The values are means &#x000b1; SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8). <bold>b</bold> Principal coordinates analysis (PCoA) of bacterial communities in the colonic digesta of pigs (based on the Bray-Curtis distance). Circles with dash line or solid indicate that groups were significantly distinct using AMOVA analysis (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). <bold>c</bold> Phylum-level relative abundance of 16S rRNA gene sequences from the colonoc digesta of pigs</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40104_2019_358_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par34">At the phylum level, the Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes were the two dominant phyla, contributing 74.99% and 22.09% to the control group, 75.75% and 21.40% to the H1 group, and 78.54% and 17.93% to the H2 group, respectively (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). Proteobacteria and Actinobacteria were the next two most dominant phyla, accounting for 1.78% and 0.19% in the control group, 1.69% and 0.55% in the H1 group, 2.17% and 0.66% in the H2 group, respectively. No significant changes were found in the abundances of any of the phyla.</p><p id="Par35">At the genus level, the 30 most predominant genera in the colonic digesta are presented as a heat map (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Figure S2). The 10 most predominant genera (those with a relative abundance &#x02265;3% in at least one treatment) were <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, unclassified Ruminococcaceae, unclassified Lachnospiraceae, <italic>Clostridium</italic>_sensu_stricto_1, unclassified Prevotellaceae, unclassified S24&#x02013;7, <italic>Prevotella</italic>, unclassified Peptostreptococcaceae, and unclassified Christensenellaceae. The relative abundance of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic>Pseudobutyrivibrio</italic>, <italic>Roseburia</italic>, <italic>Oribacterium</italic>, and <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic> increased significantly in pigs fed the H1 diet (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) compared with control diet, but the abundance of <italic>Streptococcus</italic> decreased (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). Meanwhile, the H1 diet resulted in a higher abundance of <italic>Peptococcus</italic> than that of the H2 diet (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Significantly changed bacteria genera (<bold>a</bold>) and species (<bold>b</bold>) by <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae treatments. The values were expressed as the medians (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8). Asterisks indicated statistical differences between different group (Kruskal-Wallis test): *FDR-adjusted <italic>P</italic>-value &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; ** FDR-adjusted <italic>P</italic>-value &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01. OTU, operational taxonomic unit</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40104_2019_358_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par36">At the species level, a total of 1505 OTUs was identified in the colonic digesta. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b, the relative abundance of OTUs closely related to <italic>Streptococcus pasteurianus</italic>, <italic>Streptococcus gallolyticus</italic>, <italic>Treponema</italic> sp., <italic>Ruminococcus</italic> sp., <italic>Clostridium</italic> sp., <italic>Kineothrix alysoides</italic>, <italic>Oscillibacter</italic> sp., <italic>Clostridium asparagiforme</italic>, <italic>Eubacterium</italic> sp., <italic>Prevotella</italic> sp., and <italic>Barnesiella</italic> sp. (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>) significantly decreased in pigs fed the H1 diet (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) compared with the control diet, while the relative abundance of OTUs closely related to <italic>Lactobacillus johnsonii</italic> and <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> sp. increased (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Meanwhile, the H1 diet also increased (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) the abundance of OTU closely related to <italic>Peptococcus</italic> sp. compared with the H2 diet.</p><p id="Par37">Some key bacteria groups were determined by qPCR to identify the quantitative changes in the bacterial groups in the colonic digesta following treatment with <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, the H1 diet significantly increased (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) the numbers of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster IV, and <italic>Roseburia</italic> compared with the control diet. The H2 diet also increased (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) the number of <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster IV compared with the control diet. However, no significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) were observed in the numbers of total bacteria, Firmicutes, Bacteroidetes, <italic>Ruminococcus</italic>, <italic>Prevotella</italic>, <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa, <italic>E. coli</italic>, or <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> among the different dietary treatments. Taken together, these results indicate that a diet including 4% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae meal significantly changed the colonic digesta bacterial community structure.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Response of the copy numbers (log<sub>10</sub> gene copies/g digesta sample) of major bacterial taxonomic groups in the colonic digesta of pigs toward <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae treatments. The values are means &#x000b1; SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8). Asterisks indicated statistical differences between different group (One-way ANOVA with a Tukey <italic>post hoc</italic> test): *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40104_2019_358_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Fermentation metabolites in the colonic digesta</title><p id="Par38">To explore whether feeding <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae affects the fermentation profile of the colonic digesta, some microbial metabolites were determined. For SCFAs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b), the concentrations of total SCFAs, butyrate, and isobutyrate increased significantly in pigs fed the H1 diet (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) compared with the control diet. The concentration of butyrate also increased (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) in response to the H2 diet compared with the control diet. However, the dietary treatment did not affect the acetate, propionate, branch-chain fatty acid (BCFA), valerate, or isovalerate concentrations (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05). The concentration of lactate in the colonic digesta was not affected by the dietary treatments (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Effect of the dietary inclusion of <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae on the concentration of lactate (<bold>a</bold>) and short-chain fatty acid (SCFA) (<bold>b</bold>) in the colonic digesta of pigs. The values are means &#x000b1; SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8). Asterisks indicated statistical differences between different group (One-way ANOVA with a Tukey <italic>post hoc</italic> test): *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. Abbreviations: Total SCFA, total short-chain fatty acid; BCFA, branched-chain fatty acid</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40104_2019_358_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par39">Biogenic amines and ammonia are produced from bacterial decarboxylation and deamination of amino acids, respectively. For biogenic amines (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a), cadaverine, putrescine, and tryptamine were the major biogenic amines in the colonic digesta. The concentrations of total amines, cadaverine, and tryptamine decreased significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) in pigs fed the H1 diet compared with the control diet, as well as the concentration of total amines decreased (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) compared with the H2 diet. However, the concentrations of putrescine, spermine, methylamine, tyramine, and spermidine were not affected by the different dietary treatments (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05). The dietary treatments also did not affect the ammonia concentration (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Effect of the dietary inclusion of <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae on the concentration of amino acid fermentation products in the colonic digesta of pigs: biogenic amines (<bold>a</bold>), ammonia (<bold>b</bold>), and phenolic and indole compounds (<bold>c</bold>). The values are means &#x000b1; SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8). Asterisks indicated statistical differences between different group (One-way ANOVA with a Tukey <italic>post hoc</italic> test): *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40104_2019_358_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par40">Phenol and indole compounds are derived from metabolism of aromatic amino acids by intestinal bacteria. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c, the H1 and H2 diets significantly decreased (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) the concentrations of phenol, <italic>p</italic>-cresol, and skatole compared with the control diet. However, the concentration of indole was not affected by the different dietary treatments (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05). Overall, these results indicate that a diet including <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae markedly increased the concentrations of SCFAs (total SCFAs, butyrate, and isobutyrate), but decreased the concentrations of biogenic amines as well as phenol and indole compounds in the colonic digesta, suggesting a strong impact of <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae on carbohydrate and amino acid metabolism characteristics in the colon.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Gene expression in colonic mucosa</title><p id="Par41">To assess whether feeding <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae affects the intestinal immune function, the mRNA expression of several TLR, cytokines, and tight junction proteins were determined. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, the H1 diet significantly down-regulated the relative mRNA expression of <italic>TLR-4</italic> and <italic>IFN-&#x003b3;</italic> compared with control diet (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), while up-regulated the relative mRNA expression of <italic>IL-10</italic>, <italic>ZO-1</italic>, <italic>occludin</italic>, and <italic>mucin-1</italic> (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). The H2 diet also down-regulated the relative mRNA expression of <italic>IFN-&#x003b3;</italic> compared with control diet (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), while up-regulated the relative mRNA expression <italic>ZO-1</italic> (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). However, there was no significant difference in the expression of <italic>TLR-2</italic>, <italic>TLR-5</italic>, <italic>IL-8</italic>, <italic>TNF-&#x003b1;</italic>, and <italic>mucin-2</italic> among the three groups (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Effect of the dietary inclusion of <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae on the relative mRNA expression of genes related to TLR, cytokines, and barrier function in the colonic mucosa. Asterisks indicated statistical differences between different group (One-way ANOVA with a Tukey <italic>post hoc</italic> test): *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40104_2019_358_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Correlation analysis between mucosal gene expression with colonic microbiome or bacterial fermentation metabolites</title><p id="Par42">A Spearman&#x02019;s rank correlation analysis matrix was carried out to determine whether there was any relationship among mucosal gene expression and microbial composition (abundance of bacterial genera and qPCR results) and the concentrations of metabolites (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). The correlation analysis revealed that the mRNA expression level of <italic>TLR-4</italic> was positively correlated with <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, total amines, cadaverine, skatole, and phenol (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), while negatively correlated with <italic>Peptococcus</italic> and total SCFA (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). The mRNA expression level of <italic>IFN-&#x003b3;</italic> was positively correlated with <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, total amines, cadaverine, and phenol (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), while negatively correlated with <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic>Pseudobutyrivibrio</italic>, <italic>Roseburia</italic>, <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic>, <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa, total SCFA, and butyrate (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). The mRNA expression level of <italic>IL-10</italic> was positively correlated with <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic>Peptococcus</italic>, <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa, and butyrate (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), while negatively correlated with <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, total amines, cadaverine, and phenol (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Furthermore, the mRNA expression level of <italic>ZO-1</italic> showed positive correlations with <italic>Pseudobutyrivibrio</italic>, <italic>Roseburia</italic>, <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic>, <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa, total SCFA, and butyrate (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), while showed negative correlations with <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, total amines, cadaverine, skatole, and phenol (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). The mRNA expression level of <italic>occludin</italic> was positively correlated with <italic>Roseburia</italic> and total SCFA (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), while negatively correlated <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, total amines, cadaverine, and skatole (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). The mRNA expression of <italic>mucin-1</italic> was positively correlated with <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic>, <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa, total SCFA, and butyrate (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Additionally, the correlation between bacteria and the concentrations of metabolites were also analyzed and showed in supplementary Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Figure S3. Collectively, these results indicate that the changes in the colonic digesta microbiota and metabolites were correlated with alterations of epithelial gene expression in pig.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Spearman&#x02019;s correlation analysis between the abundance of colonic microbiota (at the genus level and qPCR), microbial metabolites and mucosal gene expression level affected by dietary treatment. Cells are colored based on the correlation coefficient between the significantly changed bacteria (the relative abundance and the numbers of bacteria) and metabolites (concentrations) and mucosal gene expression level. The intensity of the colors represents the degree of association. Red represented a significant positive correlation (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), blue represents significantly negative correlation (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), and white shows that the correlation was not significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05). Total SCFA: total short-chain fatty acids</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40104_2019_358_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par43"><italic>H. illucens larvae</italic> are a novel source of dietary protein that have been used widely in the diets of animals, such as broiler chickens, laying hens, and weaning piglets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The present study, used 16S rRNA Miseq sequencing and biochemical analyses, for the first time to identify the changes in the microbiota and metabolites of the colonic digesta and mucosal immune genes expression in finishing pigs in response to administration of <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae. Our results showed that dietary supplementation with 4% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae dramatically increased the abundance and numbers of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and some butyrate-producing bacteria (<italic>Pseudobutyrivibrio</italic>, <italic>Roseburia</italic>, and <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic>), SCFAs concentrations, anti-inflammatory cytokine, and intestinal barrier genes expression in the colon, but decreased the abundance of <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, the concentrations of nitrogenous fermentation products (cadaverine, tryptamine, phenol, <italic>p</italic>-cresol, and skatole), and pro-inflammatory cytokine genes expression. The changes in the colonic mucosal gene expression were associated with changes in bacterial composition and their metabolites (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). These findings suggest that feeding low levels (about 4%) of <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae in the diet may act as a potential prebiotic for finishing pigs.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Proposed function model of <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae meal. Items with blue down-arrow indicated the decreased bacteria, metabolites, or genes expression in the <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae diet group compared with the control diet, whereas those with a red up-arrow indicated the decreased ones in the <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae diet group. Total SCFAs: total short-chain fatty acids; <italic>IFN-&#x003b3;</italic>: interferon-&#x003b3;; <italic>IL-10</italic>: interleukin-10; <italic>TLR-4</italic>: Toll-like receptors-4; <italic>TNF-&#x003b1;</italic>, tumor necrosis factor-&#x003b1;; <italic>ZO-1</italic>: Zona occludens protein 1</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40104_2019_358_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec17"><title><italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae significantly alter the colonic microbiota structure of finishing pigs</title><p id="Par44">Diet composition is the major factor that affects the gastrointestinal tract microbiota [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. In the present study, a diet including 4% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae caused a significant difference in the colonic microbial composition compared with the control group, as revealed by the Bray&#x02013;Curtis PCoA and AMOVA analyses. The univariate statistical analysis indicated that a <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae meal (in 4% supplementation) markedly increased the abundance of many potentially beneficial bacteria and reduced the abundance of potentially opportunistic pathogens compared with control diet. Among the genera affected by the <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae, bacterial species, such as <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> markedly increased in the H1 pigs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). The <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae treatment also increased the numbers of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> in laying hens by an average of 7.44-fold [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> mainly exerts health-promoting effects on gut physiology and is generally considered a potentially beneficial microbe. Thus, these results suggest that <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae increased the potentially beneficial bacteria. Meanwhile, <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae also increased some butyrate-producing bacteria, such as <italic>Roseburia</italic>, <italic>Pseudobutyrivibrio</italic>, and <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic> in the colon (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). Some species within the genera <italic>Roseburia</italic>, <italic>Pseudobutyrivibrio</italic>, and <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic> together with butyrate, are essential for maintaining the intestinal metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], and have many beneficial effects for colonic homeostasis by promoting epithelial energy metabolism and stimulating immune development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. In addition, another important finding was that <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae significantly increased the number of <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa bacteria (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Bacteria within <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa are regarded as a predominant population and are butyrate producers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. which play a crucial role in maintaining gut health. Therefore, the increase in the abundance of <italic>Roseburia</italic>, <italic>Pseudobutyrivibrio</italic>, and <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic> and the number of <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa in the colon indicate that carbohydrate metabolism by bacteria may have been affected by administration <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae.</p><p id="Par45">On the other hand, diet including 4% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae markedly decreased the abundance of <italic>Streptococcus</italic> compared with the control diet (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). Some bacteria within the genus S<italic>treptococcus</italic>, including <italic>S. gallolyticus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] and <italic>S. pasteurianus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] are opportunistic pathogens that induce diarrhea in pigs or are associated with digestive tract malignancies, respectively. An increase in the abundance of S<italic>treptococcus</italic> has been reported in the feces of patients with colorectal cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Thus, the decrease in the abundance of <italic>Streptococcus</italic> suggests that the dietary inclusion of 4% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae may have beneficial to intestinal health for finishing pigs.</p><p id="Par46">Until now, the exact mechanism for the change in the colonic microbiota by <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae has remained unclear. <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae contain chitin (about 4.65% in the present study), which serves as a substrate for gut microbiota and then alters their composition. Previous studies have indicated that low-level chitin restores the compositional balance in the microbial communities of humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] or mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae also have a high concentration of the medium-chain fatty acid (MCFA) lauric acid (C12:0, about 28% of total fatty acids in the present study, unpublished data), which is a natural antimicrobial agent and particularly active against Gram-positive bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Furthermore, <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae are also a potential source of antimicrobial peptides (AMP) and have broad-spectrum activity against both Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Therefore, administering <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae regulates the microbiota in the colon probably through chitin, lauric acid, and/or AMPs, but should be further studied to clarify the underlying mechanisms.</p><p id="Par47">Additionally, we found that dietary inclusion of 8% <italic>H. illucens</italic> did not result in beneficial effects on the colonic microbiota in the current trial. To the best of our knowledge, the current study is the first to test partially <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae inclusion in the diets of finishing pigs. Therefore, the available information on the effect of dietary <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae inclusion on gut microbiota of finishing pigs is very limited. As mentioned above, <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae contain chitin, which is not digestible by monogastric animals. A previous study has indicated that low concentrations of chitin might increase the number of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and decrease <italic>E.coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> in the intestine of broilers, while high concentrations of chitin have adverse effects on these bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. In weaning piglets, 8% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae diet had lower counts of Lactobacilli than the control and 4% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae diet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Thus, dietary inclusion of 8% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae had no positive effects on the microbiota may be due to the higher level of chitin in the diets. Additionally, recent studies have indicated that insects contain non-protein nitrogen, such as chitin, nucleic acids, ammonia, nitrites, etc., could lead to an overestimation of the insect protein content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. In the present study, we used the conventional nitrogen-to-protein conversion factor value of 6.25 to express the protein content of <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae, which may result the true protein content in the diet and colonic digesta were lower in the H2 group than in the control group. A previous study has showed that non-protein nitrogen can inhibit the growth of beneficial bacteria, such as <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic>, and <italic>Megasphaera</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] Therefore, additionally potential explanation for had no beneficial effects on the colonic microbiota may be an increasing of non-protein nitrogen content when pigs fed the dietary inclusion of 8% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae, but further study will be required to elucidate the underlying mechanisms. Nevertheless, our findings suggest that dietary inclusion of 4% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae altered the microbiota structure of finishing pigs toward a host-friendly gut environment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae significantly increase SCFA concentrations in the colon of finishing pigs</title><p id="Par48">A change in intestinal microbiota is often accompanied by changes in microbial metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Undigested carbohydrates in stomach and small intestine can be fermented by microbes with the production of SCFAs in the large intestine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. SCFAs, including acetate, propionate, and butyrate, play an important role in the metabolic functions of the gut. In the present study, the <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae induced an increase in the concentration of total SCFAs and butyrate. Previous studies also observed that <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae as a soybean meal substitute increase the concentration of SCFAs in the cecum of laying hens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. This increase may have been the result of an increased abundance or the number of microbes capable of producing butyrate in the colon. The correlation analysis indicated the trophic linkage between the abundance of <italic>Roseburia</italic>, <italic>Pseudobutyrivibrio</italic>, <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic>, the number of <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa and butyrate concentration in the colonic digesta, suggesting that the increase in <italic>Roseburia</italic>, <italic>Pseudobutyrivibrio</italic>, <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic>, and <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa may have resulted in the increase in colonic butyrate concentration. Additionally, <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae are rich in chitin, which can not be degraded or absorbed by the small intestine but can flow into the large intestine, and subsequently be fermented by bacteria in large intestine. Thus, another potential explanation for the increase in butyrate concentration may be attributed to the alteration of substrate for microbial fermentation after administering <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae. Butyrate is the major energy source for colonic epithelial cells and exerts an anti-inflammatory function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Therefore, the increase in butyrate concentration in the current study suggests a host-friendly gut environment after administering <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae markedly decrease the end products of amino acid fermentation</title><p id="Par49">Undigested protein or other nitrogenous compounds, such as amino acids, are fermented by microbes to produce BCFAs, biogenic amines, ammonia, phenol and indole compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In the present study, <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae markedly impacted the nitrogen metabolic profiles. For biogenic amines, cadaverine and putrescine are the most abundant amines and are formed from decarboxylation of lysine, arginine and ornithine, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. A diet including 4% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae markedly decreased the concentrations of total amines and cadaverine compared with the control group, suggesting decreased microbial amino acid decarboxylation, which may be attributed to a decrease in the abundance of amines-producing bacteria in the colon. Our correlation analysis showed that the decreases in total amines and cadaverine were positively correalted with the decreased abundance of <italic>Streptococcus</italic>. This finding is consistent with some previous studies, showing that <italic>Streptococcus</italic> bacteria have amine-producing ability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. High levels of biogenic amines, such as cadaverine, might be toxic to gut health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Thus, the decrease in total amines and cadaverine concentrations by <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae may extert a beneficial effect on gut health.</p><p id="Par50">On the other hand, administering <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae also altered the aromatic amino acid metabolism by bacteria in the colon. Tryptophan, an aromatic amino acid, can be decarboxylated into tryptamine by gut bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In the present study, diet including 4% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae decreased the tryptamine concentration in the colonic digesta. Tryptamine induces serotonin secretion by enterochromaffin cells and subsequently regulates intestinal motility and platelet function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Therefore, the decrease in tryptamine may affect intestinal function. In addition, <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae also reduced the concentrations of phenol, <italic>p</italic>-cresol, and skatole, indicating that bacterial fermentation of tryptophan and tyrosine decreased. Phenol and <italic>p</italic>-cresol are produced from tyrosine catabolism by gut bacteria, while skatole is derived from tryptophan catabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], and are regarded as co-carcinogens and colon cancer promoter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Thus, the decrease in the concentrations of phenolic and indolic compounds in the current study indicates that <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae may have a beneficial effect on gut health. In general, together with the increase in SCFAs, our findings clearly indicate an evident change in microbial metabolic activity, with higher microbial carbohydrate fermentation and lower microbial catabolism of amino acids after the <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae treatment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae affected the colonic mucosal response involved in colonic health</title><p id="Par51">The change of intestinal microbiota and their metabolites could affect intestinal immunity of host. In the current study, diet including <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae (especially supplementation with 4% group) down-regulated mRNA expression of <italic>TLR4</italic> and pro-inflammatory cytokines <italic>IFN-&#x003b3;</italic>, while up-regulated the expression of anti-inflammatory cytokines <italic>IL-10</italic> in the colonic mucosa. As the novel receptors, TLR can mediate innate immune responses, recognize microbiota and their products and then initiate pro-inflammatory pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Some species of <italic>Streptococcus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>] and their products (amines, indolic and phenolic compounds) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] can trigger intestinal inflammation through <italic>TLR4</italic> signaling pathways, while SCFAs-producing bacteria and SCFAs can down-regulate the pro-inflammatory responses through <italic>TLR4-NFkB</italic> signaling pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. In particular, the correlation analysis also revealed that the down-regulation in the expressions of <italic>TLR4</italic> and pro-inflammatory cytokines (<italic>IFN-&#x003b3;</italic>) positively correlated with the decreased abundance of <italic>Streptococcus</italic> and the concentrations of total amines, cadaverine, and phenol, while negatively correlated with the increase in butyrate-producing bacteria (<italic>Psedobutyrivibrio</italic>, <italic>Roseburia</italic>, <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic>, <italic>Clostridium</italic> cluster XIVa) and the concentrations total SCFA, and butyrate (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Thus, the down-regulation gene expression levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines while up-regulation of the anti-inflammatory cytokine after the <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae treatment may be attributed to enrichments of some butyrate-producing bacteria and SCFAs concentrations, and the depression of potential pathogen (<italic>Streptococcus</italic>) abundance and several toxic compounds concentrations.</p><p id="Par52">As the critical line, the intestinal barrier can protect against pathogenic agents and luminal antigens. In the current study, dietary inclusion of <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae up-regulated the expression of intestinal barrier genes expression in the colonic mucosa, such as <italic>ZO-1</italic>, <italic>occludin</italic>, and <italic>mucin-1</italic>, suggesting that <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae may enhance the integrity of the mucous layer, and then generate a host-friendly gut environment which can defend against pathogen infection. To the best of our knowledge, our study is the first to test partially <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae inclusion in the diets of finishing pigs, and the available information on the effect of dietary <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae inclusion on mucosal response involved in colonic health is very limited. A previous study has shown that SCFAs, especially butyrate can maintain the gut integrity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. As mentioned above, diet inclusion of <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae increased the concentrations of total SCFAs and butyrate, and correlation analysis also revealed that the total SCFAs and butyrate concentrations and SCFA-producing bacteria were positively correlated with mRNA expression levels of <italic>ZO-1</italic>, <italic>occludin</italic>, and <italic>mucin-1</italic>. Therefore, the high total SCFAs and butyrate concentrations and the abundance or counts of SCFA-producing bacteria after the <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae treatment may lead to up-regulation of intestinal barrier genes expression, but further studies will be required to clarify the underlying mechanisms. Nonetheless, these findings suggest that diet inclusion of <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae down-regulated the expression of pro- inflammatory genes, while up-regulated the expression of anti-inflammatory and intestinal barrier genes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par53">In conclusion, the present study demonstrates that dietary supplementation with 4% <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae meal significantly altered colonic microbial composition, metabolic profiles, and immune status of finishing pigs, likely toward a host-friendly gut environment. Colonic bacteria, such as <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> and several butyrate-producing bacteria were increased after <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae supplementation, whereas the abundance of <italic>Streptococcus</italic> was decreased. Intestinal metabolism was altered by <italic>H. illucens</italic> larvae, as evidenced by the increase in the concentrations of SCFAs, and the decrease in the concentrations of metabolites involved in amino-acid metabolism. The colonic mucosal mRNA expression of <italic>TLR-4</italic> and pro-inflammatory cytokines were decreased, while the expression of anti-inflammatory and intestinal barrier genes were increased. Furthermore, the changes in the microbiota composition and metabolites concentrations were associated with the alterations in the colonic mucosal immune homeostasis and barrier function. These findings provide a new perspective on insect meal as a sustainable protein source rich in nutrients for swine feed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec22"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="40104_2019_358_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S1.</bold> Primers used for quantification in this study. (DOCX 16 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="40104_2019_358_MOESM2_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S2.</bold> Primers used for host genes in this study. (DOCX 15 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="40104_2019_358_MOESM3_ESM.tif"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S1.</bold> Rarefaction curves comparing the number of sequences with the number of phylotypes found in the 16S rRNA gene libraries from the microbiota in the digesta of the colon of pigs. (TIF 12962 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="40104_2019_358_MOESM4_ESM.tif"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S2.</bold> Influence of <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> larvae meal on the 30 most abundant genera in the colonic digesta. The color represents the relative abundance of bacteria. (TIF 15073 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="40104_2019_358_MOESM5_ESM.tif"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S3.</bold> Spearman&#x02019;s correlation analysis between the abundance of colonic microbiota (at the genus level and qPCR) and microbial metabolites affected by dietary treatment. Cells are colored based on the correlation coefficient between the significantly changed bacteria (the relative abundance and the numbers of bacteria) and metabolites (concentrations). The intensity of the colors represents the degree of association. Red represented a significant positive correlation (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), blue represents significantly negative correlation (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), and white shows that the correlation was not significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05). Total SCFA: total short-chain fatty acids. (TIF 9517 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AMOVA</term><def><p id="Par4">Analysis of molecular variance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BCFA</term><def><p id="Par5">Branched-chain fatty acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FDR</term><def><p id="Par6">False discovery rate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IFN-&#x003b3;</term><def><p id="Par7">Interferon-&#x003b3;</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IL</term><def><p id="Par8">Interleukin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OTU</term><def><p id="Par9">Operational taxonomic units</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCoA</term><def><p id="Par10">Principal coordinate analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><bold>S</bold>CFAs</term><def><p id="Par11">Short-chain fatty acids</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TLR</term><def><p id="Par12">Toll-like receptors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TNF-&#x003b1;</term><def><p id="Par13">Tumor necrosis factor-&#x003b1;</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ZO-1</term><def><p id="Par14">Zona occludens protein 1</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank Dr. Dun Deng, Dr. Zhichang Liu, Ms. Zhimei Tian, and Ms. Yiyan Cui for their help in the successful completion of this study.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par54">This study was supported by the Presidential Foundation of the Guangdong Academy of Agricultural Sciences (201802B, 201621) and Guangdong Modern Agro-industry Technology Research System (2016LM1080, 2017LM1080). We also would like to thank EditorBar (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://online.editorbar.com">http://online.editorbar.com</ext-link>) for English language editing.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par55">The datasets supporting the conclusions of this article are included within the article.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>MY, WDC, and XYM conceived and designed the whole trial; ZML and TR conducted the pig trial; MY and ZML conducted laboratory analyses. MY, XYM, and GW wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par56">The experimental proposals and procedures for the care and treatment of the pigs were approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee of Guangdong Academy of Agricultural Sciences (authorization number GAASIAS-2016-017).</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par57">Not applicable</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par58">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO)</collab></person-group><article-title>Edible insects &#x02013; prospects for food and feed security</article-title><source>FAO Forestry Paper No. 171</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc><publisher-name>FAO</publisher-name><fpage>ix</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makkar</surname><given-names>HPS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Heuz&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ankers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>State-of-the-art on use of insects as animal feed</article-title><source>Anim Feed Sci Tech.</source><year>2014</year><volume>197</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2014.07.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Huis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential of insects as food and feed in assuring food security</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><year>2013</year><volume>58</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-ento-120811-153704</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23020616?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23020616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barragan-Fonseca</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Loon</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutritional value of the black soldier fly (<italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> L) and its suitability as animal feed&#x02013;a review</article-title><source>J Insects Food Feed</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3920/JIFF2016.0055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cutrignelli</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tulli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Randazzo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivotto</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of an insect meal of the black soldier Fly (<italic>Hermetia illucens</italic>) as soybean substitute: intestinal morphometry, enzymatic and microbial activity in laying hens</article-title><source>Res Vet Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2017.12.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29304440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29304440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maurer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Holinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Amsler</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fr&#x000fc;h</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wohlfahrt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Replacement of soybean cake by <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> meal in diets for layers</article-title><source>J Insects Food Feed.</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3920/JIFF2015.0071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spranghers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Michiels</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrancx</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ovyn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eeckhout</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Clercq</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gut antimicrobial effects and nutritional value of black soldier fly (<italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> L) prepupae for weaned piglets</article-title><source>Anim Feed Sci Tech</source><year>2018</year><volume>235</volume><fpage>S0377840117307721</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2017.08.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wa&#x0015b;ko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Polak-Berecka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Polakowski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieganowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The first report of the physicochemical structure of chitin isolated from <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic></article-title><source>Int J Biol Macromol</source><year>2016</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>316</fpage><lpage>320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2016.07.038</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27422042?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27422042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of chitosan as growth promoter on diarrhea, nutrient apparent digestibility, fecal microbiota and immune response in weaned piglets</article-title><source>J Applied Anim Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1437</fpage><lpage>1442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09712119.2018.1531763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cullere</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasoniero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Giaccone</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Miotti-Scapin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Claeys</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De Smet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Black soldier fly as dietary protein source for broiler quails: apparent digestibility, excreta microbial load, feed choice, performance, carcass and meat traits</article-title><source>Animal.</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1923</fpage><lpage>1930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731116001270</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27339654?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27339654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borrelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Coretti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dipineto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bovera</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Menna</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiariotti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insect-based diet, a promising nutritional source, modulates gut microbiota composition and SCFAs production in laying hens</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16269</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-16560-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29176587?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29176587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Holzman</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Butyrate enhances the intestinal aarrier by facilitating tight junction assembly via activation of AMP-activated protein kinase in Caco-2 cell monolayers</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><year>2009</year><volume>139</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1619</fpage><lpage>1625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/jn.109.104638</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19625695?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19625695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rist</surname><given-names>VTS</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Eklund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosenthin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of dietary protein on microbiota composition and activity in the gastrointestinal tract of piglets in relation to gut health: a review</article-title><source>Animal.</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1067</fpage><lpage>1078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731113000062</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23410993?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23410993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davila</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Blachier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotteland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Andriamihaja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Benetti</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Re-print of &#x0201c;intestinal luminal nitrogen metabolism: role of the gut microbiota and consequences for the host&#x0201d;</article-title><source>Pharmacol Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>68</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phrs.2012.11.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23183532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23183532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Black soldier fly (<italic>Hermetia illucens</italic>) larvae enhances immune activities and increases survivability of broiler chicks against experimental infection of <italic>Salmonella Gallinarum</italic></article-title><source>J Vet Med Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>736</fpage><lpage>740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.17-0236</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29657236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29657236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">AOAC. Official methods of analysis. 18th ed. Gaithersburg, MD: Association of Official Analytical Chemists. 2007.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NRC. Nutrient requirements of swine. 11th ed Washington, DC: Natl Acad Press. 2012.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increases in circulating amino acids with in- feed antibiotics correlated with gene expression of intestinal amino acid transporters in piglets</article-title><source>Amino Acids</source><year>2017</year><volume>49</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1587</fpage><lpage>1599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00726-017-2451-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28623466?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28623466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">AOAC. Official methods of analysis, 18th ed. AOAC Int, Arlington, VA. 2004.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bovera</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Loponte</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Marono</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Piccolo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Iaconisi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of larvae meal as protein source in broiler diet: effect on growth performance, nutrient digestibility, and carcass and meat traits</article-title><source>J Anim Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>94</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/jas.2015-9201</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27065134?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27065134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term effects of early antibiotic intervention on blood parameters, apparent nutrient digestibility, and fecal microbial fermentation profile in pigs with different dietary protein levels</article-title><source>J Anim Sci Biotechnol</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>60</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40104-017-0192-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28781770?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28781770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaney</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marbach</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modified reagents for determination of urea and ammonia</article-title><source>Clin Chem</source><year>1962</year><volume>8</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><?supplied-pmid 13878063?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13878063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of biogenic amines in digesta by high performance liquid chromatography with precolumn dansylation</article-title><source>Anal Lett</source><year>2014</year><volume>47</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1290</fpage><lpage>1298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00032719.2013.871550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sch&#x000fc;ssler</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nitschke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Death of fish due to surface water pollution by liquid manure or untreated wastewater: analytical preservation of evidence by HPLC</article-title><source>Water Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>33</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2884</fpage><lpage>2887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0043-1354(98)00507-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterising the bacterial microbiota across the gastrointestinal tracts of dairy cattle: membership and potential function</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>16116</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep16116</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26527325?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26527325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauber</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg-Lyons</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Huntley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fierer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ultra-high-throughput microbial community analysis on the Illumina HiSeq and MiSeq platforms</article-title><source>ISME J.</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1621</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2012.8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22402401?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22402401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Polson</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuur</surname><given-names>EAG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of nutrient deposition on bacterial communities in Arctic tundra soil</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1842</fpage><lpage>1854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2010.02189.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20236166?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20236166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Time-course responses of ileal and fecal microbiota and metabolite profiles to antibiotics in cannulated pigs</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biot</source><year>2018</year><volume>102</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2289</fpage><lpage>2299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-018-8774-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Search and clustering orders of magnitude faster than BLAST</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>2460</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq461</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20709691?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20709691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schloss PD, Westcott SL, Thomas R, Hall JR, Martin H, Hollister EB, et al. Introducing mothur: open-source, platform-independent, community-supported software for describing and comparing microbial communities. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title><source>J R Stat Soc</source><year>1995</year><volume>57</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>300</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gratz</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheridan</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of diet on the gut microbiota</article-title><source>Pharmacol Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>69</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phrs.2012.10.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23147033?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23147033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of the gut microbiota in nutrition and health</article-title><source>Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>577</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrgastro.2012.156</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22945443?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22945443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hold</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The gut microbiota, bacterial metabolites and colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>661</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3344</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25198138?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25198138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the effects of diet on bacterial metabolism in the large intestine</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>102</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1197</fpage><lpage>1208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2007.03322.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boleij</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tjalsma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The itinerary of <italic>Streptococcus gallolyticus</italic> infection in patients with colonic malignant disease</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(13)70107-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23831427?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23831427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janda</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genus <italic>Streptococcus</italic> &#x02013; part I: emerging pathogens in the &#x0201c;<italic>Pyogenic Cocci</italic>&#x0201d; and the &#x0201c; <italic>Streptococcus bovis</italic> &#x0201d; groups</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Newsl</source><year>2014</year><volume>36</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinmicnews.2014.10.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural segregation of gut microbiota between colorectal cancer patients and healthy volunteers</article-title><source>ISME J</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>320</fpage><lpage>329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2011.109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21850056?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21850056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Terada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Higashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of dietary chitosan on faecal microbiota and faecal metabolites of humans</article-title><source>Microb Ecol Health Dis</source><year>2011</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/08910609509141377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neyrinck</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Possemiers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstraete</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Backer</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cani</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Delzenne</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary modulation of <italic>clostridial</italic> cluster XIVa gut bacteria ( <italic>Roseburia</italic> spp.) by chitin&#x02013;glucan fiber improves host metabolic alterations induced by high-fat diet in mice</article-title><source>J Nutr Biochem</source><year>2012</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jnutbio.2010.10.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21411304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21411304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decuypere</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dierick</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The combined use of triacylglycerols containing medium-chain fatty acids and exogenous lipolytic enzymes as an alternative to in-feed antibiotics in piglets: concept, possibilities and limitations. An overview</article-title><source>Nutr Res Rev</source><year>2003</year><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/NRR200369</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19087389?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19087389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sk&#x00159;ivanov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Marounek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dlouh&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ka&#x00148;ka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Susceptibility of <italic>Clostridium perfringens</italic> to C-C fatty acids</article-title><source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1472-765X.2005.01709.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15960756?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15960756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insect antimicrobial peptides and their applications</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotech</source><year>2014</year><volume>98</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>5807</fpage><lpage>5822</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-014-5792-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khempaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chitsatchapong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Molee</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of chitin and protein constituents in shrimp head meal on growth performance, nutrient digestibility, intestinal microbial populations, volatile fatty acids, and ammonia production in broilers</article-title><source>J Appl Poul Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/japr.2010-00162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincken</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Brock</surname><given-names>LAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fogliano</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakemond</surname><given-names>CMM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen-to-protein conversion factors for three edible insects: <italic>Tenebrio molitor</italic>, <italic>Alphitobius diaperinus</italic>, and <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic></article-title><source>J Agri Food Chem</source><year>2017</year><volume>65</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2275</fpage><lpage>2278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.7b00471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nery</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dabbou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiavone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein composition and digestibility of black soldier fly larvae in broiler chickens revisited according to the recent nitrogen-protein conversion ratio</article-title><source>J Insects Food Feed</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3920/JIFF2018.0006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsuoka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Namioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of nonprotein nitrogen in pigs: effects of dietary urea on the intestinal microflora</article-title><source>Am J Vet Res</source><year>1985</year><volume>46</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>962</lpage><?supplied-pmid 4014847?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4014847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The colonic microbiome and epithelial transcriptome are altered in rats fed a high-protein diet compared with a normal-protein diet</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><year>2016</year><volume>146</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>474</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/jn.115.223990</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26843585?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26843585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tremaroli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;ckhed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional interactions between the gut microbiota and host metabolism</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>71</volume><issue>7415</issue><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Marked response in microbial community and metabolism in the ileum and cecum of suckling piglets after early antibiotics xxposure</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1166</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01166</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29899739?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29899739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Athanasiou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashrafian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the role of gut microbiome&#x02013;host metabolic signal disruption in health and disease</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>19</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2011.05.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21684749?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21684749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shastri</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Phoebe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Indigenous bacteria from the gut microbiota regulate host serotonin biosynthesis</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>161</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2015.02.047</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25860609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25860609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Libudzisz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of phenol, p-cresol and indole on growth and survival of intestinal lactic acid bacteria</article-title><source>Anaerobe.</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anaerobe.2005.10.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16701619?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16701619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abreu</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toll-like receptor signalling in the intestinal epithelium: how bacterial recognition shapes intestinal function</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri2707</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20098461?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20098461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PI3K/Akt/mTOR signaling pathway participates in <italic>Streptococcus</italic> uberis-induced inflammation in mammary epithelial cells in concert with the classical TLRs/NF-&#x00138;B pathway</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2018.10.031</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30473339?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30473339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The response of colonic mucosa-associated microbiota composition, mucosal immune homeostasis, and barrier function to early-life galactooligosaccharides intervention in suckling piglets</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2018</year><volume>67</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.8b05679</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>