<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In a related study, GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) developed a series of 3-aminomethylbenzoxaborole derivatives 
 <bold>4</bold> and 
 <bold>5</bold> that target 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis (Mtb)</italic> LeuRS [
 <xref rid="B20-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The boron atom in the molecules was critical for 
 <italic>Mtb</italic> LeuRS activity since it forms a bidentate covalent adduct with the terminal nucleotide of tRNA, Ade76, and traps the 3′ end of tRNA
 <sup>Leu</sup> in the editing site to inhibit leucylation and thus protein synthesis. The (
 <italic>S</italic>)-aminomethyl side chain at C-3 in 
 <bold>4</bold> and 
 <bold>5</bold> was critical for binding, and C-4 halogen atoms (Cl and Br) significantly improved 
 <italic>Mtb</italic> LeuRS activity, antitubercular activity against 
 <italic>Mtb</italic> H37Rv, and selectivity against other bacteria. However, potential toxicity issues from the inhibition of mammalian cytoplasmic LeuRS and tolerance issues of 
 <bold>5</bold> in a once daily dose of 50 mg/kg in a mouse acute tuberculosis (TB) infection model caused serious concerns for its use as a TB drug in long-term therapy. Throughout a series of medicinal chemistry campaigns to examine the structure–activity relationship (SAR) of 3-aminomethylbenzoxaborole derivatives, compounds 
 <bold>6</bold>–
 <bold>10</bold> were found to improve both selectivity against human cytoplasmic LeuRS and HepG2 cell toxicity compared with 
 <bold>4</bold> and 
 <bold>5</bold>, presumably by decreased lipophilicity and increased polarity in the molecule (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biomolecules-10-01625-f004">Figure 4</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B21-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Triaging lead compounds through in vivo pharmacokinetic (PK) analysis and efficacy assays using acute and chronic mouse TB infection models identified 
 <bold>8</bold> (GSK656) as a preclinical candidate for tuberculosis; 
 <bold>8</bold> successfully completed its first-time-in-human (FTIH) study to evaluate the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics, and food effects of single (5, 15, and 25 mg) and repeat oral doses (5 and 15 mg, 14 days, qd [quaque die, once a day]; NCT03075410) [
 <xref rid="B22-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Moreover, 
 <bold>8</bold> is currently in a phase 2 clinical trial for drug-sensitive pulmonary tuberculosis to evaluate its early bacterial activity, safety, and tolerability (NCT03557281). Details of the clinical studies of 
 <bold>8</bold> will be discussed in a later section.
</p>
