<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The previous work of Kapchina-Toteva et al. [
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-24-01913" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>] also investigated the effect of micropropagation on the essential oil content in leaf extracts of 
 <italic class="italic">Lamium album</italic> L. plants grown under in vitro and ex vitro conditions in contrast to in situ-grown plants. The in situ-grown plants were found to consist of 45 hydrocarbons, and as a result of micropropagation, the content of these compounds reduced about two-fold, reaching 24 during in vitro cultivation, and finally 19 after ex vitro acclimation. Moreover, while the in situ plants were characterized by the accumulation of long-chain alkanes (nonadecane; heneicosane; heptadecane; tricosane), both in vitro and ex vitro plants contained shorter hydrocarbons such as octane (3.9% and 1.1%, respectively) and undecane (3.0% in in vitro samples). Besides, certain alcohols such as phytol; octen-3-ol; 3-hexene-1-ol and acetate were observed to rise in micropropagated plants compared to in situ-grown ones. As for terpenes, 60 compounds were detected in the oil of in situ plants while it decreased in both in vitro and ex vitro ones—44 and 35 compounds. A variation in the terpene composition was also detected. The major sesquiterpenes in the in situ-grown plants were germacrene D (6.9%) and β-caryophyllene E (1.1%). In the course of micropropagation, elevated accumulation of these compounds was observed in both, in vitro- and ex vitro-grown plants [germacrene D (44.1% and 46.7%, correspondingly) and β-caryophyllene E (13.0% and 6.5%, correspondingly)]. Therefore, these results demonstrated the significance of growing conditions which were accountable for the variability in the level and composition of plant metabolites. The chemical structure of the main volatile secondary metabolites from 
 <italic class="italic">Lamium</italic> species are represented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01913-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>.
</p>
