<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>
  <bold>Background:</bold>
  <italic>Gynura</italic> species have been used traditionally to treat various ailments, such as fever, pain, and to control blood glucose level. This systematic review critically discusses studies regarding 
  <italic>Gynura</italic> species that exhibited antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects, thus providing perspectives and instructions for future research of the plants as a potential source of new dietary supplements or medicinal agents.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Methods:</bold> A literature search from internet databases of PubMed, Scopus, Science Direct, e-theses Online Service, and ProQuest was carried out using a combination of keywords such as “
  <italic>Gynura</italic>,” “antioxidant,” “anti-inflammatory,” or other related words. Research articles were included in this study if they were experimental (
  <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
  <italic>in vivo</italic>) or clinical studies on the antioxidant or anti-inflammatory effects of 
  <italic>Gynura</italic> species and if they were articles published in English.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Results:</bold> Altogether, 27 studies on antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects of 
  <italic>Gynura</italic> species were selected. The antioxidant effects of 
  <italic>Gynura</italic> species were manifested by inhibition of reactive oxygen species production and lipid peroxidation, modulation of glutathione-related parameters, and enzymatic antioxidant production or activities. The anti-inflammatory effects of 
  <italic>Gynura</italic> species were through the modulation of inflammatory cytokine production, inhibition of prostaglandin E
  <sub>2</sub> and nitric oxide production, cellular inflammatory-related parameters, and inflammation in animal models. The potential anti-inflammatory signaling pathways modulated by 
  <italic>Gynura</italic> species are glycogen synthase kinase-3, nuclear factor erythroid 2-related factor 2, PPARγ, MAPK, NF-κB, and PI3K/Akt. However, most reports on antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects of the plants were on crude extracts, and the chemical constituents contributing to bioactivities were not clearly understood. There is a variation in quality of studies in terms of design, conduct, and interpretation, and in-depth studies on the underlying mechanisms involved in antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects of the plants are in demand. Moreover, there is limited clinical study on antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects of 
  <italic>Gynura</italic> species.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Conclusion:</bold> This review highlighted antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects of genus 
  <italic>Gynura</italic> and supported their traditional uses to treat oxidative stress and inflammatory-related diseases. This review is expected to catalyze further studies on genus 
  <italic>Gynura</italic>. However, extensive preclinical data need to be generated from toxicity and pharmacokinetic studies before clinical studies can be pursued for their development into clinical medicines to treat oxidative stress and inflammatory conditions.
 </p>
</abstract>
