<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The flow rate of helium through the column was kept at 1.2 mL·min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>. The initial temperature of the column was 45 °C, then it was increased to 200 °C at a rate of 5 °C·min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> (kept constant for 10 min), and then heated up to a final temperature of 250 °C at a rate of 5 °C min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>. The oven was kept at this temperature for 20 min. The injector temperature was 250 °C, the transfer line temperature was 280 °C, and the ion source temperature was 230 °C. The solvent delay was 4 min. The scan range of the MSD was set at 40 to 550 m
 <italic class="italic">m</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">z</italic>. The total running time for a sample was about 71 min. The relative percentage of the essential oil constituents was evaluated from the total peak area (TIC) by apparatus software [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-24-00606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-24-00606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. Essential oil constituents were identified by comparison of their mass spectra with those stored in the Wiley NBS75K.L and NIST/EPA/NIH (2002 version, National Institute of Standards and Technology, Gaithersburg, MD, USA) mass spectral libraries using various search engines (PBM, Nist02). The identity of compounds was also confirmed by comparison of their calculated retention indices with those reported in NIST Chemistry WebBook (
 <uri xlink:href="http://webbook.nist.gov/chemistry/" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://webbook.nist.gov/chemistry/</uri>). For retention indices (RI) calculation [
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-24-00606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-molecules-24-00606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>], a mixture of homologus series of n-alkanes C
 <sub class="sub">7</sub>-C
 <sub class="sub">40</sub> (Supelco, Bellefonte, PA, USA) was used, under the same chromatographic conditions which were applied for the analysis of the lavender essential oils.
</p>
