<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Animal experimental protocols were approved (October 29, 2013) by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee, University of Malaya (UM IACUC - Ethics reference no. 2013-09-17/MOL/R/TNH). Female athymic NCr nude mice (4 weeks old) were purchased from InVivos, Singapore. The mice were housed under specific pathogen-free environment with temperature set between 22 ± 2 °C under 12 h light/dark cycle and relative humidity of 60 ± 10%. All the mice were given an unlimited supply of sterile food (Altromin #1324 Rodent Maintenance Diet, Denmark) and water. The mice were quarantined and acclimatized to laboratory conditions for 14 days prior to experimental procedures. 17β-estradiol (E
 <sub>2</sub>) silastic capsules containing 1:31 of E
 <sub>2</sub> and cholesterol in a total of 3 mg (
 <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Ju et al., 2006</xref>) were implanted subcutaneously in dorsal flank of the mice (
 <italic>n</italic> = 12). Four days after the implantation, 200 µL of an equal mixture of MCF7 cells (1 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> cells) and Matrigel™ was injected subcutaneously into the mammary fat pad of the mice. Tumor growth was monitored over time using an electronic caliper. Tumor volume (mm
 <sup>3</sup>) was determined using the following formula (
 <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Faustino-Rocha et al., 2013</xref>): 
 <disp-formula id="NONUM-d2e650">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="peerj-08-9650-e001.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" position="float" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}\begin{eqnarray*}\text{Tumor volume} ({\text{mm}}^{\text{3}})=\text{Length (mm)}\times [\text{Width (mm)}]^{2}/2. \end{eqnarray*}\end{document}</tex-math>
   <math id="mml-NONUM-d2e650">
    <mstyle displaystyle="true">
     <mtext>Tumor volume</mtext>
     <mspace width="1em"/>
     <mrow>
      <mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")">
       <msup>
        <mrow>
         <mtext>mm</mtext>
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
         <mtext>3</mtext>
        </mrow>
       </msup>
      </mfenced>
     </mrow>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mtext>Length (mm)</mtext>
     <mo>×</mo>
     <msup>
      <mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mfenced separators="" open="[" close="]">
         <mtext>Width (mm)</mtext>
        </mfenced>
       </mrow>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mn>2</mn>
      </mrow>
     </msup>
     <mo>∕</mo>
     <mn>2</mn>
     <mo>.</mo>
    </mstyle>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula>Mice were randomly assigned into PBS control group (
 <italic>n</italic> = 6) and HMWp treatment group (
 <italic>n</italic> = 6) when the tumor volume reached 100–150 mm
 <sup>3</sup>. Treatment group received intraperitoneal (
 <italic>i.p.</italic>) administration of 5 µg/g of body weight/200 µL of HMWp on alternate days over a period of 21 days. Mice were observed for behavioral changes at 2 h after dosing and at 24 h for mortality and signs of toxicity. Throughout the study, animals that showed severe pain or signs of enduring severe distress, having a tumor burden greater than 10% body weight, bearing a tumor that exceeds 15 mm in any one dimension, having tumors that had ulcerated/necrotized/infected and tumors that interfered with eating or impaired ambulation were included as criteria of humane endpoints. The tumor volume and body weight of individual mice were monitored and recorded weekly over the 21-day treatment period. At day 22, all the mice from both treated and control groups were euthanized using carbon dioxide.
</p>
