<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The suppression of the synthesis of hepatic fatty acids and cholesterol by tofu (Tables 
 <xref rid="pone.0210950.t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210950.s011" class="xref">S6</xref>) suggested that circulating levels of TG and LDL were sufficient to satisfy physiological demands in rats fed the tofu diets. The levels of CM2 and VLDL (major carriers of TG) and LDL1 and LDL2 (major carriers of cholesterol) in tofu groups were not markedly lower or higher than those in the CS group (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210950.s003" class="xref">S3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210950.s004" class="xref">S4</xref> Figs). These results implied that abundant TG was supplied by the diet. Moreover, the ratio of TG to cholesterol in CM1 and CM2 was higher in the tofu groups (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210950.s005" class="xref">S5 Fig</xref>): this increase suggested that the absorption efficacies of TG and cholesterol varied for some reason even though food consumption did not significantly differ among the groups (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210950.s009" class="xref">S4 Table</xref>). In contrast to CM, the ratio of TG to cholesterol was similar in VLDL classes, and was significantly lower in the LDL1 class when tofu-fed animals were compared with casein-fed animals (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210950.s005" class="xref">S5 Fig</xref>). Tofu may have increased the chance of contact between TG carriers and lipase in peripheral tissue or the activity of lipoprotein lipase. Since this was not observed in LDL2, the latter may be excluded as a possibility. The increased affinity of TG-rich lipoproteins for lipoprotein lipase was also proposed. Increased TG absorption in the intestines and its transport from lipoproteins to peripheral tissues may contribute to sufficient deposits of TG on adipose tissues. Furthermore, the levels of LDL1 and LDL2 in the tofu groups were higher and slightly lower, respectively, than those in the casein groups (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210950.s003" class="xref">S3 Fig</xref>), indicating that serum cholesterol and TG were sufficient to supply lipids to peripheral tissues. Therefore, the suppression of lipogenesis may have contributed to a decreased burden on the liver, which, in turn, slightly reduced liver weights.
</p>
