<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par82">A benzamide HDAC inhibitor, MS-275 (
 <bold>93</bold>), is reported to be a selective HDAC inhibitor targeting class I HDACs, which is currently in phase II. Furthermore, reported X-ray crystal structure of Dasatinib (
 <bold>5</bold>) bound to Abl and MS-275 docked to HDAC1 homolog. The 2-aminothiazole of Dasatinib occupies the ATP-binding pocket of Abl with three hydrogen bonds. In the case of HDAC, 2-aminophenylbenzamide moiety, which is one of the most potent zinc ion chelating group among all types of zinc-binding groups and shows the potent selectivity to HADC1, forms four hydrogen bonds with His131, Asp168, Gly140, and His140. Given the known binding modes of the Abl inhibitor Dasatinib and HDAC1 inhibitor MS-275, it was envisaged that amalgamation of these pharmacophores would be a viable strategy to single molecules retaining both activities. Therefore, Chen et al. designed a new series of N-(pyrimidin-4-yl)thiazol-2-amine derivatives with a novel design approach in the chimeric HDAC/kinase inhibitors. Among derivatives, compounds 
 <bold>94a</bold> and 
 <bold>94b</bold> exhibited the most active against HDAC1 and Bcr-Abl. Heterocycle group of R
 <sub>1</sub> had a great impact on the effectiveness of the set of compounds against HDAC1. According to the SAR studies, presence of anilino or benzyl amino group in R
 <sub>1</sub>, replacement of the pyridyl group with a phenyl group in R
 <sub>1</sub> resulted in the decreased of enzymatic inhibitory activity against HDAC1. These results may suggest a preference for a certain hydrophilic group as a surface recognition cap group. Also, the fluorine substituent on the 
 <italic>para</italic>-position of the amide had the similar effect. This result showed that this replacement of fluorine is helpless for the ZBG to chelate with the Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> ion located at the bottom of the active site of HDAC1. The aromatic group in R
 <sub>1</sub> reduced Bcr-Abl inhibition and the fluorine atom on the 
 <italic>para</italic>-position of the amide increased inhibitory activity against Bcr-Abl. Compound 
 <bold>94b</bold> exhibited the most potential inhibitory activity against Bcr-Abl with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 17.8 nM. In cellular assays, compound 
 <bold>94a</bold> and 
 <bold>94b</bold> as dual Bcr-Abl/HDAC inhibitors displayed high antiproliferative activities against human leukemia cell line (K562) and prostate cancer cell line (DU145) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig19" ref-type="fig">19</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>].
</p>
