<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Moreover, the type of chitin matrix in insects may negatively influence chitinase activity and thus protein digestibility [
 <xref rid="B35-animals-09-00181" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Those enzymes are essential for the breakdown of chitin [
 <xref rid="B36-animals-09-00181" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>], the main structural polysaccharide present in insect exoskeletons [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-09-00181" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. The efficacy of chitin utilization by monogastric animals is frequently discussed in connection with the presence, or lack of, of chitinolytic enzymes; however, some studies confirmed the presence and activity of chitinolytic enzymes in various organs of fish species, such as the gastric mucosa, intestinal mucosa, pyloric caeca and pancreas [
 <xref rid="B37-animals-09-00181" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-animals-09-00181" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-animals-09-00181" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-animals-09-00181" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. As an omnivorous fish species with a great capacity to feed on plankton, Nile tilapia may have some advantages in chitin degradation, once that polysaccharide is present in zooplankton composition [
 <xref rid="B41-animals-09-00181" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. The feeding nature and significant intake of chitin make it likely that chitinolytic enzymes play an important role on tilapia digestive physiology. Köprücü and Özdemir [
 <xref rid="B34-animals-09-00181" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>] assessed the digestibility of chitin from crustacean meals (
 <italic class="italic">Gammarus kischineffensis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Astacus leptodactylus</italic>) for Nile tilapia and reported chitin ADC of 71.5% and 69.3%, respectively. For cobia 
 <italic class="italic">Rachycentron canadum</italic>, chitin ADC from brown shrimp (
 <italic class="italic">Penaeus aztecus)</italic> and crab meals (
 <italic class="italic">Brachyura</italic>) were 78.2% and 66.8% respectively [
 <xref rid="B30-animals-09-00181" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. The chitin ADCs those authors reported were close to those presented in this study, which ranged from 59.8% to 81.3%. Studies on chitinase and chitobiase activity as well as the absorption and utilization capacity of chitin and its derivates, such as N-acetyl glucosamine by Nile tilapia are needed.
</p>
