<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par81">
 <italic>P. cablin</italic> Benth., commonly known as patchouli, is an important medicinal herb with huge market potential in the fragrance industry; it is also the main ingredient in numerous Chinese patent medicines. Comprehensive experimental research studies performed in the past five years have complemented the pharmacological activities and mechanisms of action of patchouli, including anti-peptic ulcer effect, antimicrobial effect, anti-oxidative effect, anti-inflammatory effect, I/R injury protection, analgesic effect, antitumor effect, antidiabetic effect, anti-hypertensive effect, immunoregulatory effect, effect on intestinal microecology, antidiarrheal effect and others. Results from multiple studies demonstrated that patchouli and its derivatives can promote protective effects on the stomach, intestines, liver, and even the middle ear. The pharmacological activities of patchouli noted above are featured in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. With the development of research, the monomeric components in patchouli such as PA, β-patchoulene, patchoulene epoxide, pogostone, as well as pachypodol have been explored to some extent, and the pharmacological mechanisms study of PA is the most profound. The molecular and cellular targets of PA mentioned in this review are portrayed in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. From these studies, we can conclude that the therapeutic actions of PA are related to its capacity to suppress inflammation, alleviate oxidative stress, regulate apoptosis, relieve ER stress, increase VLDL metabolism, and others. Further investigations focusing on the molecular mechanisms indicated that multiple signalling pathways are involved in the treatment process. The PA-mediated relief of peptic ulcer is associated with the activation of PXR signalling pathway, the inhibition of the NF-κB pathway, the preservation of intestinal barrier integrity, the suppression of tryptophan catabolism, and the inhibition of cell death signaling [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. The modulations of the these pathways result in the decrease of pro-inflammatory cytokines, the downregulation of the necroptosis related RIP3 and MLKL proteins, the downregulation of the IDO-1 and TPH-1 protein, the downregulation of pro-apoptotic protein Bax, and increase of the anti-apoptotic protein Bcl-2. In addition, the PA-mediated treatment of diabetes is related to the inhibition of the PERK, IRE1, ATF6, and Wnt/β-catenin pathways, which eventually results in the downregulation of PERK, IRE1, and ATF6, the inhibition of VLDLR, the increase of apoB 100, the enhancement of MTP, the increased expression of smad7, and the stabilization of β-catenin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Moreover, by activating the ERK signaling pathway and inhibiting the MAPKs pathway, PA plays a important role in the treatment of I/R injury [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Furthermore, other pathways such as the EGFR pathways, JNK pathways, Nrf2-keap1 pathways, as well as Cholinergic channel, Nitrergic channel, K
 <sup>+</sup> channel, and Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> channel also participate in the therapeutic actions of PA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>]. The novel pharmacological effects associated with PA, for instance, its role in preventing obesity and promoting analgesia, have attracted significant attention in recent years, although the underlying mechanisms remain unclear. Likewise, more researches are needed to elucidate the molecular mechanism of action and protein targets of other ingredients in patchouli.
</p>
