<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Progress on lignin and nanocellulose applications is accelerating rapidly. This includes uses as rheology modifiers, in coatings and stabilization of multiphase systems,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref75" class="xref">75</xref>
 </sup> in liquid crystals,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42" class="xref">42</xref>
 </sup> in hybrid materials,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref118" class="xref">118</xref>
 </sup> and as templates for functional materials,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup> among many others. A recent development in our group was the construction of nanocellulose-based customizable, three-dimensional structures. This was accomplished by a biofabrication technique that relied on hydrophobic particles that prestabilized the air/water interface and resulted in a robust network of cellulose fibrils synthesized by bacteria.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref119" class="xref">119</xref>
 </sup> As a starting point for related developments, the use of emulsions can be quite attractive. 
 <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig" class="xref">9</xref>
 </xref>, for example, illustrates the different possibilities, which include O/W or W/O emulsions in the presence of CNF (
 <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig" class="xref">9</xref>
 </xref>a) or solubilized lignins in the stabilization of O/W emulsions (
 <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig" class="xref">9</xref>
 </xref>b). Such systems can be useful in the design of advanced materials. One of the routes for lignin particle fabrication has been introduced before (aerosol flow method). If a control in the lignin particle size is wanted, emulsions can be used to produce such uniform lignin particles, which can be further crosslinked (
 <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig" class="xref">9</xref>
 </xref>c). In turn, they can also be used in the stabilization of emulsions (
 <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig" class="xref">9</xref>
 </xref>d). The multiphase systems that are presented here, based on nanocelluloses or lignins, are ideal for the fabrication of microbeads, hollow microcapsules, and magneto-responsive hybrid materials.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref120" class="xref">120</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
