<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In vivo antioxidant properties</div>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Animal</div>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Male 
   <span class="italic">Wistar</span> rats, weighing about 200–220 g, were purchased from the Central Pharmacy of Tunisia (SIPHAT, Tunisia). They were housed at 22 ± 3 °C with light/dark periods of 12 h and a minimum relative humidity of 40%. The animals had free access to commercial pellet diet (SICO, Sfax, Tunisia) and water ad libitum. The general guidelines for the use and care of living animals in scientific investigations were followed [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. The handling of the animals was approved by the Tunisian Ethical Committee for the Care and Use of laboratory animals.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental design</div>
  <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After acclimatizing to the laboratory conditions for 1 week, 70 rats were divided into 7 groups of 10 animals and treated for 7 days as follow [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]:
  </p>
  <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rats of group 1 served as normal control and received saline orally daily for 7 days and were injected with 1 ml/kg BW of just olive oil (the solvent of CCl
   <sub>4</sub>) on the 7 day. The rats of group 2 served as CCl
   <sub>4</sub>-hepato and renotoxicity control and were received saline orally daily for 7 days and were injected with 1 ml/kg BW of CCl
   <sub>4</sub> and olive oil mixture on the 7 day (a single intraperitoneal injection). The CCl
   <sub>4</sub> dose was selected according to the reference dose for chronic oral exposure (RFD) as recommended for CCl
   <sub>4</sub> (CASRN 56–23-5) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rats of group 3 were pretreated orally seven times with a dose of 50 mg/kg BW of reference drug silymarin with an interval of 24 h [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rats of groups 4, 5, 6 and 7 were pretreated orally seven times with doses of 5, 15 and 40 mg MpEO /kg BW, respectively with an interval of 24 h [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After pretreatment with either silymarin or MpEO for 7 days, the rats of groups 3, 4, 5 and 6 received a single intraperitoneal injection of CCl
   <sub>4</sub> (1 ml/kg BW) on the 7 day.
  </p>
  <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rats were killed 24 h after vehicle or CCl
   <sub>4</sub> single injection. The animals in the different groups were killed by cervical decapitation to avoid stress conditions.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample collection</div>
  <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Serum was prepared by centrifugation (1500×
   <span class="italic">g</span>, 15 min, 4 °C; Beckman-Coulter, Marseille, France) and stored at −80 °C for further biochemical assays. The liver and kidney tissues were immediately removed and dissected over ice-cold glass slides and a part was homogenized (10% 
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">v</span>) with an Ultra Turrax homogenizer in ice-cold, 1.15% KCl-0.01 M sodium, potassium phosphate buffer. Homogenates were centrifuged at 10000×
   <span class="italic">g</span> for 20 min at 4 °C. The resulting supernatants were used for immediate lipid peroxidation and protein oxidation determination. Homogenate aliquots were stored at −80 °C for further biochemical assays. Other parts of these livers and kidney tissues were fixed in 10% formaldehyde solution and processed for paraffin sectioning and histological studies.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
