<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this series, β-elemene was found to be influential in glioblastoma therapy by activating p38 MAPK, which is an important factor for the antiproliferation effect [
 <xref rid="B59-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. It has potential effects on glioblastoma multiform (GBM), which is associated with tumor, poor radiotherapy prognosis and resistance to temozolomide (TMZ). Subsequent investigation of β-elemene in radio sensitivity and chemo sensitivity of GBM cells lead to the conclusion that it can be combined with radiotherapy and TMZ. In this way, assist in blocking the survival and proliferation of the cell lines of GBM, through the inhibition of DNA damage repair. Additionally, a decrease in phosphorylation of Ataxia telangiectasia mutated (ATM), ERK and Akt were observed when these cells were treated with β-elemene, followed by chemotherapy and radiotherapy. Thus, β-elemene is beneficial in combination therapy on GBM cells [
 <xref rid="B60-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. Furthermore, Zhu et al. with a background of previous accounts on the role of β-elemene in arresting glioblastoma cells (U87 and C6) in G0/G 1 phase, showed that by regulating the glia mutation factor β/mitogen activated protein kinase 3/6/p38 and extracellular signal regulated kinase 1/2/B cell lymphoma 2/surviving pathways, inhibition of cell proliferation was facilitated and promotion of in vitro and in vivo differentiation of glioblastoma stem cells (GSCs). They found that this was a crucial step in the treatment of glioblastoma. For this, they recognized many GSC markers that can be used for the differentiation of these tumor cells such as human CD133, ATP-binding cassette subfamily G member 2 (ABCG2), glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP), Notch 1, and Sonic hedgehog (SHH). These findings led their investigation to understand the effects and mechanism of β-elemene on cell survival, stemness differentiation, proliferation, and epithelial mesenchymal transition (EMT) in vitro and in vivo. Along with this, the downregulation of expression levels of stemness markers CD133, ATP-binding cassette subfamily G member 2, mesenchymal markers N-cadherin, and β-catenin were facilitated. Moreover, upregulation of expression levels of differentiation related to effectors of glial fibrillary acidic protein, sonic hedgehog, Notch 1 and epithelial marker (e-cadherin), in vitro and in vivo, were promoted. In addition, their studies underlined that β-elemene promoted apoptosis, impaired invasiveness in glioblastoma cells and suppressed growth of animal xenografts and inhibit proliferation. Furthermore, it showed an increase in expression level of vimentin in vitro with noticeable inhibition of β-catenin that enhanced the effects of EMT-inhibition, antiproliferation, and specific marker expression regulatory of β-elemene [
 <xref rid="B61-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>].
</p>
