<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Moreover, there were many studies that indicated the efficacy of the derivatives of β-elemene as an anticancer agent. Xu et al. synthesized and characterized fourteen β-elemene derivatives containing morpholine, piperzine, terahydropyrrole, cyclohexamine, or thiophenylethylamine groups. These derivatives were compared with β-elemene for their proliferative activity in human leukemia K562, gastric carcinoma SGC-7901, cervix epithelioid carcinoma HeLa cells. This proved that 13,14-bis(cis-3,5-dimethyl-1-piperazinyl)-β-elemene and 13,14-bis(cyclohexamino)-β-elemene have similar potency as β-elemene [
 <xref rid="B62-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>]. Even, β-elemene mono-substituted amine, rhenium and ether coordinated complex structure exhibited in vitro antiproliferative activity in human cervix epithelioid carcinoma HeLa cells. This reduction of cyclin D1 protein expression and Rb phosphorylation seized the cell cycle at G1 phase [
 <xref rid="B63-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. Moreover, three synthetic analogs of β-elemene, such as β-elemenal, β-elemene fluoride, and β-elemenol have also displayed significant anticancer activities by the considerable suppression in the non-small cell lung cancer cell proliferation. Among them, β-elemene enhanced cisplatin activity by causing lung cancer cell death, which was regulated by the CHK2-mediated cdc25C/cdc2/cyclin B1 signaling pathway to block cell cycle progression at G2/M phase [
 <xref rid="B64-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. Among the three analogs of β-elemene, namely, Lr-1: [(R or S)-2-((1R,3S,4S)-3-isopropenyl-4-methyl-4-vinylcyclohexyl)-propane-1,2-diol], Lr-2: [(S)-2-((1R,3S,4S)-3-isopropenyl-4-methyl-4-vinyl-cyclohexyl)-propane-1,2-diol, and (R)-2-((1R,3S,4S)-3-isopropenyl-4-methyl-4-vinylcyclohexyl)-propane-1,2-diol] and Lr-3 [1-((1R,3S,4S)-3-isopropenyl-4-methyl-4-vinyl-cyclohexyl)-ethanone], Lr-1 and Lr-2 can be used as an alternative to β-elemene for the treatment of brain tumors. For this, the cytotoxic efficacy of β-elemene and its synthetic analogs (Lr1 and Lr 2) in the brain tumor cell lines U-87MG, CCF-STTG1, and A172 were compared. It was observed that β-elemene suppressed tumor cell survival and mediated induction of apoptosis via signaling pathways. This study provided evidence that the synthetic analogs of β-elemene are also therapeutically potent compounds [
 <xref rid="B65-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. Another derivative of β-elemene, named 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>-(β-elemene-13-yl) tryptophan methyl ester (ETME), when combined with arsenic trioxide (ATO), synergistically enhances the antiproliferative activity and apoptosis of hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). It also downregulated Bcl-2 and pro-proteins of caspase family, decreased the mitochondrial membrane potential (MMP), and facilitated upregulation of BH3-interacting domain death agonist (Bid) and Bax, which were reversed by pifithrin-α, p53 inhibitor. Hence, reducing the tumor weight and volume in nude mice, MMP in HCCSMMC-7721 cells, and brought cell cycle arrest at the G2/M phase [
 <xref rid="B66-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]. Chen et al. studied that novel furoxan-based NO-donating β-elemene hybrids are promising anticancer agent [
 <xref rid="B67-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>]. Their studies also demonstrated isopropanolamine derivatives of β-elemene are effective chemotherapeutic agents [
 <xref rid="B68-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>].
</p>
