<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Cereal fungal contamination causes both economic and human health problems. Economically important diseases, such as smuts, leaf spots, crown rots, and root rots are usually caused by 
 <italic class="italic">Bipolaris</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Curvularia</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Fusarium</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Alternaria</italic> species.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup> Infection of cereal seeds is a serious problem because these pathogens can remain viable for 10 years and are subsequently capable of propagating across other geographical areas, infecting further crops and achieving global dissemination.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2" class="xref">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic class="italic">Bipolaris</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Curvularia</italic> are closely related genera of plant pathogens as well as emerging opportunistic human pathogens.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4" class="xref">4</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup> Several species, according to the method of infection and immune status, have been reported, from mild skin and nail infections to severe invasive human diseases. 
 <italic class="italic">Curvularia</italic> is an important dematiaceous fungus involved in phaeohyphomycosis; 
 <italic class="italic">Curvularia australiensis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Ctenochaetus hawaiiensis</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Curvularia spicifera</italic> have frequently been isolated from human phaeohyphomycoses.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7" class="xref">7</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup> These three species were formerly classified as members of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Bipolaris</italic>; however, phylogenetic studies have demonstrated that species previously placed in 
 <italic class="italic">Bipolaris</italic>, especially those known as human pathogens, actually belong to the 
 <italic class="italic">Curvularia</italic> genus.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
