<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="st6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SUMMARY</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Comparative analysis of the investigated oil samples indicates more pronounced monoterpene contents in 
     <span class="italic">Ferula tingitana</span> flower. The principle monoterpenoid constituents of both oils are α-thujene. Sesquiterpenes presence is considerably more pronounced in the leaves-derived oil sample
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Elemol, cadinol, α-thujene and a-terpinoline, the major components of the flower- and leaves-derived oil in the present work and were not detected in the Turkish sample. The differences may be due to climatic and other extrinsic conditions such as where and when the samples were collected</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>When screened for antimicrobial activity, the flower- and leaves-derived oil of 
     <span class="italic">F. tingitana</span> exhibited a mild effect against all tested Gram-negative and Gram-positive microorganisms. However, not displayed growth inhibitory effect against the fungus 
     <span class="italic">Aspergillus flavus</span> and 
     <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>On assessing the cytotoxic activity, the flower- and leaves-derived oil exhibited specific and significant effects on the viability of the selected human cell lines, viz., hormone-responsive breast carcinoma cell line (MCF7), cervical carcinoma cell line (HELA), and liver carcinoma cell line (HEPG2).</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span xlink:href="PM-13-446-g001.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">Abbreviations used:</span> F: Flower-derived oil of 
  <span class="italic">F. tingitana</span>; L: Leaves-derived oil of 
  <span class="italic">F. tingitana</span>; IPP: Isopentenyl pyrophosphate or also isopentenyl diphosphate; DMAPP: Dimethylally pyrophosphate or also dimethylallyl diphosphate; GPP: Geranyl pyrophosphate; GGPP: Geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate; MEP: Methylerythritol phosphate pathway; FPP: Farnesyl pyrophosphate; GC/MS: Analysis gas chromatography/mass spectroscopy; SRB: Sulforhodamine B.
 </p>
</sec>
