<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another important aspect is related to the shape, size, and morphological structure of MeNPs, which influence their functionality and toxicity on the environment and human body [
 <xref rid="B199-molecules-26-03061" ref-type="bibr">199</xref>]. Transmission electron microscopy (TEM), scanning electron microscopy (SEM), and dynamic light scattering (DLS) techniques are used for such determinations. As seen in 
 <xref rid="molecules-26-03061-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, AgNPs obtained from 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic> spp. have a spherical shape and a wide particle size distribution. Unlike AgNPs, which are mostly spherical, the morphology for AuNPs obtained using 
 <italic>A. dracunculus</italic> and 
 <italic>A. vulgaris</italic> determined by TEM is diverse: spherical, triangular, and hexagonal [
 <xref rid="B206-molecules-26-03061" ref-type="bibr">206</xref>,
 <xref rid="B210-molecules-26-03061" ref-type="bibr">210</xref>], while in the case of AuNPs synthesized from 
 <italic>A. annua</italic>, almost all are spherical with a few triangular or irregularly shaped particles [
 <xref rid="B191-molecules-26-03061" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>]. As previously mentioned, the particle size is strongly influenced by the reaction conditions. Basavegowda et al. proved that spherical particles are smaller than triangular ones and can agglomerate to form slightly larger non-spherical particles [
 <xref rid="B191-molecules-26-03061" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>]. On the other hand, the size distribution and morphology of ZnONPs showed spherical or granular [
 <xref rid="B187-molecules-26-03061" ref-type="bibr">187</xref>,
 <xref rid="B195-molecules-26-03061" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>] NPs with an average size of 20–30 nm or hexagonal-shaped NPs with an average size of 50–100 nm [
 <xref rid="B211-molecules-26-03061" ref-type="bibr">211</xref>]. For these examples, a tendency of agglomeration or clustering was observed [
 <xref rid="B187-molecules-26-03061" ref-type="bibr">187</xref>,
 <xref rid="B195-molecules-26-03061" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>]. SEM analysis indicates a spherical shape for CuNPs and TiO
 <sub>2</sub>NPs, but the average sizes differ: 35.36 ± 44.4 nm for CuNPs and 92.58 ± 56.98 nm for TiO
 <sub>2</sub>NPs [
 <xref rid="B202-molecules-26-03061" ref-type="bibr">202</xref>]. 
</p>
