<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> from different geographical locations has been of pharmaceutical and botanical importance and has been used traditionally for the management of several disorders including hepatocyte enlargement, hepatitis, gastritis, jaundice, wound healing, splenomegaly [
 <xref rid="B17-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], dyspepsia and indigestion, flatulence, gastric pain, anemia, anorexia [
 <xref rid="B18-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], esophageal bowel syndrome with irritation, weak memory tremors [
 <xref rid="B19-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], depression, epilepsy, chronic fever [
 <xref rid="B20-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], skin diseases, gout, and rheumatism [
 <xref rid="B21-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Additionally, it is used as anthelmintic and insect repellents [
 <xref rid="B22-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], as an additive source for ruminants, particularly in promoting the rumen fermentation pattern for efficient utilization of diets (
 <xref rid="antibiotics-09-00353-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Kim et al. [
 <xref rid="B23-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] showed that administration of dried 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> rather than rice straw did not alter the pH of the rumen. Moreover, it has been documented to alleviate pains during labor and for the management of sclerosis and leukemia [
 <xref rid="B24-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. It is widely used in the food industry for the production of aperitifs, spirits, and bitters [
 <xref rid="B25-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Additionally, 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> ointment has been used externally to reduce the stiffness of muscles and joints as well as help in healing bruises [
 <xref rid="B26-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Furthermore, wormwood is employed to relieve childbirth pain and it is also employed to relieve pains during the menstrual cycle [
 <xref rid="B27-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], and for the cardiac disorder and hypertension [
 <xref rid="B1-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].
</p>
