<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plants belonging to the Apiaceae family are rich in secondary metabolites and embody numerous genera of high economic and medicinal value, yielding flavonoids, coumarins, acetylenes, terpenes, and essential oils (
  <a rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref1">1</a>). It is well known that the existence of essential oils and oleoresin is a characteristic feature of this family (
  <a rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref2">2</a>). 
  <span class="italic">Pycnocycla</span> is a genus belonging to the Apiaceae family, subfamily Apioideae, tribe Echinophoreae, and comprises approximately 20 species of herbaceous perennial, multicaulis, and spinous plants widely distributed in subtropical and tropical regions (
  <a rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref3">3</a>). 
  <span class="italic">Pycnocycla</span> is characterized by eight species in Iran, all of which are native or endemic (
  <a rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref4">4</a>). 
  <span class="italic">Pycnocycla bashagardiana</span> Mozaff. is an endemic species found only in the south of Iran. It is commonly distributed in the Jask County, Hormozgan Province (
  <a rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref4">4</a>). Due to the widespread use of 
  <span class="italic">P. bashagardiana</span> fruits in Iranian traditional medicine for relief and treatment of pain and inflammation-based disorders such as rheumatoid arthritis, we were prompted to assess the analgesic and anti-inflammatory activities of the fruit’s essential oil and examine the pharmacological basis for the folkloric use of it as an antinociceptive and anti-inflammation agent. As the fruits of 
  <span class="italic">P. bashagardiana</span> contain a high amount of essential oils (1.6%, v/w) and possess a strong smell, we were prompted to evaluate the mentioned effects of its essential oil for the first time. The 
  <span class="italic">P. bashagardiana</span> fruit’s essential oil (PBFEO) was also analyzed by Gas chromatography and GC-MS in order to detect the potentially responsible compounds for observed activities.
 </p>
</sec>
