<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Optimization of the temperature and media pH can enhance the production of sesquiterpene as observed with the microbial production of vetispiradiene, 5-
 <italic class="italic">epi</italic>-aristolechene and (+)-δ-cadinene [
 <xref rid="B11-genes-10-00478" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. For the production of (+)-zizaene, the optimal fermentation conditions were found at 20 °C and pH 7.0, which differ from the optimal reaction conditions from the ZS in in vitro biotransformations with FDP (36 °C, pH 7.5) [
 <xref rid="B20-genes-10-00478" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Thus, the greatest difference between the experimental conditions was the temperature, due to its relevant effect over protein synthesis rate, cell growth, and enzyme activity [
 <xref rid="B11-genes-10-00478" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-genes-10-00478" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. Accordingly, tests cultivated at 16 °C and pH 6.5‒7, overexpressed high amounts of soluble ZS protein but the (+)-zizaene levels and cell growth were low. These results suggest that the activity of the ZS was drastically reduced at 16 °C, due to its preference for higher temperatures (optimal at 36 °C). On the other hand, temperatures higher than 20 °C resulted in higher amounts of insoluble ZS protein than the soluble form. These observations confirm that an optimal temperature of 20 °C was required to achieve a balance between cell growth and active ZS protein. Regarding the effect of the media pH on (+)-zizaene production, the optimal pH was found to be neutral pH and values different than that lowered the (+)-zizaene titers. Additionally, lower pH values promoted the formation of insoluble ZS protein. Such behavior was observed before in uncontrolled-pH 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> cultures grown in shake flasks, whereas overexpression of fused SpA-βgal protein at pH &lt; 5.5 augmented the inclusion body formation, possibly due to regulatory mechanisms for pH homeostasis [
 <xref rid="B49-genes-10-00478" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. Therefore, tests grown at pH 7 at 20 °C achieved the balance between insoluble and soluble ZS protein fractions that led to the highest production of (+)-zizaene.
</p>
