<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In traditional medicine, 
 <italic>A. dracunculus</italic> is used in ailments of the digestive system, and as an appetite and digestive stimulant, especially when red meat is consumed in large quantities (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Uhl and Strauss, 2000</xref>). Moreover, the 
 <italic>A. dracunculus</italic> herb was used to accelerate the metabolism (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Senderski, 2007</xref>). It was also used as an anesthetic for toothache, wounds and cuts (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Mamedov et al., 2004</xref>). In Europe the plant’s uses also included constipation, intestinal cramps, ulcers and cancer (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Obolskiy et al., 2011</xref>). In Arabic cultures, the species was used in the treatment of insomnia, gingivitis, foot and mouth disease and as an agent for masking the taste of medicines, while in Central Asia, including Russia, it was used to treat irritation, allergic rashes, gastritis, dyspepsia, dermatitis, and to promote digestion and improve appetite (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Mamedov et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Sharopov et al., 2020</xref>). In Azerbaijan, 
 <italic>A. dracunculus</italic> was used as an anti-epileptic drug (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Alakbarov, 2001</xref>). Indian traditional medicine–Ayurveda–relates that the species is effective in the treatment of helminthiasis, intestinal smooth muscle spasms, fever of various origins, and a good tonic, an immunostimulant and to regulates the menstrual cycle (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Miller and Miller, 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Obolskiy et al., 2011</xref>). Native people of Himachal Pradesh and Kashmir use a paste from the leaves of 
 <italic>A. dracunculus</italic> in the treatment of wounds on the legs of yaks and donkeys. Moreover, they use extract of tarragon for toothache, fever, dysentery, intestinal worms and stomach ache (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Joshi et al., 2016</xref>).
</p>
