<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The integration of systems biology and omics approaches, covering genomics, transcriptomics, proteomics, metabolomics and functional analysis; provide a potential solution to comprehend the multigenic nature of resin biosynthesis in 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria</italic>. On the basis of large number of previously conducted agarwood induction experiments, transcriptomic and metabolites studies (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Naef, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gao X. et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ye et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wu et al., 2017</xref>), integrated omics analysis can indeed serve as a platform to build a more comprehensive picture of agarwood resin biosynthetic mechanism that involve different omics layers. The development of high-throughput mass spectrometry (MS), microarray and sequencing technologies (DNA and RNA) have made it possible to integrate such data into a system biological framework via integrated-omics which would help to predict gene-gene interactions, identify driver genes and the molecular signatures of agarwood formation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" class="xref">Figure 5</xref>). Likewise, potential signaling molecules for agarwood formation can be predicted in a wake of this dramatically increased availability of data. Experimentally validated effective signaling molecules can be added into the existing recipe of chemical inducer to further enhance the induction performance. Moreover, predetermination of resin composition or the agarwood quality is conceivable with deep understanding of the key quality indicators and the specific pathways involved for agarwood production by integrated elucidation of different metabolite and transcript profiles under different induction methods. Future improvement of agarwood induction efficiency should accompany with the development of monitoring system for early detection of non-responsive trees which could avoid cutting down of 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria</italic> trees that are unsuccessfully been induced. This can be achieved by monitoring the expression of a set of genes involved in agarwood resin biosynthesis.
</p>
