<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Application of high performance counter-current chromatography enabled us to obtain β-elemene of high purity and recovery in 70 min. The previously reported isolation of β-elemene is mostly based on silica gel column chromatography [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>] or silver ion coordination chromatography [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]; however, the latter one is more effective due to the formation of coordination complex between silver ion and the double bond of β-elemene [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. The formation of coordination complex is, therefore, selective, and enabled the removal of all compounds without double bonds. Wei et al. [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>] obtained β-elemene with 56.1% purity using AgNO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> silica gel column chromatography; however, they also show that HP20 macroporous resin chromatography gives higher purity of target compound (82.9%). To obtain β-elemene with purity similar to obtained in our study (96%), the additional step of preparative HPLC was required after HP20 column chromatography [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. There were also a few attempts to isolate β-elemene applying counter-current chromatography. High-performance centrifugal partition chromatography (HPCPC) resulted in elution of β-elemene after 400 min [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>], whereas our protocol enabled the elution of target compound in 70 min. Also, silver ion coordination high-speed counter-current chromatography resulted in higher elution time of β-elemene (over 80 min) [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] compared to our method. The differences in the elution time come from different separation conditions between these techniques (HPCCC vs. HPCPC or HSCCC; e.g., rotation speed, column volume, solvent system flow rate); however, they also come from the different essential oils used. In both previously applied counter-current chromatographic techniques, 
 <italic class="italic">C. Wenyuj in</italic> essential oil was used for β-elemene isolation. Because 
 <italic class="italic">C. wenyujin</italic> essential oil contains a lot of constituents, Lu et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] introduced a silica gel column chromatography step before HSCCC separation. This enabled the removal of impurities and increased β-elemene content in the purified fraction [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. The two steps separation resulted in around 63% recovery [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. The isolation protocol described in our study is more effective, since no purification step is required to obtain β-elemene with purity up to 96% and 80% yield. Although 
 <italic class="italic">C. wenyujin</italic> essential oil served as material for separation of curdione, curcumol, germacrone, curzerene, 1,8-cineole, and β-elemene [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>], it is not the most abundant source of β-elemene. In our study, we used 
 <italic class="italic">N. damascena</italic> essential oil as more cost-effective source of target compound. The chosen essential oil contains less constituents (29) than 
 <italic class="italic">C. wenyujin</italic> essential oil (72) [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>], and the content of β-elemene in the first essential oil is at least three times higher, which makes the isolation more effective. The source of β-elemene for industry processing is an extract of rhizome curcuma obtained by means of supercritical CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> extraction [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]; however, it contains smaller amount of compound of interest (up to 27.83%) than source used in our study, and supercritical CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> extraction technique itself is much more expensive and far less effective in β-elemene isolation than simple hydrodistillation, which was proved by Sajfrtova et al. [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. What is more, the β-elemene injection applied clinically as a national second-class anticancer drug in China contains β-elemene accompanied by its structural isomers, γ- and δ-elemene, and small amount of other terpenoids, among them β-caryophyllene as a main impurity. β-, γ-, and δ-Elemene account for 85% in elemene injection [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-23-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. In our study, we obtained β-elemene of better purity, up to 96%, depending on the amount of sample loaded into column, and we proved the usefulness of 
 <italic class="italic">N. damascena</italic> essential oil as a source for β-elemene isolation. To our knowledge, this is the first application of HPCCC technique for β-elemene isolation from the plant material and the first one from 
 <italic class="italic">N. damascena</italic> essential oil.
</p>
