<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nowadays, food safety and food quality are major challenges for all countries, it is estimated that there are around 30% of people are suffering annually from food illness disease in developed countries [
 <xref rid="B84-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,
 <xref rid="B85-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Many natural polymers such as proteins and carbohydrates have antibacterial and antifungal properties, which prevent or reduce the growth of microorganisms in food. Infectious microorganisms are extensively spread everywhere on the earth which causes a serious problem for society. Furthermore, natural polymers are more effective in the treatment of those diseases and also prevent several side effects that can be led by antimicrobial agents [
 <xref rid="B86-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. While mucilage has an antibacterial and antifungal property which can also prevent or reduce the risk of food-borne illness disease and food spoilage. Much seed-based mucilage has an antimicrobial property such as Chia seed [
 <xref rid="B86-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>], Cress seed [
 <xref rid="B78-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>], okra seed [
 <xref rid="B65-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], and quince seed [
 <xref rid="B80-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] Tantiwatcharothai and Prachayawarakorn [
 <xref rid="B89-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>] prepared Basil seed-based sponges hydrogel for measuring the antibacterial activity (against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>) in wound dressing. ZnO nanocomposite and borax crosslinking were also incorporated with basil seed mucilage. The result showed that there was no effect of borax in the antibacterial activity of Basil seed mucilage sponge. Whereas, ZnO nanocomposite loaded resulted in good antimicrobial activity against the gram-positive (
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus)</italic> and gram-negative 
 <italic>(Escherichia coli)</italic> bacteria. Furthermore, better antibacterial activity was observed against gram-positive (
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>aureus)</italic> than that of gram-negative 
 <italic>(Escherichia coli)</italic> because of the structural difference of the cell wall. Gram-negative bacteria possess a complex cell wall, while gram-positive bacteria contain a thick cell wall of peptidoglycan, therefore, it is more resistant to attack by the microbial agent. Jouki et al. [
 <xref rid="B80-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] prepared quince seed mucilage-based film with the incorporation of thyme essential oil in different concentrations ranging from 0 to 2.0%. The film was separated against eleven food associated with bacterial strains by agar disc-diffusion assay. And observed that 1% thyme essential oil containing film was more effective against all microorganisms including gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria such as 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes,</italic> and 
 <italic>Shewanella putrefaciens</italic>. Mujtaba et al. [
 <xref rid="B90-polymers-13-01066" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>] also prepared chia seed mucilage composite films with the incorporation of cellulose nanofibrils at various concentrations by using the solution casting method. Microorganisms such as 
 <italic>Escherichia coli, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Staphylococcus mutans, Salmonella typhimurium, Bacillus thuringiensis,</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> were incubated in LB agar at 37 °C for 24 h. the result indicated that chia seed-based cellulose nanofibrils composite film improved antimicrobial activity with the increasing of cellulose nanofibrils concentrations (3–6%) and observed that mucilage films containing 6% cellulose nanofibrils had the highest antimicrobial capacity against all the exanimated microorganisms. The inhibition zone range of all the exanimated microorganisms was 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (20.17 mm), 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (18.25 mm), 
 <italic>Staphylococcus mutans</italic> (17.79 mm), 
 <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> (6.12 mm), 
 <italic>Bacillus thuringiensis</italic> (17.19 mm), and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (18.89 mm). The antimicrobial activity of different mucilage-containing plants is represented in 
 <xref rid="polymers-13-01066-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.
</p>
