<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The demonstration that the immune system can control tumor growth has been provided for the first time by Thomas and Burnet (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). This evidence has been confirmed after several decades, demonstrating the prognostic role of immune cells infiltrating the tumor lesions (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The crescent knowledge of cancer immunology and immunotherapy has allowed the development of novel biological agents that showed unprecedented clinical results (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). These results contributed to turn into reality the paradigm that patient’s immune system represents effective “living drugs” against cancer cells. Among these, adoptive cell therapy (ACT) that implies the isolation and expansion 
 <italic>ex vivo</italic> of tumor antigen-specific T lymphocytes and their re-infusion in patients has shown promising clinical activity improving the overall survival of cancer patients (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). T-lymphocytes engineered with Chimeric Antigen Receptors (CARs), that consist of an antibody-derived domain for antigen recognition linked to T-cell signaling molecules, can recognize in a MHC-independent manner tumor antigens expressed on tumor cell surface (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). These biological drugs are based on the engineering of T-lymphocytes, isolated from patient’s or, less frequently, from donor’s peripheral blood, with either gamma-retroviral (RV) or lentiviral (LV) vectors encoding CARs linked to co-stimulatory molecules (either CD28 or 4-1BB linked to zeta-chain) (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). The development of anti-CD19 CAR-T cells and their application in several clinical trials showed durable clinical responses in both adult and pediatric cancer patients with disease relapse or refractory to other therapeutic interventions. Complete responses (up to 70–80%) and significant improvement of overall survival (OS) were documented in patients with either acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) or high grade non-Hodgkin lymphomas (NHLs), including diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL) (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) and mantle cell lymphoma (ML) (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). These clinical trials led to the accelerated approval by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and the European Medicines Agency (EMA) of two CD19-CAR-T cell medicinal drug products, tisagenlecleucel (Kymriah) and axicabtagene ciloleucel (Yescarta). For the first time, ACT products entered commercial production by few pharmaceutical companies. Nevertheless, the clinical grade manufacturing is complex and with relatively long timeline for cell production, requiring the availability of patients’ or donors’ peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) to be shipped to good manufacturing practice (GMP) facilities, if not locally available, and the return to clinical sites for infusion into patients. One of the challenging factors of CAR-T cells is represented by the short-term associated toxicities arising in patients immediately after infusion. Cytokine release syndrome (CRS) represents the most common side effects of this type of therapy with a range of incidence among the different clinical studies of 50–90% (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). The mechanistic hypothesis behind CRS still needs to be fully dissected; however, it is a life-threatening situation that requires timely and effective interventions (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Other common side effects observed after CAR-T cell therapy for B-cell malignancies involve neurotoxicity, B-cell aplasia and hypogammaglobulinemia (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). CAR-T cells have been also investigated for the treatment of solid tumors with limited clinical responses, thus suggesting that this therapeutic strategy might be promising, but still needs optimization. One of the principal limitations is represented by the choice of target antigens; the majority of solid tumors have epithelial origins with many of tumor-associated antigens (TAAs) being shared with normal tissues (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). This translates into high risk of inducing off-tumor toxicities following the infusion of CAR-T cells specific for these TAAs. In addition, the homing of CAR-T cells to tumor site for solid tumors showed low efficiency due to the complexity of the tumor microenvironment (TME) (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Multiple studies are aimed at addressing the choice of target molecules, such as IL-13alpha2, B7-H3, CSPG4, CD44v6, MUC1, Mesothelin, EGFRvIII, Her-2, GD2 
 <italic>etc</italic>., allowing to specifically redirect the CAR-T cells to tumors with selected histological origins (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). A remarkable number of clinical trials are ongoing worldwide to assess the clinical activity of these immunobiological drugs against solid tumors and the optimal clinical setting for cancer patients (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>).
</p>
