<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Scavenging ROS antioxidants of acetyl cysteine additionally L-carnitine are observed to cure the inflammatory diseases [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. However, it does not performed well against ROS-related diseases due to poor bioavailability and various limitations of clinical screening [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Recently, studies reported that copper-based nanoparticles improved the ROS-related diseases and higher scavenging ability of this treatment [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Copper (Cu) is one of the best elements in recommendation for human usage, which play an important role in tyrosinase and Cu–ZnSOD enzyme [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Cu enzyme activity is basically a response to many bioactivities such as connective tissue biosynthesis, cellular respiration, neurotransmitter production, iron homeostasis, peptide biogenesis, pigment formation, and antioxidant defense [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Particularly, Cu-NPs has outstanding catalytic activity to scavenge H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> and O
 <sub>2</sub> [
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] but cannot eliminate OH· simultaneously [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and also can promote electron transfer reactions to inactivate H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> or OH· [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The catalytic behavior of Cu compounds in organic reaction motivated us to focus our attention on the application of our research. As a result, we assume that the capacity of Cu-Nps acts as catalytic as well as antioxidant activities simultaneously. In addition, the stability of Cu-NPs can be largely enhanced, which is also developing the overall ROS scavenging ability [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Based on the above observation, we designed to synthesize, high active 2-pyrimidinamine connected with Cu nanoparticles and evaluated the antioxidant of ABTS
 <sup>·+</sup>, linoleic acid peroxidation, and cytotoxic activities.
</p>
