<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>C. coggygria</italic> has a consistent traditional use in Europe and Asia. The Encyclopedia of Romanian Ethnobotany points to the use of the plant as both a dye and medicine, employed for the treatment of wounds and pharyngitis (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Butură, 1979</xref>). An enthnobotanical survey performed in the region of Dobrogea (South-East Romania) reported on the use of the plant as a cicatrizing agent of open wounds and the treatment of gynecological disorders (
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr">Tudor and Georgescu, 2011</xref>). The application of 
 <italic>C. coggygria</italic> (called “skumpina”) has also been acknowledged in a survey focused on plants used by the Czech diaspora from Romanian Banat region (
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr">Vlková et al., 2015</xref>). In the local folk medicine of Southwestern Romania, several parts of the smoketree are used: young twigs and leaves boiled in water represent a remedy against sore throat, stomatitis, gingivitis and gastritis. More conspicuously, wood slices extracted in badger fat (
 <italic>Meles</italic>) were mentioned as ointment ingredients intended to treat slowly healing wounds (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Antal and Ardelean, 2015</xref>). The ethnomedical use in skin and mucosal lesions is commonly accepted across countries, according to reports from Bulgaria (
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">Nedelcheva, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Koleva et al., 2015</xref>), Bosnia and Herzegovina (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">Redžić, 2007</xref>), Serbia (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Jarić et al., 2015</xref>), Albania (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Nedelcheva and Draganov 2014</xref>), and Turkey (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Kültür, 2007</xref>). Other uses include fever reduction (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Williams 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">Redžić, 2007</xref>), cardiac diseases, hypertension, urinary diseases, cough, asthma, hemorrhoids, diabetes, numbness of arm (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Kültür, 2007</xref>), and liver disease (
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Shen et al., 1991</xref>). The plant is as well mentioned in cancer treatment in Turkey (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Kültür, 2007</xref>) and Bosnia and Herzegovina (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">Redžić, 2007</xref>). Usually, leaves are the most frequently used plant parts in traditional medicine (as infusions or fresh).
</p>
