<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">The genus 
  <italic class="italic">Callistemon</italic> comprises evergreen shrubs or small trees, widely cultivated as ornamentals and for essential oil production. 
  <italic class="italic">Callistemon</italic> is well-recognized in folk medicine for its anti-cough, anti-bronchitis, and insecticidal activities. In the current study, we profiled the essential oil composition of the leaves of 
  <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">citrinus</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">rigidus</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">viminalis</italic> (Myrtaceae) collected during different seasons by GLC-MS coupled to multivariate data analysis. Antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and anti-proliferative activities of 
  <italic class="italic">Callistemon</italic> essential oils were evaluated. A total of 29 compounds were tentatively identified. Oxygenated monoterpenes dominated in essential oils, where eucalyptol represented the major constituent in the three 
  <italic class="italic">Callistemon</italic> species in all seasons. Multivariate data analysis including Principal Component Analysis (PCA) and Hierarchical Cluster Analysis (HCA) were applied to discriminate between different 
  <italic class="italic">Callistemon</italic> species in each season and to investigate any correlation between the metabolic profile of each species within different seasons. As expected, PCA plot could discriminate the three 
  <italic class="italic">Callistemon</italic> species in the four seasons. The dendrogram from HCA confirmed the results of PCA as it showed the same segregation pattern regarding the discrimination of different 
  <italic class="italic">Callistemon</italic> species. 
  <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">viminalis</italic> showed more pronounced antioxidant activity than 
  <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">citrinus</italic>, exhibiting IC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> values of 1.40 mg/mL and 1.77 mg/mL, respectively. Meanwhile, 
  <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">rigidus</italic> showed very weak antioxidant activity. All oils showed membrane stabilization activity in hypotonic solution induced haemolysis assay, where 
  <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">viminalis</italic> showed potent membrane stabilizing activity exhibiting IC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> value of 25.6 μg/mL comparable to that of the standard drug, indomethacin (17.02 μg/mL). Nevertheless, Callistemon essential oils were not cytotoxic in HCT-116 and Hela human cancer cell lines.
 </p>
</abstract>
