<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0310">Beginning from the ancient times, the traditional use of AR constantly develops and changes with the deepening of cognition. AR is listed as a top grade in Shennong Bencao Jing (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Gu, 1955</xref>), in which it was recorded as “removing wind-cold and resolving dampness, dead muscle spasm, and jaundice. The decoctions are taken for a long time, lighting body and prolonging life without hunger.” AR is pungent and fragrant. It can relax muscle and induce perspiration. It can dispel the cold and pathogenic wind on the surface of the skin. However, the effect of sweating is not obvious. AR is most suitable for treating cold and dampness because it is good at dehumidification. According to the Yaopin Hua Yi (
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Jia, 2015</xref>), AR is the main drug from the treatment of the syndrome of dampness, turbidity, and stagnation of middle-jiao (the upper part of the abdominal cavity). Mingyi Bielu (
 <xref rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr">Tao, 2013</xref>) documented “curing headache, eliminating phlegm and water-retention, removing the swelling of wind and water between the skin, eliminating heart disease and vomiting in cholera, warming the stomach and eliminating food”. AR could invigorate spleen-Qi, and activate the spleen and stomach. The Yang is clear and rising, nourishing and clearing orifices, leading to a clear-sight. The Taiping Shenghui Fang (
 <xref rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 1958</xref>) recorded it as “treating night blindness” and Jingyan Fang recorded “treating internal and external barriers to the eyes”. AR eliminates dampness with aromatics by avoiding filth and pestilence. Bencao Qiuyuan (
 <xref rid="bib143" ref-type="bibr">Zhao, 2009</xref>) added the treatment of “injury from food, heat, and diarrhea, spleen dampness and blood”. The records of doctors from all dynasties reflected the main treatment scopes of AR. Therefore, the Materia Medica in the Ming and Qing Dynasties summarized the functions of AR as drying dampness and strengthening the spleen, eliminating pollution and turbidity, eliminating wind dampness, relieving symptoms, and clarifying the eyes.
</p>
