<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The oral acute toxicity of AcEO resulted on an LD
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub> value greater than 2 g/kg, body weight. The essential oil caused a minimal lethality witnessed by one dead animal in the group fed by 2 g/kg, body weight, and which was marked with an intense perforations and ulcerations of gastric mucosa that probably causes the death. Otherwise, there were any adverse effects on the body weight or the organs weights monitored during the 15 days of the study. On the basis of the present data AcEO is considered as toxic at 2 g/kg due to gastric lesions induced. Additional studies about the toxicity of 
 <italic class="italic">A. campestris</italic> L. are available, showing that the intraperitoneal administration of aqueous extract to mice showed an earlier toxicity with an LD
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub> = 2.5 g/kg of body weight [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>]. Furthermore, an acute toxicity test of the essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">A.campestris</italic> L. on brine shrimp larvae (
 <italic class="italic">Artemia</italic> sp.) gave the median lethality dose ranging from 15 to 20 μg/ml [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" class="xref">69</xref>]. Concerning the platelet aggregation induced by both agonists thrombin (0.1 U/ml) and ADP (1 μM), AcEO was able to reduce it about 50%; so it can be postulated that this oil may interact with the site of action of ADP and thrombin and hence interrupting their cellular signaling and antagonizing the aggregation process. This results seems to be very considerable, by reference to a previous study conducted by our team, where the pharmaceutical anti-aggregant reference acetylsalicylic acid (1 mg/ml) induced a total inhibition of the aggregability caused by thrombin but at a quite high dose (1 mg/ml), if compared with our study when thrombin is tested at the dose 0.1 mg/ml [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" class="xref">78</xref>]. It has been reported that platelet activation and aggregation are participating in the emergence of hypertension in different ways [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" class="xref">79</xref>]. Platelets activation in hypertension can be explained by several mechanisms, among which the auto-degranulation that leads to activation of platelets exposed to increased shear force as result of high blood pressure [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" class="xref">80</xref>]. Activated platelets released endogenous mediators like ADP which is known as a platelet aggregating agent that interact with two platelets receptors: Gq-coupled P2Y
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</sub> that induces a transient rise in free cytoplasmic calcium and Gi-coupled P2Y
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">12</sub> that provoke inhibition of adenylyl cyclase. Both pathways are necessary to elicit platelet aggregation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" class="xref">81</xref>]. Thrombin is a another platelet agonist that enhance aggregation; in fact, thrombin induced platelets activation via protease-activated receptors (PARs) that has a protein Gq-action, enhancing activation of phospholipase C (PLCβ), which hydrolyzes phosphatidylinositol 4,5 bisphosphate (PIP
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</sub>), that promote the production of second messenger IP
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3</sub>, which contributes to the increase in intracellular Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> through mobilization from internal stores and influx from the extracellular department. The increase in intracellular Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> regulates many events leading to platelet aggregation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" class="xref">81</xref>].
</p>
