<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The endothelium is a highly specialized layer of luminal blood vessel, playing a key role in the vasorelaxation, mediated mainly by the release of endothelium-derived vasodilators, like nitric oxide (NO) and prostacyclin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" class="xref">83</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" class="xref">86</xref>]. By reference to our data, AcEO vasorelaxant effect appears to be endothelium-independent, since the vascular response persisted after removal of the endothelium. In the endothelial cell, the signalling mechanism responsible for muscarinic receptor-dependent NO production involves Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> and calmodulin-dependent activation of eNOS [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" class="xref">87</xref>]. Once produced, calcium/calmodulin complex (Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup>/CaM) enhance the dissociation of eNOS from caveolae, which become catalytically active and induces NO production [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" class="xref">88</xref>]. The NO, as released by endothelial cells, increased cGMP levels in the smooth muscle, activated PKG, and phosphorylated the same vascular smooth muscle proteins, which induces a decrease in intracellular calcium concentration and a subsequent vasorelaxation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" class="xref">89</xref>]. To check up the involvement of this pathway in the vasorelaxant action of AcEO, aorta was submitted to specific inhibitors and blockers of endothelium mediators that triggered the vasorelaxant action like atropine (non-selective antagonist muscarinic receptors), calmidazolium (Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup>-calmodulin binding to NOS blocker), L-NAME (NOS inhibitor), hydroxocobalamin (NO scavenger), ODQ (inhibitor of soluble guanylyl cyclase) and protein kinase G (PKG) inhibitor (Rp-8-Br-PET-cGMPs). Even though, the vasorelaxation was not affected in the presence of these drugs, which confirm that endothelium and specifically NO-GC-PKG pathway was not involved in this effect.
</p>
