<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In 
 <italic>M. oryzae</italic>, deletion of 
 <italic>MoDcl2</italic> leads to increased abundance of MAGGY mRNA when it is introduced into the native genome [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. With these reports in mind, it was expected that deletion of 
 <italic>MoDcl2</italic> in our experiments would increase the transcript abundance of genes which are known to possess more sRNAs in one or more libraries, in comparison with mycelia grown in complete media (control condition). Conversely, our results showed there is an overall reduction in transcript levels of these genes in the 
 <italic>Δmodcl2</italic> mutant and an increased level in the 
 <italic>Δmodcl1</italic> mutant. Interestingly, the known virulence gene 
 <italic>ACE1</italic> was among the few genes that fit this profile. 
 <italic>ACE1</italic> is tightly regulated at the transcriptional level; transcripts are only found in the penetration peg of the fungus, a specialized hypha that allows ingress through the surface of the leaf and into the plant cell [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>]. We postulate that strong control of this gene might be governed at the post-transcriptional level. Further studies will reveal whether these and the other genes tested show the same profile when the biosynthetic mutants are subjected to the environmental stress conditions, or during pathogenicity. Several studies have shown that MoDcl2 is exclusively involved in siRNA production for transgenes and active transposons in 
 <italic>M. oryzae</italic>, while less active transposons are not silenced by this same mechanism [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>]. Moreover, MoDcl1 is also involved in silencing when it is over-expressed in a 
 <italic>Δmodcl2</italic> mutant background. Together, these findings along with results presented here suggest the hypothesis that MoDcl1, at least in 
 <italic>M. oryzae</italic>, might define the existence of a MoDcl2-independent RNAi mechanism. The recent discovery of Argonaute associated Dicer independent siRNAs (disiRNAs) in 
 <italic>N. crassa</italic>, the first discovered Dicer-independent siRNAs in the fungal kingdom, supports this hypothesis. Surprisingly, in 
 <italic>M. circinelloides</italic>, Dicer2 plays a critical role in transgene-induced silencing [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>], but redundancy for the two Dicer genes was observed for production of endogenous sRNAs with DCL2 being the primary protein responsible for producing the majority of endogenous sRNAs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. Taken together, these studies suggest that 
 <italic>M. oryzae</italic> presumably has similar redundant Dicer-based mechanisms for the production of sRNAs.
</p>
