<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent years, extensive research has focused on the identification of bioactive ingredients and their cellular targets to explain the physiological benefits exerted by essential oils. TRP channels have emerged as potential targets for several essential oils that have health benefits, such as antinociception, anti-anxiolytic, anticonvulsant, anti-inflammatory, and immunomodulatory activities. To our knowledge, this is the first study investigating 
 <italic>M. fistulosa</italic> essential oils and their effects on TRP channels. TRP channels are a family of 28 nonselective cation channels grouped into six subfamilies and exhibiting a high permeability to calcium. These channels are thermosensitive, nociceptive, and osmoregulatory, along with playing significant roles in vision, taste transduction, and hormone release. We focused on the TRPA1, TRPV1, and TRPV4 channels, based on previous reports of phytochemicals activating these channels with physiological significance. For example, cinnamaldehyde from cinnamon exerts beneficial effects on cardiovascular functions [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-25-04873" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and decreases blood sugar levels [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-25-04873" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-25-04873" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-25-04873" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] through the activation of TRPA1 channels. Topical application of capsaicin, the active ingredient in chili peppers, has proven to be beneficial in treating arthritis [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-25-04873" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] and diabetic peripheral neuropathy [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-25-04873" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-25-04873" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], possibly by the desensitization of TRPV1 channels. Likewise, eugenol, one of the active ingredients in basil and clove, exhibits anti-inflammatory properties by activating TRPV1 [
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-25-04873" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Both TRPV4 and TRPV1 have been suggested to contribute to paclitaxel-induced neuropathy [
 <xref rid="B55-molecules-25-04873" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Finally, our recent studies suggest that the activation of TRPV1 channels by 
 <italic>Ferula iliensis</italic> and 
 <italic>Ferula akitschkensis</italic> essential oils contributed to their neutrophil immunomodulatory activity [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-25-04873" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
</p>
