<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant material and essential oils</div>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oils of 
   <span class="italic">Citrus aurantifolia</span>, 
   <span class="italic">A. nobile</span> and 
   <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> were purchased from Kampo de Ervas Ind. &amp; Com. Ltda-ME (Ribeirão Preto, SP, Brazil), accompanied by the technical datasheets and serial numbers of each species thus: Lot. No. 116, density (
   <span class="italic">d</span>) = 0.868; Lot. No. 297, density (
   <span class="italic">d</span>) = 0.908; Lot. No. 229, density (
   <span class="italic">d</span>) = 0.891, respectively. The essential oils were extracted by hydrodistillation from the fruit peel of 
   <span class="italic">C. aurantifolia</span> and from the flowers of 
   <span class="italic">A. nobile</span> and 
   <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC-MS analysis</div>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Samples of each essential oil were analyzed by gas chromatography coupled to mass spectrometry (GC-MS) (Varian, model Saturn 2100T) using the following technical conditions: DB-5 capillary column (30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm); gun: 240 °C; detector: 230 °C; electron impact: 70 eV; carrier gas: He; flow rate: 1.0 ml/min; split: 1/20; temperature program: 60–240 °C, 3 °C/min; injection volume: 1 μl. The chemical compounds were identified by comparison of their mass spectra with the GC-MS database (Nist 62 library) and Kovats retention index [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Animals and artificial infection with 
   <span class="italic">Haemonchus contortus</span>
  </div>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two male Santa Inês sheep (4–6 months-old, 20–30 kg) were used as feces donors for all experimental protocols. The animals were purchased in the region of Ribeirão Preto (SP, Brazil) and kept at the experimental farm of the University of Ribeirão Preto (UNAERP), receiving ration and hay two times per day and water 
   <span class="italic">ad libitum</span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For artificial and monospecific infection with 
   <span class="italic">H. contortus</span>, the animals were first treated with Zolvix® (Monepantel, Novartis Animal Health, 2.5 mg/kg body weight; Dundee, UK) according to the manufacturer's recommendations. After 14 days, a total reduction in egg load was confirmed by counting the number of eggs per gram of feces (epg = 0). The multidrug-resistant 
   <span class="italic">H. contortus</span> strain, Embrapa 2010, was used for monospecific infection and each animal was inoculated orally with approximately 4000 third-stage (L3) larvae. After 28 days of incubation, infection was confirmed by epg count. Animals with a count of 1500 to 5000 epg were considered parasitologically competent as feces donors for the in vitro assays. According to Chagas et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>], strain Embrapa 2010 was isolated from naturally contaminated animals of Embrapa Pecuária Sudeste, São Carlos, SP, and is characterized as resistant to anthelmintics of the benzimidazole, macrocyclic lactone and imidazothiazole classes.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In vitro anthelmintic assays</div>
  <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Egg recovery technique</div>
   <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The egg hatch test (EHT) and larval development test (LDT) described below were carried out after the recovery of 
    <span class="italic">H. contortus</span> eggs according to the method described previously [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. Approximately 20 g of feces were collected from the rectal ampulla of monospecifically infected animals and immediately filtered under running water (37 °C) through sieves with a mesh size of 500, 150, 90 and 20 μm, respectively. The eggs retained on the last sieve were washed, centrifuged for 5 min at 1811× 
    <span class="italic">g</span> with distilled water, and recovered in super-saturated saline by simple flotation. After recovery, the eggs were stored on the 20 μm sieve for abundant washing with distilled water to produce a final and quantified aqueous solution of eggs.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Egg hatch test (EHT)</div>
   <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the EHT, 24-well plates (TPP ref. no. 92024) containing aqueous solutions of approximately 100 eggs/well were used as proposed by Katiki et al. [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. The treatments consisted of different concentrations of each essential oil (50, 25, 12.5, 6.25, 3.125, 1.562, 0.781, 0.390, 0.195 and 0.097 mg/ml) in a final volume of 0.5 ml/well completed with distilled water. The oils were solubilized in distilled water and Tween 80 (3%, v/v). After incubation for 24 h (27 °C), the number of eggs and first-stage (L1) larvae were counted under an inverted microscope and compared to the positive (thiabendazole, 0.025 mg/ml) and negative controls (3% Tween 80, v/v). The results were expressed as the mean percentage of inhibition of egg hatching in three independent experiments performed in triplicate.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Larval development test (LDT)</div>
   <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The LDT was also carried out in 24-well plates containing approximately 100 eggs/well. Following the method described previously [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>], 80 μl of nutritive medium (
    <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span>, yeast extract, amphotericin B) was added to each well and completed with distilled water to a final volume of 250 μl. After incubation for 24 h (27 °C), different concentrations of each essential oil (3.0, 1.5, 0.75, 0.375, 0.187, 0.0937, 0.0468, 0.0234, 0.0117, 0.0058 and 0.0029 mg/ml) were solubilized in distilled water and DMSO (1%, v/v) and added to each well, resulting in a final volume of 0.5 ml. After 6 days, the differential count of L1, L2 and L3 larvae was performed and compared to the data obtained for the positive (levamisole, 20 mg/ml) and negative controls (1% DMSO, v/v). The results are the average of three replicates and are expressed as the percentage of larval development inhibition of three independent experiments.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adult worm motility test (AWMT)</div>
   <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The AWMT was performed after necropsy for removal of the abomasum and recovery of adult parasites from sheep infected artificially with the resistant isolate Embrapa 2010, using the method described previously [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>]. In 24-well plates, five adult parasites/well were treated separately with each essential oil at final concentrations of 50, 5.0 and 0.5 mg/ml. The oils were solubilized in PBS + antibiotic solution (penicillin/streptomycin) (4%) + Tween 80 (2%) in a final volume of 1 ml/well. The plates were kept in an oven at a controlled temperature (37 °C) throughout the experiment and mobile and immobile adult parasites were counted at intervals of 2 h. The total time of the experiment was defined when extensive parasite death was observed in the negative control (24 h). In fact, the effect of essential oils on the adult worm motility was estimated considering the natural nematode motility inhibition in the negative controls. Levamisole (20 mg/ml) was used as positive control and the negative controls consisted of PBS + antibiotic solution (penicillin/streptomycin) (4%) + Tween 80 (2%) and PBS + antibiotic solution (penicillin/streptomycin) (4%). The results are the average of three replicates and are expressed as the percentage of motility of adult parasites when exposed to different concentrations of essential oils of three independent experiments.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistics</div>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's test (
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05) was used for statistical analysis. Nonlinear regression/logarithmic distributions were applied to calculate the minimum concentration that inhibited 50% (IC
   <sub>50</sub>) of egg hatching or larval development.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
