<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Leishmaniasis are parasitic diseases. More than 20 
  <span class="italic">Leishmania</span> species have about 70 natural reservoir hosts and vectors including animals, such as dogs or rodents, and human bodies, and are transmitted by more than 90 sand fly species. These diseases are considered as a serious health concern which are occurring in Africa, Asia, Southern Europe and Latin America. Their prevalence rate was estimated from 900 000 to 1.3 million new cases and from 20 000 to 30 000 deaths annually. The parasite may survive for decades in asymptomatic infected people and can also be transmitted directly from person to person. Many factors can increase leishmaniasis like malnutrition, migration, poor housing, a weak immune system, environmental and climatic changes such as deforestation and temperature variation and lack of financial resources [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. In the absence of effective and sustainable vaccines, its control is still considered as a major public health problem [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>]. The chemotherapy and the drugs based on pentavalent antimonials as sodium stibugluconate (Pentostam®) and meglumine antimoniate (Glucantime®) are the current means of treatment [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>]. Therefore, the required long-term treatment, toxicity, grave side-effects, pain, cost, drug resistance associated with treatment failures point out the crucial need for new agents in the treatment of leishmaniasis [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Natural products traditionally used in folk medicine to treat several diseases are analyzed worldwide. In this regard, complex mixtures or purified compounds obtained from organic/aqueous extracts and essential oils of roots, stems, leaves, flowers, fruits and spices are various sources of diverse bioactive natural constituents [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. The investigations showed that wild and cultivated plants exhibited various pharmacological activities such as antimicrobial, anticancer, anti-inflammatory, antiparasitic including anti-leishmanial ones [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. Moreover, some plants essential oils and their main constituents displayed anti-leishmanial activities [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Haplophyllum tuberculatum</span> A. Juss is a perennial herb, belonging to the rutaceae family, native of North Africa and other areas of the Middle East. The aerial part of this plant is used as laxative, to cure gastro-intestinal affections, intermittent fevers, rheumatisms [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>], malaria, gynecological disorders and renal disorders [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]. Moreover, reviews have reported 
  <span class="italic">H. tuberculatum</span> as having nematicidal [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>], hepatoprotective [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>], antiplasmodial [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>] and insecticidal activities [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. Previous studies have also shown that 
  <span class="italic">H. tuberculatum</span> is rich in volatile oils. Furthermore, these essential oils exhibited nematicidal [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>], antimicrobial [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>], acetylcholinesterase inhibition and repellent activities [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main aim of the present study is to analyze the volatile oils of different 
  <span class="italic">H. tuberculatum</span> parts collected during two different seasons, to evaluate their anti-leishmanial effects against 
  <span class="italic">L. mexicana mexicana</span> promastigote forms and their cytotoxic activities against CHO cells in an in vitro model. In order to relate the oils bioactivities to pure components ones, a major compound, limonene, and two minor ones, octanol and linalool, were tested in vitro. The other identified major compounds, 
  <span class="italic">cis</span>-p-menth-2-en-1-ol, 
  <span class="italic">trans</span>-p-menth-2-en-1-ol, 
  <span class="italic">cis</span>-piperitol are not commercially available.
 </p>
</sec>
