<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec20" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results showed that the chemical composition varied according to the year of collection, but that stabilities issues may also modify the composition n along the time, as shown by the variation observed in the re-analyzed volatile oils.</p>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results showed that the chemical composition of the essential oils of different parts (leaves, stems and leaves+stems) from 
  <span class="italic">H. tuberculatum</span> varied according the period of collection. The re-analyzed volatile oils indicated that stabilities issues may also modify their composition along the time. The tested essential oils and one of their major component (
  <span class="italic">R</span>-(+)-limonene) were biologically active against 
  <span class="italic">L. mexicana mexicana</span> coupled to a cytotoxic effect on CHO in vitro.
 </p>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, as limonene is only present at concentration &lt; 10%, other compounds and/or synergistic effects remain to be analyzed to explain the observed activities. Thus, the biological activities of the identified major compounds, 
  <span class="italic">cis</span>-p-menth-2-en-1-ol, 
  <span class="italic">trans</span>-p-menth-2-en-1-ol, 
  <span class="italic">cis</span>-piperitol should be evaluated.
 </p>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results obtained in this study confirm the importance of chemical and biological investigations of essential oils but also toxicity risks. So in vitro studies are needed to assess the potential of these oils as anti-leishmanial agents and analyze deeper toxicity risks.</p>
 <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To our knowledge this is the first report of the anti-leishmanial and cytotoxic activity of the essential oils of 
  <span class="italic">H. tuberculatum</span>.
 </p>
</sec>
