<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A study aimed to characterize the carvacrol/β-CD inclusion complex, establish its physicochemical properties and evaluate its antimicrobial and antioxidant activities, since CDs can improve the solubility and dissolution of this water insoluble constituent by inclusion in the CDs’ hydrophobic cavities. CD-IC of carvacrol were prepared by the lyophilization and kneading methods, and were analyzed using DSC and phase solubility analysis. Both methods showed high entrapment efficiencies, drug loading, and increased solubility in water. Minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) for the inclusion complexes and pure carvacrol were determined using a broth dilution assay using 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella enterica</italic> cultures. The concentration of the carvacrol in the inclusion complexes used in the tests ranged from 2000 to 18,000 μg/mL (200 to 1800 μg·g/mL of carvacrol concentration based on the entrapment efficiency), while the concentrations of free carvacrol ranged from 250 to 1600 μg/mL. Minimum inhibitory concentration and minimum bactericidal concentration (MIC and MBC) values for free carvacrol were 1150 and 1000 μg/mL for 
 <italic class="italic">S. typhimurium</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic>, respectively. MIC values for HP-β-CD encapsulated carvacrol showed improvement in inhibition (MIC) ranging from 60 to 74% (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) more than free carvacrol for both pathogens. Moreover, bactericidal activity was also improved (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) for both pathogens, thereby reducing the carvacrol concentration needed to be effective. Both types of complexes inhibited 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. typhimurium</italic> at a lower concentration than free carvacrol, indicating that encapsulation may enhance the mechanism of antimicrobial action and decrease the concentration of antimicrobial compound required for inhibition [
 <xref rid="B79-ijms-20-00642" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>].
</p>
