<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par49" class="p">Closing this subsection, the SAR of the hydrophobic azoxy compounds jietacins (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig" class="xref">9</xref>) has been explored and reported recently [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" class="xref">117</xref>]. This compound class, produced by 
 <italic class="italic">Streptomyces</italic> bacteria, and its nematocidal activity were first described decades ago by workers at the Kitasato Institute [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118" class="xref">118</xref>], but no reports of chemical development had appeared until 2018. Interestingly, a Japanese patent application was filed a year before the first communication by the original authors (JP S6366155 A), but it seems to have been abandoned. However, a Chinese institution did obtain local intellectual property (IP) protection for methods to prepare the compounds in 1995 (CN 1027905 C). The SAR study now published by Sugawara et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" class="xref">117</xref>] indicates that a vinyl azoxy group, located at the end of a linear aliphatic chain of 9–14 carbon atoms, is most efficacious 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic>. Compounds were tested 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> for inhibition of motility of xL3 larvae of both 
 <italic class="italic">Cooperia curticei</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">H. contortus</italic>, and for inhibition of enzyme secretion by adult 
 <italic class="italic">Nippostrongylus brasilensis</italic>. The most active compounds exhibited complete inhibition in the three assays at concentrations of 1–5 µg/ml (3–16 µM) and showed 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> efficacy in mice infected with 
 <italic class="italic">Heligmosomoides polygyrus</italic> at 25–100 mg/kg, p.o., q.d., for 4 days [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" class="xref">117</xref>]. The parent compound, jietacin A, was also efficacious 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> under the same conditions and, unlike some of the simplified analogues, did not present tolerability issues in mice, although it lacked activity against 
 <italic class="italic">H. contortus</italic>. These compounds could be regarded as simple amphiphiles, which are able to disrupt biological membranes and protein–protein interactions by virtue of their detergent-like physicochemical properties. However, the reported jietacins displayed some striking 
 <italic class="italic">regio</italic>-isomerism and chiral effects, which would be difficult to explain if they acted as simple detergents. The vinyl azoxy group, in particular, appears to be worth investigating in other structural contexts.
</p>
