<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0054">Strata of mankind has been marred with the onset of the unexpected pandemics, leading to the atrocious effects on their entire communities. Considering themselves invincible to conquer the world, they have now become the cocoons of their houses against COVID-19 storm. Unfortunately, SARS-CoV-2 has led the global population on their toes due to its highly infectious nature and susceptibility towards humans in causing higher mortalities among them. We can also introspect that about a lot many cases of COVID-19 have been undetected and by looking into the ongoing trends, the cases are going to inflate in the coming future. This would ultimately affect the world economy, specifically within developing and under-developing nations. Besides, WHO has advised the world to take preventive measures, owing to which government has facilitated nationwide shutdowns, self-quarantine, physical distancing to ensure public safety. Thus far, the prevailing drugs and vaccines for antiviral diseases have been used as clinical trials to fight against coronavirus. Furthermore, by studying the gene pool of SARS-CoV-2, researchers would be able to invent the vaccine for this petrified virus. While, the zeal and zest for the discovery of therapeutics have been plummeted in last few years, yet the dominance of plants and their products are still gaining light in this darkness. Our review projected the possible role of herbal plants and their sources in the treatment of COVID-19 infections due to its bioactive ingredients acting as substantial warriors in this battle. Intriguingly, pro-active devotions in this research would definitely enable us to develop vaccines or drugs to cure COVID-19, for which it is pre-requisite to unlock this treasure of information pertaining to traditional medicines. However, there is an urgent need to invest time on these studies for acquiring about appropriate doses and formulations for discovering drugs or vaccines from these formulations. For this purpose, scientific evidences and comprehensive pharmaco-dynamic knowledge related to medicinal plants should be made available to scientists to design clinical trials. Integration of this concept would certainly develop the drug therapy in the near future. All what we can do is wait for the hope of radiance at the terminating point of the tunnel, in solitude.</p>
