<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Red propolis sample collection and essential oil preparation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Red propolis was collected from the municipality of Brejo Grande, located in the state of Sergipe, in northeastern Brazil (S 10°28'25” and W 36°26'12”). Samples were collected in September 2011 and were maintained frozen at −20 °C until use. For the preparation of the essential oil, conventional hydrodistillation was carried out using a Clevenger-type apparatus. Briefly, 380 g of BRP was transferred to a volumetric flask, and 2 L of distilled water was added. A heating mantle was placed onto the Clevenger apparatus. The essential oil was extracted after boiling the mixture for a time period of one hour. The essential oil obtained was collected in amber vials and stored at 4 °C until use. The total yield obtained was approximately 0.25%.</p>
  <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography–mass spectrometry (GC-MS)</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemical composition analysis was performed using a gas chromatograph coupled with a mass-selective detector (Hewlett Packard 6890/MSD5973, Palo Alto, USA) equipped with the HP ChemStation software and the Wiley 275 library. A capillary column composed of HP-INNOWax fused silica (30 m × 250 μm) of 0.50 μm film thickness (Hewlett-Packard, Palo Alto, USA) was used for the study. The temperature program used was as follows: the column temperature started at 40 °C (held for 8 min) and was increased to 180 °C at 3 °C/min and then to 230 °C (held for 20 min) at 20 °C/min; the injector was at a temperature of 250 °C and the interface at 280 °C. The split ratio was 1:100, helium was the carrier gas (56 kPa), the flow rate was 1 mL/min, the ionization energy was 70 eV, and the injected volume was 0.4 mL.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anti-
   <span class="italic">Trichomonas vaginalis</span> activity assay
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
   <span class="italic">T</span>. 
   <span class="italic">vaginalis</span> 30236 isolate used for evaluating antiparasitic activity in this study was obtained from the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC). Trophozoites were axenically cultured in trypticase-yeast extract-maltose (TYM) medium (without agar; pH = 6.0) supplemented with 10% sterile bovine serum (inactivated at 56 °C) and incubated at 37 °C [
   <a rid="pone.0191797.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref032">32</a>]. Cultures with 95% viability, as confirmed through observation of motility, morphology, and trypan-blue exclusion (0.4%) assay under the light microscope at 400X magnification, were considered as alive and were used for evaluating the activity of EOP.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All assays were performed in 96-well microtiter plates (Cral
   <span class="sup">®</span>). Parasites were seeded at an initial density of 2.6 × 10
   <span class="sup">5</span> trophozoites/mL of TYM and incubated in the presence of EOP. Three experimental controls were also performed: parasites only, the vehicle used for solubilization of EOP (0.6% DMSO) and 100 μM MTZ (metronidazole; Sigma-Aldrich) (as a positive control). The microculture plates were incubated at 37 °C with 5% CO
   <sub>2</sub> for 24 h. Subsequent to the incubation, a preparation containing trophozoites and trypan blue (0.4%) in a 1:1 ratio was prepared and counted in a Neubauer chamber. Cultures with 95% viability were utilized for the assay.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC), different concentrations of EOP (25, 50, 100, 200, 300, 400, and 500 μg/mL) were tested as described by Hübner et al. [
   <a rid="pone.0191797.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref033">33</a>], with some modification. Parasite pellets were used to establish the MIC as well as concentrations below and above the MIC value. Samples used as controls were inoculated in fresh TYM medium at 37 °C. Parasites were counted in a Neubauer chamber with trypan blue every 24 h for 96 h to confirm MIC. The viability of trophozoites was assessed by the exclusion of the trypan blue dye as well as by motility and morphology. The IC
   <sub>50</sub> (half the maximum inhibitory concentration) values were determined at the same concentrations used for the MIC test.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A kinetic growth curve was constructed in order to obtain a more comparable activity profile of EOP activity against 
   <span class="italic">T</span>. 
   <span class="italic">vaginalis</span>. The viability of trophozoites was observed under a light microscope 96 h after incubation with EOP at the required MIC. Growth analysis was performed at 1, 6, 12, 24, 48, 72, and 96 h by the trypan blue (0.4%) exclusion method and by the evaluation of motility and morphology. All assays were performed independently at least three times in triplicate, and the results were expressed as the percentage of viable trophozoites compared to untreated parasites.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the Anti-
   <span class="italic">Trichomonas vaginalis</span> activity assay, statistical analysis was conducted using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA), and a probability value of 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. Tukey’s test was utilized to identify significant differences between the means of different treatments. GraphPad Prism version 5.0 for Windows (GraphPad Software, USA) was used for statistical analysis.
  </p>
  <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cytotoxicity assay</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chinese hamster ovary (CHO-K1) cells were obtained from the Rio de Janeiro Cell Bank (PABCAM, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil) and cultured as a monolayer in Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle’s Medium (DMEM) (Vitrocell Embriolife) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) (Vitrocell Embriolife), 1% L-glutamine, and 1% penicillin/streptomycin. The cells were grown at 37 °C in an atmosphere of 95% humidified air and 5% CO
    <sub>2</sub>.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The post-treatment proliferation of the CHO-K1 cell line was determined by measuring the reduction of soluble 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl tetrazolium bromide (MTT, Sigma-Aldrich) to water-insoluble formazan. Cells were seeded in 96-well plates at a density of 2 × 10
    <span class="sup">4</span> cells per well in 100 μL volumes and grown at 37 °C in a 5% CO
    <sub>2</sub> atmosphere for 24 h before they were used in the cell viability assay. The cells were then treated with 31.25, 62.5, 125, 250 and 500 μg of EOP for 24 h. DMSO was used as vehicle control (VC), untreated cells were used as a negative control and 100 μM of metronidazole (MTZ) was used as a positive control. Following the incubation, 20 μL of MTT (Sigma-Aldrich) was added to each well and the cells were incubated for an additional period of 3 h at 37 °C. Differences in the total cellular metabolism were detected at a wavelength of 492 nm by using a microplate reader. The inhibition (%) of cell proliferation was determined as follows: inhibitory growth = (1 − Abs
    <sub>492</sub> treated cells / Abs
    <sub>492</sub> control cells) × 100%. The IC
    <sub>50</sub> was calculated using GraphPad Prism version 5.0 for Windows (GraphPad Software, USA). All observations were validated by at least three independent experiments in triplicate.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec007" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adjuvant assay</div>
  <sec id="sec008" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental animals</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Six- to eight-week-old female BALB/c mice were obtained from the Central Animal Facility of the Federal University of Pelotas, where the immunization assays were also conducted. All mice were kept in cages containing wood shavings and bedding and had free access to water and a maintenance diet 
    <span class="italic">ad libitum</span>. A 12-h light/dark cycle at room temperature (21 ± 2 °C) was also maintained. All experiments were performed in compliance with the procedures of the Brazilian College of Animal Experimentation (COBEA). The Ethics Commission on Animal Experimentation (CEEA) of Pelotas Federal University (UFPel) approved the project (number 2422). All efforts were made to minimize animal suffering.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec009" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antigen expression and purification</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The recombinant endoglycosidase CP40 (rCP40), derived from 
    <span class="italic">C</span>. 
    <span class="italic">pseudotuberculosis</span>, was used as an antigen for the adjuvant assay. The pAE/
    <span class="italic">cp40</span> recombinant plasmid previously constructed by our group [
    <a rid="pone.0191797.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref034">34</a>] was transformed into the 
    <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span> BL21 (DE3) Star strain by the heat shock method. The induction of expression was performed by adding 1 mM of IPTG followed by incubation at 37 °C for 3 h with constant agitation. Western blotting using a monoclonal anti-6x-His-tag antibody conjugated to peroxidase (Sigma-Aldrich) was used to confirm rCP40 expression. A sepharose-nickel column, HisTrapTM (GE Healthcare), was used for purification of the recombinant protein. Purity was determined by 12% SDS-PAGE, and the concentration was measured using a BCA kit (PIERCE).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec010" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Immunization assay and blood sample collection</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the immunization assay, the mice were divided into the following three groups of six animals each: (a) G1: a negative control group immunized with 0,4 ng/kg BW EOP; (b) G2: inoculated with only 50 μg of rCP40 protein; and (c) G3: the test group inoculated with 0,4 ng/kg BW EOP plus 50 μg of rCP40. All doses were prepared in a final volume of 200 μL using sterile saline solution (0.9% NaCl) as a vehicle and administered via the intramuscular route. The animals were immunized with two doses administered 21 days apart. Animals were bled at days 0, 21, and 42 post-immunization to determine the antibody levels. Blood was collected from the retro-orbital sinus with Pasteur pipettes. All blood collections were performed under anesthesia with 10% ketamine (1 mL/kg) and 2% xylazine (0.1 mg/kg) (Agener União Saúde Animal, Brazil). After coagulation, the blood was centrifuged at 1,500 g for 15 min. The serum was removed and stored at −20 °C.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec011" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assessment of antibody production</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Serum samples from the immunized mice were used in immunoassays (indirect ELISA) for the quantification of total IgG, IgG1 and IgG2a anti-rCP40 antibodies. Polystyrene 96-well plates (Maxisorp-Nunc) were coated with 100 μL of a bicarbonate-carbonate buffer (pH 9.8) containing 0.1 μg/well of rCP40 protein. Plates were incubated for 18 h at 4 °C and washed 3 times with PBS-T (PBS 1X, pH 7.4, 0.1% Tween 20). The plates were then incubated with 200 μL/well of 5% skim milk in PBS for 2 h at 37 °C, for blocking purposes. A three-step wash was then performed. All serum samples obtained from mice were diluted in PBS (v/v 1:50), and 100 μL of each diluted sample was added to the plates in duplicate. Plates were incubated for 1 h at 37 °C. After washing three times with PBS-T, 100 μL/well of anti-mouse IgG conjugated to horseradish peroxidase (Sigma-Aldrich) was added (1: 5,000 in PBS-T) to the plates in order to detect total IgG prior to the revelation step. In plates designated for the detection of IgG1 and IgG2a, 100 μL/well of either goat anti-mouse IgG1 (1: 5,000 in PBS-T) or goat anti-mouse IgG2a (1: 2,000 in PBS-T) was added. The plates were incubated at 37 °C for 1 h and then washed three times with PBS-T, subsequent to which 100 μL/well of anti-goat IgG conjugated to horseradish peroxidase (Sigma-Aldrich) was added (1: 5,000 in PBS-T). The plates were re-incubated for 1 h at 37 °C and then washed five times with PBS-T. The reaction was developed by the addition of 100 μL/well of the substrate-chromogen solution [
    <span class="italic">o</span>-phenylenediamine dihydrochloride; OPD tablets (Sigma-Aldrich) in 0.4 mg/mL phosphate-citrate buffer containing 0.04% of 30% hydrogen peroxide, pH = 5.0] and incubation at room temperature in the dark for 15 min, and it was stopped by the addition of 50 μL/well of H
    <sub>2</sub>SO
    <sub>4</sub> solution (4N). Optical density (OD) was determined using a microtiter-plate reader (Microplate Reader Mindray MR–96A) set at 492 nm.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data were analyzed using the software GraphPad Prism version 5.0 for Windows (GraphPad Software, USA). Differences in IgG levels between the groups were analyzed using one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's test for multiple comparisons. The results were considered statistically significant if p-value &lt;0.05.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
