<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Currently, the Brazilian propolis is classified in 13 different types, according to its physical-chemical properties, botanical origin and geographic area where propolis can be collected. Initially, Park et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref001">1</a>] classified propolis samples from different Brazilian regions in 12 groups. Afterwards, a 13
  <span class="sup">th</span> type of propolis with peculiar chemical composition was found in hives located alongside the coast and mangroves in the Brazilian northeast and was called Brazilian red propolis (BRP) [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref002">2</a>]. In the last decade, the chemical composition of BRP has been revealed and related to its bioactivities. The main chemical components found in BRP are classified as isoflavones, flavones, flavonols, aurones, chalcones, pterocarpans and xanthones groups [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref003">3</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref006">6</a>]. The botanical origin of BRP was identified as resinous exudates of 
  <span class="italic">Dalbergia ecastophyllum</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref007">7</a>], however, likely a second plant species participates as one of the main sources of resins for BRP [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref005">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the variety of chemical compounds of BRP incorporated within the resin mixture, especially phenolic compounds, many biological activities have been reported like antioxidant [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref002">2</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref008">8</a>], antibacterial [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref010">10</a>], fungicide [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref011">11</a>], antiparasitic [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref010">10</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref012">12</a>], antineoplasic [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref013">13</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref014">14</a>], anti-caries [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref015">15</a>], cytotoxic [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref002">2</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref010">10</a>], anti-inflamatory [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref017">17</a>], antinociceptive [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref018">18</a>] and was also beneficial to the wound healing process [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref019">19</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several experiments and clinical investigations have shown the antiparasitic and adjuvant properties of the hydroalcoholic extract of propolis (HEP). HEP of different types of propolis showed antiparasitary efficacy against 
  <span class="italic">Giardia lamblia</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref020">20</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref021">21</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Toxoplasma gondii</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Trichomonas vaginalis</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref022">22</a>]. It is important to highlight that 
  <span class="italic">T</span>. 
  <span class="italic">vaginalis</span> is the etiological agent of trichomoniasis, the most common non-viral, sexually transmitted disease (STD) in the world [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref023">23</a>]. In addition, metronidazole-resistant T. vaginalis has been implicated in an increasing number of refractory cases, which are usually treated with increased doses of the drug, leading to an increase in the occurrence of side effects [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref024">24</a>]. Clearly, alternative curative therapies are needed, and propolis emerges as a natural product for alternative drugs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moreover, HEP has been used to formulate veterinary vaccines against bacterial or viral diseases, once some phenolic compounds has presented immunomodulatory activity [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref025">25</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref027">27</a>]. As adjuvant, propolis confers to the vaccinal formulation desirable properties, such as reduced viscosity, good stability, low reactogenicity, low toxicity, and is able to induce a robust humoral and cellular response [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref026">26</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As aforementioned, most of the previous studies describing the biological activities of BRP uses ethanol as the extraction solvent, and the extraction method influences directly the yield and selectivity for some compounds [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref010">10</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref028">28</a>]. Volatile compounds like those found in essential oils are in low concentrations in propolis, but play an important role by contributing to propolis pleasant aroma and its biological activities. Researchers have applied various methods to obtain propolis volatiles such as distilllation-extraction or hydrodistillation [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref029">29</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand, studies focusing on essential oils of propolis volatiles are relatively scarce, most of them dealing with antimicrobial properties against fungus, Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref029">29</a>]. Volatiles of propolis from stingless bees were able to stimulate the immune system of elderly patients by increasing their natural killer cell activity [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref030">30</a>]. Essential oils of Chinese propolis inhibited the proliferation of human colorectal cancer cells by inducing cell cycle arrest and apoptosis [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref031">31</a>]. However, to the best of our knowledge, there are no studies describing the chemical composition or the biological activities of the essential oil derived from the Brazilian red propolis (EOP). Herein, the chemical composition of the EOP is showed. Still, in vitro trichomonacidal and cytotoxic activities, and the adjuvant action of EOP in a recombinant vaccine are assessed.
 </p>
</sec>
