<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It has been well established from biological, biochemical and behavioural studies that the consumption of diets high in omega-3 fatty acids has many health advantages such as reducing the risk of heart disease, inflammation, obesity, cancer, hypertension, depression and asthma [
 <xref rid="B14-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. These effects can be mediated through autoimmune functions, pathological responses, insulin-stimulated energy disposal, gene expressed signal transduction, eicosanoid metabolism. If omega-3 fatty acids are beneficial in improving the health and wellbeing of humans and animals, it could possibly be through amelioration of oxidative stress, immune suppression and cell damage enhanced by the antioxidant defence. In this case, there should be associative effects between activity and/or relative mRNA expressions of antioxidant enzymes and diet-induced changes in muscle essential n-3 fatty acids, for example, ALA. Feeding alfalfa (lucerne) forage or supplemental flaxseed to sheep increased muscle essential n-3 fatty acid concentration, mainly ALA, in sheep [
 <xref rid="B8-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Therefore, the hypothesis to be tested in the present experiment is that if there was a significant increase in muscle ALA concentration with dietary intervention, it should alter the activity and(or) relative mRNA expression of antioxidant enzymes through cellular biochemical mechanisms and signal transductions. To test this, we used feedlot diets that generally provide high proportions of LA so that muscle n-6 levels will be increased significantly to compare with a pasture diet such as lucerne (alfalfa) that may enrich muscle n-3 levels, providing an extreme range of fatty acids for comparisons.
</p>
