<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<app-group>
 <app id="app1-microorganisms-09-00138">
  <title>Supplementary Materials</title>
  <p>Supplementary materials can be found at 
   <uri xlink:href="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2607/9/1/138/s1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2607/9/1/138/s1</uri>, Table S1: Soil properties from different plant communities, Table S2: The relative abundance of bacterial phyla between SC, TC and MC samples, where 1 represents the 0–15 cm soil layer and 2 represents the 15–30 cm soil layer. Table S3: The relative abundance of fungal phyla between SC, TC and MC communities, where 1 represents the 0–15 cm soil layer and 2 represents the 15–30 cm soil layer. Table S4: Relative abundance (&gt;1%) of bacterial potential functional pathways at level 2 in the SC, TC and MC communities. Table S5: Relative abundance (&gt;1%) of fungal potential functional groups at the level of Guilds in the SC, TC and MC communities (There was no significant difference of each functional group among the three plant communities in the same soil layer at a 
   <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05 according to Tukey test). Table S6: Results of PerMANOVA test in bacterial community composition among the SC, TC and MC communities. Table S7: Results of PerMANOVA test in fungal community composition among the SC, TC and MC communities. Table S8: Results of PerMANOVA test in bacterial function composition among the SC, TC and MC communities. Table S9: Results of PerMANOVA test in fungal function composition among the SC, TC and MC communities. Table S10: The barcode information corresponding to samples’ information. Figure S1: Results of PCoA showing the first two principal coordinates that, combined, explain 70.78% and 30.97% of the observed variation in bacterial (a) and fungal (b) functional structure. The shapes of up triangle and square on the figure legend correspond to the soil layer of 0–15 cm and 15–30 cm, and the colors of red, green and yellow correspond to the SC, TC and MC communities, respectively (PerMANOVA test, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).
  </p>
 </app>
</app-group>
