<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we did not investigate the related functions of each brain area; however, we investigate a function related with arousal level. The sleep onset-latency was measured in this study to further extend the knowledge related with sedative function of tangerine oil. We prepared the oil in the level of subthreshold and threshold concentration instead of suprathreshold, undiluted oil. We found that both the subthreshold and threshold showed an interesting function opposite to undiluted oil. It showed a sedative effect in these ranges of dilutions. We hypothesized that the oil may help sleep function. Only female subjects were recruited in this study and the result confirms the hypothesis. The result briefly showed the effect on the alertness system. Sleep onset latency decreased in female subjects. 
 <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> essential oil also decreased sleep onset latency, which is like the threshold level of tangerine oil [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In vivo study revealed that limonene significantly increased γ-aminobutyric acid (GABA) and other neurotransmitter changes [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. GABA is acting though GABA
 <sub>A</sub> receptor, which is potentiating chloride current resembling alcohol, barbiturates, and benzodiazepines. Moreover, other neurotransmitters were reported to change after limonene administration such as dopamine (DA), serotonin (5-HT), and glutamate (Glu). These neurotransmitters play an important role related with the waking system of the brain so the direct effect of the oil to neurotransmitter function may be the underlying mechanism related with its sedative and vigilance effects. This detailed mechanism is still needed to be investigated. The gender difference was indirectly observed in this study. Previous studies also showed different brain waves between female and male during inhalation of (+)-α-pinene and (+)-β-pinene as well as black pepper essential oil [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Moreover, the other studies revealed that reproductive hormones and odor reception are the cause of different responses between genders [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Different olfactory sensitivity between genders of many animal species may be caused by the physical receptor [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In other studies, corpus collosum of females is larger than males; in addition, the development of cerebral lateralization of females is also faster than males [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Furthermore, the other study showed that females responded to the molecules of the essential oil more than male did, and Haehner et al. also revealed that responses of females and males to grapefruit or a combination of orange, lime and lemon fragrances are different [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In addition, sex-related performance can be explained by reproductive hormone influences on odor perception. Doty et al. explained that alterations of olfactory performance were observed in different states of hormone reproduction, such as gonadectomy, hormone replacement therapy, pregnancy, and menstrual cycle [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. All the above are consistent with the present study because females have more brain activity during inhalation of tangerine essential oil compared with male subjects. Cognitive tasks should be further examined in the future to study the related brain functions. A previous study showed that San-Jo-In essential oil can increase attention and relaxation with a significant increase in fast alpha power at the left prefrontal, right prefrontal and left frontal regions in the same way as the effect of lavender and bergamot [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Moreover, alpha increase in the frontal brain region was related to moods, helping to decrease tension and stress states [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. With regards to the effect of increased beta wave power in frontal regions, other studies showed that it was related to alertness and concentration state including memory task performance improvement [
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Kim et al. showed that alpha wave was increased during inhalation of (+)-α-pinene and (+)-β-pinene, which may improve brain functions and enhance relaxation. This study only measured overall brain responses and related functions such as sleep function. The mechanism related with brain communication is still obscured during essential oil inhalations.
</p>
