<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Ageratina altissima</italic> is a noxious weed and an invasive plant that is very difficult to control (Chun et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Kim, Jang, &amp; Park, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Lee, Yoo, &amp; Lee, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>; Lee et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). In the field, invasion success is determined by the interplay among environmental conditions, propagule pressure, and biotic resistance (Catford, Jansson, &amp; Nilsson, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; D'Antonio, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">1993</xref>; Dethier &amp; Hacker, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Perelman, Chaneton, Batista, Burkart, &amp; León, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0082" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). Although this experiment did not test all these factors affecting invasion, the approach generally revealed the importance of biotic resistance. The forest edge, disturbed by human activities such as trampling and creation of paths, is the site for much of the invasion by this invasive plant (Chun et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Kim et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Lee et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>), and 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> was identified as an indicator species of edge effect following recent silvicultural clearcutting in a mixed mesophytic forest (Landenberger &amp; Ostergren, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). Trampling has a role in the invasion window of 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic>, and sites in which they grow vigorously show low species diversity due to their dense cover (Lee et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). Human activities that result in disturbance increase the susceptibility of most ecosystems, which highlights the requirement, when applicable, to minimize damage to the matrix of vegetation cover and/or facilitate the rapid establishment of competitive cover with the goal to restore disturbed habitat. In these cases, the results of this study showed that functional group identity and diversity of resident or restored plant communities were good indicators of potential biotic resistance to seed‐mediated invasion by 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic>. We suggest the use of FG1 species, such as 
 <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> and 
 <italic>Secale cereal</italic>, primarily, to restore native plant cover to suppress invasion by 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> and also mixing FG1 with FG3 species for niche partitioning and potential long‐term effects. Concerning propagule pressure, most field situations are expected to have much lower seed pressure than the level tested in this experiment; however, even then, complete competitive exclusion may not be achieved. Follow‐up monitoring and selective control of 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> establishment could be necessary. The distribution of 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> is closely correlated with the soil contents of total nitrogen and available phosphorus (Suh, Kil, Kim, &amp; Lee, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0107" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>), and 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> is adaptable to a broad range of soil conditions (Kim et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>); therefore, controlling for these elements will help to further suppress the growth of 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic>. Growth of 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> is highest at a light intensity of 7,500 lux (Suh et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0107" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>) and is correlated with decreasing litter depth (Kim et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>); thus, increased cover of native plants will decrease light intensity and increase litter depth to contribute to the suppression of this plant.
</p>
