<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Intercontinental introductions of 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> species have occurred over several centuries (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU027F3">3</xref>). The first reports were of the introduction of 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> species from the Americas to Senegal in 1822, and to Australia, Hawaii, India, Philippines, South Africa, Sri Lanka and Sudan in the late 1800s and early 1900s (
 <xref rid="PLU027C62" ref-type="bibr">Pasiecznik 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2001
 </xref>). However, most of the widespread introductions were made into Africa and Asia between the 1970s and 1990s (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU027F3">3</xref>) as part of reforestation programmes after major droughts in the Sahel. Many areas, notably India, South Africa and Sudan, have had multiple introductions over many decades. There is no evidence of new introductions post 1990, with the last recorded introductions being in Malawi and Burkina Faso in 1986 (
 <xref rid="PLU027C70" ref-type="bibr">Ræbild 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2003
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU027C13" ref-type="bibr">Chikuni 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2004
 </xref>). There have, however, been recent calls for the introduction of known invasive 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> species to new locations. 
 <xref rid="PLU027C35" ref-type="bibr">Hasan and Alam (2006)</xref> recommend that the planting of 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> would be beneficial to combat degradation in Bangladesh. 
 <xref rid="PLU027C57" ref-type="bibr">Parvaresh (2011)</xref> proposed using 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> to stabilize dunes to protect important biologically diverse wetlands and mangrove forests in Iran. The promotion of biofuels could also lead to the spread of invasive woody species such as 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> (
 <xref rid="PLU027C96" ref-type="bibr">Witt 2010</xref>). There has also been extensive natural spread (commonly by means of flood water) and human-assisted spread (livestock trade) into new areas within countries where it is already naturalized and invasive (
 <xref rid="PLU027C83" ref-type="bibr">Van den Berg 2010</xref>). 
</p>
