<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045" class="p">Antibacterial susceptibility testing was performed according the CLSI laboratory standard for broth microdilution assays 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[16]</xref>. Concentrations tested in the assays ranged from 6400 to 50 μg/ml in bisecting dilution steps. Assays were performed using sterile 96 well microplates (transparent, F-bottom) (Greiner bio-one, Frickenhausen, Germany). Each concentration was tested in triplicate and a single blank (broth with corresponding EO-concentration). Three oils were tested in parallel per plate (n = 3). Ultimately, each well contained 100 μl of EO dispersion. Inoculum was prepared by a hundredfold dilution of the adjusted cell suspension in double concentrated (2*) MHB. Each well was spiked with 100 μl inoculated 2*MHB resulting in a final cell count of 1.0*10
 <sup class="sup">5</sup> cfu per well. Inoculation media were used immediately to avoid growth dependent shifts in the cell count. Growth, sterility and quality controls were analyzed for every culture, but on separate microplates. Chloramphenicol (2.0–0.008 μg/ml) served as control bacteriostatic to assess cell susceptibility for each batch culture (data not shown). Prior to incubation for 24 h at 37 °C, the inoculated plates were shaken orbital for 30 s on a plate mixer (Kisker, Steinfurt, Germany). To avoid loss of volatile essential oil and humidity during incubation each plate was sealed with a sterile, gas-permeable seal (BREATHseal, Greiner bio-one, Frickenhausen, Germany). Turbidity measurement was performed after incubation in a microplate reader (Tecan, Männedorf, Switzerland) at 595 nm. The seals were removed and plates were shaken orbital for 30 s. Each well was measured at nine spots with 5 flashes per spot. Obtained spot-OD-values of each well were averaged as well-OD-values. Values of parallel wells were averaged afterwards and blank-OD-values were subtracted. The minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) was defined as the lowest concentration tested which did not allow cell growth within 24 h at 37 °C.
</p>
