<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">EOs from 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> genus are the most popular EOs and are the largest proportion of natural flavors and fragrances [
 <xref rid="B4-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Some orange varieties such as bitter orange (
 <italic class="italic">Citrus aurantium</italic>) are grown primarily for their peel and the associated essential oil industrial production for citrus flavor applications [
 <xref rid="B5-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. As an example, EOs from the dried peel of unripe bitter orange fruits flavor drinks and liquors, like Curaçao, Cointreau, and Triple Sec [
 <xref rid="B2-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. In the food industry, there is strong interest in their antimicrobial activity linked to the main constituents of their volatile fraction [
 <xref rid="B6-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Fruit ripening has the most important impact on the development of flavor and other chemical quality attributes, such as nutritional and biochemical compositions, in citrus fruits. Many researchers have pointed out the importance of ripening on quality attributes of citrus peels and their products such as essential oils [
 <xref rid="B6-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Owing to the commercial importance of bitter orange EO its characterization and analysis has been extensively developed [
 <xref rid="B10-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. For quality assessment, two main types of methods can be used, subjective (sensorial analysis) and objective (analytical methods). The first option is sensorial analysis. This step has several undesired features such as the need of involving a group of trained panelists; this can be problematic for routine analysis [
 <xref rid="B11-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>] as they can suffer adaptation or fatigue [
 <xref rid="B12-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Sensorial analysis can have large sources of variation, low throughput [
 <xref rid="B12-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>], and it can be costly [
 <xref rid="B13-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. For this reason, alternative analytical techniques such as separation techniques based on chromatography in tandem with mass spectrometry could be very beneficial; they are non-subjective, highly repeatable, and reproducible. Additionally, the possibility to identify the compounds from mass spectral data is a major factor in favor of this technique [
 <xref rid="B14-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Several studies have already investigated the composition of the volatile compounds of bitter orange EO by this technique. They were conducted to determine chemical families present in the EO [
 <xref rid="B15-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>], authenticity [
 <xref rid="B16-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], olfactive properties [
 <xref rid="B17-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] or the effects of several factors including geographical location [
 <xref rid="B19-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>], season [
 <xref rid="B21-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]
 <bold class="bold">,</bold> and variety, on composition [
 <xref rid="B8-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. While most research is focused on direct injection of the EO, there are also authors that propose to directly sample the headspace focusing directly on the more volatile fraction [
 <xref rid="B23-sensors-18-01922" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>].
</p>
