<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">The major flavonoids of tea are catechins which include (−)-epicatechin-3-gallate (ECG), (−)-epigallocatechin-3-gallate (EGCG), (−)- epicatechin (EC), (−)- epigallocatechin (EGC, primary component) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. These catechins are converted to flavins and the arubigins, by an enzymatic reaction, are known as effective vasodilators. These catechins are also responsible for major elevation in blood flow by increased liberation of NO through a simultaneous decline in intensities of oxidative stress and dimethylarginine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. Moreover, Hong et al. reported that EGCG was capable of reduceactivation of an NF- kB in endothelial cells of humans. It has the secondary metabolites like purine alkaloids, phenolic acids, flavan-3-ols, flavonols, saponins, hydrolyzable tannins, and condensed tannins as well as their glycoside forms. Many chemical constituents such as flavan-3-ols derivatives, theaflavins, thearubigins, etc
 <italic>.</italic> are emerged to form new constituents with a change in the concentration of others.Sodepending on the process each type of tea has different flavorsand constituents. Aqueous extract of 
 <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> can produce pleiotropic effects as well as anti-diabetic, anti-inflammatory antibacterial, antihypertensive and anti-cancer activities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. Deka and Vita, according to them the person consuming regularly green and black tea having a minor risk of hypertension [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. Peng et al. also reported based on meta-analysis that regular use of tea has a major decreasing result on diastolic blood pressure (DBP) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>], other studies showed that it is concentration dependent [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. According toa Japanese group analysis, regular consumption of concentrated, only green tea can reduce the CVD mortality risk [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. The 
 <italic>o</italic>-methylated EGCG content of tea can inhibit angiotensin-converting enzyme therefore consumption of black tea extract by regular 7 days has a decreasing effect on systolic blood pressure (SBP). Cheang et al. on basis of their study explain that theaflavin-3,3-digallate can inhibit acetylcholine dependent contraction and enhance endothelial functionby reducingthe stress of endoplasmic reticulum and modifyingHcyenzymes such as cystathionine gamma-lyase and cystathionine-
 <italic>β</italic>-synthase. By consumption of lyophilized extract of green tea, a majordecline in SBP (− 4.9 mmHg) andDBP (− 4.7 mmHg) in slightly hypertensive patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]. According to Peng et al. gree tea can reduce blood pressure by different mechanisms such as by maintaining balance among vasoconstricting, vasodilating and hyperpolarizing factors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. It has a rising effect on the production of nitric oxide (NO) to enhance ventricular function and manage ROS production by provoking antioxidant enzymes and reducing pro-oxidant enzymes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>].
</p>
