<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In agreement with Hadaš et al. [
 <xref rid="B42-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>] and Liu et al. [
 <xref rid="B36-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>], liveborn mortality in the current study tended to be lower for piglets born to dams fed the CLA diet. However, Lee et al. [
 <xref rid="B35-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>] found no effect, and Barowicz et al. [
 <xref rid="B43-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>] and Krogh et al. [
 <xref rid="B37-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] actually found higher mortality rates in piglets born to sows fed CLA. The finding that SB was higher in CLA-fed sows compared to CON sows—and that NBA was lower in CLA-fed primiparous sows than those primiparous sows on the other dietary treatments—was surprising, as most previous studies found no difference [
 <xref rid="B8-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>], and some even suggested that CLA increased NBA [
 <xref rid="B5-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. In addition, Liu et al. [
 <xref rid="B36-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>] found that feeding CLA had no effect on farrowing duration in primiparous sows, which suggests that increased farrowing difficulty was not the reason for higher SB or lower NBA in the current study. These differences may be due to inconsistencies between methodology, as there are variations between these studies in time period (e.g., first week, 21, 28, or 35 day lactations), inclusion level of CLA (ranging from 1 to 2.25% CLA product), and (or) average parity of the experimental sows (e.g., primiparous sows only, parities 2-5, 1-3, or 3-4). These studies also had a comparatively low number of animals studied compared to the present study (eight to twelve versus &gt;30 dams per treatment), an important consideration when measuring variables such as pre-weaning mortality rates. Regardless, it seems from this study that liveborn pre-weaning mortality rates are improved by the inclusion of CLA in the sow diet for reasons other than improving colostrum and milk IgG concentration or piglet energy metabolism, as suggested by other authors who fed CLA at higher inclusion levels [
 <xref rid="B4-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. It is more likely that overall colostrum intake was increased in these piglets, and that the concentrations of CLA isomers in colostrum and milk were enhanced [
 <xref rid="B4-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. This may have had impacts on adipocyte function, protein accretion, hepatic lipid metabolism, and immune function [
 <xref rid="B44-animals-09-00062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] that may not have manifested as differences in serum metabolite concentrations of piglets at three days of age in the current study. It may therefore be more beneficial to feed CLA at these inclusion rates from farrowing until weaning rather than from day 107 of gestation, as was the case in the current study. This feeding regime may therefore have less of an impact on fetal development, the farrowing process, and hence the rate of stillbirths, but this requires further investigation.
</p>
