<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The global food market has strict demands regarding food safety and quality. Nowadays, society lives in a continuously changing environment, which sometimes has an important impact on the food industry. Currently, consumers prefer foods with natural food additives because these are correlated with various health benefits. This phenomenon has increased interest in searching for natural compounds with bioactive properties to preserve the quality of different types of foods. Biopolymer films could be a viable solution for some of the problems arising from the use of traditional food plastic packaging materials (e.g., originating from fossil resources, limited ability for bioactive behavior, very low biodegradability). Biopolymers with film forming properties [
 <xref rid="B1-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>] are suitable materials for adding different additives, such as antioxidants [
 <xref rid="B3-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>], antifungal [
 <xref rid="B4-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>] or antimicrobial agents [
 <xref rid="B5-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>], etc. Specifically, several biopolymer materials such as cellulose, starch, alginate, chitosan or pectin have good film forming capacity. Additionally, using natural polymers as coatings can prolong the shelf life of foods by controlling water loss, oxidation, or color changes, but these natural polymers have poor water vapor barriers due to their high hydrophilic nature [
 <xref rid="B6-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Many studies have been conducted on edible bio-based films to demonstrate their capacity to avoid oxygen penetration to the food material or water absorption by the food matrix, loss of flavor, and solute transports [
 <xref rid="B7-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. One of the most promising edible active films is the one based on chitosan because of its particular physicochemical properties. Chitosan is a modified, cationic, non-toxic carbohydrate polymer, obtained through chitin deacetylation and has a complex chemical structure formed by β-(1,4) glucosamine units as its main component (&gt;80%) and N-acetyl glucosamine units (&lt;20%), randomly distributed along the chain. It presents some important advantages over other matrices used as edible films packaging materials such as excellent biocompatibility and biodegradability, non-toxicity, good antimicrobial activity (against bacteria and fungi), oxygen impermeability and film forming properties [
 <xref rid="B8-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Chitosan has been approved as a food additive in some countries from Asia, like Japan (1983), Korea (1995) or China (2007). In Europe, chitosan is still not permitted as food contact material; although the European Food Safety Authority decided that chitosan is sufficiently well characterized [
 <xref rid="B12-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. There is a good opportunity of using chitosan-based materials as films and coatings since new regulation dealing with active and intelligent packaging was issued by the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) [
 <xref rid="B13-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. The antimicrobial activity of chitosan is determined by its cationic nature. Therefore, the positively charged amino groups (NH
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>) can interact with negatively charged microbial cell membranes of microorganisms. However, the antimicrobial effect against Gram-positive or Gram-negative bacteria was found to be questionable in many studies. In some reports it was found that chitosan generally has stronger effects on Gram-positive bacteria (
 <italic class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus megaterium, Bacillus cereus, Staphylococcus aureus</italic>) than on Gram-negative bacteria (
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli, Salmonella typhymurium,</italic> etc.) [
 <xref rid="B14-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Due to the higher hydrophilicity in Gram-negative bacteria, it was demonstrated that this type of bacteria were most sensitive to chitosan [
 <xref rid="B16-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Even though chitosan has good film forming properties, a selective permeability to gasses (CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) and acceptable mechanical properties, the highly permeability to water vapor limits its use in contact with food. Accordingly, different methods have been used to improve the physical properties of biopolymer based films. For example, good results in increasing the hydrophobicity have been obtained by addition of neutral lipids, fatty acids, waxes, or clay [
 <xref rid="B8-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>].
</p>
