<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Hydrophilic (D-glucosamine) and hydrophobic parts (N-acetylated residues) in chitosan molecules offer to it the ability to form emulsion systems; therefore, it is used as emulsifier in the food industry, to uniformly stabilize oil droplets [
 <xref rid="B22-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. The emulsifying property of chitosan can be influenced by chitosan characteristics (e.g., molecular weight, degree of deacetylation) or by the type of oil used and concentration. It was found that chitosan with lower molecular weight was adsorbed more easily on the surface of the oil droplets than chitosan with higher molecular weight [
 <xref rid="B23-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Rodriguez et al. [
 <xref rid="B24-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>] have studied the emulsification of sunflower oil by chitosan solution and found that the chitosan emulsifying capacity was proportional to chitosan concentration. Li and Xia also tried to understand the effects of molecular weight and degree of deacetylation on emulsifying properties of chitosan [
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. The conclusions of their study were that chitosan showed superior emulsifying activity and emulsifying stability within the range of 60.5–86.1% degree of deacetylation and that the chitosan with low molecular weight exhibited better emulsifying activity than that with high molecular weight. In the present study, a medium molecular weight chitosan with a deacetylation degree (DD) of 83.2% was selected. The vegetable oil will also act as a plasticizer for chitosan, increasing the flexibility of the final product, which is important when applying as wrapping on a food product [
 <xref rid="B26-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. However, the mechanical and water vapor barrier properties of polysaccharides-based films are, in general, poor. An alternative to improve these properties is the addition of layered silicates nanoparticles (e.g., sodium montmorillonite). Several studies found improvement in mechanical [
 <xref rid="B26-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>] and barrier properties [
 <xref rid="B27-materials-12-00373" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] of chitosan films containing 1–5 wt% nanoclay. 
</p>
