<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nowadays, rosemary is widely used for its antioxidant activity [
  <a rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref33">33</a>-
  <a rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref38">38</a>], antimicrobial properties [
  <a rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref38">38</a>-
  <a rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref41">41</a>], and bio-preservative in the food industry [
  <a rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref42">42</a>-
  <a rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref44">44</a>]. Recently, in poultry, Borghei-Radand 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref17">17</a>] reported positive effects of diet supplementation using 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> leaves on sperm motility and fertility in aging roosters. However, very few relevant data are present regarding the protective effect of 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> essential oil on avian spermatozoa, particularly when used 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, the chemical composition of 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> essential oil and the effects on rooster sperm motility during 4°C short-term were studied. Phytochemical screening of 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> essential oil (using the GC–MS analysis) allowed the identification of 25 active compounds. According to the results, the major constituents were camphor (18.88%), 1,8-cineole (7.85%), β-thujone (13;66%), chrysanthenone (12.05%), and β-cubenene (7.97%). Similar results were reported by Zermane 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref45">45</a>] when investigating the chemical analysis of Algerian essential oil under optimal conditions. The analyzed essential oil presented some differences when compared to Moroccan 
  <span class="italic">R</span>. 
  <span class="italic">officinalis</span> essential oil. The latter showed high proportions of pinene (37-40%), cineole (58.7-63.7%), and camphor (41.7-53.8%) and 
  <span class="italic">R</span>. 
  <span class="italic">officinali</span>s essential oil from Tunisia is rich in cineole and contained usual monoterpenes [
  <a rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref46">46</a>,
  <a rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref47">47</a>]. Previous studies revealed that 
  <span class="italic">R</span>. 
  <span class="italic">officinalis</span> essential oil composition might be influenced by various factors such as the genotype of the plant, soil type, bioclimatic conditions, or the extraction method [
  <a rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref47">47</a>-
  <a rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref49">49</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study, the beneficial and potentially harmful effects of different concentrations of 
  <span class="italic">R</span>. 
  <span class="italic">officinalis</span> essential oil on rooster semen stored at 4°C for 48 h were investigated. The results demonstrated that semen quality (revealed through progressive motility and gametes velocities) was significantly preserved, especially with the lowest concentrations of the essential oil (87 µg/ml and 8.7 µg/ml). The highest dose (870 µg/ml) showed a complete spermicidal effect evidenced after 24 h of storage. This concentration caused alterations probably similar to those described in bacteria [
  <a rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref50">50</a>-
  <a rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref52">52</a>]. The mechanism described in bacteria was the ability of the essential oil to disrupt and penetrate the lipid structure of the cell wall leading to the destruction of the membranes [
  <a rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref41">41</a>,
  <a rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref42">42</a>]. Chaftar 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref53">53</a>] reported that 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> essential oil was active against several strains of 
  <span class="italic">Legionella pneumophila</span> with a concentration of &lt;0.55 mg/mL. As well, Outaleb 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref54">54</a>] indicated that rosemary essential oil exhibited appreciate antibacterial activities with concentrations ranging only from 4 to 20 µg/ml. Similarly, it is reported that spermicidal activity in numerous animal species is associated with considerable damages on different spermatozoa structures including cell membranes and acrosome integrity [
  <a rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref8">8</a>-
  <a rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref12">12</a>,
  <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">31</a>,
  <a rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref55">55</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the results of this study, the use of small concentrations 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> might be beneficial to rooster spermatozoa under 4°C conditions. In fact, total and progressive motility and kinematics parameters were significantly preserved in 87 and 8.7 µg/ml treatments. After 24 h of storage, the percentage of progressive gamete was 43.25 and 63.08 at 87 and 8.7 µg/ml treatments, respectively, compared to 26.86±2.36% of the control group. Elmi 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">31</a>] reported that the total and progressive motility was significantly altered from the concentration of 0.8 mg/ml of 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> essential oil in swine spermatozoa. This concentration was almost identical to the spermicidal concentration used in our experiment (870 µg/ml). At 0.2 mg/ml, the authors observed motility values similar to those of the control group. Conversely, when used as supplementation diet, 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> essential oil enhanced spermatogenesis and limited lipid peroxidation in quail testicular tissue [
  <a rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref55">55</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several active molecules such as 1,8-cineole, camphor, β-thujene, chrysanthenone, β-cubebene, and camphene, known for their antioxidant activity, were identified in the phytochemical analysis (
  <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table-1</a>). These compounds are probably involved in the observed protective effects. These findings are in accordance with previous reports using rosemary aqueous extract (polyphenols rich fraction) in boar [
  <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">28</a>,
  <a rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref56">56</a>] and buck [
  <a rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref57">57</a>]. The beneficial effects of 
  <span class="italic">R</span>. 
  <span class="italic">officinalis</span> essential oil may be related to the antioxidant activity limiting lipid peroxidation and membrane damages during the chilling storage.
 </p>
</sec>
