<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2-1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethical approval</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiment was carried out in accordance with the guidelines laid down by the Directive 2010/63/EU of the European Parliament for Animal Ethics Committee for the use of poultry birds.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aerial part (stems and leaves) of 
   <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> was harvested during April 2015, in the region of El-Euchre, in the Department of Bordj Bou Arreridj, located in Northeastern Algeria. The harvested plants were dried in the shade for 10 days before extraction.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Extraction of the essential oil was carried out by hydrodistillation process using a Clevenger’s type apparatus (Clevenger, 1928). Distillations were carried out by boiling aerial plant parts for 3 h, and the essential oil was kept in air-tight sealed vials and stored at 4°C until further use.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phytochemical identification</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The identification of the active compounds of the 
   <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> essential oil was carried out by Agilent 2890 HP-type gas chromatography coupled to mass spectrometry (Model 6890) (GC/MS), equipped with a fused silica HP-5MS capillary column (Length: 30 m, internal diameter: 0.25 mm, and film thickness 0.25 μm). The temperature of the injector was maintained at 250°C. The carrier gas was helium (0.5 ml/min) with an injection volume of 0.2 μl, and the division ratio was adjusted to 1:20. The oven temperature was programmed from 60 (8 min) to 280°C at 2°C/min and then held isothermally at 280°C for 10 min. Analysis mode: Digitized, interface temperature: 280°C, ionization type: Electronic, filament strength: 70 eV, mass analyzer type: Quadrupole, source temperature: 230°C, and empty: 65m torr.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Animals</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All experiments were conducted in accordance with the legislation governing the ethical treatment of animals. 10 of 45-week-old Hubbard commercial broiler reproductive cocks were used during the experiment. The animals were housed in conventional individual cages under 14 h of daily illumination and fed with a standard commercial food at the rate of 155 g/day/animal.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sperm collection</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The roosters were subjected to biweekly semen collections during 3 weeks by dorso-abdominal massage as described by Burros and Quinn [
   <a rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref32">32</a>] and individual ejaculates were gently mixed and pooled. To minimize animal stress, the collection was carried out by the same operator and under the same conditions. Necessary precautions were taken during collection to avoid contamination by cloaca fluids. Sperm concentration was calculated using a computer-assisted sperm analyzer (CASA) (Sperm class analyzer, SCA Microptic, S.L., Version 3.2.0, Barcelona, Spain).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sperm treatment</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pooled sperm was diluted at 1/2 ratio at room temperature (18-22°C) in Tris extender (3.028 g of hydroxymethylaminomethane, 1.25 g of fructose, 1.7 g of citric acid, 800 Ul/ml of penicillin G sodium, and 1 mg/ml of streptomycin sulfate in 100 ml of distilled water) and then split into four equal aliquots. Each aliquot was diluted with Tris extender supplemented with 870, 87, or 8.7 µg/ml of 
   <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> essential oil, identified as treatments R, R5, and R10, respectively (26). Tris-based extender without any supplementation was considered as a control group. All samples were then stored at 4°C and analyzed at 0, 6, 24, and 48 h. The experimentation was repeated 6 times (n=6).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sperm motility analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Various sperm motility parameters were analyzed using a CASA (Sperm class analyzer, SCA Microptic, S.L., Version 3.2.0, Barcelona, Spain). The measured parameters were: Percentage of motile spermatozoa (Mob T %), percentage of progressive spermatozoa (Prog T %), curvilinear velocity (VCL μm/s), straight line velocity (VSL μm/s), average path velocity (VAP μm/s), amplitude of the lateral head displacement (ALH μm), and frequency to which the sperm head crosses the mean trajectory (beat-cross frequency [BCF]/Hertz).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SAS software (SAS Institute, 2001) was used for all statistical analyses. The data were checked for normal distribution with a Shapiro–Wilk test. Treatment and time effect on each motility parameters (MobT, ProgT, VCL, VSL, VAP, ALH, and BCF) were assessed by the following general linear model:</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Y
   <sub>ijkl</sub>=μ+A
   <sub>i</sub>+B
   <sub>j</sub>+(AB)
   <sub>ij</sub>+e
   <sub>ijk</sub>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Y=The studied motility parameters measured on the sperm;</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">μ=Mean;</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A
   <sub>i</sub>=Fixed effect of the medium (i=1-4: R, R5, R10, and Tris);
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B
   <sub>j</sub>=Fixed effect of time (j=1-4: 0, 6, 24, and 48 h);
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(AB)
   <sub>ij</sub>=Interaction between time and medium;
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">e
   <sub>ijk</sub>=The residual effect.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Least-squares means and standard errors (SE) were calculated for motility parameters measurements.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Differences were considered statistically significant at p&lt;0.05.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
