<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Classical molecular biological methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The majority (&gt;99%) of bacterioplankton in marine environments remains largely recalcitrant to cultivation. Applications of molecular biological methods such as 16S rRNA clone library, terminal restriction fragment length polymorphism (T-RFLP), denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis (DGGE), temperature gradient gel electrophoresis (TGGE), fluorescence 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span> hybridization (FISH), and real-time quantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) are useful techniques in investigating the composition and potential functions of indigenous bacterial communities in a specific environment.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">16S rRNA gene clone library</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 16S rRNA gene is well-known as a marker gene for the reconstruction of prokaryotic (bacterial and archaeal) phylogenies and for the investigation of microbial diversity (Woese and Fox, 
   <a rid="B108" ref-type="bibr" href="#B108">1977</a>; Klindworth et al., 
   <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">2013</a>). The construction of clone libraries based on 16S rRNA genes has extensively been used to investigate bacterial communities until the advent of next generation sequencing (NGS). 16S rRNA gene-based clone library analysis provides a useful, though somewhat limited, tool for capturing the diversity and composition of bacterial communities (Kumar et al., 
   <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">2007</a>; Schäfer et al., 
   <a rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" href="#B90">2010</a>). In the literature on the DWH oil spill, 16S rRNA gene-based clone library analysis was one of the most popular techniques for investigating microbial communities. Several studies using 16S rRNA gene clone libraries revealed the microbial community responses to the contamination caused by the deep-sea plumes of hydrocarbons. These communities exhibited significant differences in different habitats (plume and non-plume water, surface and deep-sea water, sediments, and beach sands; see Table 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">1</a>) and presented dramatic changes over the duration of the spill (Hazen et al., 
   <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">2010</a>; Valentine et al., 
   <a rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" href="#B102">2010</a>; Kessler et al., 
   <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">2011</a>; Redmond and Valentine, 
   <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">2011</a>; Yang et al., 
   <a rid="B110" ref-type="bibr" href="#B110">2016</a>). For instance, Hazen et al. (
   <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">2010</a>) identified members of the order 
   <span class="italic">Oceanospirillales</span> in the γ
   <span class="italic">-Proteobacteria</span> class as dominant in deep-sea plumes. 
   <span class="italic">Oceanospirillales</span> were not detected in most of the plume samples in June, while 
   <span class="italic">Cycloclasticus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Colwellia</span> were dominant (more than 95% of the sequences). This indicates that the DWH 
   <span class="italic">Oceanospirillales</span> bloomed initially, followed by 
   <span class="italic">Colwellia</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Cycloclasticus</span> (Redmond and Valentine, 
   <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">2011</a>; Yang et al., 
   <a rid="B110" ref-type="bibr" href="#B110">2016</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Construction and analysis of 16S rRNA gene clone libraries provided useful information on the structures and responses of bacterial communities during the first stage after the spill occurred. However, the 16S rRNA gene clone library technique became less prevalent after NGS was used to investigate microbial communities.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gene fingerprinting techniques</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis (DGGE) and temperature gradient gel electrophoresis (TGGE) are two commonly used gene fingerprinting techniques that separate different DNA/RNA in the same sample via chemical or temperature gradients. Muyzer et al. (
   <a rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" href="#B77">1993</a>) first introduced DGGE into the field of microbial ecology to describe the composition of bacterial communities. Different bands on the gel indicate different bacterial phylotypes and band intensity shows the relative abundance of certain bacterial taxa. By cutting DGGE/TGGE strips, building clone libraries, and sequencing, the information related to a band can be further interpreted. Although the information provided by these two techniques are thought to be insufficient (as there are always dozens of bands for one sample) and NGS can generate more data, DGGE/TGGE techniques are still widely used to study microbial communities as they can intuitively display the differences between different samples via gel profiles within short time periods (1–2 d for an experimental cycle).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After the DWH oil spills, DGGE provided some of the first information on naturally occurring microbial communities in the sediment from shorelines along the northern coast of the Gulf of Mexico (Lisle, 
   <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">2011</a>). Some active bacterial species exhibited increases in biomass during the degradation process. Bacosa et al. (
   <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">2015a</a>) used 16S rRNA gene-based DGGE to detect microbial community dynamics and composition with the stressor of Light Louisiana Sweet (LLS) crude oil under dark and natural light conditions. The results demonstrated that different bacterial groups were involved in the degradation of n-alkane under the dark and light conditions.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Like DGGE/TGGE, TRFLP, or sometimes T-RLP is another gene fingerprinting technique. By generating a fingerprint for pattern comparison and then complementing the data with a clone library, resolving peaks using a database, and performing multivariate analysis, TRFLP can reveal the differences in unknown microbial communities in various environmental samples (Liu et al., 
   <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">1997</a>). T-RFLP was applied to investigate the composition and succession of bacterial communities after the oil spill and successfully revealed the relatively higher contribution of the bacterial group 
   <span class="italic">Flavobacteria</span>, which is a secondary consumer of methane, oil, or cellular decay products (Redmond and Valentine, 
   <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">2011</a>). Profiles generated by TRFLP indicated that up to 56% of the total bacteria in plume samples collected in September 2010 were affiliated with 
   <span class="italic">Flavobacteria</span>, whereas this number was only 10–30% when 16S rRNA gene-based clone library techniques were applied (Redmond and Valentine, 
   <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">2011</a>). In a recent study, the TRFLP analysis for community composition of ammonia oxidizers in salt marshes after the DWH oil spill revealed that exposure to oil, even 2 years post-spill, could contribute to subtle changes in population dynamics of bacterial communities (Bernhard et al., 
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">2016</a>). Although T-RFLP could provide more authentic data compared to clone libraries, it could still underestimate community diversity, especially when complex and large amounts of data were applied. In the abovementioned study (Redmond and Valentine, 
   <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">2011</a>), some terminal restriction fragments could be assigned to multiple groups. Due to the significant overlaps between the 
   <span class="italic">methanotrophs, methylotrophs</span>, and some other γ-
   <span class="italic">proteobacteria</span>, it was not possible to distinguish the δ-
   <span class="italic">proteobacteria, Actinobacteria</span>, and SAR406 clades from each other. Nevertheless, some groups, such as 
   <span class="italic">Flavobacteria</span>, α-
   <span class="italic">proteobacteria</span>, and γ-
   <span class="italic">proteobacteria</span> could be readily differentiated.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other classic molecular methods</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the aforementioned molecular methods, other molecular tools were also used to study indigenous microbial communities, such as FISH and real-time quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR). The FISH method has been widely used to investigate composition of bacterial communities in recent years. It can provide fluorescent images indicating the existence and relative abundance of target genes combing with special fluorescent probes. 16S rRNA genes or functional genes can be detected by this approach without PCR amplification (DeLong et al., 
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">1989</a>; Amann and Fuchs, 
   <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2008</a>). Catalyzed reporter deposition in combination with FISH (CARD–FISH) were performed to detect the microbial aggregate formations in a microcosm study using deep plume seawater with addition of nutrients (Kleindienst et al., 
   <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">2015</a>). The results revealed that the potential dispersant-degrader, 
   <span class="italic">Colwellia</span> was one of the dominant bacterial phylotypes in microaggregate which indicated that this bacterial group could play an important role in marine oil snow formation. By developing two new 16S rRNA-targeted oligonucleotide probes (Mrb-0625-aandMrb-0625-b) for the FISH assay, McKay et al. (
   <a rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73">2016</a>) successfully monitored the rapid increase of the oil-degrading bacterium, 
   <span class="italic">Marinobacter</span>, after amending n-hexadecane in an enrichment experiment with a deep-sea oil plume water sample. Compared to FISH, qPCR can quantify targeted functional bacterial phyla more accurately. It provides relatively accurate data via real-time monitoring of the fluorescent signals generated by fluorescent probes (Heo et al., 
   <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">2010</a>; Yuan et al., 
   <a rid="B112" ref-type="bibr" href="#B112">2010</a>). Because probes and primes are necessary for both FISH and RT-qPCR detection, only bacterial phylotypes with probes/primers can be detected and quantified, whereas some unknown groups without specific probes/primers are difficult to be detected using these methods.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
