<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How to illustrate the cooperation of different bacteria?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A global perspective calls for a deep understanding of the composition and activity of the bacterial communities in a relevant environmental context (Faust and Raes, 
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">2012</a>). We should not only focus on functional bacterial communities that are directly degrading pollutants, but also on the other biological components involved in the biodegradation or bioremediation processes via chemical and biological interactions (Head et al., 
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">2006</a>). For instance, microorganisms without oil-degrading capability could also be involved in the biodegradation process by consuming the metabolites released by oil-degrading bacteria. Some non-oil-degrading microorganisms can either provide limiting nutrients or produce surfactant or emulsification of oil and water for the primary oil degraders (Head et al., 
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">2006</a>). Reconstructing the microbial network might be an efficient method for investigating the complicated interactions among indigenous bacteria. Zhou et al. (
  <a rid="B115" ref-type="bibr" href="#B115">2010</a>; 
  <a rid="B116" ref-type="bibr" href="#B116">2011</a>) developed a random matrix theory (RMT)-based conceptual framework to reconstruct functional molecular ecological networks based on metagenomics and genechip data. This approach was applied to evaluate the responses of bacterial communities under long-term, free-air CO
  <sub>2</sub> enrichment (Zhou et al., 
  <a rid="B115" ref-type="bibr" href="#B115">2010</a>, 
  <a rid="B116" ref-type="bibr" href="#B116">2011</a>). The reconstructed networks revealed dramatic changes in the interactions among different phylogenetic groups/populations. The changes in network structure were significantly correlated with nutrient contents. In our previous study, we investigated the responses and activities of bacterial communities under stresses from hydrocarbons with different structures by reconstructing microbial networks and predicting the individual roles of functional bacteria in the key nodes of the networks. The interactions of different bacteria in the networks helped microbes co-acclimate to the changing environment and initiate biodegradation (Wang et al., 
  <a rid="B104" ref-type="bibr" href="#B104">2016</a>). In all, the microbial networks can provide additional information besides the composition of bacterial communities. Most importantly, the key functional bacterial phyla, including the degrading conductor and tightly associated non-degrading bacteria, could be identified (key nodes in the network). Based on this information, the bacterial communities in polluted sites can be manipulated for enhancing the abundances of beneficial species and functions for bioremediation (Faust and Raes, 
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">2012</a>). The key strategies for applications based on network reconstruction and analysis is engineering a whole community instead of a single species (Curtis et al., 
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">2003</a>; Dunham, 
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">2007</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
