<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Metatranscriptomics</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Metagenomics can provide useful information on the genomic potential of a microbial community, whereas metatranscriptomics can be used to investigate genes that are transcribed under certain environmental conditions. It can assess microbial gene expression in a special environment or under unusual conditions via pyrosequencing of total RNA directly extracted from natural microbial assemblages (Shi et al., 
  <a rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" href="#B94">2009</a>; Warnecke and Hess, 
  <a rid="B106" ref-type="bibr" href="#B106">2009</a>). Metatranscriptomic data takes into account the dynamic state of RNA levels and thereby overcomes the constraint of metagenomics which relies on DNA for the reconstruction of metabolic models to improve prediction accuracy. Thus, metatranscriptomic analysis could provide supporting data or more convincing data in comparison to metagenomic analysis. In addition to metagenomic analysis, Mason et al. (
  <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">2012</a>) conducted metatranscriptomic analysis to determine the expressed functional genes in the active microbial community in the oil plume. Metatranscriptomic data revealed more pronounced differences in the relative abundance of active genes that have the potential for biodegradation compared to DNA-based analysis. These active genes were mostly associated with aliphatic hydrocarbon degradation but not PAH degradation, which is consistent with metagenomic analysis. In a study that considered the microbial communities of methane degradation (Lesniewski et al., 
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">2012</a>), data generated from metatranscriptomics revealed that the bacterial communities of both the plume and background samples were dominated by the same groups of methanotrophs and chemolithoautotrophs despite marked increases in plume total RNA concentrations (3–4 times) and microbial-mediated manganese oxidation rates (15–125 times background levels).
 </p>
</sec>
