<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other classic molecular methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the aforementioned molecular methods, other molecular tools were also used to study indigenous microbial communities, such as FISH and real-time quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR). The FISH method has been widely used to investigate composition of bacterial communities in recent years. It can provide fluorescent images indicating the existence and relative abundance of target genes combing with special fluorescent probes. 16S rRNA genes or functional genes can be detected by this approach without PCR amplification (DeLong et al., 
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">1989</a>; Amann and Fuchs, 
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2008</a>). Catalyzed reporter deposition in combination with FISH (CARD–FISH) were performed to detect the microbial aggregate formations in a microcosm study using deep plume seawater with addition of nutrients (Kleindienst et al., 
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">2015</a>). The results revealed that the potential dispersant-degrader, 
  <span class="italic">Colwellia</span> was one of the dominant bacterial phylotypes in microaggregate which indicated that this bacterial group could play an important role in marine oil snow formation. By developing two new 16S rRNA-targeted oligonucleotide probes (Mrb-0625-aandMrb-0625-b) for the FISH assay, McKay et al. (
  <a rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73">2016</a>) successfully monitored the rapid increase of the oil-degrading bacterium, 
  <span class="italic">Marinobacter</span>, after amending n-hexadecane in an enrichment experiment with a deep-sea oil plume water sample. Compared to FISH, qPCR can quantify targeted functional bacterial phyla more accurately. It provides relatively accurate data via real-time monitoring of the fluorescent signals generated by fluorescent probes (Heo et al., 
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">2010</a>; Yuan et al., 
  <a rid="B112" ref-type="bibr" href="#B112">2010</a>). Because probes and primes are necessary for both FISH and RT-qPCR detection, only bacterial phylotypes with probes/primers can be detected and quantified, whereas some unknown groups without specific probes/primers are difficult to be detected using these methods.
 </p>
</sec>
