<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Single-cell sequencing</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Single-cell sequencing is a newly developed technique to obtain genomes of individual microorganisms. This technique was first reported by Raghunathan et al. (
  <a rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" href="#B82">2005</a>) and was selected as the method of the year in 2013 by “Nature Publishing Group.” Single cells can be first isolated from various environments (soil, seawater, marine sediments, and human gastrointestinal tracts) by micro manipulation, flow cytometry or microfluidics. The whole genomes of selected single cells are then amplified by multiple displacement amplification (MDA) to generate sufficient amounts of genetic material for sequencing. Genomes can be sequenced by NGS and analyzed by new methods in bioinformatics (SPAdes) (Woyke et al., 
  <a rid="B109" ref-type="bibr" href="#B109">2009</a>). By generating genomic information on previously inaccessible species from different environments, the structure of microbial communities and the physiology of single cells can be deeply investigated. Mason et al. (
  <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">2012</a>) successfully obtained two single-cell genomes of the genus 
  <span class="italic">Oceanospirillales</span>, which have been shown to be dominant phylotypes after the DWH oil spill (Hazen et al., 
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">2010</a>; Redmond and Valentine, 
  <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">2011</a>). Single-cell sequencing revealed that both cells possessed genes encoding for n-alkane and cycloalkane degradation. Furthermore, the genomic information helped in the reconstruction of the near-complete pathway for cyclohexane oxidation in the two single cells. This provided powerful evidence proving that bacteria in the order 
  <span class="italic">Oceanospirillales</span> were responsible for the biodegradation of aliphatic hydrocarbons in the deep sea (Mason et al., 
  <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">2012</a>). Thus, with the support of metagenomic sequencing data, single-cell sequencing analysis (e.g., the genomic properties of 
  <span class="italic">Colwellia</span>) could extend our understanding of the successional changes of the dominant microbial players (Mason et al., 
  <a rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69">2014a</a>) and their specific metabolic activities in biochemical cycle (Musat et al., 
  <a rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" href="#B76">2012</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
