<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A mixture of different EOs was reported to have inhibitory effects on CNS. The central nervous system inhibitory effects of the EO from 
 <italic class="italic">SuHeXiang Wan</italic> (Storax pill) on fragrance inhalation (aromatherapy) were evaluated. 
 <italic class="italic">SuHeXiang Wan</italic> consists of 15 crude herbs, among them 
 <italic class="italic">Liquidambar orientalis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Saussurea lappa</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria agallocha</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Santalum album</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Boswellia carterii</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Eugenia caryophyllata</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Styrax benzoin</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Dryobalanops aromatica</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Cyperus rotundus</italic>. All of them have the term “Xiang” (fragrance) in their Chinese plant names. The fragrance inhalation of the EO from 
 <italic class="italic">SuHeXiang Wan</italic> progressively prolonged the pentobarbital-induced sleeping time and inhibited brain lipid peroxidation to which the anticonvulsive action is attributed [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. The studies confirm that the inhibitory effects of the EO of 
 <italic class="italic">SuHeXiang Wan</italic> on the CNS were mediated by the GABAergic system [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Similarly, the perfume, which is a mixture of different EOs, affects the frame of the human mind. The effects of the perfume and phytoncid on GABA
 <sub class="sub">A</sub> receptors expressed in 
 <italic class="italic">Xenopus</italic> oocytes were studied [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. The chemical constituents in the perfume such as hinokitiol, pinene, eugenol, citronellol, and citronellal potentiated the GABA
 <sub class="sub">A</sub> receptor expressed in 
 <italic class="italic">Xenopus</italic> oocytes. These results suggest that the GABAergic system is a common target of EOs.
</p>
