<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Cymbopogon citratus</italic> (DC) Stapf., commonly known as lemongrass, and 
 <italic class="italic">Cymbopogon winterianus</italic> Jowitt, are widely used in traditional medicine as an infusion or decoction, sedative, and analgesic for treating nervous disturbances [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. The anticonvulsant activities of the EOs from 
 <italic class="italic">C. winterianus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. citratus</italic> were evaluated in mice [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. The results showed that both EOs were more active on the pentylenetetrazol-induced convulsion model, and 
 <italic class="italic">C. citratus</italic> was even more efficient in increasing latency to the first convulsion and latency to death. The mechanism of action of the EOs (
 <italic class="italic">C. citratus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. winterianus</italic>.) for the anticonvulsant effect was, at least in part, dependent upon GABAergic neurotransmission [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. Costa et al. [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] investigated the anxiolytic-like activity of 
 <italic class="italic">C. citratus</italic> EO in a light/dark box and marble-burying test and the antidepressant activity was investigated in forced-swimming test model in mice. The results demonstrated that acute treatment with the EO from 
 <italic class="italic">C. citratus</italic> was effective against generalized anxiety disorder and epilepsy in experimental procedures in mice [
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. Studies on the underlying mechanism showed that the anxiolytic-like effect of its EO was mediated by the GABA
 <sub class="sub">A</sub> receptor complex [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. The main EO compounds were identified as monoterpene citral (71.29%), a mixture of the stereoisomers geranial and neral, or β-myrcene (16.5%) [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>].
</p>
