<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Melissa officinalis</italic> is known to have sedative, cognitive-enhancing, and relevant physiological actions. Abuhamdah et al. [
 <xref rid="B38-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>] reported that EO from 
 <italic class="italic">M. officinalis</italic> reversibly inhibited GABA-induced currents in a concentration-dependent manner whereas no inhibition of NMDA- or AMPA-induced currents was noted. 
 <italic class="italic">Lippia alba</italic> (Mill.) N.E. Brown is known as “false-melissa” in Brazil. This plant has been commonly used for its sedative properties, which also have been demonstrated in some rodent studies [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. Three main chemotypes obtained from 
 <italic class="italic">L. alba</italic> EO were reported and classified according to their major constituent as citral, carvone, and linalool [
 <xref rid="B56-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. Recently, the anesthetic effect of 
 <italic class="italic">L. alba</italic> EO was demonstrated in silver catfish and the GABAergic system was involved in this effect [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Thus, the EO of 
 <italic class="italic">L. alba</italic> is considered to be a novel natural sedative and anesthetic agent that can be potentially used in aquaculture practices due to its ability to reduce stress in fish with a consequent reduction of economic losses in fish culture [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Meanwhile, repeated treatment with an EO from 
 <italic class="italic">L. alba</italic> displayed anxiolytic effects in the elevated T-maze mouse model [
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>].
</p>
