<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Mortensen et al. compared the acute effect of protein type on postprandial lipemia by providing 12 patients with T2D a test meal containing 100 g butter and 45 g carbohydrates in combination with 45 g casein, whey, cod, or gluten [
 <xref rid="B111-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>]. Compared to other sources of proteins, whey led to a decrease in the AUC of postprandial TG concentration after 360 min (−27% to −31%), in both plasma and CM-rich fraction, suggesting a concomitant lower production of CM, as illustrated by a lower retinyl palmitate concentration in the CM-rich fraction and a decrease in FFA secretion. No differences in insulin, glucagon and incretin concentrations or gastric emptying were observed. Using the same setting in 11 obese non-diabetic patients, the same group observed a significant lowering effect of whey proteins on postprandial plasma TG, notably in the CM-rich fraction, with an increase in insulin and glucagon secretion compared to cod and gluten but not compared to casein [
 <xref rid="B112-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>]. In a group of 20 overweight or obese postmenopausal women, the addition of 45 g whey to a breakfast meal significantly decreased postprandial TG concentrations as well as the exposure to smaller TG-enriched CM particles, as reflected by a decrease in the AUC of the TG:apoB-48 ratio, compared to the addition of 45 g glucose or casein to the same meal (−21% and −27%, respectively) [
 <xref rid="B113-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>]. In 11 obese non-diabetic subjects, Homer-Jenssen et al. did not observe any difference between the addition of 45 g of four whey fractions (alpha-lactalbumin, whey isolate, caseino-glycomacro-peptide and whey hydrolysate) to a high-fat meal on postprandial TG, insulin, glucagon or incretin concentrations although whey hydrolysate led to a smaller decrease in postprandial FFA production compared to the other proteins [
 <xref rid="B114-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>]. No difference in postprandial TG concentration was observed in a similar setting in 12 T2D subjects [
 <xref rid="B115-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>].
</p>
