<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The response of plants to oil pollution can manifest itself at various levels (physiological, biochemical, and molecular). Detailed information about the effect of oil contamination on photosynthetic activity is scarce. For example, it has recently been reported that crude oil pollution reduces overall photosynthetic activity and chlorophyll contents in plants [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Notable symptoms observed in plants growing on oil-polluted soil also include a decrease in the activity of starch metabolizing enzymes [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and a decrease in content of total carbohydrates, total proteins, and total amino acids [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The most dangerous disorder, resulted from the effect of pollutants, including crude oil and petroleum hydrocarbons, on plants, is oxidative stress, which leads to the formation of many reactive oxygen species (ROSs) with high oxidizing capacity in cells (superoxide radical (O
 <sub>2</sub>
 <sup>•−</sup>), H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, hydroxyl radical (
 <sup>•</sup>OH), etc.). In one respect, the ROSs destroy cell-membrane complexes, disrupt transport processes and intracellular reactions, and thereby inhibit growth activity [
 <xref rid="B13-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Contrastingly, plants use ROS as a second messenger in many signal transduction cascades, and therefore ROS accumulation is essential to plant development and defense [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-10-00157" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. For these reasons, the plant antioxidative defense network plays a crucial role in controlling the lifetime of the ROS signals and preventing uncontrolled oxidation.
</p>
