<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Fig. 4</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">(A) Schematic of post-emulsion modification strategy with surfactants 
   <bold class="bold">16</bold> and 
   <bold class="bold">17</bold>. (B) Dynamic light scattering data of emulsions formed from 
   <bold class="bold">8</bold>, 
   <bold class="bold">16</bold>, 
   <bold class="bold">17</bold>. Emulsions were prepared with 10 vol% 7 : 3 PFD/PFTPA and 2.8 wt% surfactant in PBS, diluted 1 : 100 in MilliQ water and analyzed 
   <italic class="italic">via</italic> DLS. (C) CuAAC chemistry is employed for emulsion surface functionalization with azidorhodamine dye 
   <bold class="bold">22</bold> (NaAsc = sodium ascorbate). (D) Emulsions formed from 
   <bold class="bold">8</bold> and 
   <bold class="bold">17</bold> were subjected to the CuAAC chemistry conditions in (C). After 12 h, the reaction mixtures were diluted 1 : 100 in MilliQ water and their absorbance was measured (pre-dialysis, solid lines; red = 
   <bold class="bold">17</bold>, blue = 
   <bold class="bold">8</bold>). The remaining solution was dialyzed in water for 24 h with 3 water changes, at which point the emulsion solution was removed and analyzed by UV/Vis at the approximate concentration as the previous measurements (post-dialysis, dotted lines; red = 
   <bold class="bold">17</bold>, blue = 
   <bold class="bold">8</bold>). All the data were normalized to emulsion 
   <bold class="bold">8</bold> pre-dialysis. See Fig. S17
   <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" class="xref">†</xref> for size analysis before and after reaction and dialysis. (E) Thiol–ene chemistry allows for modulation of zeta potential with thiols methyl mercaptoacetate (
   <bold class="bold">23</bold>), mercaptoacetic acid (
   <bold class="bold">18</bold>), and 2-dimethylaminoethanethiol (
   <bold class="bold">24</bold>). (F) Zeta potential of the emulsions at pH 7.4 before (
   <bold class="bold">16</bold>) and after thiol–ene modification following the conditions in (E). Black = emulsions stabilized by 
   <bold class="bold">16</bold>; yellow = emulsions stabilized by 
   <bold class="bold">16</bold> and modified by 
   <bold class="bold">23</bold>; red = emulsions stabilized by 
   <bold class="bold">16</bold> and modified by 
   <bold class="bold">18</bold>; blue = emulsions stabilized by 
   <bold class="bold">16</bold> and modified by 
   <bold class="bold">24</bold>. The surface charge was analyzed by diluting the reaction mixtures 1 : 100 in MilliQ H
   <sub class="sub">2</sub>O and measuring the zeta potential. Data is representative of five replicate measurements. Error bars represent the standard deviation of five measurements. See Fig. S21
   <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" class="xref">†</xref> for raw zeta potential traces.
  </title>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="c8sc05735d-f4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
