<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig6" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Fig. 6</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">(A) Schematic of cellular uptake study of differentially charged nanoemulsions. Nanoemulsions were fluorescently labeled 
   <italic class="italic">via</italic> the addition of a fluorous-tagged rhodamine. (B) Fluorous rhodamine 
   <bold class="bold">25</bold>. (C/D) Flow cytometry of (C) non-macrophage (A375) and (D) macrophage (RAW) cell lines incubated with PFC nanoemulsions. PFC nanoemulsions with modified surface charges were prepared 
   <italic class="italic">via</italic> the thiol–ene modification of emulsions formed from 
   <bold class="bold">16</bold> as described in 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" class="xref">Fig. 4E and F</xref>. Excess reagents were removed 
   <italic class="italic">via</italic> thrice centrifugation and resuspension in MilliQ H
   <sub class="sub">2</sub>O. After the final wash, the emulsions were resuspended in PBS and 
   <bold class="bold">25</bold> in acetone was added. The emulsions were rocked for 1 min then introduced to A375 or RAW cells for 3 hours. The cells were thrice washed with excess FACS buffer (PBS plus 1% FBS) to remove non-uptaken emulsions, lifted with trypsin and transferred to a V-bottom plate. The cells were further washed 
   <italic class="italic">via</italic> centrifugation (×3, FACS buffer) and analyzed by flow cytometry. Cells were gated (see Fig. S30 and S31
   <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" class="xref">†</xref>) and FL2 mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) was plotted. Error bars represent the standard deviation of three replicate samples. Green = control cells; black = emulsions stabilized by 
   <bold class="bold">16</bold>; yellow = emulsions stabilized by 
   <bold class="bold">16</bold> and modified by 
   <bold class="bold">23</bold>; red = emulsions stabilized by 
   <bold class="bold">16</bold> and modified by 
   <bold class="bold">18</bold>; blue = emulsions stabilized by 
   <bold class="bold">16</bold> and modified by 
   <bold class="bold">24</bold>; grey = emulsions stabilized by 
   <bold class="bold">1</bold>. (E/F) Confocal microscopy of (E) A375 cells and (F) RAW cells. The procedure was identical to (C/D) except for a one-hour incubation followed by five initial washes (3× media, 2× FACS buffer). After the final wash, the cells were transferred to an FBS-treated microscope slide, incubated for 1 h in media, stained with Hoescht dye and LysoTracker Green and imaged 
   <italic class="italic">via</italic> confocal microscopy. These cells were analyzed for rhodamine (Ex 532 nm, false color red) and LysoTracker Green (Ex 488 nm, false color green), and Hoescht dye (Ex 405 nm, false color blue). Scale bar indicates 10 μm. Images are representative of two independent experiments. See Fig. S32 and S33
   <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1" class="xref">†</xref> for single channel images and DIC.
  </title>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="c8sc05735d-f6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
