<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par44">The Panax (“all healing”) has self-confidence traditionally to heal all ill health problems of the human body [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR197">197</xref>]. Roots of Panaxmainly used in folk medicine for amplevariety of pharmacological and therapeutic purposes for centuries either in solid form or in liquid. Till date, some of 40 ginsenosides have been discovered most active and useful of them are Rb1, Rg1, Rg3, Rh1, Re, and Rd [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR180">180</xref>]. This medicinal plant has many biological benefits as hypotensive, antioxidation, antidiabetic, vasorelaxation, anti-carcinogenic, anti-allergic, anti-inflammatory, antidiabetic, anticancer, etc.[
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR197">197</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR198">198</xref>]. Amazingly, Kim reported that 
 <italic>ginseng</italic> can “normalize” hypertensive and hypotensive conditions. It also acts as an anti-carcinogenic and antidiabetic agent [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR180">180</xref>]. This is well reported in the literature that 
 <italic>ginseng</italic> has a reducing effect on blood pressure but according to Mucalo
 <italic>et al.</italic> it can also increase blood pressure to regularize hypotensive conditions rheostatically probably by alteration of vascular character, adjustingANS, or adapting baroreflex of arteries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR199">199</xref>]. Rhee et al
 <italic>.</italic> found that ginsenoside of 
 <italic>P. ginseng</italic> can cause a major decreasing effectin SBP and DBP in patients having gentle hypertension as well as healthy subjects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR200">200</xref>]. Ginsenoside Rg3 produces an increasing effect onexpression of eNOS leads to an increase in the production of NO followed by vasorelaxation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR201">201</xref>]. Also, 
 <italic>ginseng</italic> also inhibits adrenal catecholamines emission, which has an additional effect on antihypertensive character [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR180">180</xref>].
 <graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="13659_2020_281_Figq_HTML" id="MO23" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</p>
