<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our inventories show that the invasive 
 <italic>P. serotina</italic> in the Netherlands harbours a surprisingly rich community of herbivores. Although the densities were lower than on native 
 <italic>P. padus</italic>, the species diversity was greater. Also, contrary to expectations, the 
 <italic>P. serotina</italic> herbivore community contained similar proportions of specialists versus generalists as the one on 
 <italic>P. padus</italic>. The only species strikingly absent from 
 <italic>P. serotina</italic> were two abundant 
 <italic>P. padus</italic> monophages, 
 <italic>Y. evonymellus</italic> and 
 <italic>R. padi</italic>. Consistent with 
 <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Leather (1985)</xref>, both species were responsible for more than two thirds of all insects found feeding on 
 <italic>P. padus</italic>, whereas they occurred on 
 <italic>P. serotina</italic> only in small numbers (we found only a single 
 <italic>Y. evonymellus</italic> caterpillar and a single 
 <italic>R. padi</italic> colony on 
 <italic>P. serotina</italic>). Nonetheless, laboratory data (
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Kooi, Van de Water &amp; Herrebout, 1991</xref>) and field data from Poland (
 <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Karolewski et al., 2014</xref>) suggest that at least 
 <italic>Y. evonymellus</italic> has the potential to feed on 
 <italic>P. serotina</italic>. 
 <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Karolewski et al. (2014)</xref> state that in Poland, the latter species has progressed from avoiding 
 <italic>P. serotina</italic> altogether to feeding and developing on it massively over the past decade. The near-absence from 
 <italic>P. serotina</italic> of this herbivore in our study area suggests that a similar colonization event may not yet have taken place, but this may change in the near future, possibly aided by long-distance gene flow from the populations in Poland. Another striking difference between both hosts is the relatively large numbers of non-Rosaceae specialists on 
 <italic>P. serotina</italic>. While some of these may be accidental “tourists”, the high number of individuals for some of these species (e.g., the 
 <italic>Quercus</italic>-specialist 
 <italic>Harpocera thoracica</italic>) is noteworthy.
</p>
