<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Acacia arabica</italic> (
 <italic>A. arabica</italic>) belongs to the family of 
 <italic>Fabaceae</italic> and is widely distributed in Asian regions [
 <xref rid="B167-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>]. It is basically used for the treatment of various diseases, such as Newcastle disease, vaccinia virus, bursal disease virus, H9N2 influenza disease, skin diseases, and possesses many biological properties including antimicrobial, anti-diabetic, and antioxidant effects. The mechanism of action of 
 <italic>A. arabica</italic> is known. It specifically inhibits the stage of viral intracellular multiplication [
 <xref rid="B149-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>,
 <xref rid="B167-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>,
 <xref rid="B168-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>,
 <xref rid="B169-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>]. Furthermore, 
 <italic>A. arabica</italic> contains several bioactive components extracted from the leaves of the plant which are responsible for its bioactivity, such as flavonoids, methyl 3,4,5 tri hydroxyl benzoate, 
 <italic>p</italic>-coumaroyl glucoside, 
 <italic>p</italic>-coumaroylquinic acid, ferulic acid, isoferulic acid, epicatechin-3-gallate, ascorbic acid, quercetin 3-O-(4′-O-acetyl)-rhamnopyranoside, oleic acid, myristic acid, palmitic acid and steroidal sapogenin aglycone [
 <xref rid="B166-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>,
 <xref rid="B167-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>,
 <xref rid="B168-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>,
 <xref rid="B276-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">276</xref>]. 
 <italic>A. arabica</italic> also has the potential to inhibit the viral replication against HIV infection [
 <xref rid="B149-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>,
 <xref rid="B169-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>]. Due to its antiviral nature, it is highly recommended to use 
 <italic>A. arabica</italic> for controlling/managing SARS-CoV-2 infection.
</p>
