<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">
  <italic class="italic">Aeollanthus suaveolens</italic> species popularly known as catinga de mulata belongs to the Lamiaceae family. In the Amazon region, it is used in folk medicine for the treatment of gastritis, convulsions of epileptic origin, stomach pain and diarrhea in the form of tea and juice. Essential oils have analgesic, anti-inflammatory, and antimicrobial activity. This study evaluated the chemical composition of the 
  <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">suaveolens</italic> essential oil, and its cytotoxic, antimicrobial and antioxidant activity on 
  <italic class="italic">Artemia salina</italic> Leach. The plant species was collected in Fazendinha district in the city of Macapa-AP. The essential oil obtained from the process was performed by hydrodistillation and identification of components by gas chromatography coupled with mass spectrometer. The antioxidant activity was evaluated by the kidnapping method of 2,2- diphenyl -1-picrilhidrazil radical, while the cytotoxic activity was assessed using saline A. and the microbiological activity was carried out by microdilution method with 
  <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> sp. and 
  <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> bacteria. In a chromatographic analysis, the major constituents found in the essential oil of 
  <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">suaveolens</italic> were (E) -β-farnesene (37.615%), Linalool (33.375%), α-Santalene (3.255%) and linalyl acetate (3.222%). The results showed that the 
  <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> sp. bacteria were more susceptible to MIC 50 mg.mL
  <sup class="sup">-1</sup> when compared with the 
  <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> bacterium MIC 100 mg.mL
  <sup class="sup">-1</sup>. With respect to MBC concentration of 100 mg.mL
  <sup class="sup">-1</sup> it was sufficient to inhibit the growth of 
  <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">coli</italic>. The essential oil did not show antioxidant activity, however, has a high cytotoxic activity against the 
  <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">salina</italic>, LC
  <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub> 8.90 μg.mL
  <sup class="sup">-1</sup>.
 </p>
</abstract>
