<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Either superhydrophobic or superhydrophilic 3D PMs, they only have one single wetting property and can only absorb or separate specific liquids. In addition, oils, especially the high viscos oil (e.g., crude oil) are easily adhering onto the superhydrophobic surface causing the reduction of adsorption capacity and difficult to desorb [
 <xref rid="B203-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">203</xref>]. Smart 3D porous materials with switchable wettability are receiving more and more attention due to the advantages of responding to external stimulation, ease of adsorb-desorption, self-cleaning, multi-functional oil/water separation under varied environment. A series of 3D-PMs have been reported to utilize in oil/water separation which can switch their wettability under the stimulation of light [
 <xref rid="B204-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">204</xref>], heat [
 <xref rid="B205-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">205</xref>], pH [
 <xref rid="B206-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">206</xref>] showing ease of desorption after oil absorption and self-cleaning (
 <xref rid="polymers-11-00806-t003" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>). Li et al. [
 <xref rid="B204-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">204</xref>] reported to fabricate light responding PU sponge through immersing into octadecanoic acid and titanium dioxide (TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) solution under ultrasonication and obtained coral-like cluster rough structures with superhydrophobicity (WCA: 151°). The superhydrophobic composite sponge (151.1°) was switched into superhydrophilic (0°) under UV irradiation by from the generation of Ti
 <sup class="sup">3+</sup>, oxygen vacancy and the formation of hydrogen bonds. This smart TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> PU sponge can absorb 27–60 times oil or organic solvents of its original weight and shows certain antifouling and self-cleaning properties. The adhered oil on the sponge skeleton causing the decreasing of separation efficiency which can be released under UV irradiation attributing to the conversion of hydrophobicity to hydrophilicity. Kim et al. [
 <xref rid="B117-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">117</xref>] further investigated the mechanisms of oil desorption under UV irradiation indicating that the oil desorption was attributed to the growth and diffusion of the generated bubbles from the dissolved oxygen and nitrogen under the catalysis of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. The bubbles wrapped oil to increase its diffusion power and thus desorb from porous materials surface into water (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="polymers-11-00806-f016" class="xref">Figure 16</xref>a,b).
</p>
