<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Comparing with UV irradiation which requires the generation of UV light, thermal and pH response can also be utilized to tune the super-wetting property of surfaces relatively simply. Poly (
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>-isopropyl acrylamide) (PNIPAAm) is a type of thermal response material with relatively low hydrophilic and hydrophobic transition temperature (LCST) of 32 °C [
 <xref rid="B205-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">205</xref>]. When the temperature is less than the LCST, PNIPAAm forms hydrogen bonds with water molecule to hydrate, swell and outstretch resulting in hydrophilicity; when the temperature is higher than the LCST, the C=O group combines with the N-H group to form intramolecular hydrogen bond resulting in hydrophobicity [
 <xref rid="B205-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">205</xref>]. Lei et al. [
 <xref rid="B205-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">205</xref>] grafted hydrophobic octadecyltrichlorosilane (OTS) modified PNIPAAm onto melamine sponge to artificial control wettability by changing temperature. Water contact angle increased from 0° to 150° when the temperature rises from 25 to 40 °C showing superhydrophobicity. Oil can be quickly adsorbed at 37 °C (the modified sponge can absorb about 35 times pump oil/peanut oil/gasoline of its initial weight) while the oil can be quickly and completely discharged after applying a slightly pressure at 20 °C (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="polymers-11-00806-f016" class="xref">Figure 16</xref>c
 <sub class="sub">1</sub>). Furthermore, the thermal response performance was stable after 5 adsorption/desorption cycles (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="polymers-11-00806-f016" class="xref">Figure 16</xref>c
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>). pH responded and switchable super-wetting melamine sponge was developed by grafting poly-4-vinylpyridine (PVP) [
 <xref rid="B206-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">206</xref>]. Water contact angle gradually rises from 0° to 137° when pH increases from 1 to 7. When pH = 7, WCA reached to 137°, achieving a transition between superhydrophilicity and superhydrophobicity. PVP deprotonated and agglomerated at pH=7 showing hydrophobicity and it can quickly absorb oil stains; the PVP protonated pyridyl group stretches at pH=1 showing hydrophilicity and rapidly releasing of oil stains. By changing the environmental parameters, the sponge with switchable wettability provides a good solution for the treatment of highly viscous oil e.g., crude oil. 
</p>
