<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the World Health Organization (WHO), noncommunicable diseases (NCDs) will be responsible for more than three-quarters of all deaths in 2030, among which cardiovascular diseases (CVD) represent a major risk. The mortality rate by CVD should rise from 17.1 million in 2004 to 23.4 million in 2030. The epidemiological data show that lifestyle and dietary habits are the main factors of the high prevalence of hypertension [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conventional medicines used in the treatment of CVD have numerous collateral effects [
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>], and they are expensive [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>]. Thus, there is a requirement for a safer, cheaper, and more powerful alternative. The professional community has increasingly accepted natural medicine, due to advances in understanding the mechanisms by which plants positively influence health and quality of life [
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>, 
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pharmaceutical studies have shown that natural products represent an extremely valuable source for the production of new chemical products and treatment of untreated diseases [
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>–
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>]. Natural products are present in diverse parts of plants, produced through their metabolism, and their pharmacological potential has been confirmed in scientific studies; moreover, they are easily extracted and are economically viable [
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>]; hence, essential oils have a large tradition in popular medicine [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among the various aromatic plants, present in our region, with powerful pharmaceutical properties, the species
  <span class="italic"> Protium heptaphyllum</span> (Aubl.) Marchand is highlighted due to its wide distribution in our community, frequently found in core markets, used in folk medicine and extensive potential therapeutic applications.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">P. heptaphyllum</span>, belonging to the Burseraceae family, is a tree present almost all over Brazil, especially in damp or dry sandy soil areas; it is evergreen or semideciduous and aromatic, with a height of 10 m to 20 m and stem of 40 cm to 60 cm in diameter [
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>]. It is found mainly in the Amazon region and in some northeastern states, such as Bahia, Ceará, and Piauí, and other countries of South America (Colombia, Paraguay, Suriname, and Venezuela). From its trunk exudes an oily resin called
  <span class="italic"> Almécega</span> or
  <span class="italic"> Breu-branco</span>, which hardens in contact with air; this exudate has a greenish-white coloration and a pleasant aroma and is rich in essential oils [
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>, 
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Almécega presents several therapeutic indications such as anti-inflammatory, contraceptive, antineoplastic, cicatrizing, expectorant, antimicrobial, and antifungal indications [
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>]. It is also used by the indigenous Brazilians as a nasal decongestant [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>, 14–17] for being present in various parts of the plants produced through its secondary metabolism; its pharmacological potential has been reported in some scientific studies; because they are easy to extract and are economically viable, essential oils have assumed a prominent role in research on natural products; however, still few studies investigate their cardiovascular effects, being the first time reported in the species under study.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The emergence of drug resistant strains of pathogens, the increase in the immunocompromised population, and the limitations of the available antibiotics/drugs have motivated people to use complementary and alternative therapies, including the use of essential oils [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil obtained from the resin of Almécega has been proven to have anti-inflammatory, antitumor, antioxidant, antimicrobial, and cytotoxic actions against
  <span class="italic"> Artemia salina </span>[
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>]. In this context,
  <span class="italic"> P. heptaphyllum</span> has become a potential ally, since many pharmacological studies have shown its positive effects in the treatment of various diseases coupled with the fact that there are no studies that prove the action of this essential oil from
  <span class="italic"> P. heptaphyllum</span> (EOPh) in contraction of vascular smooth muscle.
 </p>
</sec>
