<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Photosynthesis is considered to be the most important photochemical reaction in plants and is highly sensitive to temperature. In this study, the expression of genes in the photosynthesis pathway of 
 <italic>S. trilobata</italic> were not significantly different under HT stress. Conversely, 
 <italic>PsbA</italic> and 
 <italic>PsbP</italic> gene expression in the leaves of 
 <italic>S. calendulacea</italic> was significantly decreased under HT stress (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-00748-f005">Figure 5</xref>A,B). A low level of 
 <italic>PsbA</italic> gene expression has been shown to negatively influence the D1 content in PSII [
 <xref rid="B19-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and decrease the photosynthesis capability [
 <xref rid="B20-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The OEC protein is encoded by the 
 <italic>PsbP</italic> gene, and its damage will also inevitably affect the heat tolerance of PSII under HT stress [
 <xref rid="B21-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. HT stress further inhibited the electron transfer from the OEC protein to the PSII acceptor side [
 <xref rid="B22-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The result of this study showed that F
 <sub>v</sub>/F
 <sub>m</sub> and Φ
 <sub>PSII</sub> in 
 <italic>S. trilobata</italic> were close to or even slightly higher than normal temperature, while all of them were significantly decreases in 
 <italic>S. calendulacea</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-00748-f002">Figure 2</xref>B,C). It was suggested that compared with 
 <italic>S. trilobata,</italic> the leaves of 
 <italic>S. calendulacea</italic> were the most seriously damaged under HT stress. Similar results were also found in tomato seedlings [
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Studies have shown that the capacity for ribulose-1,5-diphosphate (RuBP) regeneration could be dramatically inhibited by the disruption of electron transfer and the inactivation of the OEC enzyme [
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The RT-qPCR results demonstrated that the 
 <italic>RubiscoL</italic> gene expression was significantly decreased in 
 <italic>S. calendulacea</italic> under HT stress (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-00748-f005">Figure 5</xref>C), thus limiting the rate of CO
 <sub>2</sub> fixation [
 <xref rid="B12-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. This is in accordance with the results of P
 <sub>n</sub> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-00748-f002">Figure 2</xref>A). Liu et al. have found that lower quantities of the photosynthetic pigments may inhibit the photosynthetic capacity [
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The results showed that HT stress reduced Chl contents in the leaves of 
 <italic>S. calendulacea</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-00748-f001">Figure 1</xref>B–F) and limited the absorption of light energy [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Particularly, there was a significant increase in the photosynthetic pigment content in 
 <italic>S. trilobata</italic> and its leaves remained green, indicating the photosynthetic capacity of 
 <italic>S. trilobata</italic> was basically not affected by HT stress. These results are consistent with Song et al. [
 <xref rid="B10-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
</p>
