<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant materials</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rhizomes of 
   <span class="italic">C. rotundus</span>, which were harvested in the region of Taian County of Shandong Province, China in 2015, were obtained as commercial products from the local market in March 2016. The moisture content, which was determined using a laboratory oven at 110 °C, was 11.4% for dried 
   <span class="italic">C. rotundus</span> rhizomes.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemicals and reagents</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2, 4, 6-Tri (2-pyridyl)-s-triazine (TPTZ) were purchased from Fluka (Switzerland). 2,2′-azino-bis (3-ethylbenothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) diammonium salts (ABTS), 2,2′-azobis (2-methylpropionamidine) dihydrochloride (AAPH), 3-(4,5-dimethyl-2-thiazolyl)- 2,5-diphenyl-2H-tetrazolium bromide (MTT), 2,2-Diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH), the homologous series of 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-hexane (C
   <sub>8</sub>-C
   <sub>24</sub>) and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) activity assay kit were from Sigma (USA). Propidium iodide (PI) was from BD Biosciences. The pBR322 plasmid DNA was from Takara Bio Co. Ltd. (Dalian, China). Other chemicals used were all of analytical grade and obtained from China.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bacterial strains and culture</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three Gram-positive strains were 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> (ATCC 25923), 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</span> (ATCC 8799) and 
   <span class="italic">Bacillus subtilis</span> (ATCC 6051). Three Gram-negative bacteria were 
   <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span> (ATCC 25922), 
   <span class="italic">Salmonella typhimurium</span> (ATCC 19430), and 
   <span class="italic">Shigella dysenteriae</span> (CMCC (B) 51252). Strains were provided by the School of Life Science, Shanxi Normal University, and cultured at 37 °C on nutrient agar and nutrient broth mediums.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oil extraction</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dried rhizomes of 
   <span class="italic">C. rotundus</span> were ground with a micro plant grinding machine to a powder and then hydrodistilled for 6 h using a Clevenger-type apparatus. The oil was separated from water and dried over anhydrous sodium sulfate and stored in tightly closed dark vials at 4 °C until use.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC-MS analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analysis of the essential oil was performed using a Hewlett-Packard 5890 II GC, equipped with a HP-5 MS capillary column (30 m × 0.25 mm; film thickness, 0.25 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>m) and a HP 5972 mass selective detector for the separation. The mass selective detector was operated in electron-impact ionization (EI) mode with a mass scan range from 
   <span class="italic">m</span>/
   <span class="italic">z</span> 30 to 550 at 70 eV. Helium was the carrier gas at a flow rate of 1 mL/min. The initial temperature at 50 °C, held for 1 min, ramped at 5 °C/min to 280 °C and held for 1 min. Injector and MS transfer line temperatures were set at 230 and 300 °C, respectively. The oven temperature was programmed as in the GC-FID analysis. A sample of 1 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>L of 1% essential oil was injected manually using a 1:10 split ratio. Most components were identified by comparing their GC retention indices which were determined in relation to a homologous series of 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes (C8-C24) under the same operating conditions, NIST mass spectral search program (version 2.0, National Institute of Standards and Technology), and mass spectra with publish data. Component relative percentages were calculated based on GC peak areas without using correction factors.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DPPH assay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The scavenging rate and scavenging activity of the sample on DPPH radicals were determined according to the method as previously described
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">37</a>. The scavenging activity was expressed by EC
   <sub>50</sub> value that is the effective concentration at which free radicals are scavenged by 50% and is obtained by interpolation from regression analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ABTS assay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ABTS cation radical scavenging activity was determined according to the method as previously described
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">37</a>. The scavenging rate and EC
   <sub>50</sub> value were calculated using the equation described for DPPH assay.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ferric reducing antioxidant power (FRAP) assay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reducing ability was determined by using FRAP assay as previously described
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">37</a>. The absorption of the reaction mixture was measured at 593 nm after incubation for 30 min at 37 °C. Increased absorbance of the reaction mixture indicated increased reducing power.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Protection of DNA oxidative damage induced by Fe
   <span class="sup">2+</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ability of samples to protect supercoiled pBR322 plasmid DNA against Fe
   <span class="sup">2+</span> and H
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub> was estimated with the DNA nicking assay as previously described
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">37</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Protection of DNA oxidative damage induced AAPH</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ability of samples to protect supercoiled pBR322 plasmid against AAPH was measured according to the method described by Zhang and Omaye with some modifications
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" href="#b38">38</a>. Intact pBR322 plasmid (0.5 μg) was mixed with various concentrations of samples and 2 μL of 25 mM AAPH in PBS (pH 7.4), and the mixture was incubated for 30 min at 37 °C. Then the samples were electrophoresed on 0.8% agarose gel containing 0.5 μg/mL ethidium bromide, photos of DNA bands were taken under gel image analysis system.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cytotoxicity activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the cytotoxic effects, the human neuroblastoma SH-SY5Y cell line was used in this study. Cells were seeded into 96 and 24-well plates in 1:1 mixture of DMEM/F-12 supplemented with 10% FBS, 2 mM L-glutamine, antibiotic and antimycotic solution in a humid atmosphere of 5% CO
   <sub>2</sub> and 95% air at 37 °C. The media was changed on alternative days and once the confluency was reached, the cells were treated with sample at different concentrations. The MTT assay and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) release assay was performed to determine the cell viability as described in a previous report
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" href="#b2">2</a>. Briefly, the SH-SY5Y cells were seeded in 96-well plates at a density of 1 × 10
   <span class="sup">4</span> cells/well and grown for 36 h and then subjected with essential oil at concentrations ranging from 50 to 1000 μg/mL. After treatments, MTT (0.5 mg/mL) was added to each well and incubated for 2 h at 37 °C and the formed formazan crystals were dissolved in DMSO, and then the percentage of cell viability was calculated. For LDH release assay, the SH-SY5Y cells were plated at a density of 5 × 10
   <span class="sup">4</span> cells/well in 24-well plates. After 24 h, the cells were treated with essential oil for 24 h and then lysed with, 10 μL of 2% Triton X-100. The cells were precipitated by centrifugation at 3000 rpm for 5 min at 4 °C. The supernatant (100 μL) was mixed with 900 μL of kit reaction mixture and the enzyme activity was measured in terms of intracellular LDH released into the medium at a wavelength of 340 nm.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antibacterial activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
   <span class="italic">in vitro</span> antibacterial activity of the tested sample was carried out by disc diffusion method. The inoculum suspension containing 1 × 10
   <span class="sup">7</span> CFU/mL of bacteria was spread on nutrient agar medium uniformly. The sample was dissolved and then loaded on 6 mm sterile individual discs. The loaded discs were placed on the surface of medium and the diameter of zone of inhibition (ZOI) was measured after 24 h of incubation at 37 °C. Minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) and minimum bactericide concentration (MBC) of sample were determined according to the method as previously described
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" href="#b39">39</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fluorescence microscopy analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Logarithmic phase bacteria were collected by centrifugation at 6000 × g for 5 min, washed three times, and resuspended in PBS (pH 7.4). Tested bacteria were treated with different concentrations of samples and incubated at 37 °C. After 1 h and 2 h, cells containing approximately 1 × 10
   <span class="sup">8</span> CFU/mL were harvested by centrifugation at 6000 × g for 5 min and stained for 15 min with the equal volume of 1 mg/mL PI in the dark at room temperature. Ten microliters of the stained bacterial suspensions were dropped onto glass slides and covered with coverslips, and images were captured by a fluorescence microscope (Leica, DMi8).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Duncan’s multiple range tests were carried out to determine significant differences (
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05) between the means by Data Processing System (DPS, version 7.05) and EXCEL program.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
