<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Auxins are a group of plant hormones that play a cardinal role in the plant growth and behavioural processes
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>27</sup>
 </xref>. Biological effects of naturally occurring auxins in plants include indole-3-acetic acid (IAA), 4-chloroindole-3-acetic acid (4-Cl-IAA), phenylacetic acid (PAA), indole-3-butyric acid (IBA), and indole-3-propionic acid (IPA), have exhibited inhibitory activities against human tumour cell lines
 <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref>. However, development of auxins as anticancer agents has been rarely reported. In our previous study, a potent IBHA with antitumor activity was derived by substitution of carboxyl group of IBA with hydroxamic acid
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref>. Compared with SAHA, IBHA exhibited reduced activities in the HDAC enzymatic inhibition and antiproliferative assays. Inspired by structures of high potent HDACIs Panobinostat and Dacinostat which have the 3-alkyl indole pharmacophores in the cap region, structural modification was performed to IBHA. In the present study, to enhance the binding affinity of IBA derivatives with HDACs, and improve the antitumor activity of IBA derivatives, phenyl group was introduced to the linker of IBHA. Substituted groups were introduced to the nitrogen in the indole ring, and hydroxamic acid was utilised as zinc binding group (ZBG). Hydrazide has been reported as ZBG with good HDAC inhibitory activity
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref>. Therefore, to investigate the performance of hydrazide in the present structure, hydroxamic acid groups of several active molecules have been replaced by hydrazide groups (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>). The anticancer activities of the derived molecules were evaluated in the enzymatic assay, 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> cancer cell based screening, apoptosis, and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> anticancer test.
</p>
