<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par44">Alpha1 subunit of the Na
 <sup>+</sup>/K
 <sup>+</sup>-ATPase (NAK) is significantly overexpressed in gliomas, melanomas and NSCLCs and impairing its activity kills cancer cells and an efficient approach to killing MDR cancer cells. A number of thiazole derivatives including 4-halo-2,5-disubtituted-1,3- thiazoles and thienothiazoles were evaluated for their in vitro growth inhibitory activity against a panel of 6 glioma cell lines. Compounds 
 <bold>48a</bold> and 
 <bold>48b</bold> exhibited ~ 10 times higher in vitro growth inhibition of α subunits of the Na
 <sup>+</sup>/K
 <sup>+</sup>-ATpase than perillyl alcohol (POH), which is a NAK inhibitor. The in vitro cytostatic activities of 
 <bold>48a</bold> and 
 <bold>48b</bold> were independent of the inherent resistance to pro-apoptotic stimulus related with cancer cell lines. Derivatives 
 <bold>48a</bold> and 
 <bold>48b</bold> demonstrated similar inhibition on purified guinea pig brain preparations that largely expressed subunits of NAK alpha-2 and alpha-3, while analogue 
 <bold>48b</bold> was effective towards purified guinea pig kidney preparations that largely expressed the NAK alpha-1 subunit that was also overexpressed in gliomas, melanomas and non-small-cell lung cancers NSCLCs. The best anti-NAK inhibitors were cardiotonic steroids that showed cardiotoxicity and had very narrow therapeutic index as potent anticancer agents. Compound 
 <bold>48b</bold> will not probably show cardiotoxic effects. POH as noncardiotonic steroid-related compound demonstrated remarkable therapeutic benefits to glioma patients. POH created its anti-glioma activity at least partly via inhibition of both α1 NAK subunit and Ras oncogene. Particularly, derivative 
 <bold>48b</bold> was about 3 times more effective than POH in inhibition of α1 NAK subunit and was 40 times more potent than POH in inhibition of Ras (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>].
</p>
