<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>DDRP requires daily 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>min</italic>
 </sub> and 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>max</italic>
 </sub> data in a gridded format for an area of interest in CONUS (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0244005.g001">Fig 1</xref>). For real-time modeling, we have been using daily 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>min</italic>
 </sub> and 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>max</italic>
 </sub> data at a 4 km spatial resolution from the PRISM (Parameter-elevation Relationships on Independent Slopes Model) database (available at 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://prism.oregonstate.edu/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://prism.oregonstate.edu</ext-link>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0244005.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Daily PRISM data become available 
 <italic>ca</italic>. 1 day after weather station observations are reported, and are typically updated and improve in quality as more observations are added (see PRISM website for details). The phenology mapping system of the USA National Phenology Network [
 <xref rid="pone.0244005.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] uses Real-Time Mesoscale Analysis (RTMA) weather data at a 2.5 km resolution, which are available within hours after data are observed. The daily 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>min</italic>
 </sub> and 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>max</italic>
 </sub> RTMA data set could potentially be used in DDRP; however, the RTMA methodology lacks PRISM’s update and quality control regimes [
 <xref rid="pone.0244005.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Another alternative is Daymet v3, which offers daily climate data for North America, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico at a very high spatial resolution (1 km) (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://daymet.ornl.gov/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://daymet.ornl.gov</ext-link>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0244005.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. However, Daymet data are released months after the end of each year, so they would be less useful for within-season modeling and decision support.
</p>
