<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The activities on the Central Nervous System (CNS) are not usually investigated for the EOs [
 <xref rid="B39-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], due to antibacterial and antifungal properties being the most common. Nevertheless, the literature reports several volatile fractions with an interesting in vitro inhibition activity [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] versus AChE and BChE. Some of them are also significantly active against AD in vivo, or even in clinical trials [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The secondary metabolites that have been recognized to be active as pure compounds are linalool, 
 <italic>α</italic>-terpinene, carvacrol, 
 <italic>α</italic>-terpineol, thymol, 
 <italic>α</italic>-pinene, (
 <italic>E</italic>)-
 <italic>β</italic>-caryophyllene and eugenol [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Five of them are also present in the investigated EO of 
 <italic>C. taxifolium</italic>, where (
 <italic>E</italic>)-
 <italic>β</italic>-caryophyllene is the main constituent with an abundance of 17.8–14.5% on the two columns, respectively. However, the 
 <italic>C. taxifolium</italic> EO produced a selective inhibition of BChE, differing from what is usually described in the literature, where (
 <italic>E</italic>)-
 <italic>β</italic>-caryophyllene, and some of the above mentioned terpenoids, inhibit both enzymes [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Actually, the selective inhibition of BChE is a very interesting property, since many studies have been investing the clinical application of similar drugs during the last 20 years [
 <xref rid="B42-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. AChE and BChE are both present in the CNS but in different locations. In particular, AChE is typically found in neurons, whereas BChE is common in glial cells [
 <xref rid="B42-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In normal brain, about 80% of the total cholinesterase is constituted by AChE, and only 20% by BChE. However, with the progress of the AD, the ratio between the activities of BChE and AChE can increase from the normal value of 0.5 up to 11 [
 <xref rid="B42-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. This phenomenon could convert BChE to the main ChE in the development of AD. From a speculative point of view, the inhibition mechanism for 
 <italic>C. taxifolium</italic> EO can be explained considering the different shapes of the active sites. According to X-ray diffraction data, the selective activity can be achieved by using the additional space present in the active site of BChE [
 <xref rid="B42-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], which implies that selective inhibitors are usually bigger molecules than those of AChE. Since this is not the case for 
 <italic>C. taxifolium</italic> EO components, the most probable hypothesis is a synergic effect of the whole mixture, where the combined effect of many constituents is different from that of the sum of the same pure components. This behaviour has already been demonstrated for some essential oils and described in the literature, e.g., for 
 <italic>Salvia lavandulifolia</italic> and 
 <italic>Melaleuca alternifolia</italic> (tea tree) EOs [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The other major EO constituents were 
 <italic>α</italic>-copaene (10.5–8.0%), 
 <italic>β</italic>-bourbonene (9.9–8.2%), 
 <italic>δ</italic>-cadinene (6.6–5.4%), 
 <italic>cis</italic>-cadina-1(6),4-diene (6.4–6.2%) and germacrene D (4.9–4.9%). These components can be responsible for the selective synergic effect, although, to the best of the authors’ knowledge, no evidence has been reported in this respect. Although the IC
 <sub>50</sub> value calculated for this EO is quite higher than the one calculated for the positive control, the EO can be considered an active product. In fact, donepezil (positive control) is a pure substance while the EO is a mixture of at least 37 compounds, most of them likely inactive.
</p>
