<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0095">In addition to pharmacopeia uses presented in 
 <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, 
 <italic>M. spicata</italic> and 
 <italic>M. viridis</italic> are widely consumed in Morocco to make tea infusion. 
 <italic>M. spicata</italic> is recommended for hypertension, cardiac diseases, gastrointestinal disorders, infectious and parasitic diseases, complications of pregnancy and childbirth, skin pathologies, burns, and undefined symptoms (headache, thirst, tonic) [
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. 
 <italic>M. viridis</italic> is especially used to heal respiratory disorders, renal pathologies, hypertension, skin pathologies, headache, and tiredness [
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. When 
 <italic>M. pulegium</italic>, 
 <italic>M. spicata</italic>, and 
 <italic>M. viridis</italic> are widely used in all Morocco, the other Mentha species are used only in limited zones. 
 <italic>M. suaveolens</italic> is administered by the populations of High Atlas and Oujda regions [
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The main routes of administration of the plant are decoction, oral ingestion, inhalant, and external application (
 <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). In High Atlas, 
 <italic>M. suaveolens</italic> is mainly used for respiratory diseases, gastrointestinal disorders, musculoskeletal illnesses, otolaryngological and pediatric illnesses, while in the Oujda region it is used for diabetes, digestive disorders, and allergies. 
 <italic>M. rotundifolia</italic> is recommended in the Ouazzane region for skin pathologies, while it is used in the Taounat region for respiratory and digestive disorders [
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In High Atlas, 
 <italic>M. gattefossei</italic> is administered as a decoction, for general health [
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], while 
 <italic>M. vulgare</italic> is used in the Fez-Boulemane region for diabetes [
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The difference in use of the same plant depending on the region must be linked to the cultural heritage of the medicinal plants' use in the region. It could also be explained by factors such as degradation and deforestation that affect the availability of the plant to the local population [
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].
</p>
