<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Allelochemicals from tree species also could be used as insecticides. Among four main types of botanical products used for insect control—pyrethrum, rotenone, neem, and essential oils [
 <xref rid="B312-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">312</xref>], the latter two are obtained from woody plants (fully and partially, respectively). Among them, the most famous is limonoid triterpene azadirachtin discovered in the 1960s (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01636-f020" class="xref">Figure 20</xref>) and extracted from the seeds of the Indian neem tree [
 <italic class="italic">Azadirachta indica</italic> A. Juss (Meliaceae)] [
 <xref rid="B313-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">313</xref>]. In 1994, the EPA registered a botanical insecticide containing azadirachtin, and a number of commercial preparations are currently produced where it is an active ingredient. Azadirachtin is a system pesticide and has two effects on insects: it blocks the synthesis and releases molting hormones (ecdysteroids) leading to incomplete ecdysis in immature insects or to sterility in adult female insects, and it is a potent antifeedant [
 <xref rid="B312-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">312</xref>]. Azadirachtin is nontoxic to mammals, birds, fish, and pollinators, as well it has a short half-life and popular in the organic agriculture. In forestry azadirachtin demonstrated its efficiency in protecting ash trees from emerald ash borer (
 <italic class="italic">Agrilus planipennis</italic> Fairmaire)—an exotic invasive pest that threatens 
 <italic class="italic">Fraxinus</italic> spp. trees throughout North America [
 <xref rid="B314-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">314</xref>]. Results support the use of azadirachtin as an environmentally acceptable systemic insecticide in urban [
 <xref rid="B315-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">315</xref>] and in ecologically sensitive [
 <xref rid="B316-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">316</xref>] environments, such as riparian and source-water forests, wooded wetlands, or conservation areas.
</p>
