<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Juglone toxicity for various insects has been shown in various studies [
 <xref rid="B330-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">330</xref>,
 <xref rid="B331-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">331</xref>], although some lepidopteran species were resistant, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Actias luna</italic> that possesses high activity of quinone reductase and was able to detoxify juglone [
 <xref rid="B332-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">332</xref>]. The mechanism of insecticidal activity of juglone has not fully understood. Mitchell and Smith [
 <xref rid="B333-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">333</xref>] assumed that juglone may inhibit activity of ecdysone 20-monooxygenase, an enzyme responsible for converting the molting hormone ecdysone. Magiri et al. [
 <xref rid="B334-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">334</xref>] has showed that juglone inhibited respiration in the 
 <italic class="italic">Glossina morsitans</italic> mitochondria. Using metabolomics analysis, it was demonstrated that the juglone caused a disturbance of the 
 <italic class="italic">Apis gossypii</italic> physiology by affecting its hemolymph metabolomic profile [
 <xref rid="B335-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">335</xref>]. Finally, Hu et al. [
 <xref rid="B336-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">336</xref>] found that juglone inhibits phenoloxidase activity in haemolymph of larvae of 
 <italic class="italic">Pieris rapae</italic> Linne and 
 <italic class="italic">Helicoverpa armigera</italic> Hübner. In insects, phenoloxidase plays an important role in the developmental processes of immunity defence, and its inhibitor has a perspective as a bioinsecticide. In addition, studies have been also conducted to evaluate the toxic activity of juglone derivatives. Evaluation of substituted hydroxyquinones, their salts and halogenated quinines on 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes aegypti</italic> L. has showed that three substances are several times more effective than juglone, and activity of 3-bromojuglone is similar to the temephos pesticide [
 <xref rid="B337-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">337</xref>]. These results indicated that the bromo substituent, in bromoquinones, is highly reactive and may be used as efficient biocontrol agent against the mosquito larvae.
</p>
