<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To overcome the disadvantage of the administration of large volumes of (micro)emulsions per dose, several researchers focused their studies on the design of preconcentrated organic liquid phases loaded with poorly water soluble drugs, capable of reconstituting the (micro)emulsion spontaneously once in contact with an aqueous milieu (gastric fluids after ingestion). The resulting formulation is commonly termed in the literature as a liquid self-emulsifying drug delivery system (SEDDS) [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-24-02155" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-molecules-24-02155" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>]. The essential property that must be satisfied in the development of a liquid SEDDS formulation is that the drug must remain partitioned within the O/W droplets after dilution with the aqueous medium in the GIT. Otherwise, the drug could undergo an unwanted precipitation that would lead to poor bioavailability in vivo. Among the first documented studies on the application of SEDDS as potential nanocarrier to increase SIL solubilization and its oral bioavailability, we mention the work by Wu et al. [
 <xref rid="B70-molecules-24-02155" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>], who optimized the multi-component oily phase, ethyl linoleate/Tween80/ethyl alcohol, to solubilize SLM. The self-emulsifying properties of that system were tested upon titration with various aqueous media until a stable O/W microemulsion was obtained. During the titration, the samples were agitated gently in order to reach equilibrium quickly. Dilution volume had no significant effect on droplet sizes (mean value of dozens nm), which were found also unaffected by the increase of drug loading up to 100 mg per 1 g of oil phase. Relative drug bioavailability after oral administration of the said lipid emulsion, improved approximately 1.88- and 48.82-fold that of SLM dissolved in PEG 400 solution and aqueous suspension, respectively.
</p>
