<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The sulforhodamine B (SRB) assay as described previously [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] was adapted for the cytotoxicity screening. Adult human dermal fibroblast cells (HDFa; C-013-5C) were grown at 37°C in a humidified atmosphere of 5% in a culture flask (75 cm
 <sup>2</sup>) which contained Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium, modified with 10% FBS, 1% nonessential amino acids, and 0.1% gentamicin and amphotericin B. The grown cells were seeded in a 96 well microtitre plate, and a determined quantity of test samples was added. The samples were then incubated for 72 h at 37°C in 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub>. Afterwards, 50 
 <italic>μ</italic>L of cold 40% 
 <sup>W</sup>/
 <sub>V</sub> trichloroacetic acid (TCA) solution was added and incubated for an hour at 4°C and washed four times with distilled water. Cultured cells were then stained with 0.4% 
 <sup>W</sup>/
 <sub>V</sub> SRB solution and left for an hour at room temperature. Afterwards, the plate was rinsed four times with 1% acetic acid and left for 24 h to dry. Prior to optical density (OD) determination at 510 nm using a microtitre plate reader (Tecan Infinite® M200), 100 
 <italic>μ</italic>L of 10 mM Tris buffer solution was dispensed into the wells and agitated in an orbital shaker for 5 min, to allow solubilisation of SRB-protein complex. The percentage of viable cell was calculated using the following formula:
 <disp-formula id="EEq1">
  <label>(1)</label>
  <math id="M1">
   <mtable>
    <mtr>
     <mtd>
      <mtext>percentage of viable cell </mtext>
      <mo>=</mo>
      <mtext> </mtext>
      <mfrac>
       <mrow>
        <mtext>OD of test sample</mtext>
        <mo>−</mo>
        <mtext>OD of blank</mtext>
       </mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mtext>OD of control</mtext>
        <mo>−</mo>
        <mtext>OD of blank </mtext>
       </mrow>
      </mfrac>
      <mtext> </mtext>
      <mo>×</mo>
      <mtext> </mtext>
      <mn>100.</mn>
     </mtd>
    </mtr>
   </mtable>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
