<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Aware of all the above-mentioned regulatory networks, it is clear that research has largely focused on the role of TFs, which play pivotal roles in regulating genes involved in all aspects of plant development, including specialized metabolism. TFs are regulatory proteins that modulate the expression of genes, and the set of genes regulated by a specific TF is referred to as a regulon. TFs bind—alone or as part of multimeric complexes—specific short sequences (
 <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements) in the regulatory regions of target genes, promoting or blocking the recruitment of the transcriptional machinery [
 <xref rid="B185-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>]. Mutations and neo-functionalization of metabolic genes are largely responsible for the increase in chemo-diversity among metabolites; however, there are limits to the extent that an enzyme can be modified without affecting its stability. For this reason, it has been proposed that TFs play a priming role in the recruitment of metabolic genes into regulons—as a consequence of the emergence of cognate 
 <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements, which might largely fuel the diversification of specialized metabolic pathways [
 <xref rid="B186-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>,
 <xref rid="B187-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">187</xref>]. While plant regulons often consist of genes scattered through the genome in non-contiguous loci, there is evidence that biosynthetic gene clusters (BGCs) and regulatory gene cluster (RGCs) might be recurrent for pathways of specialized metabolism; this is the case for steroidal glycoalkaloid genes organized in a BGC in tomato, all controlled by a RGC of AP2/ERF TFs resulting from tandem repeats of ancestral genes [
 <xref rid="B184-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>,
 <xref rid="B188-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">188</xref>]. All major families of TFs have been described as regulators of plant specialized metabolism. Due to the combinatory nature of metabolic networks, closely related enzymes can be recruited in different regulons and TFs of different families contribute (synergistically or antagonistically) in the regulation of metabolic pathways [
 <xref rid="B189-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">189</xref>].
</p>
