<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genetic engineering could help obtaining further benefits from the tuning of this regulatory mechanism; this was proven by the molecular strategies used to increase anthocyanins in tomato fruits, recently summarized [
 <xref rid="B195-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>]. Cultivated tomatoes do not accumulate anthocyanins in their fruits, although biosynthetic genes are present in their genome, and some wild tomato species produce green fruits that, upon suitable light conditions, can accumulate anthocyanins in the peel [
 <xref rid="B196-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>]. Hence, researchers moved to the TF strategy with the overexpression in tomato of two maize TFs, belonging to the bHLH and R2R3-MYB families, known to regulate anthocyanin biosynthesis. Moreover, this approach turned out to be unsuccessful, due to the lack of activation of one of the tomato anthocyanin synthesis structural genes [
 <xref rid="B197-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>]. In 2008, another attempt was successful: Butelli and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B198-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>] overexpressed the 
 <italic>Delila bHLH</italic> and the 
 <italic>Rosea 1 R2R3-MYB</italic> genes from 
 <italic>Anthirrinum majus</italic> under the control of the fruit-specific E8 promoter, obtaining tomato fruits accumulating anthocyanins at a concentration of 2 mg g
 <sup>−1</sup>, similar levels as in blueberries and blackberries. The purple tomatoes showed a protective effect against cancer progression when used to feed cancer-susceptible Trp-53-/-knockout mice [
 <xref rid="B198-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>]. The purple tomato line was then crossed with another line expressing the 
 <italic>AtMYB12</italic> gene, known to regulate flavonol biosynthesis in 
 <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, under the fruit-specific E8 promoter. The Indigo tomato was obtained, characterized by a strong increase in chlorogenic acids, flavonols and anthocyanins, with an increased total antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B199-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">199</xref>]. Finally, the 
 <italic>V. vinifera</italic> stilbene synthase gene was overexpressed in the Indigo line, and the obtained Bronze tomatoes, characterized by increased flavonols, anthocyanins and stilbenoids, alleviated inflammation bowel disease in mice [
 <xref rid="B200-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">200</xref>].
</p>
