<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">Bambara groundnut [BGN] is mainly cultivated for its seed in most rural areas in sub-Saharan Africa [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Mayes 
 <italic>et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] reported BGN as a crop that researchers have ignored despite its nutritional value. This could be attributed to less knowledge of the plant's phytochemical composition and their associated nutraceutical properties including its antimicrobial and antioxidant potentials. In sub-Saharan Africa, BGN is grown locally to sustain families by providing a source of protein, carbohydrates and nutrients (functional food) and income for households especially in rural communities [
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Bambara groundnut has been a research focus as a functional food alternative as well as characterization of its phytochemical properties since the identification of its nutritional and nutraceutical values. For example, Bambara groundnut cultivars from Zambia were reported to exhibit antioxidant potency similar to lentils, common beans and chickpeas [
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Furthermore, the presence of flavonoids, tannins and alkaloids in BGN cultivars were found in Nigeria and the alkaloids were reported to possess analgesic properties [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In addition, work done by many other researchers has shown that BGN possesses antioxidant and antimicrobial properties and are used to treat many ailments [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. However, literature is scant on the uses and potential nutraceutical and antimicrobial properties of BGN especially against plant pathogens of economic importance. Therefore, this review examined the background information on the cultivation and uses of BGN. The nutraceutical and antimicrobial properties of BGN were also considered and examined to ascertain the medicinal uses of the plant especially its antimicrobial potentials for control and management of both human and plant pathogens.
</p>
