<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Conventionally, saffron has a long history of being used as a spice and food additive [
 <xref rid="B10-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Besides its use in culinary [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and cosmetic preparation [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], saffron has been used as a folk remedy for coughs, colds, insomnia, cramps, asthma and bronchospasms, liver disease, pain, and epilepsy [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Saffron tea has been reputed to be a potential complementary treatment for psoriasis in medical nutrition therapy [
 <xref rid="B13-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Many pharmacological studies have shown that this plant and its phytochemicals have emerged as nutraceutical elements, endowed with beneficial effects on health showing antibacterial [
 <xref rid="B14-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], antioxidant, cytotoxic [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], antifungal [
 <xref rid="B17-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], immunomodulatory [
 <xref rid="B18-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], anti-mutagenic [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], aphrodisiac [
 <xref rid="B21-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], antitussives [
 <xref rid="B22-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], and antiplatelet effects [
 <xref rid="B24-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Traditional and modern biomedical reports have also proved saffron to cure coronary artery diseases [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], respiratory diseases [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], menstrual disorders [
 <xref rid="B27-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], and neurodegenerative disorders [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. All these desirable properties of saffron have been attributed to the stigmas, whereas other parts of the plant have been much less studied. Nevertheless, a large quantity of saffron by-products is produced during the stigmatization process with little commercial value but thrown away after harvesting. According to an estimate, approximately 1500 kg of leaves, 350 kg of petals, and several hundred cormlets too small for cultivation or biologically and physically damaged to be regrown are rejected to get spice of only 1 kg [
 <xref rid="B30-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. However, this biomass contains a multitude of phytochemical ingredients whose exploitation would significantly enhance the sustainability and profitability of saffron yield. These saffron based by-products need to be tested to assess its pharmacological applications.
</p>
