<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite similar abundances of individuals carrying staminate flowers (n = 19 for 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>scandens</italic> and n = 25 for 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>orbiculatus</italic>), the invasive vine had an extreme advantage in male floral production, producing hundreds more flowers per staminate plant than the native. In 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>orbiculatus</italic>, the axillary positioning of inflorescences allows flowers to form along an entire stem
 <italic>—</italic>as opposed to the terminal inflorescences in 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>scandens</italic> that are limited to the end of a stem [
 <xref rid="pone.0248635.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. An extreme advantage in flower production by invasive species compared to their native relatives seems to be a common trait of invasive plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0248635.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The 200-fold advantage for 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>orbiculatus</italic> we found in terms of male floral production (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0248635.g002">Fig 2</xref>) is similar to the average reported in a recent meta-analysis [
 <xref rid="pone.0248635.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. These authors suggest that high floral production of invasive plants allow them to avoid pollen limitation by attracting more pollinators than native species. The invasive species also had an advantage in female floral production, with 65 times more flowers per pistillate plant. Both species had similar rates of fertilization and fruit development in this study, and 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>orbiculatus</italic> was found to have greater seed germination rates in other studies [
 <xref rid="pone.0248635.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248635.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Thus, we also have evidence of a large advantage in female fecundity for the invasive vine. For 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>orbiculatus</italic>, fruit set decreased in pistillate plants with greater total output, where the strongest predictor of fruit development was a negative association with total floral production (
 <xref rid="pone.0248635.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). This may indicate that 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>orbiculatus</italic> experiences resource limitation at our study site.
</p>
