<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1-foods-06-00063" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Garlic (
  <span class="italic">Allium sativum</span> L., Amaryllidaceae) likely originated in Central Asia [
  <a rid="B1-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-foods-06-00063">1</a>]. The plant has been used as a flavoring agent and a traditional medicine since antiquity, and is now cultivated worldwide [
  <a rid="B1-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-foods-06-00063">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-foods-06-00063">2</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">Allium vineale</span> L. (wild garlic, crow garlic) is native to Great Britain, most of Europe, North Africa, and the Middle East. The plant has been introduced to North America, Australia, and New Zealand [
  <a rid="B3-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-foods-06-00063">3</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Allium sativum</span> has been used as a diaphoretic, diuretic, expectorant, and stimulant [
  <a rid="B4-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-foods-06-00063">4</a>]. Extracts of 
  <span class="italic">A. sativum</span> have shown broad-spectrum antibacterial [
  <a rid="B5-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-foods-06-00063">5</a>] and antifungal [
  <a rid="B6-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-foods-06-00063">6</a>] activity and the plant has been used to treat tuberculosis, coughs, and colds [
  <a rid="B7-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-foods-06-00063">7</a>]. Garlic preparations have demonstrated hypotensive activity in moderately hypertensive subjects, and garlic-based phytotherapeutic products are used in France for minor vascular disorders [
  <a rid="B8-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-foods-06-00063">8</a>]. There is an inverse correlation between regular consumption of garlic and stomach cancer frequency [
  <a rid="B8-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-foods-06-00063">8</a>], but there seems to be no correlation between garlic consumption and other cancers. Garlic has been used in food preparation not only for its flavor, but also as a digestive aid [
  <a rid="B4-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-foods-06-00063">4</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">Allium vineale</span> has been used as a substitute for 
  <span class="italic">A. sativum</span> in cooking; the bulb is used as a flavoring agent and the leaves as an addition to salad [
  <a rid="B9-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-foods-06-00063">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-foods-06-00063">10</a>]. Cherokee Native Americans used both 
  <span class="italic">A. vineale</span> and 
  <span class="italic">A. sativum</span> as carminatives, diuretics, and expectorants [
  <a rid="B11-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-foods-06-00063">11</a>,
  <a rid="B12-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-foods-06-00063">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although there have been numerous investigations on the phytochemistry of garlic (
  <span class="italic">A. sativum</span>) [
  <a rid="B1-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-foods-06-00063">1</a>,
  <a rid="B13-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-foods-06-00063">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-foods-06-00063">14</a>], the chemistry of wild garlic (
  <span class="italic">A. vineale</span>) has not been investigated, and because of the history of the uses of 
  <span class="italic">Allium</span> species as both condiments and phytopharmaceuticals, we have investigated the essential oil compositions of 
  <span class="italic">A. sativum</span> from Spain, obtained by different isolation methods, and 
  <span class="italic">A. vineale</span> growing wild in north Alabama, USA.
 </p>
</sec>
