<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-foods-06-00063" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-foods-06-00063" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Plant Material</div>
  <sec id="sec2dot1dot1-foods-06-00063" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1.1. Allium sativum</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bulbs of 
    <span class="italic">Allium sativum</span> were collected from a field in Las Pedroñeras, Spain (39°26′59″ N, 2°40′23″ W, 745 m elevation), in December 2015. Garlic bulbs were finely chopped, and were subjected to three different distillation methods: laboratory hydrodistillation using a Clevenger apparatus for 3 h, industrial hydrodistillation for 4 h, and industrial steam distillation for 5 h. Pale yellow essential oils were obtained in 0.2%, 0.22% and 0.18% yields, respectively. The obtained essential oils and hydrosol were separated by decantation; remaining water was removed from the essential oils with sodium chloride. The collected essential oil samples were stored under refrigeration (−4 °C) until analysis.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot1dot2-foods-06-00063" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1.2. Allium vineale</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Four different samples of 
    <span class="italic">Allium vineale</span> were collected from a field in Huntsville, Alabama (34°38′46″ N, 86°33′27″ W, 191 m elevation) on 10 April 2017, 8 a.m. Each sample was cleaned of debris, the entire plant (leaves and bulbs) chopped, and hydrodistilled using a Likens-Nickerson apparatus for 4 h with continuous extraction with dichloromethane (CH
    <sub>2</sub>Cl
    <sub>2</sub>). Evaporation of the dichloromethane yielded pale yellow essential oils with an extremely pungent odor (
    <a ref-type="table" rid="foods-06-00063-t001" href="#foods-06-00063-t001">Table 1</a>).
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-foods-06-00063" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry (GC-MS)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC-MS characterization of 
   <span class="italic">A. sativum</span> oils was carried out as previously described using a Shimadzu GCMS-QP2010 Ultra (Shimadzu Scientific Instruments, Columbia, MD, USA) [
   <a rid="B15-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-foods-06-00063">15</a>,
   <a rid="B16-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-foods-06-00063">16</a>]. This instrument was operated in the electron impact (EI) mode set at electron energy 70 eV with a scan range of 40–400 amu, a scan rate of 3.0 scans per second, and with GC-MS solution software. A ZB-5 fused silica capillary column (Phenomenex, Torrance, CA, USA), 30 m length × 0.25 mm inner diameter, with a (5% phenyl)-polymethylsiloxane stationary phase and a film thickness of 0.25 μm was used as the GC column. Helium was used as the carrier gas and the pressure was set at 551.6 kPa with a flow rate of 1.37 mL/min on the column head. The temperature of the injector was set at 250 °C and the temperature of the ion source was set at 200 °C. The temperature of the GC oven was programmed to be 50 °C initially and was programmed to increase at a rate of 2 °C/min to a final temperature of 260 °C. The samples were prepared with CH
   <sub>2</sub>Cl
   <sub>2</sub> in a 5% 
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">v</span> solution. Then, 0.1 µL of the solutions were injected into the instrument with a split ratio of 30:1.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC-MS analysis of 
   <span class="italic">A. vineale</span> oils was carried out as previously described [
   <a rid="B17-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-foods-06-00063">17</a>]: Agilent 6890 GC (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA), Agilent 5973 mass selective detector (Agilent Technologies), EI mode (70 eV), 40–400 mass scan range, 3.99 scans/s scan rate, and operated through an Agilent ChemStation data system (G1701CA, Agilent Technologies); HP-5ms capillary column (30 m length × 0.25 mm inner diameter × 0.25 μm film thickness), helium carrier gas, head pressure (92.4 kPa), flow rate (1.5 mL/min); oven temperature program (60 °C initial temperature, which was held for 5 min, temperature increased at a rate of 3 °C/min up to 280 °C), inlet temperature (250 °C), interface temperature (280 °C). 
   <span class="italic">Allium vineale</span> solutions (1 μL of 1% in CH
   <sub>2</sub>Cl
   <sub>2</sub>) were injected using a splitless mode.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The retention indices were determined by reference to a homologous series of 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes. The components of each essential oil sample were identified based on their retention indices and mass spectral fragmentation patterns compared to reference literature [
   <a rid="B18-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-foods-06-00063">18</a>,
   <a rid="B19-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-foods-06-00063">19</a>,
   <a rid="B20-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-foods-06-00063">20</a>,
   <a rid="B21-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-foods-06-00063">21</a>,
   <a rid="B22-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-foods-06-00063">22</a>] and our in-house library.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-foods-06-00063" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Semi-Quantitative Gas Chromatography</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Semi-quantitative GC was performed with an Agilent 6890 GC with Agilent FID (flame ionization detector) (Agilent Technologies), HP-5ms column (30 m length × 0.25 mm inner diameter × 0.25 μm film thickness), He carrier gas, head pressure (144.1 kPa), flow rate (2.0 mL/min); oven temperature program (as above). The percent compositions of the essential oils were determined from raw peak area percentages without standardization.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot4-foods-06-00063" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Hierarchical Cluster Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chemical compositions of 
   <span class="italic">A. sativum</span> from this current study along with garlic oil compositions from previously published works (hydrodistillations and steam distillations only) [
   <a rid="B6-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-foods-06-00063">6</a>,
   <a rid="B23-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-foods-06-00063">23</a>,
   <a rid="B24-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-foods-06-00063">24</a>,
   <a rid="B25-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-foods-06-00063">25</a>,
   <a rid="B26-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-foods-06-00063">26</a>,
   <a rid="B27-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-foods-06-00063">27</a>,
   <a rid="B28-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-foods-06-00063">28</a>,
   <a rid="B29-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-foods-06-00063">29</a>,
   <a rid="B30-foods-06-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-foods-06-00063">30</a>] were used as operational taxonomic units (OTUs). The percentages of the major sulfur-containing compounds (diallyl sulfide, allyl methyl disulfide, dimethyl trisulfide, diallyl disulfide, allyl (
   <span class="italic">Z</span>)-1-propenyl disulfide, allyl (
   <span class="italic">E</span>)-1-propenyl disulfide, allyl methyl trisulfide, 2-vinyl-4
   <span class="italic">H</span>-1,3-dithiine, diallyl trisulfide, and diallyl tetrasulfide) were used to evaluate the chemical similarities and differences between the garlic oil samples by agglomerative hierarchical cluster (AHC) analysis using the XLSTAT software, version 2015.4.01 (Addinsoft™, New York, NY, USA). Pearson correlation was used to evaluate similarity and clusters were defined by the unweighted pair-group method with arithmetic averaging (UPGMA). 
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
