<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many works have supported the antibacterial, antifungal and antiviral properties of tannins [
 <xref rid="B10-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. For example, walnut leaves have been approved for the topical treatment of mild skin inflammation, due to their anti-inflammatory and antimicrobial activities. An ethanolic extract of immature 
 <italic>J. regia</italic> fruits was able to inhibit methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> (MRSA) growth when administrated in a concentration range of 128–512 μg/mL. At 16 μg/mL, the extract reduced biofilm formation and adherence. Thus, this extract was suggested to be an efficient treatment for skin and soft tissue infection processes [
 <xref rid="B87-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Similarly, extracts obtained from 
 <italic>S. brasiliensis</italic> have shown antimicrobial potential against MRSA [
 <xref rid="B88-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. A very recent work performed transcriptome and metabolome data analysis to find the mechanism of action of tannins from 
 <italic>Diospyros kaki</italic> against MRSA. The results suggest that some main mechanisms are related to physical damage of the bacterial cell membrane [
 <xref rid="B89-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. Tannins obtained from 
 <italic>A. mearnsii</italic> were evaluated as antibacterial agents, both as free and encapsulated molecules. Free tannins showed antibacterial activity, especially against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, with MBC (Minimum Bactericidal Concentration) of 0.32 and 1.25 of mg/mL. They also acted against fungal (
 <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic>, MIC (Minimum Inhibitory Concentration) 0.62 mg/mL) and yeast (
 <italic>Candida</italic> sp., MIC 2.5 mg/mL) growth. The most efficient antimicrobial encapsulated showed IZs for 
 <italic>S. aureus, Escherichia coli, A. niger</italic> and 
 <italic>Candida</italic> sp, which were larger of those observed with the free tannins, except for 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B34-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].
</p>
