<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0008">Pandemic diseases are of global concern in the present era, to cause gigantic morbidity and transience, regardless of, extensive medical facilities. Particularly, anti-viral therapies have been fraught because of surfacing of mutants competent enough to subdue the drugs targeting viral elements (
 <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 2020a</xref>). Most importantly, enhanced universal travel and swift urbanization has led to contagious outbreak by rising or re-emergence of viruses, posing a serious menace towards communal health and safety, specifically in such unprecedented times where there are no preventive vaccines available. With the advent of twenty first century, our planet has observed the incidence of catastrophic viral outbreaks namely, SARS-CoV (Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome) and MERS-CoV (Middle East Respiratory Syndrome) within human populace (
 <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">Markotić and Kuzman, 2020</xref>). At present, COVID-19 (Coronavirus) is the third most important disease of animal origin, which is prevailing in almost four corners of the world by getting initiated from a single place. Nearly, 213 countries of all continents have been affected in less than three months by this pernicious virus (
 <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Acharya, 2020</xref>). After studying its clinical characteristics, experts affirmed that it is quite similar to pneumonia and therefore, named as Novel Coronavirus. However, in the second week of March, 2020, COVID-19 was stated as pandemic by World Health Organisation (WHO) (
 <xref rid="bib0057" ref-type="bibr">Gautret et al., 2020</xref>). As of August, 24
 <sup>th</sup>, 2020, there have been reported 23,584,259 COVID-19 cases with 812,517 deaths globally as depicted by WHO (WHO, 2020). The causal agent of COVID-19 is SARS-CoV-2 (Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus-2) as per officially named by ICTV (International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses) (
 <xref rid="bib0057" ref-type="bibr">Gautret et al., 2020</xref>). After incessant investigations, it has been acquired that SARS-CoV resembles sequence homology with bat coronavirus. Though, its spike glycoproteins have highest affinity for human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptors, that enable them to invade and transmit through human to human (
 <xref rid="bib0072" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2020</xref>). Even though it shares resemblance with SARS-CoV, yet its spreading ability and diagnosis is relatively different. The distinctive feature is most likely the nucleotide pattern of spike proteins along with its receptor binding domains (
 <xref rid="bib0242" ref-type="bibr">Wan et al., 2020</xref>). Moreover, belonging to the category of β-coronaviruses, a highly prevalent virus family in nature, it has several hosts, natural, intermediate as well as final. Henceforth, it is a colossal issue to prevent and cure the outbreak of this viral infection owing to its greater transmitting and infecting power.
</p>
