<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One of our previous studies also confirmed the presence of tannins, phenolic compounds, cardiac glycosides, flavonoids, alkaloids, and saponins in both 
 <italic>E. divaricata</italic> and 
 <italic>V. zizanioides</italic> plant extracts [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Dos Santos et al. reported that 
 <italic>β</italic>-vetivenene, khusimol, vetiselinenol, isovalencenol, vetivenic acid, 
 <italic>α</italic>-vetivone, and 
 <italic>β</italic>-vetivone are the major constituents of dichloromethane fraction of 
 <italic>Vetiveria zizanioides</italic> [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Antimicrobial activity of plant phenolics including flavonoids has also been documented in the past [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. As evident from the abovementioned studies, active compounds isolated from medicinal plants have a significant potential to alleviate the symptoms associated with skin infections. Composition of active compounds in these plants could vary from one country to another due to different geographical and environmental conditions. Antimicrobial activities could be enhanced if the active compounds of the species under study that were collected from Sri Lanka are purified [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Therefore, further investigations which involve fractionation, purification, and identification of active compounds are necessary to develop these two plants as potential therapeutic agents in the future. Previous studies conducted in our laboratory reported the absence of any toxicological effects (biochemical, haematological, and histopathological) in ICR mice when treated with water extracts of 
 <italic>E. divaricata</italic> and 
 <italic>V. zizanioides</italic> [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. However, toxicological studies on hexane and ethanol extracts have not been conducted yet. To develop potential therapeutics with anti-MRSA properties from these plant extracts, the toxicity of active compounds and their pharmacokinetics should be investigated. 
 <italic>In vivo</italic> studies including clinical trials are necessary to confirm the efficacy of active compounds.
</p>
