<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The rationale of study is based on facts that the area under research is mostly mountainous and has many hilly terrains populated by different ethnic groups with specific biocultural paradigm. These indigenous people of the area depend on local plants for their life sustenance and traditional medicines to treat various diseases. The practise of use of herbal or green medicines (GMs) is also well promulgated in different areas of the world. The people of the study area prefer to use TEMs due to cost-effective, accessible, safe and affordable to prepare in home [
 <xref rid="pone.0243151.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0243151.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. It is known that approximately 85% traditional medicines used around the globe are botanic in origin prepared from one or more plants species according to folklore recipes [
 <xref rid="pone.0243151.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Hence, it is envisaged that MPs are the indigenous phytoheritage or bioheritage and nearly 50, 000 plant species are known for their use in TEMs in different traditional medicine systems of the world [
 <xref rid="pone.0243151.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0243151.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Currently, research on traditional herbal medicines is gaining great attention of the world scientific community and in Pakistan many researchers have been working on TEMs of local plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0243151.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0243151.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In AJK territory, sporadic research work on TEMs of plant origin have been reported in different ethnobotanical articles [
 <xref rid="pone.0243151.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0243151.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and on District Bhimber few researchers have conducted the descriptive EB research work [
 <xref rid="pone.0243151.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0243151.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] while hitherto no comprehensive quantitative ethnobotanical research has been conducted on this study area. The present study is focused on documentation of traditional knowledge of indigenous communities of Tehsil Samahni on wild MPs of the area. The purpose of the research was aimed to: (i) to explore and document traditional knowledge of local inhabitants of rural areas about use of wild plants in traditional ethnomedicines (TEMs), (ii) to collect and compile the data of TEMs along with mode of preparation, use-form, parts used, folklore recipes used by local herbalists, (iii) to authenticate the data of TEMs by using quantitative tools like RPL, ROP, ICF, UVI, FL and RFC in order to explore the most prevalently used species in TEMs and to recommend it for further ethnopharmacological screening for drug discovery and development and (iv) to give recommendations for conservation of wild medicinal plants endemic in the area.
</p>
