<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variability in oils composition</div>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The multivariate analysis of PCA (Principal Component Analysis) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>) and HCA (Hierarchical Cluster Analysis) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>) were applied to the primary constituents present in oils (content ≥ 5.0%), for the evaluation of chemical variability among the 
  <span class="italic">P. guineense</span> specimens.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Dendrogram representing the similarity relation in the oils composition of
     <span class="italic"> P. guineense</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13065_2018_428_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Biplot (PCA) resulting from the analysis of the oils of
     <span class="italic"> P. guineense</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13065_2018_428_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The HCA analysis performed with complete binding and Euclidean distance showed the formation of three different groups. These were confirmed by the PCA analysis, which accounted for 79.5% of the data variance. The three groups were classified as:</p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Group I</span> Characterized by the presence of the monoterpenes α-pinene (13.4-35.6%) and limonene (3,7-37,2%), composed by the specimens PG-01 to PG-06, collected in Curuçá (PG -01 to PG-05) and Santarém (PG-06), Pará state, Brazil, with 49.2% similarity between the samples.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Group II</span> Characterized by the presence of the sesquiterpenes β-bisabolene (4.0-8.9%) and epi-β-bisabolol (6.5-18.1%), consisting by PG-07 to PG-10 specimens collected in Monte Alegre (PG-07 and PG-08) and Santarém (PG-09 and PG-10), Pará State, Brazil, with 50.3% similarity between samples.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Group III</span> Characterized by the presence of a significant content of β-caryophyllene (24.0%) and caryophyllene oxide (14.1%), constituted by the PG-12 specimen, collected in the city of Ponta de Pedras, Pará state, Brazil, which presented zero% similarity with the other groups.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus, based on the study of these essential oils, the multivariate analysis (PCA and HCA) has suggested the existence of three chemical types among the twelve specimens of 
  <span class="italic">P. guineense</span> collected in different locations of the Brazilian Amazon. It would then be the chemical types α-pinene/limonene (Group I), β-bisabolene/
  <span class="italic">epi</span>-β-bisabolol (Group II) and β-caryophyllene/caryophyllene oxide (Group III). Taking into account that two essential oils with a predominance of α-pinene/limonene and β-bisabolene/
  <span class="italic">epi</span>-β-bisabolol, respectively, were previously described [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>], it is understood that adding these two chemical types to that one rich in β-caryophyllene + caryophyllene oxide, which was a product of this study, besides the other chemical type with a high value of spathulenol, before reported by Nascimento and colleagues (2018) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>], will be now, at least, four chemical types known for the 
  <span class="italic">P. guineense</span> essential oils.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several studies have demonstrated the anti-inflammatory activities of limonene, α-pinene and β-caryophyllene, the primary constituents found in the oils of 
  <span class="italic">P. guineense</span> presented in this paper. Limonene showed significant anti-inflammatory effects both in vivo and in vitro, suggesting a beneficial role as a diet supplement in reducing inflammation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>]; limonene decreased the infiltration of peritoneal exudate leukocytes and reduced the number of polymorphonuclear leukocytes, in the induced peritonitis [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. α-Pinene presented anti-inflammatory effects in human chondrocytes, exhibiting potential anti-osteoarthritic activity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>], and in mouse peritoneal macrophages induced by lipopolysaccharides [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>], being, therefore, a potential source for the pharmaceutical industry. The anti-arthritic and the in vivo anti-inflammatory activities of β-caryophyllene was evaluated by molecular imaging [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
