<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We saw that SOC-poor origin populations experienced greater differences in chlorophyll content due to irrigation/drought than their SOC-rich origin counterparts. This suggests that habitats with higher nutrient availability may release plants from stresses limiting chlorophyll production, and this is less impacted by drought than in plants from low-SOC habitats. We saw that the irrigation treatment’s interaction with SOC in home habitat mirrored its interaction with the fertilization treatment. In the latter case, the impacts of nutrient limitation were significantly lowered by irrigation. Had we been able to grow the ‘− fertilizer’ plants in nutrient-free media, it is more than likely that this relationship would have been conserved, if not strengthened. Considering that agricultural populations increase chlorophyll content with the home SOC gradient, while non-agricultural populations do not, there may be a parallel between drought response and ecotypic adaptation. Specifically, we saw that, with increasing home SOC, unirrigated and agricultural populations produce more chlorophyll, while the chlorophyll content of irrigated or non-agricultural populations does not change. While we did not find a direct interaction between ecotype identity and the irrigation treatment, the combination of our findings suggests it. Speculatively, the agricultural ecotype’s response to home SOC may reflect higher stress due to less drought adaptation. Meanwhile, the non-agricultural ecotype shows similar unresponsiveness to home SOC as all unirrigated populations—a condition to which it may be adapted. The interactive effect of irrigation and fertilization on chlorophyll content has been seen in wheat (
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Dimkpa 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2020
 </xref>), while in 
 <italic>S. bicolor</italic> it may be mediated by microbes aiding in phosphorus acquisition (
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Kour 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2020
 </xref>). Others have found instances of wild and cultivated ecotypes with differentially adapted nutrient uptake and chlorophyll production (
 <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Papafilippaki and Nikolaidis 2020</xref>). 
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Kausar and Gull (2019)</xref> found some genotypes of 
 <italic>S. bicolor</italic> to be more tolerant of salinity stress (which inhibited normal nutrient uptake) than others. In fact, much of the research that compares plant ecotypic differences in chlorophyll content does so in the context of tolerance to polluted soils and their phytoremediation (
 <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Park 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Alirzayeva 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2017
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Liu 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2019
 </xref>). Our comparison of home habitat and ecotype identity as drivers of adaptation is novel; however, our approach yielded results similar to others that found ecotypic differences in experimental stress response.
</p>
