<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In recent years, there has been a growing appreciation for the ability of the gut microbiota to produce neurochemicals that can influence the peripheral enteric and central nervous systems [
 <xref rid="B103-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>]. For example, gamma amino butyric acid (GABA) is a major inhibitory neurotransmitter in the brain [
 <xref rid="B104-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>] and neuropsychiatric disorders, including anxiety and depression have been linked to GABA system dysfunction [
 <xref rid="B105-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>]. Strains of culturable lactobacilli and bifidobacteria from the human intestine were shown to produce GABA, namely 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus brevis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Bifidobacterium dentium</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">adolescentis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">infantis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B106-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>]. Furthermore, GABA was found to serve as a growth factor for a previously uncultured gut bacterium, 
 <italic class="italic">Flavonifractor sp.</italic> which was shown to ferment GABA [
 <xref rid="B107-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">107</xref>]. In the same study, the authors identified several gut bacteria capable of producing GABA which included 
 <italic class="italic">Bacteroides</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Dorea</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Parabacteroides</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Alistipes</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ruminococcus</italic> species. More recently, a co-culture experiment revealed that GABA produced by 
 <italic class="italic">Bacteroides fragilis</italic> was essential for the growth of a gut isolate termed KLE1738 which is believed to be an unreported bacterial genus [
 <xref rid="B108-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">108</xref>]. This led to the isolation of a variety of GABA-producing bacteria and the 
 <italic class="italic">Bacteriodes</italic> species in particular were found to produce large quantities of GABA. Furthermore, in the same study relative abundance levels of faecal 
 <italic class="italic">Bacteriodes</italic> negatively correlated with brain signatures associated with depression in patients with major depressive disorder. Bacterially-produced GABA is generated by the enzyme glutamate decarboxylase (GAD) which catalyzes the irreversible α-decarboxylation of glutamate to GABA and is believed to protect the microorganism against stomach acidity [
 <xref rid="B109-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">109</xref>]. GAD is also found in higher plants and animals [
 <xref rid="B110-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">110</xref>]. Interestingly, daily consumption of a GABA-producing 
 <italic class="italic">Bif. dentium</italic> gut isolate was found to modulate sensory neuron activity in a rat faecal retention model of visceral hypersensitivity revealing that bacterially-produced GABA can modulate abdominal pain [
 <xref rid="B111-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>]. GABA-enriched black soybean milk fermented with a GABA-producing fish gut isolate, 
 <italic class="italic">L. brevis</italic>, generated similar antidepressant activity in rats as the common antidepressant drug, fluoxetine, but without the side effects normally associated with the drug, such as appetite loss and reduced body weight [
 <xref rid="B112-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>]. 
</p>
