<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Serotonin (5-hydroxytryptamine, 5-HT) is a brain neurotransmitter and performs regulatory functions in the gut and other organ systems [
 <xref rid="B113-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>]. It is derived from the amino acid tryptophan and plays an important role in the regulation of mood [
 <xref rid="B114-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>] such that several antidepressants act on serotonin transporters in the brain [
 <xref rid="B115-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>]. Yano et al. [
 <xref rid="B113-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>] demonstrated that human- and mouse-derived gut bacteria promote serotonin biosynthesis in colonic enterochromaffin cells which supply serotonin to the lumen, mucosa and circulating platelets. Spore forming bacteria, dominated by clostridial species, were found to elicit this effect. Furthermore, conventional mice were found to have 2.8 times more plasma serotonin levels than their germ-free counterparts [
 <xref rid="B116-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>]. This peripherally produced molecule does not pass the blood brain barrier under physiological conditions [
 <xref rid="B117-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">117</xref>] but is an important signalling molecule in the gut involved in peristalsis, secretion, vasodilation, pain perception and nausea, as well as promoting inflammation and being involved in neuron development and maintenance in the enteric nervous system, while platelet serotonin derived from the gut influences bone development amongst other functions [
 <xref rid="B118-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">119</xref>]. The mechanisms involved in gut microbiota-mediated serotonin biosynthesis have not yet been fully elucidated but are thought to be linked to microbial metabolite-stimulation of the enzyme tryptophan hydroxylase 1 in enterochromaffin cells which produces a serotonin precursor that is subsequently metabolised to serotonin [
 <xref rid="B113-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>]. In particular, rectal injection with the microbial metabolites deoxycholate, p-aminobenzoate, α-tocopherol and tyramine, were shown to increase colonic and serum concentrations of serotonin in mice [
 <xref rid="B113-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>].
</p>
