<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Sage (
 <italic>Salvia officinalis</italic>) belong to the Lamiaceae family. Sage is a perennial shrub, an aromatic and remedial plant endemic in the Mediterranean region [
 <xref rid="B79-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. According to Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry (GC-MS) analysis, the main detected compounds were oxygenated monoterpenes followed monohydrocarbone, squiterpenes, and others. The main essential oil constituents were α-terpineol (33.07%), camphor (11.57%), α-pinene (8.96%) camphene (5.09%) β-cymene (5.40%) caryphyllene (3.76%) β-myrcene (3.65%) β-menthen-1-ol (3.45%) and bomeol (3.38%) [
 <xref rid="B80-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Several in vivo and in vitro studies have investigated the activity of polyphenols as sage tea active ingredients that may prevent lipid peroxidation and augment antioxidant defense mechanisms [
 <xref rid="B81-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Daily drinking of sage in both mice and rat causes significant increase in the liver antioxidant enzyme glutathione-S-trans- ferase (GST) activity [
 <xref rid="B82-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Similar effect was observed when rat hepatocytes (isolated from the livers of sage drinking rats) showed an increase in glutathione (GSH) level and GST activity. Also, the treatment of rats with water extracts of sage for five weeks protected rat hepatocytes against azathioprine toxicity [
 <xref rid="B83-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. It is important to note that the method of extraction affects the antioxidant activity. The highest antioxidant activities of sage were discovered in the methanolic extract, followed by water infusion and decoction [
 <xref rid="B84-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. The hydroalcoholic extract of sage exhibited high antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B85-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. For example, earlier study has shown that the hydroalcoholic extract of sage has hepatoprotective action against isoniazid-induced hepatic damage in rats. This activity may be attributed to free radical-scavenging, and antioxidant activities of flavonoids in the extract [
 <xref rid="B86-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Furthermore, many diterpenes, isolated from plants of several species of the genus Salvia, have been demonstrated to have interesting antitumor activity [
 <xref rid="B87-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. S. officinalis essential oil inhibited human HNSCC cell by activating different anticancer mechanisms [
 <xref rid="B88-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>].
</p>
