<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cold stress parameters were based on the results of recovery of chlamydospores (an asexual survival structure) at extreme cold temperatures 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Tooley1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Turner1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. Tooley et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Tooley1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref> observed reduced recovery of free chlamydospores after exposure to temperatures of 0°C for 24 hours and little or no recovery at −10°C and −20°C, while Turner et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Turner1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref> found they were able to survive at −2°C for up to four hours in the laboratory. Hyphal colonies on the other hand have been shown to have no reduction in recovery after exposure to −5°C for 24 hours, but reductions at or below −10°C 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Browning1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. Despite the direct effects of cold on the pathogen, chlamydospores were able to survive at least one week in infected leaf tissue after exposure to a continuous −10°C, indicating that survival in infected plant tissue provides a more robust method of pathogen survival during cold periods 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Tooley1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. Turner et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Turner1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref> also found that chlamydospores inside infected leaf tissue were able to survive mild winters with minimum temperatures of −9°C over 16 weeks under field conditions in the UK. At least 50% of chlamydospores survived for 16 weeks in the study by Turner et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Turner1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, with 80% chlamydospore survival in leaves buried 5 cm beneath the soil surface. In CLIMEX, the threshold cold stress due to damaging cold temperatures (TTCS) was set to begin accumulating at −8°C, at a slow enough rate (THCS = .−0.02 week
 <sup>−1</sup>) to allow for survival for at least two months at −10°C. This accumulation rate was chosen to incorporate survival in the coldest location where the pathogen is known to survive winter, in naturally infected nursery plants kept outside in the south of Finland (A. Rytkőnen, Finnish Forest Research Institute, pers. comm.)
</p>
