<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> spp. have immense ability to degrade plant biomass, and thus are ecologically significant for releasing sequestered organic C into the carbon cycle. Previous comparative genomic studies on 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> highlighted plant cell wall degrading enzyme repertoires reminiscent of white-rot fungi [
 <xref rid="B15-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], with a characteristic enrichment of pectinolytic genes [
 <xref rid="B17-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Accordingly, recent studies treated 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> spp. as white-rot based on the presence of LDE encoding genes in their genomes [
 <xref rid="B15-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. However, previous studies have also shown that 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> species primarily decay the cellulose, hemicellulose, and pectin components of the plant cell wall, and leave lignin unattacked during early stages of decay [
 <xref rid="B22-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Chemical and microscopic analyses of wood decay by 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> produced contradictory results. 
 <italic>A. mellea</italic> was classified as Group II white-rot fungi which attack celluloses and pentosans at early stages and lignin remains unaffected [
 <xref rid="B23-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Others reported a type-I soft-rot decay where the fungal hyphae grow through the secondary cell wall layer, producing characteristic cavities in the tracheids, axial, and xylem ray parenchyma cells [
 <xref rid="B22-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Soft-rot fungi by definition are now restricted to Ascomycota [
 <xref rid="B24-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]; however, there are many Agaricomycetes that produce symptoms resembling soft rot or that do not fit the traditional white rot/brown rot dichotomy [
 <xref rid="B7-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Soft rot was suggested in 
 <italic>Cylindrobasidium</italic> spp., a close relative of 
 <italic>Armillaria,</italic> that also has a lower number of LDEs than typical white-rot decayers [
 <xref rid="B17-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-microorganisms-09-00149" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. 
</p>
