<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Obviously, there are no absolute medications to reverse neuronal and synaptic destruction in AD (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>), and currently approved drugs only alleviate clinical symptoms. The routine drugs for AD are cholinesterase inhibitors (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>), NMDA receptor antagonists (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>), and anti-oxidant and anti-inflammatory agents (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). These chemical synthetic drugs have various adverse effects such as nausea, diarrhea, bradycardia, and hepatotoxicity (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Cholinesterase inhibitors such as tacrine, donepezil, galantamine, and rivastigmine are able to inhibit AChE, increase ACh concentration, and improve cognitive function (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Memantine, as a glutamate receptor antagonist, reduces Aβ deposition and disaggregates Aβ fibrils and thus, prevents neurotoxic effects. It also reduces neuronal cell death via Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> influx regulation (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). Anti-oxidant agents such as glutathione, ascorbic acid, and ubiquinone scavenge free radicals and chelate metal ions, as well as preventing cell damage by ROS neutralization (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). NSAIDs such as ibuprofen have a protective effect against the incidence of AD (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). Also, ladostigil is a chemical neuroprotective, anti-inflammatory, and neurogenesis inducing agent that is able to slow down the progression of mild cognitive impairment to AD (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>). Interestingly, in addition to synthetic drugs, current knowledge recommends the use of micronutrients (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>), supplements (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>-
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>), and herbal medicines to relieve AD symptoms.
</p>
