<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The molecular identification of the fungi was carried out by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using oligonucleotides specific for the ITS regions of rDNA. The extraction and quantification of DNA was performed according to the method of Raeder and Broda [
 <xref rid="B17-plants-10-00852" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The fungal DNA was purified using The Wizard
 <sup>®</sup> Genomic DNA Purification Kit (A1120, Promega Corp., Madison, WI, USA). The PCR was performed using the primers ITS1-Fwd (5′-TCCGTAGGTGAACCTGCGG-3′) and ITS4-REV (5′-TCCTCCGCTTATTATTGATATGC-3′). PCR reactions were performed in a final volume of 25 µL using the GoTaq
 <sup>®</sup> Green Master Mix kit (M7122, Promega Corp. Madison, WI, USA) 1 X; 5 µM of the primer ITS1-Fwd primer; 5 µM of ITS4-Rev; and 25 ng of genomic DNA. Amplification was performed in a C1000 thermal cycler (Bio-Rad
 <sup>®</sup>, Germany) under the following conditions: initial denaturation at 94 °C for 5 min, followed by 35 cycles of denaturation at 95 °C for 30 s, 58 °C for 30 s, 72 °C for 1 min and a final extension at 72 °C for 7 min. The PCR products were separated by agarose gel electrophoresis (2%) at 80 V for 40 min, and visualized using SYBR Gold
 <sup>®</sup> (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). DNA fragments of 700 bp were selected for purification with ExoSAP-IT
 <sup>®</sup> (N/P 78200, USB Affymetrix, Inc., Cleveland, OH, USA). The purified fragments were sequenced using primer ITS1-Forward (5′-TCCGTAGGTGAACCTGCGG-3′) and ITS4-Rev (5′-TCCTCCGCTTATTATTGATATGC-3′) with the ABI PRISM BigDye
 <sup>®</sup> Terminator sequencing kit v3.1 (P/N 4336917, Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). Fragment analysis was conducted in a Genetic Analyzer 3130 sequencer (Applied Biosystems
 <sup>®</sup>, HITACHI Tokyo, Japan). The sequences were assembled using SeqMan software 8 (LaserGene) (DNASTAR
 <sup>®</sup>, Madison, WI, USA) and analyzed using the GenBank database (
 <uri xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.gov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.ncbi.nlm.gov</uri> accessed on 8 May 2014).
</p>
