<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In 
 <italic>M. oryzae</italic>, MAGGY retrotransposons are activated by heat shock and oxidative stress along with up-regulation of MAGGY RNA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>] and an EST matching to a non-LTR-retrotransposon was identified in an 
 <italic>M. oryzae-</italic>infected rice leaf library [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. Similarly, our results revealed a spike in sRNAs associated with an LTR class during oxidative stress. Several ESTs matching to LTR-retrotransposons have also been identified in the 
 <italic>in planta</italic> stage of the wheat fungal pathogen, 
 <italic>Mycosphaerella graminicola</italic>, and are less abundant compared to their mycelial stage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>]. Similarly, our data revealed that distinct sRNAs reads matching to repeats in 
 <italic>in planta</italic> growth were ~10% higher than in the mycelial libraries (Additional file 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>: Figure S5A and B). Reactivation of transposable elements during stress conditions have been found in many organisms from fission yeast to plants and animals (reviewed in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>]). Recently, a widely-studied tobacco transposon called 
 <italic>TNT1</italic> was found to be reactivated during infection of tobacco [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>]. While we did see an increase in sRNAs associated with LTR/Gypsy retrotransposons during nitrogen starvation compared to the non-stressed condition, overall, there was not a striking difference in these types of associations in the case of the LINE/Tad1 class of retrotransposon, where sRNA abundance was not markedly different in the stress versus non-stressed conditions. Together, our data and the wealth of information on transposon-associated small RNAs in other organisms suggest that retrotransposons might be suppressed via epigenetic mechanisms. Additional testing will be required to determine what underlies the increase in sRNAs associated with LTR elements during nitrogen starvation.
</p>
