<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As fish oil has been our main source of EPA and DHA up until now, the above question may appear the obvious one to ask, however, not without some further explanation. The use of the word “alternatives” was deliberate as these products should be regarded as options to “supplement”, and not simply “replace” existing fish oil supplies. This is not a matter of semantics, while fish oil is undoubtedly finite on an annual/seasonal basis and, therefore, limited, it is not necessarily an inherently “unsustainable” product. Like all fisheries globally, if the fisheries supplying fishmeal and fish oil are managed effectively through regulation and control, and many are, there can be a sustainable harvest of this valuable commodity and there is no sense in not utilising this [
 <xref rid="B65-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. This is supported by the fact that the conversion ratio in the wild is around 10 kg of prey to 1 kg of food fish, whereas aquaculture is far more efficient and productive [
 <xref rid="B66-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]. Furthermore, harvesting fish higher in the marine food web, such as cod, was shown to be far less efficient in providing marine nutrients for human consumption compared to harvesting lower trophic level species such as capelin (on which cod predate) and producing meal and oil for salmon production [
 <xref rid="B67-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>]. Thus, high trophic level predators may require many times more marine resources than lower trophic level fish, such as menhaden or anchovy used for reduction [
 <xref rid="B65-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>] and, hence, the importance of taking primary productivity into account when comparing the eco-efficiency of reduction fishing with fishing of higher trophic species for direct human consumption. 
</p>
