<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The introduction of a fluorine atom into a biologically active compound can have a significant influence on its properties. One or more incorporated fluorine atoms can alter the electrostatic and hydrogen bonding parameters of the molecule as well as its physicochemical and pharmacokinetic properties [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Currently, fluorine-containing substituents, which are commonly encountered in commercial pharmaceuticals and agrochemicals, include fluoroaromatic, trifluoromethyl (CF
 <sub>3</sub>), trifluoromethoxy (OCF
 <sub>3</sub>), and trifluoromethlythio (SCF
 <sub>3</sub>) functionalities [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Another fluorinated substituent that reflects the continuing development of a relatively new fluorinated building block with distinct properties could be the pentafluorosulfanyl (SF
 <sub>5</sub>) group. The SF
 <sub>5</sub> group is often called the “super-trifluoromethyl group”, and aryl sulfanyl pentafluorides display high thermal and chemical stability, electronegativity, and lipophilicity [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Due to its unique properties, the SF
 <sub>5</sub> group has widely been applied in drug discovery and crop protection research (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05536-f001">Figure 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], since the first organic pentafluorosulfanyl compound was described in 1950 [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-25-05536" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p>
