<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">This goal of this study was to highlight the importance of minerals in the diet of fish for meeting micronutrient requirements in the human diet. First arsenic, calcium, cadmium, copper, iron, molybdenum, magnesium, manganese, sodium, phosphorus, potassium, selenium, and zinc concentrations of twelve commercially available tilapia samples were measured. The nutritional value of fillets in regard to their mineral content were assessed to establish potential health benefits or risks for consumers. The health benefit value of selenium was also calculated. Positive health benefit values indicate that tilapia fillets in the United States marketplace of this study do not pose health risks associated with mercury exposures. Selenium was the trace mineral of interest. After the market study, a seven-week fish feeding trial was conducted to study the influence of organic versus inorganic dietary selenium on Nile tilapia (
  <italic class="italic">Oreochromis niloticus</italic>). Fish were fed two different diets enriched with the same concentration (0.01g kg
  <sup class="sup">-1</sup>) of selenium in form of inorganic (sodium selenite) or organic (seleno-L-methionine) selenium in triplicate groups. There were no significant differences between growth and biometrics of fish fed different diets (
  <italic class="italic">p&gt;</italic>0.05). At the end of trial twelve fish from each treatment were collected. Fillets of fish fed organic selenium had selenium concentrations of 0.55 ± 0.01 μg g
  <sup class="sup">-1</sup> which were significantly (
  <italic class="italic">p&lt;</italic>0.05) higher than fish fed inorganic selenium at levels of 0.22 ± 0.008 μg g
  <sup class="sup">-1</sup> or fish samples from the marketplace with a selenium level of 0.2 ± 0.03 μg g
  <sup class="sup">-1</sup>. Fish fed organic selenium also had significantly higher (
  <italic class="italic">p&lt;0</italic>.
  <italic class="italic">05</italic>) plasma and kidney selenium in comparison to fish fed inorganic selenium. No significant differences (
  <italic class="italic">p&gt;0</italic>.
  <italic class="italic">05</italic>) were observed in glutathione peroxidase activities in either the plasma or liver of Nile tilapia in the different treatment groups. This study shows that organic selenium is a better option for production of Nile tilapia fillets rich in selenium.
 </p>
</abstract>
