<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">The amplified production of fruit as well as burgeoning demand for plant-made food products have resulted in a sharp increase of waste. Currently, millions of tons of by-products are either being discarded or utilized rather ineffectively. However, these by-products may be processed and further incorporated as functional ingredients in making high-value food products with many physiological and biochemical effects. The chemical analysis of pomace oils using gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC/MS) and reversed-phase-liquid chromatography coupled with fluorescence detector (RP-HPLC/FLD) systems led to the identification and quantification of 56 individual lipophilic compounds including unsaturated, polyunsaturated and saturated fatty acids, as well as phytosterols and four homologs of tocopherol. The oils recovered from by-products of 
  <italic class="italic">Malus</italic> spp. (particularly cv. “Ola”) are rich in fatty acids such as linolenic (57.8%), α-linolenic (54.3%), and oleic (25.5%). The concentration of total tocopherols varied among the 
  <italic class="italic">Malus</italic> species and dessert apples investigated, representing the range of 16.8–30.9 mg mL
  <sup class="sup">−1</sup>. The highest content of total tocopherols was found in 
  <italic class="italic">M.</italic> Bernu prieks, followed by 
  <italic class="italic">M</italic>. cv. “Ola”, and 
  <italic class="italic">M</italic>. × 
  <italic class="italic">Soulardii</italic> pomace oils. A significantly higher amount of δ-tocopherol was established in the oil of 
  <italic class="italic">M</italic>. Bernu prieks, indicating that this species could be utilized as a natural and cheap source of bioactive molecules. β-Sitosterol was the prevalent compound determined in all tested pomace oils with a percentage distribution of 10.3–94.5%. The main triterpene identified in the oils was lupeol, which varied in the range of 0.1–66.3%. A targeted utilization of apple pomace would facilitate management of tons of by-products and benefit the environment and industry.
 </p>
</abstract>
