<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oil production has been experiencing decline in many parts of the world due to oilfield's maturity and an example of such includes the major oilfields in the North Sea [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>]. Another major concern is the increasing energy demands due to global population growth and the difficulty in discovering new oilfields as an alternative to the exploited oil fields. Therefore, there is an urge to find out alternative technologies to increase oil recovery from existing oilfields around the world. It is a fact that fossil fuels will still remain the key source of energy, regardless of the gross investments in other energy sources such as biofuels, solar energy, and wind energy. This fact is highlighted by the current global energy production from fossil fuels which currently stand at about 80–90% with oil and gas representing about 60% [
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>]. During oil production, primary oil recovery can account for 30–40% oil productions, while additional 15–25% can be recovered by secondary methods such as water injection leaving behind about 35–55% of oil as residual oil in the reservoirs [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>]. This residual oil is usually the target of many enhanced oil recovery technologies and it amounts to about 2–4 trillion barrels [
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>] or about 67% of the total oil reserves [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>]. Residual oil recovery is at present necessitated for many oil companies and so there is a constant hunt for a cheap and efficient technology which will raise the global oil production as well as the productive life of many oilfields. The recovery of this residual oil is accomplished by enhanced oil recovery (EOR) or tertiary recovery methods which are used in oil industry to increase the production of crude oil. Indigenous or in situ microbial enhanced oil recovery (IMEOR) is one of the techniques in which the inhabitant microbes in the oil reservoirs were stimulated to enhance oil recovery [
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>]. IMEOR is reported as a cost-effective method [
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>]. The microbial community composition is influenced by oil reservoir geological conditions and other external factors like nutrient and water flooding, biosurfactant and biopolymer application, and steam injection [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the advancement of a reliable MEOR protocol, understanding the microflora that exist in the oil reservoir is essential. Conventional culture-based techniques have been widely used for bacterial identification and enumeration in oil fields. Culture-based technique is selective and aids in the identification of only a few of the microbes. The problem is even worsened in extreme environmental conditions such as oil fields, where only microbes that can withstand strict circumstances will survive. Therefore, genomic analysis has become an important tool for understanding ecological biodiversity. It evades the need for laboratory cultivation and isolation of individual isolates.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Complex environmental samples need some technique which can read multiple sequences in parallel. Next-Generation Sequencing (NGS) can obtain DNA sequences directly from environmental samples [
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>, 
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>]. In the study, the distribution of bacteria in steam-injected heavy oil wells (South Oman) with alkaline pH was characterized using high-throughput sequencing technique, Ion Torrent-Personal Genome Machine (PGM). The spore-forming bacteria in the samples were also identified using culture-based method.
 </p>
</sec>
