<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The last decade has seen increased interest in the use of essential oils from plants in the food, human health, and the pharmaceutical industry [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>]. Different parts of plants can synthesize essential oils with diverse pharmacological activities, ranging from the cytotoxic, through the antioxidant, antimicrobial, and antiparasitic, to the anti-inflammatory [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>, 
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>]. Their antibacterial activity makes essential oils suitable alternatives to antibiotics [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>]. Many antibiotics can be not effective as bactericidal agents due to drug-resistancy of bacteria that have developed from the widespread use of antibiotics. Essential oils can be used as natural food preservatives against food spoilage and pathogenic bacteria [
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>]. They may be an alternative to currently used synthetic compounds, which may have toxic effects and may be carcinogenic [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>, 
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>]. The antimicrobial activity of the essential oils is associated with different functional groups and the synergistic, antagonistic, or additive effects between them [
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>, 
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>]. Essential oils may also play an important role in scavenging free radicals which may lead to oxidative stress [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>]. Oxidative stress and mitochondrial dysfunction caused by reactive oxygen species (ROS) may induce the inflammation [
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>]. The inflammation is connected with many neurological and neurodegenerative diseases, such as Parkinson's disease, Alzheimer's disease, multiple sclerosis, and other nervous pathogenesis [
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Rhaponticum carthamoides</span> (Willd.) Iljin (Asteraceae) has been used for centuries in traditional Siberian medicine in the case of overstrain and weakness after illness [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>]. The plant has demonstrated several biological activities, including adaptogenic, antioxidant, anticancer, and antimicrobial effects [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>–
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>]. The raw material of
  <span class="italic"> R. carthamoides</span> comprises roots and rhizomes of three- to four-year-old plants which are used in various dietary supplements or nutraceutical preparations. The collection of raw material from natural habitat or cultivation is not effective because it requires the destruction of the whole plants [
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>]. An alternative may be the biotechnological approaches such as the hairy root cultures obtained by
  <span class="italic"> Agrobacterium rhizogenes</span> transformation. Hairy root cultures are characterized by rapid increase of biomass in a short time (4–6 weeks) and genetic stability. The level of secondary metabolites in these cultures may be comparable to or higher than in roots of plants growing naturally [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>]. In our previous study we obtained hairy roots of
  <span class="italic"> R. carthamoides</span> and evaluated their phytochemical profile in methanol extract [
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As no description currently exists of the chemical composition of
  <span class="italic"> Rhaponticum carthamoides</span> essential oil from hairy roots (HR), the aim of the present study was to determine this. The anti-inflammatory and antioxidant activity of this essential oil in lipopolysaccharide- (LPS-) stimulated astrocytes and its antimicrobial potential were also examined. As the comparative material for phytochemical and biological studies essential oil from the roots of soil-grown plants (SGR) was used.
 </p>
</sec>
