<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Decrease of IL-1
  <span class="italic">β</span>, IL-6, and TNF-
  <span class="italic">α</span> Levels in LPS-Stimulated Astrocytes after Treatment of
  <span class="italic"> R. carthamoides</span> HR and SGR Essential Oils
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study we also evaluated the anti-inflammatory activity of HR and SGR essential oils in LPS-treated astrocytes. The levels of pro- and anti-inflammatory mediators in astrocytes incubated for 24 h with HR and SGR essential oils (25, 50, and 100 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL) and LPS (1 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL), only LPS (1 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL), or only 25, 50, and 100 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL of HR and SGR essential oils were measured using the ELISA Kits (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a>). LPS treatment of astrocytes led to increased levels of IL-1
  <span class="italic">β</span>, IL-6, IL-10, and TNF-
  <span class="italic">α</span> in comparison to the control cells. Treatment of LPS-stimulated astrocytes with HR and SGR essential oils dose-dependently reduced the levels of proinflammatory cytokines as IL-1
  <span class="italic">β</span>, IL-6, and TNF-
  <span class="italic">α</span> but not IL-10, IL-8, or GM-CSF (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a>). In addition, the expression levels of IL-1
  <span class="italic">β</span>, IL-6, IL-8, IL-10, GM-CSF, and TNF-
  <span class="italic">α</span> in LPS-stimulated astrocytes were analyzed by RT-PCR after 24 h incubation with 100 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL of HR and SGR essential oils (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3</a>). A single concentration of essential oils known to be the most effective for reducing of the levels of pro- and anti-inflammatory cytokines, as determined by an ELISA, was used in this experiment. RT-PCR analyses showed also that treatment with HR and SGR essential oils resulted in the downregulation of IL-1
  <span class="italic">β</span>, IL-6, and TNF-
  <span class="italic">α</span> mRNA expression in LPS-induced astrocytes (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3</a>). No change was observed in the mRNA expression of IL-10, IL-8, and GM-CSF in comparison with astrocytes treated with only LPS.
 </p>
</sec>
