<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cost, cleanliness and safety considerations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reduced cost of extraction is clearly advantageous for microwave method in terms of time and energy. The time needed for the complete extraction of rosemary essential oil was found as 30 
  <span class="italic">min</span> for MAHD and 90 
  <span class="italic">min</span> for HD. The extraction time was reduced by about 67% by using microwave. The reason for the reduction in the processing time is the heat generated by microwave heating which results in high pressure gradient inside the product. Microwaves interact selectively with the free water molecules present in the gland and vascular systems which leads to localized heating 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>
  </span> . As a result of internal superheating, a dramatic expansion and consequently rupture of cell walls occurs allowing the extraction of essential oil.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The energy requirements to perform the extraction, based on maximum power consumption of electro mantle for HD and microwave oven for MAHD considering the total period of a full recovery, were 1500 
  <span class="italic">W</span> for HD and 180 
  <span class="italic">W</span> for MAHD. This indicates a substantial saving in the extraction cost when using MAHD instead of HD.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The calculated quantity of carbon dioxide released into the atmosphere is higher in the case of HD (1200 
  <span class="italic">g</span> CO 
  <sub> 2 </sub>) than for MAHD (144 
  <span class="italic">g</span> CO 
  <sub> 2 </sub>). These calculations were made according to the literature: to obtain 1 
  <span class="italic">kWh</span> from coal or other fossil fuel, 800 
  <span class="italic">g</span> CO 
  <sub> 2 </sub> will be released into the atmosphere during combustion 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>
  </span> .
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Therefore, MAHD is proposed as an “environmentally friendly” extraction method suitable for essential oil extraction.</p>
</sec>
