<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis L.</span>, commonly known as rosemary, is a woody, perennial herb with fragrant, evergreen, needle-like leaves native to the Mediterranean region. Rosemary’s antioxidant properties are still used to extend the shelf life of prepared foods 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>–
   <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>
  </span> . Rosemary is also known medicinally for its powerful antioxidant activity and antibacterial properties 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>
  </span> and as a chemopreventive agent 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>
  </span> . Today, essential oil of rosemary is widely used in the cosmetic industry producing various bathing essences, hair lotions and shampoos 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>
  </span> .
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Traditional methods used for extraction of essential oil were Hydro-distillation (HD) or steam distillation. However, the loss of some components and the degradation of some unsaturated compounds by thermal effects 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>,
   <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>
  </span> or by hydrolysis can take place by these conventional extraction techniques. These disadvantages have changed the approach of the recent research and stimulated the intensification, optimization and improvement of existing and novel “green” extraction techniques 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>,
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>
  </span> . Some of these methods are: Ultrasound-Assisted Extraction, Microwave-Assisted Extraction and CO 
  <sub> 2 </sub> supercritical extraction. The supercritical fluid extraction of rosemary with CO 
  <sub> 2 </sub> has been the object of many researches 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>
  </span> and has become a valid alternative to the more conventional extraction procedures, mainly because the dissolving power of the extracting medium can be adjusted by regulating pressure and temperature conditions. However, the high cost of producing specific products has limited its use. In certain cases, the extractive power of supercritical CO 
  <sub> 2 </sub> is insufficient under conventional conditions. Microwave-assisted solvent extraction appeared to be particularly attractive for isolation of essential oil 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>,
   <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>
  </span> . Microwave-assisted Hydro-distillation (MAHD) combines rapid heating in the microwave field with the traditional solvent extraction. This significantly enables saving of time, so the extraction can be completed in meter of minutes 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>,
   <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>
  </span> . In an attempt to take advantage of microwave heating with the conventional HD, MAHD was developed and used for the extraction of essential oils from 
  <span class="italic">Xylopia aromatica</span> (Lamarck) and 
  <span class="italic">Lippia alba</span> (Mill) 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>,
   <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>
  </span> .
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tigrine-Kordjani 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>
  </span> developed a Microwave Assisted Distillation (MAD) with free solvent for laboratory scale applications in the extraction of essential oils from different kinds of aromatic plant. Sui 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>
  </span> have worked on an efficient Microwave Pretreatment (MP) method to maintain quality of postharvest rosemary leaves and observed that MP could be a good method for extracting essential oil and maintaining quality in rosemary and other aromatic herbs. Lucchesi 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>
  </span> had a study on comparing solvent-free microwave extraction of essential oil from aromatic herbs with conventional hydro-distillation. They found that the SFME method yields an essential oil with higher amounts of more valuable oxygenated compounds, and allows substantial savings of costs, in terms of time, energy and plant material. SFME is a green technology and appears as a good alternative for the extraction of essential oils from aromatic plants.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, the essential oil from rosemary obtained by microwave hydro-distillation has been compared with those obtained by conventional hydrodistillation. Then, the quality and quantity of essential oil, cost, energy consumption and safety environmental consideration of two methods were studied. Also, different parameters on essential oil extraction quantity and quality were checked.The aim of this research was finding an optimum method for extraction of essential oil.</p>
</sec>
