<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Portuguese recommended 
 <italic>M. balsamina</italic> leaves for blood, stomach, and liver deficiencies, furthermore they use leaves for herbal medicine and culinary herb (
 <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr">Thakur et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">Madala et al., 2014</xref>). 
 <italic>M. balsamina</italic> leaves are used for diabetes, digestion disorder, fevers, ulcers, and mild form of malaria. Additionally, in West Africa 
 <italic>M. balsamina</italic> is used as medicine in human and animals particular for fever, yaws and purgative (
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">Oloyede and Aluko, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Ingle et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Jabeen and Khanum, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Mostafa et al., 2018</xref>). 
 <italic>M. balsamina</italic> roots are used as ingredient in an aphrodisiac preparation and in treatment of urethral discharge on both human and animals. It is advisable to use the whole 
 <italic>M. balsamina</italic> parts of the plant for used in treating skin disease such as scabies (
 <xref rid="B140" ref-type="bibr">Waako et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Ozusaglam and Karakoca, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">Pauliuc and Botau, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B145" ref-type="bibr">Wikaningtyas and Sukandar, 2016</xref>). In South Africa, mostly the Pedi people use 
 <italic>M. balsamina</italic> leaves and tendrils as potherb and anti-emetic, while the Venda people used the leaves infusions as anti-emetic and Congo as colic. 
 <italic>M. balsamina</italic> leaves and fruit are widely used in Okavango delta for medicinal and spiritual purpose and also as skin aliments in China (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">Molehin and Adefegha, 2014</xref>). In some countries seed can be used as poison in arrow for hunting. The whole plant extract has insecticidal properties (
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr">Trakoon-osot et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B144" ref-type="bibr">Wardhani et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B141" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2016</xref>).
</p>
