<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40" class="p">The results obtained from the dose-dependent adulticidal bioassays demonstrated promising potential of the tested EOs and suggest similar susceptibility to EO and PBO in MCM-S and PMD-R strains of 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. aegypti</italic>. The comparison of efficacy between EO and permethrin demonstrates that the latter had a much stronger adulticidal effect, with LD
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values of 0.44 and 3.70 ng/mg female against MCM-S and PMD-R strains, respectively. These findings corroborate with those of many studies in that insecticides of natural origin, particularly plant-derived products, are generally less effective than synthetic substances [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>]. This is possibly due to the former being complex combinations of either active or inactive ingredients, whereas the latter is a purified single active compound. However, the variety and complexity of naturally active principles with different modes of action could be beneficial in either enhancing the bioactivity or impeding the evolution of resistance in vector populations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>]. The anti-mosquito potential of 
 <italic class="italic">C. verum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">A. galanga</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. rotundus</italic> as well as their constituents such as 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-bisabolene, cinnamaldehyde and 1,8-cineole has been reported by many researchers [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>]. However, a literature survey showed that there has been no previous report on their synergistic effects with permethrin or other synthetic insecticides against 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. aegypti.</italic>
</p>
