<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par41" class="p">The susceptibilities to permethrin observed in this study were significantly different between the two strains of 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. aegypti</italic>. While MCM-S was susceptible to permethrin, PMD-R showed far less susceptibility to it, with a resistance ratio of 8.41. The lower sensitivity to permethrin but higher sensitivity to EO of PMD-R, when compared to the sensitivity of MCM-S, opens the possibility for further investigation aimed at improving permethrin efficacy by combining it with EOs. Combination-based adulticidal bioassays for synergism found that binary mixtures of EO and permethrin produced either decreased or increased adult mortality in 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. aegypti</italic>. Adding 
 <italic class="italic">C. verum</italic> oil decreased the LD
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> of permethrin slightly against MCM-S, but increased it slightly against PMD-R, with SR values of 1.05 and 0.96, respectively. This suggests that 
 <italic class="italic">C. verum</italic> oil had no synergistic or antagonistic effect on permethrin when tested against both MCM-S and PMD-R. In contrast, the oils of 
 <italic class="italic">C. rotundus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. galanga</italic> showed significant synergistic effect by markedly minimizing the LD
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values of permethrin against either MCM-S or PMD-R. The SR values of EO-permethrin mixtures against MCM-S were 6.28 and 4.00 when permethrin combined with EOs of 
 <italic class="italic">C. rotundus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. galanga</italic>, respectively. Furthermore, a noticeable increment in the SR values was recorded when permethrin coupled with 
 <italic class="italic">C. rotundus</italic> (SR = 8.81) or 
 <italic class="italic">A. galanga</italic> (SR = 1233.33) was evaluated against PMD-R. It is worth noting that both 
 <italic class="italic">C. rotundus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. galanga</italic> potentiated the toxicity of permethrin against PMD-R 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. aegypti</italic> significantly. Similarly, PBO was found to increase the permethrin toxicity, with SR values of 1.69 and 5.69 against MCM-S and PMD-R strains, respectively. As 
 <italic class="italic">C. rotundus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. galanga</italic> had the highest SR values, they were considered the best synergists in potentiating permethrin toxicity against MCM-S and PMD-R, respectively.
</p>
