<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Jujube polysaccharide has been reported to improve hematological parameters in anemic animal models. Mice of blood deficiency model were induced by releasing blood and injection of cyclophosphamide. The levels of RBC, hemoglobin and hematocrit were decreased, and the level of platelet was increased in model mice, as compared to control group. Compared with model mice, the decreased levels of RBC, hemoglobin and hematocrit were reversed by treatment with jujube extract; while the increased level of platelet however was down regulated in jujube-treated mice (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2004</xref>). In another investigation, the activities of dietary jujube on the levels of RBC, hemoglobin and hematocrit were analyzed in colitis-associated colon cancer mice. These hematopoietic parameters in cancer mice were significantly decreased, as compared to control group; however, which were markedly increased in the jujube-treated mice (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Periasamy et al., 2020</xref>), suggesting possible beneficial effects of this fruit on cancer patients suffering from anemia. Besides, the extract of jujube possessed the ability to stimulate the activity of ATPase, i.e., Na+-K+-ATPase, Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>-ATPase and Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>-Mg
 <sup>2+</sup>-ATPase, in erythrocyte, and therefore which was shown to promote bone marrow nuclear proliferation and to inhibit atrophy thymus and spleen in blood deficient animals (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Miao et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Miao et al., 2010</xref>). Moreover, the intake of jujube extract (100–400 mg/kg) was found to increase the level of EPO in blood circulation, which suggested that jujube might promote RBC level through up regulation of EPO production. In support of this notion, the applied jujube extract at concentrations of 0.75–3 mg/ml in cultured Hep3B cells for 48 h increased the expression of EPO transcription, and the increase was shown to be in a dose-dependent manner (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2014b</xref>). In parallel, the applied jujube extract was able to stimulate the protein expression of EPO, giving ∼50% increase of the total protein (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2016</xref>). The circulating EPO is produced by adult kidney cells; while kidney dysfunction contributes to inadequate amount of EPO production and renal anemia. In ibuprofen-induced nephrotoxicity rats, the intake of jujube extract (500 mg/kg) improved kidney function by declining the levels of creatinine and urea, and this treatment could prevent histopathological damages of kidney (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Awad et al., 2014</xref>). On the other hand, the intake of Jian-Pi-Yi-Shen, a Chinese herbal decoction comprising of Astragali Radix, Atractylodis Macrocephalae Rhizoma, Dioscoreae Rhizoma, Cistanches Herba, and other four herbs, was able to improve renal function and kidney injury in anemia rats suffering from chronic kidney disease (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2019</xref>). Jian-Pi-Yi-Shen improved the hematological parameters and stimulated EPO production (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2019</xref>). Massive EPO-producing cells are identified in the renal interstitium. The occurrence of renal interstitial fibrosis is accompanied by decrease of fibroblasts, which impairs the production of EPO. Moreover, Jian-Pi-Yi-Shen was believed to ameliorate renal interstitial fibrosis, and the renal recovery might be related to improvement of EPO production. Thus, the function of jujube in promoting EPO expression in renal anemia patients was in line to that of Jian-Pi-Yi-Shen (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2019</xref>). This assumption requires further studies as to confirm the ability of jujube to prevent/treat renal anemia through regulation of EPO production.
</p>
