<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Justicia adhatoda</italic> (synonym 
 <italic>Adhatoda vasica</italic>), known as Vasaka in Ayurveda, is a well-known medicinal plant in indigenous system of medicine, mostly effective in treating respiratory ailments, as the leaf extract has a stimulant effect. Vasica leaf is an antispasmodic cum expectorant and has been used for centuries to treat asthma, chronic bronchitis, and other problems including fever, swelling, asthma, pneumonia, malaria, tuberculosis, cough, and cold (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). The infusion of 
 <italic>A. Vasica</italic> leaf is known to relieve headaches. The root is used as an expectorant and antispasmodic; while the root infusion has an anthelmintic property. The phytochemical profiling of this plant showed the presence of alkaloids, anthraquinones, flavonoids, phenols, saponins, and tannins (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). Several studies showed that the aqueous and methanolic extracts of leaves can directly interfere with the envelop proteins of many viruses. In particular, methanolic extract had a higher level of inhibition of influenza virus, by blocking viral attachment and inhibition of viral hemagglutinin (HA) protein. Detailed study revealed that the methanolic extract mainly comprised of Vasicine alkaloids have antiviral activity (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>). Aqueous extract of leaves is reported to inhibit the arachidonic acid metabolites through COX (TXB2) and LOX (LP1 and 12-HETE) pathways; while platelet aggregation studies showed butanol extract to exert strong inhibition against arachidonic acid, platelet activating factor, and collagen-induced aggregation (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). Methanolic extract also possess antiviral activity against HSV-2, while aqueous extract against HSV-1. Moreover, the methanolic extract showed 100% reduction in HA at 10 mg/ml; while the aqueous extracts at 5–10 mg/ml dose reduced the HA levels to 33 and 16.67%, respectively, suggesting strong anti-influenza activity by inhibiting viral attachment and/or replication (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>).
</p>
