<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Using Catfish frames and heads to develop a calcium‐rich supplement has the potential to combat osteoporosis and improve bone health in the elderly. Various studies indicate that the consumption of calcium has the advantage of enhancing the structural integrity of bone, and consumption of calcium has the advantage of enhancing the structural integrity of bone. There are a number of studies on the chemical and physical properties of fish bone. Toppe, Albrektsen, Hope, and Aksnes (
 <xref rid="fsn3974-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>) evaluated the chemical properties of bones from 8 different species of fish. Bones were from the frames and heads, and were removed after boiling of the tissue. This study reported differences in the lipid content of bone from different species and amino acid analysis, and element content was also reported. Other studies on properties of fish bone include those by Istiqlaal (
 <xref rid="fsn3974-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) and Techochatchawal, Therdthai, and Khotavivattana (
 <xref rid="fsn3974-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Characterization and preparation of ultrafine and nano fish bone from silver carp have been reported by Wu, Zhang, Wanga, Mothibe, and Chen (
 <xref rid="fsn3974-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>); Yin, Du, Xhang, and Xiong (
 <xref rid="fsn3974-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) and Yin, Park, and Xiong (
 <xref rid="fsn3974-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Venkatesan et al. (
 <xref rid="fsn3974-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) reported chemical and physical properties of nanohydroxyapitite derived using alkaline hydrolysis process from salmon fish bone. Ren et al. (
 <xref rid="fsn3974-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) reported using used 5 different proteases to hydrolyze channel Catfish bones to generate antibacterial agents. Chemical properties of Pacific cod and salmon bone from frames were reported by Bechtel (
 <xref rid="fsn3974-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>).
</p>
