<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In a recent in vivo experiment performed in rats, the efficacy of 
 <italic>R. fruticosus</italic> as a source of natural antidiabetic agents was supported. hydroethanolic extracts of 
 <italic>R. fruticosus</italic> were administered by intraperitoneal injection to streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats. Diabetes, like many other chronic diseases, has been found to trigger oxidative and inflammatory processes at a cellular level. The intraperitoneal administration of 
 <italic>R. fruticosus</italic> was demonstrated to reduce oxidative and inflammatory markers such as TNF-α, IL-6 and CRP [
 <xref rid="B61-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Different species recognized as tannin-rich sources have been also described as potential sources of antidiabetic agents, such as 
 <italic>C. sativa. Q. robur, S. lorentzii</italic> or 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic>. Tannins, especially HTs, have been reported to inhibit α-glucosidase, an enzyme responsible for the absorption of carbohydrates from the gut. In fact, inhibitors of α-glucosidase may be used in the treatment of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (DM) or impaired glucose tolerance [
 <xref rid="B39-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Therefore, the administration of tannins for the prevention or treatment of type 2 DM may have a doubly positive effect, as an antioxidant and as an α-glucosidase inhibitor. For instance, different extracts from the wood of 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic> were tested as potential α-glucosidase inhibitors and as antioxidants. An initial extract was fractioned into five parts, from which the best one was fractioned into seven parts. From these seven fractions, the ones with the strongest antioxidant capacity were mostly composed of the phenolic acid GA, grandinin, valoneic acid dilactone and its galloyl derivative and trigalloylglucose (TGG) molecules. The extracts with stronger α-glucosidase inhibition contained valoneic acid dilactone, three TGG isomers and PGG. The molecule common to these two extracts was the valoneic acid dilactone that has previously been reported as an α-glucosidase inhibitor [
 <xref rid="B39-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Similarly, from 
 <italic>Q. robur</italic>, different fractions were tested for antioxidant and α-glucosidase inhibition activities, with the molecules involved in the strongest antioxidant role being a monogalloylglucose (MGG) isomer, an HHDP-glucose isomer, castalin, GA, vescalagin and grandinin/roburin E isomer. The sub-fraction with the strongest α-glucosidase inhibitory activity contained castalagin as the major tannin [
 <xref rid="B55-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. From 
 <italic>S. lorentzii</italic>, fractions composed of HTs, esters of quinic acid with different units of GA (di-, tri-, tetra- and penta-galloylquinic acids) and oligomeric CTs (dimers, trimers, tetramers or pentamers of catechin or catechin-3-O-gallate and fisetinidol, or catechin-3-O-gallate) possessed the strongest α-glucosidase and α-amylase activity [
 <xref rid="B65-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. The tannin associated with the antidiabetic activity in 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> was corilagin [
 <xref rid="B80-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Other components of 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic>, like chebulanin, chebulagic acid and chebulinic acid, have been demonstrated to be able to inhibit the activity of maltase, an enzyme with a high activity rate in diabetic processes [
 <xref rid="B81-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Furthermore, ETs and GTs isolated from 
 <italic>T. bellerica</italic> and 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> have been described to improve the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-α and/or -γ signaling, which plays an important role in controlling the expression of genes related to the storage and mobilization of lipids, glucose metabolism, morphogenesis and inflammatory response, which have direct effects in insulin sensitivity [
 <xref rid="B82-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>].
</p>
