<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are various methods available for in vivo and in vitro screening of extracts of medicinal plants. Notably, this review focused on a little known method in the area of medicinal chemistry, which is mostly known as emulsion‐based in vitro compartmentalization (IVC) technique (Gianella, Snapp, &amp; Levy, 
 <xref rid="ptr6893-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). For this purpose, a “water‐in‐oil‐in‐water” emulsion is used in the compartmentalization of droplets for ultrahigh throughput screening (uHTS). Usually, IVC uses aqueous droplets that contain DNA and machinery for protein production within water‐in‐oil emulsions (Rothe, Surjadi, &amp; Power, 
 <xref rid="ptr6893-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>). In the modified protocol, template viral DNA tagged with a Green fluorescent protein (GFP) could be compartmentalized along with RdRP and plant extracts (or compounds). If RdRP is inhibited due to plant extracts and/or pure compounds, fluorescence switches off, and target droplets could be sorted using fluorescence‐activated cell sorting (FACS) (Bernath et al., 
 <xref rid="ptr6893-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). Reprogramming of similar techniques could be explored to study the inhibition of viral protease. Different cell cultures assays, chips‐based methods, animal models, and enzyme inhibition assays have been carried to find potent antiviral compounds from natural sources (Anani et al., 
 <xref rid="ptr6893-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>; Lloyd, Russell, Blanes, Doble, &amp; Roux, 
 <xref rid="ptr6893-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Mukhtar et al., 
 <xref rid="ptr6893-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Ogbole, Segun, &amp; Adeniji, 
 <xref rid="ptr6893-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Additionally, for a couple of decades, the analysis, process, and development of herbal ingredients have dramatically increased with innovation in laboratory techniques and instrumentation (Fitzgerald, Heinrich, &amp; Booker, 
 <xref rid="ptr6893-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>).
</p>
