<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> (
 <italic>T. chebula</italic>) belongs to the family of 
 <italic>Combretaceae</italic> and is mostly found in the Asian region [
 <xref rid="B283-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">283</xref>]. It is one of the most important medicinal plants due to the presence of a huge number of different kinds of phytoconstituents [
 <xref rid="B232-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">232</xref>]. It is customarily used as a household remedy and also in modern, Ayurveda, Unani and Homoeopathic medicines [
 <xref rid="B232-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">232</xref>,
 <xref rid="B283-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">283</xref>]. Its bioactive components extracted from the leaves, bark and fruit of the plant include flavonoids, polyphenols, terpenes, anthocyanins, glycosides, gallic acid, chebulagic acid, punicalagin, chebulanin, corilagin, neochebulinic acid, ellagic acid, chebulinic acid, alkaloids and many more [
 <xref rid="B232-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">232</xref>,
 <xref rid="B237-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>,
 <xref rid="B284-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">284</xref>]. It is also known to be used as a cure for irregular fevers, urinary diseases, diabetes, skin diseases, heart diseases, constipation, ulcers, vomiting, colic pain, hemorrhoids, digestive diseases, and others [
 <xref rid="B232-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">232</xref>,
 <xref rid="B235-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">235</xref>,
 <xref rid="B237-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>]. However, 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> has many pharmacological activities such as antiviral, antioxidant, antibacterial, antifungal, anti-protozoal, anti-carcinogenic, anti-mutagenic, radio-protective, chemo-preventive, hepato-protective, cardio-protective, cyto-protective, anti-diabetic, reno-protective, anti-inflammatory, anti-arthritic, adaptogenic, anti-anaphylactic, hypolipidemic, hypocholesterolemic, anti-caries, wound healing, anti-allergic, immunomodulatory, anti-ulcer, anti-spasmodic and gastrointestinal motility properties [
 <xref rid="B232-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">232</xref>,
 <xref rid="B233-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">233</xref>,
 <xref rid="B235-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">235</xref>,
 <xref rid="B236-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">236</xref>,
 <xref rid="B237-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>]. Lin et al., 2013 conducted an in vitro study and found that chebulagic acid and punicalagin from the fruit of 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> have the potential to inhibit the activity of different viruses, such as human cytomegalovirus, HCV, dengue virus, measles virus, and respiratory syncytial virus [
 <xref rid="B234-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">234</xref>]. Due to its strong biological properties, it is highly recommended to study 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> as a possible remedy against SARS-CoV-2.
</p>
