<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par42">Damrongrungruang et al. investigated azulene’s effect on peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) viability and singlet oxygen formation in vitro [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. They found out that azulene at concentrations 5–500 µM when activated with light-emitting diode at 625 nm and light dose 4.2 J/cm
 <sup>2</sup> induced singlet oxygen generation. Another conclusion was that PBMCs viability was significantly reduced by azulene at a concentration of 15 µM and red light densities of 4.2, 100, or 200 J/cm
 <sup>2</sup>. The suggested mechanism of photodynamic reaction with azulene as photosensitizer was proceeding via the generation of ROS, which further caused damage to intercellular structures, including DNA. The authors noted that a few improvements are necessary for further development of PDT in medicine, especially the length of irradiation time. The effects of azulene-light-oxygen action were analyzed in PACT study by Hayek et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. They performed microbial reduction in ligature-induced periimplantitis in dogs using azulene as a photosensitizer in photodynamic therapy approach and found it equally efficient as conventional infection treatment. Also, PACT was found to be less invasive in comparison to other approaches. This study showed that 
 <italic>Prevotella sp</italic>., 
 <italic>Fusobacterium sp</italic>., and 
 <italic>Streptococcus beta-haemolyticus</italic> were significantly reduced in both groups. During the treatment, 400 µL of azulene 25% solution w/v was applied in the form of a paste based on 10% urea peroxide, 15% tween 80 in 75% carbowax as a vehicle. The 0.01% (w/w) concentration of azulene in the paste was situated on scanned surfaces and exposed to diode GaAlAs laser operating at the wavelength of 660 nm and light dose 40 mW for 180 s. The authors did not note any therapeutic effect without light activation, which indicates that azulene antimicrobial properties rely on photodynamic mechanisms. After treatment, no significant differences were observed between the groups, which suggests that photodynamic therapy is a noninvasive method that could be used to reduce microorganisms in peri-implantitis. Recently, Nagai et al. demonstrated that azulenocyanine revealed the photodynamic antimicrobial effect on human infected dentine plates [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. In the study, dentin plates extracted from human molars were infected through immersion in a solution of 
 <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>. In the treatment procedure with 0.01% azulenocyanine (0.1 ml) after 5 min period in darkness, the 1.5 W laser irradiation at 940 nm revealed the best results in terms of bactericidal effects by reduction of the colony count assay (CFU/ml) and by the ATP assay [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].
</p>
