<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p class="p">The plants belonging to the 
   <italic class="italic">Ocimum</italic> genus of the Lamiaceae family are considered to be a rich source of essential oils which have expressed biological activity and use in different area of human activity. There is a great variety of chemotypes within the same basil species. Essential oils from three different cultivars of basil, 
   <italic class="italic">O. basilicum var. purpureum</italic>, 
   <italic class="italic">O. basilicum var. thyrsiflora</italic>, and 
   <italic class="italic">O. citriodorum</italic> Vis
   <italic class="italic">.</italic> were the subjects of our investigations.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p class="p">The oils were obtained by steam distillation in a Clevenger-type apparatus. The gas chromatography mass selective analysis was used to determine their chemical composition. The antioxidant activities of these essential oils were measured using 1,1-diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl assays; the tyrosinase inhibition abilities of the given group of oils were also assessed spectophotometrically, and the antimicrobial activity of the essential oils was determined by the agar diffusion method, minimal inhibitory concentrations were expressed.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p class="p">According to the results, the qualitative and quantitative composition of essential oils was quite different: 
   <italic class="italic">O. basilicum var. purpureum</italic> essential oil contained 57.3% methyl-chavicol (estragol); 
   <italic class="italic">O. basilicum var. thyrsiflora</italic> oil had 68.0% linalool. The main constituents of 
   <italic class="italic">O. citriodorum</italic> oil were nerol (23.0%) and citral (20.7%). The highest antioxidant activity was demonstrated by 
   <italic class="italic">O. basilicum var. thyrsiflora</italic> essential oil. This oil has also exhibited the highest tyrosinase inhibition level, whereas the oil from 
   <italic class="italic">O. citriodorum</italic> cultivar demonstrated the highest antimicrobial activity.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusions</title>
  <p class="p">The results obtained indicate that these essential oils have antioxidant, antibacterial and antifungal activity and can be used as natural antioxidant and antimicrobial agents in medicine, food industry and cosmetics.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
