<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For their part, essential oils and their ingredients alone induce both stimulatory and inhibitory effects on plants, herbivores, microorganisms 
 <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[14]</xref>,
 <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[15]</xref> and soil enzymes 
 <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[16]</xref>. They may increase or decrease the size of bacterial populations, change the microbial community profiles and influence the activity of various microbial taxa 
 <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[17]</xref>,
 <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[18]</xref>,
 <xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[19]</xref>. Hassiotis 
 <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[20]</xref>, Hassiotis and Dina 
 <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[21]</xref> found depressing effects of essential oils on AM fungi. Moreover, Papatheodorou et al. 
 <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[16]</xref> reported that specific constituents of essential oils, such as R- and S-carvone, affected the profiles of soil enzymes in a selective way. Because of the above mentioned effects, plant secondary metabolites are used as alternatives for pest management 
 <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[22]</xref> and especially essential oils are used as natural fungicides or bioherbicides 
 <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[17]</xref>,
 <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[23]</xref>. Herewith, we explored the joint effect of AMF inoculation and essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha spicata</italic> on soil microbial attributes and soil enzymatic activities. The necessity to study their joint effect comes from the fact that although both are agents of sustainable agriculture with mostly positive, independent effect on pest management and plant growth 
 <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[17]</xref>,
 <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[24]</xref>,
 <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[25]</xref>, their joint effect is largely unexplored. In a tomato pot experiment we examined the independent and combined effects exerted by the inoculation with the arbuscular-mycorrhizal fungus (AMF) 
 <italic class="italic">R. irregularis</italic> and the repeated addition of essential oil extracted from 
 <italic class="italic">M. spicata</italic> (spearmint) leaves, on the community profiles of free-living microbes and on soil enzymes, mainly those involved in the N-cycle since this cycle is entirely microbially-mediated.
</p>
