<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>
   <italic>Adansonia digitata</italic> is a plant used against cardiovascular disorders in African folk medicine. We assessed the effects of the aqueous extract of its stem bark on the development of hypertension in L-NAME-induced hypertensive rats. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p> The animals were administered L-NAME once daily for 3 weeks (25 mg/kg, i.p.), concomitantly with aqueous extract of 
   <italic>A. digitata</italic> stem bark (100 and 200 mg/kg, p.o.) or captopril (20 mg/kg, p.o.). Then, hemodynamic and electrocardiographic parameters, oxidative stress markers, and the lipid profile were assessed in the blood and heart, aorta, and kidney homogenates, and histopathological analyses were performed. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p> L-NAME-induced hypertensive control animals, but not the animals concomitantly treated with 
   <italic>A. digitata</italic> extract, displayed increases in the mean arterial blood pressure (21.64% difference, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001, vs. dose 200 mg/kg), systolic arterial blood pressure (21.33%, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and the diastolic arterial blood pressure (21.84%, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). In addition, hypertensive control animals displayed (i) increases in serum triglycerides, total cholesterol, LDL, and creatinine levels, malondialdehyde and transaminase activities, and atherogenic index; (ii) decreases in serum HDL, catalase, reduced glutathione, and nitric oxide; and (iii) aorta wall thickening, inflammatory cell infiltration, and cell loss in the cardiac muscle and renal tissues. As captopril, the extract prevented hypertension-like changes in lipid profile, cardiac, hepatic, and renal affection indicators, and oxidative stress markers. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p> Our findings suggest that the extract of 
   <italic>A. digitata</italic> has antihypertensive and antioxidant effects in L-NAME-induced hypertension rat models. These effects partly justify the traditional medicine use against cardiovascular disorders.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
