<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rotavirus belongs to family of Reoviridae and comprises of double stranded RNA which can be separated on the basis of gel electrophoresis. They include six structural proteins that are combined in order to form triple layers. Rotaviruses comprise nine groups (A-I) as established by ICTV (available at 
 <uri xlink:href="https://talk.ictvonline.org/taxonomy/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://talk.ictvonline.org/taxonomy/</uri>, accessed on 28 March 2021, which are based on presence of antigens and their subtypes [
 <xref rid="B59-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. The rotavirus from group A, B and C causes to infection in humans. Rotaviruses are most durable and their survival time in recreational and potable waters can persist for weeks. Currently, rotavirus infections are a major cause of severe and dehydrating gastroenteritis in children. In particular, rotavirus type A (RVA) is pathogenic form that most commonly causes pathology in its acute form in humans, causing approximately 215,000 deaths of children under the age of five each year [
 <xref rid="B59-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Considering only Europe, RVA resulted in 75,000–150,000 hospitalizations of children presenting with symptoms of acute gastroenteritis [
 <xref rid="B62-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. The severe form of diarrhea that occurs as a consequence of rotavirus infection occurs because this agent mainly infects enterocytes leading to destruction and therefore causing malabsorption. In addition to diarrhea, rotavirus infection can induce vomiting, malaise and fever [
 <xref rid="B63-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Vomiting is considered aggravating because it contributes to patient’s dehydration. Patients who experience vomiting and diarrhea at the same time have greater difficulty recovering as oral rehydration therapy is less effective and other therapeutic regimens are generally less successful. [
 <xref rid="B64-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. To date, vaccination is one of the most effective strategy for fighting RVA. Already since 2006, oral rotavirus vaccines have been authorized and are used in more than 100 countries around the world [
 <xref rid="B65-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. The vaccination policy has given its benefits, in fact without this important weapon, gastroenteritis associated with rotavirus has caused over 500,000 deaths in children under the age of 5 [
 <xref rid="B66-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Moreover, for RVA it has been shown that animals can represent the first cause of infection for humans. In fact, both humans and animals have the same RVA genotypes. Although animal derived RVA appears to be unable to infect or spread efficiently in the new host, however, the danger is always very high when considering the likelihood that these strains will acquire genetic segments of human origin. If such a hypothesis were to occur, the contagion would occur in a very effective way with sure development of the pathology [
 <xref rid="B67-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].
</p>
