<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Currently, despite the great progress in clinical medicine and pharmacology, herbal-based medicines find widespread use in most developed and developing countries. Their popularity has increased worldwide in the past five decades, probably because of the assumption that these preparations are safe and have very low levels of side effects. In the past few decades, researchers all over the world have increased their research activity on herbal-based secondary products with the aim of drug discovery. Phytochemical-based medicines are thought to act via synergistic effects (the combined effect of phytochemicals is greater than the sum of their separate effects) with reduced side effects. It can be considered a natural “straight” strategy which has evolved by nature to obtain more efficacy at low cost. In this regard, synergistic effects may be observed in the interaction between herbal-based medicines and conventional drugs or other natural products. It is important to identify and exploit these interactions since any improvement brought by such a kind of interaction can be advantageously used to achieve the best outcomes, including providing a greater benefit to patients or avoiding adverse side effects [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Greco-Arab herbal medicine has achieved a remarkable progress in the field of dermatology and presented tens of effective plants for treating acne and other skin diseases. For example, a large screening conducted by our group revealed that 29 medicinal plants are still used in the treatment of acne in Israel and Palestine [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In the present study, nine medicinal plants 
 <italic>Cappris spinose</italic> (CS), 
 <italic>Solanum nigrum</italic> (SN), 
 <italic>Ferula hermonis</italic> (FH), 
 <italic>Eruca sativa</italic> (ES), 
 <italic>Hypericum triquetrifolium</italic> (HT), 
 <italic>Inula helenium</italic> (IH), 
 <italic>Linum pubescens</italic> (LP), 
 <italic>Urtica dioica</italic> (UD), and roots of 
 <italic>Saponaria officinalis</italic> (SO) or seeds of 
 <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> (NS), which have been used extensively in Greco-Arab traditional medicine [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], were examined for their antiacne effects by testing their ability to inhibit the growth of 
 <italic>C. acnes,</italic> release of proinflammatory cytokines, and excessive production of sebum. Results obtained here indicate that SO, IH, and SN were the most safe and effective plant extracts in 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> tests using cells from HaCaT and THP-1 cell lines as well in 
 <italic>C. acnes</italic> tests. Therefore, they were chosen for building up a cream product prototype called AHC, which was tested clinically on 21 acne patients. AHC showed unique synergistic effects; it significantly inhibited sebum production from sebaceous glands and showed antiseptic and anti-inflammatory activities. Sixty percent of acne inflammatory and noninflammatory lesions almost disappeared after five weeks of application with 75% efficacy at the end of the sixth week.
</p>
