<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060" class="p">The antimicrobial activity of essential oils has been explored in many 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> assays which showed that thymol, eugenol and carvacrol have high antimicrobial activity against pathogenic bacteria such as 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella typhimurium</italic>, both of which are potential risk factors of enteric infections (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bassolé and Juliani, 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Franz et al., 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hippenstiel et al., 2011</xref>). Thymol, eugenol and carvacrol are structurally similar, and have been proved to exert synergistic or additive antimicrobial effects when combined at lower concentrations (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bassolé and Juliani, 2012</xref>). Therefore, it is necessary to unravel the synergistic mechanism to optimize their formulation. Different 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> methods as well as different pathogens exist for ranking the antimicrobial capacity of essential oil components, which could vary dramatically as shown in 
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>. In 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> studies, essential oils used either individually or in combination have shown clear growth inhibition of 
 <italic class="italic">Clostridium perfringens</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> in the hindgut and ameliorated intestinal lesions and weight loss than the challenged control birds (
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jamroz et al., 2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jerzsele et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mitsch et al., 2004</xref>). One well-known mechanism of antibacterial activity is linked to their hydrophobicity, which disrupts the permeability of cell membranes and cell homeostasis with the consequence of loss of cellular components, influx of other substances, or even cell death (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brenes and Roura, 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Solórzano-Santos and Miranda-Novales, 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Windisch et al., 2008</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">O'Bryan et al., 2015</xref>). It is of note that Gram-negative bacteria are more tolerant to the actions of essential oil than Gram-positive bacteria due to their hydrophilic constituents in the outer membrane (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brenes and Roura, 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Giannenas et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Seow et al., 2014</xref>).
</p>
