<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec19" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bioassay for fumigant action</div>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fumigant chambers covered with non-woven fabric of three thicknesses (10, 25, and 30 mm) were used to determine whether the 
  <span class="italic">M</span>. 
  <span class="italic">officinalis</span> oil (France) and 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal were effective in the control of 
  <span class="italic">D</span>. 
  <span class="italic">farinae</span> and 
  <span class="italic">D</span>. 
  <span class="italic">pteronyssinus</span> that live deep in pillows, carpet, and other fabric materials. A fumigation chamber was constructed with two petri dish bottoms (5.5 cm i.d. × 1.5 cm deep each), stacked lip-to-lip to create a total volume of 71.24 cm
  <span class="sup">3</span> (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>). The two plastic petri dish bottoms were separated by a 7 × 7 cm section of non-woven fabric of the three thicknesses. Approximately two-fold concentrations of the contact + fumigant LD
  <sub>90</sub> values of each test samples were applied to 5.5 cm diameter filter. After drying under a fume hood for 3 min, each treated filter paper was attached with double-sided adhesive tape (3 M, South Korea) to the lid of the upper chamber. For each test, 30 adult mites (both sexes, 8–10 days old) were introduced into the untreated 5.5 cm diameter filter paper on the bottom of the lower chamber. A wad of cotton saturated with distilled water (50 µL) had been introduced to the bottom of the lower chamber. The two plastic petri dish bottoms were held together, and wrapped in several layers of Parafilm
  <span class="sup">®</span>, and the mites were held at 24 °C and 74% relative humidity for 24 h. The mortality of each bioassay was determined by observing the number of mites under a binocular microscope (20×, Olympus, Tokyo, Japan). All experiments were replicated three times.
 </p>
</sec>
