<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0005">The microorganisms induced many diseases are highly responsible for about 50% mortality and are still a major concern to public health (
 <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization (WHO), 2002</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr">Valsalam et al., 2019a</xref>). Synthetic antibacterial and antifungal drugs are very expensive and generally unavailable in under developed countries (
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Roopan et al., 2019</xref>). These synthetic drugs cause various side effects. Emergence of resistance against various pathogenic bacteria due to unlimited use of drugs is important concern (
 <xref rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr">Valsalam et al., 2019b</xref>). Infectious disease causes morbidity and mortality among the populations, mainly in under developed and developing countries. So, Pharma industries have also been initiated to formulate potent antibacterial drugs in recent times, mainly due to the constant emergence of resistance among pathogenic microorganisms. The drug resistance microorganisms have the ability to acquire and transmit resistance against presently available various antimicrobial drugs (
 <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Natarajan et al., 2005</xref>). Medicinal plants contain phytochemicals such as, tannins, terpenoids, alkaloids and flavonoids and these phytochemcials have various antimicrobial properties (
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Aron and Kennedy, 2008</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Al-Dhabi and Arasu, 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Barathikannan et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Cuong et al., 2017</xref>). Infectious disease caused by drug resistance microorganisms are the Global health care problem (
 <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Al-Dhabi et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Elango et al., 2017</xref>). Many bacteria including, Proteus vulgaris, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Bacillus subtilis, Staphylococcus aureus and Escherichia coli cause many infections. Emergence of multiple drug resistance and toxicity severely limit the application of various currently available antibacterial agents (
 <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Chitra et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Elango et al., 2016a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Elango et al., 2016b</xref>). Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA), MDR Mycobacterium tuberculosis and Vancomycin-resistant enterococci (VRE) and some Gram-negative bacteria are reported as the highly difficult healthcare-associated serioud infections to treat and control. The development of extended-spectrum β-lactamases (ESBLs) that specifically target Gram-negative organisms has resulted in serious infections that can be very difficult to treat leading to severe increased death rate and illness (
 <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization (WHO), 2002</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Fowsiya et al., 2016</xref>). Multiple drug resistance demand to screen many medicinal plants for their antimicrobial potential, which are mainly due to the presence of secondary metabolites such as, alkaloids, tannins, flavonoids, phenolic compounds, resins, steroids, gums and fatty acids which are capable of producing various physiological action on body (
 <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad and Beg, 2001</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Dahiya and Purkayastha, 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Glorybai et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2016a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2016b</xref>). About 80% of world population using herbal medicine for the treatment of various infectious diseases, injuries and inflammations, etc. Most of the medicinal plants used in traditional medicine system are effectively proved and cheaper than modern medicine (
 <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Mann et al., 2008</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Haritha et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Helan et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Ilavenil et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
