<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">In Ayurvedic medicine system, the combinations of medicinal herbal plants have been used previously. For example, the combinations of long pepper with black pepper significantly enhances mucous-, and heat- reducing effects. Neem, ginger, cold herbs and bitter positively regulate any negative effects in the human body. Likewise, black pepper, cumin are applied to minimize weak digestion, whereas, the combination of turmeric and guduchi enhance immunity (
 <xref rid="b0275" ref-type="bibr">Thyagarajan et al., 2002</xref>). There are two possible mechanism involved in synergism effects, pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamics. Pharmacokinetic synergism involves absorption of herb, distribution of phytochemicals, metabolism of absorbed chemicals and removal (
 <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">Surendra et al., 2016b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">Surendra et al., 2016a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">Surendra et al., 2016c</xref>). In the other hand, pharmacodynamic synergism involves analysis of synergistic property when potent molecules with sample bioactivity are targeted to a similar physiological or receptor system. It is also believed that certain diseases cause multiple complications, leading to both invisible and visible symptoms. In these cases the combination of various herbs critically acts on various targets simultaneously to give maximum relief (
 <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">Spinella, 2002</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Gurusamy et al., 2019</xref>). Because of synergistic property, polyherbal provides more benefits not generally available in the formulation of single herbal medicine. It is more evident that good therapeutic property can be achieved with a formulation of a single multi-constituent formulation. For the formulation of poly-herbal medicine, medicinal plants with lower dose is highly preferable because to avoid side effects and to achieve required pharmacological activity. These kinds of poly-herbal formulations also avoid consuming more than one formulation at the time. All these positive effects resulted advantages of polyherbal formulation. Many medicinal plants have been directly used as the raw drug and these medicinal plants posses various therapeutic values. These medicinal plants are rich source of unique chemical substances with potent therapeutic effect. Plants contain many metabolites and are used as raw material for the production of new drugs. In developing countries and developed countries traditional medicine play very important role in primary healthcare system (
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Kannan et al., 2009</xref>). The plant based medicines are easily acceptable to the humans body than synthetic drugs. Hence, it is very important to utilize these natural medicines for providing good healthcare service to rural places.
</p>
