<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Stock solutions were prepared in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) and were further diluted with medium, supplemented with 1% fetal calf serum (FCS). The final DMSO concentration in the medium was 0.5% for all experiments. Treatment-resistant MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cells from Cell Biolabs (San Diego, CA, USA) were cultured in Dulbecco´s Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM, 4.5 g/L glucose, GlutaMax; Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA) supplemented with 10% FCS, 0.1 mM MEM nonessential amino acids, 100 U/mL penicillin, and 100 mg/mL streptomycin and passaged twice a week at a density of 5000 cells/cm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) isolated from whole venous blood of healthy volunteers by density gradient centrifugation by using Biocoll (Biochrom GmbH, Berlin, Germany) were cultured in RPMI 1640 medium, 2 mM L-glutamine (Life Technologies) supplemented with 10% FCS and penicillin/streptomycin. The study using human blood was approved by the institutional Ethic Committee and the volunteers gave their formal consent. Cells were cultured in a humidified incubator at 37 °C and 5% CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> atmosphere. For the experiments, 3000 MDA-MB-231 cells or 300,000 PBMC were seeded per well into 96-well plates in medium supplemented with 10% FCS overnight. Next day, cells were treated with different concentrations of the extracts, pure compounds, or 0.5% DMSO vehicle for 72 h by using a Tecan D300e Digital Dispenser (Tecan, Männedorf, Switzerland). Cell viability was analyzed after addition of 2,3-Bis-(2-methoxy-4-nitro-5-sulfophenyl)-2H-tetrazolium-5-carboxanilide salt (XTT). Absorbance of the orange formazan dye formed by reduction of the tetrazolium salt by mitochondrial dehydrogenases of viable cells was measured using an Infinite M1000 PRO Tecan plate reader at 450 nm with a 630 nm reference filter. Quantification of the viability was accomplished by subtracting a blank value containing the respective extract and by normalization to the vehicle control.
</p>
