<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Adv Pharm Technol Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Adv Pharm Technol Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JAPTR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Advanced Pharmaceutical Technology &#x00026; Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2231-4040</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0976-2094</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer - Medknow</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7832191</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JAPTR-12-14</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/japtr.JAPTR_187_20</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The antiaging property of aqueous extract of <italic>Millingtonia</italic> hortensis flowers in aging neuron</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jumnongprakhon</surname><given-names>Pichaya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pinkaew</surname><given-names>Decha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Phuneerub</surname><given-names>Pravaree</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Department of Anatomy, Faculty of Medical Science, Naresuan University, Phitsanulok, Thailand</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Department of Physical Therapy, Faculty of Associated Medical Science, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai, Thailand</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>2</label>Department of Applied Thai Traditional Medicine, School of Integrative Medicine, Chiang Rai, Thailand</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>3</label>Medicinal Plants Innovation Center of Mae Fah Luang University, Mae Fah Luang University, Chiang Rai, Thailand</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence: </bold> Dr. Pravaree Phuneerub, Department of Applied Thai Traditional Medicine, School of Integrative Medicine, Mae Fah Luang University, Chiang Rai 57100, Thailand. E-mail: <email xlink:href="pravaree.phu@mfu.ac.th">pravaree.phu@mfu.ac.th</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jan-Mar</season><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2021 Journal of Advanced Pharmaceutical Technology &#x00026; Research</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0"><license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Cellular senescence is the key mediator of cellular dysfunction before undergoing degenerative disease such as Alzheimer's disease. The aging process was mainly by the overactivation of senescence associated &#x003b2;-galactosidase (SA-&#x003b2;-gal) enzyme before mediated several negative responses, including intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS) production, cellular senescence regulation, and death prior encourage synaptic loss. Thus, in the recent work, we evaluated the <italic>in vitro</italic> effects of aqueous extract of <italic>Millingtonia hortensis L.</italic> (MH) from flower in hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>)-induced senescence in SK-N-SH cells. Herein, we demonstrated that MH significantly increased cell viability and decreased both of apoptotic cells and ROS production in a dose-dependent manner comparing to aging group (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) using 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide, flow cytometry, and ROS assay. Furthermore, the number of SA-&#x003b2;-gal-positive cells was also reduced in MH treatment (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) together with the promotion of Sirt-1 protein. Importantly, MH also promoted the synaptic plasticity by decreased acetylcholinesterase activity and increased synaptophysin expression in aging neurons comparing to aging group (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01). Hispidulin (the active ingredient in MH) was also revealed the similarly effects to MH. Therefore, we suggested that MH might be beneficially for neurodegenerative disease that caused by aging.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Key words:</title><kwd>Aging neuron</kwd><kwd>cellular dysfunction</kwd><kwd><italic>Millingtonia hortensis L</italic></kwd><kwd>neurodegenerative disease</kwd><kwd>Sirt-1</kwd><kwd>Hispidulin</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Cellular senescence or aging is the cellular response implicated with various pathological conditions such as heart disease and Alzheimer's disease (AD).[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Previous reports demonstrated that the aging process in brain tissue of AD was commonly found in several cell types such as neuron, glia cells, and brain endothelial cells before leading the cell stress, dysfunction, and death in finally.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] The pathological hallmark in aging neuron was primarily mediated the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) that caused protein degradation, intracellular antioxidant defense imbalance, and lipid peroxidation prior encourage various negative responses such as inflammation.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] Simultaneously, the inflammatory response in neuronal cells also suppressed sirtuin (silent mating type information regulation 2 homolog)-1 (Sirt-1), the mediator of cellular defense system and cell division, before underwent senescence and death.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Moreover, the reduction of Sirt-1 also promoted the overactivation of senescence-associated &#x003b2;-galactosidase enzyme (SA-&#x003b2;-gal) and telomerase enzyme leading telomere shortening and then the cells become aging.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] Afterward, the cell death response or apoptosis will activate by firstly modulated the cleavage caspase-3 that caused cellular deformation and then affected to neuronal function, especially decreasing both of pre- and postsynaptic protein such as synaptophysin.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] The degradation of synaptic protein was mainly by monoamine oxidase and acetylcholinesterase (AchE) that caused AD progression.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] Several studies were showed that the reduction of AchE activity in neuronal tissue plays a key role in the reversing of synaptic protein degradation in the AD model.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] Therefore, the reduction of aging-induced negative response in neurons might be helpful for promoting of AD or brain disease recovery.</p><p><italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> (MH) belongs to family Bignoniaceae. The common name in English is &#x0201c;Indian cork tree&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;tree jasmine&#x0201d; and commonly known in Thai as &#x0201c;Peep.&#x0201d;[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] In Thai traditional, the flower of MH has an efficacy for curing disease, especially in respiratory system disease such as asthma, sinusitis, cholagogue, and tonic.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Moreover, it has high antioxidant component such as flavonoid and hispidulin which were recorded in the reduction of negative response-induced cellular dysfunction and death in brain tissue.[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] Nevertheless, its effect has not been understood in aging neuronal cells. Based on the above data, we speculated that MH would reduce cell stress, senescence, death, and synaptic plasticity impairment on aging neuron. To investigate this hypothesis, the SK-N-SH cells were triggered by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> to establish an aging neuronal model and then explored the effect of MH on the aging neuron.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Reagent Hydrogen</title><p>Hydrogen peroxide, Hispidulin, were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich Chemical Company (St. Louis, MO, USA). 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT), 2&#x02032;,7&#x02032;-dichlorofluorescine diacetate, Muse&#x000ae;Annexin V and Dead Cell kit, and BetaRed&#x02122; &#x003b2;-Gal assay kitwere purchased from Merck Millipore, (Millipore, MA, USA). The anti-Sirt1, anti-synaptophysin, and anti-actin were purchased from Abcam, Cambridge, UK.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Preparation of <italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic></title><p>Flowers of MH were collected at Chiang Rai Province in Thailand in October 2019. The plant material was authenticated by a botanist at the office of the QSNC, Thailand. Flowers were dried at 40&#x000b0;C. Then, drug was powdered by grinder (coarse powder) and macerated with water. The water extracts were lyophilized to dryness and stored at &#x02212; 20&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Phytochemical screening</title><p>MH extract was evaluated by phytochemical which was divided into 10 groups: alkaloids, flavonoids, anthraquinones, terpenoids, phenolic, saponins, tannins, steroids, carbohydrate, and cardiac glycosides.[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Determination of hispidulin in the extract by high-performance liquid chromatography</title><p>High-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) method was used for the determination of hispidulin in MH by comparing it with the standards of hispidulin. The stock solution of hispidulin and MH was freshly prepared at 1 mg/mL in methanol and aqueous, respectively. HPLC analysis was performed using Dionex Ultimate 3000, equipped with an auto sample, a column oven, and DAD detector. The separation was performed with Acclaim C18 (3 &#x003bc;m &#x000d7; 4.6 mm &#x000d7; 150 mm) using aqueous and acetonitrile as mobile phases. The flow rate was 0.6 ml/min. The column temperature was set at 35&#x000b0;C, and then injection volume was 1.5 and 10 &#x003bc;l of hispidulin and MH, respectively. The detection wavelength was determined at 280 nm.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Brine shrimp lethality assay</title><p>Brine shrimp lethality assay was a preliminary toxicity investigation. Ten shrimps per vial were added. Extract plants at 10, 100, and 1000 ug/ml were prepared on filtered paper. After 24 h, the number surviving were recorded and determined percentage LC<sub>50</sub> from the graph. LC<sub>50</sub> value lower than 1000 ug/ml is considered Toxic.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Total phenolic content</title><p>The total phenolic content was investigated by using Folin&#x02013;Ciocalteu reagent and external calibration with gallic acid. In brief, 800 &#x003bc;l of samples was added with 200 &#x003bc;l of Folin&#x02013;Ciocalteu reagent. After 5 min, 1 ml of a 7.5% Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> solution was mixed in the dark for 60 min at room temperature. The absorbance was measured at 756 nm using a spectrophotometer. The results were averaged which expressed as micrograms of gallic acid equivalents (GAE) per 100 &#x003bc;g of extract sample.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>DPPH scavenging activity</title><p>The 100 &#x003bc;l of various concentrations of MH extract dissolved in DMSO were added to 100 &#x003bc;L DPPH (2,2-diphenyl-1-picryl-hydrazyl-hydrate) radical solution 0.5 mM in ethanol. The absorbance is read at 517 nm after incubated 30 min with a microplate reader. The positive control was ascorbic acid. IC<sub>50</sub> values were used for the expression of the activity.[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</p></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Antiaging activities in human neuroblastoma (SK-N-SH) cell lines</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Cell culture</title><p>SK-N-SH cells were culture in 10% fetal bovine serum with minimum essential medium supplemented with penicillin/streptomycin (GIBCO-BRL, Gainthersburg, MD) at 37&#x000b0;C in humidified 5% CO<sub>2</sub> incubator.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Cell viability assay</title><p>Briefly, 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> cells/mL of SK-N-SH cells were seeded in 96-well microplate, followed by treatment with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (0&#x02013;100 &#x003bc;M) for 4 h, the both MH and hispidulin (0&#x02013;1,000 &#x003bc;g/mL) for 24 h. Assessing of therapeutic effect of both MH and hispidulin on H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced aging, cells were treated with 10 &#x003bc;M H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 4 h prior treated with 0.1, 1, and 10 &#x003bc;g/mL of MH or hispidulin for 24 h. Thereafter, the (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide assay was performed. The wavelength was measured at 570/600 nm using spectrophotometer.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>Flow cytometry</title><p>To determine the number of apoptosis, 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells/mL cells were incubated with Muse&#x02122;Annexin-V. The dead cell reaction assay kit was measured using Muse Cell Analyzer (Merck Millipore, MA, USA), according to the manufacturer's protocol.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Reactive oxygen species assay</title><p>The 20 &#x003bc;M of H2DCF-DA in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) was incubated with the cell treatment (2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> cells/mL) for 2 h. The fluorescence values were then measured wavelength at 485/535 nm using a Synergy HT microplate reader (Biotek, VT, USA).</p><sec id="sec3-4"><title>Senescence-associated &#x003b2;-galactosidase enzyme assay</title><p>According to the manufacturer's instruction, the cells (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells/mL) were incubated with fixing solution for 15 min at room temperature. After that, the assay was incubated with the SA-&#x003b2;-Gal detection solution for 24 h. Finally, the cells were investigated under phase contrast microscopy for counting the SA-&#x003b2;-gal-positive cells (blue) as a percentage of the total cell number.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title>Acetylcholinesterase activity (AChE) assay</title><p>The AChE activity in SK-N-SH cells was assessed following to Ellman's method. First, the cell lysate was preincubated with 3 mM DTNB. Then, the acetylthiocholine iodide was mixed in the reaction and immediately read the absorbance at 405 nm for a regular interval of 2 min using a spectrophotometer (Synergy HT microplate reader, Biotek, VT, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p>The 50 &#x003bc;g proteins were electrophoresed to 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate&#x02013;polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis, followed by transferred to a Polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membraneand blocked with 5% skim milk at room temperature for 2 h. The membranes were then incubated overnight with anti Sirt1 (1:1000) and anti synaptophysin (1:1000). Thereafter, the membranes were probed with anti rabbit IgG peroxidase conjugated secondary antibodies (1:2000). Finally, the HRP substrate was used to incubate the membrane and then detected with an X ray film. The ImageJ&#x000ae;software was used for analyzing the densitometry.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-11"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All data were expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error of the mean (<italic>N</italic> = 3) and were considered using one-way analysis of variance. After that, <italic>post hoc</italic> Dunnett's test was used comparing the significance between the groups. <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 was analyzed as statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="sec2-12"><title>Phytochemical screening and determination of hispidulin in <italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic></title><p>From phytochemical screening tests of the MH extract, it was found that there were five types of phytochemicals: flavonoids, terpenoids, phenolic, cardiac glycosides, and carbohydrate [<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>]. Hispidulin showed at retention time 18.67 min (1.09%) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref>]. HPLC chromatogram of MH extract revealed several chemical compounds containing in the extract [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Phytochemicals screening of MH extract</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MH extract</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkaloids test</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[a] Dragendorff&#x02019;s Test</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[b] Mayer&#x02019;s Test</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavonoids Test</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpenoids (Salkowski Test)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenolic compounds</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Steroids (Liebermann-Burchard Test)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiac Glycosides (Killer-Kallani Test)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saponins (Foam Test)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tannins (Ferric Chloride Test)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthraquinones (Borntragerts Test)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbohydrate (Benedicts Test)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Chromatogram of hispidulin (a) and <italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> extract (b) (280 nm)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAPTR-12-14-g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-13"><title>Brine shrimp lethality assay</title><p>The % lethality of MH extract at 10, 100, and 1000 &#x003bc;g/ml showed 0% &#x000b1; 0%, 0% &#x000b1; 0%, and 36% &#x000b1; 1.73%, respectively. MH extracts had LC<sub>50</sub> &#x0003e;1000 &#x003bc;g/ml which was considered as nontoxic.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-14"><title>Determination of antioxidant activities of <italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> extract</title><p>The total phenolic content in the aqueous extract was found to be 55.5 &#x000b1; 0.03 &#x003bc;gGAE/100 &#x003bc;g extract [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>]. For DPPH assay, MH extract showed IC<sub>50</sub> at 0.6 mg/ml [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>] and ascorbic acid showed IC<sub>50</sub> at 0.03 mg/ml.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Graph showed standard curve of gallic acid equivalent. (a) DPPH activity of <italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> extract (b)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAPTR-12-14-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2-15"><title>Antiaging activities</title><sec id="sec3-6"><title>The cytotoxicity to SK-N-SH cells</title><p>The concentration of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> at 10 &#x003bc;M significantly reduced cell viability (80.6% &#x000b1; 3.7%) (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) which previously report for aging model by Nopparat <italic>et al</italic>.,[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3a</xref>]. The results revealed that the MH and hispidulin at 50 &#x003bc;g/mL showed the cytotoxicity effect (95.0% &#x000b1; 2.9% and 94.4% &#x000b1; 2.8%) (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">c</xref>]. According to the subsequent experiment, we used the concentration of MH at 0.1, 1, and 10&#x003bc;g/mL, and hispidulin at 10 &#x003bc;g/mL (positive control).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The cytotoxicity test in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment for 4 h (a), <italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> treatment for 24 h (b), and Hispidulin treatment for 24 h (c) were analyzed by using 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide assay in SK-N-SH cells. The values present the mean &#x000b1; standard error of the mean from 3 independent experiments. **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, in comparison with the control treatment</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAPTR-12-14-g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-7"><title>Millingtonia hortensis alleviated cell apoptosis and inhibited reactive oxygen species production on H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced aging in SK-N-SH cells</title><p>The results demonstrated that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment significantly decreased cell viability (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4a</xref>] and promoted apoptosis (21.7% &#x000b1; 3.5%) (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). On the other hand, MH significantly reversed these effects in dose-dependent manner [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">b</xref>]. Importantly, 10 &#x003bc;g/mL MH has similarly affected hispidulin in the promotion of cell viability (95.4% &#x000b1; 2.1%) and reduction of apoptosis (7.3% &#x000b1; 2.5%).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> promoted cell survival and inhibited apoptosis in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treated SK-N-SH cells. The SK-N-SH cells were prior treated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 4 h and then discard the media and replaced with <italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> or His treatment for 24 h. The cell viability was analyzed by using 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide assay and the number of apoptotic cells was investigated by flow cytometry. The values present the mean &#x000b1; standard error of the mean from 3 independent experiments. **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, in comparison with the control treatment;<sup>#</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05,<sup>##</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01,<sup>###</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, in comparison with the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment alone</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAPTR-12-14-g004"/></fig><p>For inhibited ROS production, MH treatment demonstrated the reduction of ROS production in dose-dependent manner comparing H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment (231.8% &#x000b1; 17.6%) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>]. Interestingly, the MH (133.7% &#x000b1; 10.3%) has a similar effect comparing to hispidulin treatment (132.5% &#x000b1; 10.6%). Taken together, the MH and hispidulin treatment alone did not show any negative effect in the neuronal cells.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> scavenged intracellular free radical in SK-N-SH cell-treated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. The level of intracellular reactive oxygen species production was determined by reactive oxygen species assay. The values present the mean &#x000b1; standard error of the mean from 3 independent experiments. **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, in comparison with the control treatment;<sup>#</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05,<sup>##</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01,<sup>###</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, in comparison with the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment alone</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAPTR-12-14-g005"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-8"><title>Millingtonia hortensis reversed senescence on H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced aging in SK-N-SH cells</title><p>The result showed that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> promoted a high number of SA-&#x003b2;-gal-positive cells (blue) approximately 50% [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6a</xref>]. Treatment with MH significantly decreased of SA-&#x003b2;-gal-positive cells (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). Importantly, we found that the highest concentration of MH treatment has higher potency in the inhibition of senescence (24.7% &#x000b1; 7.4%) than hispidulin (35.1% &#x000b1; 1.6%). Moreover, the Sirt-1 protein expression, which is the cellular senescent suppressor, was also investigated. The result showed that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment significantly decreased Sirt-1 expression (48.7% &#x000b1; 7.0%) (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0001) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6b</xref>]. On the other hand, we found that both MH (86.4% &#x000b1; 4.7%) and hispidulin (85.3% &#x000b1; 5.1%) treatment could promote the expression of Sirt-1 in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced aging in the cells.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> reversed H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced cellular senescence in SK-N-SH cells. The &#x003b2;-galatoxidase assay was used to investigate the percent of &#x003b2;-Galactosidase-positive cells in SK-N-SH cells (a). The western blot analysis was used for determining the expression of Sirt1 (b). The values present the mean &#x000b1; standard error of the mean from 3 independent experiments. ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, in comparison with the control treatment;<sup>#</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05,<sup>##</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01,<sup>###</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, in comparison with the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment alone</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAPTR-12-14-g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec3-9"><title>Millingtonia hortensis promoted synaptic plasticity on H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced aging in SK-N-SH cells</title><p>The results indicated that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> group significantly promoted the AChE activity (1.76 &#x000b1; 0.07) (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0001) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7a</xref>] together with significantly decreased of synaptophysin expression (43.3% &#x000b1; 12.1%) (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0001) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7b</xref>]. Treatment with MH significantly caused reduction of AChE activity (1.26 &#x000b1; 0.21) and promotion of synaptophysin expression (82.97% &#x000b1; 6.9%) (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). Interestingly, at the highest dose of MH treatment (10 &#x003bc;g/mL) has similarly affect to hispidulin (84.8% &#x000b1; 7.2%).</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> reversed H2O2-impaired synaptic plasticity in SK-N-SH cells. The SK-N-SH cells were prior treated with H2O2 for 4 h and then discard the media and replaced with <italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> or this treatment for 24 h. The activity of AChE in the cells was determined by AChE assay (a). The expression protein of synaptophysin (b) was determined by western blot analysis. The values present the mean &#x000b1; standard error of the mean from three independent experiments. ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, in comparison with the control treatment;<sup>#</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05,<sup>##</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01,<sup>###</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, in comparison with the H2O2 treatment alone</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAPTR-12-14-g007"/></fig></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Brine shrimp lethality was used for investigation the preliminary cytotoxicity of MH extract. The result revealed that MH extract was nontoxic. The qualitative phytochemical analyses of extract showed the flavonoids, terpenoids, phenolic, cardiac glycosides, and carbohydrate. The obtained results are in concordance with reported previously.[<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] Phenolic compounds are the key agent's incumbent and promote largely in the antioxidant activities of medicinal plants.[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] The result revealed that MH extract had high phenolic content and exhibited potential in scavenging free radical, the observed result agreed with previous studies.[<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] One active ingredient of MH flower is hispidulin which is one of the polyphenols that has the ability in the scavenging of free radical-induced brain diseases.[<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] Hispidulin was used as a positive control to compare the potential in antiaging with MH extract. From the results, the qualitative analysis demonstrated that MH extract was found to be less hispidulin. The results were related to the previous studies in 1986, which found hispidulin from the flowers of MH.[<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</p><p>This study showed the result of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced aging in SK-N-SH cells that it significantly decreased in cell viability at 10 &#x003bc;M comparing to control (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) and it also affected to cellular formation (data not showed) and promoted SA-&#x003b2;-gal expression over than 50% of total cells. The reduction of cell survival in senescence neuron is one of the major events in aging response and it was commonly recorded with the high level of apoptosis.[<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] This study found that the SK-N-SH cells exposing to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> significantly decreased of cell survival (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) that closely related to the significantly increased of apoptotic cells (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). The high number of apoptosis might cause by the activation via intrinsic apoptotic pathway that correlated with the intracellular stress from ROS production.[<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] From our result, we found that the decline of cell survival in SK-N-SH treated-H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> was closely associated with the overproduction of ROS content. Thus, we suggested that the ROS plays an important role in cell survival and apoptosis response in aging neurons. Sirt-1 plays an important role in cellular division, cellular defense system, and autophagy induction. Previous study found that the high level of cellular stress from free radical could suppress both cellular defense system and Sirt-1 protein leading cell aging, dysfunction, and death.[<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] From our results, we suggested that the Sirt-1 might be the target of free radical-induced aging which mostly reports in several evidences.[<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] This study revealed that the treatment of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in SK-N-SH cells mediated the AchE activity (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) and suppressed the synaptophysin protein expression (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) comparing to control. In accordance to the results, we suggested that the loss of synaptic plasticity in neurons might be closely associated with the negative responses in aging. However, the treatment of brain disease was mainly focused on the promotion of synapse by using the drug-inhibited enzyme degraded neurotransmitter or drug influencing neurotransmitter, and the reduction of negative response-suppressed synapse did not recommend.[<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] Therefore, the reduction of negative responses in aging neuron might be beneficial as the alternative treatment for promoting neuronal cell survival and its function.</p><p>Recently, studies found that MH treatment has high potency in the promotion of cell viability in dose-dependent manner in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-treated SK-N-SH cells. Interestingly, the results showed that MH treatment also caused reduction of apoptotic cell number (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) and the highest concentration of MH showed a slightly better effect than hispidulin. We suggested that the effect of MH on apoptosis in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-treated SK-N-SH cells might be by hispidulin and other active ingredients such as flavonoid that has a high number of studies on anti-apoptosis in neuronal tissue.[<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] We found that the MH could alleviate ROS production in SK-N-SH cell-treated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in a dose-dependent manner (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). Otherwise, the highest concentration of MH has similarly effect comparing to hispidulin treatment, so the reduction of ROS by MH treatment might be by the hispidulin effect.</p><p>To confirm the indirect effect in scavenging of ROS by MH, the Sirt 1 was then evaluated. In this study we found that the both of MH and hispidulin treatment showed the significantly increased of Sirt 1 expression (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) that correlated with the decline of ROS.Consequently, we suggested that the reduction of ROS in aging neurons by MH and hispidulin might be by both direct and indirect free radical scavengers. Moreover, Sirt-1 was also recorded as the cellular senescence inhibitor. Hence, we then evaluated the number of senescence cells in MH treatment whether involved with Sirt-1 expression or not. The result showed that MH treatment in SK-N-SH treated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> markedly decreased of SA-&#x003b2;-gal-positive cells (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). Interestingly, the high concentration of MH has slightly better effect in the reduction of SA-&#x003b2;-gal-positive cells than hispidulin. We suggested that hispidulin in MH plays a pivotal role in the induction of Sirt-1, but the inhibition of senescence by MH might cause by hispidulin and other polyphenol.[<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</p><p>According to our present study, it was found that MH has potency in the reduction of negative responses in aging neuron; hence, we then investigated the role of MH on synapse in aging neuron. This study revealed that MH treatment in aging neuron markedly decreased AchE activity and promoted the synaptopysin expression (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). We suggested that the MH could promote the synaptic plasticity in aging neurons via the reduction of negative responses and the positive effect might be by the hispidulin.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec1-5"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>The therapeutic role of MH in diminishing the negative responses including cell stress response, apoptosis, cell senescence, and loss of synapse in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2&#x02013;</sub>treated SK-N-SH cells was mainly by hispidulin. These present studies might be beneficial implications in the use of MH for alternative treatment in aging brain disease.</p><sec id="sec2-16"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>The authors are grateful to Mae Fah Luang University for funding the research and providing laboratory facilities throughout the work. This work was supported by providing laboratory facilities throughout the work from Medicinal Plants Innovation Center of Mae Fah Luang University and Faculty of Medical Science, Naresuan University, Thailand, and the authors would like to thank for all suggestion of Associate Professor Dr. Jiraporn Tocharus from Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-17" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors are grateful to MFU for funding the research and providing laboratory facilities and they would like to thank for suggestion of Associate Professor Dr. Jiraporn Tocharus from Chiang Mai University.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorgoulis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Alimonti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bischof</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cellular senescence: Defining a path forward</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2019</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>813</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31675495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Babbar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasselbalch</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ageing as a risk factor for neurodegenerative disease</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurol</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31501588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accelerating neuronal aging in <italic>in vitro</italic> model brain disorders: A focus on reactive oxygen species</article-title><source>Front Aging Neurosci</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>292</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25386139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Goligorsky</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sirtuins, cell senescence, and vascular aging</article-title><source>Can J Cardiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26948035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Csiszar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakatta</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ungvari</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inflammation and endothelial dysfunction during aging: Role of NF-kappaB</article-title><source>J Appl Physiol (1985)</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>1333</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18599677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fielder</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>von Zglinicki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The DNA damage response in neurons: Die by apoptosis or survive in a senescence-like state?</article-title><source>J Alzheimers Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>S107</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28436392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Parambi</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Inasu</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Emerging therapeutic potentials of dual-acting MAO and AChE inhibitors in Alzheimer's and Parkinson's diseases</article-title><source>Arch Pharm (Weinheim)</source><year>2019</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>E1900177</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31478569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abidar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yildiz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Degirmenci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Amakran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>El Maadoudi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nhiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glucose-mediated protein glycation: Contribution of methanolic extract of <italic>Ceratonia siliqua</italic> L. in protection and <italic>in vitro</italic> potential inhibition of acetylcholinesterase</article-title><source>J Food Biochem</source><year>2019</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>e13009</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31393019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aruna</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Review on <italic>Millingtonia Hortensis</italic> Linn</article-title><source>Int. J. Pharm. Sci. Rev. Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>92</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phongboonrod</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mai Thed Mueng Thai, Folkloric Uses of Thai and Foreign Medicine Plants</source><year>1976</year><publisher-loc>Bangkok</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Chiwat Press Co Publishers</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autophagy induction by hispidulin provides protection against sevoflurane-induced neuronal apoptosis in aged rats</article-title><source>Biomed Pharmacother</source><year>2018</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>460</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29287193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Gulbarga University, G.(n.d.)</article-title><source>Phytochemical and Pharmacological Studies on Rumex Vesicarius Linn</source><year>2014</year><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrigni</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brine shrimp: a convenient general bioassay for active plant constituents</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>1982</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leibfritz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moncol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Telser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Free radicals and antioxidants in normal physiological functions and human disease</article-title><source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16978905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nopparat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinjanakhom</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Govitrapong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Melatonin reverses H2O2- induced senescence in SH-SY5Y cells by enhancing autophagy via sirtuin1 deacetylation of the RelA/p65 subunit of NF-&#x003ba;B</article-title><source>J Pineal Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>11</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babitha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Banji</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Banji</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and hepatoprotective effects of flower extract of <italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> Linn. on carbon tetrachloride induced hepatotoxicity</article-title><source>J Pharm Bioallied Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23248564</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Djeridane</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yousfia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadjemib</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutassounaa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stocker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity of some Algerian medicinal plants extracts containing phenolic compounds</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>654 60</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chumbhale</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Upasani</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic content and <italic>in vitro</italic> antioxidant activity of <italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> Linn</article-title><source>Int J Pharm Chem Biol Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hispidulin potently inhibits human glioblastoma multiforme cells through activation of AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK)</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2010</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>9511</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20698539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anulakanapakorn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bunyapraphatsara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Satayavivad</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical and pharmacological studies of the flower of <italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> Linn. F</article-title><source>J Sci Soc Thailand</source><year>1987</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>83</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baar</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Putavet</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Derks</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourgeois</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Targeted apoptosis of senescent cells restores tissue homeostasis in response to chemotoxicity and aging</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28340339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roca Agujetas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>de Dios</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lest&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mar&#x000ed;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Colell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent insights into the mitochondrial role in autophagy and its regulation by oxidative stress</article-title><source>Oxid Med Cell Longev</source><year>2019</year><volume>2019</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cornelius</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Trovato Salinaro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Scuto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fronte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Cambria</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennisi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cellular stress response, sirtuins and UCP proteins in Alzheimer disease: Role of vitagenes</article-title><source>Immun Ageing</source><year>2013</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>41</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24498895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SIRT1 ameliorates oxidative stress induced neural cell death and is down-regulated in Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>BMC Neurosci</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>46</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28578695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-217/138-5p downregulation inhibits inflammatory response, oxidative stress and the induction of neuronal apoptosis in MPP(+)-induced SH-SY5Y cells</article-title><source>Am J Transl Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>6619</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31737212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wille</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaminsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guideline-conform exact diagnosis and coding of dementia</article-title><source>Z Gerontol Geriatr</source><year>2019</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30830315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chulasiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bunyapraphatsara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Moongkarndi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutagenicity and antimutagenicity of hispidulin and hortensin, the flavonoids from <italic>Millingtonia hortensis</italic> L</article-title><source>Environ Mol Mutagen</source><year>1992</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1425610</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shuang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenfang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytosterols and dementia</article-title><source>Plant Foods Hum Nutr</source><year>2016</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27663717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jayasena</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Poljak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Smythe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Braidy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;nch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachdev</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of polyphenols in the modulation of sirtuins and other pathways involved in Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Ageing Res Rev</source><year>2013</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>867</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23831960</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>