<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Instead of extracting the PI under dry rubber form, it can be extracted as an emulsion. Spence was the first to propose a latex process [
 <xref rid="B85-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Plants are directly processed upon harvest. They are crushed and milled in a buffer solution (pH &gt; 7.2) to prevent PI coagulation, by maintaining the hydrogen ion concentration close to the plant itself. A diluted latex dispersion is formed, then filtered and put in settling tanks where the fine particles (biomass, sand), are separated. By using centrifugation, a concentrated latex (GNRL; 40% of PI) can be prepared. Eventually a heating and acidifying step allows to obtain coagulated rubber (GNRL) [
 <xref rid="B85-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Like previous processes, some improvements have since been made:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>Improvement of centrifugation: a continuous process using a centrifugal separator to concentrate dilute rubber dispersion in such a way that little or no pasty or firmly coagulated rubber is formed in the bowl to avoid interfering with the efficiency of separation [
    <xref rid="B86-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Improvement of the cleaning of the product: by cleaning the latex with polar and non-polar solvent (simultaneously or sequentially) or by freezing the latex, or drying the latex to obtain dry rubber [
    <xref rid="B87-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Improvement of grinding shrub: grinding plants by rotary shearing [
    <xref rid="B50-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Improvement of latex stabilization: in order to stabilize the latex, grinding of the plants can be made in a buffer containing ammonium hydroxide (or potassium hydroxide, sodium colehydroxide, sodium bicarbonate) and an antioxidant, such as sodium sulfite (or butylated hydroxytoluene, butylated hydroxyanisole) [
    <xref rid="B90-molecules-26-00664" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
