<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Mexican oregano EO, the hydrosol and the extracts and subfractions obtained from oregano bagasse were analyzed using a GC Perkin Elmer Turbo Mass Gold MS-Auto system XLTM (Perkin-Elmer, Norwalk, CT, USA) with a splitless injector and 70 eV electronic fragmentation detector, equipped with an AT-1 capillary column (30 m × 0.25 I.D. × 0.25 μm). Helium was used as the carrier gas, and the following conditions were set for the analysis: the temperature of the injector and detector was 220 °C; the initial oven temperature was 120 °C held for 1 min, followed by a ramp-up of 3 °C/min up to 180 °C, and a second ramp-up of 25 °C/min up to 225 °C, and held at the final temperature for 7 min, with a flow of 10 mL/min. For all samples (EO and extracts, at an initial concentration of 10 mg/mL), ethyl alcohol was used as solvent for GC–MS analysis; the volume used for injection was 1 µL, and the relative abundance was determined for each of the components identified in the chromatogram. The spectra obtained were compared with the mass spectra for the respective pure compounds and with the mass profile of the same compounds available from the US National Institute of Standard Technology (NIST) library. For the MS analysis, the molecular weight range was of 35–430 
 <italic class="italic">m/z</italic>. The chromatographic peaks were identified by comparison with their Kovats retention indices (RI), based on mass spectral-retention index libraries, considering the temperature of analysis [
 <xref rid="B46-plants-08-00022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. Thymol and carvacrol were further quantified by external standard calibration (0.5 to 5.0 mg/mL), using the pure compounds (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA). In all extracts, the rosmarinic and caffeic acids were elucidated using HPLC (Agilent model 1000, Palo Alto, CA, USA) with a zorbax eclipse C18 reverse phase column (5 μm in particle size, 250 mm in length and 4.6 mm in inner diameter) at 30 °C, with a wavelength of 280–520 nm, and a flow rate of 1 mL/min, using the following solvent gradients: gradient A—90% water-ATF 0.1%; and gradient B—10% ethanol.
</p>
