<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">The C-terminal tail of HLF1, on the other hand, is very likely much more effective compared to the C-termini of both HLF3l and HLF4b. Even at the low concentration of 0.32 μmol/l in the thrombin time assay HLF1V completely blocked the activity of hirudin (Müller et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020</xref>). The inhibitory potencies of both HLF-Hyb3c and HLF-Hyb4b were much lower (Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), and this might very well be explained by a combination of length and charge effects of their C-terminal tails. The C-terminal tails of hirudins block the exosite 1, the fibrinogen binding site, of thrombin (Rydel et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1991</xref>; Maraganore et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">1989</xref>; Fenton 2nd et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1991</xref>). This effect is mainly due to several ionic and non-ionic interactions between particular amino acid residues in both hirudin and thrombin (Betz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1991b</xref>; Huang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2014</xref>; Braun et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1988</xref>). Of particular importance within this context are the numerous acidic amino acid residues (7 out of 29 residues in HV1, 9 out of 27 residues in HM1) (Betz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1991a</xref>). HLF1V (13 out of 24) contains even more acidic amino acid residues in its tail. However, as already pointed out, an elongated acidic tail per se does not guarantee a significant inhibitory potency of a hirudin or a hirudin-like factor but needs a functional N-terminus and an appropriate central globular domain as well. We therefore concluded that the C-terminal tails are much less constrained compared to the N-termini and the central globular domains with respect to determining thrombin-inhibitory potency of the resulting molecules. However, an overall acidic character of the C-terminus seemed to be essential for thrombin inhibiting potency of the final construct (Müller et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020</xref>). The C-terminal tails of HLF3l and HLF4b almost perfectly fit into this scheme. Both are shorter compared to HV1 and HLF1 but contain several charged amino acid residues (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). However, whereas the tail of HLF4b is shorter, but indeed acidic and negatively charged (pI value of 4.53), the tail of HLF3l is longer, but basic and positively charged (pI value of 9.40). The shorter and acidic tail of HLF4b resulted in a somewhat higher thrombin-inhibitory potency compared with HLF3l which has the longer, but positively charged tail (compare the activities of HLF-Hyb3b and HLF-Hyb4c; Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). We concluded that an overall acidic character of the C-terminal tail of hirudins/hirudin-like factors is advantageous, but not absolutely mandatory for anti-thrombin activity, as long as several charged including some acidic amino acid residues are present.
</p>
