<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The mechanisms of action of the antigenotoxic agents are complex and can be categorized according to the site of action or by the specific type of action. An obvious approach is to avoid exposure to recognized risk factors. However, complementary strategies are to render the organism more resistant to mutagens/carcinogens and/or to inhibit progression of the chronic disease by administering chemopreventive agents. In a primary prevention setting, addressed to apparently healthy individuals, it is possible to inhibit mutation and cancer initiation by triggering protective mechanisms either in the extracellular and intracellular environment, e.g., modifying transmembrane transport, modulating metabolism, blocking reactive species, inhibiting cell replication, maintaining DNA structure, modulating DNA metabolism and repair, and controlling gene expression. Tumor promotion can be counteracted by favoring antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activity, inhibiting proteases and cell proliferation, inducing cell differentiation, and modulating apoptosis and signal transduction pathways. In a secondary prevention setting, when a premalignant lesion has been detected, it is possible to inhibit tumor progression via the same mechanisms or through affecting the hormonal status and the immune system, and inhibiting tumor angiogenesis. Finally, in tertiary prevention (strategy considered outside of the classical definition of chemoprevention) addressed to cancer patients after therapy, similar mechanisms have been explored, highlighting the possibility to affect cell-adhesion molecules and activation of antimetastasis genes [
 <xref rid="B7-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. The main chemopreventive mechanisms along with some examples of dietary antimutagens are shown in 
 <xref rid="nutrients-10-01954-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>.
</p>
