<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nutmeg has antioxidant and antimicrobial properties which can be used to protect chewable gel tablets from mold (fungal growth). It has an effect on 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Shigella dysteriae</italic>, 
 <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic>, also, 
 <italic>Myristica fragrans</italic> extracts prepared in different conditions have many other activities against other bacteria [
 <xref rid="B22-pharmaceutics-13-00238" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-pharmaceutics-13-00238" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-pharmaceutics-13-00238" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-pharmaceutics-13-00238" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-pharmaceutics-13-00238" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Additionally, it was determined that nutmeg essential oil has effect on suppressed 
 <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic>, 
 <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> (referent), and 
 <italic>Pasteurella multocida</italic> bacteria [
 <xref rid="B32-pharmaceutics-13-00238" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Talking about 
 <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic>, it is related to oral diseases, such as caries, endodontic infections, periodontitis, and peri-implantitis [
 <xref rid="B33-pharmaceutics-13-00238" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-pharmaceutics-13-00238" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Using natural essential oil or other materials from nature can help reduce bacterial growth. Antioxidant compounds in nutmeg seeds are: myristphenone, phenolic volatile compounds, phenolic acid (caffeic acid), flavanols (catechin). Compared with other spices and herbs, nutmeg has more than 50% activity of inhibition of DPPH (2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl) [
 <xref rid="B22-pharmaceutics-13-00238" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-pharmaceutics-13-00238" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Nutmeg can not only preserve a product and prolong its shelf life (which is very important for chewable gel tablets that have water in their composition) but also it decreases bacterial growth in mouth and binds free radicals, this adds additional benefits.
</p>
