<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Flavonoids are commonly found in nature and are well known to contribute to the various aromas and colours of plants [
 <xref rid="B77-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Likewise, in the 
 <italic>Echium</italic> species, flavonoids together with glycosylation and conjugation (especially C3 substituted flavonoids) have been extensively identified. This includes flavones, such as apigenin and luteolin, flavonols, such as quercetin and kaempferol, as well as anthocyanins, such as delphinidin and cyanidin (
 <xref rid="antioxidants-09-00722-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-antioxidants-09-00722">Figure S1</xref>). Identification of flavonoids within 
 <italic>Echium</italic> has been predominately conducted by comparison of analytical standards via high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) attached to various analysis detectors, such as a diode-array detector (DAD) or pulsed amperometric detector (PAD). Kefi et al. [
 <xref rid="B57-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] reported that four flavonoids (luteolin-7-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucoside, myricitrin, myricetin, and quercetin) were identified from 
 <italic>E. arenarium</italic> extracts by RP-HPLC analysis, with Luteolin-7-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucoside (60.56 μg/mg DE) the major flavonoid among all the compounds. Identification of nineteen flavonoids, in various species, both in coloured and noncoloured extracts have been described, including kaempferol, peonidin, cyanidin, malvidin, and their monoglucoside or disaccharide C3-linked derivatives, with kaempferol-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-neohesperidoside found to be the major constituent [
 <xref rid="B78-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B79-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Radwan et al. [
 <xref rid="B55-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] used proton nuclear magnetic resonance (
 <sup>1</sup>H-NMR) and fast atom bombardment (FAB-MS) to characterise four flavonoids, such as apigenin, luteolin-7-
 <italic>O</italic>-rutinoside, apigenin-7-
 <italic>O</italic>-rhamnoside, and quercetin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-rhamnoside. These compounds were identified in 
 <italic>E. sericeum (E. creticum</italic>).
</p>
