<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Structural impact on regeneration refers to alien plants causing changes in the structural biotope characteristics of the native environment, nutrient and/or water cycles, disturbance regimes, or natural succession. At species level the structural impact was observed for the IAS 
 <italic>Prunus serotina, Robinia pseudoacacia</italic> and 
 <italic>Ailathus altissima</italic> (
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">Rahmonov, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Campagnaro et al., 2018</xref>). This impact mechanism is mainly discussed as the indirect ability of individual plant invaders to serve as indicators for changes in forest habitat structures and functions as well as regeneration (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Campagnaro et al., 2018</xref>). Structural impacts on regeneration include the homogenization of species composition in the herb layer, changes to the seed bank, effects on species diversity and changes in the forest structure due to ruderalization (
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">Rahmonov, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Halarewicz and Zołnierz, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">Staska et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Nobis et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Campagnaro et al., 2018</xref>). The effects of structural changes to forest ecosystems are time-dependent. For example, structural changes caused by the invasion of a deciduous forest by 
 <italic>Impatiens glandulifera</italic> are documented as becoming visible 5 years after the invasion and causing significant alterations after 13 years (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">Rusterholz et al., 2017</xref>). Oak forests and riparian forests in particular are reported as being affected by the impact mechanism of structural changes caused by alien plants (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Kopeć et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Nobis et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Chudomelová et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">Nobis et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Radovanović et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
