<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Phenolic compounds inhibit lipid oxidation by scavenging free radicals, chelating metals, activating antioxidant enzymes, reducing tocopherol radicals and inhibiting enzymes that cause oxidation reactions. The conducted studies may provide the basis for the rapidly growing interest in the use of natural antioxidants and antimicrobials. The difference in the extraction yields could probably be explained by the different methods of extraction and the considered solvents. The selection of a suitable solvent is an essential point for the obtainment of phenolics extracts with high antioxidant activity, which is useful for the development and application of the extracts derived from different parts of walnut. In most studies, dealing with the extraction and evaluation of the antioxidant content of different parts of walnut tree, the prepared extracts using polar solvents (methanol, ethanol or water) exhibited higher phenolic content and antioxidant potential than the extracts prepared by nonpolar solvents, i.e., petroleum ether or n-hexane. This fact can be supported by the importance of solvent polarity and also the solubility of different phenolic compounds. Thus, the solubility and the efficiency of the extraction procedure are considerably affected by the differences in the polarity of the solvents used. Various polar solvents were reported to be the best choice for the extraction of phenolics constituents from different parts of the walnut plant, while the non-polar solvents were found as non-effective solvents and frequently used for the extraction of less polar compounds, such as chlorophylls, carotenoids tocotrienols, and tocopherols. Therefore, the obtained walnut extracts using polar solvents are probably contained phenolics (phenolic acids, flavonoids, and tannins), while the resulting extracts from nonpolar solvents are mostly enriched in non-polar constituents such as tocopherols, tocotrienols, fatty acids and sterols and deficient in phenolic compounds. Methanol, ethanol and the hydroalcoholic are generally suggested as suitable extraction solvents for the preparation of the phenolic extract. Additionally, the differences may be attributed in part to different extraction methods, varieties evaluated, year of harvest, orchard location, processing, and storage. The differences in phenolic compound distribution in different parts of the nut could be the reason for the low content of total phenolic in walnut oil.</p>
