<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to previous researches, phenological and harvest stages are bare bone essential factors that influence phenolic compounds contents as well as their biological activities in different organs of medicinal plants(Esmaeili et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31916-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Grevsen et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31916-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Hazrati et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31916-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Choosing the best‐growing stage will help us to harvest the higher amount of essential oil yield as well as other beneficial compounds. Moreover, the amount of phenolic compounds in medicinal plants is affected by genetic variation among different species, even within the same species and also by the maturity of plant organs at harvest time (Alirezalu et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31916-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Deveci et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31916-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Hazrati et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31916-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>; Li et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31916-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31916-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). However, the proper time of harvest to achieve the maximum beneficial compounds of 
 <italic>H. persicum</italic> remains unknown and needs more research work. Until now, there is limited information on phenolic compounds of 
 <italic>H. persicum</italic> in different organs and different growth stages. Thus, it is essential to specify more precisely the time when 
 <italic>H. persicum</italic> plant should be harvested to attain the highest possible quality and quantity of beneficial contents. In this study, we aimed to investigate the distribution pattern of phenolic compounds and essential oil in the 
 <italic>H. persicum</italic>. We also tried to find the best phenological stage that has the high concentration of these components in the aerial parts of 
 <italic>H. persicum</italic> that were collected from the Iranian population at different developmental stages. To the extent of our knowledge, this is the first report aimed to evaluate the phytochemical composition of different growing stages of 
 <italic>H. persicum</italic>, during its biological cycle, which results will be useful to find the best harvest time to reach the high beneficial yield with less harm to the environment.
</p>
