<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As shown in 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>
 </xref>a, how surface roughness and surface energy affect surface wettability is determined by the intrinsic wetting threshold (IWT) of the water, which is the boundary of the wettability between hydrophilic and hydrophobic when the liquid is deposited.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4" class="xref">4</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup> When the intrinsic WCA (θ) on a flat solid surface is larger than 
 <italic class="italic">θ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">I</sub>
 <sub class="sub">W</sub>
 <sub class="sub">T</sub>, superhydrophobic surfaces can be obtained by increasing the surface roughness. Conversely, when the intrinsic WCA (θ) on a flat solid surface is smaller than 
 <italic class="italic">θ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">I</sub>
 <sub class="sub">W</sub>
 <sub class="sub">T</sub>, superhydrophilic surfaces can be obtained. The relationship between surface roughness and apparent contact angle (θ
 <sub class="sub">a</sub>) can be described by the Koch curve fractal formula:
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15" class="xref">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup>
 <inline-formula id="d30e227" class="inline-formula">
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="oc-2018-00504w_m001.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>. 
 <italic class="italic">f</italic>
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is the fraction of the air surface under the water droplet, and 
 <italic class="italic">f</italic>
 <sub class="sub">1</sub> + 
 <italic class="italic">f</italic>
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> = 1. 
 <italic class="italic">L</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">l</italic> are the upper- and lower-limit scales of the surface, respectively, and 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> is the fractal dimension. Surface roughness and apparent contact angle have close ties to the value of 
 <italic class="italic">L</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">l</italic>. Thus, the existence of a nanoscale structure promotes superwettability. It is worth mentioning that 90° is considered as the intrinsic wetting threshold of water according to Young’s equation. However, by considering the interphase water molecular interactions and structures, a lower intrinsic wetting threshold of 65° is proposed. The WCA of 65° has also been proven to be the limit between hydrophilicity and hydrophobicity when increasing surface roughness to construct superhydrophilic or superhydrophobic surfaces.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9" class="xref">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17" class="xref">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup> It is the key criteria to construct artificial superhydrophilic and superhydrophobic materials.
</p>
