<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030">Metal incorporated nanoparticles have received wide interest in the area of industrial and medicinal applications. Among them, Nobel metals gold, silver, platinum and palladium based nanoparticles have received much attention due to their unique electrical, optical and electronic as well as catalytic properties. Nanoparticles reveal atom like behaviours due to high surface to volume area and wide gap between valance band and conduction band [
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Silver Nanoparticles have initiated useful interest not only fundamental development in research but also the industrial level owing to their versatile properties [
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>]. This feature has attracted many researchers to find new methods for their synthesis [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. A number of physical and chemical methods like reduction in solutions, thermal decomposition of silver compound, microwave assisted and photochemical reactions have been reported by several workers. The most common method for the synthesis of silver nanoparticles is a chemical reduction using inorganic and organic reducing agents such as hydrazine [
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], N-dimethylformamide [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], Sodium borohydride [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], poly(ethyleneglycol) [
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and surfactant template approach [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The synthesis of nanoparticles through green routes using microorganisms [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>] enzymes [
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and plant extracts [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>]were suggested as possible environmental friendly alternatives to chemical methods. Additionally, these methods were reported to be of cost effective and synthesized particles were found more stable. Several medicinal plants such as 
 <italic>Acorus calamus</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], 
 <italic>Alternanthera dentata</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], 
 <italic>Ocimumsanctum</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], 
 <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], 
 <italic>Brassica rapa</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], 
 <italic>Coccinia indica</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], 
 <italic>Vitex negundo</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], 
 <italic>Melia dubia</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]have already been used to synthesize and stabilize metallic NPs, very particularly biogenic AgNPs.
</p>
