<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Myricetin (
 <bold>18</bold>), 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-03846-f003">Figure 3</xref>, is commonly found in foods such as fruits, berries, nuts, vegetables, and tea, but has also been isolated from medicinal plants in the Myricaceae family like 
 <italic>Myrica rubra</italic>. In contrast to its known antioxidant properties, myricetin also appeared to be a possible pro-oxidant, especially in the presence of specific ions such as Fe
 <sup>2+</sup> (compare to resveratrol below). Thus, there have been concerns that myricetin may cause DNA damage. In contrast, some studies showed that myricetin could protect cells from mutagenesis and tumorigenesis by environmental pollutants like polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, but the mechanism of its protective action was not established. Myricetin is also considered to possess powerful anti-inflammatory activity, although the evidence is mostly from animal models and in vitro studies. Various mechanisms for its action have been proposed including the inhibition of cytokines, IL-12, IL-1β and TNFα or the inhibition of cyclooxygenase and lipoxygenase enzymes, COX-1, COX -2, and 5-LOX [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Myricetin was also tested in clinical trials as an antidiabetic agent, although with equivocal results [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. It was suggested to act as an inhibitor of the glucose transporters, GLUT2 and GLUT4, and thus interfere with the normal uptake of glucose [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Other mechanisms were proposed as well, such as agonistic activity towards GPCRs (G protein-coupled receptors) [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Myricetin affects cholesterol levels as well as being anti-inflammatory, and these functions may also afford some benefit in diabetes [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Myricetin has demonstrated antiviral and neuroprotective activity in vitro. It was also suggested to be of benefit in atherosclerosis and in vascular conditions through its antithrombotic activity, though little data are available to support this. Overall, clinical data proving that myricetin is medicinally useful are still missing. It is marketed as a dietary supplement and is also available in dihydro form (ampelopsin; 
 <bold>19</bold>), 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-03846-f003">Figure 3</xref>, which was also claimed to be of benefit in various diseases. It was especially promoted in alcohol use disorders, exerting its effect via interaction with GABA receptors [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].
</p>
