<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Patients with weak immunity when infected with a contagious viral infection can be deadly and the recent novel coronavirus pandemic showed that immunocompromised people are especially vulnerable to the COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B236-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">236</xref>]. Serious efforts have been made to synthesize antiviral agents with efficient activity. Natural bioactive flavonoids present in medicinal plants and herbs have been widely reported to have antiviral activity and are concentrated and modified for its better action [
 <xref rid="B237-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>]. 
 <italic>Houttuynia cordata</italic> Thunb is a plant found in Eastern Asia, having promising antiviral activities against enveloped viruses such as influenza virus, herpes simplex virus-1 and human immunodeficiency virus-1 in vitro [
 <xref rid="B238-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">238</xref>]. Both natural and synthetic flavonoids are potential medicines for many diseases, including HIV [
 <xref rid="B239-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">239</xref>]. Glabranine and 7-
 <italic>O</italic>-methyl-glabranine are the two flavonoids extracted from Mexican plant 
 <italic>Tephrosia madrensis</italic>. The plaque assay confirmed that these isolates exhibit antiviral activities, and inhibit dengue virus replication. The structures of the isolates were determined spectroscopically and then the stoichiometry was analyzed alongside cytotoxicity using [3
 <italic>H</italic>]-thymidine assay. At a concentration of 25 μM, glabranine inhibited the dengue virus by 76.9% while 7-
 <italic>O</italic>-methyl-glabranine inhibited the replication of virus at the same concentration by 75%. Both of these compounds have a prenyl side-chain in C-8 which is considered to have a role in inhibition of virus (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05243-f009">Figure 9</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B240-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">240</xref>], and catechins against the influenza virus [
 <xref rid="B241-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">241</xref>]. Anthocyanins found in berry fruits have antiviral activity against influenza virus [
 <xref rid="B242-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">242</xref>]. Baicalein, quercetin, and fisetin are active inhibitors of chikungunya virus [
 <xref rid="B243-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">243</xref>]. The epicatechin 3-gallate, fisetin, quercetin reduces murine norovirus and daidzein, and kaempferol reduce feline calicivirus [
 <xref rid="B244-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">244</xref>]. Four flavonoids (5-hydroxy-7,8-dimethoxyflavone, 5-hydroxy-6,7-dimethoxyflavone, acacetin, apigenin) extracted from 
 <italic>Mosla scabra</italic> display antiviral activity against influenza viruses [
 <xref rid="B245-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">245</xref>]. Burs (involucre) of 
 <italic>Castanea crenata</italic>, have a wide range of biological activities attributed to the bioactive phtyo-constituents present in it that includes flavonoid, tannins, phenolic acids, coumarins, phenylpropanoids, and steroids. The antiviral activity of the extract was determined by SRB method using cytopathic effect (CPE) reduction assay in HeLa or Vero cells. The isolated flavonoid, kaempferol, showed enhanced antiviral properties against HRV1B, CVB3, and PR8 [
 <xref rid="B246-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">246</xref>]. Using molecular docking and simulation studies, flavonoid analogues are also found to be active against H1N1 virus neuraminidase [
 <xref rid="B247-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">247</xref>]. Of the various types of influenza virus, IAV is a single stranded RNA virus that is dangerous and most responsible for an annual deaths of around 500,000 globally. The antigenic shift give rise to new a subtype of viruses, this occurs when two or more strains of same virus or of different viruses combine or mutate to form a new subtype that is resistance to available, common antiviral agents. Purified guava flavonoid glycosides inhibit IAV replication by early regulation of interleukin-1 beta and interleukin-8 via protein gene expression [
 <xref rid="B248-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">248</xref>].
</p>
