<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0005">Recurrent urinary tract infections (UTIs) are the most frequent infectious diseases to human beings, which caused by overuse of frequent antibiotics consumption (
 <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Michael et al., 2015</xref>). Worldwide, every person has suffered by UTIs at least one time in their life, and 10% of the women got recurrent UTIs (
 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">Nabakishore et al., 2014</xref>). Most of the UTIs are caused by enterobacteriaceae with multi drug resistance (MDRs) ability. Among the enterobacteriaceae, the topmost pathogen is 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> and second most bacteria is 
 <italic>P. mirabilis</italic>, both are covered almost 90% of complicated UTIs (
 <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Jarratt and Miller, 2013</xref>). In particular, the 
 <italic>P. mirabilis</italic> caused UTIs are very important, because it connected with all the UTIs parts and make abnormalities and long term catheterized infections (
 <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Mohammad Reza et al., 2019</xref>). The unnecessary dosage of drug and antibiotic consumption lead to persistent the development of resistance in 
 <italic>P. mirabilis</italic> (
 <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Mehri et al., 2015</xref>). Those extracellular leakages are affecting the beta lactam ring due to the beta lactamases enzyme production (
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Dhanasekaran et al., 2019</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">Rajivgandhi et al., 2014</xref>). Importantly, 
 <italic>P. mirabilis</italic> has more virulence factors including MR/P fimbriae, cell signaling factors of QS, enzymes of ESBLs and carbapenemases, which are responsible for frequent development of recurrent and continuous catheterization due to the antibiotic denature (
 <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Jarratt and Miller, 2013</xref>). Among the different virulence factors, the biofilm formation is a major virulence factors in 
 <italic>P. mirabilis</italic> causing UTIs. The biofilm formed 
 <italic>P. mirabilis</italic> has critical roles in UTIs and make MDRs and recurrent infections to current antibiotics.
</p>
