<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">The 
 <italic>S. nigrum</italic> is a medicinal plant which available in entire world including temporal and tropical regions, and several countries including Saudi Arabia (
 <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Migahid, 1996</xref>). It is used in various biomedical fields due to the extraordinary medicinal properties. In particular, morethan 100 years it is frequently used in cancer treatment and reported by many researchers (
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Razali et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Murungi et al., 2013</xref>). It is frequently strengthening the traditional value and believes that this 
 <italic>S. nigrum</italic> has excess biomedicine properties like antimicrobial, antiviral, larvicidal, anti-oxidant and anti-cancer (
 <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Jeong et al., 2010</xref>). It directly involved in the DNA damages in bacteria, fungus and viruses. Also, the most favorable MCF-7 inhibitor compound of 12-O-Tetradecene-noylphorbol-13-acetate is reported from plant of 
 <italic>S. nigrum</italic> (
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Razali et al., (2016</xref>). Consecutively, the essential oils of 
 <italic>S. nigrum</italic> also have several biomedical activities including anti-oxidant, anti-biofilm, anti-microbial and anti-cancer activities (
 <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Mallika and Chennam Srinivasulu, 2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Razali et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Murungi et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">Ibanez and Blazquez, 2020</xref>). It has more polysachharide derivatives and simply called as black nightshade. Also, it is a short live plant, which given more biomedical properties in their short period. The seeds of 
 <italic>S. nigrum</italic> have excellent antimicrobial, anti-biofilm and anti-cancer activity. It is extensively use in traditional medicine in India and also other countries (
 <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Wu-Ching et al., 2018</xref>). It is a well-known plant that frequently used in Indian homes for inflammation, pain, fever, jaundice, eye infections and some other common infections. Therefore, we have chosen 
 <italic>S. nigrum</italic> for this study to inhibit biofilm producing 
 <italic>P. mirabilis</italic>.
</p>
