<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="T3" position="float">
 <label>Table 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>The cross-culturally most salient medicinal plant species in Mesoamerica (MA).</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taxon (Family) – English vernacular name – common names in MA</th>
    <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># of studies citing (# use-records)</th>
    <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predominant uses (# of studies) and brief description</th>
    <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pharmacological evidence on possible therapeutic benefits related to predominant uses</th>
    <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toxicological evidence on the safety of traditional uses</th>
    <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evaluation</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Dysphania ambrosioides</italic>
     </bold> (L.) Mosyakin &amp; Clemants (syn.: 
     <italic>Chenopodium ambrosioides</italic> L.); Amaranthaceae) – wormseed – 
     <italic>epazote</italic>
     <break/>Native1
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (62)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (22), particularly as anthelmintic; skin (10);
     <break/>Infusion of aromatic aerial parts used throughout MA against gastrointestinal parasites; added to bean dishes as a condiment. Aerial parts are topically applied to treat skin infections.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiascariasis: observational study with 60 children aged 3–14 with diagnosed ascariasis; 30 children received plant juice (1–2 ml/kg/d for 3 days) and 30 children received the standard anthelmintic drug albendazole (200-400 mg single dose). The qualitative efficacy, as measured in complete eradication of eggs in fecal samples, was similar in both groups (59.5% vs. 58.3%; 
     <xref rid="B288" ref-type="bibr">López de Guimaraes et al., 2001</xref>). Nematocidal activity demonstrated in several preclinical studies (
     <xref rid="B295" ref-type="bibr">MacDonald et al., 2004</xref>).
     <break/>Anti-
     <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>: 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> MIC of 16 μg/ml essential oil; 60% eradication of 
     <italic>H</italic>. 
     <italic>pylori</italic> in mice receiving essential oil (49.32 mg/kg/d PO for 28 days) was below the 70% eradication in mice receiving triple antibiotic treatment (lansoprazole, metronidazole, and clarithromycin) (
     <xref rid="B491" ref-type="bibr">Ye et al., 2015</xref>).
     <break/>Antileishmaniasis: prevention of lesion development in mice infected with 
     <italic>Leishmania amazonensis</italic> receiving essential oil (30 mg/kg ID every 4 days for 14 days) was statistically superior to treatment with the standard leishmaniasis drug glucantime (28 mg/kg ID every 4 days for 14 days) (
     <xref rid="B325" ref-type="bibr">Monzote et al., 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">While infusions appear to be safe, toxicological issues persist in regard to the internal use of the essential oil, due to high concentrations of the terpene ascaridole (
     <xref rid="B295" ref-type="bibr">MacDonald et al., 2004</xref>). No significant signs of acute (0.3-3 mg/kg, IG) or subchronic (0.3-1 mg/kg/d, PO, 15 days) toxicity from aqueous leaf extracts in rats (
     <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr">da Silva et al., 2014</xref>); nor for subchronic (5–500 mg/kg/d PO for 15 days) toxicity from hydroalcoholic leaf extracts in mice was noted (
     <xref rid="B365" ref-type="bibr">Pereira et al., 2010</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good evidence on therapeutic benefits and safe with reservations
     <break/>D1
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Psidium guajava</italic>
     </bold> L. (Myrtaceae) – guava – 
     <italic>guayaba</italic>
     <break/>Native2
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (66)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (23), particularly as antidiarrheal; skin (12);
     <break/>Infusion of astringent leaves used throughout MA against diarrheal disorders and maceration topically for inflammatory skin conditions; common fruit tree.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antidiarrheal and antispasmodic: randomized, double blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial with 100 adult patients (61 f, 39 m), aged 20-59, diagnosed with acute diarrheic disease; treatment group (n = 50) received one capsule containing 500 mg leaf preparation standardized for concentration of the flavonoid quercetin (1 mg/capsule) every 8 h for 3 days; while there was no significant difference in five outcome measures (number of defecation/d, consistency of stool, presence of mucus in stool, presence of fever, episodes of vomiting), the remaining 2 (degree of abdominal pain, number of spasms/d) were significantly improved in the treatment group in comparison to placebo (
     <xref rid="B292" ref-type="bibr">Lozoya et al., 2002</xref>).
     <break/>ntidiarrheal and antirotavirus: observational study with 62 children aged 2–18 diagnosed with infantile rotaviral enteritis; improvement in all four outcome measures (recovery rate after 3 days, time of ceasing diarrhea, content of Na
     <sup>+</sup> and glucose in stool, rate of negative conversion of human rotavirus antigen) was significantly superior in the treatment group (n=31) receiving aqueous leaf extract (10–20 g every 12 h for 3 days) in comparison to the control group (n = 31) receiving the Chinese compound drug 
     <italic>gegen qinlian</italic> (33
     <italic> g</italic> every 12 h for 3 days; 
     <xref rid="B466" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2000</xref>).
     <break/>Antidiarrheal, spasmolytic, antiinflammatory, broad antibacterial (incl. gastrointestinal as well as dermatological pathogens), fungicidal, and antirotavirus activity of aqueous and alcoholic leaf and bark extracts at therapeutically realistic doses demonstrated in a number of 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> models, as extensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B208" ref-type="bibr">Gutiérrez et al., 2008</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B326" ref-type="bibr">Morais-Braga et al., 2016</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No adverse effects in clinical trial administering 500 mg leaves every 8 h for 3 days to 50 adult patients (
     <xref rid="B292" ref-type="bibr">Lozoya et al., 2002</xref>).
     <break/>Several 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> studies demonstrated no acute or subchronic toxicity at therapeutic doses, as extensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B208" ref-type="bibr">Gutiérrez et al., 2008</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B326" ref-type="bibr">Morais-Braga et al., 2016</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good evidence on therapeutic benefits and safety
     <break/>D2, S1
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Persea americana</italic>
     </bold> Mill. (Lauraceae) – avocado – 
     <italic>aguacate</italic>
     <break/>Native3
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (88)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (13); respiratory (10); skin (10); musculoskeletal (8); pregnancy (8);
     <break/>Leaves, bark, and seeds common for diverse therapeutic uses throughout MA, apart from its culinary uses. For gastrointestinal and respiratory uses oral administration is most frequent, whereas bathes and topic applications predominate for dermatological, musculoskeletal, pregnancy-related disorders.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antidiarrheal: significant, dose-dependent reduction in all 3 measures (water content in feces, frequency of defecation, enteropooling) of castor oil-induced diarrhea in rats after treatment with either chloroform or methanol leaf extract (100–200 mg/kg PO) (
     <xref rid="B121" ref-type="bibr">Christian et al., 2014</xref>).
     <break/>Anti-
     <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>: 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> MIC of 7.5 μg/ml methanolic leaf extract (
     <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Castillo-Juárez et al., 2009</xref>).
     <break/>Antidermatophytosis: 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> MIC of 31.3 μg/ml ethanolic leaf extract against 
     <italic>Trichophyton</italic> spp. (
     <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Biasi-Garbin et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Broad antimicrobial (incl. gastrointestinal, respiratory, dermatological, and gynecological pathogens): significant activity of chloroformic and ethanolic seed extracts (
     <xref rid="B245" ref-type="bibr">Jiménez-Arellanes et al., 2013</xref>), aqueous and ethanolic seed extracts (
     <xref rid="B387" ref-type="bibr">Raymond Chia and Dykes, 2010</xref>), aqueous and butanolic stem bark extract (
     <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Akinpelu et al., 2015</xref>), glycolic leaf extract (
     <xref rid="B244" ref-type="bibr">Jesus et al., 2015</xref>).
     <break/>Nutraceutical properties in relation to maternal health (
     <xref rid="B127" ref-type="bibr">Comerford et al, 2016</xref>), osteoarthritis (
     <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr">Christensen et al., 2008</xref>), and wound healing (
     <xref rid="B335" ref-type="bibr">Nayak et al., 2008</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity in rats at therapeutic doses (10–2,600 mg/kg PO) of chloroform-methanol leaf extract (
     <xref rid="B121" ref-type="bibr">Christian et al., 2014</xref>).
     <break/>No signs of subchronic toxicity in rats at therapeutic doses (2.5–10 mg/kg/d PO for 28 days) of aqueous seed extract (
     <xref rid="B352" ref-type="bibr">Ozolua et al., 2009</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe but limited evidence for efficacy of external uses
     <break/>D3, S2
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Ricinus</italic>
      <italic>communis</italic>
     </bold> L. (Euphorbiaceae) – castor oil plant – 
     <italic>higuerilla</italic>
     <break/>Exotic1
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (65)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (17); general and unspecified (15); musculoskeletal (7);
     <break/>Introduced species, seeds (rather than castor oil) used as emetic and purgative, leaves topically against pain (mostly stomachache, rheumatic pain, and general body pain).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Purgative: there is little doubt on the efficacy of castor oil for colon cleansing, yet there are more effective alternatives with less side effects (e.g., 
     <xref rid="B116" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 1999</xref>).
     <break/>Analgesic: methanolic leaf extracts (100–150 mg/kg IP) significantly reduced nociception in mice in the formalin, tail flick, and writhing tests similar to diclofenac (
     <xref rid="B439" ref-type="bibr">Taur et al., 2011</xref>).
     <break/>Antiosteoarthritis: randomized, double blind, comparative clinical trial with 100 adult patients (68 f, 32 m), aged 40–90, diagnosed with knee osteoarthritis; treatment group (n = 50) received one capsule containing 0.9 ml castor oil every 8 h for 28 days, the control group (n = 50) received diclofenac sodium (50 mg/8 h for 28 days); both groups reported similar reductions in symptoms, yet the control group reported more adverse side effects (
     <xref rid="B310" ref-type="bibr">Medhi et al., 2009</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The severe toxicity of castor seeds and particularly the lectin ricin has been extensively reviewed (e.g., 
     <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr">Doan, 2004</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B484" ref-type="bibr">Worbs et al., 2011</xref>). The hydrogenated castor oil is regarded as safe, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Anonymous, 2007</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good evidence on therapeutic benefits but highly toxic.
     <break/>Limited evidence on the safety and efficacy of the leaves
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Tagetes erecta</italic>
     </bold> L. (Asteraceae) – Aztec marigold – 
     <italic>cempoaxochitl</italic>
     <break/>Native4
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (75)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (15); general and unspecified (12), mostly for spiritual illnesses; respiratory (9); skin (9);
     <break/>Aerial parts of this common ornamental plant are used in infusions mainly for gastrointestinal pain and respiratory infections, macerations are topically applied for diverse skin conditions, and the flowers are important in healing rituals.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nematocidal: acetonic flower extract produced 99% lethal activity 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> against fourth larval stage of 
     <italic>Haemonchus contortus</italic> after 24 h (
     <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Aguilar et al., 2008</xref>).
     <break/>Antimicrobial: aqueous and organic root extracts demonstrated significant activity 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> against three Gram-positive and two Gram-negative bacteria and 2 fungal strains with MIC ranging 12.5–100 μg/ml (
     <xref rid="B206" ref-type="bibr">Gupta and Vasudeva, 2010</xref>).
     <break/>Analgesic: hydroalcoholic flower extract (100–300 mg/kg IP) induced significant, dose-dependent reduction in nociception in mice writhing test (
     <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Bashir and Gilani, 2008</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity of aqueous flower extract (0.03–12 mg/kg IP) in mice (
     <xref rid="B303" ref-type="bibr">Martínez et al., 2009</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence for safety and efficacy of traditional uses
     <break/>S3
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Zea mays</italic>
     </bold> L. (Poaceae) – maize – 
     <italic>maíz</italic>
     <break/>Native5
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (71)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urological (17), as diuretic; digestive (13); general and unspecified (9);
     <break/>Infusions of corn silk are used throughout MA as diuretic, kernels of the carbohydrate staple in diverse preparations as antidiarrhoeic, bracts and kernels particularly of red varieties in ritual healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diuretic: several studies demonstrated significantly increased urinary discharge as well as kaliuresis and natriuresis in rodents after oral administration of aqueous corn silk extracts, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B214" ref-type="bibr">Hasanudin et al., 2012</xref>). A randomized, double blind, placebo-controlled study on 38 healthy adult male volunteers aged 18–27, however, showed no significant difference in urine output over a 24 h period between treatment group (n = 19) receiving corn silk decoction (16.7 g every 8 h for 1 day) and placebo group receiving a cane sugar solution (
     <xref rid="B151" ref-type="bibr">Du Dat et al., 1992</xref>).
     <break/>Antidiarrhea: the efficacy in reducing duration and symptoms of diarrhea of maize-based oral rehydration solutions has been demonstrated in several clinical studies (e.g., 
     <xref rid="B489" ref-type="bibr">Yartey et al., 1995</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B379" ref-type="bibr">Ramakrishna et al., 2008</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity of aqueous extract up to 3200 mg/kg in mice after 48 h (
     <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Adedapo et al., 2016</xref>) and no signs of subchronic toxicity of aqueous corn silk extract 10 g/kg/d for 90 days) in rats (
     <xref rid="B465" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2011</xref>). Inconsistent results found by 
     <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Adedapo et al., 2016</xref> in mice developing tachycardia at 200 and 400 mg/kg/d over 7 days but not at 800 mg/kg/d as well as moderate inflammation of the atrium and ventricle at 400 and 800 mg/kg/d after 7 days.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and effective, with reservations for diuretic activity
     <break/>D4, U1
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic>
     </bold> (DC.) Stapf (Poaceae) – lemongrass - 
     <italic>zacate limón, telimón, té de limón</italic>
     <break/>Exotic2
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (52)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (10); respiratory (10); general and unspecified (7);
     <break/>Infusion of aromatic leaves used throughout MA for stomachache, cough, common cold, and flu.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broad antimicrobial: several preclinical studies demonstrated significant antimicrobial (incl. gastrointestinal and respiratory pathogens) activity attributed mostly to the essential oil fraction, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B154" ref-type="bibr">Ekpenyong et al., 2015</xref>).
     <break/>Analgesic and antiinflammatory: several preclinical studies demonstrated significant activity in different rodent models, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B154" ref-type="bibr">Ekpenyong et al., 2015</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute or subchronic toxicity on 11 (5 f, 6 m) healthy volunteers aged 19–24 receiving aqueous leaf extract (4g/d for 14 days) (
     <xref rid="B276" ref-type="bibr">Leite et al., 1986</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe and effective
     <break/>A1, D5, R1
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Ocimum</italic>
      <italic>basilicum</italic>
     </bold> L. (Lamiaceae) – basil – 
     <italic>albahaca</italic>
     <break/>Exotic3
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (67)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (14); digestive (11); neurological (9);
     <break/>Aromatic twigs used throughout MA for ritual healing, infusion of leaves drunk against gastrointestinal pain, maceration topically applied against headache.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broad antimicrobial: a number of preclinical studies reported significant antibacterial, antiviral and fungicidal activities attributed to essential oil fractions, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B433" ref-type="bibr">Suppakul et al., 2003</xref>).
     <break/>Anticolitis: essential oil (100–400 μl/kg PO) significantly protected rats from acetic acid-induced colitis (
     <xref rid="B386" ref-type="bibr">Rashidian et al., 2015</xref>).
     <break/>Analgesic: essential oil (50–200 mg/kg SC) significantly and dose-dependently reduced nociception in mice in the hot plate, formalin, and writhing tests (
     <xref rid="B458" ref-type="bibr">Venâncio et al., 2011</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute or subchronic toxicity at therapeutic doses of essential oil (&lt;1,000 mg/kg/d IG for 14 days) and hydroalcoholic leaf extract (50–500 mg/kg/d IG for 14 days) in rats (
     <xref rid="B163" ref-type="bibr">Fandohan et al., 2008</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B385" ref-type="bibr">Rasekh et al., 2012</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe and effective
     <break/>A2, D6, N1
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Piper auritum</italic>
     </bold> Kunth (Piperaceae) – 
     <italic>hierba santa, santa maria, acuyo, momo</italic>
     <break/>Native6
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (61)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (9); skin (9); musculoskeletal (7); general and unspecified (7);
     <break/>Apart from culinary uses, the aromatic leaves are used throughout MA to treat diverse inflammatory conditions internally and topically.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiinflammatory: significant effect of ethanolic leaf extract (287–863 mg/kg IP) in carrageenan-induced rat paw edema model (
     <xref rid="B456" ref-type="bibr">Vega Montalvo and Lagarto Parra, 1999</xref>).
     <break/>Antileishmaniasis: essential oil showed 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> IC
     <sub>50</sub> of 22.3 μg/ml against 
     <italic>L</italic>. 
     <italic>donovani</italic> (
     <xref rid="B324" ref-type="bibr">Monzote et al., 2010</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No sign of acute dermal toxicity or irritation in rabbits and rats treated with aqueous leaf extract (
     <xref rid="B287" ref-type="bibr">López Barreiro et al., 2014</xref>).
     <break/>Safrole, making up around 70% of essential oil, has well studied hepatotoxic and hepatocarcinogenic properties (
     <xref rid="B207" ref-type="bibr">Gupta et al., 1985</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B247" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 2011</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited data on efficacy and safety
     <break/>S4
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Byrsonima crassifolia</italic>
     </bold> (L.) Kunth (Malpighiaceae) – 
     <italic>nanche</italic>, 
     <italic>nance</italic>
     <break/>Native7
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (50)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (13), particularly as antidiarrheal; skin (8);
     <break/>Decoction of astringent bark of fruit tree used in lowland MA for diarrhea and inflammatory skin conditions.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiinflammatory: significant, dose-dependent effect of lipophilic bark extract (30–300 μg/cm
     <sup>2</sup> TOP) in croton oil-induced ear dermatitis in mice (
     <xref rid="B299" ref-type="bibr">Maldini et al., 2009</xref>).
     <break/>Antibacterial: moderate effects of root and stem extracts on several enteropathogenic strains in disk diffusion assay (
     <xref rid="B302" ref-type="bibr">Martínez-Vázquez et al., 1999</xref>). A 50% ethanolic bark extract showed activity against 
     <italic>Salmonella thyphi</italic> and 
     <italic>Shigella flexneri</italic> with inhibition zones ≥ 9 mm (
     <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Cáceres et al., 1990</xref>)
     <break/>Antifungal: significant effects (MIC 10–200 μg/ml) of aqueous and organic extracts from different organs on four dermatophytic strains (
     <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">Cáceres et al., 1993b</xref>).
     <break/>Wound healing: significant effects hexane seed extracts in different wound healing models in diabetic rats (
     <xref rid="B367" ref-type="bibr">Pérez Gutiérrez and Muñiz Ramirez, 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of serious acute toxicity of organic extracts of aerial parts in mice (500–2,000 mg/kg PO) (
     <xref rid="B224" ref-type="bibr">Herrera-Ruiz et al., 2011</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly effective and safe, yet no data on antidiarrheal activity
     <break/>D7, S5
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Phyla scaberrima</italic>
     </bold> (Juss. ex Pers.) Moldenke (syn.: 
     <italic>Lippia dulcis</italic>) (Verbenaceae) – Aztec sweet herb – 
     <italic>hierba dulce</italic>, 
     <italic>orozus</italic>
     <break/>Native8
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (40)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory (11); digestive (10);
     <break/>Infusions of sweet, aromatic leaves used throughout MA against stomachache and cough.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spasmolytic: significant effect of essential oil on porcine bronchial segments at 100 μg/ml (
     <xref rid="B198" ref-type="bibr">Görnemann et al., 2008</xref>).
     <break/>Antibacterial: moderate effects on several enteropathogenic strains of organic leaf extracts in disk diffusion assay (
     <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Cáceres et al., 1993a</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: ethanolic leaf extract (400 mg/kg PO; 0.5 mg/ear TOP) showed significant inhibition of carrageenan-induced rat paw edema and TPA-induced mice ear edema (
     <xref rid="B366" ref-type="bibr">Pérez et al., 2005</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camphor, present at relatively high concentrations in the leaves and flowers, could be responsible for toxic symptoms – such as nausea, drowsiness and abortifacient properties – sometimes reported after ingestion of the plant (
     <xref rid="B129" ref-type="bibr">Compadre et al., 1986</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly effective yet possibly toxic
     <break/>D8, R2
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Matricaria</italic>
      <italic>chamomilla</italic>
     </bold> L. (Asteraceae) – chamomile – 
     <italic>manzanilla</italic>
     <break/>Exotic4
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (57)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (14);
     <break/>Infusions of this aromatic introduced herb are used throughout MA to alleviate gastrointestinal pain.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spasms and inflammatory conditions of the digestive system: while internationally published clinical trials using only chamomile tea are lacking, the German Commission E has approved its internal use for spasms and inflammations of the gastrointestinal tract based on clinical trials (
     <xref rid="B480" ref-type="bibr">Wichtl, 2004</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B308" ref-type="bibr">McKay and Blumberg, 2006</xref>). Further, several RCTs using combinations of chamomile and other species demonstrated significant improvement on infants and children suffering from colic or diarrhea, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B308" ref-type="bibr">McKay and Blumberg, 2006</xref>).
     <break/>Antidiarrheal, broad antimicrobial, antiinflammatory, and antiulcer activities: have been demonstrated in a considerable number of 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> models, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B308" ref-type="bibr">McKay and Blumberg, 2006</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generally regarded as safe, although allergic reactions may occur (
     <xref rid="B480" ref-type="bibr">Wichtl, 2004</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B308" ref-type="bibr">McKay and Blumberg, 2006</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Likely effective and possibly safe
     <break/>D9
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Rosmarinus</italic>
      <italic>officinalis</italic>
     </bold> L. (Lamiaceae) – rosemary – 
     <italic>romero</italic>
     <break/>Exotic5
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (50)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (10); digestive (8); pregnancy (8);
     <break/>The aromatic twigs of this introduced species are used throughout MA in ritual healing, particularly as an alcoholic maceration; decoctions are drunk against stomachache and used in post-partum baths.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dyspepsia: while internationally published clinical trials are lacking, the German Commission E has approved the use of rosemary leaves for dyspeptic conditions (
     <xref rid="B480" ref-type="bibr">Wichtl, 2004</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B447" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2010</xref>).
     <break/>Improvement of mental state: some “methodologically weak” human trials showed significant effects of aromatherapy with rosemary essential oil, on cognitive performance and subjective well-being, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B447" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2010</xref>).
     <break/>Antidepressant and anxiolytic: several studies showed significant effects in different rodent models, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B447" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2010</xref>).
     <break/>Broad antimicrobial: a number of 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> studies have demonstrated moderate antibacterial and antifungal effects of various rosemary extracts, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B447" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2010</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: significant effects of various rosemary extracts have been demonstrated in several 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> models, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B447" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2010</xref>).
     <break/>Antinociceptive: significant effects of various rosemary extracts have been demonstrated in several 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> models, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B447" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2010</xref>).
     <break/>Antiparasitic: 3 studies showed significant effects of different extracts on different protozoan parasites, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B447" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2010</xref>).
     <break/>Antiulcer: a crude hydroalcoholic extract significantly reduced ulcerative lesion in several rat models, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B447" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2010</xref>).
     <break/>Antiviral: several studies report significant effects of various rosemary extracts on HI and herpes simplex virus, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B447" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2010</xref>).
     <break/>Spasmolytic: a single study demonstrated significant effects of an alcoholic leaf extract on isolated guinea pig ileum, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B447" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2010</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generally regarded as safe, although allergic reactions and interactions with other drugs may occur; unsafe for women who are pregnant or are trying to become pregnant (
     <xref rid="B480" ref-type="bibr">Wichtl, 2004</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B447" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2010</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly effective in certain conditions and likely safe with reservations
     <break/>A3, D10
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Sambucus canadensis</italic>
     </bold> L. (syn. 
     <italic>Sambucus nigra</italic> supsp. 
     <italic>canadensis</italic>) (Adoxaceae) – American elder – 
     <italic>saúco</italic>
     <break/>Native9
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (75)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory (14); skin (9); digestive (8);
     <break/>Infusions of the inflorescence are drunk against coughs; the leaves are used topically for skin infections and internally for gastrointestinal ailments.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungicidal: aqueous leaf extract was shown to be effective against several strains of dermatophytic fungi with tube dilution method (
     <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">Cáceres et al., 1991</xref>)
     <break/>Common cold: the use of the flowers of the closely related 
     <italic>S. nigra</italic> for colds has been approved by the German Commission E (
     <xref rid="B450" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2014</xref>). Antiviral: Several 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> studies reported significant antiinflammatory and antiviral (including several strains of influenza) effects of 
     <italic>S. nigra</italic> fruit extracts, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B450" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flowers from 
     <italic>S. canadensis</italic> are generally recognized as safe by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA). Products derived from other plant parts are potentially toxic due to the presence of considerable quantities of the cyanogenic glycoside sambunigrin.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flowers for respiratory conditions likely safe and effective; other uses likely unsafe
     <break/>R3, S6
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Tagetes lucida</italic>
     </bold> Cav. (Asteraceae) – sweet-scented marigold – 
     <italic>pericón</italic>
     <break/>Native10
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (55)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (12), mostly stomachache; pregnancy (8); general and unspecified (8), respiratory (7);
     <break/>Infusions of the anise-scented aerial parts are drunk against gastrointestinal pain and respiratory infections and used as washings after childbirth and in ritual healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broad antimicrobial: significant effects against several bacterial and fungal strains (incl. pathogens of the digestive and respiratory tract) shown in several 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> models (
     <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">Céspedes et al., 2006</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Castillo-Juárez et al., 2009</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B275" ref-type="bibr">Leal et al., 2014</xref>). A 10% alcoholic leaf and flower extract showed good activity against 
     <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> in the disk diffusion assay (50 μL/disc; unknown conc.) while the n-hexane extract (at 10, 30 and 50 μg) showed the best activity in the disk minimal inhibitory concentration method against different strains of the bacteria (
     <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">Cáceres et al., 1993c</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: induced nitric oxide and prostaglandin E2 production as well as the expression of COX-2 in macrophages was significantly inhibited by the essential oil (0.05–0.2 mg/ml) (
     <xref rid="B407" ref-type="bibr">Sepúlveda-Arias et al., 2013</xref>).
     <break/>Antidepressant and anxiolytic: aqueous and organic extracts (10–300 mg/kg IP or 5–200 mg/kg PO for 14 days) showed significant effects in various rodent models; the antidepressant-like effects were shown to be mediated 
     <italic>via</italic> a serotonergic mechanism (
     <xref rid="B204" ref-type="bibr">Guadarrama-Cruz et al., 2008</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B174" ref-type="bibr">Gabriela et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B205" ref-type="bibr">Guadarrama-Cruz et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Bonilla-Jaime et al., 2015</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B369" ref-type="bibr">Pérez-Ortega et al., 2016</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low acute toxicity in mice with LD
     <sub>50</sub> values of 2,000 mg/kg (IP) and 970 mg/kg (IP) for an aqueous and ethanolic extract respectively; after administration the mice did not show signs of toxicity during a 14 days observation period (
     <xref rid="B369" ref-type="bibr">Pérez-Ortega et al., 2016</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and effective
     <break/>A4, D11, R4
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Aloe vera</italic>
     </bold> (L.) Burm.f. (Asphodelaceae) – 
     <italic>sábila</italic>
     <break/>Exotic6
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (81)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (15); digestive (10); respiratory (10); musculoskeletal (9); general and unspecified (9);
     <break/>The leaves of this introduced ornamental are used internally and topically to treat diverse infectious and inflammatory conditions as well as pain and fever.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiinflammatory, analgesic, wound healing, antimicrobial, antiulcer and other pharmacological effects relevant to 
     <italic>A</italic>. 
     <italic>vera</italic>’s traditional uses have been demonstrated in a number of preclinical studies as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Akaberi et al., 2016</xref>). However, in most cases critical reviews find mixed, contradictory or insufficient evidence such as for wound healing (
     <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr">Dat et al., 2012</xref>) and ulcers (
     <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">Borrelli and Izzo, 2000</xref>). On the other hand, a systematic review on clinical efficacy concludes that aloe gel might be effective in the treatment of genital herpes and psoriasis while several studies suggest topical antiinflammatory properties of aloe gel in mice (
     <xref rid="B461" ref-type="bibr">Vogler and Ernst, 1999</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf juice and polysaccharides are safe as cosmetic ingredients with anthraquinone levels not exceeding 50 ppm.
     <break/>Aloe extracts for internal applications based on the laxative anthranoids are generally not regarded as safe (
     <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Andersen, 2007</xref>). Generally, ingestion of 
     <italic>A. vera</italic> derived products is associated with diarrhea, electrolyte imbalance, kidney dysfunction and drug-drug interaction; further, contact dermatitis, erythema, and phototoxicity have been reported from topical applications (
     <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">Boudreau and Beland, 2006</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effective and safe for topical applications, likely unsafe upon ingestion
     <break/>S7
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Bryophyllum pinnatum</italic>
     </bold> (Lam.) Oken (syn. 
     <italic>Kalanchoe pinnata</italic>) (Crassulaceae) – air plant, miracle leaf - 
     <italic>sanalotodo</italic>, 
     <italic>belladonna</italic>, 
     <italic>hoja de aire</italic>
     <break/>Exotic7
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (50)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (11); neurological (9); musculoskeletal (7); general and unspecified (7);
     <break/>The succulent leaves of this introduced plant are applied topically for inflammatory skin disorders, fever and pain.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiinflammatory: upon administration of aqueous (400 mg/kg PO) as well as ethanolic extracts (0.1–1 mg/ear TOP) significantly reduced inflammatory response parameters in several rodent models (
     <xref rid="B117" ref-type="bibr">Chibli et al., 2014</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr">F̈rer, et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Antimicrobial: 2 studies showed significant effects on various bacterial and fungal strains 
     <italic>in vitro</italic>, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr">F̈rer, et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Antileishmaniasis: an observational study with a single patient and a study with mice showed significant effects of aqueous leaf extracts (
     <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr">F̈rer, et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Antinociceptive: various leaf extracts showed significant effects on rodents in the writhing and hot plate tests (
     <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr">F̈rer, et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Wound healing: ethanolic leaf extract (0.25–1 mg/kg/d TOP for 14 days) significantly reduced the size of wound area in a rat wound excision model (
     <xref rid="B336" ref-type="bibr">Nayak et al., 2010</xref>).
     <break/>Neuro-depressive effects: aquatic leaf extract (50 to 200 mg/kg PO) showed sedative and muscle relaxant activities in rodents and an observational study found a subjective improvement of sleep quality in 49 pregnant women with sleeping disorders, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr">F̈rer, et al., 2016</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapeutic applications have been well tolerated in human trials. However, the herbal drug contains bufadienolides, which are potentially toxic upon ingestion (
     <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr">F̈rer, et al., 2016</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Topical applications possibly safe and effective; internal administration likely unsafe
     <break/>A5, S8
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Bursera simaruba</italic>
     </bold> (L.) Sarg. (Burseraceae) – gumbo-limbo – 
     <italic>palo mulato</italic>, 
     <italic>chaca</italic>, 
     <italic>jiote</italic>
     <break/>Native11
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (50)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (13), mainly as antipyretic; skin (7);
     <break/>Macerations of the bark are used throughout MA in washings against fever and burns.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiinflammatory: lipophilic bark extracts showed antiinflammatory activity (ID
     <sub>50</sub> values of hexane and chloroform extracts of 221 and 143 μg/cm
     <sup>2</sup> TOP, respectively) in an experimentally induced ear edema model in mice (
     <xref rid="B426" ref-type="bibr">Sosa et al., 2002</xref>). Hexane leaf extract (at an equivalent of 1.5 g/kg PO) significantly reduced carrageenan-induced rat paw edema (
     <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">Carretero et al., 2008</xref>).
     <break/>Antimicrobial: aqueous, alcoholic and chloroform stem bark extracts showed moderate activity against 
     <italic>C. albicans</italic> and 
     <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> in the disc diffusion assay (
     <xref rid="B377" ref-type="bibr">Rahalison et al., 1993</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B394" ref-type="bibr">Rosas-Piñón et al., 2012</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence on efficacy and lacking evidence on safety
     <break/>S9
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Carica papaya</italic>
     </bold> L. (Caricaceae) – papaya
     <break/>Native12
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (27)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (10), mainly as anthelmintic;
     <break/>Seeds and sap of this fruit shrub are used in lowland MA against gastrointestinal parasites.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nematocidal: latex was shown active against the intestinal mouse nematode 
     <italic>Heligmosomoides bakeri</italic> (
     <xref rid="B293" ref-type="bibr">Luoga et al., 2015</xref>), while papaya seed extracts containing benzyl isothiocyanate were toxic for 
     <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> (
     <xref rid="B258" ref-type="bibr">Kermanshai et al., 2001</xref>).
     <break/>A RCT confirmed the efficacy of cysteine proteinase obtained from papaya latex against 
     <italic>Trichuris suis</italic> infection in pigs. A single oral dose of 450 μmol was effective against low and high infection with 
     <italic>T. suis</italic> eggs (
     <xref rid="B282" ref-type="bibr">Levecke et al., 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Papain, a bioactive protein present in 
     <italic>C. papaya</italic> latex did not show mutagenic or toxic effects against 
     <italic>E. coli</italic> strains (
     <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr">da Silva et al., 2010</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and therapeutically effective
     <break/>D12
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic>
     </bold> (L.) Osbeck (Rutaceae) – orange – 
     <italic>naranja</italic>
     <break/>Exotic8
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (64)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (11); respiratory (11); general and unspecified (10); psychological (8);
     <break/>Infusions of leaves, flowers and fruit peel of this introduced fruit tree are used throughout MA for stomachache, respiratory infections, anxiety-like disorders, and for ritual healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broad antimicrobial: crude plant extracts, essential oils and isolated compounds demonstrated significant effects against a variety of fungal and bacterial strains incl. gastrointestinal and respiratory pathogens 
     <italic>in vitro</italic>, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr">Favela-Hernández et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Anxiolytic and sedative: a limited number of clinical trials and rodent models showed significant tranquilizing effects of orange aroma and IP administration of organic extracts, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr">Favela-Hernández et al., 2016</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No toxicological studies directly relevant to traditional uses have been published. Synephrine a component similar to the banned ephedrine and present in the leaves, peel and juice should not give rise to concerns (
     <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Arbo et al., 2008</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B430" ref-type="bibr">Stohs et al., 2011</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B449" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly effective, yet limited evidence on safety
     <break/>A6, D13, P1, R5
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Hamelia patens</italic>
     </bold> Jacq. (Rubiaceae) – firebush – 
     <italic>chichipince</italic>, 
     <italic>coralillo, chacloso</italic>
     <break/>Native13
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (50)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (12); digestive (7);
     <break/>The leaves are used for wound healing and dermatological and gastrointestinal infections.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiinflammatory: lipophilic bark extracts showed antiinflammatory activity (ID
     <sub>50</sub> value of the chloroform extract = 255 μg/cm
     <sup>2</sup> TOP) in experimentally induced ear edema in mice (
     <xref rid="B426" ref-type="bibr">Sosa et al., 2002</xref>). The hexane extract of the leaves applied orally reduced carrageenan induced edema and inflammation in rats at 200 and more readily at 500 mg/kg (
     <xref rid="B246" ref-type="bibr">Jiménez-Suárez et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Wound healing: ointment produced with 5% and 10% ethanolic extract of the aerial parts significantly augmented the healing process of experimentally induced wounds in rats (
     <xref rid="B191" ref-type="bibr">Gomez-Beloz et al., 2003</xref>).
     <break/>Antibacterial: hexane and methanol leaf extract showed moderate MIC (2.5 mg/ml) against 
     <italic>E. coli</italic> (
     <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">Camporese et al., 2003</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute (14 days) or sub-acute (28 days) toxicity of ethanolic leaf extract in mice and rats, with LD
     <sub>50</sub> determined at 2900 mg/kg IP and &gt; 5000 mg/kg PO (
     <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Alonso-Castro et al., 2015b</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and effective
     <break/>S10
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Mangifera</italic>
      <italic>indica</italic>
     </bold> L. (Anacardiaceae) – mango
     <break/>Exotic9
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (38)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (10); respiratory (7);
     <break/>Decoctions of leaves and bark of this introduced fruit tree are used against diarrhea, gastrointestinal inflammations, and respiratory infections.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antidiarrheal: aqueous leaf extract (25, 50 and 100 mg/kg PO) dose-dependently reduced the severity of diarrheal episodes in rats (
     <xref rid="B487" ref-type="bibr">Yakubu and Salimon, 2015</xref>); further, 2 mice studies showed antidiarrheal effects of seed extracts, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B408" ref-type="bibr">Shah et al., 2010</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B355" ref-type="bibr">Parvez, 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: a limited number of studies showed significant effects of seed and bark extracts in different 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> and 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> models, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B408" ref-type="bibr">Shah et al., 2010</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B355" ref-type="bibr">Parvez, 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Antimicrobial: several studies showed significant effects of aqueous and alcoholic leaf and bark extracts against a series of bacterial and fungal strains, incl. gastrointestinal and respiratory pathogens, in disk diffusion assays, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B408" ref-type="bibr">Shah et al., 2010</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B355" ref-type="bibr">Parvez, 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Gastroprotective: mangiferin, a xanthanoid abundant in the stem bark was shown to mediate antiinflammatory and gastroprotective effects (10 and 20mg/kg IP) in a gastric ulcer model with rats (
     <xref rid="B298" ref-type="bibr">Mahmoud-Awny et al., 2015</xref>). Mangiferin at 3, 10 and 30 mg/kg PO dose-dependently reduced gastric lesion induced by alcohol in rats (
     <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">Carvalho et al., 2007</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity of aqueous stem bark extracts (up to 2,000 mg/kg PO and TOP) in mice and rats (
     <xref rid="B178" ref-type="bibr">Garrido et al., 2009</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and effective
     <break/>D14, R6
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>
     </bold> L. (Solanaceae) – tobacco – 
     <italic>tabaco</italic>
     <break/>Native14
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (50)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (11), particularly against snakebites; respiratory (8); general and unspecified (8);
     <break/>Leaves are used topically against snakebites as well as skin and respiratory infections, tobacco is also important in ritual healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broad antimicrobial: aqueous and organic leaf extracts as well as isolated polyphenols and nicotine significantly inhibited the growth of various strains of bacteria and fungi (incl. pathogens of the skin and respiratory system) in the disk diffusion and broth dilution methods (
     <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Akinpelu and Obuotor, 2000</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B363" ref-type="bibr">Pavia et al., 2000</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B464" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2008</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Bakht et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B254" ref-type="bibr">Kalayou et al., 2012</xref>).
     <break/>Antisnake venom: as the neurotoxic effects of some snake venoms are mediated 
     <italic>via</italic> nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (nAChR), nicotine may be effective in alleviating the symptoms of certain snakebites, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B187" ref-type="bibr">Giovannini and Howes, 2017</xref>).
     <break/>Respiratory stimulation: in small doses nicotine can act as a respiratory stimulant. In larger doses, however, it causes respiratory depression (
     <xref rid="B146" ref-type="bibr">Dewick, 2002</xref>: 314)
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intoxication with nAChR agonists such as nicotine is biphasic and may lead to abdominal pain, hypertension, tachycardia, and tremors and successively give way to hypotension, bradycardia, and dyspnea while high doses may result in coma and respiratory failure (
     <xref rid="B404" ref-type="bibr">Schep et al., 2009</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly effective yet probably unsafe</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Pimenta dioica</italic>
     </bold> (L.) Merr. (Myrtaceae) – allspice – 
     <italic>pimienta gorda</italic>
     <break/>Native15
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (55)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (12); female genital (8); pregnancy (8), particularly postpartum care;
     <break/>Leaves of this culinary spice are used in lowland MA as infusions for gastrointestinal ailments and as washings for reproductive health.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broad antimicrobial: aqueous and organic leaf extracts, essential oil as well as isolated tannins and eugenol (the major compound of the essential oil) significantly inhibit the growth of various pathogenic bacterial and fungal strains (
     <xref rid="B409" ref-type="bibr">Shaival et al., 2001</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B255" ref-type="bibr">Kamatou et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B497" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Lokeshwar, 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Bhat and Raveesha, 2016</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Al-Harbi et al., 2018</xref>).
     <break/>Analgesic: leaf and fruit extracts as well as isolated eugenol have well demonstrated antinociceptive effects, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B255" ref-type="bibr">Kamatou et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B497" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Lokeshwar, 2012</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: aqueous leaf extracts, isolated eugenol and eugenol-rich extracts proved effective in various inflammation models, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B255" ref-type="bibr">Kamatou et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B497" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Lokeshwar, 2012</xref>).
     <break/>Antidiarrheal: isolated eugenol significantly reduced various parameters of castor oil-induced diarrhea in rats (
     <xref rid="B255" ref-type="bibr">Kamatou et al., 2012</xref>).
     <break/>Antiulcer: aqueous leaf extracts and isolated eugenol significantly reduced the lesions from experimentally induced gastric ulcers in mice and rats, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B255" ref-type="bibr">Kamatou et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B497" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Lokeshwar, 2012</xref>).
     <break/>Antispasmodic: isolated eugenol significantly reduced contractions in isolated ileum and tracheal muscles, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B255" ref-type="bibr">Kamatou et al., 2012</xref>).
     <break/>Anticancer: eugenol’s antiproliferative and cytotoxic effects against different cancer cell lines were demonstrated in several 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> studies, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B255" ref-type="bibr">Kamatou et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B497" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Lokeshwar, 2012</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eugenol is generally recognized as safe by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA). The safety of crude plant extracts has not been evaluated. (
     <xref rid="B255" ref-type="bibr">Kamatou et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B497" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Lokeshwar, 2012</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and effective
     <break/>D15, W1, X1
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Punica</italic>
      <italic>granatum</italic>
     </bold> L. (Lythraceae) – pomegranate – 
     <italic>granada</italic>
     <break/>Exotic10
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (26)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (13);
     <break/>Infusions of the astringent fruit skin of this introduced tree are used throughout MA against oral infections and diarrhea.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antidiarrheal: aqueous fruit peel extracts (100, 200, 300, 400 mg/kg IP) significantly and dose-dependently reduced gastrointestinal transit and castor oil-induced enteropooling in rats and contractions in isolated rat ileum (
     <xref rid="B376" ref-type="bibr">Qnais et al., 2007</xref>).
     <break/>Wound healing: TOP-applied gel, using methanolic fruit peel extract significantly accelerated the healing process in the wound excision model in rats (
     <xref rid="B330" ref-type="bibr">Murthy et al., 2004</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LD
     <sub>50</sub> = 1321 mg/kg of aqueous fruit peel extract (IP) determined in mice (
     <xref rid="B376" ref-type="bibr">Qnais et al., 2007</xref>). Also, an acute toxicity study in mice with IP-administered hydroalcoholic whole fruit extract concluded that toxic effects occurred only at doses far higher than those used in T&amp;CM (
     <xref rid="B459" ref-type="bibr">Vidal et al., 2003</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and effective
     <break/>D16
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Allium sativum</italic>
     </bold> L. (Amaryllidaceae) – garlic – 
     <italic>ajo</italic>
     <break/>Exotic11
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (63)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (11); general and unspecified (10); musculoskeletal (9); skin (8); respiratory (7);
     <break/>The raw bulbs of this introduced, cultivated plant are used internally against gastrointestinal parasites and respiratory infections, topically against musculoskeletal pain and fungal infections, and for ritual healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthelmintic: subchronic (7d) oral administration of garlic homogenate demonstrated more effective against 
     <italic>Aspiculuris tetraptera</italic> in natural infected mice than the standard antiparasitic ivermectin (0.2 mg/kg IM) (
     <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Ayaz et al., 2008</xref>).
     <break/>Broad antimicrobial (incl. gastrointestinal, dermatological, and respiratory pathogens): a number of studies have demonstrated significant antibacterial, antiviral, and fungicidal effects of garlic extracts, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B213" ref-type="bibr">Harris et al., 2001</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory and antiarthritis: topically administered isolated thiacremonone (1 μg/kg – 10 mg/kg) demonstrated significant activity in several rodent models (
     <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Ban et al., 2009</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No serious toxicological risks although allergic reactions can occur, as extensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Aviello et al., 2009</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe and effective
     <break/>D17, L1, R7, S11
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Artemisia ludoviciana</italic>
     </bold> Nutt. (Asteraceae) – silver wormwood – 
     <italic>estafiate</italic>
     <break/>Native16
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (39)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (12); general and unspecified (7);
     <break/>Infusions of the aromatic and bitter aerial parts are drunk in Mexico for diverse gastrointestinal ailments.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-
     <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>: 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> MIC of 125 μg/ml aqueous extract (
     <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Castillo-Juárez et al., 2009</xref>).
     <break/>Anti-
     <italic>Giardia lamblia</italic> and 
     <italic>Entamoeba hystolitica</italic>: 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> IC
     <sub>50</sub> of aqueous extracts &gt; 1900 μg/ml; IC
     <sub>50</sub> of hexane extracts &lt; 140 μg/ml, for both pathogens (
     <xref rid="B399" ref-type="bibr">Said Fernández et al., 2005</xref>).
     <break/>Antinociceptive: essential oil (1–316 mg/kg) significantly and dose-dependently reduced the response of mice in the hot-plate and formalin tests, likely mediated 
     <italic>via</italic> an opioid mechanism (
     <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Anaya-Eugenio et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Not spasmolytic: organic extracts (0.97–1,000 μg/ml) showed no antispasmodic activity in isolated rat ileum (
     <xref rid="B159" ref-type="bibr">Estrada-Soto et al., 2012</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence on efficacy and no data on safety
     <break/>A7, D18
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Bixa orellana</italic>
     </bold> L. (Bixaceae) – achiote
     <break/>Native17
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (45)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (10); general and unspecified (9), mainly as antipyretic;
     <break/>Leaves and seeds are applied topically to treat skin infections and fever in lowland MA. Seeds also as coloring agent and culinary condiment.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broad antimicrobial as well as antileishmaniasis: leaf extracts as well as seed powder (annatto) showed significant activity in a number of preclinical studies on a broad range of pathogens, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B448" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B432" ref-type="bibr">Stohs, 2014</xref>). A 50% ethanolic leaf extract (90 ml/10 g powdered leaves) showed significant inhibition zones (17 mm) in the disk diffusion assay (50 μL/disk) against 
     <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> (
     <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Cáceres et al., 1995</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: significant activity of leaf extracts in a several rodent models, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B448" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B432" ref-type="bibr">Stohs, 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No serious toxicological risks although allergic reactions can occur, as extensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B448" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B432" ref-type="bibr">Stohs, 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe and effective with reservations; lacking evidence for antipyretic activity
     <break/>S12
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Hyptis verticillata</italic>
     </bold> Jacq. (Lamiaceae) – 
     <italic>hierba San Martín</italic>
     <break/>Native18
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (51)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (10); digestive (7); musculoskeletal (7);
     <break/>The aerial parts are used in lowland MA for ritual healing, infusions drunk for diverse gastrointestinal ailments, and alcoholic macerations are used for massaging aching bones.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial and antiinflammatory: few studies have been carried out and shown limited activity, as extensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B372" ref-type="bibr">Picking et al., 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infusions and topic applications appear safe, some concern exists in regard to the use of alcoholic macerations due to elevated concentrations of cytotoxic lignans, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B372" ref-type="bibr">Picking et al., 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lack of evidence on efficacy, safe with reservations</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Lantana camara</italic>
     </bold> L. (Verbenaceae) – 
     <italic>cinco negritos</italic>, 
     <italic>conchita</italic>
     <break/>Native19
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (46)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (10); respiratory (7);
     <break/>Infusions of the aromatic leaves are drunk against gastrointestinal pain and respiratory infections.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broad antimicrobial (incl. gastrointestinal and respiratory pathogens) and nematocidal: a number of preclinical studies demonstrated significant antibacterial, antiviral, fungicidal, and nematocidal activities of essential oil and leaf extracts, as extensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B183" ref-type="bibr">Ghisalberti, 2000</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B412" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et al., 2007</xref>).
     <break/>Antidiarrheal: methanolic leaf extract (125–1,000 mg/kg IP) induced significant dose-dependent reduction in fecal output in mice with castor oil-induced diarrhea (
     <xref rid="B398" ref-type="bibr">Sagar et al., 2005</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severely hepatotoxic and phototoxic, attributed mostly to phenolics and triterpenoids, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B183" ref-type="bibr">Ghisalberti, 2000</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B412" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et al., 2007</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effective but unsafe</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Tecoma stans</italic>
     </bold> (L.) Juss. ex Kunth (Bignoniaceae) – yellow trumpetbush – 
     <italic>tronadora</italic>
     <break/>Native20
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (36)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endocrine (10); mainly as antidiabetic;
     <break/>Decoctions of the aerial parts are drunk against hyperglycemia.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antidiabetic: The decoction of the leaves and stem showed hypoglycemic effects in the glucose tolerance test in rabbits (
     <xref rid="B392" ref-type="bibr">Román-Ramos et al., 1991</xref>) and a leaf decoction antidiabetic activity in STZ-induced hyperglycemia in rats (
     <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Aguilar et al., 1993</xref>). Several studies reported antidiabetic effect of leaf extracts (
     <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Aguilar-Santamaría et al., 2009</xref>) while the aqueous leaf extract significantly reduced plasma cholesterol and triglycerides at 500 mg/kg/d for 21 days in STZ and healthy rats without affecting glycaemia (
     <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Aguilar-Santamaría et al., 2009</xref>). Moreover, the aqueous leaf and the methanolic bark extracts were shown to inhibit α-glucosidase 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> (
     <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Aguilar-Santamaría et al., 2009</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B160" ref-type="bibr">Evangeline et al., 2015</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not signs of toxicity in 
     <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> larvae being fed aqueous extracts of aerial parts for 48 h (
     <xref rid="B425" ref-type="bibr">Sortibrán et al., 2011</xref>). A 50% alcoholic leaf extract showed no acute toxicity up to 5,000 mg/kg PO and no signs of chronic toxicity at 500 mg/kg/d over 28 days in mice (
     <xref rid="B271" ref-type="bibr">Larbie et al., 2019</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effective with reservations, limited data on safety
     <break/>T1
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Cedrela odorata</italic>
     </bold> L. (Meliaceae) – 
     <italic>cedro</italic>
     <break/>Native21
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (43)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (7);
     <break/>Aqueous extracts of leaves, bark or wood of this important timber species are applied in a bath or orally as an antipyretic in lowland MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimalaria: 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> IC
     <sub>50</sub> of 1.1–9.3 μg/ml of ethanolic wood extracts from different populations against 
     <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> W2 and D6 clones, attributed to the limonoid gedunin (
     <xref rid="B296" ref-type="bibr">MacKinnon et al., 1997</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No serious toxicological risks: low acute (10–5,000 mg/kg IP) and subchronic (500 mg/kg/d PO) of hydroethanolic bark extract in mice even at elevated doses (
     <xref rid="B186" ref-type="bibr">Giordani et al., 2015</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe but limited data on efficacy</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Citrus</italic> ×
      <italic>aurantium</italic>
     </bold> L. (Rutaceae) – bitter orange – 
     <italic>naranja agria</italic>
     <break/>Exotic12
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (54)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (9); psychological (8); digestive (7); respiratory (7);
     <break/>Infusions of leaves, flowers, and zest of this introduced fruit tree are drunk for emotional and anxiety-like disorders, fever, respiratory infections, and stomachache and used for ritual healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiolytic: clinical evidence for significant anxiolytic effects of flower distillate, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B431" ref-type="bibr">Stohs et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B403" ref-type="bibr">Sarris et al., 2013</xref>) and recently reaffirmed (
     <xref rid="B373" ref-type="bibr">Pimenta et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Antimicrobial and antirotavirus: limited evidence from preclinical studies, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B449" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2013</xref>)
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No serious toxicological risks Synephrine a component similar to the banned ephedrine and present in the leaves, peel and juice should not give rise to concerns (
     <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Arbo et al., 2008</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B430" ref-type="bibr">Stohs et al., 2011</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B449" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited data on efficacy, save with reservations
     <break/>A8, D19, P2, R8
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Jatropha curcas</italic>
     </bold> L. (Euphorbiaceae) – purging nut – 
     <italic>piñon</italic>
     <break/>Native22
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (25)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (12);
     <break/>The sap of this shrub, used for living fences, is applied to skin infections, particularly around the lips.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial: significant 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> activity not including dermatological pathogens, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B443" ref-type="bibr">Thomas et al., 2008</xref>). In a placebo-controlled study the milk sap was shown effective against common warts (
     <xref rid="B301" ref-type="bibr">Marroquin et al., 1997</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severely acutely toxic upon oral ingestion, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B443" ref-type="bibr">Thomas et al., 2008</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unsafe upon ingestion and limited evidence for efficacy in topical applications</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Petiveria alliacea</italic>
     </bold> L. (Petiveriaceae) – 
     <italic>hierba de zorrillo, apacín</italic>
     <break/>Native23
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (44)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (9); digestive (7); musculoskeletal (7);
     <break/>Infusions of the entire plant are used in washings against fever and pain or drunk against stomachache in lowland MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analgesic: significant antinociceptive effects of aqueous and organic extracts were demonstrated in several rodent models, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B294" ref-type="bibr">Luz et al., 2016</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low acute and subchronic toxicity of aqueous and organic extracts of different plant parts in several animal studies, as extensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B294" ref-type="bibr">Luz et al., 2016</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effective and safe with reservations
     <break/>A9, D20, L2
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Spondias purpurea</italic>
     </bold> L. (Anacardiaceae) – hog plum – 
     <italic>ciruela, jocote</italic>
     <break/>Native24
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (29)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (8); digestive (7);
     <break/>Maceration of leaves of this lowland fruit tree are topically applied for inflammatory skin conditions and drunk for diverse gastrointestinal ailments.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibacterial: significant 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> activity of hexane leaf extracts against several skin- and enteropathogens demonstrated with the disk diffusion method (
     <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Cáceres et al., 1993a</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B319" ref-type="bibr">Miranda-Cruz et al., 2012</xref>).
     <break/>Antiulcer: hexane leaf extract (12.5–50 mg/kg PO) significantly and dose-dependently reduced area of induced GI ulcerative lesions in mice and rats (
     <xref rid="B141" ref-type="bibr">De Almeida et al., 2017</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence on efficacy and no data on safety
     <break/>D21, S13
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Tanacetum</italic>
      <italic>parthenium</italic>
     </bold> (L.) Sch.Bip. (Asteraceae) – feverfew – 
     <italic>Hierba Santa María</italic>
     <break/>Exotic13
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (53)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (12); pregnancy (8); general and unspecified (7);
     <break/>Infusions of aerial parts of this introduced aromatic herb are drunk against diverse gastrointestinal ailments and used in post-partum washing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analgesic: significant activity of ethanolic flower extracts (10–300 mg/kg PO) in several rodent models (
     <xref rid="B237" ref-type="bibr">Jain and Kulkarni, 1999</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B300" ref-type="bibr">Mannelli et al., 2015</xref>) but insufficient evidence for significant prevention from migraine headache based on several double-blind RCTs against, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B374" ref-type="bibr">Pittler and Ernst, 2004</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: significant activity of ethanolic flower extracts (10–300 mg/kg PO) in carrageenan-induced rat paw edema model (
     <xref rid="B237" ref-type="bibr">Jain and Kulkarni, 1999</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B300" ref-type="bibr">Mannelli et al., 2015</xref>) as well as of the isolated sesquiterpene lactone parthenolide demonstrated in a number of studies, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B307" ref-type="bibr">Mathema et al., 2012</xref>).
     <break/>Antibacterial (incl. several gastrointestinal pathogens): 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> IC
     <sub>50</sub> of 4–38 μg/ml of essential oil against 8 different Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria (
     <xref rid="B322" ref-type="bibr">Mohsenzadeh et al., 2011</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No major safety concerns, as only mild and transient adverse effects established in a number of clinical trials, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B374" ref-type="bibr">Pittler and Ernst, 2004</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe and effective with reservations
     <break/>A10, D22, W2
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Allium cepa</italic>
     </bold> L. (Amaryllidaceae) – onion – 
     <italic>cebolla</italic>
     <break/>Exotic14
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (44)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory (8); skin (7);
     <break/>The bulbs of this introduced food plant are used internally for respiratory infections and topically for diverse skin disorders.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound healing: a number of clinical trials evidenced efficacy of topically applied onion extracts for skin scarring, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B416" ref-type="bibr">Sidgwick et al., 2015</xref>).
     <break/>Antibacterial: significant 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> activity against a number of Gram-positive strains, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr">Corzo-Martínez et al., 2007</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B410" ref-type="bibr">Sharifi-Rad et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Antiasthmatic and antiinflammatory: limited evidence from 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> models, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr">Corzo-Martínez et al., 2007</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generally regarded as safe, although some adverse effects may occur, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr">Corzo-Martínez et al., 2007</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B416" ref-type="bibr">Sidgwick et al., 2015</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe and effective with reservations
     <break/>R9, S14
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Citrus limon</italic>
     </bold> (L.) Osbeck (Rutaceae) – lemon – limón
     <break/>Exotic15
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (53)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (10); respiratory (9); general and unspecified (7);
     <break/>The fruit juice, zest, and leaves of this introduced fruit tree are used internally for infections of the digestive and respiratory tract as well as for ritual healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiviral (incl. influenza virus) and broad antimicrobial (incl. enteropathogens): several 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> studies demonstrated significant effects of essential oil, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B189" ref-type="bibr">Goetz, 2014</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory specifically antibronchitis: a few 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> studies demonstrated significant activity, and attributed to flavonoids, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B189" ref-type="bibr">Goetz, 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generally regarded as safe although irritation may occur, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B189" ref-type="bibr">Goetz, 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effective and safe
     <break/>D23, R10
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Guazuma ulmifolia</italic>
     </bold> Lam. (Malvaceae) – West Indian elm – 
     <italic>caulote, guácimo</italic>
     <break/>Native25
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (34)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (11), mainly as antidiarrheal;
     <break/>Decoctions of the astringent bark and fruits are used in lowland MA against diarrhea.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial: significant 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> activity against a number of enteropathogens (
     <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Cáceres et al., 1990</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">Camporese et al., 2003</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B235" ref-type="bibr">Jacobo-Salcedo et al., 2011</xref>).
     <break/>Antidiarrheal: complete inhibition of cholera toxin-induced chloride secretion in rabbit distal colon and significant reduction of intestinal motility in mice upon administration of crude bark extract (
     <xref rid="B228" ref-type="bibr">Hör et al., 1995</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B316" ref-type="bibr">Michelin et al., 2010</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not acutely toxic in 
     <italic>Artemia salina</italic> essay (aqueous leaf extract 10–1,000 ppm) (
     <xref rid="B334" ref-type="bibr">Navarro et al., 2003</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Likely effective but no evidence on safety of bark
     <break/>D24
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Justicia spicigera</italic>
     </bold> Schltdl. (Acanthaceae) – Mexican honeysuckle – 
     <italic>muicle, añil, hoja de tinta</italic>
     <break/>Native26
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (42)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (12);
     <break/>The aerial parts are used for dying and in ritual healing, including the oral administration of infusions.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antidepressant: significant, dose-dependent effect of the isolated flavonoid kaempferitrin (1–20 mg/kg PO) in two mice models (
     <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">Cassani et al., 2014</xref>).
     <break/>Immunostimulatory: ethanolic leaf extract as well as isolated kaempferitrin induced significant effects in several 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> assays (
     <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Alonso-Castro et al., 2012b</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B251" ref-type="bibr">Juárez-Vázquez et al., 2013b</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not acutely toxic in mice, LD
     <sub>50</sub> of ethanolic leaf extract &gt; 5,000 mg/kg (IP and PO) (
     <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Alonso-Castro et al., 2012b</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe and possibly effective
     <break/>A11
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Lippia alba</italic>
     </bold> (Mill.) N.E.Br. ex Britton &amp; P.Wilson (Verbenaceae) – bushy matgrass – 
     <italic>malvareal, salviareal</italic>
     <break/>Native27
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (35)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (9);
     <break/>Infusions of the aromatic leaves are applied internally for diverse gastrointestinal disorders.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broad antimicrobial (incl. a number of enteropathogens): several 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> studies have demonstrated significant activity of aqueous and organic extracts, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B222" ref-type="bibr">Hennebelle et al., 2008</xref>).
     <break/>Analgesic and antiinflammatory: a few studies showed significant effects of essential oil and organic extracts in different rodent models, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B222" ref-type="bibr">Hennebelle et al., 2008</xref>). In a longitudinal, prospective, phase 2, non-controlled cohort study with 21 women the hydroethanolic leaf extract (chemotype geranial-carvenone) was shown effective in controlling symptoms and the impact of migraine. Dose was one drop of a 70% alcoholic tincture made from 1L of solution and 200g of fresh leaves (macerated for 10 days) per kg body weight/d over 2 months (
     <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">Carmona et al., 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not acutely toxic at therapeutic doses, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B222" ref-type="bibr">Hennebelle et al., 2008</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe and effective
     <break/>D25
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Manilkara zapota</italic>
     </bold> (L.) P.Royen (Sapotaceae) – sapodilla – 
     <italic>chicozapote</italic>
     <break/>Native28
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (20)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (7);
     <break/>Infusions of the leaves of this fruit tree are used for diverse gastrointestinal disorders.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antidiarrheal: ethanolic leaf extract (200–400 mg/kg PO) significantly reduced defecation in castor oil-induced diarrhea model on mice (Ganguly et al., 2016).
     <break/>Analgesic: ethanolic leaf extract (200–400 mg/kg PO) significantly reduced nociception in mice in the writhing and tail-flick tests (Ganguly et al., 2016).
     <break/>Antimicrobial: significant 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> activity of aqueous and methanolic leaf extracts against a number of enteropathogens (
     <xref rid="B333" ref-type="bibr">Nair and Chanda, 2008</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity in rats after administration of ethanolic leaf extract (200–3200 mg/kg PO) (
     <xref rid="B176" ref-type="bibr">Ganguly et al., 2016</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe and effective
     <break/>D26
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Mentha</italic> ×
      <italic>piperita</italic>
     </bold> L. (Lamiaceae) – peppermint – 
     <italic>hierbabuena, menta</italic>
     <break/>Exotic16
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (47)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (13);
     <break/>Infusions of the leaves of this introduced potherb are used throughout MA to treat stomachache.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analgesic and antispasmodic (gastric and colonic): good scientific evidence from a number of clinical trials, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B257" ref-type="bibr">Keifer et al., 2007</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe at therapeutic doses, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B257" ref-type="bibr">Keifer et al., 2007</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe and effective
     <break/>D27
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Momordica</italic>
      <italic>charantia</italic>
     </bold> L. (Cucurbitaceae) – bitter gourd – 
     <italic>cunduamor/cundeamor</italic>
     <break/>Exotic17
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (33)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endocrine (8);
     <break/>Infusions of aerial parts of this introduced weed are used in lowland MA to treat diabetes.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antidiabetic: while a number of preclinical and clinical studies suggest antidiabetic activity (
     <xref rid="B210" ref-type="bibr">Habicht et al., 2014</xref>), the four RCTs standing up to the quality criteria of a recent Cochrane review found limited efficacy in glycaemia control, the risk of bias being high in all four studies (
     <xref rid="B345" ref-type="bibr">Ooi et al., 2012</xref>). A newer systematic review and meta-analysis evaluating 10 clinical studies, however, concluded that different 
     <italic>M. charantia</italic> preparations improved glycemic control in T2DM patients but based on low quality evidence for the primary outcomes (
     <xref rid="B371" ref-type="bibr">Peter et al., 2019</xref>)
     <break/>A placebo-controlled, double-blind trial with T2DM patients showed that the application of 2,000 mg dried fruit pulp/d over 3 months decreased a range of parameters associated with diabetes such as BW, BMI, waist circumference, fat percentage, glycated hemoglobin A1c, 2-h glucose in the oral glucose tolerance test and glucose in parallel to an increase in insulin secretion (
     <xref rid="B130" ref-type="bibr">Cortez-Navarrete et al., 2018</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No serious adverse effects in four clinical trials with a total of 479 adult patients but transient effects may occur, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B345" ref-type="bibr">Ooi et al., 2012</xref>) but more trials assessing safety are recommended (
     <xref rid="B371" ref-type="bibr">Peter et al., 2019</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Musa</italic> × 
      <italic>paradisiaca</italic>
     </bold> L. (Musaceae) – banana, plantain - 
     <italic>plátano, guineo</italic>
     <break/>Exotic18
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (32)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (10); skin (7);
     <break/>The (unripe) fruits of this introduced food staple are used against diarrhea; the fruit skin, leaves and sap are topically applied for diverse skin disorders.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antidiarrheal: randomized, controlled trial with 80 children (1–28 months of age) hospitalized for persistent diarrhea; all outcome measures (stool output and consistency, stool weight, diarrhea duration, daily gain in body weight) improved significantly in the treatment group (n = 40) receiving a diet based on green plantains (for 7 days) in comparison to and control (n = 40) receiving a yoghurt based diet (
     <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Alvarez-Acosta et al., 2009</xref>).
     <break/>Antibacterial (incl. gastrointestinal and dermatological pathogens): 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> MIC of 15.6–125.0 μg/ml organic leaf extracts against nine bacterial strains (
     <xref rid="B256" ref-type="bibr">Karuppiah and Mustaffa, 2013</xref>).
     <break/>Wound healing: banana leaf wound dressings compared positively to paraffin gauze in 3 clinical trials, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Benskin, 2013</xref>); the topically application of methanolic stem extract significantly improved wound healing in rats in comparison to control (
     <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Amutha and Selvakumari, 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Antileishmaniasis: significant 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> activity of different fractions of fruit peel extracts against 
     <italic>L</italic>. 
     <italic>infantum chagasi</italic> promastigotes and amastigotes (
     <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Accioly et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B419" ref-type="bibr">Silva et al., 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No adverse effects were reported in clinical trials using internal or topical applications (
     <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Alvarez-Acosta et al., 2009</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Benskin, 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe and effective
     <break/>D28, S15
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Solanum americanum</italic>
     </bold> Mill. (Solanaceae) – American black nightshade – 
     <italic>hierbamora</italic>
     <break/>Native29
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (37)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (10);
     <break/>The leaves of this common leaf vegetable are topically applied for diverse skin disorders.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broad antimicrobial (incl. dermatologic pathogens): a number of studies reported significant activity of organic extracts on diverse bacteria and fungi, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr">Chauhan et al., 2012</xref>).
     <break/>Antileishmaniasis: methanolic leaf extracts showed 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> IC
     <sub>50</sub> of 40 μg/ml against 
     <italic>L</italic>. 
     <italic>amazonensis</italic> (
     <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">Braga et al., 2007</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: ethanolic leaf extract (400 mg/kg IP) significantly protected chickens from histamine- and carrageenan-induced inflammatory dermal lesions (
     <xref rid="B286" ref-type="bibr">Lomash et al., 2010</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toxic upon ingestion, yet no evidence on safety of topic applications, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B238" ref-type="bibr">Jain et al., 2011</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effective but lacking evidence for safety
     <break/>S16
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Tradescantia zebrina</italic>
     </bold> Bosse (syn. 
     <italic>Zebrina pendula</italic>) (Commelinaceae) – inchplant – 
     <italic>hierba del pollo, siempreviva, madali</italic>
     <break/>Native30
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (35)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (7);
     <break/>Macerations of the aerial parts of this common weed and ornamental are used for washings against fever.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibacterial: methanolic leaf extracts showed MIC values of 5–10 mg/ml against 12 Gram-positive and -negative strains (
     <xref rid="B437" ref-type="bibr">Tan et al., 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lacking evidence on efficacy and safety</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Argemone mexicana</italic>
     </bold> L. (Papaveraceae) – Mexican prickly poppy – 
     <italic>cardosanto</italic>, 
     <italic>chicalote</italic>
     <break/>Native31
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (22)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eye (6);
     <break/>The latex of this common weed is dripped into the eye to treat cataracts and glaucoma.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibacterial (incl. ophthalmological pathogens): several studies describe the significant 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> activity of aqueous and organic extracts of the stems, leaves, roots and seeds as well as the essential oil, against Gram-positive and -negative bacteria, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">Brahmachari et al., 2013</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B395" ref-type="bibr">Rubio-Piña and Vázquez-Flota, 2013</xref>).
     <break/>Anticholinergic: the presence of alkaloids in the aerial parts and seeds, e.g., berberine, capable of blocking acetylcholine, are prescribed for the treatment of glaucoma, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B395" ref-type="bibr">Rubio-Piña and Vázquez-Flota, 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Several reviews point out the whole plant, especially the seeds, as toxic. Effects reported include dermatitis, abortifacient and neurotoxicity, mainly related with the presence of alkaloids such as berberine and saguinarine (
     <xref rid="B361" ref-type="bibr">Paul and Seaforth, 2011</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Alonso-Castro et al., 2017b</xref>). Acute toxicity of the plant extracts in mice (LD
     <sub>50</sub> 400 mg/kg, IP); hepatotoxicity of sanguinarine in mice (10 mg/kg, IP); neuroparalysis and death of several people, were reviewed (
     <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">Brahmachari et al., 2013</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B395" ref-type="bibr">Rubio-Piña and Vázquez-Flota, 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solutions of berberine HCl are used as eye drops. Though applying the crude latex to the eyes is possibly unsafe. Limited evidence for efficacy</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Asclepias curassavica</italic>
     </bold> L. (Apocynaceae) – tropical milkweed, bloodflower – 
     <italic>quebramuela</italic>, 
     <italic>flor de mariposa</italic>
     <break/>Native32
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (27)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurological (7); skin (7);
     <break/>The latex is dripped onto aching teeth and topically applied to treat skin infections and insect bites throughout lowland MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound healing: a latex enzyme fraction was shown to reduce plasma-clotting time with human blood 
     <italic>in vitro</italic>, to hydrolyze fibrinogen and to induce the formation of fibrin clots in a dose-dependent manner (
     <xref rid="B414" ref-type="bibr">Shivaprasad et al., 2009</xref>).
     <break/>Antileishmaniasis: methanolic leaf extract showed moderate activity (IC
     <sub>50</sub> = 99 μg/ml) against 
     <italic>Leishmania mexicana</italic> promastigotes 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> (
     <xref rid="B364" ref-type="bibr">Peraza-Sánchez et al., 2007</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The whole plant contains cardiotoxic cardenolides (
     <xref rid="B421" ref-type="bibr">Singh and Rastogi, 1969</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence on therapeutic benefits and highly toxic if ingested</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Capsicum annuum</italic>
     </bold> L. (Solanaceae) – chili pepper – 
     <italic>chile</italic>
     <break/>Native33
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (23)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (9);
     <break/>Fresh and dried fruits of this commonly cultivated culinary spice are used for a variety of disorders, particularly in ritual healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND related to possible effects in ritual healing; there is however a large range of health effects of the fruits and isolated capsaicin, as extensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B400" ref-type="bibr">Sanati et al., 2018</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generally recognized as safe but strong irritations may occur (
     <xref rid="B249" ref-type="bibr">Johnson, 2007</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe but therapeutic benefits difficult to evaluate</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Cinnamomum verum</italic>
     </bold> J.Presl (Lauraceae) – cinnamon – 
     <italic>canela</italic>
     <break/>Exotic19
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (44)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pregnancy (9); respiratory (9); digestive (8);
     <break/>The bark of this introduced spice tree is used in infusions against labor pain, respiratory tract infections, and gastrointestinal pain.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broad antimicrobial (incl. gastroenteral and respiratory pathogens: numerous studies reported significant 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> effects against a wide variety of bacteria and fungi, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B382" ref-type="bibr">Ranasinghe et al., 2013</xref>).
     <break/>Antinociceptive: ethanolic bark extracts (200–400 mg/kg PO) significantly and dose-dependently reduced the nociception of mice in the writhing and hot-plate tests (
     <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Atta and Alkofahi, 1998</xref>).
     <break/>Antidiarrheal: aqueous bark extract (100–200 mg/kg PO) significantly reduced the intensity of castor oil- and magnesium sulfate-induced diarrhea in mice (
     <xref rid="B384" ref-type="bibr">Rao and Lakshmi, 2012</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No serious adverse effects at therapeutic doses as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B382" ref-type="bibr">Ranasinghe et al., 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Likely effective and safe
     <break/>D29, R11, W3
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Coffea arabica</italic>
     </bold> L. (Rubiaceae) – coffee – 
     <italic>café</italic>
     <break/>Exotic20
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (29)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (5);
     <break/>The roasted and ground seeds of this introduced cash crop are applied topically to facilitate wound healing in lowland MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound healing: a carbopol hydrogel of aqueous extract from green coffee beans residual press cake (10% v/v; 0.1 g per animal, TOP, 1 × day for 14 days) significantly reduced the wound area in the mice excision wound assay using animals 9 months old, similarly to the positive control allantoin (1% w/v) (
     <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Affonso et al., 2016</xref>). In 2-month-old animals the same study failed to show an effect of the coffee extract superior to the negative control.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute or sub-chronic toxicity of whole fruit powder, aqueous and hydroalcoholic extracts (up to 4,000 mg/kg/d PO for up to 90 days) in rats. Further, no mutagenic effects of the extracts were found with 
     <italic>S. typhimurium</italic> and 
     <italic>E. coli</italic> strains and no genotoxicity with the micronucleus test using murine peripheral cells (
     <xref rid="B217" ref-type="bibr">Heimbach et al., 2010</xref>). No topic safety studies have been performed.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence on therapeutic benefits and safety</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Crescentia cujete</italic>
     </bold> L. (Bignoniaceae) – calabash tree – 
     <italic>morro</italic>, 
     <italic>jícara</italic>
     <break/>Native34
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (29)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory (8);
     <break/>Decoctions and syrups of the fruit are orally administered against cough throughout lowland MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibacterial: ethanolic and chloroform leaf and bark extracts (100–200 μg/disc) 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> inhibited the growth of 
     <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and 
     <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> with zones of inhibition of 8–29 mm (
     <xref rid="B356" ref-type="bibr">Parvin et al., 2015</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: ethanolic leaf and bark extracts (0.1–1 mg/ml) demonstrated significant and dose-dependent effects in the human red blood cell membrane stabilization test (
     <xref rid="B356" ref-type="bibr">Parvin et al., 2015</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence on therapeutic benefits and lack of evidence on safety</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Hibiscus</italic>
      <italic>rosa</italic>-
      <italic>sinensis</italic>
     </bold> L. (Malvaceae) – Chinese hibiscus – 
     <italic>tulipán</italic>
     <break/>Exotic21
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (24)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory (5); general and unspecified (5);
     <break/>The petals of this introduced ornamental are topically applied or drunk in infusions against coughs and fevers and used in ritual healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antipyretic: ethanolic flower extract (125, 250, 500 mg/kg PO) dose-dependently reduced experimentally induced increases of rectal temperature in rats (
     <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Birari et al., 2009</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: ethanolic flower extract (125, 250, 500 mg/kg PO) dose-dependently reduced carrageenan-induced rat paw edema. At 250 and 500 mg/kg the extract significantly reduced xylene-induced ear edema as well as cotton pellet-induced granuloma formation in rats (
     <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Birari et al., 2009</xref>).
     <break/>Analgesic: ethanolic flower extract (125, 250, 500 mg/kg PO) dose-dependently reduced acetic acid-induced writhing as well as formalin-induced paw licking in mice (
     <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Birari et al., 2009</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethanolic and hydroalcoholic extracts of the leaves and aerial parts showed LD
     <sub>50</sub> values above 1,000 mg/kg (IP) in rodents, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B236" ref-type="bibr">Jadhav et al., 2009</xref>). The safety of flowers and topic administration has not been evaluated.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence of safety and efficacy
     <break/>A12
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Mimosa</italic>
      <italic>pudica</italic>
     </bold> L. (Fabaceae) – sensitive plant, touch-me-not – 
     <italic>dormilona</italic>, 
     <italic>vergonzosa</italic>
     <break/>Native35
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (28)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Psychological (8);
     <break/>This pantropical weed, well known for its rapid leaf movement, is used in washings, infusions and ritual healing to treat anxiety and insomnia in lowland MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anxiolytic and antidepressant: aqueous and organic solvent leaf and root extracts in rel. high doses (200–2,000 mg/kg PO) showed significant, dose-dependent anxiolytic- and antidepressant-like effects in a number of rodent models (e.g., 
     <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Ayissi Mbomo et al., 2011</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B360" ref-type="bibr">Patro et al., 2016</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B413" ref-type="bibr">Shashikumara et al., 2018</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The leaves petroleum ether extract shows no signs of acute toxicity in rat Lorke test (2,000 mg/kg PO) (
     <xref rid="B360" ref-type="bibr">Patro et al., 2016</xref>). Ethanolic root extract did not show acute toxicity in mice (5,000 mg/kg PO) (
     <xref rid="B413" ref-type="bibr">Shashikumara et al., 2018</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe but limited evidence for therapeutic benefits</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Mirabilis</italic>
      <italic>jalapa</italic>
     </bold> L. (Nyctaginaceae) – four o’clock flower – 
     <italic>maravilla</italic>, 
     <italic>flor de linda tarde</italic>
     <break/>Native36
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (30)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (6); general and unspecified (6);
     <break/>The petals and leaves of this common weed and ornamental are topically applied to treat skin infections and fever and are used in ritual healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial (incl. dermatological pathogens): the methanolic extract of aerial parts showed low inhibitory activity (MIC 1 mg/ml) against Gram-positive and -negative bacteria (
     <xref rid="B494" ref-type="bibr">Zachariah et al., 2012</xref>). The ethanolic extract of the aerial parts displayed a slight activity against multi-drug resistant bacterial strains (6 – 18 mm inhibition diameter) (
     <xref rid="B350" ref-type="bibr">Oskay et al., 2009</xref>).
     <break/>Wound healing: aqueous and ethanolic extracts of aerial parts (25 and 50 µg/ml) significantly promoted keratinocyte growth in the MTT assay (
     <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Alerico et al., 2015</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: ethanolic flower extract (100–200 mg/kg PO) significantly reduced CFA-induced rat paw edema (
     <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Augustine et al., 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The ethanolic flower extract (2,000 mg/kg PO) did not show any signs of acute toxicity in rats (
     <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Augustine et al., 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and effective for dermatological conditions; no evidence for antipyretic activity
     <break/>S17
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Neurolaena</italic>
      <italic>lobata</italic>
     </bold> (L.) R.Br. ex Cass. (Asteraceae) – 
     <italic>tres puntas</italic>, 
     <italic>mano de lagarto</italic>
     <break/>Native37
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (19)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (6);
     <break/>The leaves of this intensely bitter weed are topically applied to treat skin infections and insect bites.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound healing: significant improvements of various parameters in the rat wound excision model after treatment with ethanolic leaf extract (1:1 petroleum jelly, 100 mg/kg/d for 13 days) (
     <xref rid="B337" ref-type="bibr">Nayak et al., 2014</xref>). The sequiterpenelactones present in the leaves have shown potent antiinflammatory properties 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> (reduced LPS stimulated TNF-α production) and in carrageenan-induced paw edema in rats receiving 60 mg/kg MeOH extract IP (
     <xref rid="B463" ref-type="bibr">Walshe-Roussel et al., 2013</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B309" ref-type="bibr">McKinnon et al., 2014</xref>).
     <break/>Antimicrobial (incl. dermatological pathogens): several 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> studies showed significant effects of ethanolic leaf extracts against various bacterial and fungal strains (
     <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Cáceres et al., 1998</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B277" ref-type="bibr">Lentz et al., 1998</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B337" ref-type="bibr">Nayak et al., 2014</xref>).
     <break/>Antileishmaniasis: significant 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> activity of ethanolic extracts of different plant parts against promastigotes (
     <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr">Chinchilla-Carmona et al., 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute or sub-acute toxicity of ethanolic and hydroalcoholic leaf extracts in mice (1–5 g/kg PO; 500 mg/kg every second day for 21 days) (
     <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Cáceres et al., 1998</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B199" ref-type="bibr">Gracioso et al., 1998</xref>)
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and therapeutically effective
     <break/>S18
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Ocimum</italic>
      <italic>campechianum</italic>
     </bold> Mill. (syn. 
     <italic>O</italic>. 
     <italic>micranthum</italic>) (Lamiaceae) – 
     <italic>albahaca cimarrón</italic>
     <break/>Native38
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (24)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurological (4); general and unspecified (4);
     <break/>The aerial parts of this aromatic weed are topically applied or drunk in infusions against headache and fatigue as well as used in ritual healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analgesic: the essential oil (15–100 mg/kg PO) showed significant, dose-dependent antinociceptive activity in the acetic acid-induced writhing and formalin-induced licking tests in mice yet not in the hot plate test (
     <xref rid="B142" ref-type="bibr">De Pinho et al., 2012</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity in mice receiving essential oil (1 – 5 g/kg PO) (
     <xref rid="B142" ref-type="bibr">De Pinho et al., 2012</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and effective
     <break/>A13, N2
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Parmentiera</italic>
      <italic>aculeata</italic>
     </bold> (Kunth) Seem. (syn. 
     <italic>P</italic>. 
     <italic>edulis</italic>) (Bignoniaceae) – 
     <italic>cuajilote</italic>
     <break/>Native39
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (38)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory (8):
     <break/>The fruits of this common shrub or small tree are split open, heated and topically applied to the chest or boiled and eaten to treat respiratory tract infections.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lacking evidence for safety and efficacy</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Piper</italic>
      <italic>amalago</italic>
     </bold> L. (Piperaceae) – 
     <italic>cordoncillo</italic>
     <break/>Native40
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (24)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (6); general and unspecified (6);
     <break/>The leaves of this and several other 
     <italic>Piper</italic> spp. known as 
     <italic>cordoncillo</italic> are topically applied to treat skin infections and inflammations and fever as well as being used in ritual healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial: methanolic extract of the leaves exhibit limited activity against 
     <italic>E. coli</italic> (MIC 512 µg/ml) and 
     <italic>S. aureus</italic> (MIC1024 µg/ml) (
     <xref rid="B490" ref-type="bibr">Yasunaka et al., 2005</xref>). The essential oil of the leaves did not show antifungal activity at evaluated conc. (0.48 – 1,000 µg/ml) (
     <xref rid="B185" ref-type="bibr">Giannetti et al., 2010</xref>).
     <break/>Antileishmaniasis: two amides isolated from the chloroform extract of the leaves showed significant activity (IC
     <sub>50</sub> of 20±0.88 and 15±0.25 µM) against promastigotes 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> (
     <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">Carrara et al., 2013</xref>).
     <break/>Analgesic: ethanolic leaf extract (100 mg/kg PO) and two isolated pyrrolidine amides (1 mg/kg PO) showed significant antinociceptive activity on mice in several pain models (
     <xref rid="B135" ref-type="bibr">da Silva Arrigo et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Anxiolytic: ethanolic leaf extract 8–75 mg/kg PO) showed significant, dose-dependent anxiolytic-like effects in several rodent models (
     <xref rid="B328" ref-type="bibr">Mullally et al., 2016</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence for therapeutic benefits and lacking evidence on safety
     <break/>A14, S19
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Ruta</italic>
      <italic>chalepensis</italic>
     </bold> L. (Rutaceae) – fringed rue – 
     <italic>ruda</italic>
     <break/>Exotic22
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (58)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (10); digestive (9); neurological (9);
     <break/>The aerial parts of this introduced aromatic plant – as well as its close relative 
     <italic>R. graveolens</italic> (together cited in 20 studies with 109 use-records) – are used throughout MA in infusions, topically applied macerations, washings and in ritual healing to alleviate fever, diarrhea, pain and general illness.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antipyretic: ethanolic extract of the aerial parts (10–500 mg/kg IP) dose-dependently reduced yeast-induced hypothermia in mice (
     <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Al-Said et al., 1990</xref>)
     <break/>Analgesic: ethanolic extract of the aerial parts (3–300 mg/kg PO) failed to show antinociceptive activity in the hot plate and writhing tests yet showed significant, dose-dependent effects in the mouse formalin test (
     <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Al-Said et al., 1990</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B197" ref-type="bibr">Gonzalez-Trujano et al., 2006</xref>).
     <break/>Antimicrobial (incl. enteropathogens): a number of 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> studies demonstrated significant effects of aqueous and alcoholic extracts of the leaves and aerial parts as well as the essential oil on a broad range of pathogenic bacteria and fungi (e.g., 
     <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Alzoreky and Nakahara, 2003</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Alanís et al., 2005</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">Cho et al., 2005</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B211" ref-type="bibr">Haddouchi et al., 2013</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B182" ref-type="bibr">Ghazghazi et al., 2015</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B252" ref-type="bibr">Kacem et al., 2015</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Alotaibi et al., 2018</xref>).
     <break/>Antiprotozoal: ethanolic extract of aerial parts showed an IC
     <sub>50</sub> of 62 μg/ml against 
     <italic>Entamoeba histolytica</italic> and 38 μg/ml against 
     <italic>Giardia lamblia</italic> while metronidazole an IC
     <sub>50</sub> of 0.04 and 0.21 μg/ml, respectively (
     <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">Calzada et al., 2006</xref>).
     <break/>Antidiarrheal: ethanolic extract of areal parts (300 mg/kg PO) significantly inhibited cholera toxin-induced intestinal secretion in the rat jejunal loops model (
     <xref rid="B457" ref-type="bibr">Velázquez et al., 2006</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: ethanolic extract of the aerial parts (500 mg/kg PO) significantly reduced carrageenan-induced paw edema and cotton pellet-induced granuloma formation in rats (
     <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Al-Said et al., 1990</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embryotoxic effects in mice were demonstrated with aqueous extracts (10–1,600 mg/kg/d), administered PO on days 1–14 post-coitus and IP days 9–17 post-coitus (
     <xref rid="B496" ref-type="bibr">Zeichen de Sa et al., 2000</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B196" ref-type="bibr">Gonzales et al., 2007</xref>).
     <break/>The fresh plant and extracts cause contact dermatitis through phototoxic reactions (
     <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">Brener and Friedman, 1985</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B195" ref-type="bibr">Gonçalo et al., 1989</xref>).
     <break/>Extracts of the aerial parts in mice showed LD
     <sub>50</sub> values &gt; 2,500 mg/kg (methanolic IP) and &gt; 5,000 mg/kg (ethanolic PO) (
     <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Aguilar-Santamaría and Tortoriello, 1996</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B197" ref-type="bibr">Gonzalez-Trujano et al., 2006</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly effective yet unsafe in pregnancy and for topic administration</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Sechium</italic> edule
     </bold> (Jacq.) Sw. (Cucurbitaceae) – 
     <italic>chayote</italic>, 
     <italic>güisquil</italic>
     <break/>Native41
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (24)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urological (6);
     <break/>The consumption of cooked fruits and young leaves of this common vegetable is recommended to alleviate urinary tract infections and kidney stones.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial: ethanolic leaf extracts exhibited significant activity on a large range of Gram-positive (MIC 4.16–8.32 µg/ml), Gram-negative (MIC 20–160 µg/ml) antibiotic-resistant bacteria and fungi (MIC 20 – 800 µg/ml), all of them related with urinary tract infections and renal complications (
     <xref rid="B346" ref-type="bibr">Ordoñez et al., 2003</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B347" ref-type="bibr">Ordoñez et al., 2009</xref>).
     <break/>Nephroprotective: aqueous leaf extracts (200 mg/kg, PO) significantly protected rats against gentamicin- and potassium dichromate-induced nephrotoxicity and streptozotocin-induced diabetic nephropathy; showing a significant decrease of blood urea, blood urea nitrogen, serum uric acid and serum creatinine as well as improving the kidney histology (
     <xref rid="B329" ref-type="bibr">Mumtaz et al., 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The methanolic fruit extract shows no signs of acute toxicity in mice Lorke test (&lt;5,000 mg/kg PO) (
     <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Aguiñiga-Sánchez et al., 2017</xref>).
     <break/>No toxic effect of aqueous leaf and stem extracts when tested in bacterial and human lymphocyte systems and no genotoxic effect in Ames test (
     <xref rid="B492" ref-type="bibr">Yen et al., 2001</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B347" ref-type="bibr">Ordoñez et al., 2009</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and effective
     <break/>U2
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Senna</italic>
      <italic>occidentalis</italic>
     </bold> (L.) Link (syn. 
     <italic>Cassia occidentalis</italic>) (Fabaceae) – coffee senna – 
     <italic>frijolillo</italic>, 
     <italic>hormiguillo</italic>
     <break/>Native42
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (29)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (7);
     <break/>Decoctions of the aerial parts of this common weed are used in washings to alleviate general fatigue and body pain.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The phytochemistry and the pharmacological data obtained with extracts was reviewed (
     <xref rid="B486" ref-type="bibr">Yadav et al., 2010</xref>) but none with a specificity associated to the main uses in MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The seeds are highly toxic (e.g., 
     <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Barbosa-Ferreira et al., 2005</xref>). Hydroalcoholic extract of the aerial parts produced no signs of acute (5g/kg PO) or sub-acute (2.5 g/kg/d for 30 days PO) toxicity in rats (
     <xref rid="B418" ref-type="bibr">Silva et al., 2011</xref>). Topical toxicity has not been evaluated.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lack of evidence on therapeutic benefits and concerns regarding safety</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Sida</italic>
      <italic>acuta</italic>
     </bold> Burm.f. (Malvaceae) – common wireweed – 
     <italic>malva</italic>, 
     <italic>escobillo</italic>
     <break/>Native43
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (36)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (7); skin (7);
     <break/>Decoctions of this weedy plant are drunk against gastrointestinal parasites and inflammations and used in washings against diverse skin infections.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial: a number of 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> studies have demonstrated significant activity against a broad spectrum of bacteria and fungi, including gastrointestinal pathogens, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B148" ref-type="bibr">Dinda et al., 2015</xref>).
     <break/>Antiulcer: two studies demonstrated significant effects in various GI rat models using ethanolic whole plant and leaf extracts, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B148" ref-type="bibr">Dinda et al., 2015</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not acutely toxic at therapeutic doses of aqueous extract, LD
     <sub>50</sub> of 3200 mg/kg (IP) in mice; no signs of subchronic toxicity in rats receiving aqueous extract (75–200 mg/kg/d for 28 days PO) (
     <xref rid="B264" ref-type="bibr">Konaté et al., 2012</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly effective and likely safe
     <break/>D30, S20
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Solanum</italic>
      <italic>torvum</italic>
     </bold> Sw. (Solanaceae) – prickly nightshade – 
     <italic>sosa</italic>, 
     <italic>lavaplatos</italic>
     <break/>Native44
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (37)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (6);
     <break/>Infusions and macerations of the leaves of this common weed are topically applied to treat skin infections and inflammations.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial (incl. dermatological pathogens): methanolic leaf extract showed moderate activity in disc diffusion assay at 1 mg extract per disc against several bacterial and fungal strains (
     <xref rid="B478" ref-type="bibr">Wiart et al., 2004</xref>).
     <break/>Antileishmaniasis: organic solvent leaf extract inhibited the proliferation of 
     <italic>Leishmania donovani</italic> promastigotes 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> (IC
     <sub>50</sub> = 90 μg/ml) (
     <xref rid="B230" ref-type="bibr">Hubert et al., 2013</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: aqueous leaf extract showed significant effects in several rodent models, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B493" ref-type="bibr">Yousaf et al., 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity on liver and kidney in chickens receiving aqueous leaf extract (2 g/kg PO) (
     <xref rid="B215" ref-type="bibr">Hashemi et al., 2008</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly effective and likely safe
     <break/>S21
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Tithonia</italic>
      <italic>diversifolia</italic>
     </bold> (Hemsl.) A.Gray (Asteraceae) – Mexican sunflower, tree marigold – 
     <italic>árnica</italic>, 
     <italic>girasol</italic>
     <break/>Native45
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (57)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Musculoskeletal (8); skin (8); general and unspecified (8); digestive (7);
     <break/>Decoctions of the bitter leaves of this common weed are applied orally, topically, and in washings for diverse inflammatory conditions throughout lowland MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiinflammatory: an ethanolic leaf extract (50–200 mg/kg PO) significantly and dose-dependently reduced carrageenan-induced paw edema in rats (
     <xref rid="B351" ref-type="bibr">Owoyele et al., 2004</xref>). Aqueous and acetonic leaf rinse extracts (10–150 mg/kg PO) significantly and dose-dependently reduced carrageenan-induced paw edema and croton oil-induced ear edema in mice (
     <xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr">Chagas-Paula et al., 2011</xref>).
     <break/>Gastroprotective: methanolic and dichloromethanolic leaf extracts (10–100 mg/kg IG) significantly protected rats from ethanol-induced gastric ulcers (
     <xref rid="B401" ref-type="bibr">Sánchez-Mendoza et al., 2011</xref>).
     <break/>Leishmanicidal: an acetonic leaf rinse extract demonstrated an LD
     <sub>50</sub> value of 1.5 μg/ml on promastigotes of 
     <italic>L</italic>. 
     <italic>braziliensis</italic> (
     <xref rid="B145" ref-type="bibr">de Toledo et al., 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderately toxic; at doses below 100 mg/kg aqueous leaf extracts (10–100 mg/kg/d, IG for 90 days) induced only few alterations in hematological and biochemical parameters in rats. Acetone (10–100 mg/kg/d IG for 90 days) and ethanolic leaf extracts (400–1,600 mg/kg PO) proved toxic to liver and kidneys of rats. (
     <xref rid="B155" ref-type="bibr">Elufioye et al., 2009</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B357" ref-type="bibr">Passoni et al., 2013</xref>)
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly effective but moderately toxic when applied orally
     <break/>L3, S22
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Zingiber</italic>
      <italic>officinale</italic>
     </bold> Roscoe (Zingiberaceae) – ginger – 
     <italic>jengibre</italic>
     <break/>Exotic23
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (33)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (7);
     <break/>Decoctions of the rhizome of this introduced plant are drunk against stomach pain and gastrointestinal inflammations.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General gastrointestinal: Ginger is used globally and there is a large amount of clinical and preclinical evidence supporting its uses, especially against nausea, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B342" ref-type="bibr">Nikkhah-Bodagh et al., 2019</xref>). A number of clinical and preclinical trials have further demonstrated the analgesic and antiinflammatory activities of ginger, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B203" ref-type="bibr">Grzanna et al., 2005</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B441" ref-type="bibr">Terry et al., 2011</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generally regarded as safe, including during pregnancy; moderate to mild stomach upset, eructation, heartburn and nausea may occur rarely (
     <xref rid="B342" ref-type="bibr">Nikkhah-Bodagh et al., 2019</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe and effective
     <break/>D31
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Annona reticulata</italic>
     </bold> L. (Annonaceae) – custard apple, sweetsop – 
     <italic>anona</italic>
     <break/>Native46
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (26)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (8);
     <break/>The leaves of this common fruit tree are topically applied to reduce fever and alleviate general illness throughout lowland MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antipyretic: aqueous and methanolic leaf extracts (100–200 mg/kg PO) significantly reduced brewer’s yeast-induced hyperpyrexia in rats (
     <xref rid="B239" ref-type="bibr">Jamkhande and Wattamwar, 2015</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B269" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2015</xref>).
     <break/>Antiplasmodial: ethanolic bark extract was active against 
     <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> (IC
     <sub>50</sub> = 0.29 µg/ml) but aqueous and leaf extracts were inactive (
     <xref rid="B488" ref-type="bibr">Yamthe et al., 2015</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity of methanolic leaf extract (2,000 mg/kg PO) in rats (
     <xref rid="B269" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2015</xref>). Topical applications have not been evaluated.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe but limited evidence for therapeutic benefits</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Baccharis inamoena</italic>
     </bold> Gardner (syn. 
     <italic>B</italic>. 
     <italic>trinervis</italic>) (Asteraceae) – 
     <italic>Santo Domingo</italic>
     <break/>Native47
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (34)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (7);
     <break/>Infusions of the aerial parts of this common weed are drunk to lower fever and used in washing and ritual healing to alleviate fatigue and general illness.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial and antiviral: several 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> studies showed moderate activity of aqueous extracts of the aerial parts and the essential oil against pathogenic bacteria and fungi as well as against 
     <italic>Herpes simplex</italic> and HI Virus strains, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B241" ref-type="bibr">Jaramillo-García et al., 2018</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytotoxic and genotoxic effects of aqueous extract of the aerial parts and different organic solvent fractions were reported in different assays (
     <xref rid="B241" ref-type="bibr">Jaramillo-García et al., 2018</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence on therapeutic benefits and possibly unsafe</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Bougainvillea glabra</italic>
     </bold> Choisy (Nyctaginaceae) – bougainvillea – 
     <italic>bugambilia</italic>
     <break/>Exotic24
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (22)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory (10);
     <break/>Most frequently cited species in this genus of common ornamental vines, the bracts of which are used to prepare antitussive infusions throughout MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial (incl. respiratory pathogens): a number of 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> studies demonstrated significant but moderate activity of aqueous and organic solvent extracts of flowers and leaves of 
     <italic>B</italic>. 
     <italic>glabra</italic> and other 
     <italic>Bougainvillea</italic> species against a range of bacterial and fungal species, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abarca-Vargas and Petricevich, 2018</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: several studies showed significant activity of leave and flower extracts of 
     <italic>B</italic>. 
     <italic>glabra</italic> and other 
     <italic>Bougainvillea</italic> species in mice and rats, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abarca-Vargas and Petricevich, 2018</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity in rodents after oral administration of different extracts of flowers and leaves of 
     <italic>B</italic>. 
     <italic>glabra</italic> and other 
     <italic>Bougainvillea</italic> species, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abarca-Vargas and Petricevich, 2018</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence on therapeutic benefits but possibly safe
     <break/>R12
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Cecropia obtusifolia</italic>
     </bold> Bertol. (Urticaceae) – trumpet tree, snakewood – 
     <italic>guarumbo</italic>, 
     <italic>guarumo</italic>, 
     <italic>chancarro</italic>
     <break/>Native48
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (26)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endocrine (7);
     <break/>Infusions or decoctions of the leaves of this common native tree – as well as of its close relative 
     <italic>C</italic>. 
     <italic>peltata</italic>, together accounting for 60 use-records in 17 studies – are drunk as an antidiabetic throughout MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antidiabetic: a number of 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> studies reported significant effects (incl. hypoglycemic, increased glucose uptake by adipocytes, gluconeogenesis inhibition, improved glucose metabolism by liver glycogen accumulation and α-glucosidase inhibition) of aqueous and organic leaf extracts, as extensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Andrade-Cetto and Heinrich, 2005</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Alonso-Castro et al., 2008</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">Costa et al., 2011</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">Cadena-Zamudio et al., 2019</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B169" ref-type="bibr">Fortis-Barrera et al., 2019</xref>).
     <break/>A non-controlled clinical trial (22 type 2 diabetics, 1g of dry leaf in boiling water 3 × day for 21 days PO) showed significant reductions in fasting blood glucose cholesterol and triglycerides values (
     <xref rid="B223" ref-type="bibr">Herrera-Arellano et al., 2004</xref>). As the patients also received glibenclamide at varying doses, the effects cannot be attributed to 
     <italic>C</italic>. 
     <italic>obtusifolia</italic> alone. An additional non-controlled clinical trial (12 type 2 diabetics, aqueous extract of 13.5 g dry leaves per day for 32 days PO) showed significant reductions in plasma glucose and glycosylated hemoglobin levels (
     <xref rid="B389" ref-type="bibr">Revilla-Monsalve et al., 2007</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low toxicity, as an LD
     <sub>50</sub> of 1450 mg/kg, IP for aqueous leaf extracts in mice was determined (
     <xref rid="B368" ref-type="bibr">Pérez-Guerrero et al., 2001</xref>).
     <break/>A daily dose of 13.5 g of dry leaves in water for 32 and 85 days in type 2 diabetics did not generate any genotoxic or cytotoxic effects in a human micronucleus assay in culture lymphocytes (
     <xref rid="B305" ref-type="bibr">Martínez-Toledo et al., 2008</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and effective
     <break/>T3
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Cissampelos pareira</italic>
     </bold> L. (Menispermaceae) – velvetleaf – 
     <italic>curalina</italic>, 
     <italic>alcotán</italic>, 
     <italic>bejuquillo</italic>, 
     <italic>redondillo</italic>
     <break/>Native49
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (19)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (7);
     <break/>Decoctions of the intensely bitters root of this vine are drunk against stomach pain and diarrheal disorders in lowland MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antidiarrheal: ethanolic root extract (25–100 mg/kg PO) significantly and dose-dependently reduced castor oil-induced diarrhea in mice, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B406" ref-type="bibr">Semwal et al., 2014</xref>).
     <break/>Gastroprotective: several studies reported significant protective effects of organic solvent leaf and root extracts against experimentally-induced ulcer formation in rodents, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B406" ref-type="bibr">Semwal et al., 2014</xref>).
     <break/>Antimicrobial (incl. gastrointestinal pathogens): a number of studies reported significant 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> activity of aqueous and organic solvent extracts against a broad range of bacteria and fungi, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B406" ref-type="bibr">Semwal et al., 2014</xref>).
     <break/>Analgesic: several studies demonstrated significant and dose-dependent effects of aqueous and hydroalcoholic leaf and root extracts in different rodent models, as reviewed and reaffirmed (
     <xref rid="B406" ref-type="bibr">Semwal et al., 2014</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B422" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: several studies demonstrated significant and dose-dependent effects of aqueous and ethanolic leaf and root extracts in different rodent models, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B406" ref-type="bibr">Semwal et al., 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute or chronic toxicity in mice receiving hydroalcoholic extract of the whole plant (1,000–2,000 mg/kg/d for 28 days, PO).
     <break/>However, the LD
     <sub>50</sub> values determined in different studies with different extracts range between 282 and 8500 mg/kg (PO), with ethanolic root extract having the lowest value, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B406" ref-type="bibr">Semwal et al., 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and effective
     <break/>D32
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Citrus aurantiifolia</italic>
     </bold> (Christm.) Swingle (Rutaceae) – key lime – 
     <italic>lima</italic>, 
     <italic>limón criollo</italic>
     <break/>Exotic25
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (54)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory (8); general and unspecified (8); digestive (7);
     <break/>The leaves and fruit skin of this commonly cultivated introduced fruit tree are prepared as infusions and macerations and drunk or used topically, in washings or in ritual healing against respiratory infections, fever, general illness, gastrointestinal pain and inflammations as well as diarrheal disorders.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial (incl. respiratory and gastrointestinal pathogens): several 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> studies demonstrated significant activity of alcoholic and hexane extracts of the leaves and fruit peel as well as the essential oil and fruit juice on a variety of bacterial and fungal strains (
     <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Adeleye and Opiah, 2003</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B312" ref-type="bibr">Meléndez and Capriles, 2006</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B378" ref-type="bibr">Rahman et al., 2011</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B359" ref-type="bibr">Pathan et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B402" ref-type="bibr">Sandoval-Montemayor et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B318" ref-type="bibr">Miller et al., 2015</xref>).
     <break/>Antiprotozoal: volatile components of the hexane fruit peel extract showed IC
     <sub>50</sub> values of 34.2 -229.49 μg/ml against 
     <italic>Giardia lamblia</italic>; in comparison to 0.52 μg/ml of metronidazole (
     <xref rid="B150" ref-type="bibr">Domínguez-Vigil et al., 2015</xref>).
     <break/>Antispasmodic: the essential oil (2–10 μg/ml) obtained from the fruit peel showed significant reduced contractions of smooth muscles from isolated rabbit jejunum and aorta (
     <xref rid="B427" ref-type="bibr">Spadaro et al., 2012</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In sensitive or allergic persons, the essential oil can cause contact dermatitis and phototoxic reactions (e.g., 
     <xref rid="B435" ref-type="bibr">Swerdlin et al., 2010</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly effective and safe with reservations
     <break/>A15, D33, R13
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Cocos nucifera</italic>
     </bold> L. (Arecaceae) – coconut – 
     <italic>coco</italic>
     <break/>Native50
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (22)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (9);
     <break/>Coconut water (the liquid endosperm of this pantropical multipurpose palm) is drunk throughout lowland MA against gastrointestinal parasites.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthelmintic: several studies demonstrated significant activity against intestinal nematodes in different mammals of aqueous and organic extracts of coconut husk (mesocarp) (
     <xref rid="B344" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira et al., 2009</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr">Costa et al., 2010</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B263" ref-type="bibr">Klimpel et al., 2011</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B283" ref-type="bibr">Lima et al., 2015</xref>). Anthelmintic activity of coconut water has not been studied.
     <break/>Antibacterial: an 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> study on 
     <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> showed no zone of inhibition using both fresh and pasteurized coconut water (
     <xref rid="B396" ref-type="bibr">Rukmini et al., 2017</xref>).
     <break/>Gastroprotective: coconut water (2 ml/d PO for 40 days) reduced indomethacin-induced formation of gastric ulcers in rats by 39% (
     <xref rid="B343" ref-type="bibr">Nneli and Woyike, 2008</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity in mice and rats receiving 3,000 mg/kg coconut water orally. Nor were there any signs of sub-chronic or chronic toxicity, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B283" ref-type="bibr">Lima et al., 2015</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Likely safe and effective
     <break/>D34
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic>
     </bold> L. (Apiaceae) – coriander, cilantro – 
     <italic>cilantro</italic>
     <break/>Exotic26
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (16)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (7);
     <break/>Infusions of the leaves or seeds of this very common introduced culinary herb are drunk against vomits, gastrointestinal pain or ulcers by speakers of Mayan and Totonac.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial (incl. gastrointestinal pathogens): a number of studies showed significant 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> effects of essential oil, and isolated peptide as well as aqueous and organic solvent extracts of leaves and seeds against a broad range of bacteria and fungi, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B272" ref-type="bibr">Laribi et al., 2015</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B467" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2019</xref>).
     <break/>Anticolitis: hydroalcoholic seed extract (250–1,000 mg/kg PO) and essential oil (0.25–1 ml/kg PO) significantly and dose-dependently protected rats from acetic acid-induced colitis (
     <xref rid="B216" ref-type="bibr">Heidari et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Anthelminthic: 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> studies showed moderate effects of aqueous and alcoholic extracts against 
     <italic>Haemonchus contortus</italic> and 
     <italic>Hymenolepis nana</italic> (
     <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr">Eguale et al., 2007</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B229" ref-type="bibr">Hosseinzadeh et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Analgesic and antiinflammatory: few studies showed moderate effects of aqueous and ethanolic (50–200 mg/kg PO) seed extracts in different rodent models, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B272" ref-type="bibr">Laribi et al., 2015</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generally regarded as safe, based on its long history of human consumption and a number of toxicity studies, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B272" ref-type="bibr">Laribi et al., 2015</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B467" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2019</xref>). The no-observed-effect-level; (NOEL) for the essential oil has been reported as 160 mg/kg/day. The maternal no-observed-adverse-effect-level (NOAEL) is 250 mg/kg/day a compared to the developmental NOAEL was established as 500 mg/kg/day (
     <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">Burdock and Carabin, 2009</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and effective
     <break/>D35
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Euphorbia</italic>
      <italic>tithymaloides</italic>
     </bold> L. (syn. 
     <italic>Pedilanthus pringlei</italic> and 
     <italic>P</italic>. 
     <italic>tithymaloides</italic>) (Euphorbiaceae) – Christmas candle, devil’s backbone, red slipper spurge etc. – 
     <italic>mayorga</italic>
     <break/>Native51
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (23)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (5);
     <break/>Infusions of the leaves or the latex of this common weed and ornamental plant are topically applied to treat sores, wounds and skin infections in MA close to the Atlantic Ocean.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound healing: ointments prepared with methanolic leaf extract (2.5 and 5% w/w TOP) and isolated compounds (0.25% w/w TOP) showed significant effects on a range of relevant parameters in different rat models (
     <xref rid="B184" ref-type="bibr">Ghosh et al., 2012</xref>).
     <break/>Antibacterial (incl. dermatological pathogens): ethanolic leaf extract showed moderate activity against some bacterial strains 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> (
     <xref rid="B460" ref-type="bibr">Vidotti et al., 2006</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taken orally it is highly toxic and known to irritate mucous membranes (
     <xref rid="B338" ref-type="bibr">Nellis, 1997</xref>). Safety of topic applications have not been assessed.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly effective but toxic when ingested and lacking evidence of safety when applied on open wounds</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Gliricidia sepium</italic>
     </bold> (Jacq.) Walp. (Fabaceae) – 
     <italic>madrecacao</italic>, 
     <italic>cocohuite</italic>
     <break/>Native52
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (26)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (9);
     <break/>In lowland MA the branches are commonly used in healing ceremonies and the macerations of the leaves are topically applied against fever.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial: ethanolic leaf extract showed moderate inhibition against Gram-positive 
     <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> and the yeast 
     <italic>Candida albicans</italic> in the agar well-diffusion method (
     <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Abdulaziz et al., 2019</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence for therapeutic benefits and lacking evidence on safety</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Lepidium virginicum</italic>
     </bold> L. (Brassicaceae) – least pepperwort, Virginia pepperweed – 
     <italic>lentejilla</italic>, 
     <italic>jilipliege</italic>, 
     <italic>mostaza</italic>
     <break/>Native53
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (28)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (6);
     <break/>Infusions of the root or the whole plant of this common weed are orally administered to alleviate gastrointestinal pain and diarrheal disorders.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiamoebic: benzyl glucosinolate was identified as the major antiamoebic compound from a methanolic root extract, which had an IC
     <sub>50</sub> of 100 µg/ml against 
     <italic>Entamoeba histolytica</italic> (
     <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Calzada et al., 2003</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lacking evidence on safety and limited evidence for therapeutic benefits
     <break/>D36
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Malvaviscus</italic>
      <italic>arboreus</italic>
     </bold> Cav. (Malvaceae) – Turkcap, wax mallow – 
     <italic>monacillo</italic>, 
     <italic>tulipán de monte</italic>
     <break/>Native54
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (31)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (7);
     <break/>Decoctions or infusions of the root, leaves or fruits are drunk against different gastrointestinal disorders, incl. dysentery, diarrhea, constipation and pain.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hepatoprotective: the ethyl acetate and dichloromethane fractions (300 mg/kg/d for 6 days, PO) of an ethanolic extract of the aerial parts significantly protected rats from carbon tetrachloride-induced liver injuries (
     <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Abdelhafez et al., 2018</xref>).
     <break/>Antibacterial (incl. gastrointestinal pathogens): aqueous leaf extract showed significant activity against six pathogenic bacteria (
     <xref rid="B391" ref-type="bibr">Rodríguez-García et al., 2019</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence on therapeutic benefits and lacking evidence on safety</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Mimosa</italic>
      <italic>albida</italic>
     </bold> Willd. (Fabaceae) – 
     <italic>dormilona</italic>, 
     <italic>uña de gato</italic>, 
     <italic>vergonzosa</italic>, 
     <italic>zarza</italic>
     <break/>Native55
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (30)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (6);
     <break/>Macerations of the leaves or root of this spiny vine are topically applied against skin infections and for wound healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity in mice receiving aqueous root extract (3.2–400 mg/kg IP) (
     <xref rid="B388" ref-type="bibr">Rejón-Orantes et al., 2013</xref>). Safety of the leaves and topical applications have not been evaluated.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence on safety and lack of evidence on therapeutic benefits</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Sida</italic>
      <italic>rhombifolia</italic>
     </bold> L. (Malvaceae) – arrowleaf sida, Indian hemp – 
     <italic>malva</italic>, 
     <italic>escobillo</italic>
     <break/>Native56
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (35)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (7);
     <break/>Decoctions and macerations of this weedy plant are used in bathes and washings against fever.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiplasmodial: significant and dose-dependent effects against 
     <italic>P</italic>. 
     <italic>berghei</italic> in mice receiving methanolic leaf extract (200–600 mg/kg PO) (
     <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Akele, 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity upon oral administration of up to 6 g/kg as demonstrated in several studies with rodents, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B148" ref-type="bibr">Dinda et al., 2015</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe but limited evidence on therapeutic benefits</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Solanum</italic>
      <italic>lycopersicum</italic>
     </bold> L. (Solanaceae) – tomato – 
     <italic>jitomate</italic>
     <break/>Native57
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (19)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (5);
     <break/>The leaves of this very common food plant are topically applied to alleviate fever, against mumps and folk illnesses of children.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiinflammatory: methanolic leaf extract significantly and dose-dependently inhibited prostaglandin E
     <sub>2</sub> production and cyclooxygenase-2 gene expression 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> (
     <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Amid et al., 2011</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity in mice receiving ethanolic leaf extract (2 g/kg PO) (
     <xref rid="B415" ref-type="bibr">Shukla and Kumar, 2015</xref>). Dermatitis upon contact with the leaves has been described and the glycoalkaloid solanine, present in the leaves, gives rise to safety concerns (
     <xref rid="B181" ref-type="bibr">Germosén-Robineau, 2005</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concerns regarding safety and very limited evidence on therapeutic benefits</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Tamarindus</italic>
      <italic>indica</italic>
     </bold> L. (Fabaceae) – tamarind – 
     <italic>tamarindo</italic>
     <break/>Exotic27
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (26)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (8);
     <break/>Macerations of the leaves of this introduced tree, commonly cultivated for its edible fruit pulp, are topically applied or used in washings to alleviate fever.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiplasmodial: aqueous stem bark extract (100 mg/kg/d for 4 days PO) reduced 
     <italic>P. berghei</italic> parasitemia in mice by 30% (
     <xref rid="B331" ref-type="bibr">Mwangi et al., 2015</xref>). Febrifuge or antimalarial activities of the leaves have not been studied.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of acute toxicity in rats receiving hydroalcoholic leaf extract (2,000 mg/ml PO) (
     <xref rid="B158" ref-type="bibr">Escalona-Arranz et al., 2016</xref>). Safety of topical administration has not been studied.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence on safety and therapeutic benefits</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic>
     </bold> L. (Asteraceae) – absinthe wormwood – 
     <italic>ajenjo</italic>
     <break/>Exotic28
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (23)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (9);
     <break/>Infusions of the leaves or aerial parts of this introduced aromatic plant are drunk to alleviate gastrointestinal pain, cramps and diarrheal disorders throughout MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General gastrointestinal: Some clinical evidence indicates that preparations from the aerial parts are superior to placebo in reducing symptoms of inflammatory bowel disease. There is also some clinical evidence that herbal extracts can be effective in the treatment of amoebiasis and increase biliary, gastric and intestinal excretion of. Further, several 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> studies showed that aqueous and organic solvent extracts of the aerial parts had significant antiulcer, hepatoprotective effects and increased the excretion of bile and gastric juices, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B157" ref-type="bibr">EMA/HMPC, 2017</xref>).
     <break/>Broad antimicrobial (incl. gastrointestinal pathogens): several 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> studies showed significant effects of the essential oil against a number of bacterial and fungal strains, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B157" ref-type="bibr">EMA/HMPC, 2017</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No toxic effects were observed in animal studies using herbal extracts. The isolated compound thujone, however is known to be toxic at higher doses and there is a lack of studies on reproductive and developmental toxicity. Thus, herbal products should not be used in larger amounts or extended periods and not at all during pregnancy and lactation or in children and adolescents, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B157" ref-type="bibr">EMA/HMPC, 2017</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly effective and safe with reservations
     <break/>D37
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Begonia heracleifolia</italic>
     </bold> Cham. &amp; Schltdl. (Begoniaceae) – star begonia – 
     <italic>caña agria</italic>, 
     <italic>mano de león</italic>
     <break/>Native58
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (21)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (5);
     <break/>The crushed rhizomes are topically applied to treat snakebites.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lacking evidence on both safety and therapeutic benefits</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Brugmansia</italic> ×
      <italic>candida</italic>
     </bold> Pers. (Solanaceae) – angel’s trumpet – 
     <italic>flor de campana</italic>, 
     <italic>floripondio</italic>
     <break/>Exotic29
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (22)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (5);
     <break/>The most frequently cited of different 
     <italic>Brugmansia</italic> spp., the leaves of which are topically applied to alleviate skin infections and inflammations.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibacterial (not incl. dermatological pathogens): an isolated peptide showed significant activity against Gram-positive and -negative bacteria 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> (
     <xref rid="B253" ref-type="bibr">Kaewklom et al., 2018</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The whole plant contains highly toxic tropane alkaloids, which can result in severe poisoning and death after ingestion (e.g., 
     <xref rid="B232" ref-type="bibr">Isbister et al., 2003</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B260" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2014</xref>). Topical toxicity has not been evaluated.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toxic upon ingestion and very limited evidence on therapeutic benefits</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Cornutia pyramidata</italic>
     </bold> L. (syn. 
     <italic>C</italic>. 
     <italic>grandiflora</italic>) (Lamiaceae) – 
     <italic>carreto</italic>, 
     <italic>piojillo</italic>, 
     <italic>tabaquillo</italic>
     <break/>Native59
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (17)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (6);
     <break/>The leaves are used in ritual healing and macerations as washings to reduce fever.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiplasmodial: isolated diterpenoids from the leaves showed only marginal activity against two strains of 
     <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> (
     <xref rid="B243" ref-type="bibr">Jenett-Siems et al., 2003</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lack of evidence on safety and therapeutic benefits</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Datura stramonium</italic>
     </bold> L. (Solanaceae) – jimsonweed – 
     <italic>toloache</italic>
     <break/>Native60
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (23)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (5);
     <break/>One of several 
     <italic>Datura</italic> spp. (together cited in 13 studies with 35 use-records) the leaves of which are topically applied to treat infectious and inflammatory skin disorders.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiinflammatory: ethanolic leaf extract (200 mg/kg, PO) showed significantly reduced carrageenan-induced rat paw edema, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B175" ref-type="bibr">Gaire and Subedi, 2013</xref>).
     <break/>Antibacterial (incl. dermatological pathogens): methanolic, ethanolic and aqueous extracts of the aerial parts significantly inhibited the growth of different Gram-positive and -negative bacteria, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B175" ref-type="bibr">Gaire and Subedi, 2013</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral and systemic administration may lead to severe toxicity, characterized by anticholinergic symptoms, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B266" ref-type="bibr">Krenzelok, 2010</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B175" ref-type="bibr">Gaire and Subedi, 2013</xref>); topic administrations have not been evaluated.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toxic upon ingestion and very limited evidence on therapeutic benefits</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Dorstenia contrajerva</italic>
     </bold> L. (Moraceae) – snakewort – 
     <italic>contrayerba</italic>, 
     <italic>cresta de gallo</italic>, 
     <italic>hoja de sapo</italic>
     <break/>Native61
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (19)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (5);
     <break/>The inflorescence, leaves or root are topically applied to treat warts and snakebites in lowland Zoquean and Mayan communities.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND, although the presence of furanocoumarins (
     <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">Cáceres et al., 2001</xref>) might raise concerns of phytophototoxicity.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lack of evidence on safety and therapeutic benefits</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Eryngium foetidum</italic>
     </bold> L. (Apiaceae) – Mexican coriander – 
     <italic>culantro</italic>, 
     <italic>cilantro cimarrón</italic>, 
     <italic>perejil</italic>
     <break/>Native62
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (31)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (5);
     <break/>Decoctions or infusions of the root or leaves of this common culinary herb are used to treat gastrointestinal pain and inflammations as well as diarrheal disorders.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibacterial (incl. gastrointestinal pathogens): a few 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> studies demonstrated limited but significant activity of alcoholic leaf extracts against Gram-positive and –negative bacteria (
     <xref rid="B362" ref-type="bibr">Paul et al., 2011</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B265" ref-type="bibr">Kouitcheu-Mabeku et al., 2016</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B354" ref-type="bibr">Panda et al., 2016</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: several studies showed significant effects of different leaf extracts in various 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> models (
     <xref rid="B362" ref-type="bibr">Paul et al., 2011</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B311" ref-type="bibr">Mekhora et al., 2012</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B139" ref-type="bibr">Dawilai et al., 2013</xref>).
     <break/>Anthelminthic: two 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> studies showed significant effects of methanolic leaf extract and refined plant extract rich in eryngial against 
     <italic>Paramphistomum</italic> sp. and 
     <italic>Strongyloides stercoralis</italic> respectively (
     <xref rid="B362" ref-type="bibr">Paul et al., 2011</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B434" ref-type="bibr">Swargiary et al., 2016</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of serious chronic toxicity in mice receiving a diet supplemented with ground leaves (0.8%–3.2% for 24 weeks), although at elevated doses some adverse effects on kidney function were observed (
     <xref rid="B240" ref-type="bibr">Janwitthayanuchit et al., 2016</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Likely safe but limited evidence on therapeutic benefits
     <break/>D38
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Foeniculum</italic>
      <italic>vulgare</italic>
     </bold> Mill. (Apiaceae) – fennel – 
     <italic>hinojo</italic>
     <break/>Exotic30
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (24)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (8);
     <break/>Infusions of the aerial parts and fruits of this introduced aromatic plant are orally administered to treat gastrointestinal pain and vomiting.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General gastrointestinal: observational, 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> and 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> studies support the use of fennel fruit in the treatment of mild gastrointestinal complaints, especially spasmodic ailments and bloating. Further, several preclinical studies showed significant hepatoprotective, antiinflammatory and antinociceptive effects as well as relaxing effects on isolated smooth muscles, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr">EMA/HMPC, 2008</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Badgujar et al., 2014</xref>).
     <break/>Broad antimicrobial (incl. gastrointestinal pathogens): a number of 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> studies demonstrated significant effects of the essential oil and diverse extracts against a variety of bacterial and fungal strains, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr">EMA/HMPC, 2008</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Badgujar et al., 2014</xref>).
     <break/>The reviewed studies mostly refer to the fruits; the leaves, which are frequently used in MA have received much less attention.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of serious acute or chronic toxicity were recorded in several 
     <italic>in vivo</italic> studies with doses up to 3g/kg (PO). Due to the lack of studies, however, the medicinal use of fennel should be avoided in children under 4 years of age, as comprehensively reviewed (
     <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr">EMA/HMPC, 2008</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Badgujar et al., 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe and good evidence for therapeutic benefits
     <break/>D39
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Litsea</italic>
      <italic>glaucescens</italic>
     </bold> Kunth (Lauraceae) – Mexican bay leaf – 
     <italic>laurel</italic>
     <break/>Native63
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (26)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (6); general and unspecified (6);
     <break/>The leaves of this culinary condiment are used in ritual healing and infusions or decoctions are drunk to alleviate gastrointestinal pain and diarrheal disorders.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antispasmodic: methanolic leaf extract exerted a slight inhibition (IC
     <sub>50</sub> 885 ± 125 µg/ml) of isolated rabbit jejunum muscular contractility (
     <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Arroyo et al., 2004</xref>).
     <break/>Antiinflammatory: ethanolic leaf extract (3, 30, 100 mg/kg IP) showed significantly reduced carrageenan-induced rat paw edema in mice and was also active (30 mg/kg IP) in carrageenan induced pleurisy in mice (
     <xref rid="B420" ref-type="bibr">Simão da Silva et al., 2012</xref>).
     <break/>Antihyperalgesic: ethanolic leaf extract (30 mg/kg IP) exerted a significant preventive effect on mechanical hyperalgesia induced by partial sciatic nerve ligation in mice (
     <xref rid="B420" ref-type="bibr">Simão da Silva et al., 2012</xref>).
     <break/>Antibacterial (incl. enteropathogens): methanolic leaf extracts showed moderate activity (
     <italic>S. aureus</italic> MIC
     <sub>50</sub> 400 µg/ml, 
     <italic>E. coli</italic> MIC
     <sub>50</sub> &gt;1,000 µg/ml) (
     <xref rid="B289" ref-type="bibr">López-Romero et al., 2018</xref>).
     <break/>Antidepressant: essential oil (100 - 300 mg/kg IP) showed antidepressant-like activity in different mice models, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B209" ref-type="bibr">Guzmán-Gutiérrez et al., 2014</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lacking evidence of safety and good evidence on therapeutic benefits
     <break/>D40
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Parthenium</italic>
      <italic>hysterophorus</italic>
     </bold> L. (Asteraceae) – Santa Maria feverfew – 
     <italic>hierba maestra</italic>, 
     <italic>altamisa</italic>
     <break/>Native64
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (25)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General and unspecified (7);
     <break/>Infusions of the aerial parts of this common weed are orally administered to reduce fever.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiplasmodial: hydroalcoholic extract of the root showed partial activity (IC
     <sub>50</sub> 45.2 µg/ml) against chloroquine-susceptible 
     <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> Ghana strain (
     <xref rid="B453" ref-type="bibr">Valdés et al., 2010</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systemic toxic effects on grazing animals have been repeatedly reported, as reviewed (
     <xref rid="B358" ref-type="bibr">Patel, 2011</xref>).
     <break/>Genotoxicity of crude extracts and the isolated sesquiterpene lactone parthenin demonstrated in several studies (e.g., 
     <xref rid="B380" ref-type="bibr">Ramos et al., 2001</xref>; 
     <xref rid="B381" ref-type="bibr">Ramos et al., 2002</xref>).
     <break/>Known to cause contact dermatitis (e.g., 
     <xref rid="B411" ref-type="bibr">Sharma and Sethuraman, 2007</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unsafe and limited evidence on therapeutic benefits</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Plumeria</italic>
      <italic>rubra</italic>
     </bold> L. (Apocynaceae) – frangipani – 
     <italic>flor de mayo</italic>, 
     <italic>cacalosúchil</italic>
     <break/>Native65
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (22)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (5);
     <break/>An infusion of the flowers or decoction of the bark of this common ornamental tree is orally administered to treat gastrointestinal pain, particularly the folk illness 
     <italic>empacho</italic>.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastroprotective: the water-soluble protein fraction of the latex (0.5–50 mg/kg IV) significantly protected mice from ethanol-induced gastric lesions (
     <xref rid="B140" ref-type="bibr">de Alencar et al., 2015</xref>).
     <break/>Antimicrobial (not incl. gastrointestinal pathogens): all but 1 of 13 isolated compounds from the stem bark exhibited 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> antibacterial, antifungal and/or antialgal activities (
     <xref rid="B268" ref-type="bibr">Kuigoua et al., 2010</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited evidence on therapeutic benefits and lack of evidence on safety</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Pouteria</italic>
      <italic>sapota</italic>
     </bold> (Jacq.) H.E.Moore &amp; Stearn (Sapotaceae) – mamey sapota – 
     <italic>mamey</italic>, 
     <italic>zapote</italic> (
     <italic>colorado</italic>)
     <break/>Native66
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (17)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin (7);
     <break/>Macerations of the seed are topically applied to treat skin infections, dandruff and hair loss in lowland MA.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No signs of dermal toxicity, irritation or edema in rabbits receiving aqueous or hydroalcoholic seed extract (200 mg/6 cm
     <sup>2</sup> patch TOP). Both extracts (40 mg/eye) caused mild and reversible eye irritation in rabbits. Acute IG administration of seed extracts (300–2,000 mg/kg) to rats resulted in cyanosis, rectal bleeding and death (
     <xref rid="B152" ref-type="bibr">Dutok et al., 2015</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Possibly safe for topic administration yet lacking evidence on efficacy</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Tagetes</italic>
      <italic>filifolia</italic>
     </bold> Lag. (Asteraceae) – liquorice herb, sweet Irish lace – 
     <italic>anís del monte</italic>
     <break/>Native67
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (17)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestive (8);
     <break/>Infusions of the aerial parts of this strongly scented weed are orally administered to alleviate gastrointestinal pains, cramps and diarrheal disorders.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthelminthic: methanolic leaf extract showed a significant effect against 
     <italic>Haemonchus contortus</italic> larvae and eggs 
     <italic>in vitro</italic> (
     <xref rid="B242" ref-type="bibr">Jasso Díaz et al., 2017</xref>).
     <break/>Antimicrobial: the 50% ethanol leaf extract inhibited moderately the growth of 
     <italic>Salmonella typhi</italic> (≥ to 9mm) and 
     <italic>Shigella flexneri</italic> (6 ≥ 8) in the disc diffusion assay (
     <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Cáceres et al., 1990</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very limited data on therapeutic benefits and lack of evidence on safety</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>
      <italic>Theobroma</italic>
      <italic>cacao</italic>
     </bold> L. (Malvaceae) – cacao, cocoa – 
     <italic>cacao</italic>
     <break/>Native68
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (13)</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pregnancy (4); general and unspecified (4);
     <break/>A hot drink prepared from the roasted seeds of this sacred and commonly cultivated fruit tree is drunk to induce and facilitate childbirth. The fruits and seeds are also important in ritual healing.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pregnancy and childbirth: Through the increase of endogenous cyclic 3’,5’-AMP levels, caffeine is able to antagonize the response to oxytocin in rat uterine smooth muscle (
     <xref rid="B320" ref-type="bibr">Mitznegg et al., 1970</xref>).
     <break/>A prospective cohort study found that regular chocolate consumption (≥ 1–3 servings/week) during the first and third trimester of pregnancy is associated with significantly reduced risk of preeclampsia when compared to women who reported no regular chocolate consumption in these periods. Regular chocolate consumption, but only during the first trimester, was also associated with reduced odds gestational hypertension (
     <xref rid="B397" ref-type="bibr">Saftlas et al., 2010</xref>).
     <break/>Another prospective cohort study found umbilical cord serum theobromine concentrations negatively associated with preeclampsia and first and third trimester chocolate consumption associated with reduced preeclampsia risk (
     <xref rid="B445" ref-type="bibr">Triche et al., 2008</xref>)
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A dietary survey monitoring the intake of theobromine, caffeine and theophylline were not found to have negative effects in pregnant women or on the fetus (
     <xref rid="B440" ref-type="bibr">Tebbutt et al., 1984</xref>).
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Likely safe yet limited evidence on therapeutic benefits
     <break/>W4
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn>
   <p>The species are ranked in order of the number of studies citing and alphabetically sorted among species with the same number of citations. As predominant uses, all ICPC categories with at least seven citing studies are included or alternatively the most frequently cited category if no category is cited in at least seven studies. Abbreviations are as follows: day (d), female (f), male (m) inhibitory concentration (IC), intragastric (IG), intradermal (ID), intravenous (IV), oral (PO), maximal zones of inhibition (MZI), minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC), randomized controlled trial (RCT), topically (TOP). For ICPC key to A, D, L, N, P, R, S, T, U, W, and X (Column “Evaluation”) see 
    <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">
     <bold>Table 2</bold>
    </xref>. For references of use-records please see 
    <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">
     <bold>Table 4.1</bold> in the 
     <bold>Supplementary Material</bold>
    </xref> and 
    <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">
     <bold>Table 1</bold>
    </xref>.
   </p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
