<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">Dispersal ability was negatively correlated with socio-climatic factors (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Southeast regions of China demonstrate the presence of a mild climate, with high precipitation levels, temperatures, and humidity levels, and this supports the survival of a high density of alien plant species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. In contrast, northwest regions of China demonstrate the presence of a harsh environment–with low precipitation levels, temperatures, and humidity levels–and therefore supports the survival of a low density of alien plant species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. However, our findings are contrary to these relationships observed between alien plant species density and socio-climatic factors
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. Our results implied that alien plant species with a low dispersal ability (or fewer dispersal modes) could adapt to mild climatic environments as these might render easier invasion
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. However, alien plant species with a high dispersal ability (or a greater number of dispersal modes) tend to adapt better to harsh environments and can thus invade these regions successfully
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, studies should be conducted more on the investigation of the northwest regions of China compared to the southeast regions of China in terms of formulation of strategies to prevent the establishment of invasive species. Land managers and policy makers should develop more such measures to eliminate natural dispersal routes of alien plant species, based on their natural dispersal modes, and enforce stricter regulations to control anthropogenic dispersal routes.
</p>
