<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Silver nanoparticles exhibit the capability to interact with bacteria. This allows the size of silver nanoparticles 1–10 nm in diameter. The smaller size provides better antibacterial activity. Scientific research has proven the antibacterial activity of electrospun nanofibers containing polylactic acid and silver nanoparticles (AgNPs) against Staphylococcus aureus and 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic>. Fibers of silver nanoparticles and polyethylene oxide were mixed with polyurethane fibers exhibiting antibacterial activity on 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> [
 <xref rid="B103-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>]. Antimicrobial efficacy increases with an increase in the concentration of silver. The activity can also be increased by reducing silver nanoparticles. Smaller silver nanoparticles have the ability to disperse the bacterial membrane and inhibit bacterial growth. Antimicrobial activity of electrospun nanofibers results from the distribution of silver nanoparticles to electrospun nanofibers. Increased access of silver nanoparticles to electrospun nanofibers increases microbial capacity [
 <xref rid="B108-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">108</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">109</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">110</xref>]. Polyacrylonitrile fibers combined with silver nanoparticles showed antibacterial activity on gram positive Bacillus cereus and gram negative 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic>. The fibers formed from the combination of silver nanoparticles and Nylon 6 have an antibacterial effect on the gram of negative 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> and gram positive on Staphylococcus aureus [
 <xref rid="B111-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>]. 
</p>
