<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Much research has been focused on the learning and operation of plant extracts using electrospun fibers [
 <xref rid="B113-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>]. Researchers have managed to encapsulate with the use of electrospun fibers several raw plant extracts such as Centella asiatica, baicalein, green tea, Garcinia mangostena, Tecomella undulata, aloe vera, Grewia mollis, chamomille, grape seed, Calendula officinalis, Indigofera aspalathoides, Azadirachta indica, Memecylon edule and Myristica andamanica [
 <xref rid="B112-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>]. Also, essential oils such as linalool, pinene, eugenol and cymene are used [
 <xref rid="B115-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">117</xref>]. Antibacterial action with essential oils is determined by their hydrophobic nature. Bioactivity of essential oils combined using electrospun fibers to create scaffolding of fibers with antibacterial properties and thermo-mechanically controlled mobility. Electrospinning of chitosan nanoparticles and cinnamon essential oils in the ratio 1:1 has been demonstrated [
 <xref rid="B112-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>]. Fibers with a diameter of 38-55 nm were formed. The fibers were prepared from an aqueous solution containing 5% w/v acetic acid and various concentrations of essential oil (0.5 and 5.0% by volume). After fabrication, the fibers were cross-linked with glutaraldehyde to increase the stability of their chemical properties. The activity of chitosan nanofibres and ether oil particles has been proven in action against 
 <italic class="italic">P. aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic>. Efficacy of the essential oil was demonstrated in a study in which cellulose acetate was used as a polymer matrix [
 <xref rid="B118-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">118</xref>]. Fibers containing essential oils of peppermint and lemongrass were also analyzed. The generated scaffolds inhibited 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> proliferation and were non-toxic to fibroblasts and keratinocytes [
 <xref rid="B116-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>]. The Shikonin component of Lithospermum erytrorhizon root dried was also used in the electrospinning technique [
 <xref rid="B116-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>]. It has anticancer, antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and antibacterial effects. Shikonina was encapsulated and placed on PCL/poly (trimethylene carbonate) fibers. Note that the drug was released in the first hour at an increased rate and then for 48 h at a fixed dose. The shikonin-laden fibers showed a profound effect against 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli and S. aureus</italic>. The healing properties were also tested in combination with alkannins, which are naturally occurring hydroxynaphthoquinone. The connection was used for the preparation of topical and transdermal patches. Cellulose acetate, poly (lactic acid) (PLA) and two different poly (lactic-glycol) mixtures were used as a matrix. Inclusion complexes of cyclodextrins (CD-IC) with plant extracts and complexes with eugenol (EG) were also formed [
 <xref rid="B119-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">119</xref>]. Eugenol has a bactericidal effect and, in combination with inclusion cyclodextrins, has been used in electrospun fibers. The use of cyclodextrins complexes, increases the solubility of natural extracts in water affects antioxidant and antibacterial activity. Chitosan-based dressings were also developed for biomedical applications. A mixture of chitosan, TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, poly (
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>-vinyl pyrrolidone) a synthetic polymer with good biocompatibility was prepared [
 <xref rid="B120-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">120</xref>]. The membrane thus formed showed high activity against the microorganisms 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus, B. subtilis, E. coli, P. aeruginosa</italic>. The use of a membrane of chitosan, poly (
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>-vinylpyrrolidone) and silver oxide showed a similar effect, but with the added advantage of film transparency, allowing for observation of the wound [
 <xref rid="B120-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">120</xref>].
</p>
