<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In light of the limited available information on the effect of EO on ruminal microbiomes, we took advantage of a dairy calf production trial to investigate the response of ruminal bacterial composition and SCFA levels to dietary supplementation with EO. All dairy calves sampled in this study were on a diet regimen to promote early rumen development with the use of calf starter pellets, which provided a mix of the main substrates that rumen microorganisms would metabolize from a typical solid diet. Milk replacer was offered in buckets once to twice every day for calves to drink from, which not only promoted solid feed consumption, but also minimized formation of the esophageal groove which is induced by suckling. Thus, under this regimen, development of the rumen would have started well prior to weaning, so there was no sudden transition of the rumen from non-functional to functional status. As the main precursor for glucose synthesis, higher propionate levels are generally considered beneficial for ruminant production [
 <xref rid="B29-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Since significantly greater concentrations of propionate were observed in the rumen of EO-fed calves, inclusion of this blend in the diet of young ruminants appeared to create a ruminal environment that was favorable for animal performance. For growing calves, butyrate is typically considered the more desirable SCFA, as it is involved in initiating the development of rumen papillae through stimulation of rumen epithelial metabolism [
 <xref rid="B30-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. While propionate may also be used to a lesser extent as a source of energy for rumen papillae development [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>], its main effect would more likely be to improve animal performance, through its role as a major substrate for gluconeogenesis, rather than promoting rumen development. 
</p>
