<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The predominance of Firmicutes in the rumen of calves fed the control diet is consistent with a number of studies conducted with pre-weaned dairy calves [
 <xref rid="B39-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>], while other groups have reported combinations of Bacteriodetes, Firmicutes, and Proteobacteria [
 <xref rid="B11-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. Notably, Patra and Yu (2015) [
 <xref rid="B42-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>] have observed a lower abundance of Firmicutes combined with higher levels of 
 <italic class="italic">Prevotella</italic> in response to phenolic EO extracted from oregano, which is consistent with our observations. The same report also indicated that the effects of EO on rumen bacterial communities were dependent on the chemical nature of the EO provided as supplement. Indeed, the type of EO used, the composition of their active components, as well as their dosage, may affect their ability to modulate performance or the rumen environment [
 <xref rid="B9-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. For instance, a phenolic structure, as well as the presence of hydroxyl groups and their respective position in a compound, can affect the antimicrobial potency of certain EO [
 <xref rid="B45-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. While the specific modes of action of EO still remain to be determined, they are thought to be more effective in combinations, as different types of compounds may be more likely to affect microbial growth or survival through distinct mechanisms. For instance, additive effects of carvacrol and thymol against 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> have previously been reported [
 <xref rid="B47-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. As Gram-negative bacteria appear to be less susceptible to the antimicrobial properties of EO compared to Gram-positive, perhaps because of their cell wall structure [
 <xref rid="B45-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>], compounds such as p-cymene, which can induce swelling of bacterial cell walls, could act in synergy with other EO components by facilitating their uptake into target cells [
 <xref rid="B48-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. Conversely, we would anticipate that bacterial species able to thrive in the presence of EO would possess structural and/or enzymatic adaptations to counter EO antibacterial mechanisms. In the context of the current search for effective and sustainable alternatives to antibiotics, further investigations of EO-resistant bacteria could yield valuable insight into cellular mechanisms that could be targeted by future generations of antimicrobials. As the analyses presented in this report were performed using relative abundance, it also remains to be determined whether the observed changes in composition were the result of increased cell numbers for EO resistant bacterial OTUs or a consequence of growth suppression of susceptible bacterial groups. In addition to their antimicrobial effects, EO can also affect host gut cells, notably by modulating the activity of membrane channels and the uptake of ions [
 <xref rid="B49-microorganisms-07-00120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]; thus it also remains to be determined whether EO modulation of ruminal bacterial communities and host cell activity represent independent effects or can act in synergy.
</p>
