<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Cocrystals are homogenous crystalline formulations comprising of two or more compounds in which one of the active moieties are in the form of definite stoichiometric crystal structure bonded by noncovalent and nonionic bonds comprising of hydrogen bonds. These cocrystals prove to be advantageous in altering the physicochemical properties increasing the hygroscopicity, solubility, dissolution, and stability. This formulation also facilitates combination therapy such as drug-herb, drug-drug, and herb-herb, which help to improve patient compliance and diminish adverse effects. Many attempts have come forth for successful cocrystalization of turmeric constituent particularly curcumin. Suitable coformers of benezenetriols and benezenediols such as resorcinol, catechol, hydroxyquinol, hydroquinone, phloroglucinol, and pyrogallol were employed, among which pyrogallol and resorcinol formed successful hydrogen bond (O-H---O) in between hydroxyl phenol group and keto functional groups of curcumin enriching the physicochemical properties of curcumin. Various methods have also been developed up until now, mainly, rapid solvent evaporation to form pure phase crystals with curcumin. In addition, profound improvement of curcumin was demonstrated in contrast with individual coformers in terms of its hygroscopicity, stability and dissolution [
 <xref rid="B120-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">120</xref>]. It is believed that the linker (β-diketone) in the seven-carbon chain of curcumin is the key factor responsible for its low solubility and reaction with this keto-enol form can be altered by tailoring intermolecular hydrogen bonds with coformers through cocrystalization Hence, these cocrystals provide promising platform for future development of curcuminoids, as well as non-curcuminoids, particularly compounds which are structurally similar to curcumin, like cyclocurcumin and calebin A, to be tailored as solid dosage form with immense solubility and stability [
 <xref rid="B120-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">120</xref>,
 <xref rid="B121-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">121</xref>].
</p>
