<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The volatiles can act by chemical signaling for herbivores, and their biosynthesis can be altered in response to herbivory (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Valladares et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Banchio et al., 2005</xref>), as observed for 
 <italic class="italic">M. splendens</italic> regarding the concentration of volatiles. Currently, gall induction alters the size and area of the oil glands, and accordingly the concentration of VOCs in the samples of non-galled leaves and of galls is distinct. The substantial changes in the emissions of volatiles as gall induction consequence is expected (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Izzo et al., 2006</xref>), and is clearly perceived in the content of sesquiterpenes in 
 <italic class="italic">M. splendens</italic>. Such quantitative changes have been reported for other three galling herbivore-host plant systems (
 <italic class="italic">cf</italic>. 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tooker et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tooker and Hanks, 2004</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>). The volatiles, besides attracting reproductive partners (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Koschier et al., 2000</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>) may act in direct or indirect plant defenses against natural enemies (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dudareva et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Koschier et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Oates et al., 2016</xref>). Due to the high frequency of galls in the population of 
 <italic class="italic">M. splendens</italic> along the year, we can infer that the repellent properties of the sesquiterpenes were not effective against the associated galling 
 <italic class="italic">Nexothrips.</italic> The quantitative differences in the content of sesquiterpenes detected by the SPME analysis in 
 <italic class="italic">Nexothrips</italic> sp. galls in comparison to the non-galled condition implied favorable features for the galling Thysanoptera. The volatiles produced in the different samples of 
 <italic class="italic">M. splendens</italic> should be related both to insect–plant and to plant–plant interactions.
</p>
