<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During plant-pathogen interactions, pathogens produce effectors to resist and escape the immune response of plants. Our results found that loss of 
 <italic>MoSEC61β</italic> impacts the localization of the apoplastic effectors Bas4 and Slp1 and thus faces a strong plant immune response, including defects in ROS scavenging and callose degradation, and high expression of 
 <italic>PR1a</italic>. Accordingly, in heat-killed plant cells, the growth of the invasive hypha of Δ
 <italic>Mosec61β</italic> was not affected. This result is in keeping with the fact that the secretion of apoplastic effectors is transported via the ER-to-Golgi pathway. We thus conclude that unlike in yeast, where Sec61β is not necessary, in 
 <italic>M. oryzae</italic>, the β subunit is necessary for the transposon function of the Sec61 complex. A previous study also suggested other roles played by Sec61β in addition to its function as a component of the translocon. In yeast, Sec61β was found to interact with Sec4p and the exocyst complex component, including Sec8p and Sec15p [
 <xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. It is well-known that the transport of cytoplasmic effectors is mediated by the exocyst complex. Loss of the exocyst components Exo70 and Sec5 causes defects in proper secretion of the cytoplasmic effector Pwl2 [
 <xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. We therefore investigated whether the loss of MoSec61β in 
 <italic>M. oryzae</italic> would also influence the ability of exocysts and ultimately affect the function of cytoplasmic effectors. We observed the localization of Pwl2 during Δ
 <italic>Mosec61β</italic> invasion and found similar localization of Pwl2 between the Δ
 <italic>Mosec61β</italic> and wild-type strains. These results showed that the β subunit is necessary for the transposon function of the Sec61 complex and that the absence of Sec61β did not affect the normal function of exocysts in the rice blast fungus.
</p>
