<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The manual mixing method involves directly mixing the crystal suspension and the delivery medium physically using a spatula (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>). This method was used in the sample preparation process of various delivery media such as mineral-oil based grease [
 <xref rid="B52-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>], HA [
 <xref rid="B55-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>], synthetic grease [
 <xref rid="B55-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>], HEC [
 <xref rid="B56-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>], and nuclear grade grease [
 <xref rid="B56-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. For example, in the method using mineral oil grease, the grease spread on the glass slide, and crystal suspension was dispensed under the grease [
 <xref rid="B52-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. The grease and crystal suspension are manually mixed (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>A) and placed into the dispenser tip using a spatula (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>B). After sealing the exit port of the dispenser tip using Parafilm, the mixture was moved to the side of exit port in the dispenser tip by centrifuging for a few seconds (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>C). Next, the grease containing the crystal samples in the dispenser tip was transferred to the sample injector using a pipette (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>D). Then, the SFX experiment was performed [
 <xref rid="B52-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. The advantage of this method is simplicity and can be easily performed in the laboratory. Meanwhile, fragile crystal samples may be physically damaged during the manual mixing process. Rapid mixing may be required when a crystallization solution containing a chemical of high evaporation rate is included. Moreover, viscous materials may be deposited on the spatula or dispenser tip during the handling, which may result in sample loss.
</p>
