<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Chemical Composition of Essential Oils</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analysis of the chemical composition of the essential oils showed their chemical constituents and the percentage composition of the essential oils. According to the data presented in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab1" href="#tab1">Table 1</a>, the EOCz contained 31 compounds, among which (E)-cinnamaldehyde, cinnamoyl (E)-acetate, and eugenol were found in the highest percentages (68.7, 71.2, and 6.33%, respectively). In the EOCc, 18 substances were detected, with the major component being (E)-cinnamaldehyde, corresponding to 90.22% of the total components. The chromatograms are in Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">2</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A study carried out in Iran using
  <span class="italic"> C. zeylanicum</span> stalks extracted by hydrodistillation revealed the presence of 17 compounds in the extracted essential oil. The major groups of compounds were monoterpene hydrocarbons and phenolic compounds. Cinnamaldehyde (80.42%), 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-copaene (2.73%) and trans-calamenene (2.16%) were the primary chemical constituents of the oil. Other components analysed in the oil were present at amounts below 2% [
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">36</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a study to evaluate the chemical composition of the essential oil of
  <span class="italic"> C. cassia</span> bark obtained from the lower part of the stems at eight growth stages, most of the identified compounds observed belonged to the sesquiterpene hydrocarbon and oxygenated sesquiterpene fractions at all stages. The major component identified was (E)-cinnamaldehyde [
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">37</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The factors that determine the yield and composition of the essential oils are numerous. In some cases, it is difficult to isolate these factors from each other as they are interrelated and influence each other. These parameters include seasonal variations, the organ of the plant used, and the maturity of the plant, as well as its geographic origin and genetics [
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">38</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
