<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Antimicrobial Activity</div>
 <sec id="sec2.5.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.1. Minimum Inhibitory Concentration</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antimicrobial activity of the
   <span class="italic"> Cinnamomum</span> stem essential oils against the five bacterial strains in their planktonic forms was tested by the microdilution method in polystyrene plates. The minimum inhibitory concentration was determined by the microdilution technique in 96-well polystyrene plates. For the assembly of the plates, 100 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l of the essential oil solutions was serially diluted in culture medium, with the final concentrations varying from 2.00 to 0.01 mg/ml. Next, 100 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l of culture medium containing the microorganisms was added at the adjusted concentration of 10
   <span class="sup">7</span>-10
   <span class="sup">8</span> CFU/ml as described above. The negative control consisted of growing the microorganisms in TSB culture medium with 2% Tween 20. The MIC was considered the lowest concentration of the substances at which no growth of the microorganisms was detected [
   <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">34</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.5.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.2. Minimum Bactericidal Concentration</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The minimum bactericidal concentration was determined by withdrawing a 10 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l aliquot of the bacterial suspensions at concentrations where no visual growth of the microorganisms was observed. The aliquot was inoculated into Petri dishes containing TSA and incubated in an oven at 37°C, in triplicate, with bacterial growth observed after 24 h [
   <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">34</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
