<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Essential Oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two 10 ml units of essential oils, extracted from
   <span class="italic"> C. cassia </span>and
   <span class="italic"> C. zeylanicum</span> trunk bark by steam distillation, were purchased from Lazlo® (Belo Horizonte, MG), and (E)-cinnamaldehyde was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich®.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Chemical Analysis of Essential Oils</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chemical compositions of the essential oils were analysed by gas chromatography coupled to a mass spectrometer (GC-MS) using a Shimadzu QP2010 Plus chromatograph with helium (He) as the carrier gas and a FactorFour/VF-5 ms capillary column (30 m long, 0.25 mm internal diameter, and 0.25 mm film thickness). The carrier gas was used at a flow rate of 1 ml/min. The initial oven temperature was 60°C, followed by constant heating for 2 min, and was increased 2°C per minute to 110°C, 3°C per minute to 150°C, and 15°C per minute to 290°C, with a final isotherm of 290°C for 17 minutes. The temperatures of the injector and detector were, respectively, set at 250°C and 310°C. The injection mode was split and the injection volume used was 1 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l. The mass spectra were produced by electron impact (70 eV).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantitative analyses of the chemical compositions of the essential oils were performed on a gas chromatograph coupled to an HP5890 Series II ionization detector (GC-FID), using the same operating conditions and the same column type as was used in the GC/MS analysis, except the temperatures of the injector and detector which were set at 220°C and 250°C, respectively.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The percentage of each constituent was calculated by the integral of the area of the respective peaks in relation to the total area of all constituents of the sample. The various constituents of the essential oil were identified by visual comparison of their mass spectra with those previously published and with standards from the Nist08 library on the instrument, as well as by comparing retention indices with those previously published. A standard solution of n-alkanes (C8-C20) was injected under the same chromatographic conditions of the sample and used to obtain the retention indices [
   <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">33</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Substances and Preparation of Solutions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The substances used in the tests were included the essential oils from the trunk bark of
   <span class="italic"> C. cassia</span> and
   <span class="italic"> C. zeylanicum</span>, cinnamaldehyde, and oxacillin as a positive control. Calculations for the preparation of the solutions containing the oils and cinnamaldehyde were performed on the basis of the density of the substances and, to facilitate solubilization, 2% Tween 20 was used. All solutions were prepared at an initial concentration of 4 mg/ml and, after being diluted in broth, the resulting concentrations ranged from 2 to 0.01 mg/ml for all substances.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Bacterial Strains and Culture Conditions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bacteria used in this study were included
   <span class="italic"> S. aureus</span> ATCC6538,
   <span class="italic"> S. epidermidis</span> ATCC12228,
   <span class="italic"> S. pyogenes</span> ATCC19615,
   <span class="italic"> P. aeruginosa </span>ATCC15442, and
   <span class="italic"> E. coli</span> ATCC11303. The strains were maintained in BHI (Brain Heart Infusion-Difco®) + glycerol (20%) at -80°C. To perform the experiments, a 100 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l aliquot was inoculated onto TSA medium (
   <span class="italic">Trypticase Soy Agar</span>-Difco®) and grown in a greenhouse at 37°C for 24 h. After this initial growth, a 100 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l inoculum was subcultured into 10 ml of TSB (
   <span class="italic">Trypticase Soy Broth</span>- Difco®) and grown for 18 h under the same conditions described above. In the antimicrobial activity assays, the cultures were washed with Mili-Rios water and their concentrations were adjusted to 10
   <span class="sup">7</span>-10
   <span class="sup">8</span> CFU/ml using a microplate reader (SpectraMax i3 Multi-Mode Microplate Reader®) at 620 nm.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Antimicrobial Activity</div>
  <sec id="sec2.5.1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.1. Minimum Inhibitory Concentration</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antimicrobial activity of the
    <span class="italic"> Cinnamomum</span> stem essential oils against the five bacterial strains in their planktonic forms was tested by the microdilution method in polystyrene plates. The minimum inhibitory concentration was determined by the microdilution technique in 96-well polystyrene plates. For the assembly of the plates, 100 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>l of the essential oil solutions was serially diluted in culture medium, with the final concentrations varying from 2.00 to 0.01 mg/ml. Next, 100 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>l of culture medium containing the microorganisms was added at the adjusted concentration of 10
    <span class="sup">7</span>-10
    <span class="sup">8</span> CFU/ml as described above. The negative control consisted of growing the microorganisms in TSB culture medium with 2% Tween 20. The MIC was considered the lowest concentration of the substances at which no growth of the microorganisms was detected [
    <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">34</a>].
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2.5.2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.2. Minimum Bactericidal Concentration</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The minimum bactericidal concentration was determined by withdrawing a 10 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>l aliquot of the bacterial suspensions at concentrations where no visual growth of the microorganisms was observed. The aliquot was inoculated into Petri dishes containing TSA and incubated in an oven at 37°C, in triplicate, with bacterial growth observed after 24 h [
    <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">34</a>].
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6. Antibiofilm Activity</div>
  <sec id="sec2.6.1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.1. Quantification of Biofilm Biomass</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The plates were assembled in a process similar to the MIC test, and after 24 h the antibiofilm activity was assessed through the methods mentioned and described below. After 24 h incubation, the plates were washed with sterile water (200 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>l/well) to remove the loosely adhered and air-dried cells. The adhered cells of the biofilm were fixed in the plate wells by addition of 200 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>l of methanol for 15 min. Afterwards, the methanol was removed and 200 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>l of a 1% violet crystal solution was added for 15 min. Subsequently, the plates were washed and air dried again, after which 200 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>l of ethanol (96%) was added to each well which were left shaking for 5 min and then read on a microplate reader at 595 nm [
    <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">35</a>].
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2.6.2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.2. Verification of Cell Viability in the Biofilm</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After the incubation period, the culture medium was removed and the plates were subjected to three washes with distilled water. Next, 200 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>l of a 0.9% saline solution was aliquoted into the wells, and the plate was incubated in a sonic bath (LK-D32 Ultrasonic Bath) operating at 50 kHz for 10 min. The liquid from the wells for each concentration teste was pooled to bring the volume to 1 ml, after which a 20 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>l aliquot was withdrawn and subjected to serial dilution in 180 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>l volumes of 0.85% saline solution (10
    <span class="sup">−1</span> to 10
    <span class="sup">−7</span>). In a Petri dish containing TSA, three 10 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>l aliquots were cultured for each concentration. These plates were incubated for 24 h at 37°C, after which the resulting colonies were counted [
    <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">35</a>].
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7. Statistical Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical evaluation of the data was performed with the program GraphPad®, San Diego California, USA, version 5.0. The statistical test used was ANOVA for multiple comparisons, followed by the Bonferroni test. Values of p &lt;0.01 were considered statistically significant and are indicated by an asterisk. Each MIC experiment and indirect biofilm biomass quantification was performed with five replicates, and the CBM tests and CFU counts were performed using three replicates. All tests were performed in three independent experiments.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
