<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We have recently synthesised steroidal triazoles via the transformation of the phenolic OH group of the core-modified D-secoestrone scaffold
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref>. 13α and 13β epimers of D-seco derivatives were used as starting compounds. The triazole moiety was introduced onto C-3-
 <italic>O</italic> via CuAAC reaction of 3-(prop-2-inyloxy) derivatives with benzyl azides. The evaluation of cell growth-inhibitory properties of 3-[(1-benzyl-1,2,3-triazol-4-yl)methoxy]-D-secoestrones against certain cervical, breast, and ovarian cancer cells was carried out. The determination of structure–activity relationship revealed that the antiproliferative effect greatly depends on both the orientation of the angular methyl group and the nature and size of the 
 <italic>para</italic> substituent of the benzyl group. 13β Derivatives seemed to be generally more active, but a 13α compound displayed a substantial effect. The most potent compound displayed an IC
 <sub>50</sub> value in the low micromolar range. It was proved that the presence of the phenolic OH group is disadvantageous concerning the desired antiproliferative activity, but the introduction of a benzyl or, in particular, a 1-benzyl-1,2,3-triazol-4-yl moiety onto C-3-
 <italic>O</italic> leads to marked activity improvements. D-Secoestrone triazole 
 <bold>3</bold> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>) was subjected to additional biological investigations in order to shed light on its mechanism of action
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref>. The immunocytochemical flow cytometric analysis alluded to a cell cycle arrest at G2/M in HeLa cells with cell accumulation in the M phase. It was proved by an 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> tubulin polymerisation assay that compound 
 <bold>3</bold> significantly increases the maximum rate of microtubule formation. The antimigratory experiment showed that this triazole (
 <bold>3</bold>) inhibits the migration and invasion of HeLa cells. Based on these encouraging results, the 1-benzyl-1,2,3-triazol-4-yl moiety was introduced onto C-3-
 <italic>O</italic> of 13α-oestrone bearing an intact ring D
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref>. Our concept was to improve the one-micromolar IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of the best D-secoestrone triazole by synthesising new compounds bearing the same structural element at C-3-
 <italic>O</italic>, but on the other promising, hormonally inactive 13α-oestrone scaffold. The most potent compound (
 <bold>4a</bold>) was that without any additional 
 <italic>para</italic> substituent with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values in the submicromolar range. These results highlight the importance of 13α-oestrone as a scaffold and the 3-
 <italic>N</italic>-benzyltriazolylmethyl moiety as a key element in the development of potent oestrone-based antiproliferative agents lacking oestrogenic action.
</p>
