<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The surface structure and loading capacity of NPs are critical for the applications of coating films [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Zolfi et al. [
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] discovered a uniform distribution at 1% and 3% wt. loading levels of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs using SEM micrographs. While Cano et al. [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] reported sufficient distribution of the nanofiller into the polymer matrix, some TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs and aggregates may appear to be adequately disseminated in the polymer matrix with elevated TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> nanoparticle content [
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">110</xref>]. Xu et al. [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>] observed that the GO-CS biopolymer acquired a rough texture following the addition of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Moreover, Roilo et al. [
 <xref rid="B139-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">139</xref>] indicated that the surface of the TEMPO-oxidized cellulose nanofiber (TO-CNF) coating was devoid of revealing pinholes and cracks, while the presence of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> nanoparticle combinations was observed. Achachlouei et al. [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>] found that SEM micrographs showed well-dispersed Na-MMT and TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs through the surface of the films, especially at low concentrations. On the other hand, as reported by Valenzuela et al. [
 <xref rid="B140-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">140</xref>], SEM images indicated that the superficial structures of CS and CS-quinoa protein films were devoid of pores and appeared homogeneous. However, the micropores were observed in the CS coating film as documented by Xing et al. [
 <xref rid="B141-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">141</xref>], Xing et al. [
 <xref rid="B94-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>] and Xing et al. [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>], which might be affected by the diverse sources and characteristics of CS, its interaction with additives, and by the various materials and preparation techniques that were employed.
</p>
