<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In a study by Jebel and Almasi [
 <xref rid="B105-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>], SEM results showed that ultrasound (US) treatment reduced ZnO particle size, and established a hybrid nanostructure that is stable, while uniformly dispersed ZnO NPs coated the bacterial cellulose (BC) nanofibers. Shankar et al. [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] found that NC films containing Gelatin/ZnO NPs exhibited rough surfaces with evenly distributed NPs Both ZnON (ZnO NPs formed in the presence of zinc nitrate) and ZnON CMC were irregular in shape, while ZnOA (the ZnO NPs formed in the presence of zinc acetate) was cubical and ZnOA CMC was elliptical. Using SEM, Hasheminya et al. [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>] determined that the CuO NPs displayed uniform distribution across the kefiran-CMC polymer matrix, while Shankar et al. [
 <xref rid="B108-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">108</xref>] discovered that the SNP were dispersed evenly in the CS film. Song et al. [
 <xref rid="B86-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>] indicated that the diffused network of nano-silica in the CS matrix with the highly porous structure (TEM results), resulted from the formation of Si-O-C and hydrogen bonds [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. SEM imaging by Lin et al. [
 <xref rid="B76-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>] revealed that the Ag/TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NC particles were deposited onto the CS adipate layer. A possible explanation for this result is that CS acted as a reducing agent using electrostatic attraction and Ag-N coordination bonds to secure the metal ions. On the other hand, the results of Zaharia et al. [
 <xref rid="B89-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>] showed that hybrid materials modified with composite NPs (ZnO/CS and Ag:ZnO/CS) displayed the smoothest surface morphology and optimal NPs distribution.
</p>
