<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We found that 
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>multiflora</italic> was more likely to occur in plots closer to a road, even when land-use history was accounted for in the model. However, there was no difference in the probability of high abundance of 
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>multiflora</italic> with differing proximity to roads and the occurrence and abundance of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>thunbergii</italic> were not affected by distance to roads. Roads are important in the spread of invasive species as they provide corridors for their spread. Roads also provide suitable habitat for invasive species as the disturbance created by roads often leads to fewer competitors and increased nutrient, moisture, and light availability [
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Additionally, roads are hypothesized to increase propagule pressure of invasive species thereby increasing the success of invasion into surrounding forest [
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The effects of roads on the occurrence and abundance of invasive species tend to vary among studies depending on which species are examined and which other variables are included in the model. For instance, Flory and Clay [
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] examined the impacts of proximity to roads on abundance of seven invasive species. Four of the seven species studied, including 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>thunbergii</italic>, increased in abundance closer to roads, whereas the abundance of 
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>multiflora</italic> and two others was not significantly related to distance to roads. However, that study did not include land-use in its models. Models such as ours that include both land-use history and proximity to roads as drivers of invasive species occurrence and abundance are essential. Simultaneously testing the effects of land-use and road proximity allows the effects of each to be assessed independently as our models include variation accounted for by all other terms when assessing the significance of each variable in the model. Thus, factors like external propagule pressures associated with proximity to roads do not confound our estimates of invasive species occurrence and abundance in plots with differing land-use histories. Of the three studies that have included land-use history in their models, one found no effect of proximity to roads on invasive species occurrence or abundance [
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], whereas the other two found that proximity to roads affected abundance, but not occurrence of invasive species, opposite to our findings [
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. However, all three of these analyses pooled results from multiple invasive species, with one study using data from 95 species, so effects on individual species may have been masked in these analyses. Given that our findings and those of Flory and Clay [
 <xref rid="pone.0128161.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] both showed species-specific effects of proximity to roads, we suggest that individual analyses of invasive species are most appropriate for assessment of disturbance and land-use impacts on occurrence and abundance.
</p>
