<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="abs0010">
 <p>Over the past few decades, complementary medicine therapy using medicinal plants have been developed in healthcare. Phytochemical studies about medicinal plants have been conducted to verify their potency as medicinal remedies in modern therapeutics. 
  <italic>Dipterocarpus littoralis</italic> commonly known as Meranti Jawa in Indonesia is traditionally used to treat diseases such as diarrhea, diabetic and malaria. This study aimed to isolate bioactive compounds from 
  <italic>D. littoralis</italic> using bioguided fractionation method. The bioactivity measured were antioxidant, antidiabetic, and antiplasmodial activity. 
  <italic>Alpha</italic>-glucosidase and 
  <italic>alpha</italic>-amylase assays were applied to estimate the 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> antidiabetic activity of 
  <italic>D. littoralis</italic>. The antioxidant activities were determined by using the free radical scavenging assays 1,1-diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) and 2-2″-azino-bis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) (ABTS). Analysis of total flavonoid and phenolic contents were expressed as Quercetin Equivalent (QE) and Gallic Acid Equivalent (GAE), respectively. The i
  <italic>n vitro</italic> antiplasmodial activity test of methanol extract of 
  <italic>D. littoralis</italic> was also conducted against 
  <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> strain 3D7. Purification of the ethyl acetate fraction of the methanol extract of 
  <italic>D. littoralis</italic> resulted in an oligostilbenes namely α-viniferin (
  <bold>1</bold>). The structure of the α-viniferin was characterized by comprehensive spectral analysis including IR, 1D and 2D NMR, and in comparison with the literature data. Compound 
  <bold>1</bold> showed an 
  <italic>alph</italic>a-glucosidase and 
  <italic>alpha</italic>-amylase inhibitory activity with IC
  <sub>50</sub> values of 256.17 and 212.79 μg/mL, respectively. The 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> antiplasmodial activity test against 
  <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> strain 3D7 at a concentration of 100 μg/mL revealed a strong antiplasmodial inhibitory activity with IC
  <sub>50</sub> value of 2.76 μg/mL. Our findings indicated that α-viniferin (
  <bold>1</bold>) which is isolated from 
  <italic>D. littoralis</italic> extract could be regarded as potential antidiabetic and antiplasmodial resources in the future.
 </p>
</abstract>
