<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bacterial endophytes can promote the growth of plants and protect them from environmental stresses and harmful microorganisms. In return, endophytic bacteria obtain greater access to nutrients and improve their growth (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Shi et al., 2010</xref>). Endophytic bacteria can stimulate medicinal plant growth through improving seed germination, and indeed this mutualistic association may be necessary for successful germination in some species (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">Verma et al., 2019</xref>). Bacteria applied in biological fertilizer can improve plant nutrition and provide an environmentally sustainable means of improving the growth and yield of plants (
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">Vaishnav et al., 2018</xref>). Furthermore, the ability of endophytic bacteria to stimulate both production and accumulation of secondary metabolites lends itself to valuable practical applications (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2015</xref>). Inoculation with one or several endophytic bacteria has enormous potentials for enhancing bio-active compound production by medicinal plants (
 <xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2015</xref>). Moreover, it may be beneficial to explore the fluctuations in medicinal plant yield and quality caused by environmental factors in order to understand the reasons why certain areas produce Dao-di medicinal plants, which are very high-quality medicinal herbs produced from specific regions and have a long tradition of use and excellent medicinal properties. Given the importance of the endophytic bacteria-medicinal plants interactions, studies of such bacteria may enable the successful development of new areas of natural medicine. Under natural environments, microbial communities with mixed species can exhibit competitive advantages in metabolic complexity, productivity, resistance to invasion, and resource efficiency over monocultures (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Karkaria et al., 2021</xref>). Being capable of reproducibly and predictably constructing microbial communities for biotechnological or synthetic biological applications would guarantee the application of such advantages. Furthermore, the endophytic associations were studied only in approximately 1–2% of the known plant species (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Khare et al., 2018</xref>), most of which were the land plants, leaving aquatic plants in lakes, ocean, etc., completely untouched. 
 <italic>In situ similis</italic> culturing and isolation strategy in different plant niches can be used for find more endophytic bacteria (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Castronovo et al., 2021</xref>).
</p>
