<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="fsn3544-abs-0001" class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Abstract</title>
 <p class="p">In this study, the effect of chitosan film (
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CF</span>) with different concentrations of anise essential oil 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AEO</span> (0, 0.5, 1, 1.5 and 2%) on the quality of chicken burger during chilled storage (4 + 1°C) were examined over a period of 12 days. For this purpose, at the first, the physical and mechanical properties of the produced films were studied. Then, the chicken burger was covered with the produced films. Different treatment were analyzed by biochemical properties such as moisture and thiobarbituric acid, bacteriological properties such as total viable counts and total psychrotrophic counts, 
  <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>,
  <italic class="italic"> Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and 
  <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic>. The results of this study showed that adding 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AEO</span> improved the properties of 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CF</span>, the moisture, solubility, and water vapor permeability decreased in these films. By increasing the concentration of 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AEO</span> the tensile strength and elasticity of film were increased. 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CF</span> with 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AEO</span>, delayed lipid oxidation in chicken burger and improved the chemical properties of chicken burger. Also, microbial spoilage in these samples decreased significantly (
  <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; .05) compared to the control sample. 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AEO</span> at 2% in all experiments had better results than other treatments (
  <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; .05), and the 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AEO</span> (1.5% and 2%) had acceptable biochemical, bacteriological attributes up to end of storage, and these treatments could reduce the population of pathogen bacteria below the acceptable level from day 3 until the end of the storage period. Sensory score of the treatment containing 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AEO</span> at 1.5% was higher than the sensory score of 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AEO</span> at 2%. Overall, the results of this study showed that the use of 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CF</span> with 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AEO</span> as a natural preservative increased the shelf life of meat products. Considering the relatively similar anti‐oxidation and antimicrobial effect of 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AEO</span> at 1.5 and 2% and also economic aspects, optimum dose for 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AEO</span> could be 1.5% in the film.
 </p>
</abstract>
