<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The two metrics we have used in the analyses, RRN and RRI, are sensitive to the size of both the native and alien species pools, which allows us to assess the relative consequences of plant invasions on floristic composition and impacts. Socio-economic pressures are more important than biogeography and the physical environment for both RRN and RRI, but the relative importance of socio-economic factors is higher when explaining RRI (~50 % of the explained variation) than RRN (~40 % of the explained variation; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>; 
 <bold>see</bold>
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">
  <bold>Supporting Information—Fig. S3</bold>
 </xref>). This finding challenges the expectation of 
 <xref rid="CIT0077" ref-type="bibr">Williamson (2006)</xref> that socio-economic pressures are more relevant for plant naturalization than for invasive plants. Our result shows that human pressures such as the level of economic prosperity (per-capita GDP), land-use intensity (proportion of agricultural land) and human population density are pivotal for explaining plant invasions on a global scale. These socio-economic variables are proxies for the relevant causes of biological invasions such as propagule pressure (
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Pyšek 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Dyer 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2017
 </xref>), land use and associated habitat destruction (
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Chytrý 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2008a
 </xref>) and eutrophication (
 <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">Scherer-Lorenzen 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2007
 </xref>), i.e. factors that facilitate plant naturalization, and even more profoundly increase the relative richness of invasive plants. As a future challenge, there is a critical need for identifying the actual socio-economic pressures that facilitate invasions, and to improve our understanding of their importance for different steps in the invasion process.
</p>
