<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Researchers also tested chemical constituents extracted from different species of 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic> in order to make the botanical insecticides with a single and effective constituent. 
 <italic>T
  <italic>rans</italic>
 </italic>-ethyl cinnamate (LD
 <sub>50</sub> 0.37 μg/larva) isolated from 
 <italic>A. judaica</italic> oil was more potent than piperitone (LD
 <sub>50</sub> 0.68 μg/larva) against 
 <italic>Spodoptera 
  <italic>littoralis</italic>
 </italic> and also both these compounds caused complete inhibition of feeding activity at 1000 μg/mL [
 <xref rid="B81-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. 1,8-cineole and terpinen-4-ol (extracted from 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic>, 
 <italic>A. santonicum</italic> and 
 <italic>A. spicigera</italic> oils) were more effective against 
 <italic>S. granaries</italic> with 100% mortality at 0.5, 0.75 and 1.0 μL/L air doses after 12 h of exposure [
 <xref rid="B92-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Similarly, among chemical constituents of 
 <italic>A. mongolica</italic> essential oil, 4-terpineol exhibited strongest contact toxicity (LD
 <sub>50</sub> 8.62 μg/adult) against 
 <italic>L. serricorne</italic> adults and camphor and alpha-terpineol in fumigant toxicity (LC
 <sub>50</sub> 2.91 and 3.27 mg/L air, resp.) [
 <xref rid="B41-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. α-Terpinyl acetate (LD
 <sub>50</sub> 92.59 μg/cm
 <sup>2</sup>) of 
 <italic>A. rupestris</italic> oil showed more contact toxicity than α-terpineol (140.30 μg/cm
 <sup>2</sup>), 4-terpineol (211.35 μg/cm
 <sup>2</sup>), and linalool (393.16 μg/cm
 <sup>2</sup>) against book lice 
 <italic>L. bostrychophila</italic> infesting stored cereals [
 <xref rid="B96-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Some chemical constituents of 
 <italic>A. argyi</italic> oil such as camphor (11.30 μg/adult), eucalyptol (15.58 μg/adult), β-caryophyllene (35.52 μg/adult) and β-pinene (65.55 μg/adult) exhibited more toxicity against 
 <italic>L. serricorne</italic> adults having lower LD
 <sub>50</sub> values than that of α-terpinyl acetate, 4-terpineol, and linalool isolated from 
 <italic>A. rupestris</italic> oil [
 <xref rid="B37-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In their fumigant toxicity test eucalyptol (LC
 <sub>50</sub> 5.18 mg/L air) and camphor (LC
 <sub>50</sub> 2.91 mg/L air) had more toxicity than β-pinene (LC
 <sub>50</sub> 29.03 mg/L air). Essential oil of 
 <italic>A. ordosica</italic> possessed less toxicity (LC
 <sub>50</sub> 18.65 mg/L air) against 
 <italic>T. castaneum</italic> adults than its chemical constituents capillene, capillin, capillinol, 
 <italic>cis</italic>-dehydromatricaria ester (LC
 <sub>50</sub> 4.06 to 6.16 mg/L air) tested individually, however, among the essential oil and compounds tested, capillin showed strong repellency (100%) at 62.91, 12.58 and 2.52 μL/cm
 <sup>2</sup> after 2 h of exposure [
 <xref rid="B102-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. This revealed that the toxic properties of the oil could be attributed to the synergistic effects of its diverse major and minor components. All these results evidence that essential oils from these species of 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic> oils and their constituents can be used in the formulation of botanical insecticides against the said insects for the long-term preservation of food commodities infested by these insects. The mechanism behind the insect mortality in the contact toxicity test is that the volatiles penetrate in the insect body via the respiratory system and result in abnormal breathing, which leads to asphyxiation and finally the death of insects [
 <xref rid="B103-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. During fumigant application, main target sites of essential oils and their constituents in insects is the octopaminergic system. When insects are exposed to the essential oils, a breakdown of the nervous system of insects occurs [
 <xref rid="B104-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>] which lead to the blockage of the nerve impulse, later paralysis and then death of the insects occurs.
</p>
