<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">The essential oil fraction obtained from the rind of 
  <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> spp. is rich in chemical compounds of interest for the food and perfume industries, and therefore has been extensively studied during the last decades. In this manuscript, we provide a comprehensive review of the volatile composition of this oil fraction and rind extracts for the 10 most studied 
  <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> species: 
  <italic class="italic">C. sinensis</italic> (sweet orange), 
  <italic class="italic">C. reticulata</italic> (mandarin), 
  <italic class="italic">C. paradisi</italic> (grapefruit), 
  <italic class="italic">C. grandis</italic> (pummelo), 
  <italic class="italic">C. limon</italic> (lemon), 
  <italic class="italic">C. medica</italic> (citron), 
  <italic class="italic">C. aurantifolia</italic> (lime), 
  <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic> (bitter orange), 
  <italic class="italic">C. bergamia</italic> (bergamot orange), and 
  <italic class="italic">C. junos</italic> (yuzu). Forty-nine volatile organic compounds have been reported in all 10 species, most of them terpenoid (90%), although about half of the volatile compounds identified in 
  <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> peel are non-terpenoid. Over 400 volatiles of different chemical nature have been exclusively described in only one of these species and some of them could be useful as species biomarkers. A hierarchical cluster analysis based on volatile composition arranges these 
  <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> species in three clusters which essentially mirrors those obtained with genetic information. The first cluster is comprised by 
  <italic class="italic">C. reticulata, C. grandis, C. sinensis, C. paradisi</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic>, and is mainly characterized by the presence of a larger abundance of non-terpenoid ester and aldehyde compounds than in the other species reviewed. The second cluster is comprised by 
  <italic class="italic">C. junos</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">C. medica</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">C. aurantifolia</italic>, and 
  <italic class="italic">C. bergamia</italic>, and is characterized by the prevalence of mono- and sesquiterpene hydrocarbons. Finally, 
  <italic class="italic">C. limon</italic> shows a particular volatile profile with some sulfur monoterpenoids and non-terpenoid esters and aldehydes as part of its main differential peculiarities. A systematic description of the rind volatile composition in each of the species is provided together with a general comparison with those in leaves and blossoms. Additionally, the most widely used techniques for the extraction and analysis of volatile 
  <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> compounds are also described.
 </p>
</abstract>
