<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phytochemicals are the chemicals derived from plants and are useful for health when taken as part of the routine diet or medicine. Dates are rich in phytochemicals such as polyphenols (flavonoids, lignans, isoflavones and phenolic acids), carotenoids, sterols and tannins.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr4-1559325820962609" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
 </sup> Carotenoids are considered the major phytochemicals found in the lipid fractions of date fruits and are vitamin A precursors playing vital role in vision and act as antioxidants protecting the cells from deleterious effects of free radicals.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr5-1559325820962609" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
 </sup> Another major phytochemicals found in date fruit are phytosterols.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr6-1559325820962609" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
 </sup> Phenolic acids contain hydroxyl functional group on aromatic benzene ring having carboxylic acid groups. These act as free radical scavenger or captor, hence effective antioxidant.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr7-1559325820962609" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
 </sup> The presence of significant amounts of phenolic acids in dates has been reported in various published studies from several research groups.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr8-1559325820962609" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr9-1559325820962609" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 </sup> Mansouri et al. studied different varieties of date fruits cultivated in Algeria and identified the major phenolic acids such as sinapic acid, ferulic acid and 
 <italic>p</italic>-coumaric acid.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr10-1559325820962609" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
 </sup> Saudi date fruit varieties contain p-coumaric acid, gallic acid and ferulic acid derivatives as the major phenolic acids.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr11-1559325820962609" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
 </sup> Flavonoids are the polyphenolic secondary metabolites found in vegetables and a variety of fruits act as antioxidant and anti-inflammatory agents with notable health benefits.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr12-1559325820962609" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
