<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Intensive studies have shown that mimosine is of interest for medicine and agriculture, as it exhibits anti-cancer, anti-inflammation, anti-fibrosis, anti-influenza, anti-virus, herbicidal and insecticidal activity [
 <xref rid="B202-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">202</xref>]. Studies on mammalian cells shown that mimosine inhibits DNA synthesis, which prevents the formation of the replication fork by altering deoxyribonucleotide metabolism [
 <xref rid="B209-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">209</xref>] and is able specifically and reversibly block cell cycle at late G1 phase [
 <xref rid="B210-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">210</xref>]. In addition, mimosine can chelate divalent metallic ions and 5′-phosphate (PLP), which leads to inactivation of a wide range of enzymes that depend on divalent metal ions or PLP [
 <xref rid="B211-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">211</xref>]. The phytotoxicity of mimosine was demonstrated in 1966 on seedlings of 
 <italic class="italic">Phaseolus aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Subsequently, the inhibitory activity of mimosine (mainly on growth) was also shown on other plant species: 
 <italic class="italic">Oryza sativa</italic> [
 <xref rid="B212-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">212</xref>], 
 <italic class="italic">Bidens pilosa</italic> L. 
 <italic class="italic">var radiata</italic> Schertt, 
 <italic class="italic">Brassica rapa var. amplexicaulis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Lolium multiflorum</italic> L., 
 <italic class="italic">Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L. 
 <italic class="italic">var. humilis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B205-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">205</xref>], 
 <italic class="italic">Sesbania exaltata</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Senna obtusifulia</italic> [
 <xref rid="B213-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">213</xref>]. The use of mimosine on plants led to a decrease in chlorophyll content [
 <xref rid="B213-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">213</xref>] and inhibition of activity of various enzymes: antioxidant [
 <xref rid="B212-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">212</xref>,
 <xref rid="B214-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">214</xref>] or lignin biosynthesis [
 <xref rid="B214-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">214</xref>]. It was demonstrated that mimosine when mixed with FeCl3 at a ratio of 4:6 becomes non-toxic to plants—this effect of mimosine inactivation with iron had previously been reported in animals [
 <xref rid="B205-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">205</xref>]. The strong induction of accumulation of mimosine by acute UV-C exposure suggests that, like several secondary metabolites, mimosine can participate in general oxidative stress modulation, acting as a hydrogen peroxide and superoxide anion quencher [
 <xref rid="B215-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">215</xref>].
</p>
