<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Zhumeria majdae </italic>is a perennial fragrant shrub, belongs to Lamiaceae (Labiatae) family, endemic to the southern parts of Iran that grows on rather bare rocky slopes (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>). Its EO has a strong pleasant odor. Essential oils are one of the main sources of biologically active compounds (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>). For some time, this plant have been used as a curative for stomach aches, flatulence, diarrhea, indigestion, cold, headache, wound healing and as antiseptic and treatment of painful menstruation (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>). Phytochemically, the presence of some compounds such as flavonoids, diterpenoids and triterpenoids in 
 <italic class="italic">Z. majdae </italic>have revealed (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>). Cytotoxic, antileishmanial and antiplasmodial activities of 12,16-dideoxy aegyptinone B from 
 <italic class="italic">Z. majdae </italic>were reported (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>)
 <bold class="bold">. </bold>There are reports about the anti-inflammatory (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>), antinociceptive, acute toxicity (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>) and anticonvulsant (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>) activities of the EO and extract of 
 <italic class="italic">Z. majdae</italic>. In case of antimicrobial activity, the EO of 
 <italic class="italic">Z. majdae </italic>was more active on 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> than 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus </italic>(
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>)
 <bold class="bold">. </bold>In another study, its EO showed high antimicrobial activity against 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus pumulis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus subtilis </italic>(
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>). Previous studies on the volatile composition of 
 <italic class="italic">Z. majdae </italic>EO have shown the high levels of linalool (35.6-53.3%) and camphor (23.8-43.0%) (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>-
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>). Our current study, the cytotoxic and antioxidant activity of 
 <italic class="italic">Z. majdae</italic> EO was reported for the first time. Previous study showed that light, day length, mineral nutrients, drought, light intensity and altitude affected plants EO content (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>). However, according to our knowledge, no comparative study has been published on volatile composition and biological activity of 
 <italic class="italic">Z. majdae </italic>with respect to the impact of geographic variation. Therefore, the purpose of this work was to evaluate the effect of different environmental conditions on yield, volatile composition, antioxidant and cytotoxic properties of 
 <italic class="italic">Z. majdae </italic>EO.
</p>
