<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">In the use of CMMs, a large emphasis has been placed on the identification of DMMs since ancient times. As recorded in 
 <italic>Shen Nong Ben Cao Jing</italic> (The Divine Shennong’s Classic of Materia Medica, 25–220 A.D.) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], “each medicinal material has laws for its production region, authenticity, and freshness.” In various chapters of that book, locations in ancient kingdoms and regions, such as mountain valley, river valley or marshes, were mentioned for the first time as medicinal herbs sources. This record indicates that different CMMs come from certain specific areas. In his immense book 
 <italic>Ben Cao Jing Ji Zhu</italic> (Collection of Commentaries on the Classic of the Materia Medica, 480–498 A.D.) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>], Tao Hongjing, a well-known physician in the Northern and Southern Dynasties (420–589 A.D.), used such terms “good”, “quite good”, “fairly good”, “excellent” and “best” to describe the effects of over 40 medicinal herbals commonly used in medical treatment. Moreover, correlations between the sources, developmental stages and efficacy of these medicinal herbs were described. Sun Simiao, a famous physician and pharmacologist of the Tang Dynasty (618–907 A.D.), stated the following in his book 
 <italic>Qian Jin Yi Fang</italic> (Formulas Worth a Thousand Gold Pieces, 682 A.D.) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]: “Medicinal herbs used by ancient physicians were always from designated original sources, which accounted for their great effectiveness in medical treatment”. In that book, he comprehensively sorted 519 DMMs and systematically stipulated 133 regions of production. According to Kou Zongshi, a famous physician of the Song Dynasty (960–1279 A.D.), in his book 
 <italic>Ben Cao Yan Yi</italic> (Extension of the Materia Medica, 1116 A.D.), “in prescribing medicinal herbs, care should always be taken to select those from proper sources to ensure their effectiveness”, greatly emphasizing the designated original sources of medicinal herbs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. During the Jin and Yuan Dynasties (1115–1368 A.D.), the text 
 <italic>Yong Yao Fa Xiang</italic> (Medication Method, 1249 A.D.) also suggested that one could achieve excellent treatment results only by using DMMs with proper production regions and harvest time. Then, the Ming Dynasty (1368-1644 A.D.) document 
 <italic>Ben Cao Meng Quan</italic> (Materia Medica Companion, 1565 A.D.) stated that “the effect will be definitely different if medicinal materials are produced in a different environment” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. The record in 
 <italic>Yi Xue Yuan Liu Shi</italic> (Origins of Medicine, 1767 A.D.) attached similar importance to the use of DMMs collected from certain original sources [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. All of this historical literature showed that the use of DMMs has been a practice since ancient times.
</p>
