<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Nanotechnology deals with the engineering of matter at atomic or molecular scale. Nano materials are novel and conventional materials engineered deliberately to be nanostructured and used frequently for many nanotechnology applications. The size range of the material in an unbound state, as an aggregate or as an agglomerate including external dimensions and/or internal structure for 50% or more of the particles in the number size distribution are measured in nanometres (nm), and the delimiting size range of the nanoscale and the microscales is 100 nm [
 <xref rid="B1-bioengineering-06-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-bioengineering-06-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. The major properties of a nano-system depend on the size of the matter. The interaction of nanoparticles (NPs) with the food environment is defined by the size of the NPs, agglomeration/aggregation state, composition, particle size distribution, shape (including length to diameter ratio for nanofibers and nanotubes), solubility, dispersibility, surface area, surface chemistry (including surface coating/functionalisation), surface charge density, surface hydrophobicity, water permeability, etc. In terms of properties and transport, nanoparticles are considered to be tiny entities that act as a complete unit. Other factors that define the characteristics of a nanoparticle are its physical and chemical properties, such as surface area, surface charge, hydrophobicity of the surface, thermal stability of the nanoparticle and its antimicrobial activity, and NPs are used in numerous food applications. Therefore, a legal framework had been setup to regularise some fundamental postulates for the safety and quiescence of the NPs in food. The properties that interest food technologists to include nanotechnology in their studies is the highly reactivity, adherence, improved bioavailability and bioactivity and surface effect of NPs.
</p>
