<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Protein is crucial for several body functions such as production of hormones, enzymes, maintenance of fluid balance, boosting the immune system, and body building (Emebu and Anyika, 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Achi et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). The protein content of 
 <italic>H. arborescens</italic> leaves was observed to be moderate, and it can therefore be considered a good source of protein and potential protein supplements in the diet. Carbohydrate content indicates the energy content, and it is efficient for oxidation of fats (Omoyeni &amp; Adeyeye, 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Considering the substantial quantity of carbohydrate observed in the plant, it can be regarded as a good dietary energy source. Dietary fiber functions in the regulation of bowel movement, proper digestion, and effective eradication of wastes from the body. They also lower the serum cholesterol; the risks of coronary heart diseases, hypertension, constipation, diabetes, colon, and breast cancers (Narzary &amp; Basumatary, 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>; Viuda‐Martos et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). The high fiber content exhibited by 
 <italic>H. arborescens</italic> leaves is indicative of its great health benefitting potential. Vegetables are generally characterized by low lipid contents (Achi et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>); therefore, low fat content observed in 
 <italic>H. arborescens</italic> leaves supports this fact and suggests its potential to maintain body weight, for the management of obesity, cardiovascular, and other high fat associated diseases (Adegbaju et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>; Otunola &amp; Afolayan, 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). The value of ash content is suggestive of its elemental composition. Considerable ash content observed in this study suggests the moderate elemental composition of 
 <italic>H. arborescens</italic> leaves. Likewise, the low moisture content of the samples reveals its long shelf‐life and low risk of microbial contamination, since high moisture content could increase microbial action that can lead to spoilage (Olumide et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>; Ooi et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). The high energy content shown is attributed to the high carbohydrate content, which suggests that it can be a good source of dietary energy.
</p>
