<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the results of avoidance responses from bed bugs to residues of EOCs are promissory for protection of personal items, they are not robust enough to be considered for general use without further context-specific testing. For example, more testing is required to determine the responses of bed bugs to EOCs in the presence of stimuli occurring in natural infestations such as bed bug aggregation pheromones, and host-associated attractants such as human odors, carbon dioxide, or heat. Information regarding host-associated attractants is crucial to determine the potential use of essential oils for personal protection against bites. In attempt to begin to elucidate these interactions, we developed an assay to determine whether barriers of EOCs would deter a bed bug from orienting to and feeding. The assay was designed following guidelines from the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) for testing methods for bed bug repellents [
 <xref rid="B51-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and consists of a host-mimicking feeding assay that uses heat, a short-range attractant [
 <xref rid="B52-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. In our assay, bed bugs would need to cross a paper band treated with EOCs to reach the heated blood meal. We released the bugs within the first hour of the scotophase and ran the bioassay for 12 h to represent the approximate time a bed bug would forage for a host [
 <xref rid="B2-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Overall, bands impregnated with fresh residues of geraniol, eugenol, carvacrol, and citronellic did not prevent hungry bed bugs from crossing and acquiring a blood meal. However, a reduction in the bed bugs’ feeding rate was observed in assays with citronellic acid, which suggest that this component might alter blood uptake. Similar inhibitory feeding effects have been observed in the kissing bug, 
 <italic>Triatoma rubida</italic> (Uhler), exposed to citronella oil [
 <xref rid="B25-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Regardless, our results indicated that attraction of bed bugs to a close-range heat source may take precedence over avoidance responses to EOCs, and similar responses have been also reported when essential oil-based products were tested in the presence of carbon dioxide [
 <xref rid="B27-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Therefore, little benefit of protection against bed bug bites can be expected when EOC-based products are applied to items present in close proximity of a sleeping host such as mattress covers, liners, or around the bed. Further studies that evaluate responses of bed bugs to EOCs in the presence of human attractants (e.g., body odors) are required to determine the potential of EOC-based products for protecting luggage and personal items from hitchhikers.
</p>
