<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Polyphenols (i.e., flavonoids and phenolic compounds) are naturally occurring antioxidants that are believed to play a major role in the prevention of various diseases such as diabetes, cardiovascular diseases, neurodegenerative diseases, liver disease, and cancers [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Consequently, the determination of TPC and TFC is necessary for predicting a plant extract's antioxidant capacity. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> shows the presence of significant TPC and TFC in the four extracts of 
 <italic>Z. spinosa</italic>. R-AME possessed the highest TPC (87.72 ± 7.75 mg GAE/g), whereas Ap-AEE had the lowest TPC (30.17 ± 4.24 mg GAE/g). Similarly, the maximum TFC was recorded in R-AME (25.60 ± 1.57 mg QE/g) and the lowest TFC was present in Ap-AEE (7.40 ± 1.02 mg QE/g). These results indicate that the solvent type exerted significant influence on the TPC and TFC extraction profiles. In this study, AME was found to be the best extractant for phenolic compounds compared to AEE. Importantly, the magnitude of the values for TPC and TFC obtained for the 
 <italic>Z. spinosa</italic> aerial parts and root extracts are consistent with those obtained for phenols and flavonoids during the preliminary phytochemical screening (
 <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). These TPC and TFC values are considered to be lower when compared to the findings of Bouchouka et al. [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], who analyzed the fruits extract of 
 <italic>Z. spinosa</italic> collected from the Algerian Sahara. Meanwhile, another study [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] tested the aerial parts of 
 <italic>Z. spinosa</italic> from Algeria, indicating much lower values compared with our results. These variations in TPC and TFC values might be due to the distinct geographical conditions of the areas being studied, considering plants produce polyphenols as a response to environmental factors (e.g., light, temperature, and competition), as well as edaphic factors such as soil type [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Moreover, the types and amounts of polyphenols vary depending on the species and geographic origin and, importantly, the types of solvents used for their extractions. The present estimations indicate that 
 <italic>Z. spinosa</italic> contains a significant amount of phenolic and flavonoid content as well as considerable amounts of other essential phytochemicals. The presence of valuable constituents could account for the pharmacological activities reported for 
 <italic>Z. spinosa</italic> and might explain its extensive use in traditional medicine.
</p>
