<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> was first recorded in the classic medical book “Wang Bing Hui Chun” in the Ming Dynasty: “To treat snakebites, it is appropriate to use 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic>, tamping juice, mixing with alcohol, and rubbing the wound with dregs.” Essentials of Medicinal Properties of Raw Herbs (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">He, 2009</xref>) records that it tastes a little bitter, the medicine property is mild, the color of fruit is blue, and it is edible. Textual Research on The Name and Reality Map of Plants (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Wu, 1963</xref>) records that 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> has the function of promoting blood flow and treating gonorrhea. In addition, 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> is listed in the quality standard of traditional Chinese medicine in Guizhou Province (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Guizhou Medical Products Administration, 2003</xref>), and also recorded in many local medical books. According to the Collection of Folk Prescriptions in Guizhou (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Yang and Yang, 1978</xref>), 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> mixed with borneol and sesame oil can be used for the treatment of infectious pustulosis. 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> is known to have the ability of diuresis and detumescence, as well as treat joint swelling and pain of the lower extremities (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Fujian Medical Research Institute, 1970</xref>). Jiangxi Herbal Medicine (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Jiangxi Provincial Health Bureau Revolutionary Committee, 1970</xref>) recorded that 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> stewed with pig large intestine can be used to treat hemorrhoids. 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> is also widely used in the treatment of herpes zoster. In ancient times, people called this viral infectious skin disease “waist wrapping fire.” It was named because it often appeared in clusters of erythema blisters on the skin of the waist, showing a banded distribution, and its hurts like being roasted by fire. People collected the 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> from the valleys, fields, or ditches, then mashed it and applied it to the affected area, which could effectively relieve the pain of the patient and could be cured in 3‒5 days.
</p>
