<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Growth form was the best predictor of the ability of competitor species to either resist or suppress 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic>, but this effect varied with soil history and competition metric. For example, 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> suppressed the growth of all three growth forms in control soil, but this effect was more modest in 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history soil. By contrast, grasses suppressed invader biomass in both soil treatments, whereas forbs had no effect, and trees appeared to facilitate the growth of 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in control soils. The ability of grasses to suppress 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> may have occurred because they were taller than other growth forms at a young age, which would increase light acquisition (
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Grime, 1977</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Gaudet &amp; Keddy, 1988</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Goldberg &amp; Landa, 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr">Rosch, Van Rooyen &amp; Theron, 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Keddy et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>). Grasses also had relatively fine roots (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Fig. 5</xref>), which would increase nutrient uptake capacity (
 <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Aerts, Boot &amp; Van der Aart, 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Goldberg, 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Casper &amp; Jackson, 1997</xref>). Nonetheless, height may be the most important factor because grasses and forbs had similar photosynthetic capacity and root architecture, yet forbs did not suppress 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> biomass. 
 <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Meekins &amp; McCarthy (1999)</xref> also found that 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> was a weaker competitor against tall relative to short species. Though the ability of 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> to suppress tree growth has been previously observed (
 <xref rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr">Stinson et al., 2007</xref>), the observation that trees might facilitate 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> growth was unexpected. This effect may be due to aspects that were unique to the two tree species, 
 <italic>P. strobus</italic> and 
 <italic>T. occidentalis</italic>, which had the strongest beneficial effect on 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic>. These species were the only conifers in the sample and also ranked lowest in terms of growth rate (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>). The relatively strong growth form effects of competitor species on 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> we report here may not be universal however. Other studies suggest that trees can be strong competitors (
 <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Meekins &amp; McCarthy, 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Smith &amp; Reynolds, 2014</xref>) and grasses can be weak competitors (
 <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Smith &amp; Reynolds, 2014</xref>) against 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic>.
</p>
