<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In conclusion, our findings suggest that 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> has the potential to displace resident species in a community upon initial invasion via a relatively strong competitive ability. However, its competitive ability is weakened, rather than strengthened, by conspecific soil history effects. Like previous studies, we observed that soil with a history of 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> reduces the ability of mycorrhizal fungi to colonize the roots of competitor species. However, this negative novel weapons effect on mycorrhizal plant species did not appear overcome the negative history effects of soil nutrient depletion on 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic>. These findings suggest that the inhibitory potential of 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> on competitor species via mycorrhizal suppression may not be as strong as previously suggested. In addition, because longer term effects of 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> invasion include an overall increase in plant available soil nitrogen and phosphorus (
 <xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Rodgers et al., 2008</xref>), mycorrhizal suppression is unlikely to be a strong mechanism of competition in the years following invasion. This is because the effect of losing the fungal symbiont approaches neutrality when mycorrhizal plants are grown with supplemental nutrients (
 <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Hoeksema et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Johnson, 2010</xref>). The potential for weak mycorrhizal suppression effects suggests that eradication or control measures based on minimizing novel biochemical weapons effects in 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> may be less successful than other approaches. As suggested by other studies, reducing propagule pressure by removal of flowering individuals (
 <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Herold et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Phillips-Mao, Larson &amp; Jordan, 2014</xref>) and suppressing browsing by deer (
 <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Kalisz, Spigler &amp; Horvitz, 2014</xref>) could be more effective strategies to counteract the invasion of 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in North America.
</p>
