<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The essential oil was chemically analyzed and the relative peak areas for individual compounds were averaged. For the analysis a ThermoQuest GC-Trace gas-chromatograph (ThermoQuest Italia, Rodano, Italy) equipped with an FID detector and a Varian FactorFour VF-5ms poly-5% phenyl-95%-dimethylsiloxane column (internal diameter, 0.25 mm; length, 30 m; film thickness, 0.15 µm) were used. The following conditions were adopted: injector temperature 300 °C, FID temperature 300 °C, carrier (Helium) flow rate 1 mL/min and split ratio 1:50. Oven temperature was as follow: from 55 to 100 °C at a rate of 1 °C/min, from 100 to 250 °C at a rate of 5 °C/min and then kept constant at 250 °C for 15 min. The volume injected was 1 µL, previously dissolved in CH
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>Cl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. The oil percentage composition was performed by the normalization method from the GC peak areas, without using correction factors. The chemical characterization of essential oil compounds was performed by a Varian GC-3800 gas chromatograph (Palo Alto, CA, USA) equipped with a Varian MS-4000 mass spectrometer (Palo Alto, CA, USA) using electron impact and hooked to the NIST (National Institute of Standards and Technology) library. The conditions and column were the same described for GC analysis. The mass spectroscopy conditions were as follows: ionization voltage, 70 eV; emission current, 10 µAmp; scan rate, 1 scan/s; mass range, 29–400 Da; trap temperature, 150 °C, transfer line temperature, 300 °C. The essential oil components were characterized by comparing their relative retention time (AI) and the MS fragmentation pattern with those of other known essential oils, with pure compounds and by matching the MS fragmentations patterns and retention indices with the above mentioned mass spectra libraries, and with those in the literature [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-22-01163" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. The Arithmetic Index of the components was determined adding a C8–C32 n-alkanes (Sigma-Aldrich) to the essential oil before injecting in the GC-MS equipment and analyzed under the same conditions reported above [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-22-01163" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>].
</p>
