<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">In previous reports, it has been elaborated that 
 <italic>P. frutescens</italic> has two types of glandular trichomes (PGTs and CGTs), and PGTs were the primary tissues of biosynthesis and accumulation of essential oils with a predominant number and size [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. We certified another finger-like shaped GT, named DGT (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref> I-L), similar to the type II CGTs with a unicellular base, two elongated stalk cells, and one head cell [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The number of secretory cells was consistent with published papers (PGT usually with 8 cells, CGTs usually with one or two cells) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Under a stereomicroscope, the PGTs were filled with yellow essential oil in a large sub-cuticular storage space formed by the separation of the cuticle from secretory cells, such as PGTs in peppermint [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Compared with PGTs, the storage capacity of CGTs was limited to smaller sizes and fewer secretory cells. As shown in Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>E-G, there were two types of CGTs containing colored and transparent glandular heads. Whether there are two types of CGTs, or their developmental sequence, needs to be further studied. As for DGTs, there was only one transparent head cell that was unknown to have a secretory capacity. Its base cell may enlarge during development, as shown in Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref> I-K. PGTs, CGTs and DGTs were distributed on both the adaxial and abaxial leaf (mostly) surface and stems and were especially abundant in the central vein and the area near the leaf base. In summary, the morphological features and occurrence of GTs in our data were similar to previous reports of 
 <italic>P. frutescens</italic>, which is also similar to GTs in 
 <italic>S. tenuifolia</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] and 
 <italic>Mentha</italic> x 
 <italic>piperita</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]
 <italic>,</italic> belonging to Labiaceae.
</p>
