<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Animals can avoid unfavourable circumstances, and the survival of native species is mainly dependent on intraspecific or interspecific competition for foods, not the ecological environment; however, immobile plants can get enough light from the sun, but must face high temperatures, drought, and low soil fertility stress factors, so various adverse effects are almost uninterrupted. Under stress, the light energy absorbed by chloroplasts far outweighs the need to capture CO
 <sub>2</sub>, leading to a surfeit of light energy. In addition, closed stomata under stress block O
 <sub>2</sub> emissions outward, and the reduction of O
 <sub>2</sub> to O
 <sup>•-</sup>
 <sub>2</sub> (Mehler reaction) is exacerbated [
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. O
 <sup>•-</sup>
 <sub>2</sub> radicals can be converted further into ·OH and H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>. These molecules have a strong oxidation power and are described as reactive oxygen species (ROS) that can modify the structures of proteins, including enzymes, by affecting disulfide bridges and regulating various metabolic processes. Therefore, a suitable level of ROS also acts as an indispensable messenger to regulate various physiological actions in plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], but once ROS are overproduced, a range of destructive forces follow, such as altered adjacent molecular configurations, a reduced cell-membrane stability, DNA strand destruction, protein crosslinking, and peptide chain breakage, resulting in metabolic disorders and even cell death [
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. It has been confirmed that increased ROS levels are a result of stress, resulting in a 3-fold increase in O˙
 <sup>-</sup>
 <sub>2</sub> and a 10-fold increase in H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> under certain conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Under high levels of O˙
 <sup>-</sup>
 <sub>2</sub>, metabolic alterations under stress can be reproduced; the activities of superoxide dismutase (SOD), catalase (CAT), and peroxidase (POD) are decreased, and the content of baicalein, an antioxidant compound, was shown to increase from 0.28% to 1.96% [
 <xref rid="pone.0238927.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].
</p>
