<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Theory predicts that under counter‐gradient gene flow, the strong directional gene transfer could prevent local adaptation (Sexton et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0090" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Sultan &amp; Spencer, 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0092" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). This is contrary to the strong IBE that we found between the introduced and native ranges, which suggests that either local adaptation to climate has occurred in the introduced range or the introduced genotypes were preadapted prior to the introduction. The 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> haplotype M lineage was introduced into the East Coast of North America at least 150 years ago, but it started to become widely dispersed in middle and western North America only in the last half century (Kulmatiski, Beard, Meyerson, Gibson, &amp; Mock, 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Saltonstall, 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0083" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>); in a few states, the invasion was recognized only recently (Guo et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Kettenring &amp; Mock, 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Melchior &amp; Weaver, 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). This suggests that local adaptation might have occurred on the East Coast before the introduced population spread westward (Allen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Bhattarai et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). This is in agreement with conclusions of McCormick, Kettenring, Baron, and Whigham (
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>) who suggested that the lag time between the introduction and expansion of invasive 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> in North America could be due to Allee effect, that is, the time needed for the introduced genotypes to build up population density and fitness before spreading invasively across the continent. Several recent studies confirm that the introduced 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> populations heavily rely on sexual reproduction (Belzile, Labbé, LeBlanc, &amp; Lavoie, 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Pyšek et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0079" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). By dispersing pollen and/or seeds widely, the likelihood of outcrossing (Kettenring &amp; Whigham, 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Kirk et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; McCormick et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Meyerson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33869-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>) increases and the Allee effect is self‐enforced, as well as the adaptive potential of the introduced population.
</p>
