<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29" class="p">The tested substrates, i.e. chicken manure (CM), kitchen waste (KW) and brewers’ spent grain (SG), were all sourced locally. CM was collected form a broiler poultry farm in the greater Nairobi area and used one week after it was harvested. Though the use of manure in feeding farmed animals including insects is prohibited in the European Union (EU), feeding farmed insects with any type of substrate is not an issue as long as the end product is free of heavy metals, microbial and mycotoxins contaminants
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">85</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" class="xref">86</xref>
 </sup>. KW was a mixture of potato peeling, carrot remaining and peelings, rice and bread debris (contained no meat) collected from a local restaurant in Nairobi. SG was sourced from Tusker House, Kenya Breweries Ltd. in Nairobi after fermentation of barley in the beer production process. The substrates were chosen on the basis of their availability in Nairobi, with a view of their potential future use for large scale industrial BSFL production in Kenya and beyond in Africa. Metallic trays measuring 23 × 15 cm were used to contain 1 kg of the different substrates. Each substrate had six replications placed randomly in a wooden frame in a room. Five-hundred (500) neonatal BSFL were placed carefully on top of the substrate in each of the trays. During the rearing process, the temperature was maintained at 28 ± 2 °C and relative humidity (r.h.) at 65 ± 5%. Distilled water was sprinkled on the substrate to ensure 65–70% moisture content. All substrates were replenished weekly with fresh ones. After reaching the prepupal stage, the insects were harvested, washed with tap water, oven dried at 60 °C for 48 hours, crushed using a laboratory blender and then stored for subsequent analyses in a refrigerator at −20 °C. A sample of the BSFL was collected from each replication, pooled and a 200 g sample was used for the subsequent analyses.
</p>
