<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group content-type="other" class="fn-group">
 <title class="title">Patent Disclosures</title>
 <fn id="addinfo-2" class="fn">
  <p class="p">The following patent dependencies were disclosed by the authors:</p>
  <p class="p">Acevedo KBV. Formula for removing lice and nits and process for manufacturing the same. Mexican Patent application, MX 2010010985 A, 2010-10-06.</p>
  <p class="p">Bernstein JE. Method and composition for treating pediculosis capitis. United States Patent, US 4,927,813, 1990-05-22.</p>
  <p class="p">Cooper N, Brunton ER. A louse ova and nit loosening composition. UK Patent application GB2550558(A), 2017-11-29 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://patents.google.com/patent/GB2550558A/en" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://patents.google.com/patent/GB2550558A/en</ext-link>.
  </p>
  <p class="p">Hayward JA, Watkins DC. Composition containing protease separate from glycosidase for removing nits in treating lice infestation. United States Patent, US 5,935,572, 1999-08-10.</p>
  <p class="p">Kolender E, Kolender B. Composition for treatment and prevention of lice. United States Patent application, US 2017/0049110 A1, 2017-02-23.</p>
  <p class="p">McGuire TM, Kross RD. Lice remover composition. United States Patent application, US 2002/0025336 A1, 2002-02-28.</p>
  <p class="p">Mehlhorn H, Schmahl G, Schmidt J, Abdel Ghaffar F, Al Rasheid K, Quraishi S, Al-Farhan A. Compositions comprising flavonoid-containing extracts from plants of the genus 
   <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> and/or isolated citrus flavonoids and specific cationic surface active agents, and said composition for use as an agent for treating infestations with head lice. United States Patent application, US 2013/0252911 A1, 2013-09-26.
  </p>
  <p class="p">Ozelkan S, Zhang Z, Malayev V. Method, composition and kit to remove lice ova from the hair. United States Patent, US 6,524,604 B1, 2003-02-25.</p>
  <p class="p">Sacker J. Improvements in or relating to hygienic combs made of metal. Great Britain Patent 550,636, 1942-04-09.</p>
  <p class="p">Upton HF. Method for removing nits from hair. International Patent WO 94/23690, 1994-10-27.</p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
