<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Sodium citrate was added to a flask in which sheep blood that was aseptically collected from the Animal House at the University of Zimbabwe was kept. An equal volume of Alsever's solution (Sigma-Aldrich), pH 7.4, an anticoagulant, was added. The blood was centrifuged at 3 000 rpm for 10 min, and the supernatant was discarded. The residue was washed with a 1 : 5 volume of phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), pH 7.4, by centrifuging at 4 000 rpm for 5 min. The supernatant was discarded, and the cells were diluted fourfold with PBS to make a 25% sheep erythrocyte suspension. The resulting suspension was used for the determination of haemolysis. The erythrocyte suspension (500 
 <italic>µ</italic>l) was incubated with an equal volume of test sample extracts dissolved in PBS, in varying concentrations from 0.625 to 5 mg/ml, in 1.5 ml microtubes (Eppendorf, USA) for 90 min at 37°C. After incubation, the tubes (including the negative control tube) were spun in a microcentrifuge at 3000 rpm. A volume of 3 ml of Drabkin's reagent was added to 200 
 <italic>µ</italic>l of resulting supernatant. The positive control contained uncentrifuged erythrocyte suspension and buffer, while the negative control contained centrifuged erythrocyte suspension and buffer. Aliquots of the supernatants in Drabkin's reagent were added to 96-well plates. To determine the amount of haemoglobin released, the absorbance of samples was determined at 590 nm in a GeniosPro microplate reader (Tecan Group Ltd, Mӓnnedorf, Switzerland). The percentage haemolysis was calculated as follows [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]:
 <disp-formula id="EEq1">
  <label>(1)</label>
  <math id="M1">
   <mtable>
    <mtr>
     <mtd>
      <mfrac>
       <mrow>
        <mfenced open="(" close=")" separators="|">
         <mrow>
          <mtext>simple absorbance </mtext>
          <mo>−</mo>
          <mtext>negative control absorbance</mtext>
         </mrow>
        </mfenced>
       </mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mfenced open="(" close=")" separators="|">
         <mrow>
          <mtext>positive control absorbance </mtext>
          <mo>−</mo>
          <mtext>negative control absorbance</mtext>
         </mrow>
        </mfenced>
       </mrow>
      </mfrac>
      <mo>×</mo>
      <mn>100</mn>
      <mtext>%.</mtext>
     </mtd>
    </mtr>
   </mtable>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
