<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19" class="p">The results of the present study indicated that 
 <italic class="italic">Schizochytrium</italic> meal fed at different levels or in combinations with SBO and/or LSO as a replacer to FO did not cause a significant difference in the growth or feed efficiency of shrimp. Moreover, there were no indications of feed rejection when shrimp were fed diets without FO and shrimp appeared healthy throughout the feeding trial. In fact, shrimp fed diets with the highest amounts of the microalgae meal tended to have slightly higher growth than those fed the control diet with only FO as the added lipid source although differences were not statistically significant. In addition, the tail muscle fatty acids composition had significantly higher amounts of LC-PUFA compared to shrimp fed the control diet. FO can be completely replaced with SBO and LSO in the diet of 
 <italic class="italic">L. vannamei</italic> by balancing the omega-3/omega-6 ratios
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>. Recently, Kumar 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup> have used the algal (
 <italic class="italic">Schizochytrium</italic> sp.) meal as a fish oil replacer in fish meal free diets for shrimp, however the in the current study we have used the algae meal as a substitute to fish oil, but our experimental diets were fish meal-based diets (25% fish meal). Kumar 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup> observed that replacement of fish oil with algal meal and vegetable oil increased the weight of shrimp and nutritional value (n-3 PUFA and LC-PUFA significantly increased) of shrimp muscle. Algal meal combined with vegetable oil could replace 75% fish oil in shrimp diets. Recently, a combination of SBO, LSO, and beef tallow led to significantly better growth in 
 <italic class="italic">L. vannamei</italic> compared to FO only
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>
 </sup>. Nevertheless, the use of terrestrially-based oils substantially reduces the LC-PUFA content
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>, which is less healthy for the human consumer. The use of algae meal, including 
 <italic class="italic">Schizochytrium</italic> sp. and 
 <italic class="italic">Mortierella</italic> sp., are a viable replacement for FO in the diets of 
 <italic class="italic">L. vannamei</italic>, that maintain or even enhance the LC-PUFA content
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>. This is attributed to the high LC-PUFA content of the microalgae meals used, but the oil from 
 <italic class="italic">Schizochytrium</italic> sp. had relatively high and low levels of DHA and EPA, respectively. An imbalance in these fatty acids in other microalgae meals was implicated as a potential reason for lower growth in the shrimp, 
 <italic class="italic">Litopenaeus schmitti</italic>
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>. This is consistent with the concept that a monoculture of microalgae is inferior compared to the use of microalgae mixtures when compensating for any potential nutritional deficiencies to various aquatic animals
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>. In this study, 
 <italic class="italic">L. vannamei</italic> appeared to utilize 
 <italic class="italic">Schizochytrium</italic> sp. well despite the much higher DHA levels relative to EPA.
</p>
