<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110">Nanosponges are emerging innovative drug delivery or encapsulation systems that result from the advancement of nanotechnology. They are microscopic, sponge-like particles with nanometer cavities, which can encapsulate both hydrophilic and lipophilic substances including toxins, but when doing so, enhance their stability, bioavalability and solubility (
 <xref rid="bib172" ref-type="bibr">Ananya et al., 2020</xref>). Nanosponges are non-irritant, non-toxic, non-mutagenic and non-allergenic agents made-up of a polyester mixed with crosslinkers in a solution. The polyester is biodegradable and effective in delivering the drug to the targeted site (
 <xref rid="bib118" ref-type="bibr">Pawar et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Bhowmik et al., 2018</xref>). Nanosponges come in different forms including cyclodextrin which is most widely used and promising in encapsulation of phytochemicals. Cyclodextrin nanosponges are natural polymers formed from enzymatic degradation of starch and consist of a ring of oligosaccharides molecules. They are characterized by a highly porous spherical, amorphous or crystalline structure (
 <xref rid="bib135" ref-type="bibr">Sherje et al., 2017</xref>). An interesting property of cyclodextrin-based nanosponges is that some important physicochemical properties of the nanomaterials such as dimension of the polymeric mesh, polarity and release of incorporated bioactive molecules can easily be manipulated by using different types of cross-linkers and varying the degree of cross-linking (
 <xref rid="bib135" ref-type="bibr">Sherje et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib119" ref-type="bibr">Pawar et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib172" ref-type="bibr">Ananya et al., 2020</xref>). There are three widely known isomers of cyclodextrins, viz., alpha (⍺), beta (β) and gamma (ɣ) (
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Haimhoffer et al., 2019</xref>) that form inclusion and non-inclusion with different drugs to improve their stability, permeability, solubility and cytotoxicity (
 <xref rid="bib113" ref-type="bibr">Osmani et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
