<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Diabetes mellitus (DM) is a polygenic disorder, in which body does not deliver enough of the insulin, and/or body develops defects in insulin action which finally causes elevated amount of sugar in bloodstream. The estimated increase in global occurrence of diabetics would be from 4% in 1995 to 5.4% in the year of 2025 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. It is estimated that in India, the prevalence of diabetics is high as nearly 33 million adults are affected by the diabetes and at the end of year 2025, the number is expected to reach at 57.2 million [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Diabetes is principally characterised by hyperglycaemia which alters lipid, carbohydrates, protein metabolism and it enhances the tendency to get easily affected by serious long-term disorder including cardiovascular diseases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Prolonged hyperglycaemia can lead to severe compilation which probably affects body systems and even patient’s medication [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Untreated cases of diabetes shows severe vascular as well as tissue injury which finally comes up with serious health problems like ulceration, neuropathy, retinopathy and cardiovascular compilation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Among the two most well-known types of diabetes, Type 1 is dependent on insulin and it is caused due to insufficiency or dysfunction of insulin. The condition is mainly caused by the limitations in activity of beta cells. Whereas, Type 2 diabetics is considered as insulin independent [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] and major treatment procedures are through changes in dietary pattern, workout and medication. Such type of diabetes is comparatively more common as it consists 90% of total diabetic population and usually happens in obese individuals. Both two types of diabetics are associated with hypertension, dyslipidemia, unusual thrust, frequent urination, and extreme hunger with vomiting, weight change, blurred vision, excessive weakness, nausea and mood swings [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In addition, diabetes has an indirect relationship with many other endocrine disorders which includes abnormalities in production of proteins and lipids. Extra-cellular proteins such as elastin, collagen, laminin and laminin, which are produced in diabetic patients, are converted to form glycoproteins due to hyperglycemia. Development of complications due to diabetes, like cataracts, microangiopathy, atherosclerosis and nephropathy, normally come up with the alteration of these proteins which exist in associated tissues such as basement membranes, lens and vascular wall. The disease is mainly characterized as hyperglycemia, hypercholesterolemia and hypertriglyceridemia due to insulin secretion defects or reduced tissue sensitivity to insulin. Patients who are unable to make enough insulin are additionally treated with insulin dosages whereas those patients whose cells are unable to respond properly to insulin are treated with different drugs, developed to cure carbohydrate-metabolism disorders. Several therapies have been implemented for the treatment of diabetics but all are having certain restrictions due to their expensive nature and risks for the generation of hypoglycemia, gastrointestinal problems [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Considering the recent developments, efforts are being made to develop natural, economic and effective herbal medicine, having suitable antidiabetic property and fewer side effects.
</p>
