<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Sustainable extraction of NTFPs is considered the best feasible strategy for forest conservation in biodiversity-rich areas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The past decade has witnessed a rapid growth of interest among conservation and development organizations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The growing commercial trade of natural products, in particular plant medicines and crafts, has resulted in an increase in the harvest volume from wild areas that leads overexploitation of many species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Some species are considered commercially viable and may provide better livelihoods to communities residing in far-flung areas of the state [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Therefore, scientific documentation and information on diversity, distribution and use pattern, and economic importance of species can prove pivotal in the conservation and sustainable use of such plant resources in any given state and region. Further, quantitative on the relationship between biological and cultural diversity and the relative importance of natural resources for the local population can play an important role in the sustainable use and conservation of many NTFPs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Considering this, the present study has been undertaken with a focus to provide baseline information on diversity, distribution, use pattern, and conservation status of selected NTFPs that have market potential and can support the livelihood along with enhancement of the ecological, natural, cultural, and socio-economic capital assets and values in a Himalayan state. By collecting data and information from all possible sources, it is expected that a comprehensive strategy may be developed for the conservation and sustainable uses of NTFPs in the target state. Considering that many other states and countries have similar circumstances, the information may be used to improve the NTFPs sector in such areas as well.
</p>
