<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26" class="p">Hodge (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">1953</xref>) divided the chemistry of the browning reaction into three stages, now generally adopted as the three stages of the Maillard reaction. These are: (i) the early stage (sugar-amine condensation, the Amadori rearrangement); (ii) the intermediate stage (sugar breakdown and dehydration, Strecker degradation) and (iii) the final stage (aldol condensation, aldehyde-amine condensation and formation of heterocyclic nitrogen compounds). Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref> shows a schematic overview based on Hodge (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">1953</xref>) and van Boekel (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109" class="xref">2006</xref>). Two reactions occur during the early stage, the condensation of an aldose sugar and an amino compound (
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>-glycosylamine formation), and the rearrangement reaction leading to the Amadori compound (the 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>-substituted 1-amino-2-deoxy-2-ketose) or the Heyns compound if the reducing sugar is a ketose. While the first reaction is reversible, the second is not and is thought to be acid-catalysed. There is no formation of any aroma or colour at this stage. In the intermediate stage, the relatively stable Amadori/Heyns compound can react via two enolisation routes depending on the pH conditions. Sugar fragmentation and release of the amino group occurs, and Strecker aldehydes, among others, are formed (Rizzi 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" class="xref">2008</xref>); (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). These corresponding Strecker aldehydes contain one less carbon atom than the original amino acid (Whitfield 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113" class="xref">1992</xref>) and can be colourless or yellow. They are considered important contributors to the aroma of food products. Many patents have been granted which involve Strecker degradation to produce flavouring materials of foodstuff such as maple syrup, chocolate, coffee, tea, honey, mushroom and bread (Morton et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">1960</xref>). The final stage of the Maillard reaction is comprised of many complex and interconnected reactions of dehydration, fragmentation, cyclization, condensation and polymerisation, in which amino groups again participate. Strecker aldehydes formed from the previous stages can react with each other by an aldol condensation, or they can react with amines at high temperatures to give ‘polymeric’, high molecular mass, coloured products of generally unknown structure, called melanoidins. Heterocyclic ring systems, such as pyridines, pyrazines, pyrroles, and imidazoles, have also been shown to be present in food materials after these reactions (Nursten 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" class="xref">2005</xref>). However, little is known about their mechanisms of formation.
</p>
