<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The species response to climate has been successfully used for the development of a number of species distribution models (SDMs) to assess the relative suitability of habitats for species [
 <xref rid="B33-entropy-21-00571" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. SDMs predict species fundamental ecological niche or the area occupied by the species in the absence of interactions between living organisms [
 <xref rid="B34-entropy-21-00571" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The geographic distribution of species is constrained by several factors such as biotic interactions, dispersal ability, evolutionary history, geographical obstacles or human influences [
 <xref rid="B21-entropy-21-00571" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-entropy-21-00571" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Thus, the species cannot occupy the entire fundamental niche though the climate is suitable and therefore the fundamental niche is generally larger than the realized niche that the species’ actually occupies [
 <xref rid="B36-entropy-21-00571" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. This explains that the prediction can be mostly an over-prediction of the area than the species can establish and spread. SDMs can be projected under changing climate to different geographical areas or time periods to forecast the potential area of spread or assess invasion risk of a species [
 <xref rid="B21-entropy-21-00571" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Relevant to native species, SDMs can be used to assess potentially vulnerable species and sites under climate change [
 <xref rid="B37-entropy-21-00571" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. This has made SDMs more important in applied ecology to understand species response in the current and future climate [
 <xref rid="B38-entropy-21-00571" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] to develop effective and appropriate strategies for conservation and management. A large number of studies use SDMs to predict potential areas of distribution. Literature shows the importance of updated climate change projections using multiple scenarios as many distribution studies are based on older versions of climate change projections and a significant number of them cover only one climate change scenario [
 <xref rid="B39-entropy-21-00571" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].
</p>
