<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0195">Milk powder and anhydrous milk fat are used to make milk chocolate, and its addition affects tempering conditions as well as inhibiting fat blooming (
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Liang and Hartel, 2004</xref>). However, replacing milk powder could be economically beneficial and can allow the formulation of products that are lactose free and vegan. Mixture of peanut and cowpea milk has been considered as a substitute for milk powder as these two plants are common in Ghana, where cow milk is harder to find (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Aidoo et al., 2012</xref>). An earlier study used sensory tests to determine the optimum amount of peanut-cowpea milk in the chocolate formulation (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Aidoo et al., 2010</xref>). This milk mixture has a high milk fat content, which dilutes CB leading to slower crystal formation. This gives a softer chocolate with acceptable sensory properties (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Aidoo et al., 2012</xref>). Considering both rheological properties and sensory analysis helps to understand what ranges of different rheological properties can produce an acceptable product. Plant milks may not be able to supress fat blooming like milk powder; therefore, the addition of other bloom inhibitors may be needed for this type of chocolate. Lactose free chocolate is good for lactose intolerant consumers but the lactose in the milk powder influences the chocolate properties. In particular, a change in chocolate viscosity was noticed depending on the lactose particles being amorphous or crystalline; but it is still unknown if the inclusion of lactose itself affects chocolate properties (
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Bolenz et al., 2014</xref>). Some studies considered the use of soy milk as a milk chocolate ingredient, but samples with complete substitution were not given a high overall sensory acceptability, since the hardness of the chocolate was increased significantly (
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Pandey and Singh, 2011</xref>). There was no change in CB crystallization behaviour when using up to 15%–20% of soy milk in the chocolate mass (
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Pajin et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr">Zarić et al., 2015</xref>). Unfortunately, there is a lack of studies looking at milk replacements in milk chocolate and more research is needed in this area.
</p>
