<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>TPCs possess an aromatic benzenoid-ring attached to a hydroxyl group. Among all TPCs, mangiferin particularly is a potential bioactive compound in ML. In recent years, diets enriched with bioactive compounds are getting much attention due to their potential to minimize the risks of several chronic diseases’ development. Pan et al. [
 <xref rid="B30-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] stated mangiferin (7.43%) is a major constituent in ML extract, whereas other compounds reported in higher concentration include quercetin-3-O-β-Dglucoside (0.82%), quercetin-3-O-β-D-galactoside (0.86%), and isoswertisin (1.25%). Mangiferin is a natural xanthonoid polyphenol antioxidant and plays role in ameliorating insulin resistance, modulating glucose metabolism, lowering cholesterol synthesis, and inhibiting the expression of the inducible nitric oxide synthase and TNFα [
 <xref rid="B34-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. TPC and total flavonoid content in crude, MeOH, and EtOAc extracts of ML was reported as 230, 99, and 186, and 131, 46, and 191 mg/g, respectively. The phytochemical investigation of MeOH, EtOAC, and crude extracts of ML using ultra high-pressure liquid chromatography (UPLC)-MS/MS identified several secondary metabolites, including eleven phenols, ten benzophenones, nine flavanols, four derivatives of gallotannins, four xanthones, and seven terpenoids. The EtOAC extract showed higher TPC and total flavonoids (TFC) compared to the MeOH extract [
 <xref rid="B13-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Ouf et al. [
 <xref rid="B18-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] identified 83 compounds in ML essential oils of five cultivars using gas chromatography–mass spectrometry (GC–MS). Among them, trans-caryophyllene (8.06–18.88%), α-selinene (4.33–16.92%), and α-humulene (8.48–25.98%) were found in the higher concentrations. Gu et al. [
 <xref rid="B31-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] isolated and characterized four benzophenone derivatives, manindicin A, manindicin B, mangiferin, and norathyriol from ML extract by nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopic technique. Some of these compounds exhibited significant 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase inhibitory, immunosuppressive, and antioxidant activities. These studies proved that ML can be served as potential source of food supplement for improving human health.
</p>
