<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Moreover, locusts are nutritionally rich in protein, fiber, and essential fatty acids. Compositional data concerning locusts is scarce and exact values are highly variable depending on species, habitat, diet, metamorphic stage, and processing method. Orthopteran species contain high amounts of fat averaging around 13% (dry weight basis), with promising amounts of essential polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA); omega-3 (α-linolenic acid) and omega-6 (linoleic acid) [
 <xref rid="B4-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Moreover, insects are particularly noted for their high protein content. Orthopteran species can range from 15% to 81% protein [
 <xref rid="B5-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>], with averages around 50% to 65% for 
 <italic class="italic">Locusta migratoria</italic> [
 <xref rid="B6-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Orthopteran species also contain satisfactory ratios of essential amino acids recommended for human consumption, making them a sustainable protein option for consumers looking for alternatives to traditional meat sources such as beef [
 <xref rid="B5-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Yet, some studies have recognised the potential overestimation of insect protein contents when the nitrogen to protein conversion for meat (6.25) is used [
 <xref rid="B9-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. The high amount of chitin, a non-protein nitrogen (NPN) polysaccharide found in the exoskeleton of insects, can cause an overestimation of digestible protein documented in literature. To more accurately determine insect protein content, Jonas-Levi and Martinez [
 <xref rid="B10-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>] recommended subtracting NPN from the total nitrogen content, or lowering the conversion factor. Nonetheless, the high protein and fat content of insects and locusts is comparable to traditional meat sources, indicating potential as a meat or protein alternative for the growing population [
 <xref rid="B2-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-insects-09-00020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>].
</p>
