<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This hypothesis has been recently explored with the functional and structural characterization of a protein named HELLF, endogenous to 
 <italic>Podospora anserina</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The 
 <italic>hellf</italic> gene is adjacent to a gene encoding an NLR protein, 
 <italic>fnt1</italic>. HELLF is a distant HET-S/s homolog constituted of 277 amino acids forming an N-terminal HeLo-like (HELL) domain and a C-terminal PFD. The pseudo-repeats comprising the PFD of HELLF belong to the HRAM5 family, which is the most diverged HRAM family from HET-s (HRAM1 family, respectively). The PFD of HELLF (HELLF(209–277)) propagated 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> as a prion termed [Φ], representing a cell-death trigger for the full-length HELLF protein. The sequence identity between the pseudo-repeats of the two distant homologs was found to be as low as 17%, nevertheless it was found that HELLF(209–277) formed amyloid fibres with a β-solenoid fold virtually identical to the backbone structure of HET-s. This discovery establishes that specific amyloids folds can be maintained well into the twilight zone of sequence identity and that (as established for globular and membrane proteins) very little sequence conservation is required to maintain structural relatedness. In spite of the very strong similarity of the amyloid backbones of the β-solenoids formed by HET-s and HELLF, no cross-seeding was observed between [Φ] and [Het-s] 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. These findings demonstrate that amyloid backbone similarity does not determine alone the cross-seeding ability of prion amyloids and suggested that key side-chain residues can impact the cross-seeding between amyloidogenic sequences. The latter statement finds additional support in the observation that a designed HELLF-derived variant (termed HEC), produced by substitutions of HRAM5-specific residues in HELLF with HRAM1-specific residues from HET-s, breaches the cross-seeding barrier 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> with [Het-s]. Structural examination of HEC showed that the chimeric PFD adopts a HELLF/HET-s-like amyloid fold 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, highlighting the importance of the side-chains of the HRAM-specific residues for the breach of the cross-seeding barrier between HELLF and HET-s. The designed synthetic prion HEC shows some level of structural promiscuity both 
 <italic>in viv</italic>o and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and this type of plasticity (not observed in natural HET-s–related amyloids) might be critical for the breaching of the seeding barriers. The characterization of HELLF shows that the HRAM families have diversified into signalling domains with distinct signalling specificities integrated into independent cell death pathways. The establishment of the HRAMs as a structurally unified superfamily provides a powerful experimental set-up for future investigations, because determinants specifying the amyloid signalling (ability to seed and cross-seed) must be reflected in the catalogues of natural variation found for these domains, which share a common β-solenoid fold.
</p>
