<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The synergy assays between DCME extract or pure compounds, 
 <italic class="italic">epi</italic>-cubenol and 15-copaenol in combination with antibiotics (ciprofloxacin and oxacillin) against 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> strains (wild type, 
 <italic class="italic">norA</italic>
 <sup class="sup">++</sup>, Δ
 <italic class="italic">norA</italic>) were evaluated by the checkerboard method described by 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Motyl et al. (2005)</xref>, with minor modifications. Briefly, seven serial, twofold dilutions of extract or pure compounds and antibiotics were prepared. In a 96-well plate, 25 μL of each dilution of DCME, 
 <italic class="italic">epi</italic>-cubenol or 15-copaenol was added in each vertical row, and 25 μL of antibiotic dilution was added in each horizontal row. Both, first horizontal and vertical rows were left with only one agent, and the following rows contained a fixed amount of one agent and increasing concentrations of the second agent. In the selection of the range of concentrations, the MICs obtained for each tested agent and tested 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> strains studied were considered. The extract concentrations used ranged from 1.95 to 125 μg/mL, 0.008 to 2 μg/mL for ciprofloxacin and 25 to 0.05 μg/mL for oxacillin. To each well, 100 μL of MH broth and 10 μL bacterial suspension to McFarland 0.5 (1 × 10
 <sup class="sup">8</sup> CFU/mL) were added. The plates were incubated at 37°C for 24 h and measured at 600 nm in Elisa lector (Thermos Labsystems Multiskan FC Model). All tests were performed in triplicate, in three different experiments. Fractional inhibitory concentrations (FICs) were calculated using the formula FIC
 <sub class="sub">sample</sub> = (MIC extract + antibiotic/MIC sample) or FIC
 <sub class="sub">antibiotic</sub> = (MIC sample + antibiotic/MIC antibiotic). The FIC index (FICI; 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Garvey et al., 2011</xref>) for each combination was calculated by the sum of both FIC values, and results were interpreted as follows: FICI ≤ 0.5 synergic effect, 0.5 &lt; FICI ≤ 4 additive effect and FICI &gt; 4 antagonistic effect (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Garvey et al., 2011</xref>).
</p>
