<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The convergence of nanotechnology and biotechnology has created huge potential for advancements in medical diagnosis, therapy and regenerative medicine, which has fostered large investments in developing novel nano-biomaterials (NBMs) for use in medical devices (MD) and in medicinal products, including advanced therapy medicinal products (ATMP) (cf. definitions in SI Section 1). NBMs are a special category of biomaterials, which possess a constituent or have a surface dimension in the nano range (i.e., 1–100 nm) [
 <xref rid="B1-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. These new materials can offer unprecedented technological benefits as their interactions with the biological systems can improve biocompatibility as well as clinical efficacy, while reducing adverse effects [
 <xref rid="B2-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. However, because of their more complex nature and nano-bio/eco interactions (i.e., interactions of the nano-sized component with biological molecules and structures, and with the surrounding environmental media in case of release in the environment), there are both scientific and societal concerns about their possible health and/or environmental risks. These concerns are magnified by the lack of fundamental research on the interactions of NBM with human physiological processes (in both patients and other users), and the interactions that NBM can have upon release into the environment during the product life cycle. In addition, there is a concern on the adequacy of regulatory guidance addressing the complexity of these materials. Today we face the issue that the research and development (R&amp;D) into nanobiomedical innovation has progressed faster than the generation of adequate tools to assess the risk-benefit balance of these technologies. It is therefore challenging to propose effective risk management strategies in accordance with the regulatory requirements legally enforced to ensure their safety, efficacy and quality [
 <xref rid="B6-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].
</p>
