<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Additionally, we found that all CEOs showed radical scavenging activity against the two most commonly used non-biological radicals. Interestingly, we observed that radical scavenging activity increased with maturation when measured against DPPH•, while an opposite trend was observed in the case of ABTS•
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>. It has been previously reported that antioxidant capacity determined by in vitro assays can significantly differ [
 <xref rid="B55-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. The ABTS assay is based on the 
 <italic class="italic">in situ</italic> generation of a blue/green radical (ABTS•
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>) that can be reduced by antioxidants by either single electron transfer (SET) or hydrogen transfer (HT) mechanisms, whereas the DPPH assay is based on the reduction of the purple DPPH• to 1,1-diphenyl-2-picryl hydrazine (DPPH-H) via HT mechanism. Moreover, it is worth noticing that CEOs are coloured (CEO1 and CEO2 are green, while CEO3 is yellow). Differences between in vitro antioxidant capacities determined by the two assays have been reported for highly pigmented samples [
 <xref rid="B55-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. Nevertheless, the combination of the results obtained from these two assays is considered of higher significance for a reliable evaluation of plant extract radical scavenging ability than the use of only one method [
 <xref rid="B56-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. Remarkably, we found that CEO2 showed high radical scavenging activity in both assays, indicating that CEO2 can act against both DPPH• and ABTS•
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>. In line with our findings, anti-inflammatory potential is often associated with free radical scavenging activity [
 <xref rid="B14-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. Reactive oxygen species (ROS) are crucial in the onset of the inflammation by activating transcription factors, such as the nuclear factor-kappa B (NF-κB), which induces the gene expression of inflammatory enzymes and cytokines [
 <xref rid="B1-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. 
</p>
