<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The analysis of the volatile composition revealed that limonene, linalool, and linalyl acetate were the main components in all CEOs, while γ-terpinene was found in a significant percentage in CEO2 and to a lesser extent in CEO3. The relatively low amount of limonene compared to other 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> species is in line with data from Lota and coworkers [
 <xref rid="B32-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>], while it is in contrast with other results, where limonene represented 80.1% of the oil [
 <xref rid="B33-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Interestingly, linalool and linalyl acetate were reported to be absent or present in far lower amounts in previous works [
 <xref rid="B32-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. These variations could be due to differences in ripening stage, genetic origins, or pedoclimatic conditions. In line with the previously mentioned close taxonomical relation between chinotto and bergamot (
 <italic class="italic">Citrus bergamia</italic> Risso) [
 <xref rid="B19-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>], our results were comparable to the known distribution of volatile compounds in bergamot essential oil, comprising a relatively low amount of limonene (25–53%) and high percentages of linalool (2–20%), linalyl acetate (15–40%), and γ-terpinene [
 <xref rid="B25-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Regarding individual components, limonene is by far the most abundant compound in CEO2 and CEO3 and these results can be associated with the corresponding radical scavenging activities, as limonene has been reported to exert strong DPPH• and poor ABTS•
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> scavenging abilities [
 <xref rid="B58-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. Moreover, this monoterpene is the main bioactive molecule of many essential oils known to display anti-inflammatory properties [
 <xref rid="B53-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. However, it is not possible to ascribe the reduction of NO concentration to limonene only, since CEO3 contains amounts comparable to those of CEO2 (
 <xref rid="nutrients-10-00783-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Other compounds identified in CEO2, including linalool, linalyl acetate, and γ-terpinene, have been previously reported to display antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activities 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> and in vivo [
 <xref rid="B51-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. In particular, linalool, and to a lesser extent linalyl acetate, have been found to reduce carrageenan-induced paw edema in rats [
 <xref rid="B62-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>] and to inhibit NO, IL-6 and TNF-α production and gene expression in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 cells [
 <xref rid="B63-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. γ-Terpinene treatment reduced carrageenan-induced paw edema and neutrophil migration, as well as production of pro-inflammatory cytokines, such as interleukin (IL)-1β and tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), in a carrageenan-induced peritonitis model and cell migration in LPS-induced lung injury in Swiss mice [
 <xref rid="B64-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. Moreover, γ-terpinene was found to reduce the production of pro-inflammatory cytokines, such as IL-1β and IL-6, and to enhance that of the anti-inflammatory cytokine, IL-10, in LPS-induced murine peritoneal macrophages [
 <xref rid="B64-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. However, its concentration in CEO2 is lower than that previously reported to reduce NO [
 <xref rid="B51-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. Therefore, a possible explanation is that the reduction of the NO levels elicited by CEO2 could originate from the additive and/or synergistic effects of more bioactives, rather than from a specific compound. The sum of limonene, linalool, linalyl acetate, and γ-terpinene accounted for 93.0% of the total constituents in CEO2. Such a high percentage suggests that these four compounds might be responsible for its observed anti-inflammatory activity. In line with these findings, synergistic effects of the components of other 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> essential oils in murine macrophages have been previously reported [
 <xref rid="B52-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-nutrients-10-00783" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]. Nevertheless, a variation in the individual amounts upon maturation was found and it is likely that this plays a role in the observed differences in bioactivity. In particular, γ-terpinene was found in a significant percentage only in CEO2 and, as such, could play a crucial role in the observed anti-inflammatory properties. 
</p>
