<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>Euphorbia hirta</italic> was reported to be able to decrease blood glucose level (hypoglycemic effect) on alloxan-induced diabetic rats. From other in vitro experiments, ethanol extract and ethyl acetate fractions inhibit α-glucosidase activity. In vivo tests also had the same result. [
 <xref rid="B158-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>,
 <xref rid="B159-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>,
 <xref rid="B160-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>]. The presence of various bioactive compounds, especially in chloroform and ethyl acetate extracts demonstrated the ability in the treatment of diabetes by inhibition of enzymes involving in the metabolism of saccharides such as α-amylase [
 <xref rid="B161-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. Polyphenolic compounds have popularly reported inhibitory activity against α-amylase in both in vitro and in vivo experiments. Phenolics and flavonoids found in 
 <italic>E. hirta</italic> such as quercetin, quercitrin, and rutin have been proved to be effective inhibitors of mammalian α-amylase. Although the α-amylase inhibitory activity of 
 <italic>E. hirta</italic> powder is not strong enough as acarbose—a standard drug in diabetes treatment—it also proved that 
 <italic>E. hirta</italic> had mild α-amylase inhibition. Until 2010 Sunil Kumar, Rashmi and D. Kumar presented the evaluation of the antidiabetic activity of 
 <italic>Euphorbia hirta</italic> Linn. in streptozotocin-induced diabetic mice [
 <xref rid="B160-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>]. In 2014, the ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>Euphorbia hirta</italic> was reported that it can decrease blood glucose level (hypoglycemic effect) on alloxan-induced diabetic rats. From other in vitro experiments, ethanol extract and ethyl acetate fractions inhibited α-glucosidase activity. In vivo tests also had the same result [
 <xref rid="B158-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. In 2015 Manjur Ali Sheliya and his partners studied the inhibition of α-glucosidase by new prenylated flavonoids from 
 <italic>E. hirta</italic> [
 <xref rid="B162-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>] isolated from ethyl acetate fraction of methanolic extract. By using medium pressure liquid chromatography technique, they successfully isolated four active compounds, including quercetrin (1), dimethoxy quercetrin (2), hirtacoumaroflavonoside (7-O-(
 <italic>p</italic>-coumaroyl)-5,7,4′-trihydroxy-6-(3,3-dimethyl allyl)-flavonol-3-O-β-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucopyranosyl-(2″-1″′)-O-α-
 <sc>l</sc>-rhamnopyranoside) (3) and hirtaflavonoside-B (5,7,3′,4′-trihydroxy-6-(3,3-dimethyl allyl)-8-(iso-butenyl)-flavonol-3-C-β-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucopyranoside) (4) respectively. The α-glucosidase inhibitory activity of isolated compounds was evaluated and compared with standard drug acarbose. The result showed that those flavonoids increased α-glucosidase inhibition. That study provides credence to the ethnomedicinal use of 
 <italic>E. hirta</italic> in the management of diabetes in folk medicine. In 2016 Manjur Ali Sheliya and his group continued to investigate in vitro α-glucosidase and α-amylase inhibition by aqueous, hydroalcoholic, and alcoholic extract of 
 <italic>E. hirta</italic> [
 <xref rid="B163-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>]. According to their study, the result clearly indicated that the metholic extract of 
 <italic>E. hirta</italic> had strong inhibitory activity against α-glucosidase and quietly mild inhibitory activity against α-amylase, two proteins involved in diabetes mellitus directly. 
 <italic>E. hirta</italic> extract can be used for control of postprandial hyperglycemia with lesser side effects, and provide good material for further studies on treatment type 2 diabetes mellitus.
</p>
