<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p id="Par1" class="p">
   <italic class="italic">Osmanthus fragrans</italic> has been used as folk medicine for thousands of years. The extracts of 
   <italic class="italic">Osmanthus fragrans</italic> flowers were reported to have various bioactivities including free radical scavenging, anti-inflammation, neuroprotection and antitumor effects. However, there is still lack of knowledge about its essential oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2" class="p">In this work, we analyzed the chemical composition of the essential oil from 
   <italic class="italic">Osmanthus fragrans</italic> var. 
   <italic class="italic">thunbergii</italic> by GC-MS. A complex network approach was applied to investigate the interrelationships between the ingredients, target proteins, and related pathways for the essential oil. Statistical characteristics of the networks were further studied to explore the main active ingredients and potential bioactivities of 
   <italic class="italic">O. fragrans</italic> var. 
   <italic class="italic">thunbergii</italic> essential oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p id="Par3" class="p">A total of 44 ingredients were selected from the chemical composition of 
   <italic class="italic">O. fragrans</italic> var. 
   <italic class="italic">thunbergii</italic> essential oil, and that 191 potential target proteins together with 70 pathways were collected for these compounds. An ingredient-target-pathway network was constructed based on these data and showed scale-free property as well as power-law degree distribution. Eugenol and geraniol were screened as main active ingredients with much higher degree values. Potential neuroprotective and anti-tumor effect of the essential oil were also found. A core subnetwork was extracted from the ingredient-target-pathway network, and indicated that eugenol and geraniol contributed most to the neuroprotection of this essential oil. Furthermore, a pathway-based protein association network was built and exhibited small-world property. MAPK1 and MAPK3 were considered as key proteins with highest scores of centrality indices, which might play an important role in the anti-tumor effect of the essential oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par4" class="p">This work predicted the main active ingredients and bioactivities of 
   <italic class="italic">O. fragrans</italic> var. 
   <italic class="italic">thunbergii</italic> essential oil, which would benefit the development and utilization of 
   <italic class="italic">Osmanthus fragrans</italic> flowers. The application of complex network theory was proved to be effective in bioactivities studies of essential oil. Moreover, it provides a novel strategy for exploring the molecular mechanisms of traditional medicines.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Electronic supplementary material</title>
  <p class="p">The online version of this article (10.1186/s12918-017-0523-0) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
