<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Studies show the involvement of multiple microbes, such as bacteria and fungi, causing airways diseases (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Gileles-Hillel et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Cheesman et al., 2017</xref>). The infections caused by antibiotic-resistant pathogens such as MRSA are complicated and challenging to treat. It has been reported that aromatic plant essential oils exhibit an antimicrobial effect when used alone (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Costa et al., 2015</xref>) or in combination with antibiotics to combat multidrug-resistant bacteria (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Cheesman et al., 2017</xref>). Therefore, TS Oil was also tested for possible antimicrobial potential to sort out added role of the TS Oil in addressing infectious-related airways disorders. Interestingly, TS Oil showed antimicrobial effects against MRSA, 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, and 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>, which might further demonstrate its therapeutic effects on microbial infections of respiratory system. Further studies are recommended to know the mechanism of the observed antimicrobial effect of TS Oil. GS-analysis of the TS Oil revealed the presence of various monoterpene hydrocarbons. These include the chemotypes of Thymus species; thymol (34.3%) and carvacrol (19.5%) that are identified as major phyto-constituents. Minor phyto-constituents like monoterpenes such as pinene, cymene, and caryophyllene oxide have also been identified. Thymol and carvacrol have been reported to possess bronchodilatory, antihistaminic, and sympathomimetic properties (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Boskabady and Jandaghi, 2003</xref>). Besides antibacterial and antifungal activities (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 2010</xref>), thymol and carvacrol also reduce the levels of IgE, IL-4, IL-5, and IL-13, as well as the number of inflammatory cells in the airways (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2014</xref>). Hence, the observed combination of activities (tracheal relaxation and antimicrobial) in the essential oil of 
 <italic>T. serrulatus</italic> might be co-related to its major phytochemical constituents—thymol and carvacrol. However, the involvement of more phytochemicals and unexplored mechanism(s) cannot be ruled out.
</p>
