<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Plasmolysis studies also paved the way toward understanding the species responsible for selective permeability. Two of the pioneers in this field of work were Jacques Loeb and W.J.V. Osterhout, the first two editors of 
 <italic class="italic">JGP</italic>. They independently performed some of the first studies of cell permeability in the presence of inorganic salts (
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Osterhout, 1911</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Loeb, 1912</xref>). In the first of these studies, Osterhout repeated Overton’s experiments of plasmolysis in 
 <italic class="italic">Spirogyra</italic> but this time studied the cells over a longer period of time. When placing the cells in a concentrated salt solution, he observed Overton’s initial result that the protoplast shrank away from the cell wall. However, over a longer time period, he observed the protoplast returned to its original shape and volume, which meant that the membrane was actually permeable to these inorganic ions. He went on to conclude that this must mean that the membrane was not composed of lipoid as previously asserted but instead was proteoid in nature. Perhaps this was too strong a conclusion given prior results, yet it highlights several truths about permeability across cell membranes. First, the passage of charges across the membrane must be electrostatically supported by protein, and second, membranes actually contain a large fraction of protein. A comprehensive review of permeability, and more on the work of Loeb and Osterhout, can be found in a recent Milestone article in 
 <italic class="italic">JGP</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hille, 2018</xref>). In the following sections, I highlight a few key studies that led to the solidification of integral membrane proteins as a new class of hydrophobic proteins that are responsible for the proteoid nature of cell membranes.
</p>
