<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The findings from recent animal studies support our statements: 1. animals grazing lucerne pasture or fed with flax flakes had better performance and carcass productivity than those fed other pasture diets or roughage with grain supplements [
 <xref rid="B30-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]; 2. Biomarkers of blood oxidative stress measured as total antioxidant status were significantly higher with flaxmeal or flaxseed supplementation compared with oat grain supplemented groups [
 <xref rid="B44-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] whereas isoprostanes concentration, an oxidative stress component was significantly lower with lucerne pasture feeding compared with feedlot diets [
 <xref rid="B46-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]; 3. Sheep consuming lucerne (alfalfa) had a greater concentration of muscle vitamin E, a non-enzymatic antioxidant, than the grain-based feeding [
 <xref rid="B28-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>] whereas canola oil supplementation reduced blood oxidative stress substance of TBARS in goats [
 <xref rid="B47-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. Muscle tissues collected from sheep and goats from above-mentioned studies had higher concentrations of ALA and we believe this had some influence on animal performance and productivity through improved antioxidant potential, oxidative stress status and animal health. Taken together, these results demonstrate that diet-induced ALA resulted in altered activities and mRNA expression of antioxidant enzymes in muscle tissues, which, in turn, provided the animals with a higher antioxidant potential to alleviate oxidative stress and immune suppression, and protective mechanisms from adverse environmental conditions. However, further investigation is required to look at how different durations and concentrations of dietary interventions of feeding n-3 fatty acids affect health, welfare and productivity of lactating ewes and their lambs during hot and dry seasons, when availability and nutrient concentration of pasture (diets) is low, which can be applied to other species respectively.
</p>
