<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A library of N-polyethylene glycol(PEG)ylated quinoline derivatives of PEG molecular weight 200 was prepared rapidly after the activation of PEGs using maleic anhydrides. Quinoline with a polymer backbone is essential as new material. In 1995, Zalipskyet al.[1] and Herman et al. [2] reported the functionalization of polyethylene glycol for the preparation of biologically-relevant conjugates along with some reactive end groups. Polyethylene glycol conjugation chemistry represents an emerging trend for the generation of potential therapeutic agents. Woodle et al. [3] and Allen et al. [4] have demonstrated that PEG-modified biological molecules can benefit from extended plasma lifetimes, induced by reducing the uptake by the reticuloendothelial system and more generally, from a decrease of the undesired consequences of electrostatic and van der Waals interactions. A future direction towards nonviral gene therapy is the use of PEG-grafted synthetic vectors as long-circulating carriers for receptor-mediated gene delivery [5]. PEG has been used as a solvent medium for regioselective Heck reaction with elementary recyclability of solvents [6]. The incomparable ability of PEG to be soluble in both aqueous solution and organic solvents makes it eligible for end grouping derivatization and chemical conjugation to biological molecules under insignificant physiological conditions. The PEG-modified drug has been used widely as an antitumor drug carrier because of its excellent water solubility and biocompatibility [7]. Norfloxacin, one of the fluoroquinolone antibiotics, was conjugated to mannosylated dextrin to increase the intake of the drug by cells, enabling faster access to microorganisms, [8,9]. The backbone of polyurethanes and other ordinary low-density polyethylenes with antimicrobial Norfloxacin drugs were investigated by Yang et al. [10] against several gram-positive, and gram-negative bacteria, and displayed excellent antimicrobial activities. Recent advances in tumor therapy has demonstrated that successful anticancer strategies could be developed by employing proper carrier systems able to deliver probes, drugs, or genes to tumors targets [11]. Quinoline derivatives have been widely used for their biological [12–14], antibacterial, and antimalarial actions and in addition, for their cardiovascular, antineoplastic, and receptor agonist actions [15]. PEG, a water-soluble, nonionic polymer, which has a nontoxic character, is widely used as a carrier for drug delivery systems, and in many biochemical, cosmetic, pharmaceutical, and business applications [16]. The novel facile synthesis of a family of N-PEGylated quinoline by coupling PEG 
 <sub>200(n)</sub> with 2-formyl, 3-chloro, 6-amino quinoline via maleic anhydride as an activator was presented herein. Antimicrobial activities of the quinoline-PEG polymer and quinoline were tested against gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria. The results indicated that the new polymers had potential as potent antimicrobial agents. Since these polymers were comparatively stable at high temperatures, they can be used for medical and biomaterial applications with prior thermal sterilization. SwissADME permits the review of absorption, distribution, metabolism, and excretion (ADME) restrictions of medication aspirants and small molecules and provides statistics that authorize the early hazard calculation in drug enhancement progression. Exceptionally, SwissADME affords a point to estimate Lipinski’s rule of five [17] for medication semblance of oral bioavailability. The present facile synthetic strategy can be a practical approach for incorporating the polymeric carriers conjugated with drug moieties, either in the backbone of the polymer or as a terminal and pendant group on the polymer chains. 
</p>
