<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0125">So why do we not detect abiotic or biotic trade-offs with tolerance to either abiotic or biotic stress in Canada thistle? One possibility is that there is a trade-off with survivorship under mowing stress, but our experiment lacked the power necessary to demonstrate this. Another possibility is that we studied the wrong stresses. The EICA hypothesis predicts that introduced plant species will be released from native specialist predators, but here we simulated herbivory, which might not accurately represent the effects of specialist herbivores (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Blossey and Notzold, 1995</xref>). For example, leaf trichome/spine densities have been shown to reduce the performance of a specialized herbivore on Canada thistle (
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Cripps et al., 2015</xref>), but we did not assay variation in leaf trichome/spine densities in our experiment. Alternatively, it might be that tolerance to different stresses in Canada thistle is largely uncoupled from performance, similar to that reported for introduced populations of diffuse knapweed (
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">Turner et al., 2014</xref>). Such decoupling is often reported in cultivated germplasm (e.g., 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Fereres et al., 1986</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Ali et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2019</xref>) and is prized by plant breeders. Mechanistically, this can occur in different ways. Some stress resistance traits may be able to evolve independently of general resource use and growth potential or yield (
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Chapin et al., 1993</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Munns, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Sadras and Richards, 2014</xref>). Alternatively, decoupling can be associated with inducible resistance responses (
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Sato et al., 2016</xref>), which are less costly than constitutive resistance mechanisms. This explanation is supported by transcriptomic studies, which show that native and introduced populations of Canada thistle differ with regard to inducible R-gene defense and sensitivity in response to abiotic stresses (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Guggisberg et al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
