<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Glycerophospholipids, glycolipids and betaine lipids were identified in olives and olive oil, but the identification of the lipidome of these foodstuffs is far from being fully covered. Distinct analytical approaches have been carried out to isolate and characterize the polar lipidome from these matrices, but those relying on NMR and MS have been the most successful. The diversity of polar lipid classes, the number of molecular species, and their ability to provide a molecular fingerprint for olives and olive oil claims for further research to achieve a standardized methodology for polar lipid identification. The study of polar lipids from olives and olive oil is essential for providing new insights into their quality, identity, authenticity, and traceability. The identification of polar lipids using the most modern technologies, as mass spectrometry coupled with liquid chromatography in a lipidomic approach, represent the most promising methodology to fulfill that goal. Simultaneously, it is also an innovative research opportunity in this field, as it can bring new inputs to the identity of these food matrices and their recognition as valuable components with health benefits. Few studies reported that polar lipids from olive oil and olive pomace possess bioactive properties, but this research field is still in its infancy. Polar lipids from olive pomace and olive seeds are being envisioned as promising ingredients to be recovered from olives’ and olive oil’s industrial processing for several biotechnological uses (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="foods-07-00109-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>). Additionally, more information is needed on the polar lipidome of olive-derived industrial by-products, namely olive pomace, olive seeds, and their oils, to promote their recycling and reuse. Based on their polar lipids, novel value-added products and formulations can be conceived as important sources of components with biological activity. The wide range of biotechnological applications for these lipids recovered from olive’s and olive oils’ by-products include the feed, pharmaceutical, nutraceutical and dermocosmetic industries. Therefore, further investigation of the polar lipidome will foster the knowledge, valorization and sustainable use of these natural resources.
</p>
