<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">Advancement of civilization at a rapid pace faces the spread of complex diseases and infections that threatens the human race. Among the diseases, several pandemics have wiped a predominant human population throughout history. To note a few, flu, plague, pox, yellow fever, malaria, leprosy, tuberculosis, measles, dengue, HIV/AIDS, H1N1, SARS, Ebola, and MERS were disastrous. Among these, the present-day COVID-19 (caused by Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2; SARS-CoV-2) is potentially contagious and lethal that has forced almost all the countries to practice a strict lockdown for minimizing the spread [
 <xref rid="bb0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. The virulence of this virus, along with the evolution of different strains, has urged the scientific community to identify vaccines, therapeutic drugs, and diagnostic methods for rapid detection, treatment, and immunization of the human population. Though progress has been made in the development of biological- and chemical-based strategies to diagnose the disease, there is no drug or vaccine invented so far to treat the infected patients effectually [
 <xref rid="bb0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. The appearance of disease symptoms at a late stage and the issue of asymptomatic infections have constrained the diagnosis procedures; however, testing the entire population for the virus infection holds the key to identify the infected ones, isolate and treat them in a suitable way (WHO, 2020). In case of treatment of infected patients, the use of existing antiviral drugs is prevalent, and also, repurposing of drugs is suggested for testing and application. Currently, antiviral drugs such as Lopinavir/Ritonavir and Remdesivir are predominantly used in the treatment. These commercially synthesized molecules inhibit the virus replication either by regulating the ion channel transport or inhibiting the serine protease activity [
 <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0485" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. However, the search for novel compounds that could interfere with viral replication, assembly, and spread within the human system is in progress. Devising new molecules through computational and integrative approaches that target one or the other process of virus infection and spread could be an amenable strategy. Still, the chemical synthesis of such a molecule is time-consuming and labor-intensive. Screening of existing molecules for repurposing is already being carried out, but at the same time, studying the plants for novel phytochemicals that possess potential antiviral activity is largely ignored.
</p>
