<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">Appropriate mixing parameters are critical to ensure a homogeneous product while minimizing shear-induced product degradation throughout the manufacturing process. Characterization of mixing processes, determination of the overall level of mixing, and understanding the behavior of the protein in the mixing tank are all critical for manufacturing, especially during the compounding process. In particular, bottom-mounted mixers can impart significant shear stress on the bulk drug product during mixing operations (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>). Generally, stirred mixing tanks can be evaluated through experimental investigation of the impeller design, tank geometries, and fluid rheology; however, due to material limitations during the earlier development stages of drug product manufacturing, the at-scale experimental approach could be challenging. Instead, platform knowledge of the mixing unit operation can be leveraged, or scaled-down experiments can be performed. The pH, osmolality, and/or protein concentration can be measured through sampling from the bottom, middle, and top of the mixing tank. Additionally, protein solutions should be exposed to various interfacial and shear stresses, with subsequent analysis of specific critical and product quality attributes (for example, size variants such as formation of particulates, subvisible particles, and soluble aggregates; chemical modification of the monomer; 
 <italic class="italic">etc</italic>.) (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>). Establishment of laboratory scale down models to qualify the design space for the process parameters of these key unit operations by simulating the normal operation ranges (NOR) as well as proven acceptable ranges (PAR) for unit operations is recommended. As an alternative to scale down models, an at-scale worst-case mixing study could be performed as part of engineering runs or performance qualification runs.
</p>
