<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.13.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.13.1. 
  <span class="italic">Melissa officinalis</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Melissa officinalis</span> L., also known as lemon balm, English balm, garden balm, balm mint, common balm, melissa, sweet balm, and heart”s delight, is an aromatic herb from the mint family (Lamiaceae) that includes two subspecies: 
  <span class="italic">Melissa officinalis</span> L. subsp
  <span class="italic">. officinalis,</span> the common cultivated lemon balm, and 
  <span class="italic">Melissa officinalis</span> L. subsp. 
  <span class="italic">altissima</span>, naturalized in New Zealand and known as bush balm. The first information about the usage of the plant was found in Greece, 2000 years ago. In 2007, Khare [
  <a rid="B231" ref-type="bibr" href="#B231">231</a>] published the results that the plant has antidepressant, antispasmodic, antihistaminic, and antiviral properties and can be used in cases of anxiety, neurosis and nervous excitability, palpitation and headache, and also in hyperthyroidism.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The known major components of lemon balm are hydroxycinnamic acid derivatives, particularly rosmarinic acid, caffeic acids, chlorogenic acid, and metrilic acid [
  <a rid="B232" ref-type="bibr" href="#B232">232</a>, 
  <a rid="B233" ref-type="bibr" href="#B233">233</a>], tannins [
  <a rid="B234" ref-type="bibr" href="#B234">234</a>], flavonoids, including luteolin, luteolin 7-
  <span class="italic">O</span>-beta-D-glucopyranoside, apigenin 7-
  <span class="italic">O</span>-beta-D-glucopyranoside, and luteolin 3′-
  <span class="italic">O</span>-beta-D-glucuronopyranoside [
  <a rid="B235" ref-type="bibr" href="#B235">235</a>, 
  <a rid="B236" ref-type="bibr" href="#B236">236</a>], monoterpene glycosides [
  <a rid="B237" ref-type="bibr" href="#B237">237</a>], sesquiterpenes, including 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene and germacrene [
  <a rid="B237" ref-type="bibr" href="#B237">237</a>], triterpenes [
  <a rid="B238" ref-type="bibr" href="#B238">238</a>], and volatile oils, including citronellal, citral a (geranial), citral b (neral), methyl citronellate, ocimene, citronellol, geraniol, nerol, 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene, 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene oxide, linalool, and etheric oil [
  <a rid="B239" ref-type="bibr" href="#B239">239</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">M. officinalis</span> exhibit antiviral effects against Newcastle disease virus, Semliki forest virus, influenza virus, myxoviruses, vaccinia [
  <a rid="B240" ref-type="bibr" href="#B240">240</a>], and herpes simplex virus types 1 and 2 [
  <a rid="B241" ref-type="bibr" href="#B241">241</a>], HIV-1 [
  <a rid="B242" ref-type="bibr" href="#B242">242</a>]. The antiviral effects are mediated by tannin and polyphenol constituents, rosmarinic, caffeic, and ferulic acids [
  <a rid="B240" ref-type="bibr" href="#B240">240</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">M. officinalis</span> has antibacterial effects and can be used to treat oropharyngeal diseases produced by anaerobic and facultative aerobic periodontal bacteria like 
  <span class="italic">Porphyromonas gingivalis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Prevotella</span> spp., 
  <span class="italic">Fusobacterium nucleatum</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Capnocytophaga gingivalis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Veillonella parvula</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Eikenella corrodens</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Peptostreptococcus micros</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Actinomyces odontolyticus</span> [
  <a rid="B243" ref-type="bibr" href="#B243">243</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Englberger suggests that rosmarinic acid has anti-inflammatory effects because it reduces paw edema induced by cobra venom factor in rats and inhibit passive cutaneous anaphylaxis in rats at doses of 1–100 mg/kg by mouth. The same author says that rosmarinic acid has antithrombotic effects because it inhibits the classical pathway convertase and the alternative pathway convertase [
  <a rid="B244" ref-type="bibr" href="#B244">244</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">M. officinalis</span> has antithyroid effects (inhibit the binding of bovine TSH to human thyroid plasma membranes and adenylate cyclase, inhibit the extrathyroidal enzymatic T4-5′-deiodination to both T3-and T4-5′-deiodination) [
  <a rid="B245" ref-type="bibr" href="#B245">245</a>], spasmolytic effects (observed only in 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> studies on isolated duodenum of rat) [
  <a rid="B246" ref-type="bibr" href="#B246">246</a>], sedative effects (dose-dependent sedation, inducing sleep and potentiating subhypnotic and hypnotic doses of pentobarbital) [
  <a rid="B246" ref-type="bibr" href="#B246">246</a>], and cardiovascular effects (significant reduction in the cardiac rate by the stimulation of cardiac muscarinic receptors) [
  <a rid="B247" ref-type="bibr" href="#B247">247</a>, 
  <a rid="B248" ref-type="bibr" href="#B248">248</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
