<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.16" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.16. 
  <span class="italic">Salvia</span> Genus
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Salvia</span> genus belongs to the subfamily Nepetoideae in the Lamiaceae family. In traditional medicine, salvia is one of the oldest medicinal plants used by humans, and it is considered as a universal panacea, used for its antibacterial, antiviral, antioxidative, antimalarial, anti-inflammatory, antidiabetic, cardiovascular, and antitumor effects.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Salvia</span> can be used as infusion, tincture with diuretic, hemostatic, and spasmolytic activities, volatile oils with antiseptic role, and essential oil with antimicrobial effect.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pharmacological effects of 
  <span class="italic">Salvia</span> essential oils are based on the presence of more than 100 active compounds, which can be categorized into monoterpene hydrocarbons, oxygenated monoterpenes, sesquiterpene hydrocarbons, diterpenes, nonisoprenoid compounds and oxygenated sesquiterpenes [
  <a rid="B277" ref-type="bibr" href="#B277">277</a>, 
  <a rid="B278" ref-type="bibr" href="#B278">278</a>]. The most abundant components are 1,8-cineole, camphor, and a wide variety of thujenes [
  <a rid="B279" ref-type="bibr" href="#B279">279</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis made by spectrophotometry and HPLC shows that 
  <span class="italic">Salvia officinalis</span> L. has the highest total content (1.785 g %) expressed in gram equivalent caffeic acid, and the highest value for rosmarinic acid (728.68 mg %). Rosmarinic acid is the major component, and it has adstringent, anti-iflammatory, antibacterial, and antiviral activity [
  <a rid="B280" ref-type="bibr" href="#B280">280</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">S. officinalis</span> is the most valuable species in terms of biologically active principal contents compared to other species studied, followed by 
  <span class="italic">Salvia verticillata</span> L. and 
  <span class="italic">Salvia glutinosa</span> L. [
  <a rid="B281" ref-type="bibr" href="#B281">281</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
