<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.19.2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.19.2. 
  <span class="italic">Lavandula officinalis</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Lavandula officinalis</span> Chaix is used in traditional and herbal medicine for the treatment of pain and in the reduction of the inflammatory pain. In pharmacological and biological tests, extracts, fractions, and essential oils of 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> are reported to have analgesic effects. The literature data show that 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> extract contains linalool, acetate linalool, monotril, sesquiterpene, luteolin, ursolic acid, coumarin, and umbelliferone. Hajhashemi and Ghannadi [
  <a rid="B349" ref-type="bibr" href="#B349">349</a>] showed that the aquatic, alcoholic, and phenolic extracts have antinociception effects in the second phase of the formalin test, but only the phenolic and alcoholic extracts had been able to prevent the first phase of the formalin test. Barocelli et al. (2004) [
  <a rid="B353" ref-type="bibr" href="#B353">353</a>] proved that 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> leaves inhalation attenuates pain evoked by hot-plate test, and stomach graze induced by high-dose administration of ethanol and ascetic acid. Husseini et al. (2015) [
  <a rid="B354" ref-type="bibr" href="#B354">354</a>] demonstrated that 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> hydroalcoholic extracts inhibit inflammation and pain induced by formalin and cyclooxygenase (COX) type 1 and 2 activity in mice, using the formalin and hot-plate tests. The administration of the extract (100, 200, 250, 300, 400, and 800 mg/kg, i.p.) has inhibitory effects on inflammation induced by formalin injection into the animals hind paw, effects equal to morphine, dexamethasone, and indomethacin. The extract in 100, 200, and 300 mg/kg significantly reduced heat-induced pain and COX activity in dose-dependent manner.
 </p>
</sec>
