<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.2.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.1. 
  <span class="italic">Marrubium vulgare</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Marrubium vulgare</span> L., commonly named as “marimba” or “marroio” in Brazil and white horehound in Europe, is regularly used in traditional medicine to cure a diversity of maladies [
  <a rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63">63</a>, 
  <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">64</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phytochemical investigations on different parts of 
  <span class="italic">M. vulgare</span> have reported the presence of alkaloids, lactones, steroids, tannins, a series of phenylpropanoid esters, diterpenoids [
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>], and flavonoids [
  <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">64</a>], together with their derivatives. Marrubiin, a furano labdane diterpenoid, was found to be the major chemotaxonomic marker isolated from leaves of the plant and exhibits potent antinociceptive properties and vasorelaxant activity [
  <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">66</a>–
  <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">68</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marrubiin, the main active ingredient of 
  <span class="italic">M. vulgare</span>, seems to be generated as an artifact from premarrubiin during the extraction procedure when high temperatures are involved in extraction or concentration [
  <a rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69">69</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The leaves and stems are known to have antiseptic, antispasmodic, antidiabetic, diuretic, strongly expectorant, and tonic roles [
  <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">70</a>, 
  <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">71</a>]. The intensive modern research and clinical trials have confirmed several capabilities traditionally described to 
  <span class="italic">M. vulgare</span>, such as antimicrobial against Gram-positive bacteria, antioxidant, analgesic [
  <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">66</a>, 
  <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">67</a>], anti-inflammatory [
  <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">71</a>], and anti-oedematogenic [
  <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">72</a>]. Furthermore, extracts of this plant have shown some effects on type II diabetes [
  <a rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73">73</a>] and, recently, on neurological disorders [
  <a rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74">74</a>, 
  <a rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75">75</a>]. One study found that marrubiin has dose-related antinociceptive effects. The antinociceptive properties were observed using different routes of administration (systemic and oral), and the effect was sustained over a long period of time.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The great potencies observed in the writhing test and formalin-influenced pain test propose that marrubiin acts by some peripheral mechanism. In the hot-plate test, marrubiin did not increase the latency period of pain induced by the thermal stimuli. Reducing the lactone ring of marrubiin with the formation of marrubiinic acid and two esterified derivatives has conditioned the successful analgesic effect influencing the number of writhes in mice. Marrubiinic acid exhibited a high analgesic effect that has been long established in other experimental models of pain, suggesting the possibility to use it as a new and useful analgesic agent [
  <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">67</a>]. Marrubiin does not prove any cytotoxicity against 66 cancer cell lines according to the NIH PubMed website [Marrubiin-Compound Summary (CID 73401)]. 
  <span class="italic">In vivo</span> experimental studies have documented an LD50 of 370 mg/kg body weight [
  <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">68</a>], and recent data have highlighted a safety limit up to 100 mg/kg body weight when injected into mice [
  <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">71</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
