<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.6.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.6.1. 
  <span class="italic">Stachys lavandulifolia</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Stachys lavandulifolia</span> Vahl., a type of 
  <span class="italic">Stachys</span>, also known as mountain tea (Chay-e-Kouhi) has been distributed in a variety of climatic conditions including diverse areas of Europe, Asia, Africa, and Australia. The plant is known as Chay-e-kouhi in Persian, whereas in English it is called Betony. Also, its common names include heal-all, self-heal, woundwort, betony, lamb's ears, and hedge nettle [
  <a rid="B134" ref-type="bibr" href="#B134">134</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on recent studies on this herb, 79 compounds were identified, representing 98.2% of the essential oil, in which the major components were germacrene-D (13.2%), 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-phellandrene (12.7%), 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-pinene (10.2%), myrcene (9.4%), 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-pinene (8.4%), and Z-
  <span class="italic">β</span>-ocimene (5.8%). In another study, spathulenol (35.0%) and caryophyllene oxide (25.6%) were the main components of the oil [
  <a rid="B135" ref-type="bibr" href="#B135">135</a>]. Another study revealed the existence of 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-thujone (0.3%–32.3%), Δ-cadinene (11.6%) and 1,4-methano-1H-indene (10.1%) [
  <a rid="B136" ref-type="bibr" href="#B136">136</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aqueous extract obtained from the aerial parts of 
  <span class="italic">S. lavandulifolia</span> is used in antipyretic, anti-inflammatory, spasmolytic, sedative, and hypnotic treatment [
  <a rid="B137" ref-type="bibr" href="#B137">137</a>]. Also, this plant has antibacterial, antioxidant, anxiolytic, analgesic, and wound-healing effects. Decoctions or infusions of 
  <span class="italic">Stachys</span> are applied as tonics to treat skin or taken internally for stomach disorders [
  <a rid="B138" ref-type="bibr" href="#B138">138</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some other biological activities of 
  <span class="italic">S. lavandulifolia</span> were signaled, and the main of those being possibility of abortion depending on the dosage in animals, useful in controlling premenstrual syndrome (PMS) and primary dysmenorrhea symptoms, helps in strengthening stomach and preventing gastric ulcers caused by alcohol consumption, and useful in treating 
  <span class="italic">Leishmania major</span>. Being useful to treat fatigue, nausea, and vomiting associated with primary dysmenorrhea, it could be a potentially effective treatment for dysmenorrhea, particularly because of its antipyretic and spasmolytic effects. As an undesired effect, it gives rise to failure in fetus survival and, consequently, abortion. Its action on insomnia is approved. It is also known for its antidepressive and appetite-stimulating effects [
  <a rid="B139" ref-type="bibr" href="#B139">139</a>, 
  <a rid="B140" ref-type="bibr" href="#B140">140</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the evaluation of the analgesic effect, hydroalcoholic, polyphenolic, and boiled extracts of the aerial parts from 
  <span class="italic">S. lavandulifolia</span> were prepared, and their analgesic effects were studied in mice using formalin, acetic acid-induced writhing, and light tail flick tests. Results showed that all the tested extracts were able to reduce the abdominal constrictions in acetic acid-induced writhing test. These extracts also significantly (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001) suppressed both phases of the formalin test. In the light tail flick test, none of the extracts showed analgesic activity [
  <a rid="B141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B141">141</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In another study regarding antinociceptive effects of 
  <span class="italic">S. lavandulifolia</span> extracts, the implication of essential oil (EOSl) and (−)-
  <span class="italic">α</span>-bisabolol (BIS), its main compound, was studied in algogen-induced orofacial nociceptive behavior in mice. Authors have shown that the treatment with EOS1 and BIS has significantly reduced pain in different orofacial pain tests on mice, but BIS proved to be more effective, significantly reducing nociceptive behavior in all tests including both phases of the formalin test [
  <a rid="B142" ref-type="bibr" href="#B142">142</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
