<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.19" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.19. 
  <span class="italic">Lavandula</span> Genus
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Lavandula</span> genus includes more than 39 known species, mostly distributed in Arabia, Mediterranean Coasts, Asia, Middle East, and Northern Africa. 
  <span class="italic">Lavandula officinalis, Lavandula angustifolia</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Lavandula hybrida</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Lavandula vera</span> have been considered as antidepressive, antispasmodic, antiflatulent, antiemetic, diuretic, anticonvulsant, antibacterial, antiepileptogenic, antioxidant, antibacterial, antifungal, sedative, antinociceptive, and gastroprotective effects [
  <a rid="B344" ref-type="bibr" href="#B344">344</a>–
  <a rid="B348" ref-type="bibr" href="#B348">348</a>]. Lavender comprised over 100 constituents, among which the primary components are polyphenols, anthocyanins, carotenoids, linalool and linalyl acetate, 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-pinene, limonene, 1,8-cineole, 
  <span class="italic">cis</span>- and 
  <span class="italic">trans</span>-ocimene, 3-octanone, camphor, caryophyllene, terpinen-4-ol, and flavonoids [
  <a rid="B349" ref-type="bibr" href="#B349">349</a>, 
  <a rid="B350" ref-type="bibr" href="#B350">350</a>].
 </p>
 <sec id="sec3.19.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.19.1. 
   <span class="italic">Lavandula angustifolia</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Lavandula angustifolia</span> Mill. is one of the most famous aromatic and medicinal plants [
   <a rid="B351" ref-type="bibr" href="#B351">351</a>] used in fresh state or dry condition, containing 1–6% volatile oils (monoterpenic compounds, alcohols, and esters), triterpenic acids, coumarins, flavones, resins, and polyphenols [
   <a rid="B352" ref-type="bibr" href="#B352">352</a>]. As medicinal activity, 
   <span class="italic">L. angustifolia</span> extracts or essential oils possess antispastic, carminative, analgesic, sedative, hypotensive, antiseptic, antimicrobial, antifungic, diuretic, and general tonic action, but little information on lavender analgesic properties is available in the literature.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.19.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.19.2. 
   <span class="italic">Lavandula officinalis</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Lavandula officinalis</span> Chaix is used in traditional and herbal medicine for the treatment of pain and in the reduction of the inflammatory pain. In pharmacological and biological tests, extracts, fractions, and essential oils of 
   <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> are reported to have analgesic effects. The literature data show that 
   <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> extract contains linalool, acetate linalool, monotril, sesquiterpene, luteolin, ursolic acid, coumarin, and umbelliferone. Hajhashemi and Ghannadi [
   <a rid="B349" ref-type="bibr" href="#B349">349</a>] showed that the aquatic, alcoholic, and phenolic extracts have antinociception effects in the second phase of the formalin test, but only the phenolic and alcoholic extracts had been able to prevent the first phase of the formalin test. Barocelli et al. (2004) [
   <a rid="B353" ref-type="bibr" href="#B353">353</a>] proved that 
   <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> leaves inhalation attenuates pain evoked by hot-plate test, and stomach graze induced by high-dose administration of ethanol and ascetic acid. Husseini et al. (2015) [
   <a rid="B354" ref-type="bibr" href="#B354">354</a>] demonstrated that 
   <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> hydroalcoholic extracts inhibit inflammation and pain induced by formalin and cyclooxygenase (COX) type 1 and 2 activity in mice, using the formalin and hot-plate tests. The administration of the extract (100, 200, 250, 300, 400, and 800 mg/kg, i.p.) has inhibitory effects on inflammation induced by formalin injection into the animals hind paw, effects equal to morphine, dexamethasone, and indomethacin. The extract in 100, 200, and 300 mg/kg significantly reduced heat-induced pain and COX activity in dose-dependent manner.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.19.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.19.3. 
   <span class="italic">Lavandula hybrida</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2004, Barocelli et al. [
   <a rid="B353" ref-type="bibr" href="#B353">353</a>] demonstrated the antinociceptive and the gastroprotective effects of orally administered (100 mg/kg) or inhaled 
   <span class="italic">Lavandula hybrida</span> Reverchon “Grosso” essential oil, and its principal constituents linalool and linalyl acetate in rodents. In the hot-plate test, the analgesic activity was observed after oil inhalation was inhibited by naloxone, atropine, and mecamylamine pretreatment, suggesting the involvement of opioidergic as well as cholinergic pathways. Therefore, the lavender oil reveals an interesting analgesic activity mainly relevant after inhalation, at doses devoid of sedative side effect, suggesting the interest for potential application of this oil in aromatherapy.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
