<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. 
  <span class="italic">Sideritis</span> Genus
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Sideritis</span> genus counts more than 150 species of plants that are situated primarily in the Mediterranean area and also in Atlantic regions, North Africa, and even Norway, with apparent differences in composition between the same species corresponding to the geographical place of provenience [
  <a rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" href="#B76">76</a>]. The species have been used as flavoring agents, widely as ingredients for tea preparation or with medicinal purposes [
  <a rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" href="#B77">77</a>] in some areas being listed as an endangered plant. Although the use in traditional medicine has been extensive in the abovementioned places, 
  <span class="italic">Sideritis</span> species have reduced usage in western medicine [
  <a rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78">78</a>], because medical literature are offering data mostly on the 
  <span class="italic">scardica</span>, 
  <span class="italic">lotsy</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">stricta</span> species.
 </p>
 <sec id="sec3.3.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.1. 
   <span class="italic">Sideritis scardica</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">S. scardica</span> Gris. is also known as “Greek tea” or “mountain tea.” The components of 
   <span class="italic">scardica</span> have been studied through various methods for their presence as well as medical role in both animal and human studies.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By using chromatographic separations (HPLC) and mass spectrometry, one study found six different flavonoid aglycones: luteolin, apigenin, hypolaetin, 4′-
   <span class="italic">O</span>-methylhypolaetin, isoscutellarein, and 4ʹ-
   <span class="italic">O</span>-methylisoscutellarein [
   <a rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" href="#B79">79</a>], and also other components like sterols, coumarins, flavonoids, essential oil, iridoids, terpenoids, and glycosides [
   <a rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" href="#B76">76</a>]. The presence of phenolic antioxidants (catechins) correlating to the antioxidant activity of Greek mountain tea was also established [
   <a rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" href="#B80">80</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography with mass spectrometry (GC-MS) analysis demonstrated that the composition of 
   <span class="italic">S. scardica</span> oil samples, however, varies from region to region. In the oil from Macedonia, for example, 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-cadinol is predominant as compared to the Bulgarian version of the same plant oil which contains mostly diterpenic compounds and octadecenol. Interestingly, none contained menthol, nerol, or geraniol, which are the major components in the 
   <span class="italic">S. scardica</span> oil from Yugoslavia [
   <a rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" href="#B81">81</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For an overview of the 
   <span class="italic">Sideritis</span> species in the Balkan area, mountain tea was analyzed by mass spectrometry coupled to high-performance liquid chromatography with diode-array detection. The analysis found that it contains 90% phenylethanoid glycosides and flavonoid acetylglycosides [
   <a rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" href="#B82">82</a>]. Turkish 
   <span class="italic">S. scardica</span> oil has 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-pinene in abundance as compared to the Greek version which contains 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-pinene primarily. Both these varieties are mainly rich in monoterpene hydrocarbons unlike the ones from Macedonia and Bulgaria, which are poor in these compounds [
   <a rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" href="#B83">83</a>]. Significant differences in components have also been proven between the fresh and dried versions of the plant material [
   <a rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" href="#B84">84</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An analysis of urine samples from humans who received oral administration of 
   <span class="italic">S. scardica</span> showed that the flavonoid metabolites were dominant in urine samples and that hypolaetin and isoscutellarein had the largest number of metabolites (methylhypolaetin and methylisoscutellarein glucuronides) together with apigenin [
   <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">85</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pharmacological activity of 
   <span class="italic">S. scardica</span> is attributed to the high content of flavonoid and phenolic compounds. Studies have demonstrated that plants from the 
   <span class="italic">Sideritis</span> genus have antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, diuretic, antibacterial, analgesic, and antifungal effects [
   <a rid="B86" ref-type="bibr" href="#B86">86</a>]. In experimental ex vivo models, 
   <span class="italic">S. scardica</span> showed a capacity to inhibit human serotonin transporter (hSERT) greater than in rat models [
   <a rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" href="#B77">77</a>]. Accordingly, the 
   <span class="italic">in vivo</span> test in rats showed that 
   <span class="italic">S. scardica</span> extract administered orally has been associated with psychostimulant and antidepressive effects, being classified as perhaps a substitute for adaptogens and thus useful for other pathologies correlated with depressive or altered mental status like sleep apnea or increased cardiovascular risks [
   <a rid="B87" ref-type="bibr" href="#B87">87</a>–
   <a rid="B89" ref-type="bibr" href="#B89">89</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antibacterial activity seems to be influenced by the method of obtaining the extract: carbon dioxide extraction being superior to hydrodistillation and is attributed partially to diterpenes and fatty acids and their derivates and also to other momentarily unknown elements that might be involved [
   <a rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" href="#B90">90</a>] but with a certain degree of effect on different types of pathogens.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antioxidant activity was widely demonstrated, probably due to the content of catechins but not limited to this and has multiple health benefits and implications in pain treatment proving a possible valuable agent in limiting the use of analgesics, anti-inflammatory, and antipyretic forms of self-medication [
   <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>, 
   <a rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" href="#B91">91</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">In vivo</span> models demonstrated the anti-inflammatory effects of 
   <span class="italic">S. scardica</span> over a model of carrageenan-induced rat paw edema and proved gastroprotective activity over ethanol-induced acute stress ulcer in rats and also a promising cytotoxic activity [
   <a rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" href="#B92">92</a>], attributing in part to flavonoid constituents (apigenin and luteolin) that can induce cell-cycle arrest and cellular apoptosis 
   <span class="italic">in vitro</span> [
   <a rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" href="#B93">93</a>]. 
   <span class="italic">In vivo</span> models demonstrated a preventive capacity of 
   <span class="italic">S. scardica</span> over A
   <span class="italic">β</span>-induced memory impairments in transgenic and nontransgenic mice and proved a possible positive effect in Alzheimer's disease, fully rescuing neuronal loss in transgenic mice, thus being flagged as a possible treatment forimproving memory in healthy adults and in dementia patients [
   <a rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78">78</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The usage of 
   <span class="italic">S. scardica</span> in traditional and modern medicine has demonstrated various degrees of effectiveness with promising beneficial health results in a long series of pathologies from prevention of anemia, anxiety disorders, major depression, cardiovascular disease, attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder, mental impairment, or neurodegenerative diseases [
   <a rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" href="#B77">77</a>] to rheumatic problems [
   <a rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" href="#B94">94</a>], inflammatory pain, gastric ulcer [
   <a rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" href="#B93">93</a>], pulmonary pathologies (common cold, lung emphysema, bronchitis, and asthma) [
   <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">85</a>], and also an effective cytotoxic activity [
   <a rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" href="#B92">92</a>, 
   <a rid="B95" ref-type="bibr" href="#B95">95</a>]. The anti-inflammatory and edema-reducing capabilities should be considered as the basis for further studies of 
   <span class="italic">S. scardica</span> implication in pain modulation.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.3.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.2. 
   <span class="italic">Sideritis lotsyi</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Sideritis lotsyi</span> Pit. contains tetracyclic diterpenes (ent-kaur-16-ene and epicandicandiol 7
   <span class="italic">β</span>-monoacetate-18-palmitate), rhoiptelenol, hydrocarbon ent-trachylobane, amyrin, trachinodiol, a rare diterpene 16
   <span class="italic">β</span>,18-dihydroxy-ent-atisane, and 5-hydroxy-3,7,4′-trimethoxyflavone, but the content is different between 
   <span class="italic">S. lotsyi</span> and 
   <span class="italic">S. lotsyi</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">mascaensis</span> [
   <a rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" href="#B96">96</a>]. 
   <span class="italic">S. lotsyi</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">mascaensis</span> extracts were studied in a comprehensive analysis for the antimicrobial activity, toxicity, and anti-inflammatory and analgesic proprieties.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A dose of 2 g/kg body weight 
   <span class="italic">S. lotsyi</span> extracts administered orally in mice did not show any toxic effects; however, a dose of only 250 mg/kg ethanol extract administered orally has shown analgesic proprieties on the visceral pain produced during the writhing test, and the chloroform fraction demonstrated antinociceptive effect. The same extracts manifested anti-inflammatory effect on the early, histamin-mediated, phase of paw inflammation, but much more significant effects were observed in ear inflammation with topical administration. Contrary to 
   <span class="italic">S. scardica</span>, no antimicrobial effect was noted [
   <a rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" href="#B97">97</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.3.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.3. 
   <span class="italic">Sideritis stricta</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Sideritis stricta</span> Benth. is listed as an endangered plant and is being used as an aromatic and medicinal plant containing essential oils with antimicrobial, cytotoxic, antiviral, and antioxidant properties [
   <a rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" href="#B98">98</a>]. The diterpenes composition was identified as sideroxol, 7-acetyl sideroxol, 7-epicandicandiol, linearol (5), ent-7
   <span class="italic">α</span>,15
   <span class="italic">β</span>,18-trihydroxy-kaur-16-ene, ent-7
   <span class="italic">α</span>-acetyl,15,18-dihydroxy-kaur-16-ene, foliol, sideridiol, siderol, and the recently identified ent-1
   <span class="italic">β</span>-hydroxy-7
   <span class="italic">α</span>-acetyl-15
   <span class="italic">β</span>,16
   <span class="italic">β</span>-epoxykaurane [
   <a rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" href="#B99">99</a>] together with two flavonoid glycosides and a phenolic fraction by means of spectroscopic evidence [
   <a rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" href="#B100">100</a>]. Although phenolic compounds did not manifest anti-inflammatory proprieties, the flavonoid glycosides show both anti-inflammatory and antinociceptive capabilities when combined [
   <a rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" href="#B100">100</a>]. Similarly to 
   <span class="italic">S. lotsyi</span>, the acetone extract of 
   <span class="italic">S. stricta</span> showed lower antimicrobial activity as compared to gentamicin [
   <a rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" href="#B99">99</a>], and no extensive data with the implications of 
   <span class="italic">S. stricta</span> over pain are published.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
