<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. 
  <span class="italic">Thymus</span> Genus
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Thymus</span> genus, part of the Lamiaceae family, consists of over 350 species of aromatic plants with evergreen leaves. Geographically, these plants extend to Asia, North Africa, and Europe. Although more than one species is cultivated for culinary (cheese and liqueur flavor agent) or ornamental use, the most extensively studied in literature is 
  <span class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</span>. Used for thousands of years in traditional medicine, the effects of 
  <span class="italic">Thymus</span> species in medicine is wide, from antimicrobial and anti-inflammatory to possible treatment for dementia or oncological pathologies through apigenin [
  <a rid="B101" ref-type="bibr" href="#B101">101</a>].
 </p>
 <sec id="sec3.4.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4.1. 
   <span class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC-MS and GC-FID analyses revealed that the main active components in one type of 
   <span class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</span> L. essential oil are thymol (41.0%), geraniol (26.4%), thujanol (42.2% 
   <span class="italic">cis</span>-sabinene hydrate and 7.3% 
   <span class="italic">trans</span>-sabinene hydrate), and linalool (72.5%) [
   <a rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" href="#B102">102</a>], and others also contain borneol and carvacrol. The chemotypes of thyme are determined based on oil compositions. Geographical provenience and weather influence the chemotype and composition [
   <a rid="B103" ref-type="bibr" href="#B103">103</a>], which was demonstrated by a study comparing essential oils from two regions of France (linalool chemotype with 76.2% linalool and thymol chemotype with 47.1% thymol) and two regions of Serbia (geraniol chemotype with 59.8% geraniol and sabinene hydrate chemotype with 30.8% 
   <span class="italic">cis</span>-sabinene hydrate) [
   <a rid="B104" ref-type="bibr" href="#B104">104</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The terpenoids associated with 
   <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> anesthethic capabilities are thymol (2-isopropyl-5-methylphenol) and eugenol (4-allyl-2-methoxyphenol) [
   <a rid="B105" ref-type="bibr" href="#B105">105</a>]; moreover, thymol inhibits synthetisation of vitamin K and is implicated in the inhibition of platelet aggregation [
   <a rid="B106" ref-type="bibr" href="#B106">106</a>], resulting in potential anticoagulant activity [
   <a rid="B107" ref-type="bibr" href="#B107">107</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In animals, hydroalcoholic extracts of propolis 
   <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> showed promising results in the treatment of dermal leishmaniasis or 
   <span class="italic">Tetranychus urticae</span> [
   <a rid="B108" ref-type="bibr" href="#B108">108</a>, 
   <a rid="B109" ref-type="bibr" href="#B109">109</a>]. 
   <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> also has a spasmolytic, antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory, immunomodulatory, and antioxidant capabilities, these effects being attributed to the thymol contained in the volatile thyme oil [
   <a rid="B110" ref-type="bibr" href="#B110">110</a>]. Confirming the effect of 
   <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> on respiratory pathologies and the spasmolytic effects underlined in 
   <span class="italic">ex vivo</span> studies [
   <a rid="B111" ref-type="bibr" href="#B111">111</a>], a study also has indicated its promising potential for the treatment of gastrointestinal pathologies in animal models without any toxic potential.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By inhibiting, 
   <span class="italic">in vivo</span>, TNF-
   <span class="italic">α</span>, lipopolysaccharide inflammatory induced cell influx, IL-6, protein concentration in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid, and NF-κB activation in the lung, thymol could be a promising therapeutical agent for acute lung injury [
   <a rid="B112" ref-type="bibr" href="#B112">112</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inhibitory role over the nitric oxide (NO) by limiting iNOS mRNA expression plays a major role in the anti-inflammatory proprieties of 
   <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> extracts [
   <a rid="B113" ref-type="bibr" href="#B113">113</a>]. Also, because of the antioxidant capabilities and being an inhibitor of acetylcholinesterase, 
   <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> could be a promising therapeutic agent for neurodegenerative disorders like dementia or Alzheimer's disease [
   <a rid="B114" ref-type="bibr" href="#B114">114</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">In vitro</span> activity of 
   <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> oil confirmed a high antibacterial activity over Gram-positive and also Gram-negative bacteria, though the effect was smaller on the latter [
   <a rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" href="#B102">102</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In traditional medicine and in clinical practice, 
   <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> is used, and 
   <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> shows promising results on inflammatory skin disorders [
   <a rid="B115" ref-type="bibr" href="#B115">115</a>], scabies, herpes, wounds, alopecia, dental plaque [
   <a rid="B116" ref-type="bibr" href="#B116">116</a>], ringworm, and headaches [
   <a rid="B106" ref-type="bibr" href="#B106">106</a>]. Moreover, 
   <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> showed a promising insecticidal effect on 
   <span class="italic">Culex pipiens</span>, the vector for lymphatic filariasis [
   <a rid="B117" ref-type="bibr" href="#B117">117</a>], demonstrating an increased importance in many fields.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Probably in part due to the anti-inflammatory and antioxidant capabilities, 
   <span class="italic">Thymus</span> extracts demonstrated analgesic, anti-inflammatory, and antipyretic activity in mouse models of pain. Therefore, the authors concluded that the extracts of 
   <span class="italic">Thymus</span> may be used against pain, pyrexia, and inflammation [
   <a rid="B118" ref-type="bibr" href="#B118">118</a>], correlating with other similar findings that position 
   <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> as a modulator agent over acute and chronic pain [
   <a rid="B119" ref-type="bibr" href="#B119">119</a>]. In clinical practice, comparative effects of 
   <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> and ibuprofen on pain severity associated with primary dysmenorrhea were found [
   <a rid="B120" ref-type="bibr" href="#B120">120</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.4.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4.2. 
   <span class="italic">Thymus pulegioides</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Thymus pulegioides</span> L. belongs to the genus 
   <span class="italic">Thymus</span>, and together with three other species, it has a different phenolic content than 
   <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> [
   <a rid="B121" ref-type="bibr" href="#B121">121</a>]. It grows on the European continent, and it is used as an antiseptic in local regions of Portugal [
   <a rid="B122" ref-type="bibr" href="#B122">122</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In phytochemical analysis, 
   <span class="italic">Thymus pulegioides</span> was found to have a high flavonoid content, tannins, and hydroxycinnamic acids. The 
   <span class="italic">T. pulegioides</span> oil, in one analysiss, was characterized by the presence of high amounts of thymol and carvacrol [
   <a rid="B122" ref-type="bibr" href="#B122">122</a>]. The dose-dependent scavenging effect and the chelating activity of 
   <span class="italic">T. pulegioides</span> are moderate to high, with an increased acetylcholinesterase inhibition [
   <a rid="B114" ref-type="bibr" href="#B114">114</a>]. A study in Italy places 
   <span class="italic">T. pulegioides</span> among the first medicinal plants in traditional medicine and the second most relevant in respiratory pathologies usage [
   <a rid="B123" ref-type="bibr" href="#B123">123</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has an important antioxidant role [
   <a rid="B124" ref-type="bibr" href="#B124">124</a>], but as an anti-inflammatory agent, it elicits cell-type-dependent response [
   <a rid="B125" ref-type="bibr" href="#B125">125</a>]. Another consideration that increases the medicinal importance of 
   <span class="italic">T. pulegioides</span> is that it has demonstrated considerable antifungal capacities [
   <a rid="B122" ref-type="bibr" href="#B122">122</a>]; however, more data are required to quantify its effect in pain modulation.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
