<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Physical Properties of Seed Oil</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Physicochemical properties of
  <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil are listed in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>. The oil was liquid at 19.67°C. The refractive index of oils depends on their molecular weight, fatty acid chain length, degree of unsaturation, and degree of conjugation. The refractive index of
  <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil was 1.47, which was similar to the values of
  <span class="italic"> Acacia senegal</span> (L.) Willd. (1.47) and
  <span class="italic"> Lannea microcarpa</span> (1.47) and higher than
  <span class="italic"> Phoenix canariensis</span> Hort. ex Chabaud (1.45) seed oils [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>, 
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">21</a>, 
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">22</a>]. The refractive index is positively related to iodine value, which is a measure of the degree of unsaturation of the oils and gives an idea of their oxidative stability.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The iodine value of 60.72 g of I
  <sub>2</sub>/100 g of oil was in the range of that of
  <span class="italic"> Moringa oleifera</span> Lam. oil (65.90 g of I
  <sub>2</sub>/100 g) and lower than those of olive, cotton, groundnut, and sunflower oils, which ranged from 86 to 145 g of I
  <sub>2</sub>/100 g of oil [
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">21</a>]. The relatively low iodine value implies low nutritional value, but high oxidative stability. The oxidative susceptibility of
  <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil was assessed by the determination of peroxide,
  <span class="italic"> p</span>-anisidine values, and the oxidative stability index.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The peroxide value of the
  <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil was 0.99 meq. O
  <sub>2</sub>/kg of oil, which is less than 10 meq. O
  <sub>2</sub>/kg of oil, allowed for crude oils by Codex Alimentarius Committee [
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">22</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The
  <span class="italic"> p</span>-anisidine value of the oil was 0.08 and lower than that of 0.30 reported for
  <span class="italic"> Salvia hispanica</span> L. seed oil [
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">23</a>]. The total oxidation (TOTOX) value of 2.06 was lower than those of vegetable oils reported in the literature and indicates high primary and secondary oxidative stability [
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">24</a>]. The oxidative stability of
  <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil was 52.53 h at 120°C. This value was higher than those of palm kernel oil (26.80 h) and refined-bleached-deodorized palm olein (25.50 h) measured at 110°C [
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">25</a>]. The low level of polyunsaturated fatty acids provides the oil with high oxidative stability [
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">26</a>]. The double bounds in polyunsaturated are more reactive than a double bound in a monounsaturated chain [
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">27</a>]. Consequently, the high level of monounsaturated fatty acids and the high proportion of saturated fatty acids in
  <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil are factors that positively contribute to the oil oxidative stability.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The concentration of free fatty acids and the acid value of the
  <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil were 0.39% and 0.64 mg of KOH/g of oil, respectively. These low values were a result of lower hydrolysis of triglycerides and signified that the oil could have a long shelf life, which allows it to be consumed as virgin edible oil.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">L. kerstingii</span> seed oil had a saponification value of 189.73. This value is due to high content of medium chain fatty acids (i.e., C16 and C18).
 </p>
</sec>
