<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Proximate Composition of Seeds</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of proximate analysis of
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seeds are shown in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab1" href="#tab1">Table 1</a>. The moisture content of seeds was 3.61%, which is low and therefore beneficial for prolonging the shelf life of the seeds. The seeds contained significant amounts of crude oil (57.85 g/100 g), crude protein (26.39 g/100 g), and ash (2.08 g/100 g). The ash and crude protein were in the range of those reported for
   <span class="italic"> Arachis hypogaea</span> L. and
   <span class="italic"> Pentaclethra macrophylla</span> Benth. [
   <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>]. The crude oil content was higher than those of some commercial seed oils, namely, soybean, cotton seeds, and rubber seeds [
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>].
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seeds also contained significant amounts of minerals. The most abundant was potassium followed by magnesium, calcium, zinc, iron, and sodium. These results showed that
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seeds can be regarded as a good source of oil, protein and minerals.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Amino Acid Composition of Seed Flour</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a> depicts the amino acid composition of
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed flour. The results indicated that the essential amino acids formed 36.48% of the total amino acid content and most were at higher levels than in the requirements recommended by FAO/WHO/UNU [
   <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>], with the exception for lysine which appeared as a limiting amino acid. Tryptophan had the highest amino acid score, followed by phenylalanine + tyrosine, histidine, isoleucine, methionine + cysteine, valine, threonine, leucine, and lysine.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nonessential amino acids represented 53.39% of total amino acid content. The highest levels were recorded for glutamine, followed by arginine, asparagine, glycine, serine, alanine, proline, hydroxylysine, and hydroxyproline. The total amino acid composition of
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed flour is far greater than the one of soybean [
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>].
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed flour is rich in both essential and nonessential amino acids. It constitutes a potential source of protein for human food and livestock fodder.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Fatty Acid Composition of Seed Oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fatty acid profile of
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil is shown in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>. The oil mainly contained saturated fatty acids (42.14%) and monounsaturated fatty acids (41.09%) and a low amount of polyunsaturated fatty acids (13.05%).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most abundant fatty acids of
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil were oleic (38.45%) and palmitic (33.20%) acids followed by linoleic (12.75%) and stearic (7.43%) acids, which together comprised 91.83% of the total fatty acid. The fatty acid composition of
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil was comparable to that of palm oil and like that one, the
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil can be regarded as an oleic-palmitic oil [
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>]. Therefore,
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil can be considered as an alternative to palm oil in food industries.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Physical Properties of Seed Oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Physicochemical properties of
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil are listed in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>. The oil was liquid at 19.67°C. The refractive index of oils depends on their molecular weight, fatty acid chain length, degree of unsaturation, and degree of conjugation. The refractive index of
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil was 1.47, which was similar to the values of
   <span class="italic"> Acacia senegal</span> (L.) Willd. (1.47) and
   <span class="italic"> Lannea microcarpa</span> (1.47) and higher than
   <span class="italic"> Phoenix canariensis</span> Hort. ex Chabaud (1.45) seed oils [
   <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>, 
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">21</a>, 
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">22</a>]. The refractive index is positively related to iodine value, which is a measure of the degree of unsaturation of the oils and gives an idea of their oxidative stability.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The iodine value of 60.72 g of I
   <sub>2</sub>/100 g of oil was in the range of that of
   <span class="italic"> Moringa oleifera</span> Lam. oil (65.90 g of I
   <sub>2</sub>/100 g) and lower than those of olive, cotton, groundnut, and sunflower oils, which ranged from 86 to 145 g of I
   <sub>2</sub>/100 g of oil [
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">21</a>]. The relatively low iodine value implies low nutritional value, but high oxidative stability. The oxidative susceptibility of
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil was assessed by the determination of peroxide,
   <span class="italic"> p</span>-anisidine values, and the oxidative stability index.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The peroxide value of the
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil was 0.99 meq. O
   <sub>2</sub>/kg of oil, which is less than 10 meq. O
   <sub>2</sub>/kg of oil, allowed for crude oils by Codex Alimentarius Committee [
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">22</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The
   <span class="italic"> p</span>-anisidine value of the oil was 0.08 and lower than that of 0.30 reported for
   <span class="italic"> Salvia hispanica</span> L. seed oil [
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">23</a>]. The total oxidation (TOTOX) value of 2.06 was lower than those of vegetable oils reported in the literature and indicates high primary and secondary oxidative stability [
   <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">24</a>]. The oxidative stability of
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil was 52.53 h at 120°C. This value was higher than those of palm kernel oil (26.80 h) and refined-bleached-deodorized palm olein (25.50 h) measured at 110°C [
   <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">25</a>]. The low level of polyunsaturated fatty acids provides the oil with high oxidative stability [
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">26</a>]. The double bounds in polyunsaturated are more reactive than a double bound in a monounsaturated chain [
   <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">27</a>]. Consequently, the high level of monounsaturated fatty acids and the high proportion of saturated fatty acids in
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil are factors that positively contribute to the oil oxidative stability.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The concentration of free fatty acids and the acid value of the
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil were 0.39% and 0.64 mg of KOH/g of oil, respectively. These low values were a result of lower hydrolysis of triglycerides and signified that the oil could have a long shelf life, which allows it to be consumed as virgin edible oil.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">L. kerstingii</span> seed oil had a saponification value of 189.73. This value is due to high content of medium chain fatty acids (i.e., C16 and C18).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. Vitamins and Sterols</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vitamin E includes four isomers (
   <span class="italic">α</span>, 
   <span class="italic">β</span>, 
   <span class="italic">δ</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">γ</span>) of tocopherol and four isomers (
   <span class="italic">α</span>, 
   <span class="italic">β</span>, 
   <span class="italic">δ</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">γ</span>) of tocotrienol. The contents of total and individual tocopherols and tocotrienols of
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil are presented in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab5" href="#tab5">Table 5</a>. The results revealed the presence of the three tocopherols (
   <span class="italic">α</span>, 
   <span class="italic">δ</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">γ</span>). Β-Tocopherol and tocotrienols were not detected in the oil. Total amount of tocopherols was 578.60 mg/kg, which was similar to that reported for
   <span class="italic"> L. microcarpa</span> and higher than that recorded in grapeseed oil (140.60 mg/kg), peanut oil (398.60 mg/kg), and olive oil (216.80 mg/kg) [
   <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">28</a>]. 
   <span class="italic">γ</span>-Tocopherol was the most abundant, with a value of 82% of the total tocopherol content, followed by 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-tocopherol (12%) and 
   <span class="italic">δ</span>-tocopherol (6%). The antioxidant activity of tocopherols decreased in the order of 
   <span class="italic">γ</span> &gt; 
   <span class="italic">δ</span> &gt; 
   <span class="italic">α</span> &gt; 
   <span class="italic">β</span> [
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">29</a>]. The significant quantity of 
   <span class="italic">γ</span>-tocopherols found in
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil could contribute to its high oxidative stability.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carotenoids together with tocopherols are involved in the oxidative stability of the oil and have a protective role against cancer and cardiovascular diseases [
   <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">30</a>]. More than 700 carotenoids have been identified in 89 plant foods and in the human body, but the overwhelming majority (ca. 90%) in the human diet is represented by 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-carotene, 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-carotene, lycopene, lutein, cryptoxanthin, and zeaxanthin [
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">31</a>]. The carotenoid content of
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil was 4.62 mg/kg of oil (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab5" href="#tab5">Table 5</a>). This value was similar to that reported for
   <span class="italic"> Capparis spinosa</span> L. (4.57 mg/kg of oil) and lower than those of
   <span class="italic"> Phoenix canariensis</span> seed oil (55.10 mg/kg of oil) and
   <span class="italic"> Rubus idaeus</span> L. seed oil (230.00 mg/kg of oil) [
   <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>, 
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">29</a>]. The forms of carotenoids found in
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil were lutein and 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-carotene. Lutein was the most abundant form, accounting for 80% of the total carotenoids.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sterols constitute the major fraction of the unsaponifiable matter in many oils. More than 40 phytosterols were identified; from them 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-sitosterol, campesterol, and stigmasterol account for more than 95% of total phytosterols dietary intake [
   <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">32</a>]. They are of interest due to their antioxidant activity and beneficial impact on human health [
   <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">33</a>]. The sterol content of
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil is illustrated in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab5" href="#tab5">Table 5</a>. The total sterol content was 929.50 mg/kg of oil. 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-Sitosterol was the major form (93%), followed by campesterol (7%). The presence of high 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-sitosterol was found to limit TG polymer formation in triolein, refined canola, high oleic sunflower, and flaxseed oils heated at frying temperature [
   <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">34</a>]. This suggests that
   <span class="italic"> L. kerstingii</span> seed oil could be used as frying oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
