<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rutin and nicotiflorin, as well as other glycoside flavonoids, are present in a large number of therapeutic medicinal plants and are often consumed in the form of herbal teas.
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> These compounds are vital in diets and are of great interest due their antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and antiviral activities and their human metabolites, which include quercetin from rutin hydrolysis.
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> For this reason, their absorption, metabolism, toxicity, and pharmacokinetics has been intensively investigated.
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref> Regarding these studies, rutinoside flavonoids, such as rutin and nicotiflorin, are deglycosylated prior to being absorbed into the circulation and then conjugated mainly with glucuronate and sulfate, these being the main forms in plasma.
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> Based on this information, it is reasonable to suggest that both quercetin and kaempferol sulfates and glucuronides, demonstrated above as promising SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro and RdRp inhibitors, could have a key role against these proteins, since the virus is also dominant in plasma. This hypothesis is in accordance with previous 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> antiviral studies performed with rutin. These studies indicate that rutin protects cells for about 24 h against vesicular stomatitis virus, affords immense viral embarrassment in canine distemper virus, and demonstrates a profound antiviral effect against avian influenza strain H5N1.
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> Flavonoid glucuronides have also been described as antiviral agents, including quercetin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucuronide, here described as a potential 3CLpro inhibitor.
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>25</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>26</sup>
 </xref> Moreover, previous works have pointed out the effective anti-HIV and anti-HSV activities of flavonoid sulfates.
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>27</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
