<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Centella asiatica</italic> (family Apiaceae), commonly known as Indian Pennywort, is an ethnomedical plant that is widely used in India for treating skin problems and for revitalizing the brain and nervous system [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It has been reported to have various pharmacological activities, including antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, anticancer, neuroprotective, cardioprotective, skin protective, radioprotective, immunomodulatory, memory-enhancing, and wound-healing properties [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Studies on the chemical constituents of 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> showed the presence of pentacyclic triterpenoids known as centelloids. These compounds are composed of terpene acids along with glycosides, including asiatic acid, asiaticoside, madecassic acid, madecassoside, brahmic acid, brahmoside, brahminoside, thankiniside, isothankunisode, madasiatic acid, centic acid, centelloside, and cenellic acid [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Asiatic acid and its derivatives possess a broad spectrum of pharmacological activities, such as anticancer [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], wound healing [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], anti-inflammatory [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], antidiabetic [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], hepatoprotective [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], and neuroprotective activities [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In addition, 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> contains flavonoids, phenolic acids, and volatile oils, which exhibit antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
</p>
