<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>In the present work, a new series of dihydronaphthalene derivatives were synthesized starting with 6-methoxy-1-tetralone 
  <bold>1</bold>, and the corresponding hydrazine derivative 
  <bold>2</bold>. Reaction of compound 
  <bold>2</bold> with aryl isothiocyanates produced thiosemicarbazides 
  <bold>3a-d</bold>, which were reacted with ethyl chloroacetate to give thiazolidinone derivatives 
  <bold>4a-d</bold>. Pyrano thiazolecarbonitrile derivatives 
  <bold>5a</bold>-
  <bold>f</bold> were prepared by heating a mixture of compounds 
  <bold>4a</bold> or 
  <bold>4c</bold>, aryl aldehydes, and malononitrile utilizing distilled water in the presence of catalytic amount of potassium hydrogen phthalate. Also, treatment of 
  <bold>4a</bold> with DMF-DMA under solvent-free conditions gave enaminone derivative 
  <bold>6</bold>, which condensed with ethyl acetoacetate or acetylacetone or malononitrile or cyanothioacetamide to give compounds 
  <bold>7</bold>-
  <bold>10</bold>, respectively. Finally, reaction of the enaminone 
  <bold>6</bold> with 2-aminoimidazol or 2-aminothiazol in the presence of glacial acetic acid produced derivatives 
  <bold>11</bold> and 
  <bold>12</bold>, respectively. Cytotoxic evaluation of eleven compounds, against MCF-7 (human breast adenocarcinoma) cell lines, was estimated. Results revealed that five of the examined compounds 
  <bold>5a</bold>, 
  <bold>5d</bold>, 
  <bold>5e</bold>, 
  <bold>10</bold>, and 
  <bold>3d</bold> showed potent cytotoxic activities recording, IC
  <sub>50</sub> values; 0.93 ± 0.02, 1.76 ± 0.04, 2.36 ± 0.06, 2.83 ± 0.07, and 3.73 ± 0.09 
  <italic>μ</italic>M, respectively, which were more potent than the reference used (Saturosporin, IC
  <sub>50</sub>6.08 ± 0.15 
  <italic>μ</italic>M). The new products were also examined towards normal epithelial breast cells (MCF10A). All of them showed very good safety profile with different degrees and were safer than the reference drug used. Compound 
  <bold>5a</bold> was the most effective against MCF-7 cells and was less toxic than Saturosporin by about 18.45-folds towards MCF01A normal cells. All the new compounds were fully characterized by the different spectral and analytical tools. Herein, detailed syntheses, spectroscopic, and biological data are reported.
 </p>
</abstract>
