<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The use of 
 <italic>P. granatum</italic> preparations has a long ethnomedical history and preclinical studies have described different pharmacological abilities, including chemopreventive, chemosensitization, and chemotherapeutic activities [
 <xref rid="B142-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. It was reported that 
 <italic>P. granatum</italic> has the ability to down-regulate various signaling pathways like NF-ᴋB, P13K/AKT/mTOR and Wnt, as well as reduece the expression of genes that are associated with cancer development, such as anti-apoptotic genes, MMPs, VEGF, c-met, pro-inflammatory cytokines, cyclines, and Cdks [
 <xref rid="B143-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. In this regard, the antitumor effect of punicalagin, a pomegranate polyphenol, has been investigated in a human prostate cancer cell line (PC-3) and LNCaP cells. It was found that punicalagin inhibited cell viability of both cell lines in a dose-dependent manner and induced the expression of caspase-3 and -8 in PC-3 [
 <xref rid="B144-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. Moreover, an in vivo study has shown that aqueous extract of pomegranate fruit has anticancer activity against Ehrlich-ascites-carcinoma (EAC)-bearing Swiss albino mice. After intraperitoneal injection of mice with pomegranate aqueous extract, a significant reduction has occurred in tumor volume and weight, as well as, decreased viable cell count and improvement in the life span of EAC bearing mice [
 <xref rid="B145-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. In another study, pomegranate fruit juice and two of its components (ellagic acid and luteolin) have been shown to reduce cell viability of ovarian cancer cell line (A2780), inhibit metastasis via down-regulation of matrix metalloproteinases MMP2 and MMP9. Also, all three treatments inhibited tumor growth of ovarian cancer cell line (ES-2) in nude mice experiments [
 <xref rid="B146-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>].
</p>
