<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A modified micro-broth-dilution-colorimetric assay was applied to detect the antibacterial activity [
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-25-03664" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Test microorganisms included two Gram-positive (
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 6538 and 
 <italic>S. albus</italic> CICC 10897), and three Gram-negative (
 <italic>Shigella dysenteriae</italic> CMCC 51105, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC 25922, 
 <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> CMCC 50115) bacteria. ATCC referes to American type culture collection, CICC is the abbreviation for China center of industrial culture collection, and CMCC referes to China national center for medical culture collections. Test bacteria were grown in liquid Luria-Bertani (LB) medium (yeast extract 5.0 g/L, peptone 10.0 g/L, NaCl 5.0 g/L, pH 7.2) for 24 h at 37 ºC, and the diluted bacterial suspension (1 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> CFU/mL) was ready for detection. The extracts and four phenolic compounds were dissolved and diluted with 60% methanol (40% acetone for essential oil) to obtain appropriate concentrations in the range of 0.1 mg/mL to 100 mg/mL, respectively. Then, the test sample solutions (10 μL) and prepared bacterial suspension (90 μL) were added into each well of the 96-well microplate. Each well of the negative control (CK
 <sup>−</sup>) contained 90 μL of the inoculum and 10 μL of 60% methanol or 40% acetone. Streptomycin sulfate was used as the positive control (CK
 <sup>+</sup>). The 96-well plates were agitated to mix the contents of the wells using a plate shaker, and then incubated in the dark at 37 °C for 24–48 h. The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) value was defined as the lowest sample concentration that inhibited visible growth. To determine the minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC), 10 μL of suspension liquid was removed from the well and inoculated on the LB media, and incubated at 37 °C overnight. The MBC value was determined as the highest dilution at which no growth occurred on the media. All tests were performed in triplicate.
</p>
