<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It has been known that the birds’ dietary protein sources can influence the relative weights of breast, drumstick, abdominal fat, as well as their internal organs (liver, heart, spleen, gizzard and bursa). Findings of Okupe et al. [
 <xref rid="B80-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] showed that breast weight of birds fed 0% PKC diet was significantly higher compared to those fed with 10, 20 and 30% levels of PKC, whereas drumstick weight of birds fed with 30% PKC diets was significantly higher compared to birds fed with 0, 10 and 20% PKC diet. The result obtained by Okupe et al. [
 <xref rid="B80-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] showed that the abdominal fat weight of birds fed with 0% PKC diet was significantly higher than those fed with different levels of PKC. Chinajariyawong and Muangkeow [
 <xref rid="B72-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>] reported that the abdominal fat of birds fed on diets containing PKM or FPKM was significantly lower than the control. Alshelmani [
 <xref rid="B17-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] showed that abdominal fat of chickens fed with 10 and 15% PKC included was higher than 5% PKC and FPKC included groups. Dietary composition and lipid metabolism can greatly influence abdominal fat [
 <xref rid="B81-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. The significant increase in abdominal fat for birds fed high levels PKC or FPKC attributed to the inclusion of palm oil with higher ratios in their diets than the control or low levels PKC or FPKC treatments [
 <xref rid="B17-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. β-mannan is the main component of palm kernel biomass NSPs [
 <xref rid="B10-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. It is reported that 0.5 gr/kg and 1 gr/kg mannan oligosaccharide in broilers feeding diet reduced percentage of abdominal fat in the carcass and did not significantly affect dressing percentage and liver, heart, gizzard and bursa weights of birds [
 <xref rid="B82-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>].
</p>
