<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">In this paper, we apply the ‘end-to-end’ method of Rosenzweig et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup> to explore the role of historical climatic changes in the cassava disease epidemic in parts of sub-Saharan Africa. To confirm that the CLIMEX model fitted to 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> MEAM1 is relevant to the SSA 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> we compare the temperature development response patterns for species of 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> found associated with the cassava disease outbreaks in sub-Saharan Africa with those observed for MEAM1 and MED. We run the 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> MEAM1 CLIMEX model of Kriticos et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>
 </sup> with the CLIMEX Compare Locations/Years module, using a set of gridded monthly climate time series to test the hypothesis that the modelled annual climate suitability for 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> MEAM1 is correlated with a 13-year time series of abundance of 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> in Uganda
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>
 </sup>, and that the correlation is stable through time. As a further check of model relevance, we compare the CLIMEX model outputs for long-term average climate with data on 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> abundance collected from cassava fields across Uganda, Tanzania and Malawi
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>
 </sup>. Finally, we use the time series of climate suitability to test whether the climate suitability for 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> in East and Central Africa has been increasing when and where 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> SSA, CMD and CBSD have been observed to increase in prevalence
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. In so doing, we explore whether we can attribute the observed epidemiological and ecological changes to changes in modelled climatic suitability for 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> SSA species.
</p>
