<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The variability observed for the essential oil contents between the two 
 <italic class="italic">A. schaueriana</italic> populations analyzed in this study might indicate the presence of distinct chemotypes for this species. Similar results were obtained with the extracts from 
 <italic class="italic">A. marina</italic> leaves collected at two different Indian coasts, along the Arabic Sea and the Bay of Bengal, that were analyzed by GC-MS, showing a different chemical composition for these two populations [
 <xref rid="B11-medicines-04-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-medicines-04-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. The major constituents characterized in the Arabic Sea 
 <italic class="italic">A. marina</italic> were the aromatic compounds 4-hydroxyphenylethanol and 3-methylbenzaldehyde (approximately 60%) [
 <xref rid="B11-medicines-04-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], and the major compounds characterized in the Bay of Bengal 
 <italic class="italic">A. marina</italic> were terpenes and fatty acids, such as phytol (13.3%), palmitic acid (10.70%), 6-hydroxy-3-oxo-α-ionol (8.6%) and palmitic acid ethyl ester (6.2%) [
 <xref rid="B19-medicines-04-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Similar to the 
 <italic class="italic">A. schaueriana</italic> oils, the 
 <italic class="italic">A. marina</italic> extract differences could also be explained by the occurrence of chemotypes or by environmental factors that can also have an influence on chemical composition, such as the soil composition, temperature, relative humidity, sun exposure, wind regime and exposure to pathogens [
 <xref rid="B20-medicines-04-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. A more detailed study that involves other 
 <italic class="italic">A. schaueriana</italic> populations is necessary in order to assess whether these differences are caused by environmental factors or by populational variations (chemotypes).
</p>
