<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The 
 <italic class="italic">A. schaueriana</italic> essential oils presented some radical scavenging activity with an IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> of 0.90 mg/mL for oil 
 <bold class="bold">1</bold> and 1.13 mg/mL for oil 
 <bold class="bold">2</bold>, while quercetin, used as a positive control, showed an IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value of 10.47 ± 0.91 μg/mL. These results indicated that the essential oils were weaker antioxidants, when compared with quercetin. Oil 
 <bold class="bold">1</bold> contained mainly fatty acids, palmitic and myristic acid, which are an important source of reserve energy and are components of the cell membrane in all living organisms. Additionally, in plants, fatty acid metabolic pathways also play significant roles in pathogen defense [
 <xref rid="B21-medicines-04-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Saturated fatty acids can act as antioxidants or prooxidants [
 <xref rid="B22-medicines-04-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. The antioxidant activity of fatty extracts from 10 
 <italic class="italic">Cephalaria</italic> species, containing myristic and palmitic acids, showed IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values ranging from 3.77 to 15.12 mg/mL by the DPPH method [
 <xref rid="B23-medicines-04-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. The radical scavenging activity of 
 <italic class="italic">A. schaueriana</italic> oils was higher than that found in 
 <italic class="italic">Cephalaria</italic> species. Although oil 
 <bold class="bold">2</bold> contained, as one of the major compounds, eugenol, a phenolic compound, the total oil activity was lower than that obtained for oil 
 <bold class="bold">1</bold>. Pure eugenol showed a stronger antioxidant capacity than the positive control α-tocopherol (IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> 33.85 μg/mL), and presented an IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> of 16.06 μg/mL, using the same DPPH scavenging assay [
 <xref rid="B24-medicines-04-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>].
</p>
