<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Camphor is a common component in many essential oils. It is a major component of Ho (
 <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> (L.) J.Presl) leaf oil (camphor chemotype) (37.8–84.1%) [
 <xref rid="B40-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], feverfew (
 <italic>Tanacetum parthenium</italic> (L.) Sch.Bip.) oil (28.0–44.2%) [
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], and Spanish lavender (
 <italic>Lavandula stoechas</italic> L.) oil [
 <xref rid="B64-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Upon consumption, camphor is absorbed immediately via the mucosa and can freely cross the placenta in pregnant women [
 <xref rid="B98-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>] and reach the fetal organs such as brain, liver, lungs, and kidneys [
 <xref rid="B141-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>]. At very high doses, camphor can cause hemorrhage due to severe damage to the placenta [
 <xref rid="B142-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. In female mice, camphor (300 mg/kg/day for 20 days) increased the activities of hepatic CYP, glutathione 
 <italic>S</italic>-transferase, and aryl hydrocarbon hydroxylase [
 <xref rid="B143-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. Camphor is very toxic to humans with a lethal dose of 5–20 g [
 <xref rid="B144-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>] and 50–550 mg/kg [
 <xref rid="B98-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Camphor can cause damage to several organs including liver, kidney, and brain [
 <xref rid="B145-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>,
 <xref rid="B146-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>]. It can also cause convulsions [
 <xref rid="B147-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>] and induce seizures [
 <xref rid="B148-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. Signs of camphor poisoning include seizures, lack of coordination, respiratory depression, nausea, vomiting, and coma [
 <xref rid="B125-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>,
 <xref rid="B149-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>,
 <xref rid="B150-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>]. Despite being neurotoxic, hepatotoxic, and lethal in high doses, camphor is unexpectedly non-teratogenic and non-embryotoxic. In almost fatal doses, it can be reproductively toxic and abortifacient because the fetus lacks the necessary enzymes to metabolize it [
 <xref rid="B151-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>]. Camphor caused a dose-dependent maternal toxicity when given orally to pregnant rats (0.216, 0.464, or 1 g/kg/day on gestational days 6–17) and pregnant rabbits (0.147, 0.316, or 0.681 g/kg/day on gestational days 6–18) [
 <xref rid="B152-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>]. Yet, since camphor is believed to be more toxic to humans than animals, camphor-rich oils should be avoided in pregnancy and breastfeeding.
</p>
