<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The application of tannins as antioxidants has been evaluated in living cells. For example, tannic acid is commonly utilized as purified tannin. Its antioxidant capacity has been demonstrated in an in vitro assay based on fibroblasts irradiated with UVB to create an oxidative environment that led to cellular damage, simulating photoaging. Tannic acid showed strong antioxidant properties, a broad UV absorption spectrum and also an inhibitory activity towards collagenase and elastase. Thus, this tannin acid was demonstrated to prevent photodamage by attenuating the evaluated oxidation levels and diminished photoaging parameters [
 <xref rid="B71-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. The antioxidant activity of many other types of tannins has been evaluated. In a previous study, the ability to prevent lipid peroxidation of diverse phenolic compounds, including 25 tannins (both CTs and HTs at 5 µg/L), was assessed in rat liver mitochondria. The results displayed that HTs, like pedunculagin, PGG and chebulinic acid, were the most effective inhibitors. This suggest that the presence of structures such a galloyl, HHDP or dehydro-HHDP are involved in the inhibition of lipid peroxidation [
 <xref rid="B72-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Similar results were observed when different tannins (CTs: catechin and epigallocatechin-gallate; HTs: PGG and geraniin) were used to inhibit the effects of the induced lipid peroxidation in mouse lens [
 <xref rid="B73-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. The seed coat from 
 <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> was used to extract and purify tannins and flavonoids and the antioxidant activity of these compounds was tested using a liposome assay. Delphinidin and petunidin-3-glucoside were the most active tannins, showing an activity close to the 50% of that of the synthetic antioxidant butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) [
 <xref rid="B74-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Another work characterized a CT form from 
 <italic>Diospyros kaki</italic> and then analyzed its antioxidant capacity by an ex vivo tissue system and an in vivo assay. When tested in a mouse liver homogenate, it showed strong protection against auto-oxidation and H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>-induced oxidation processes with half inhibition concentrations of 4.3 and 1.4 μg/mL, respectively. In vivo assays, performed by the oral administration of 200 or 400 mg of CT per kg of mouse body weight, displayed a reduction of the activities of the evaluated oxidative biomarkers (serum and liver superoxide dismutase (SOD), GSH (reduced glutathione) peroxidase and liver malondialdehyde (MAD) activities) [
 <xref rid="B75-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. The antioxidant properties of tannin-rich extracts obtained from different vegetal species have been assessed. For instance, a 
 <italic>Q. robur</italic> tannin-rich extract, fundamentally composed of roburins, castalagin and vescalagin, has been reported to ameliorate oxidative stress markers and serum levels of related enzymes such as catalase (CAT) or SOD in a clinical trial [
 <xref rid="B56-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Another trial with the same extract studied the effect in vivo and ex vivo, analyzing the plasmatic oxidative profile and genetic expression of cell cycle-related genes from plasma cell samples and several tissues. Although the study sample consisted of only three subjects, the results were significant and very similar in all three subjects, with a significant increase in phenolic concentration in plasma, as well as the modulation of targeted genes [
 <xref rid="B57-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. A study evaluated an extract from 
 <italic>A. mearnsii,</italic> which displayed antioxidant properties that reversed the negative effects caused by acrolein (a compound related to neurodegenerative diseases)-induced cytotoxicity in a human neuroblastoma cell line (SH-SY5Y). In addition, the extract also inhibited the action of apoptotic factors [
 <xref rid="B76-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. In the same line of experiments, oxidative stress was induced in the SH-SY5Y cell line after its previous treatment with 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic> extracts, which significantly reduced reactive oxygen species (ROS) production. In addition, it was observed that the previous treatment reduced apoptotic signals caused by the damage inducers [
 <xref rid="B37-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].
</p>
