<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-medicines-04-00081" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Material and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-medicines-04-00081" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Plant Material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fresh samples of leaves and rhizomes of 
   <span class="italic">A. calamus</span> were collected in different seasons (during 2014/2015) from three different altitudes of the Uttarakhand Himalayas in India. The plant was identified by Dr. D.S Rawat, a plant taxonomist at the Department of Biological Sciences, G.B., Pant University of Agriculture and Technology, Pantnagar, Uttarakhand, India. The GPS coordinates of the three locations were: INDIA, Uttarakhand, Pithoragarh district, Pithoragarh near Govt PG College, along stream, 29°34′59.17″ N, 80°11′49.46″ E, 1570 m a.s.l., July 2014, 
   <span class="italic">Archna Parki s.n.</span>, GBPUH specimen Acc. No. 910. Naini Tal district, Bhimtal, along stream, 29°20′58.61″ N, 79°33′14.53″ E, 1340 m a.s.l., July 2014, 
   <span class="italic">Archna Parki s.n.</span>, GBPUH Acc. No. 911 and Udham Singh Nagar district, near CBSH Pantnagar, in drainage channel, 29°01′27.2″ N, 79°29′27.2″ E, 236 m a.s.l., July 2014, Archana Parki 
   <span class="italic">s.n.</span>, GBPUH Acc. No. 912.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-medicines-04-00081" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Extraction of Essential Oils</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fresh leaves/rhizomes of 
   <span class="italic">A. calamus</span> were collected from their natural habitat and tested in the phytochemistry research lab. To extract essential oil, the plant material (500 g) was crushed and separately subjected to hydro-distillation in Clevenger apparatus for 3 h using the apparatus described in the 
   <span class="italic">European Pharmacopoeia</span> [
   <a rid="B33-medicines-04-00081" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-medicines-04-00081">33</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-medicines-04-00081" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Gas Chromatography and Gas Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC and GC/MS analyses of all the oils were performed on a Thermo Fischer GC apparatus using an DB5-5MS fused-silica capillary column (30 m × 0.25 mm i.d., 0.25 μm film thickness) equipped with a flame ionization (FID) detector. GC/MS analysis of the different essential oil samples were performed using a GC MS-QP 2010, in the following conditions. Column DB-5 (30 m × 0.25 mm i.d.; 0.25 μm film thickness; J&amp;W Scientific, Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA); carrier gas: helium, with a flow rate of 1 mL/min; injection temperature: 250 °C; oven temperature programme: initial temperature 80 °C, isothermal for 2 min, RAMP 7 °C/min, final temperature 280 °C, and isothermal for 10 °C/min. Ionization mode: EI (70 eV), mass range: 40–6500 amu. The compounds were identified with the help of NIST-MS, FFNSC Wiley Library, and comparing the data with literature reports and GC retention indices [
   <a rid="B34-medicines-04-00081" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-medicines-04-00081">34</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot4-medicines-04-00081" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Antioxidant Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To analyse the in vitro antioxidant property, the essential oils of 
   <span class="italic">A. calamus</span> were subjected to the following methods.
  </p>
  <sec id="sec2dot4dot1-medicines-04-00081" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4.1. DPPH Radical Scavenging Activity</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is a quick method to study the scavenging ability of the antioxidants [
    <a rid="B35-medicines-04-00081" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-medicines-04-00081">35</a>]. Briefly, the tested samples (5–25 μL/mL) were added to 5 mL of a 0.004% methanol solution of DPPH. Finally, the absorbance was read against a blank at 517 nm after 30 min of incubation at room temperature. Ascorbic acid was used as the standard antioxidant. Inhibition of free radical by DPPH in percent (IC %) was calculated using the equation. IC% = (A
    <sub>0</sub> − A
    <sub>t</sub>)/A
    <sub>0</sub> × 100, where A
    <sub>0</sub> = the absorbance value of the control sample, A
    <sub>t</sub> = the absorbance value of the test sample, and IC = inhibitory concentration. The radical scavenging activities of essential oils were discussed in terms of their IC
    <sub>50</sub> values.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot4dot2-medicines-04-00081" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4.2. Reducing Power</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reducing power of essential oils was determined by the method developed earlier [
    <a rid="B36-medicines-04-00081" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-medicines-04-00081">36</a>]. In brief, varying concentrations of tested samples (5–25 μL/mL) were mixed with 2.5 mL of phosphate buffer (200 mM, pH = 6.6) and 2.5 mL of 1% potassium ferricyanide, K
    <sub>3</sub> [FeCN
    <sub>6</sub>]. The mixtures were incubated for 20 min at 50 °C. After incubation, 2.5 mL of trichloroacetic acid was added to the mixtures, followed by centrifugation at 650 rpm for 10 min. The upper layer (1 mL) was mixed with 5 mL distilled water and 1 mL of 0.1% ferric chloride and the absorbance of the resultant solution was measured at 700 nm. Reducing power % = (A
    <sub>0</sub> − A
    <sub>t</sub>)/A
    <sub>0</sub> × 100, where A
    <sub>0</sub> = the absorbance value of the control sample and A
    <sub>t</sub> = the absorbance value of the test sample. The percent of chelating ability was plotted against concentrations and using a standard (gallic acid). The reducing potential of essential oils was discussed in terms of their RP
    <sub>50</sub> values.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot4dot3-medicines-04-00081" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4.3. Metal Chelating Activity</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chelation of Fe
    <span class="sup">2+</span> by essential oils was evaluated using the method developed earlier [
    <a rid="B37-medicines-04-00081" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-medicines-04-00081">37</a>]. In brief, 0.1 mL of 2 mM FeCl
    <sub>2</sub>·4H
    <sub>2</sub>O, 0.2 mL of 5 mM ferrozine, and 4.7 mL of methanol were added to different concentrations of a test sample (5–25 μL/mL). The solutions were mixed and allowed to react for 10 min. The absorbance was determined at 562 nm; IC% = (A
    <sub>0</sub> − A
    <sub>t</sub>)/A
    <sub>0</sub> × 100, where A
    <sub>0</sub> = the absorbance value of the control sample and A
    <sub>t</sub> = the absorbance value of the test sample. The percent of chelating ability was plotted against the concentration, and the standard curve was drawn using a standard antioxidant (EDTA). The metal chelating ability of essential oils was discussed in terms of their IC
    <sub>50</sub> values.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
