<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Complement Altern Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Complement Altern Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Complementary and Alternative Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6882</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6062979</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2293</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-018-2293-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Induction of programmed cell death in <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> by <italic>Lippia alba</italic> essential oils and their major and synergistic terpenes (citral, limonene and caryophyllene oxide)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>&#x000c9;rika Marcela</given-names></name><address><email>coord.maestriainfecciosas@udes.edu.co</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>Sandra Milena</given-names></name><address><email>sa.leal@mail.udes.edu.co</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stashenko</surname><given-names>Elena E.</given-names></name><address><email>elena@tucan.uis.edu.co</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9054-9328</contrib-id><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>Liliana Torcoroma</given-names></name><address><email>l.torcoroma@udes.edu.co</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.442204.4</institution-id><institution>Infectious Disease Research Program, </institution><institution>Universidad de Santander, </institution></institution-wrap>680006 Bucaramanga, Colombia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.442204.4</institution-id><institution>Bacteriology and Clinical Laboratory Program, </institution><institution>Universidad de Santander, </institution></institution-wrap>680006 Bucaramanga, Colombia </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2105 7207</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411595.d</institution-id><institution>National Research Center for Agroindustrialization of Aromatic Medical and Tropical Species (CENIVAM), </institution><institution>Universidad Industrial de Santander, </institution></institution-wrap>680002 Bucaramanga, Colombia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>225</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Chagas Disease caused by <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> infection, is one of the most important neglected tropical diseases (NTD), without an effective therapy for the successful parasite eradication or for the blocking of the disease&#x02019;s progression, in its advanced stages. Due to their low toxicity, wide pharmacologic spectrum, and potential synergies, medicinal plants as <italic>Lippia alba</italic>, offer a promising reserve of bioactive molecules. The principal goal of this work is to characterize the inhibitory properties and cellular effects of the Citral and Carvone <italic>L. alba</italic> chemotype essential oils (EOs) and their main bioactive terpenes (and the synergies among them) on <italic>T. cruzi</italic> forms.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Twelve <italic>L. alba</italic> EOs, produced under diverse environmental conditions, were extracted by microwave assisted hydrodistillation, and chemically characterized using gas chromatography coupled mass spectrometry. Trypanocidal activity and cytotoxicity were determined for each oil, and their major compounds, on epimastigotes (Epi), trypomastigotes (Tryp), amastigotes (Amas), and Vero cells. Pharmacologic interactions were defined by a matrix of combinations among the most trypanocidal terpenes (limonene, carvone; citral and caryophyllene oxide). The treated cell phenotype was assessed by fluorescent and optic microscopy, flow cytometry, and DNA electrophoresis assays.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The <italic>L. alba</italic> EOs displayed significant differences in their chemical composition and trypanocidal performance (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0001). Citral chemotype oils were more trypanocidal than Carvone EOs, with Inhibitory Concentration 50 (IC<sub>50</sub>) of 14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, 22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL and 74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, on Epi, Tryp and Amas, respectively. Limonene exhibited synergistic interaction with citral, caryophyllene oxide and Benznidazole (decreasing by 17 times its IC<sub>50</sub>) and was the most effective and selective treatment. The cellular analysis suggested that these oils or their bioactive terpenes (citral, caryophyllene oxide and limonene) could be inducing <italic>T. cruzi</italic> cell death by an apoptotic-like mechanism.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">EOs extracted from <italic>L. alba</italic> Citral chemotype demonstrated significant trypanocidal activity on the three forms of <italic>T. cruzi</italic> studied, and their composition and trypanocidal performance were influenced by production parameters. Citral, caryophyllene oxide, and limonene showed a possible induction of an apoptotic-like phenotype. The best selective anti-<italic>T. cruzi</italic> activity was achieved by limonene, the effects of which were also synergic with citral, caryophyllene oxide and benznidazole.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Lippia alba</italic></kwd><kwd>Essential oils</kwd><kwd>Citral</kwd><kwd>Caryophyllene oxide</kwd><kwd>Limonene</kwd><kwd>Synergy</kwd><kwd><italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Universidad de Santander -Vicerrector&#x000ed;a de Investigaciones</institution></funding-source><award-id>005-14</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>Liliana Torcoroma</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100009087</institution-id><institution>Universidad Industrial de Santander</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>5658</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>Liliana Torcoroma</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par60">Chagas Disease is one of the most important Neglected Tropical Diseases (NTDs) worldwide, and is one of the most relevant public health problems in Latin America. This infection, caused by the hemoflagellated protozoan <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic>, currently affects an estimated 7 million people in the world, with around 99% of all registered cases occurring in Central and South American countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The global costs of this disease are calculated at approximately USD $7.19 billion per year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], with regional economic losses of almost US $1.2 billion, annually [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In Colombia, the prevalence of this trypanosomiasis is estimated to be within a range of 700,000 &#x02013; 1,200,000 cases, with more than 8,000,000 persons at risk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par61">In regions where the condition is endemic, disease-control efforts principally centered on preventing or reducing the <italic>T. cruzi</italic> transmission cycle by vector eradication and massive blood donation screening [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. However, bigger challenges remain; in particular, those associated with the changing epidemiological profile of the infection (diversity of vectors, reservoirs, and modes of transmission), being the most significant problem, the lack of effective therapies to cure the <italic>T. cruzi</italic> infection or to prevent the progression of the disease, principally in advanced stages.</p><p id="Par62">At present, the conventional Chagas Disease treatments are etiologic, and are comprised of only two possible options, Nifurtimox (NFX) (Lampit&#x000ae;, Bayer) and Benznidazole (BNZ) (Rochagan&#x000ae; in Brazil and Radanil&#x000ae; in Argentina, Roche). These two treatments have remained the standard since their introduction into clinical therapy more than 40&#x000a0;years ago [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. As disadvantages, these treatments are highly toxic (often accompanied by serious side effects like digestive intolerance, severe anorexia and neurological disorders) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]; involve prolonged treatment times; and demonstrate variable trypanocidal effectiveness in acute stage (with about 80% being associated with natural resistance). They also display limited efficacy in the late phase of the infection (in which the benefits of these therapies have not clearly defined) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par63">In general, these conventional therapies do not take into account the complex cascade of cellular events leading to Chagasic cardiomyopathy, which are not only associated with the parasite&#x02019;s presence, but also involve exacerbated and persistent immune response (with cellular and neuronal damage) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. These latter factors are those which govern the microvasculopathy and cardiac failure associated with the condition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par64">In this regard, the research and development of new alternative therapies for Chagas Disease remain pressing concerns. New pharmacological approaches should be more efficient and selective, seeking complete parasite elimination, but with adequate modulation of the host immune response and limitation of cellular damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. To this end, in the last two decades, intensive research has been focused on the study of the properties of whole extracts or compounds isolated from plants or synthesized based on natural prototypes, which have shown promising results against parasite infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par65">Essential oils (EOs) extracted from aromatic plants and their main components have been described as broad-spectrum antimicrobial agents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], with significant anthelmintic and antiprotozoal activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Some terpenes of these oils such as citral (<italic>Lippia alba</italic> and <italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic>), caryophyllene oxide (<italic>Aframomum sceptrum, Achillea millefolium,</italic> and <italic>Piper var brachypodon</italic>), and limonene (<italic>L. origanoides</italic> and <italic>L. pedunculosa</italic>) have demonstrated efficient trypanocidal activity on extra and intracellular forms of <italic>T. cruzi</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In addition, these terpenes have been found to exhibit other interesting biological properties, such as being anti-inflammatory immunomodulators, selective antioxidants, and cytoprotectors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The presence of citral, caryophyllene and limonene has been identified in EOs isolated from two chemotypes (Citral and Carvone) of the aromatic shrub <italic>Lippia alba</italic> (Miller) N.E. Brown (Verbenaceae), that grows in the Colombian province of Santander [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. <italic>L. alba</italic> represents the seventh species most cited in traditional Brazilian medicine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. The &#x0201c;healers&#x0201d; use their leaves as an infusion to treat health problems such as hypertension, digestive, colds and local wound healing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. In the state of Boyac&#x000e1;, Colombia, it is frequently used as an analgesic, for digestive (diarrhea, stomach pain) and respiratory problems (flu and cough) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]<italic>.</italic> Previous screening studies with these oils evidenced selective inhibition and cytotoxicity against trypanosomatid parasites, in vitro [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Taking into consideration their numerous functions, <italic>L. alba</italic> EOs and their bioactive terpenes are a promising platform for development of holistic therapies to combat Chagas Disease. This kind of approach could allow for a selective eradication of the parasite, with less toxicity (even with chemoprotection), and for controlling the host immune response, through a possible synergistic interaction of the compounds involved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par66">The principal goal of this work is to characterize the inhibitory properties and cellular effects of the Citral and Carvone <italic>L. alba</italic> chemotype EOs and their main bioactive terpenes on <italic>T. cruzi</italic> epimastigotes, trypomastigotes, and amastigotes cyclic forms. The IC<sub>50</sub> was determined for each of these compounds, and possible pharmacologic interactions were defined by a matrix of combinations of the trypanocidal compounds (from Carvone chemotype: limonene and carvone; and from Citral chemotype: citral and caryophyllene oxide). The phenotype of the parasites and mammal cells treated with EOs or terpenes was followed by fluorescent and optic microscopy, flow cytometry, and DNA electrophoresis assays.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant material</title><p id="Par67">In this study, specimens of the Citral and Carvone chemotypes of <italic>Lippia alba</italic> (Miller) N. E. Brown (Verbenaceae) were planted in the National Research Center for Agroindustrialization of Aromatic Medical and Tropical species (CENIVAM, in Spanish) located in Bucaramanga, Santander, Colombia, at an altitude of 960&#x000a0;m above sea level. The formal identification of the plant specimens used in this study was provided by Prof. Jorge Luis Fern&#x000e1;ndez Alonso and the vouchers were deposited at the Colombian National Herbarium (Universidad Nacional de Colombia) under Herbarium Codes COL480750 and COL512077, for Carvone and Citral chemotypes of <italic>L. alba</italic>, respectively. A range of environmental and production conditions were used in order to produce 76 EOs with possible diversity in their main compounds. In this regard, the vegetal material was grown, collected, and extracted under the following factors. 1) season: defined as dry (January to March, 26.3&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C temperature, with 68.9% relative humidity, and 1.05&#x000a0;mm/day precipitation) and rainy (April to November, mean temperature of 24.5&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, relative humidity of 81.3%, and 4.13&#x000a0;mm of daily precipitation); 2) <italic>L. alba</italic> chemotypes (53 from Carvone and 23 from Citral); 3) part of plant harvested (root, stem, fresh and mature leaves, and flowers); 4) vegetal material conditions (fresh and dry); and 5) extraction time (from 30 to 90&#x000a0;min).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Essential oils extraction and characterization</title><p id="Par68">The oil extraction was performed by microwave-assisted hydrodistillation (MWHD), as described elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Briefly, a domestic microwave oven (Kendo, 2.45&#x000a0;GHz, 800&#x000a0;W) was modified with a side orifice through which an external Dean-Stark trap joined a round flask that contained the plant material (100&#x000a0;g) and water (0.5&#x000a0;L), inside the oven. Three 15&#x000a0;min heating periods at full power were used to perform the hydrodistillation. The Dean-Stark trap permitted to decant the essential oil from the condensate. A gas chromatograph GC 7890 (Agilent Technologies, AT, Palo Alto, CA, U.S.A.) coupled to a mass selective detector MSD 5975C (AT, Palo Alto, CA, U.S.A.), using electron impact ionization (EI, 70&#x000a0;eV) was used for essential oil characterization. This system included a split/splitless injector (1:30 split ratio), and a MS-ChemStation G1701-DA data system, with the WILEY, NIST and QUADLIB 2007 spectral libraries. For their GC-MS assays, individual essential oil samples (50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L) were mixed with <italic>n</italic>-tetradecane (2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L, internal standard) and diluted with dichloromethane to a final volume of 1.0&#x000a0;mL. Helium (99.9995%) was used as the carrier gas, with 155&#x000a0;kPa column head pressure and 27&#x000a0;cm&#x000a0;s<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> linear velocity (1&#x000a0;mL&#x000a0;minute-1, at constant flow), in two columns of different polarities (DB-5MS and DB-WAX from J&#x00026;W Scientific, USA). The GC oven temperature was programmed from 50&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C (5&#x000a0;min) to 150&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C (2&#x000a0;min) at 5&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C&#x000a0;min<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup>, then to 230&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C (10&#x000a0;min) at 5&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C&#x000a0;min<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup>. When the DB-5MS column was used, a final heating to 275&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C (15&#x000a0;min) at 10&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C&#x000a0;min<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> was added. The temperatures of the injection port, ionization chamber and of the transfer line were set at 250, 230 and 285&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, respectively. For the polar DB-WAX column, the transfer line temperature was set at 230&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Mass spectra and reconstructed (total) ion chromatograms were obtained by automatic scanning in the mass range <italic>m/z</italic> 30&#x02013;400 at 4.5 scan s<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup>. Compound relative abundances were calculated from the chromatographic area of profiles obtained with an AT 7890 gas chromatograph provided with flame ionization detection (FID, 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C). The chromatographic columns, carrier gas and oven temperature programs employed in GC-FID analysis were the same as described previously for the GC-MS system. The EO compounds were identified using mass spectra and linear retention indices relative to C<sub>8</sub>-C<sub>32</sub> n-alkanes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Several terpenoid standard compounds, such as limonene, carvone, geranial, geraniol, &#x003b2;-caryophyllene, and &#x003b2;-caryophyllene oxide, obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, U.S.A., with purities above 98%) were used. The extracted EOs were preserved at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and protected from light before GC-MS and cellular analysis. Finally, the 76 EOs were arranged into 12 groups, according to the significant differences in the percentages of their major terpenes and one oil of each group was arbitrarily selected for further biological analysis, comprising six EOs from Citral chemotype (A13, A20, A23, A24, A25, and A28), and six from the Carvone chemotype (B7, B16, B37, 2B8, 2B18, and 2B19).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Terpenes and drugs</title><p id="Par69">The terpenes S (+) carvone, D (+) limonene, (&#x02212;) caryophyllene oxide, and citral were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO). The reference medication BNZ (Radanil&#x000ae;, Roche) was donated by Santander&#x02019;s State Secretary of Health, and purified by Dr. Leonor Yamile Vargas, from the Environmental Chemistry Program at Universidad Santo Tom&#x000e1;s de Aquino (Bucaramanga). Concentrations ranging from 1.85 to 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL were used for epimastigote (Epi) and amastigote (Amas) assays and 0.39 to 3.12&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL for trypomastigote (Tryp) assays. The oils (at a density of 0.9&#x000a0;g/mL) and terpene stock solutions were prepared in dimethyl-sulfoxide (DMSO, Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO)), to get a 10% (<italic>v</italic>/v) solution, without exceeding a DMSO final concentration of 0.1%, in any solution. Working solutions (3.7 to 300&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) were diluted immediately prior to use with Liver Infusion Tryptose (LIT, Becton Dickinson, FL, USA) media and Dulbecco&#x02019;s Modified Eagle&#x02019;s Medium (DMEM, Life Technology, CA, USA) for <italic>T. cruzi</italic> cells and Vero lineage, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Cell cultures</title><p id="Par70">Vero lineage derived from African Green Monkey Kidney (Vero, ATCC CCL-81) was used for selectivity index determination and for Tryp and Amas production. These cells were grown on DMEM (Life Technology, CA, USA) media, pH: 7.4; supplemented with 10% of inactivated Fetal Bovine Serum (FBSi), 1000&#x000a0;U/mL of penicillin, and 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL of streptomycin; and incubated at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with 90% humidity and a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> atmosphere. Epi of <italic>T. cruzi</italic> I (TcI) SYLVIO-X10 strain, were donated by Dr. Marcos L&#x000f3;pez-Casillas, from Fundaci&#x000f3;n Cardiovascular de Colombia and grown in LIT medium (Merck) supplemented with 10% FBSi, and incubated at 28&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The Trypomastigotes Derived from Cells (TDC) were obtained by infection of a confluent monolayer of Vero cells with 12&#x000a0;day-old stationary growth phase Epi and incubated under the same conditions described above for Vero cells.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Cytotoxic activity on Vero cells</title><p id="Par71">Vero cells (3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> cel/mL) were incubated at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> atmosphere and at 95% humidity for 24&#x000a0;h to ensure the formation of a confluent monolayer. After this time, the cells were treated with the EOs or their terpenes in four different concentrations (11.1, 33.3, 100, and 300&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL). Thereafter, the lineages were incubated for 70&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> atmosphere and re-incubated 2 more hours with WST-1 (Roche, Mannheim, Germany), after which Optical Density (OD) measurements were analyzed by spectrophotometry. The cytotoxicity percentage was calculated using [(OD<sub>450nm</sub> Control &#x02013; OD<sub>450nm</sub> treatment) / OD<sub>450nm</sub> treatment)] &#x000d7;&#x02009;100. The results were expressed as Cytotoxic Concentration 50 (CC<sub>50</sub>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Anti-parasitic activity on <italic>T. cruzi</italic></title><p id="Par72"><italic>T. cruzi</italic> Epi (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> Epi/mL) and TDC (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> cells/mL) in the exponential growth phase were plated in a 96-well standard microplate in LIT medium (at 28&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) and in D-MEM medium (at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> atmosphere), respectively. Both cultures were supplemented with 10% FBSi. For the trypanocidal assays, the EOs or their terpenes were added at varying concentrations (3.7 to 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) and incubated at the same culture conditions for 72 (Epi) or 24&#x000a0;h (Tryp). The growth inhibition was estimated by light microscopy through a differential count using the Trypan Blue (Gibco) dye exclusion technique. The results were expressed in terms of Inhibitory Concentration 50 (IC<sub>50</sub>) or the concentration at which parasite growth is inhibited by 50%. For Amas assays, a monolayer of Vero cells (3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> cel/mL) was infected with TDC in a 1:3 cell:parasite ratio and incubated for 24&#x000a0;h until Amas development occurred. Then, these intracellular forms were exposed for 120&#x000a0;h to EOs or terpenes in a treatment applied in two doses (at 0 and 48&#x000a0;h), under the same conditions described above. Growth inhibition analysis was assessed in Giemsa-stained films using light microscopy to determine the infected and uninfected cell percentage in a total of 300 cells. Cells without treatment and those treated with BNZ were used as negative and positive controls, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Pharmacological interaction among terpenes on <italic>T. cruzi</italic></title><p id="Par73">A matrix of pharmacological interactions between limonene (the most selective terpene) and the other major EO terpenes was created for the three cyclic forms of <italic>T. cruzi,</italic> using the fixed-ratio isobologram method, as described previously by Fivelman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] with some modifications (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In the interaction matrix, the estimated IC<sub>50</sub> for each terpene was used as fixed-value for the combinations. In addition, a mixture of limonene and BNZ was also evaluated.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Interaction matrix among terpenes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Combination ID Number</th><th>Limonene (Compound X)</th><th>Compound Y</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>0.0</td><td>8&#x000d7; IC<sub>50</sub></td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>&#x000bd; IC<sub>50</sub></td><td>4&#x000d7; IC<sub>50</sub></td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>IC<sub>50</sub></td><td>2&#x000d7; IC<sub>50</sub></td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>2&#x000d7; IC<sub>50</sub></td><td>IC<sub>50</sub></td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>4&#x000d7; IC<sub>50</sub></td><td>&#x000bd; IC<sub>50</sub></td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>8&#x000d7; IC<sub>50</sub></td><td>0.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>IC</italic><sub><italic>50</italic></sub> Inhibitory Concentration 50, <italic>x</italic> Number of times</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par74">The susceptibility evaluation was performed following the protocol described above for in vitro anti-parasitic activity. The Fractional Inhibitory Concentration (FIC) was calculated by: (Compound X (FIC)&#x02009;=&#x02009;Compound X (IC<sub>50</sub>) in combination) / (Compound X (IC<sub>50</sub>) alone); and the sum of FIC (&#x003a3;FIC) was determined by: &#x003a3;FIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;Compound X (FIC)&#x02009;+&#x02009;Compound Y (FIC). In this manner, synergistic, antagonist, or additive interactions were defined by <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {}_{\overline{\mathrm{X}}} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">X</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12906_2018_2293_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x003a3;CIF &#x0003c;&#x02009;1, <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {}_{\overline{\mathrm{X}}} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">X</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12906_2018_2293_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x003a3;CIF &#x0003e;&#x02009;1 or <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {}_{\overline{\mathrm{X}}} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="inline"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">X</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12906_2018_2293_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x003a3;CIF =1, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Analysis of cell death</title><p id="Par75">The death phenotype was analyzed by optical and fluorescent microscopy using phase contrast (fluorescence microscopy, Nikon Eclipse Ni). The cell morphology in Epi treated with two doses of the IC<sub>50</sub> (2xIC<sub>50</sub>)<italic>,</italic> was examined by the 4 &#x02018;,6diamidino-2, phenylindole probe (DAPI, 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, Sigma Aldrich) and a TUNEL assay (Molecular Probes, Invitrogen) for DNA fragmentation using a Terminal desoxynucleotidyl Transferase (TdT) label with d-UTP fluorescein. Determination of an oligonucleosomal-DNA ladder in treated parasites was also evaluated through DNA gel electrophoresis. Evaluation of the mitochondrial potential membrane in living parasites was performed with MitoTracker Red CMXRos (579&#x000a0;nm/599&#x000a0;nm emission/excitation wavelength) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. As a positive and negative apoptosis control, a 15&#x000a0;day-old Epi culture and an untreated fresh parasite culture were used, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Flow cytometry analysis</title><p id="Par76">For cell death characterization, an Annexin V/Dead with SYTOX&#x000ae; Green (Molecular Probes, Invitrogen) kit was used following the procedure specified in the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The phosphatidylserine externalization was determined by employing a recombinant Annexin V conjugated to the Orange Fluorescent phycobiliprotein R-PE, and to the necrotic cells using SYTOX&#x02122; Green nucleic acid stain. Briefly, 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> Epi per mL were treated with 2xIC<sub>50</sub> for 48&#x000a0;h, washed, and suspended in 1X Annexin-Binding Buffer. Next, R-PE Annexin V and SYTOX&#x000ae; Green Stain were added and incubated at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, and 95% humidity, and analyzed in a FACSCanto II Flow Cytometer (provided by Dr. Marcos L&#x000f3;pez from Fundaci&#x000f3;n Cardiovascular de Colombia), with 488&#x000a0;nm/575&#x000a0;nm Excitation/Emission filters for R-PE and 503&#x000a0;nm/524&#x000a0;nm Excitation/Emission filters for SYTOX.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par77">Each treatment was tested in triplicate in three independent assays. The IC<sub>50</sub> and CC<sub>50</sub> were calculated by sigmoidal regression using the statistical software Msxlfit&#x02122; (ID Business Solution). The cytotoxicity analysis and statistically-significant difference determinations were performed using a Welch&#x02019;s test for analysis of variances using SPSS 15.0 Software (IBM). Multiple comparison analysis was accomplished using a Tukey test with a 95% confidence level.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Chemical composition and trypanocidal activity of <italic>L. alba</italic> EOs</title><p id="Par78">This work studied the trypanocidal properties of 12 EOs isolated from Citral and Carvone <italic>L. alba</italic> chemotypes produced under an array of standardized conditions for planting, collecting and extracting of the vegetal material. A typical chromatographic profile for each chemotype essential oil, obtained by mass spectra and linear retention indices, is showed in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref> and <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">b</xref>, for Carvone and Citral oils, respectively. The corresponding peak assignment of these chromatograms are listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Typical gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) profiles, in a DB-5 (60&#x000a0;m) column with a mass selective detector (EI. 70&#x000a0;eV), of essential oils obtained from <italic>Lippia alba</italic> Carvone (<bold>a</bold>) and Citral (<bold>b</bold>) chemotypes by microwave-assisted hydrodistillation (MWHD). The corresponding peak identification is showed in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2018_2293_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Peak assignment for GC-MS profiles of essential oils extracted by microwave-assisted hydrodistillation (MWHD) from <italic>Lippia alba</italic> Carvone (A) and Citral (B) chemotypes plants growing in Bucaramanga (Colombia)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Peak</th><th rowspan="2">Compound</th><th colspan="2">LRI</th><th colspan="2">Relative Quantity, %</th></tr><tr><th>DB-5MS<sup><italic>a</italic></sup></th><th>DB-WAX<sup><italic>b</italic></sup></th><th>Carvone (A)</th><th>Citral (B)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>6-Methyl-5-hepten-2-one</td><td>986</td><td>1241</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>3.3</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>&#x003b2;-Myrcene</td><td>991</td><td>1064</td><td>0.8</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Limonene</td><td>1034</td><td>1105</td><td>29.1</td><td>6.6</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td><italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-Ocimene</td><td>1047</td><td>1153</td><td>0.7</td><td>0.2</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Linalool</td><td>1100</td><td>1453</td><td>0.6</td><td>1.9</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>Citronellal</td><td>1154</td><td>1381</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.1</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>Borneol</td><td>1181</td><td>1613</td><td>0.8</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td><italic>cis</italic>-Dihydrocarvone</td><td>1203</td><td>1517</td><td>0.2</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td><italic>trans</italic>-Dihydrocarvone</td><td>1211</td><td>1537</td><td>0.2</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>Nerol</td><td>1231</td><td>1708</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>0.8</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>Neral</td><td>1248</td><td>1589</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>21.5</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>Geraniol</td><td>1252</td><td>1755</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5.6</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>Carvone</td><td>1258</td><td>1653</td><td>35.0</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>Piperitone</td><td>1264</td><td>1641</td><td>2.4</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>Geranial</td><td>1275</td><td>1643</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>28.7</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>Piperitenone</td><td>1349</td><td>1842</td><td>4.0</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>Geranyl Acetate</td><td>1379</td><td>1662</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.5</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>&#x003b2;-Bourboneno</td><td>1396</td><td>1428</td><td>1.2</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>&#x003b2;-Elemene</td><td>1397</td><td>1496</td><td>1.0</td><td>3.0</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td><italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-Caryophyllene</td><td>1436</td><td>1506</td><td>0.2</td><td>12.1</td></tr><tr><td>21</td><td>&#x003b2;-Gurjunene</td><td>1444</td><td>1447</td><td>0.2</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>22</td><td>&#x003b1;-Guaiene</td><td>1447</td><td>1498</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.8</td></tr><tr><td>23</td><td><italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-Farnesene</td><td>1456</td><td>1570</td><td>0.7</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>24</td><td>&#x003b1;-Humulene</td><td>1471</td><td>1580</td><td>0.1</td><td>2.7</td></tr><tr><td>25</td><td>&#x003b3;-Gurjunene</td><td>1475</td><td>1587</td><td>0.4</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>26</td><td>Germacrene D</td><td>1486</td><td>1552</td><td>0.1</td><td>2.6</td></tr><tr><td>27</td><td>Bicyclosesquiphellandrene</td><td>1496</td><td>1624</td><td>8.2</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>28</td><td>Bicyclogermacrene</td><td>1509</td><td>1608</td><td>0.5</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>29</td><td>&#x003b1;-Bulnesene</td><td>1515</td><td>1627</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.4</td></tr><tr><td>30</td><td>Cubebol</td><td>1528</td><td>1855</td><td>0.5</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>31</td><td>Germacrene-4-ol</td><td>1591</td><td>1967</td><td>0.6</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>32</td><td>Caryophyllene Oxide</td><td>1600</td><td>1909</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>LRI</italic> Linear retention index</p><p><sup>a</sup>Linear Retention Index experimentally determined in DB-5MS (60&#x000a0;m) column</p><p><sup>b</sup>Linear Retention Index experimentally determined in DB-WAX (60&#x000a0;m) column</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par79">All the EOs presented diversity in their chemical composition, and this variety also appeared as significant differences in their trypanocidal performance on the three cyclic forms of the parasite (Epi: F&#x02009;=&#x02009;1320.080; <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.000; Tryp: F&#x02009;=&#x02009;628.786; <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.000; Amas: F&#x02009;=&#x02009;853.422; <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.000) (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Relative chemical composition and anti-proliferative effect on <italic>T. cruzi</italic> of EOs extracted from the Citral chemotype of <italic>L. alba</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Season</th><th rowspan="2">Material</th><th rowspan="2">EO<sup>a</sup></th><th>Extra<sup>b</sup> Time</th><th rowspan="2">Part Plant</th><th colspan="5">Chemical Composition</th><th colspan="2">Epi<sup>f</sup></th><th colspan="2">Tryp<sup>j</sup></th><th colspan="2">Amas<sup>k</sup></th><th>Vero</th></tr><tr><th>min<sup>c</sup></th><th>Neral %</th><th>Geraniol %</th><th>Geranial %</th><th>Caryop<sup>d</sup> %</th><th>CarOx<sup>e</sup> %</th><th>IC<sub>50</sub><sup>g</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD<sup>h</sup> &#x003bc;g/mL</th><th>SI<sup>i</sup></th><th>IC<sub>50</sub><sup>g</sup> SD<sup>h</sup> &#x003bc;g/mL</th><th>SI<sup>i</sup></th><th>IC<sub>50</sub><sup>g</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD<sup>h</sup> &#x003bc;g/mL</th><th>SI<sup>i</sup></th><th>CC<sub>50</sub>
<sup>l</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD<sup>h</sup> &#x003bc;g/mL</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Dry</td><td>Dry</td><td>A28</td><td>45</td><td>Infl<sup>m</sup></td><td>19.3</td><td>31.5</td><td>31.3</td><td>2.3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>14&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.6</td><td>7.1</td><td>31&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.9</td><td>3.1</td><td>66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.8</td><td>1.5</td><td>97&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">Rainy</td><td>Fresh</td><td>A25</td><td>45</td><td>AL<sup>n</sup></td><td>22.8</td><td>5.3</td><td>27.5</td><td>4.6</td><td>2.8</td><td>18&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.7</td><td>5.3</td><td>19.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.9</td><td>4.9</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;33.3</td><td>ND<sup>r</sup></td><td>95&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">Dry</td><td>A13</td><td>30</td><td>YL<sup>o</sup></td><td>30.6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>54.5</td><td>2.9</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>17&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.7</td><td>7.0</td><td>21&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.6</td><td>5.7</td><td>88&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.4</td><td>1.4</td><td>121&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;10.1</td></tr><tr><td>A20</td><td>30</td><td>ML<sup>p</sup></td><td>32.1</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>54</td><td>4</td><td>2.4</td><td>9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.2</td><td>7.8</td><td>14&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.9</td><td>4.7</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;33.3</td><td>ND</td><td>66&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.9</td></tr><tr><td>A23</td><td>90</td><td>ML</td><td>28</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>37.8</td><td>6.8</td><td>2.9</td><td>8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.3</td><td>6.2</td><td>17&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.3</td><td>3.0</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;33.3</td><td>ND</td><td>51&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.2</td></tr><tr><td>A24</td><td>90</td><td>ML</td><td>24</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>34.3</td><td>2</td><td>5.7</td><td>16&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.6</td><td>5.7</td><td>29&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.8</td><td>3.1</td><td>69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.0</td><td>1.3</td><td>91&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.1</td></tr><tr><td>BNZ<sup>q</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>17&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.9</td><td>8.2</td><td>1.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1</td><td>116.3</td><td>6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9</td><td>22.4</td><td>139&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup><italic>EO</italic> Essential oil, <sup>b</sup><italic>Extra</italic> Extraction, <sup>c</sup><italic>min</italic> Minutes, <sup>d</sup><italic>Caryop</italic> Caryophyllene, <sup>e</sup><italic>CarOx</italic> Caryophyllene oxide, <sup>f</sup><italic>Epi</italic> Epimastigote, <sup>g</sup><italic>IC</italic><sub><italic>50</italic></sub> Inhibitory concentration 50, <sup>i</sup><italic>SD</italic> Standard deviation, <sup>i</sup><italic>SI</italic> Selectivity index (CC<sub>50</sub>/IC<sub>50</sub>), <sup>j</sup><italic>Tryp</italic> Trypomastigote, <sup>k</sup><italic>Amas</italic> Amastigote, <sup>l</sup><italic>CC</italic><sub><italic>50</italic></sub> Cytotoxic concentration 50, <sup>m</sup><italic>Infl</italic> Inflorescences, <sup>n</sup><italic>AL</italic> All leaves, <sup>o</sup><italic>YL</italic> Young leaves, <sup>p</sup><italic>ML</italic> Mature leaves, <sup>q</sup><italic>BNZ</italic> Benznidazole, <sup>r</sup><italic>ND</italic> Not determined</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Relative chemical composition and anti-proliferative effect on <italic>T. cruzi</italic> of EOs extracted from the Carvone chemotype of <italic>L. alba</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Season</th><th rowspan="2">Material</th><th rowspan="2">EO<sup>a</sup></th><th>Extra<sup>b</sup> Time</th><th rowspan="2">Part Plant</th><th colspan="3">Chemical Composition</th><th colspan="2">Epi<sup>f</sup></th><th colspan="2">Tryp<sup>j</sup></th><th colspan="2">Amas<sup>k</sup></th><th colspan="2">Vero</th></tr><tr><th>min<sup>c</sup></th><th>Limonene %</th><th>Carvone %</th><th>Piper<sup>d</sup> %</th><th>BCE<sup>e</sup> %</th><th>IC<sub>50</sub><sup>g</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD<sup>h</sup> &#x003bc;g/mL</th><th>SI<sup>i</sup></th><th>IC<sub>50</sub><sup>g</sup> SD<sup>h</sup> &#x003bc;g/mL</th><th>SI<sup>i</sup></th><th>IC<sub>50</sub><sup>g</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD<sup>h</sup> &#x003bc;g/mL</th><th>SI<sup>i</sup></th><th>CC<sub>50</sub><sup>l</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD<sup>h</sup> &#x003bc;g/mL</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Dry</td><td>Fresh</td><td>B7</td><td>30</td><td>AL<sup>m</sup></td><td>19.3</td><td>31.5</td><td>31.3</td><td>2.3</td><td>81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.4</td><td>2.5</td><td>37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1</td><td>5.5</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009; 150</td><td>ND<sup>o</sup></td><td>203&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">Rainy</td><td>Dry</td><td>2B8</td><td>90</td><td>YL<sup>n</sup></td><td>22.8</td><td>5.3</td><td>27.5</td><td>4.6</td><td>96&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.4</td><td>1.9</td><td>47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.8</td><td>4.0</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009; 150</td><td>ND</td><td>186&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.7</td></tr><tr><td>Fresh</td><td>B16</td><td>90</td><td>AL</td><td>30.6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>54.5</td><td>2.9</td><td>97&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.2</td><td>2.2</td><td>57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.0</td><td>3.8</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009; 150</td><td>ND</td><td>216&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.6</td></tr><tr><td>Dry</td><td>B37</td><td>30</td><td>YL</td><td>32.1</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>54</td><td>4</td><td>92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.9</td><td>2.1</td><td>43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.8</td><td>4.5</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009; 150</td><td>ND</td><td>196&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;18.2</td></tr><tr><td>Dry</td><td>2B18</td><td>45</td><td>AL</td><td>28</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>37.8</td><td>6.8</td><td>86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.8</td><td>1.9</td><td>34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.1</td><td>4.9</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009; 150</td><td>ND</td><td>165&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.2</td></tr><tr><td>Dry</td><td>2B19</td><td>90</td><td>AL</td><td>24</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>34.3</td><td>2</td><td>78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.5</td><td>2.9</td><td>51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4</td><td>4.4</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009; 150</td><td>ND</td><td>226&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup><italic>EO</italic> Essential oil, <sup>b</sup><italic>Extra</italic> Extraction, <sup>c</sup><italic>min</italic> Minutes, <sup>d</sup><italic>Piper</italic> Piperitenone, <sup>e</sup><italic>BCE</italic> Bicyclosesquiphellandrene, <sup>f</sup><italic>Epi</italic> Epimastigote, <sup>g</sup><italic>IC</italic><sub><italic>50</italic></sub> Inhibitory concentration 50; <sup>h</sup><italic>SD</italic> Standard deviation, <sup>i</sup><italic>SI</italic> Selectivity index (CC<sub>50</sub>/IC<sub>50</sub>), <sup>j</sup><italic>Tryp</italic> Trypomastigote, <sup>k</sup><italic>Amas</italic> Amastigote, <sup>l</sup><italic>CC</italic><sub><italic>50</italic></sub> Cytotoxic concentration 50, <sup>m</sup><italic>AL</italic> All leaves, <sup>n</sup><italic>YL</italic> Young leaves, <sup>o</sup><italic>ND</italic> Not determined</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>In vitro trypanocidal and cytotoxic activity of Citral and Carvone chemotype <italic>L. alba</italic> essential oils (<bold>a</bold>) and their bioactive terpenes (<bold>b</bold>) on cyclic forms of <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic>. IC<sub>50</sub>: Inhibitory Concentration 50 on <italic>T. cruzi</italic>; CC<sub>50</sub>: Cytotoxic Concentration 50 on Vero Cells</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2018_2293_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par80">The best trypanocidal performance was observed in oils isolated from Citral chemotype plants, with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5, 22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4, and 74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL on Epi, Tryp, and Amas, respectively (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Among these, the two lowest IC<sub>50</sub> achieved were by A20 (9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2 and 13.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, on Epi and Tryp, respectively, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) and A23 (8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3 and 17&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, on Epi and Tryp, respectively, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). However, these oils also displayed a low selectivity, with high toxicity levels on Vero cells (A20: CC<sub>50=</sub> 66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL; A23: CC<sub>50=</sub> 51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL). Alternatively, oil A13 exhibited a significant level of anti-<italic>T. cruzi</italic> activity on the three cyclic forms (with IC<sub>50</sub> of 17&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, (SI&#x02009;=&#x02009;7); IC<sub>50</sub> 21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, (SI&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.7); and IC<sub>50</sub> 88&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL (SI&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.4), on Epi, Tryp, and Amas, respectively); high cell death percentages (CDP) (Epi&#x02009;=&#x02009;85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.7%; Tryp&#x02009;=&#x02009;100%; Amas&#x02009;=&#x02009;57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.1%; <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), at 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL; and low toxic effect on mammal cells (CC<sub>50</sub> 120&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>).</p><p id="Par81">In contrast, EOs extracted from Carvone chemotype plants showed higher mean IC<sub>50</sub> values (88&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.7, 45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.5, and&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;&#x000a0;150&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL on Epi, Tryp, and Amas, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>)), with a CDP under 60%, even at high concentrations (100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), in both Epi (mean CDP of 56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.3%) and Tryp (mean CDP of 81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.1%) forms (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Among Carvone chemotype oils, the best trypanocidal activity was demonstrated by B7 with IC<sub>50</sub> 81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, SI&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.5, and a CDP of 60.1% on Epi forms; and IC<sub>50</sub> 37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, SI&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.5, and a CDP of 84.5%, on Tryp stages (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). On <italic>T. cruzi</italic> replicative intracellular forms, none of the Carvone oils demonstrated significant activity (mean IC<sub>50</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;&#x000a0;150&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL; mean CDP 21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.4%). Nevertheless, on host cells (Vero) these EOs exhibited lower cytotoxicity (mean CC<sub>50</sub> of 200&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) than Citral oils (mean CC<sub>50</sub> of 87&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Trypanocidal activity of <italic>L. alba</italic> Terpenes</title><p id="Par82">For further studies using individual compounds, four of the major terpenes were selected from the <italic>L. alba</italic> EOs from both chemotypes, Citral (citral and (&#x02212;) caryophyllene oxide) and Carvone (D (+) limonene and S (+) carvone). Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> presents the IC<sub>50</sub> values obtained on the three studied parasitic forms and the CC<sub>50</sub> values estimated on Vero cells.<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Anti-parasitic effect on <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> of the major terpenes of Citral and Carvone chemotype <italic>L. alba</italic> essential oils</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Terpenes</th><th>Epi<sup>a</sup> IC<sub>50</sub><sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD<sup>c</sup> (&#x003bc;g/mL)</th><th>SI<sup>d</sup></th><th>Tryp<sup>e</sup> IC<sub>50</sub><sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD<sup>c</sup> (&#x003bc;g/mL)</th><th>SI<sup>d</sup></th><th>Amas<sup>h</sup> IC<sub>50</sub><sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD<sup>c</sup> (&#x003bc;g/mL)</th><th>SI<sup>d</sup></th><th>Vero CC<sub>50</sub><sup>i</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD<sup>c</sup> (&#x003bc;g/mL)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>CarOx<sup>j</sup></td><td>30&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.7</td><td>4.3</td><td>22&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.3</td><td>5.9</td><td>47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0</td><td>2.7</td><td>128&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.2</td></tr><tr><td>Limonene</td><td>42&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.5</td><td>7.1</td><td>9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.8</td><td>32.8</td><td>29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td><td>10.3</td><td>297&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.4</td></tr><tr><td>Citral</td><td>37&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.7</td><td>2.4</td><td>21&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1</td><td>4.3</td><td>49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.3</td><td>1.8</td><td>90&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.9</td></tr><tr><td>Carvone</td><td>177&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.9</td><td>1.4</td><td>124&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;8</td><td>1.9</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009; 100</td><td>ND<sup>l</sup></td><td>240&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.1</td></tr><tr><td>BNZ<sup>k</sup></td><td>17&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.9</td><td>8.2</td><td>1.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1</td><td>116.3</td><td>6.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9</td><td>22.4</td><td>139&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup><italic>Epi</italic> Epimastigote, <sup>b</sup><italic>IC</italic><sub><italic>50</italic></sub> Inhibitory concentration 50, <sup>c</sup><italic>SD</italic> Standard deviation, <sup>d</sup><italic>SI</italic> Selectivity index (CC<sub>50</sub>/IC<sub>50</sub>), <sup>g</sup><italic>Tryp</italic> Trypomastigote, <sup>h</sup><italic>Amas</italic> Amastigote, <sup>i</sup><italic>CC</italic><sub><italic>50</italic></sub> Cytotoxic concentration 50, <sup>j</sup><italic>CarOx</italic> Caryophyllene oxide, <sup>k</sup><italic>BNZ</italic> Benznidazole, <sup>l</sup><italic>ND</italic> Not determinated</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par83">Among the studied terpenes, D (+) limonene exhibited the best IC<sub>50</sub> on Tryp (IC<sub>50</sub> 9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, SI&#x02009;=&#x02009;32.8, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), and Amas (IC<sub>50</sub> 29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, SI&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.3, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) forms, (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>), with the most selective and the least toxic performance on mammal cells (CC<sub>50</sub> 297&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, and SI&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.1, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), with a CC<sub>50</sub> even lower than the reference drug (BNZ: CC<sub>50</sub> 139&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL). At the other end of the spectrum, S (+) carvone constituted the terpene with the worst trypanocidal activity on all evolutionary <italic>T. cruzi</italic> forms (Epi: IC<sub>50</sub> 177&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, and SI&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.4; Tryp: IC<sub>50</sub> 124&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, and SI&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.9; Amas: IC<sub>50</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;&#x000a0;100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). It is worth pointing out that all the terpenoid fractions, except carvone, were able to induce significant cell death on extracellular forms of the parasite at 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL (Epi: CDP&#x02009;=&#x02009;66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.9%; Tryp: CDP&#x02009;=&#x02009;90&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) with caryophyllene oxide being the terpene with the highest rate of death on Epi (78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.3%), and Tryp (98&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Terpene pharmacological interactions on <italic>T. cruzi</italic></title><p id="Par84">Because D (+) limonene demonstrated the best performance as a selective trypanocidal agent on all the evolutionary forms of <italic>T. cruzi</italic>, this monoterpene was selected as a fixed-compound of a pharmacological interaction matrix among terpenes and BNZ. This matrix was assembled taking the IC<sub>50</sub> values determined previously (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). Following the FIC value interpretation described by Azeredo and Soares, (2013) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], all the evaluated interactions were found to be synergic on both extra and intracellular forms of the parasite (except limonene with carvone, with &#x003a3;FIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.10 and 1.04, on Epi and Tryp, respectively) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> shows these pharmacological relations as isobolograms of the mean FIC of each combination. The highest synergy was exhibited by limonene/BNZ combinations (Epi: &#x003a3;FIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.44; Tryp: &#x003a3;FIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.42; Amas: &#x003a3;FIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.58) (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), with the best trypanocidal performance achieved by the 4xIC<sub>50</sub> limonene:&#x000bd;IC<sub>50</sub> BNZ mixture (4 times IC<sub>50</sub> limonene plus one half of the IC<sub>50</sub> of BNZ), which reduced by 14, 16, and 17 times the BNZ IC<sub>50</sub> on Amas, Epi, and Tryp, respectively. Despite its good performance, this combination also resulted in an increased cytotoxicity on Vero cells (&#x003a3;FIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.54). On the other hand, limonene with caryophyllene oxide represented the second-best combination by anti-parasitic efficacy (Epi &#x003a3; FIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.49; Tryp &#x003a3; FIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.45; and Amas &#x003a3; FIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.71), while offering an additional advantage of reduction of the individual cytotoxicity of each terpene on Vero cells (&#x003a3;FIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.22) (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>, Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Pharmacological interactions among terpenes derived from <italic>L. alba</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Parasitic Form</th><th>Limonene&#x02009;+&#x02009;Compound</th><th>&#x003a3;FIC<sup>f</sup> &#x003bc;g/mL&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD<sup>g</sup></th><th>Pharmacological interaction</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4">Epi<sup>a</sup></td><td>CarOx<sup>d</sup></td><td>0.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13</td><td>Synergism</td></tr><tr><td>Carvone</td><td>1.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08</td><td>Antagonism</td></tr><tr><td>Citral</td><td>0.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13</td><td>Synergism</td></tr><tr><td>BNZ<sup>e</sup></td><td>0.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13</td><td>Synergism</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Tryp<sup>b</sup></td><td>CarOx<sup>d</sup></td><td>0.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.10</td><td>Synergism</td></tr><tr><td>Carvone</td><td>1.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td><td>Antagonism</td></tr><tr><td>Citral</td><td>0.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.10</td><td>Synergism</td></tr><tr><td>BNZ<sup>e</sup></td><td>0.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.10</td><td>Synergism</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Amas<sup>c</sup></td><td>CarOx<sup>d</sup></td><td>0.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.23</td><td>Synergism</td></tr><tr><td>Carvone</td><td>ND<sup>h</sup></td><td>ND<sup>h</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Citral</td><td>0.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15</td><td>Synergism</td></tr><tr><td>BNZ<sup>e</sup></td><td>0.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13</td><td>Synergism</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Vero</td><td>CarOx<sup>d</sup></td><td>1.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.16</td><td>Antagonism</td></tr><tr><td>Carvone</td><td>1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td><td>Additive</td></tr><tr><td>Citral</td><td>1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td><td>Antagonism</td></tr><tr><td>BNZ<sup>e</sup></td><td>0.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.18</td><td>Synergism</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup><italic>Epi</italic> Epimastigote, <sup>b</sup><italic>Tryp</italic> Trypomastigote, <sup>c</sup><italic>Amas</italic> Amastigote, <sup>d</sup><italic>CarOx</italic> Caryophyllene oxide, <sup>e</sup><italic>BNZ</italic> Benznidazole, <sup>f</sup><italic>FIC</italic> Fractional inhibitory concentration, <sup>g</sup><italic>SD</italic> Standard deviation, <sup>h</sup><italic>ND</italic> Not determinated</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Pharmacological interaction isobolograms among major terpenes of the Citral and Carvone chemotype <italic>L. alba</italic> essential oils: <bold>a</bold> limonene with caryophyllene oxide; <bold>b</bold> limonene with carvone; <bold>c</bold> limonene with citral; and <bold>d</bold> limonene with Benznidazole (BNZ). The interaction tests were performed on Epimastigotes, Trypomastigotes and Amastigotes of <italic>T. cruzi</italic> and Vero cells. Dotted lines correspond to an additive effect; points below, on, and above line indicate a synergistic, additive, and antagonistic effect, respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2018_2293_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Morphological analysis on <italic>T. cruzi</italic> forms</title><p id="Par85">The morphological changes induced by the treatments studied (EOs, terpenes, or BNZ, and their combinations) were analyzed by optical and fluorescent microscopy using phase contrast, and nuclear specific (DAPI) and mitochondrial membrane potential (Mitotracker Red CMXRos [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]) stains. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, some of the tested treatments induced significant changes on parasitic morphology such as: spherical cell conformation, reduced cytoplasmic volume (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>, DIC), mitochondrial membrane potential deplection (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>, MitoTracker), and formation of a nuclear speckled/condensation pattern (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>, DAPI). In one unique finding, the caryophyllene oxide treatment also caused a flagellum to be lost. Conversely, <italic>T. cruzi</italic> cells treated with BNZ displayed cellular edema and loss of cellular membrane integrity, but with conserved mitochondrial energetic potential (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). Under the same conditions, Vero host cells did not present visible morphological alterations (data not shown).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Cell morphology changes of <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> by fluorescent and optical microscopy. <bold>a</bold> Cell morphology, mitochondrial membrane potential, nuclear and kinetoplast DNA of <italic>T. cruzi</italic> epimastigotes after treatment with essential oils, terpenes, or BNZ. <bold>b</bold> DNA fragmentation analysis by TUNEL assay on <italic>T.cruzi</italic> epimastigotes treated with terpenes. The preserved parasitic DNA was visualized with a blue HOECHST fluorescent probe (negative TUNEL) and the free DNA strands were observed in green (positive TUNEL). <sup>a</sup>DIC: Differential Interference Contrast Microscopy; <sup>b</sup>NT: No Treatment; <sup>c</sup>CarOx: caryophyllene oxide; <sup>d</sup>Limo: limonene; <sup>e</sup>BNZ: Benznidazole; <sup>f</sup>PC: Positive control: DAPI: cells stained with DAPI nuclear fluorescent stain observed in UV filter. MitoTracker: cells stained with MitoTracker Red CMXRos stain observed in an Excitation/Emission 579/599 (nm) filter. Photographs are representative of 10 observed fields</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2018_2293_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>DNA fragmentation</title><p id="Par86">A possible endonuclease activation triggered by studied compounds (oils, terpenes or their combinations) was assessed through agarose gel DNA electrophoresis and TUNEL analyses. DNA degradation was observed by band disappearance in agarose gel (data not shown) and confirmed through green fluorescence on nuclei and kinetoplasts from Epi forms treated for 48&#x000a0;h with double doses at IC<sub>50</sub> (2xIC<sub>50</sub>) of limonene, caryophyllene oxide, and the mix limonene:BNZ; with percentages of 94, 99, and 98, respectively (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). Non-significant fragmentation was observed on untreated Epi (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Phosphatidylserine externalization</title><p id="Par87">A flow cytometry analysis was carried out to determine the general mechanism of cell death. As expected, untreated Epi showed high viability rates (99.7%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>), whereas the various terpene treatments (48&#x000a0;h at 2xIC<sub>50</sub>) caused high percentages of cell death, with 95.7, 89.2, 78.4, and 95.9% for cayophyllene oxide, limonene, citral, and the combination limonene:BNZ, respectively (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0001). No treatment showed statistically significant levels of negative SYTOX + positive Annexin V (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05), except the apoptosis positive control (15&#x000a0;day-old parasite culture) (13.6%) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5f</xref>). On the other hand, all the treated cultures displayed high percentages of positive SYTOX and positive Annexin V. These results suggest a possible trigger of a late apoptosis mechanism (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Flow cytometry analysis of phosphatidylserine externalization of <italic>T. cruzi</italic> epimastigotes treated with terpenes or Benznidazole. <bold>a</bold> Negative control (untreated culture). <bold>b</bold> caryophyllene oxide; <bold>c</bold> limonene; <bold>d</bold> citral; <bold>e</bold> limonene:BNZ; and <bold>f</bold> apoptosis positive control (15&#x000a0;day-old parasite culture). The flow cytometry histograms are representative of two independent experiments</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2018_2293_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par88">In Chagas Disease, the pathogen-specific treatments &#x02013; such as BNZ &#x02013; should be prescribed for acute cases and for younger patients with little or no evidence of established cardiomyopathy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. On the other hand, recent results from global trials have questioned the benefit of these therapies in chronic patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In the case of BNZ, the drug demonstrated a significant decrease of the circulating parasite load, but no substantial effect in the prevention of the clinical decline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Therefore, most patients with advanced <italic>T. cruzi</italic> disease receive only symptomatic treatment for cardiomyopathy or digestive symptoms. This absence of an association between parasite clearance by BNZ and the clinical progression of heart disease has been ascribed to both the restricted activity of the treatment in the inflammatory and fibrotic cardiomyopathy lesions, as well as the irreversibility of this damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Thus, alternative approaches for Chagas infection management should aim to control not only the parasite load, but also all the factors associated with cardiomyopathy progression (oxidative stress and immune effectors, among others) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p><p id="Par89">Since parasitic protozoa are very sensitive to oxidative stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], the most common trypanocidal and anti-chagasic drugs like Nitroimidazoles derived (BNZ) and Nitrofurans (NFX) were developed based on their capability to induce Reactive Oxygen Species (ROS) production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. However, the clinical use of both medicines has been limited due to their high toxicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], mutagenic potential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], the severity of their side effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], and the lack of significant effects on clinical disease progression in the late stages of <italic>T. cruzi</italic> infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p><p id="Par90">In general, the development of new trypanocidal agents has been focused on the use of molecules that alter the cellular redox potential and take advantage of the scarce antioxidant defenses of the parasite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. A similar anti-protozoal effect has been described for essential oils rich in terpenes extracted from aromatic plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. In this regard, EOs derived from <italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic> showed promising results, with low IC<sub>50</sub> values against <italic>T. cruzi</italic> (15.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL for Epi and Tryp; and 5.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL for Amas) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. These trypanocidal effects were attributed to the high levels of the oxygenated monoterpene citral (a mixture of neral and geranial) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Similar outcomes were obtained with oils extracted from a Colombian (Santander) variant of <italic>L. alba</italic> (Citral chemotype), which were rich in such terpenes as citral, geraniol, timol, and caryophyllene oxide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p><p id="Par91">In this work, we tested the trypanocidal and cytotoxic activity of 12 EOs, derived from two different plant chemotypes (Citral and Carvone) of <italic>L. alba,</italic> which were produced under controlled conditions of growth (geographic location, cultivation environment, and soil), plant parameters (age and part), material state (fresh or dry) and extraction conditions (time). These standardized procedures were prepared taking into consideration the recognized high phenotypical plasticity of the plant in response to genetic, environmental, and production parameters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], which can induce significant variations in its EO constituents, as well as in their biological activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].</p><p id="Par92">In this regard, our results also confirmed significant differences in the major chemical compounds (terpenes), and trypanocidal activity of the <italic>L. alba</italic> oils produced under varying parameters (Tables <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, and Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). While mixtures rich in citral and caryophyllene oxide (Citral chemotype EOs) achieved good performance on extracellular forms of <italic>T. cruzi</italic> (mean IC<sub>50</sub> values of 13.6 and 21.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL on Epi and Tryp, respectively) (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>); EOs of the same plant but rich in carvone and limonene (Carvone chemotype), displayed poor inhibitory results (mean IC<sub>50</sub> values of 88.2 and 44.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL for Epi and Tryp, respectively) (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Individual assays with a solution of citral consistently found that this compound caused an efficient arrest of the parasite&#x02019;s growth with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 37.2 and 20.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL on Epi and Tryp, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><p id="Par93">With respect to citral, several studies on cancer and immune cell line models have demonstrated its interesting biological properties. As an anti-tumoral, this monoterpene exhibited significant anti-proliferative effects, in vitro and in vivo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] and this cell growth inhibition was ascribed to the induction of mitochondrial apoptosis pathways (through p53 activation triggered by an ROS increase) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. In addition, citral has also been described as anti-inflammatory agent. In lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-stimulated macrophages, this terpene was found to suppress the expression of pro-inflammatory markers such as NLRP2 (NLR Family Pyrin Domain Containing 2), Interleukin (IL) 6 and IL-1&#x003b2; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], Tumoral Necrosis Factor (TNF) &#x003b1; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>], as well as to activate the Peroxisome Proliferator-Activated Receptor (PPAR) &#x003b3; dependent-Cyclooxygenase 2 (COX2) promotor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. It is worth mentioning that over a range of different cells, the expression of COX2 is regulated in a variety of ways; playing an important role in tumoral genesis, inflammation, development, and circulatory homeostasis. In these activated macrophages, citral also blocks the genic expression of the LPS-induced Nitric Oxide Synthase (iNOS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>] and, consequently, the production of Nitric Oxide (NO). It is thought that this inhibition could suppress transcriptional activation and the translocation of the nuclear factor-kappa B (NF-&#x00199;B). These results suggest that citral is an anti-inflammatory agent whose effects could be associated with NF-&#x00199;B suppression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], indicating that this compound may be a promising candidate for the treatment of inflammatory conditions like Chagas Disease.</p><p id="Par94">Similarly, anticancer and anti-inflammatory properties have also been attributed to caryophyllene oxide, another major and bioactive constituent of Citral chemotype <italic>L. alba</italic> EOs. On human prostate and breast cancer cells, this sesquiterpene isolated from the EOs of medicinal plants such as guava (<italic>Psidium guajava</italic>), oregano (<italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> L.), cinammon (<italic>Cinnamomum spp</italic>.), clove (<italic>Eugenia caryophyllata</italic>), and black pepper (<italic>Piper nigrum L</italic>.), inhibited constitutive survival pathways (PI3K/AKT/mTOR/S6&#x000a0;K1) and ROS-dependent MAPK activation during tumorigenesis; triggering apoptosis on tumoral lineages and preventing inflammation, angiogenesis, and metastasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Furthermore, on stimulated primary splenocytes, caryophyllene oxide significantly increases the Th2/Th1 coefficient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p id="Par95">In our work, caryophyllene oxide was correlated with a trypanocidal effect, being found to be one of the major components of the most trypanocidal EOs studied: A23 and A20 (<italic>L. alba</italic> citral chemotype). Similarly, Cheikh Ali et al.<italic>,</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], found a minimal lethal concentration of 0.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL for EOs extracted from <italic>Aframomum sceptrum</italic> on cyclic forms of <italic>T. brucei</italic>; this trypanocidal action being associated with the presence of caryophyllene oxide. In the present study, this compound demonstrated a significant anti-proliferative effect against <italic>T. cruzi</italic> Epi (IC<sub>50</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;29.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), Tryp (IC<sub>50</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;21.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), and Amas (IC<sub>50</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;47.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><p id="Par96">Another major <italic>L. alba</italic> terpene studied herein was limonene. This monoterpene is one of the main components of the Carvone chemotype oils. Due its beneficial pharmacological characteristics such as: low toxicity (used as food additive for decades) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>], high bioavailability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], and selective anti-tumoral effect on a variety of cancer cell lines (leukemia, lymphoma, prostate, hepatic, colorectal, pancreatic, gastric, and breast, among others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]); several research efforts have been undertaken with respect to this monoterpene. Interestingly, on a prostate cancer model, limonene caused apoptotic programmed cell death by the induction of a selective oxidative stress on tumoral cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. As for protozoa, cancer cells are highly vulnerable to cell death induced by pro-oxidant agents (such as limonene) due their high metabolism and their deficient antioxidant mechanisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. In this study, limonene was the best trypanocidal and most selective terpene with the lowest inhibitory doses (IC<sub>50</sub> of 9.0, 28.7, and 41.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL on Tryp, Amas, and Epi, respectively). However, this good performance was not replicated when <italic>T. cruzi</italic> forms were treated with oils rich in carvone and limonene (<italic>L. alba</italic> Carvone chemotype EOs displayed higher IC<sub>50</sub> levels on Epi&#x02009;=&#x02009;88.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, Tryp&#x02009;=&#x02009;44.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, and Amas &#x0003e;&#x02009;150&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). Interestingly, carvone was the least effective trypanocidal terpene, with the lowest values of cell death percentage induction and highest IC<sub>50</sub> results (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). These results were associated with the strong antioxidant capability previously ascribed to this monoterpene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Accordingly, a possible antagonism seems likely between limonene and carvone (which was present in the oil mixture in levels close to 42%) (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Pharmacological interaction tests confirmed that the presence of carvone in the <italic>L. alba</italic> Carvone chemotype oils, impaired the limonene&#x02019;s trypanocidal performance on <italic>T. cruzi</italic> Tryp (&#x003a3;CIF: 1.04&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) and Epi (&#x003a3;CIF: 1.10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) forms (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). In further assays, limonene presented a synergistic pharmacological interaction with the other bioactive <italic>L. alba</italic> terpenes (citral and caryophyllene oxide), and with BNZ, exhibiting &#x003a3;FIC values &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL on the three parasite forms analyzed (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). In combination with BNZ, limonene caused a significant decrease of the BNZ-IC<sub>50</sub>, by 14, 16, and 17 times on Amas, Epi, and Tryp, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).</p><p id="Par97">These positive interactions could have been due to the simultaneal action of these compounds on diverse and additive mechanisms that lead to cell death in susceptible lineages. Such mechanisms may include: a) polymerization microtubules disruption (citral) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]; b) endoplasmic reticulum stress induction (citral) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]; c) PIP3/AKT survival pathway inhibition (limonene, citral, and caryophyllene oxide) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]; d) oxidative stress stimulation (limonene, citral, and caryophyllene oxide) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]; and e) apoptosis by caspases activation (citral and limonene) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>], among others.</p><p id="Par98">It is important to add that the parasite cells treated for 48&#x000a0;h with some of the studied compounds (A23 oil, citral, caryophyllene oxide, limonene, and the mixture of limonene and BNZ) evidenced typical characteristics of apoptosis, such as cytoplasmic blebbing, cell shrinkage, flagellum absence, loss of mitochondrial membrane potential, condensation of the nuclear chromatin, and DNA fragmentation (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). Also, the treatment of parasites with caryophyllene oxide or limonene (alone, in combination, or with BNZ) led to positive results in TUNEL assays (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). Correspondingly, an impairment of membrane potential (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) and the externalization of phosphatidylserine (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) were observed on <italic>T. cruzi</italic> cells treated with citral, limonene, and caryophyllene oxide. These results suggest a possible activation of an early apoptosis mechanism that rapidly progresses to late apoptosis (positive SYTOX plus positive Annexin V) accompanied by DNA fragmentation. In trypanosomatids like <italic>Leishmania donovani, T. brucei</italic>, and <italic>T. cruzi,</italic> these same characteristics have been reported in parasites suffering calcium imbalance and oxidative stress (by ROS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>], mitochondrial enzyme knockdown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>], or treatment with sterols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. In these studies, the previously mentioned features were associated with a possible programmed cell death such as apoptosis or autophagy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>].</p><p id="Par99">In an illness with a complex pathogenesis like Chagas Disease (which involves the parasitic persistence that triggers and sustains an anti-inflammatory immune response), the use of synergic drugs (like limonene/caryophyllene oxide) with several biological advantages (significant trypanocidal activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], low toxicity on mammal tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]; and anti-genotoxic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>], chemoprotective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], and anti-inflammatory activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]) could be an interesting platform for the development of an adjuvant therapy that enhances the therapeutic effects of the conventional treatments, principally in advanced stage of the infection (probably improving trypanocidal action, reducing therapeutic doses, increasing tolerance, or retarding resistance development) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par100">In this work, a range of growth, plant, and extraction parameters were found to significantly influence the chemical composition and trypanocidal activity of essential oils isolated from <italic>L. alba</italic> Citral and Carvone chemotypes. <italic>L. alba</italic> Citral chemotype oils, extracted under known and controlled conditions, presented significant trypanocidal activity on three cyclic <italic>T. cruzi</italic> forms: epimastigotes, trypomastigotes, and amastigotes. Assays using pure solutions of the main terpenes that constitute <italic>L. alba</italic> EOs, confirmed an association among parasitological activity and the presence of citral and caryophyllene oxide. Tests using EOs extracted from Carvone chemotype (rich in carvone and limonene), and their most important components, established an antagonistic relationship between carvone and limonene in their trypanocidal performance. Nevertheless, in this study, the best anti-<italic>T. cruzi</italic>, and most selective, activity was achieved by limonene. Citral, caryophyllene oxide, and limonene exhibited the induction of a possible apoptotic-like phenotype. In the synergistic interaction tests, limonene also improved the trypanocidal performance of citral, caryophyllene oxide, and even BNZ, on the three parasitic forms studied. The best synergic terpene activity was displayed by the limonene and caryophyllene oxide combination. These results should be confirmed by further pre-clinical studies and could be of interest for the development of alternative and adjuvant treatments improving the tolerance and parasitological efficacy, and broadening the spectrum of the effects, of the current conventional therapies for late phases of Chagas Disease. In such research, <italic>L. alba</italic> EOs represent a renewable source for commercial exploitation of these terpenes.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>&#x003a3;FIC</term><def><p id="Par5">Sum FIC</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AL</term><def><p id="Par6">All Leaves</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Amas</term><def><p id="Par7">Amastigote</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ANOVA</term><def><p id="Par8">Analysis of variance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BCE</term><def><p id="Par9">Bicyclosesquiphellandrene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BNZ</term><def><p id="Par10">Benznidazole</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CarOx</term><def><p id="Par11">Caryophyllene oxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Caryop</term><def><p id="Par12">Caryophyllene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CC<sub>50</sub></term><def><p id="Par13">Cytotoxic Concentration 50</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CDP</term><def><p id="Par14">Cell death percentages</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CENIVAM</term><def><p id="Par15">National Research Center for Agroindustrialization of Aromatic Medical and Tropical Species</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>COX2</term><def><p id="Par16">Cyclooxygenase 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DAPI</term><def><p id="Par17">4&#x02032;,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMEM</term><def><p id="Par18">Dulbecco&#x02019;s Modified Eagle&#x02019;s Medium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMSO</term><def><p id="Par19">Dimethyl sulfoxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DNA</term><def><p id="Par20">Deoxyribonucleic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EO</term><def><p id="Par21">Essential oil</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Epi</term><def><p id="Par22">Epimastigotes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FBS<sub>i</sub></term><def><p id="Par23">Inactivated Fetal Bovine Serum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FIC</term><def><p id="Par24">Fractional Inhibitory Concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GC-MS</term><def><p id="Par25">Gas chromatography coupled mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IC<sub>50</sub></term><def><p id="Par26">Inhibitory Concentration 50</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IL</term><def><p id="Par27">Interleukin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Inf</term><def><p id="Par28">Inflorescences</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>iNOS</term><def><p id="Par29">Induced Nitric Oxide Synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>L. alba</italic></term><def><p id="Par30">
<italic>Lippia alba</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LIT</term><def><p id="Par31">Liver Infusion Tryptose</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LPS</term><def><p id="Par32">Lipopolysaccharide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Min</term><def><p id="Par33">Minutes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ML</term><def><p id="Par34">Mature leaves</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>mm</term><def><p id="Par35">Millimeter</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MWHD</term><def><p id="Par36">Microwave-Assisted Hydrodistillation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ND</term><def><p id="Par37">Not determined</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NF-&#x00199;B</term><def><p id="Par38">Nuclear factor-kappa B</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NFX</term><def><p id="Par39">Nifurtimox</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NLRP2</term><def><p id="Par40">NLR Family Pyrin Domain Containing 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>nm</term><def><p id="Par41">Nanometer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NO</term><def><p id="Par42">Nitric Oxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NTD</term><def><p id="Par43">Neglected Tropical Disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OD</term><def><p id="Par44">Optical Density</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PBS</term><def><p id="Par45">Phosphate Buffered Saline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Piper</term><def><p id="Par46">Piperitenone</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PPAR</term><def><p id="Par47">Peroxisome Proliferator-Activated Receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ROS</term><def><p id="Par48">Reactive species of oxygen</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RPMI</term><def><p id="Par49">Roswell Park Memorial Institute</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p id="Par50">Standard deviation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SI</term><def><p id="Par51">Selectivity index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>T. brucei</italic></term><def><p id="Par52">
<italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>T. cruzi</italic></term><def><p id="Par53">
<italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TDC</term><def><p id="Par54">Trypomastigotes Derived from Cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TdT</term><def><p id="Par55">Terminal desoxynucleotidyl Transferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TNF</term><def><p id="Par56">Tumor Necrosis Factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Tryp</term><def><p id="Par57">Trypomastigote</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UTP</term><def><p id="Par58">Uridine Triphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>YL</term><def><p id="Par59">Young leaves</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This study was supported by the Vicerrector&#x000ed;a de Investigaciones &#x02013; Universidad de Santander, under grant 005-14; and the Vicerrector&#x000ed;a de Investigaci&#x000f3;n y Extensi&#x000f3;n &#x02013; Universidad Industrial de Santander, under grant 5658. The authors would like to express their appreciation to Dr. Marcos L&#x000f3;pez Casillas and to Dr. Wendy Grey Nieto P&#x000e9;rez for their support in flow cytometry assays; to Dr. Yamile Leonor Vargas for Benznidazole purification, and to Dr. Camilo Dur&#x000e1;n, Qm. Carlos Ram&#x000ed;rez, and Qm. Yaride P&#x000e9;rez for their support during the collection and characterization of EO samples. We are grateful to Mr. Emile Blanchette for assistance in the proofreading of this study.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par101">This research was supported by the Vicerrector&#x000ed;a de Investigaciones &#x02013; Universidad de Santander, under grant 005&#x02013;14; and the Vicerrector&#x000ed;a de Investigaci&#x000f3;n y Extensi&#x000f3;n &#x02013; Universidad Industrial de Santander, under grant 5658.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par102">There are no restrictions to the availability of any materials and data. The raw data are available to other researchers upon request.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>LTG conceived the study, designed all the experiments, and reviewed all the results and findings. EMM performed and analyzed all the trypanocidal, cytotoxic, and cell death assays, carried out data collection and analysis, and wrote the manuscript. EES collected the plants, and extracted and chemically characterized the essential oils. SML participated in the trypanocidal, cytotoxic, and synergistic tests. All authors read, revised, and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par103">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par104">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par105">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par106">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group><source>Investing to Overcome the Global Impact of Neglected Tropical Diseases: 3<sup>rd</sup> WHO Rep Neglect Trop D</source><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Devleesschauwer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>De Noya</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>ON</given-names></name><name><surname>Torgerson</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Trypanosoma cruzi:</italic> time for international recognition as a foodborne parasite</article-title><source>PLoS Neglect Trop D</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e0004656</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumonteil</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Heffernan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottazzi</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innovation for the &#x02018;bottom 100 million&#x02019;: eliminating neglected tropical diseases in the Americas</article-title><source>Hot topics in infection and immunity in children IX advances in experimental medicine and biology</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>Springer</publisher-loc><publisher-name>New York</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cruz Berm&#x000fa;dez</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno Collazos</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroprevalencia de tamizaje de Chagas y factores asociados a coinfecci&#x000f3;n en un banco de sangre de Colombia durante 2006-2011</article-title><source>Rev Med Risaralda</source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coura</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The main sceneries of Chagas disease transmission. The vectors, blood and oral transmissions-a comprehensive review</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><year>2015</year><volume>110</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0074-0276140362</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25466622?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25466622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarleton</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential new clinical therapies for Chagas disease</article-title><source>Expert Rev Clin Pharmacol</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/17512433.2014.909282</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24716790?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24716790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bern</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chagas&#x02019; disease</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>373</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>456</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1410150</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26222561?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26222561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morillo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Marin-Neto</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Avezum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sosa-Estani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rassi</surname><given-names>A</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Rosas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Guhl</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Randomized trial of benznidazole for chronic Chagas&#x02019; cardiomyopathy</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>373</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>1295</fpage><lpage>1306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1507574</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26323937?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26323937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rassi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>De Rezende</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>American trypanosomiasis (Chagas disease)</article-title><source>Infect Dis Clin N Am</source><year>2012</year><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idc.2012.03.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonney</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Engman</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autoimmune pathogenesis of Chagas heart disease: looking back, looking ahead</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>2015</year><volume>185</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1537</fpage><lpage>1547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajpath.2014.12.023</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25857229?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25857229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rassi</surname><given-names>A</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rassi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic Chagas cardiomyopathy: a review of the main pathogenic mechanisms and the efficacy of aetiological treatment following the Benznidazole evaluation for interrupting Trypanosomiasis (BENEFIT) trial</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><year>2017</year><volume>112</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0074-02760160334</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28225900?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28225900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Romanha</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Biavatti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The potential of secondary metabolites from plants as drugs or leads against protozoan neglected diseases-part II</article-title><source>Curr Med Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>2176</fpage><lpage>2228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/092986712800229087</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22414104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22414104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Snafi</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiparasitic effects of medicinal plants (part 1)-a review</article-title><source>IOSR PHR</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raut</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Karuppayil</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A status review on the medicinal properties of essential oils</article-title><source>Ind Crop Prod J</source><year>2014</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2014.05.055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>De Albuquerque Aires</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Higino</surname><given-names>TMM</given-names></name><name><surname>De Medeiros</surname><given-names>MDGF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cit&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>AMDGL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>JAD</given-names></name><name><surname>De Figueiredo</surname><given-names>RCBQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trypanocidal and cytotoxic activities of essential oils from medicinal plants of northeast of Brazil</article-title><source>Exp Parasitol</source><year>2012</year><volume>132</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exppara.2012.06.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22771867?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22771867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Snafi</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiparasitic, antiprotozoal, molluscicidal and insecticidal activity of medicinal plants (part 2)&#x02013;plant based review</article-title><source>Sch Acad J Pharm</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>207</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Guimar&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>LGL</given-names></name><name><surname>Freire</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-proliferative effect of the essential oil of <italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic> (DC) Stapf (lemongrass) on intracellular amastigotes, bloodstream trypomastigotes and culture epimastigotes of <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> (Protozoa: Kinetoplastida)</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><year>2007</year><volume>134</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1649</fpage><lpage>1656</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182007002958</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17686189?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17686189</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheikh Ali</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Adiko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouttier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bories</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Okpekon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Poupon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Champy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Composition, and antimicrobial and remarkable antiprotozoal activities of the essential oil of rhizomes of <italic>Aframomum sceptrum K. Schum</italic>. (Zingiberaceae)</article-title><source>Chem Biodivers</source><year>2011</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>658</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbdv.201000216</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21480511?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21480511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dos Santos</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meira</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Guimarhes</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new source of (R)-limonene and rotundifolone from leaves of <italic>Lippia pedunculosa</italic> (verbenaceae) and their trypanocidal properties</article-title><source>Nat Prod Commun</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>739</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25115066?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25115066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villamizar</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>MDG</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Linalool, a Piper aduncum essential oil component, has selective activity against <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> trypomastigote forms at 4&#x000b0; C</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><year>2017</year><volume>112</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0074-02760160361</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28177047?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28177047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stashenko</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dur&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>C&#x000f3;rdoba</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Caballero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estudio comparativo de la composici&#x000f3;n qu&#x000ed;mica y la actividad antioxidante de los aceites esenciales de algunas plantas del g&#x000e9;nero <italic>Lippia</italic> (Verbenaceae) cultivadas en Colombia</article-title><source>Rev Acad Colomb Ci Exact F&#x000ed;s Nat</source><year>2014</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18257/raccefyn.156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ku</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory effects of 27 selected terpenoid compounds tested through modulating Th1/Th2 cytokine secretion profiles using murine primary splenocytes</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2013</year><volume>141</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1104</fpage><lpage>1113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2013.04.044</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23790892?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23790892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bai J, Zheng Y, Wang G, Liu P. Protective effect of D-limonene against oxidative stress-induced cell damage in human lens epithelial cells via the p38 pathway. Oxidative Med Cell Longev. 2015;2016:1&#x02013;12.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>LKP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory activity of neral and geranial isolated from fruits of <italic>Litsea cubeba</italic> Lour</article-title><source>J Funct Foods</source><year>2015</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jff.2015.09.034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>&#x000c9;M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stashenko</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Arteaga</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential anti-proliferative effect on K562 leukemia cells of <italic>Lippia alba</italic> (Verbenaceae) essential oils produced under diverse growing, collection and extraction conditions</article-title><source>Ind Crop Prod J</source><year>2017</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2016.11.057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hennebelle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahpaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailleul</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnopharmacology of Lippia alba</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2008</year><volume>116</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2007.11.044</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18207682?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18207682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di Stasi</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalhaes</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Queiroz-Junior</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tien</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakinami</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants popularly used in the Brazilian tropical Atlantic Forest</article-title><source>Fitoterapia</source><year>2002</year><volume>73</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0367-326X(01)00362-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11864767?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11864767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>EDPP</given-names></name><name><surname>Amorozo</surname><given-names>MCDM</given-names></name><name><surname>Furlan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conhecimento popular sobre plantas medicinais em comunidades rurais de mata atl&#x000e2;ntica&#x02013;Itacar&#x000e9;, BA</article-title><source>Brasil Acta bot bras</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-33062006000400001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toscano</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uso tradicional de plantas medicinales en la vereda San Isidro, municipio de San Jos&#x000e9; de Pare-Boyac&#x000e1;: un estudio preliminar usando t&#x000e9;cnicas cuantitativas</article-title><source>Acta biol Colomb</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1137</fpage><lpage>1146</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Milena Leal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Stashenko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and antiprotozoal activities of Colombian <italic>Lippia spp</italic> essential oils and their major components</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><year>2010</year><volume>105</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0074-02762010000200013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20428679?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20428679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azeredo</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combination of the essential oil constituents citral, eugenol and thymol enhance their inhibitory effect on <italic>Crithidia fasciculata</italic> and <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> growth</article-title><source>Rev Bras Farmacogn</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>762</fpage><lpage>768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-695X2013000500007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Polanco-Hern&#x000e1;ndez G, Escalante-Erosa F, Garc&#x000ed;a-Sosa K, Rosado ME, Guzm&#x000e1;n-Mar&#x000ed;n E, Acosta-Viana KY, Gim&#x000e9;nez-Turba A, Salamanca E, Pe&#x000f1;a-Rodr&#x000ed;guez LM. Synergistic effect of lupenone and caryophyllene oxide against <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic>. J Evid Based Complementary Altern Med. 2013;2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Adams R. Identification of essential oil components by gas chromatography / mass spectrometry. fourth ed. Illinois: Carol Stream; 2007. p. 804.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fivelman</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name><name><surname>Adagu</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Warhurst</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modified fixed-ratio isobologram method for studying <italic>in vitro</italic> interactions between atovaquone and proguanil or dihydroartemisinin against drug-resistant strains of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2004</year><volume>48</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>4097</fpage><lpage>4102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.48.11.4097-4102.2004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15504827?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15504827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pendergrass</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Poot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of MitoTracker green&#x02122; and CMXrosamine to measure changes in mitochondrial membrane potentials in living cells and tissues</article-title><source>Cytom Part A</source><year>2004</year><volume>61</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cyto.a.20033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urbina</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent clinical trials for the etiological treatment of chronic Chagas disease: advances, challenges and perspectives</article-title><source>J Eukariot Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>62</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jeu.12184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Amsterdam</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The epidemiology, clinical manifestations, and management of chagas heart disease</article-title><source>Clin Cardiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>38</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>569</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/clc.22421</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25993972?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25993972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Viotti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>De Noya</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Araujo-Jorge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Grijalva</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guhl</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Torrico</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards a paradigm shift in the treatment of chronic Chagas disease</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2014</year><volume>58</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01662-13</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24247135?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24247135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turrens</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress and antioxidant defenses: a target for the treatment of diseases caused by parasitic protozoa</article-title><source>Mol Asp Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mam.2004.02.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trypanocidal drugs: mechanisms, resistance and new targets</article-title><source>Expert Rev Mol Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e31</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1462399409001252</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19863838?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19863838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvador</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Montalva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trevi&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Serre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sao Avil&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Almirante</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxic profile of benznidazole in patients with chronic Chagas disease: risk factors and comparison of the product from two different manufacturers</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2015</year><volume>59</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>6125</fpage><lpage>6131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.04660-14</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26195525?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26195525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajao</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Furtado</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Passos Silva</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Schamber Reis</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unveiling Benznidazole's mechanism of action through overexpression of DNA repair proteins in <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic></article-title><source>Environ Mol Mutagen</source><year>2014</year><volume>55</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/em.21839</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24347026?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24347026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kpoviessi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Agbani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gbaguidi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kpadonou-Kpoviessi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinsin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Quetin-Leclercq</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition, cytotoxicity and in vitro antitrypanosomal and antiplasmodial activity of the essential oils of four <italic>Cymbopogon</italic> species from Benin</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2014</year><volume>151</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>652</fpage><lpage>659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2013.11.027</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24269775?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24269775</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Malheiro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucchese</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geographical origin and drying methodology may affect the essential oil of <italic>Lippia alba</italic> (mill) NE Brown</article-title><source>Ind Crop Prod</source><year>2012</year><volume>37</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2011.12.029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pattnaik</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Subudhi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Felder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terpenoids from <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> (ginger) induce apoptosis in endometrial cancer cells through the activation of p53</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e53178</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053178</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23300887?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23300887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Krup</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabinski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ofir</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Citral is a new inducer of caspase-3 in tumor cell lines</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>71</volume><issue>05</issue><fpage>484</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2005-864146</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15931590?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15931590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Patankar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formulation, characterization, and antitumor properties of trans-and cis-citral in the 4T1 breast cancer xenograft mouse model</article-title><source>Pharm Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>32</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2548</fpage><lpage>2558</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25673043?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25673043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mesa-Arango</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Montiel-Ramos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zapata</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dur&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Betancur-Galvis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stashenko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Citral and carvone chemotypes from the essential oils of Colombian <italic>Lippia alba</italic> (mill.) NE Brown: composition, cytotoxicity and antifungal activity</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><year>2009</year><volume>104</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>878</fpage><lpage>884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0074-02762009000600010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19876560?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19876560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Paula</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Luperini</surname><given-names>BCO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachiega</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>De Castro Marcondes</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sforcin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvadori</surname><given-names>DMF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Citral and eugenol modulate DNA damage and pro-inflammatory mediator genes in murine peritoneal macrophages</article-title><source>Mol Biol Rep</source><year>2014</year><volume>41</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>7043</fpage><lpage>7051</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11033-014-3657-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25103019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katsukawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakata</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Takizawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Citral, a component of lemongrass oil, activates PPAR&#x003b1; and &#x003b3; and suppresses COX-2 expression</article-title><source>BBA-Mol Cell Biol Lipid</source><year>2010</year><volume>1801</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1214</fpage><lpage>1220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbalip.2010.07.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Noh</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuk</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitory effect of citral on NO production by suppression of iNOS expression and NF-&#x003ba;B activation in RAW264. 7 cells</article-title><source>Arch Pharm Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12272-001-1162-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18409048?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18409048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sethi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x003b2;-Caryophyllene oxide inhibits growth and induces apoptosis through the suppression of PI3K/AKT/mTOR/S6K1 pathways and ROS-mediated MAPKs activation</article-title><source>Cancer Lett</source><year>2011</year><volume>312</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.canlet.2011.08.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21924548?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21924548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>D-limonene: safety and clinical applications</article-title><source>Altern Med Rev</source><year>2007</year><volume>12</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>259</fpage><?supplied-pmid 18072821?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18072821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiu-zhen</surname><given-names>WLZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth inhibition effects of D-limonene on human gastric carcinoma MGC803 cells</article-title><source>Life Sci Instrum</source><year>2009</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>012</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>D-limonene: an emerging antineoplastic agent</article-title><source>Hum Exp Toxicol</source><year>2013</year><volume>32</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1228</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0960327113489053</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23716733?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23716733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human breast tissue disposition and bioactivity of limonene in women with early-stage breast cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Prev Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1940-6207.CAPR-12-0452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishayee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>D-limonene sensitizes docetaxel-induced cytotoxicity in human prostate cancer cells: generation of reactive oxygen species and induction of apoptosis</article-title><source>J Carcinog</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>9</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1477-3163.51368</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19465777?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19465777</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trachootham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Demizu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelicano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selective killing of oncogenically transformed cells through a ROS-mediated mechanism by &#x003b2;-phenylethyl isothiocyanate</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2006.08.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16959615?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16959615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stashenko</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaramillo</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of different extraction methods for the analysis of volatile secondary metabolites of <italic>Lippia alba</italic> (mill.) NE Brown, grown in Colombia, and evaluation of its <italic>in vitro</italic> antioxidant activity</article-title><source>J Chromatogr A</source><year>2004</year><volume>1025</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chroma.2003.10.058</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14753676?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14753676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaimovitsh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Altshuler</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Belausov</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu Abied</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relative effect of citral on mitotic microtubules in wheat roots and BY2 cells</article-title><source>Plant Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>14</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1438-8677.2011.00511.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22039835?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22039835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of apoptosis by D-limonene is mediated by inactivation of Akt in LS174T human colon cancer cells</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/or.2012.2093</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23117412?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23117412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The in vitro study of apoptosis in NB4 cell induced by citral</article-title><source>Cytotechnology</source><year>2013</year><volume>65</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10616-012-9453-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22573288?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22573288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Felder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fass</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Czarnecki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Patankar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The monoterpene, citral, increases intracellular oxygen radicals and inhibits cancer cell proliferation by inducing apoptosis and endoplasmic reticulum stress</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>615</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>19106</fpage><lpage>14404</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Majumder</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reactive oxygen species and imbalance of calcium homeostasis contributes to curcumin induced programmed cell death in <italic>Leishmania donovani</italic></article-title><source>Apoptosis</source><year>2008</year><volume>13</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>867</fpage><lpage>882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10495-008-0224-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18506627?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18506627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Leite</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfonzo</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiemann</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> tryptophanyl-tRNA synthetases silencing by RNA interference</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><year>2007</year><volume>102</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0074-02762007000600016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17924007?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17924007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menna-Barreto</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Salom&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dantas</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Santa-Rita</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>De Castro</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Different cell death pathways induced by drugs in <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic>: an ultrastructural study</article-title><source>Micron</source><year>2009</year><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micron.2008.08.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18849169?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18849169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Paredes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sosa</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Galanti</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural programmed cell death in <italic>T. cruzi</italic> epimastigotes maintained in axenic cultures</article-title><source>J Cell Biochem</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>688</fpage><lpage>698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcb.21864</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18668509?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18668509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stashenko</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and antigenotoxic properties of <italic>Lippia alba</italic> essential oils</article-title><source>Genet Biol Mol</source><year>2011</year><volume>34</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1415-47572011005000030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Theoretical basis, experimental design, and computerized simulation of synergism and antagonism in drug combination studies</article-title><source>Pharmacol Rev</source><year>2006</year><volume>58</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/pr.58.3.10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16968952?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968952</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>