<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><?origin nihpa?><?iso-abbr Nat. Chem. Biol.?><?submitter-system nihms?><?submitter-canonical-name Nature Publishing Group?><?submitter-canonical-id NATURE-STRUCTUR?><?submitter-userid 8068858?><?submitter-authority myNCBI?><?submitter-login nature-structure?><?submitter-name Nature Publishing Group?><?domain nihpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101231976</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">32624</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Chem Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat. Chem. Biol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature chemical biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1552-4450</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-4469</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6245668</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30327559</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41589-018-0132-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">nihpa1502614</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Enzyme promiscuity drives branched-chain fatty acid synthesis in adipose tissues</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>Martina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>Courtney R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>Lindsay S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Yujung Michelle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCarville</surname><given-names>Justin L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez-Gurmaches</surname><given-names>Joan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meurs</surname><given-names>Noah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gengatharan</surname><given-names>Jivani M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hover</surname><given-names>Justin D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>Susan A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ciaraldi</surname><given-names>Theodore P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guertin</surname><given-names>David A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cabrales</surname><given-names>Pedro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ayres</surname><given-names>Janelle S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>Daniel K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Loomba</surname><given-names>Rohit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Metallo</surname><given-names>Christian M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">12</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A13">13</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Bioengineering, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, CA 92093, USA</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Departments of Chemistry, Molecular and Cell Biology, and Nutritional Science and Toxicology, University of California, Berkeley, Berkeley, CA 94720, USA</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Nomis Center for Immunobiology and Microbial Pathogenesis, The Salk Institute for Biological Studies, La Jolla, CA 92037, USA</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Division of Biological Sciences, University of California at San Diego, La Jolla, CA 92093, USA.</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Division of Endocrinology, Division of Developmental Biology, Cincinnati Children&#x02019;s Hospital Research Foundation.</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department of Pediatrics, University of Cincinnati College of Medicine, Cincinnati, OH 45209, USA.</aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Division of Pediatric Endocrinology, Department of Pediatrics, University of California at San Diego, La Jolla, CA 92093, USA.</aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label>VA San Diego Healthcare System, 3500 La Jolla Village Drive, San Diego, CA 92161, USA</aff><aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Division of Endocrinology &#x00026; Metabolism, Department of Medicine, University of California at San Diego, La Jolla, CA 92093, USA.</aff><aff id="A10"><label>10</label>Program in Molecular Medicine, University of Massachusetts Medical School, Worcester, MA 01605, USA</aff><aff id="A11"><label>11</label>NAFLD Research Center, Division of Gastroenterology, Department of Medicine, University of California at San Diego, La Jolla, CA 92093, USA.</aff><aff id="A12"><label>12</label>Moores Cancer Center, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, CA 92093, USA</aff><aff id="A13"><label>13</label>Diabetes Research Center, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, CA 92093, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Prof. Christian M. Metallo, Department of Bioengineering, University of California, San Diego, 9500 Gilman Dr. #0412, PFBH 204, 92093, La Jolla, CA USA, <email>cmetallo@ucsd.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>6</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1021</fpage><lpage>1031</lpage><!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1038/s41589-018-0132-2--><permissions><license><license-p>Users may view, print, copy, and download text and data-mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</uri></license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ABS1"><title>Summary</title><p id="P1">Fatty acid synthase (FASN) predominantly generates straight-chain fatty acids using acetyl-CoA as the initiating substrate. However, monomethyl branched-chain fatty acids (mmBCFAs) are also present in mammals but thought to be primarily diet-derived. Here we demonstrate that mmBCFAs are <italic>de novo</italic> synthesized via mitochondrial BCAA catabolism, exported to the cytosol by adipose-specific expression of carnitine acetyltransferase (CrAT), and elongated by FASN. Brown fat exhibits the highest BCAA catabolic and mmBCFA synthesis fluxes, whereas these lipids are largely absent from liver and brain. mmBCFA synthesis is also sustained in the absence of microbiota. We identify hypoxia as a potent suppressor of BCAA catabolism that decreases mmBCFA synthesis in obese adipose tissue, such that mmBCFAs are significantly decreased in obese animals. These results identify adipose tissue mmBCFA synthesis as a novel link between BCAA metabolism and lipogenesis, highlighting roles for CrAT and FASN promiscuity that influence acyl-chain diversity in the lipidome.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Branched-chain amino acids</kwd><kwd><italic>de novo</italic> lipogenesis</kwd><kwd>brown adipocytes</kwd><kwd>white adipocytes</kwd><kwd>metabolic flux analysis</kwd><kwd>branched-chain fatty acids</kwd><kwd>odd-chain fatty acids</kwd><kwd>fatty acid synthase</kwd><kwd>obesity</kwd><kwd>liver</kwd><kwd>adipose tissue</kwd><kwd>short-chain fatty acids</kwd><kwd>hypoxia</kwd><kwd>carnitine acetyl transferase</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">The branched-chain amino acids (BCAAs) leucine, isoleucine, and valine are essential amino acids important for protein synthesis, signaling, and bioenergetics. BCAA catabolism is emerging as a prominently dysregulated pathway in metabolic syndrome<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> and cancer<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>; as such, a greater and more quantitative understanding of this pathway in mammalian physiology is needed. BCAA catabolism is initiated by de-amination via branched chain amino acid transferases (BCATs), and these branched-chain keto acids are subsequently metabolized in mitochondria to generate various acyl-CoA species downstream of the branched-chain keto-acid dehydrogenase (BCKDH) complex. This pathway is active in both energetically demanding tissues such as heart and muscle as well as lipogenic tissues<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. Indeed, studies indicate that adipose BCAA catabolism can compensate for whole-body genetic deficiencies in the pathway<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. Furthermore, carbon from leucine and isoleucine contribute significantly to <italic>de novo</italic> lipogenesis in differentiated adipocytes<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>, suggesting adipose tissue BCAA catabolism may be important for adipocyte function.</p><p id="P3">The predominant product of <italic>de novo</italic> lipogenesis in mammals is the saturated 16-carbon fatty acid (FA) palmitate, which is further elongated and/or desaturated in a tissue-specific manner. Both odd-chain (OCFAs) and monomethyl branched-chain (mmBCFAs) FAs are also present in mammals, but these species are considered to be predominantly diet-derived outside of the skin<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. In lower organisms mmBCFAs are important for controlling membrane fluidity<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> and contribute to neural development<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. In mammals, mmBCFAs are found in milk<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>, sebum<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>, and vernix<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>, and mmBCFA levels differ in obese and insulin resistant patients<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. However, little is known about the metabolism of BCFAs in mammals. Here we demonstrate that mmBCFAs are endogenous products of fatty acid synthase (FASN) and their <italic>in vivo</italic> synthesis is influenced by mitochondrial BCAA catabolism, tissue-specific expression of carnitine acetyltransferase (<italic>Crat</italic>), the microbiome, hypoxia, and diet. mmBCFAs are primarily synthesized in adipose depots and decreased in the context of diet-induced obesity, where adipose-specific hypoxia potently suppresses BCAA catabolism and lipogenesis. These results identify a metabolic pathway in mammals connecting BCAA metabolism and lipid biosynthesis to acyl-chain diversity that is coordinated across distinct tissues and potently regulated by hypoxia.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Mammalian adipocytes synthesize mmBCFAs via FASN</title><p id="P4">Adipocytes undergo substantial mitochondrial and cytosolic metabolic reprogramming upon differentiation. We and others have previously shown that a distinct feature of this metabolic reprogramming is upregulation of BCAA catabolism, which becomes a significant source of carbon for both TCA cycle metabolism and lipogenic acetyl-CoA<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. In cultured adipocytes, odd-chain FAs (C15:0 and C17:0) synthesized from valine and isoleucine-derived propionyl-CoA can also accumulate due to vitamin B12 deficiency and decreased activity of the B12-dependent enzyme methylmalonyl-CoA mutase<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. In addition to the increased BCAA catabolism and OCFA synthesis observed in differentiated 3T3L1 adipocytes, we detected accumulation of several mass isomers of the FAs C16:0 (palmitate) and C17:0 (heptadecanoate), which eluted before the predominant straight-chain isomers in our gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) analysis. As compromised B12 metabolism can lead to accumulation of monomethyl branched-chain FAs (mmBCFAs) in the brain<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>, we hypothesized that these alternate mass isomers were mmBCFAs and subsequently used analytical standards to confirm their identities. We detected increases in 14-methylpentadecanoate (iso-C16:0), 14-methylhexadecanoate (anteiso-C17:0) and 15-methylhexadecanoate (iso-C17:0) during differentiation of 3T3L1 adipocytes, with iso-C16:0 occurring at the highest abundance (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1a</xref>). These FAs have a single branch at either the penultimate or antepenultimate carbon of the acyl chain (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1a</xref>), with the position impacting elution times (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). Interestingly, the relative abundance of anteiso-C17:0 was impacted by B12 availability in this culture system (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1b</xref>), suggesting that these species were actively metabolized by adipocytes.</p><p id="P5">To determine whether mmBCFAs were synthesized <italic>de novo</italic>, we cultured 3T3L1 adipocytes with [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub>]glucose, which generates <sup>13</sup>C fully labeled acetyl-CoA units and a distinct M+2 isotopologue pattern in newly synthesized FAs (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1c</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1b</xref>). We detected significant enrichment in mmBCFAs (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1d</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1c-d</xref>), demonstrating that these FAs are synthesized in a similar manner to palmitate via acetyl-CoA incorporation. Additionally, treatment with the ACC inhibitor ND646<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> led to a significant decrease in <sup>13</sup>C enrichment of both straight-chain and mmBCFAs, indicating their synthesis is dependent on malonyl-CoA from ACC (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1e</xref>).</p><p id="P6">While cytosolic FASN is the predominant enzyme used for <italic>de novo</italic> lipogenesis in mammalian cells, mitochondrial FAS II has been proposed as a hypothetical route for mmBCFA synthesis in eukaryotes<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. To determine whether the cellular location of mmBCFA synthesis differed from that of palmitate we traced adipocytes with [3-<sup>2</sup>H]glucose. Deuterium labeling on the third carbon of glucose specifically labels cytosolic NADPH via the oxidative pentose phosphate pathway but is lost in glycolysis and does not label citrate, acetyl-CoA or mitochondrial NADPH (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1f</xref>)<sup><xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. If a significant portion of mmBCFAs were synthesized within mitochondria, decreased <sup>2</sup>H enrichment relative to palmitate would be expected. We found cytosolic NADPH effectively labelled both mmBCFAs and palmitate, suggesting these FAs were primarily synthesized in the cytosol by FASN (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1g</xref>), albeit at slower rates than palmitate (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1e-f</xref>). Next, we generated pooled cultures of 3T3L1 adipocytes with CRISPR/Cas9 mediated FASN knockout (KO) prior to differentiation (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 2a-b</xref>). While the abundance of all FAs decreased, mmBCFAs were undetectable in all FASN KO cells but abundant in sgNT cells (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1h</xref>). However, differentiation was significantly impaired (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 2c</xref>). To further confirm that FASN deficiency rather than impaired differentiation and lack of substrate decreased BCFA synthesis, we supplemented cultures with the short-branched chain FAs isobutyrate, isovalerate, 2-methyl-butyrate, and propionate. Addition of these substrates increased mmBCFA and OCFA abundances in a dose-dependent manner (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1i</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1d-f</xref>). While iso-C16:0 levels significantly increased in control adipocytes and non-differentiated pre-adipocytes upon addition of isobutyrate, iso-C16:0 levels were still undetectable in FASN KO cells (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 2g</xref>), indicating that lack of FASN rather than impaired differentiation was the primary reason for the absence of BCFA synthesis. Furthermore, treatment with the FASN inhibitor TVB3166 significantly decreased synthesis of both iso-C16:0 and palmitate (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 2h</xref>). While the mitochondrial FAS II system may also contribute to mmBCFA synthesis, our results demonstrate that cytosolic <italic>de novo</italic> lipogenesis via FASN promiscuity is the primary driver of mmBCFA production in adipocytes<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>BCAA catabolic intermediates drive mmBCFA synthesis</title><p id="P7">The minor impact of B12 availability on iso-C16:0 and iso-C17:0 suggests that these FAs are not synthesized via elongation of methylmalonyl-CoA. Administration of radioisotopes to rats has indicated that BCAAs are precursors for mmBCFAs in skin<sup><xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>. In addition, provision of isovaleryl-CoA, isobutyryl-CoA or 2-methylbutyryl-CoA to enzyme extracts from rat epididymal tissue results in the production of mmBCFAs<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. To confirm this pathway architecture exists within intact adipocytes we cultured adipocytes with uniformly <sup>13</sup>C-labeled BCAAs and quantified labeling via GC-MS. This resulted in distinct labeling patterns for each of their respective mmBCFAs (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2a-d</xref>). Carbon from [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>5</sub>]valine was only incorporated into iso-C16:0 and resulted in a prominent M+4 peak in the isotopologue distribution, indicating the valine catabolic intermediate isobutyryl-CoA was used to synthesize iso-C16:0 (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2a-b</xref>). Similarly, iso-C17:0 from [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub>]leucine and anteiso-C17:0 from [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub>]isoleucine exhibited distinct M+5 shifts, indicating that isovaleryl-CoA and 2-methylbutyryl-CoA were used for mmBCFA synthesis (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2a, c-d</xref>). Notably, we detected no FA isotopologues of M+8 or M+10, indicating that only a single incorporation of these branched intermediates into the acyl chain was occurring in these cells. This result, combined with the observation that only mmBCFAs with a branch at the penultimate or antepenultimate end were detected, supports a mechanism whereby FASN is promiscuous and can use short acyl-CoAs to initiate synthesis of long chain FAs.</p><p id="P8">Multiple acyl-CoA dehydrogenases (ACAD) are annotated to carry out the dehydrogenations of isovaleryl-CoA, 2-methylbutyryl-CoA and isobutyryl-CoA. To evaluate the specific roles of these enzymes in BCAA catabolism and mmBCFA synthesis, we targeted various ACAD enzymes via shRNA-mediated knockdown and quantified FA abundances after adipocyte differentiation (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 3a-c</xref>). Knockdown of ACAD8, IVD and ACADSB specifically and significantly increased levels of iso-C16:0, iso-C17:0 and anteiso-C17:0, respectively (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2e-g</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 3d-f</xref>). Targeting of ACADM and ACADS did not impact mmBCFA levels appreciably. Each mmBCFA accumulated differently, with valine-derived iso-C16:0 having the highest abundance (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1a</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 3d</xref>), inversely consistent with the relative expression of each dehydrogenase (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2h</xref>). These findings indicate that ACAD enzyme expression influences the metabolic fate of BCAAs and mmBCFA production.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>mmBCFAs are incorporated into distinct lipid species</title><p id="P9">The above data are representative of total hydrolyzed FA pools in the cell. To further characterize the metabolic fate of mmBCFAs, we next sought to determine whether mmBCFAs were incorporated into distinct lipid species. Distinguishing lipids containing different acyl chain isomers such as iso-C16:0 and C16:0 (palmitate) is challenging with liquid chromatography due to decreased isomer resolution compared to gas chromatography, and there have been limited reports of mmBCFAs in specific, intact lipids<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. To circumvent this issue we utilized [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>5</sub>]valine tracing to differentiate lipids containing C16:0 versus iso-C16:0 acyl-chains, since lipids synthesized with the latter would contain distinct M+4 peaks (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 4a-c</xref>). We quantified M+0 and M+4 isotopologue abundances using targeted LC-MS/MS in 46 lipid species containing 16-carbon acyl chains in adipocytes cultured with [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>5</sub>]valine or [<sup>12</sup>C]valine. Of those measured species, 11 lipids had significant enrichment of M+4 ions in [U<sup>13</sup>C<sub>5</sub>]valine-traced cells over [<sup>12</sup>C]valine-traced cells (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 4d-e</xref>). The highest % total enrichments were observed in species containing alkyl chains, suggesting iso-C16:0 may be selectively incorporated into ether lipids. Notably, some BCFAs (e.g. phytanic acid) must be trafficked to the peroxisome for &#x003b1;-oxidation, and peroxisomes are the site for ether lipid synthesis due to the presence of alkyl DHAP synthase and DHAPAT. As such, mmBCFAs may be similarly directed to the peroxisome, leading to the observed high enrichment in abundant alkyl-lipids. Other significantly enriched lipids included sphingomyelin, phosphatidylserine, phosphatidylcholine, phosphatidylinositol and triacylglycerols (TAGs). In fact, induction of lipolysis via isoproterenol treatment resulted in significant mmBCFA secretion into culture medium indicating these FAs are present in lipid droplets (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 4f</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>mmBCFAs are <italic>de novo</italic> synthesized <italic>in vivo</italic></title><p id="P10">To determine whether mmBCFA synthesis occurs <italic>in vivo</italic>, we quantified the abundances of each mmBCFA across various tissues in male and female C57BL/6J mice. Consistent with our observation of mmBCFA synthesis in adipocytes, white and brown adipose tissues (WAT and BAT) exhibited the highest abundances of all mmBCFAs, including iso-C18:0, an elongated derivative of iso-C16:0 that was not detectable in 3T3L1 cultures (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3a-b</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 5a-b</xref>). Liver and brain exhibited the lowest abundances of mmBCFAs, suggesting FA composition is regulated in a tissue-specific manner. In addition, iso-C17:0 abundance differed between males and females, potentially due to hormonal effects on BCAA catabolism<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>. With the exception of anteiso-C17:0, total mmBCFAs (free and lipid bound) were present in plasma at &#x003bc;M concentrations (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 5c</xref>), and their abundances increased 2&#x02013;3 fold in plasma upon prolonged fasting (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3c</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 5d</xref>). Although these measurements are of total rather than free FAs, these data suggest that iso-BCFAs are released from adipose tissue via lipolysis along with other FAs.</p><p id="P11">As microbial metabolism is a source of both long and short BCFAs<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6a</xref>), the gut microbiome could be a significant source of mmBCFAs in animals. In addition, mmBCFAs are present in chow (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6b</xref>) and thus diet will also contribute to mmBCFA levels <italic>in vivo</italic>. To determine the relative contribution of <italic>de novo</italic> synthesis versus diet and the impact of microbiota on mmBCFA levels, we administered <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O to germ free and specific pathogen free (SPF) control mice for 8 days and measured enrichment of FAs in lipogenic tissues<sup><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3d</xref>). A significant fraction of the mmBCFAs present were newly synthesized in both germ free and SPF mice (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3e-f</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6c-d</xref>). Valine-derived iso-C16:0 was the most abundantly synthesized mmBCFA (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3g-h</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6e-f</xref>), and the fraction of newly synthesized iso-C16:0 was similar to that for palmitate (C16:0) in eWAT, iWAT and BAT (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3e-f</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6c</xref>). Overall, these data indicate that <italic>de novo</italic> synthesis is a significant source of mmBCFAs <italic>in vivo,</italic> and their production can occur in the absence of microbiota. However, both levels (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6g-j</xref>) and synthesis of mmBCFAs and other FAs differed significantly in the adipose tissues of germ free and SPF mice, indicating that microbiota impacts lipogenesis and FA diversity.</p><p id="P12">To confirm that <italic>de novo</italic> synthesis of mmBCFAs occurs in humans, we analyzed plasma from NAFLD patients administered <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 2</xref> and <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6k-l</xref>). Analysis of deuterium enrichment of FAs demonstrated that both OCFAs and mmBCFAs were synthesized <italic>de novo</italic> in humans (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3i</xref>). Plasma mmBCFAs were present in the range of 1 &#x02013; 20 &#x003bc;M in these patients (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6m</xref>), which is comparable to that of other long and very long chain FAs such as C20:0 and C24:0<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>BCAA flux to mmBCFAs is decreased by diet-induced obesity</title><p id="P13">Clinical studies have indicated that BCAA metabolism is dysregulated in the context of metabolic syndrome, as plasma BCAAs and some catabolites are elevated in insulin resistant patients<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Additionally, BCAA catabolic enzyme expression is decreased in rodents fed a high-fat diet (HFD)<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. Conversely, plasma mmBCFAs are decreased in morbidly obese patients<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>. To determine if mmBCFA levels change in mouse models of obesity, we quantified total FAs in plasma and WAT of mice fed a HFD or low-fat diet (LFD) for 15 weeks. Although intake of all FAs (including mmBCFAs) was increased in the HFD cohort (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 7a</xref>), iso-BCFA abundances were significantly lower (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4a-b</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 7b-c</xref>). In terms of fold changes, valine-derived iso-C16:0 and iso-C18:0 were the most differentially abundant FAs in these tissues. Relative abundances of straight-chain FAs increased or remained unchanged, with the exceptions of C16:1 (palmitoleate) and C15:0 (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4a</xref>). Similar results were observed in ob/ob mice, where mmBCFAs were significantly decreased in iWAT relative to control mice (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 7d</xref>). Notably, anteiso-C17:0 levels increase in the plasma of HFD mice (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4b</xref>). Given that synthesis of anteiso-C17:0 was nearly undetectable in <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O traced mice (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3g-h</xref>), this FA is primarily diet-derived and synthesis from isoleucine is not significant <italic>in vivo</italic>. These results demonstrate that individual FAs change distinctly with the onset of obesity depending on their origin and metabolism.</p><p id="P14">To directly investigate altered BCAA catabolism in the context of metabolic syndrome, we fed C57BL/6J mice a HFD or LFD for 12 weeks followed by 3 weeks of feeding with identical diets formulated with 25% enriched [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>5</sub>,<sup>15</sup>N]valine and [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub>,<sup>15</sup>N]leucine (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8a</xref>). Although fasting plasma glucose levels were elevated (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8b</xref>), plasma BCAA levels were unchanged (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8c</xref>), consistent with recent studies in C57BL/6J mice,<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> and we observed no differences in plasma leucine and valine enrichment (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8d</xref>). Significant differences were present within tissues, however (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8e-f</xref>). We detected significant <sup>13</sup>C enrichment of citrate and palmitate in all tissues measured (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4c-d</xref>), indicating leucine catabolism is a significant source of acetyl-CoA <italic>in vivo</italic>. In the HFD cohort, <sup>13</sup>C enrichment and molar abundance in citrate and palmitate, respectively, were significantly decreased in all tissues, with BAT being the most impacted, demonstrating that diet-induced obesity decreases BCAA catabolism (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4c-d</xref>). The leucine and valine-derived mmBCFAs had characteristic M+4 and M+5 mass shifts indicating these FAs were synthesized <italic>de novo</italic> from BCAAs <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4e</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8g-h</xref>). Importantly, molar enrichment of iso-BCFAs from valine and leucine were decreased in total FA pools from almost all tissues analyzed (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4f</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8i-j</xref>). The highest abundances of newly synthesized, long chain iso-BCFAs were present in brown adipose tissue, although cross-tissue transport is likely significant given the high FA enrichments detected in muscle and heart. Collectively, these data indicate that diet-induced obesity significantly decreases BCAA catabolic flux, and a downstream result of this regulation is lower mmBCFA synthesis and abundance throughout the body.</p><p id="P15">In contrast to mmBCFAs, we did not detect a pronounced M+3 shift in OCFAs (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8k</xref>), consistent with the abundance of other propionate sources in animals (e.g. gut microbes, OCFA oxidation, and cholesterol breakdown) or their production via &#x003b1;-oxidation<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. While valine is a source of propionate in cultured adipocytes, this pathway is not a major source of OCFAs <italic>in vivo</italic> under normal physiological conditions<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. However, we did note some incorporation of BCAA-derived carbon into OCFAs via acetyl-CoA (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8l-m</xref>) indicating that OCFAs are also <italic>de novo</italic> synthesized to some extent <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Adipose tissue mmBCFA synthesis is facilitated by CrAT</title><p id="P16">The above results demonstrate that BCAA catabolic flux contributes significantly to <italic>de novo</italic> lipogenesis <italic>in vivo</italic>, and mmBCFAs are abundant products of this pathway. The large (~10-fold) differences in abundance within liver and adipose tissues (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3a-b</xref>) suggest that mmBCFA synthesis is regulated distinctly in these tissues. To assess the impact of diet on tissue-specific mmBCFA synthesis and enable comparison to synthesis of other FAs, we administered <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O to HFD and LFD mice and measured enrichment in lipogenic tissues. Newly synthesized iso-C16:0 and iso-C18:0 were decreased in livers of HFD mice more than any other FA in terms of fold-change (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5a</xref>). In contrast, straight-chain and monounsaturated FA synthesis in the liver was increased or remained the same (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5a</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 9a</xref>). Within adipose tissues, HFD feeding decreased lipogenesis of all FAs, indicating pathway activity is generally suppressed (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5b</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 9b-d</xref>) as previously observed<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. We next estimated FA synthesis/turnover occurring in each tissue based on the molar abundance of each FA, fraction synthesized, and length of time tracer was administered. mmBCFA turnover was highest in white and brown adipose tissues but substantially lower in liver (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5c</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 9e-g</xref>). While brown adipose tissue exhibited the highest synthesis/turnover for all FAs, these measurements are likely a lower estimate since they do not account for &#x003b2;-oxidation and futile FA cycling, which are likely quite high in brown adipocytes<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>. HFD suppressed the synthesis of all FAs in adipose tissues but increased palmitate synthesis/turnover in liver (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5d</xref>). These results suggest that subcutaneous and brown adipocytes exhibit a high capacity for mmBCFA synthesis when lipogenesis is active in these depots (i.e. LFD). Indeed, mmBCFA synthesis in brown adipose tissue is significantly increased in cold-exposed mice (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5e</xref>), similar to the increased <italic>de novo</italic> lipogenesis of other FAs<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P17">Liver exhibited relatively low abundances of newly synthesized mmBCFAs compared to other lipogenic tissues, and these levels decreased further in response to HFD, which contrasts the changes observed for other FAs in the liver. Importantly, this tracing method does not account for lipid efflux and inter-tissue FA transport and thus likely underestimates absolute FA synthesis in liver. Nevertheless, our collective data on abundance and synthesis of all FAs strongly indicates that mmBCFAs are synthesized in adipose tissues but not liver.</p><p id="P18">BCAA catabolism and lipogenesis are highly active in liver, so we next attempted to address why mmBCFA synthesis is specific to adipose tissues. mmBCFA synthesis requires BCAA catabolic intermediates to be exported from the mitochondria into the cytosol for elongation by FASN. Prior studies have demonstrated that carnitine acetyltransferase (CrAT) but not carnitine palmitoyltransferase 2 (CPT2) exhibits enzyme activity towards BCAA-derived, short branched-chain CoAs<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. Therefore, we hypothesized that CrAT facilitates mmBCFA synthesis in adipose tissues. <italic>Crat</italic> mRNA is expressed at low levels in liver but exhibits high expression in muscle and adipose tissues (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5f</xref>). Additionally, quantitative proteomics indicates that CrAT is expressed at higher levels in white and brown adipose tissue compared to liver and brain (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 10a</xref>)<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>. Thus, tissue-specific CrAT expression may be a driver of the observed differences in mmBCFA abundance and synthesis between liver, brain, and adipose tissues.</p><p id="P19">To more directly determine how CrAT influences mmBCFA synthesis we generated CrAT KO 3T3L1 cells using CRISPR/Cas9 (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 10b</xref>). In contrast to results with FASN KO, CrAT KO did not appreciably impact adipogenesis (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 10c-d</xref>). However, CrAT KO adipocytes had significantly decreased levels of both mmBCFAs and OCFAs (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig 5g</xref>), with minimal differences in the levels of other FAs (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 10e</xref>). These data indicate that CrAT is an important component of the mmBCFA synthesis pathway, facilitating cytosolic export of precursor acyl-CoAs (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 10f</xref>). Differential expression of this enzyme in liver versus BAT and WAT likely contributes to the tissue specificity of mmBCFA synthesis and abundance.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Hypoxia suppresses BCAA catabolism and mmBCFA synthesis</title><p id="P20">Our data indicate that mmBCFAs are predominantly synthesized in adipose depots, decrease in the context of diet-induced obesity, and increase in plasma during prolonged fasting. Given the adipose origin of mmBCFAs, we sought to determine the physiological factors that drive decreased BCAA catabolism and mmBCFA synthesis in obesity <italic>in vivo</italic>. Hypoxia has been proposed as a key contributory factor to adipose tissue dysfunction in obesity<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>, and increasing adipose vascularization improves insulin sensitivity<sup><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup>. To test the impact of hypoxia on BCAA metabolism in adipocytes, we incubated differentiated 3T3L1 adipocytes in 1% oxygen for 24 hours before switching to hypoxia-equilibrated media containing uniformly <sup>13</sup>C labeled amino acids or glucose for an additional 24 hours. Intracellular BCAAs and &#x003b1;-ketoisocaproate accumulated significantly in hypoxic cultures, along with lactate and 2-hydroxyglutarate (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig 6a</xref>). Media analysis demonstrated that glycolytic flux increased along with net glutamine consumption, while BCAA uptake decreased approximately 3&#x02013;4 fold (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig 6b</xref>). Consistent with these flux changes, TCA intermediate enrichment from [U-<sup>13</sup>C]BCAAs was decreased under hypoxia (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig 6c</xref>). Isotopomer spectral analysis (ISA) demonstrated that the relative contribution of leucine to lipogenic acetyl-CoA decreased significantly, whereas the glutamine contribution to FAs increased (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig 6d</xref>). Notably, hypoxia generally decreased the synthesis of FAs, including OCFAs and mmBCFAs (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig 6e</xref>). Collectively these data indicate that hypoxia strongly decreases BCAA catabolism. These results were recapitulated in primary cells derived from various tissues, including murine brown adipocytes and human skeletal myotubes and white adipocytes (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 11a</xref>).</p><p id="P21"><italic>Bckdha</italic> and <italic>Bcat2</italic> mRNA and protein product were decreased under hypoxia in 3T3L1 adipocytes (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 11b-d</xref>). Additionally, we observed that adipose tissue oxygen tension and arterial blood flow were specifically decreased in HFD mice along with BCKDHA protein levels (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 11e-g</xref>), corroborating previous findings in obese adipose tissue<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>. Overall, these data indicate that adipose tissue in obese animals exhibits lower oxygen tension, which may contribute to the observed decreases in BCAA catabolism and BCKDHA levels we observed in adipose tissue from HFD mice. In turn, decreased flux through this pathway decreases local and circulating iso-mmBCFA levels in obesity.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P22">Here, using <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> metabolic tracing, we define a cross-tissue metabolic pathway where BCAA catabolic flux and the promiscuity of FASN and CrAT within brown and white adipose tissues support mmBCFA synthesis. Additionally, we demonstrate that mmBCFA turnover is suppressed by HFD and obesity-induced adipose hypoxia. Collectively, these results demonstrate that mmBCFAs are endogenous FAs produced by adipocytes that link mitochondrial BCAA catabolism, lipogenesis, and diet to metabolic disease.</p><p id="P23">To date, the primary metabolic role of BCAA catabolism has been attributed to its importance as a nitrogen donor<sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>, production of HIBA to modulate FA uptake<sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup>, and the generation of branched acyl intermediates that can modulate enzyme function via post-translational modifications<sup><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>. Our data adds to this knowledge, linking BCAA catabolism to modulation of FA diversity via enzyme promiscuity. Interestingly, mmBCFAs are synthesized and present at low levels in liver, despite the high abundance of BCKDH and rate of lipogenesis<sup><xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup>. We provide evidence this difference is driven by differential expression of <italic>Crat</italic>, an enzyme that has predominantly been studied in muscle, where it is thought to mitigate fatigue by facilitating acetyl-CoA consumption during exercise and preventing acetyl-CoA accumulation during rest<sup><xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup>, thus decreasing macronutrient induced lysine acetylation of mitochondrial proteins<sup><xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup>. However, its relevance in brown and white adipose tissues has not been explored, despite the high level of expression observed in brown adipose tissue<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>. Given recent evidence that branched acyl lysine modifications also alter mitochondrial enzyme function<sup><xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>, it is possible that diversion of branched CoA intermediates to long chain FAs via CrAT is beneficial for maintaining healthy mitochondrial function.</p><p id="P24">We also highlight an underappreciated aspect of <italic>de novo</italic> lipogenesis, whereby the <italic>de novo</italic> FA composition reflects the balance of acyl-CoAs within the body. Thus, FASN promiscuity integrates changes in amino acid metabolism and short chain FAs into the lipidome. Therefore, alterations in SCFA and acyl-CoA abundance driven by the gut microbiome, diet, or inborn errors of metabolism can influence FA diversity and must be considered when studying the pathophysiology of associated diseases. Indeed, elevated levels of mmBCFAs have been detected in the brains of patients with defects in cobalamin metabolism<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. Supraphysiological levels of mmBCFAs could impact neuronal function and play a role in the neurological defects that occur in patients with certain organic acidemias or B12 deficiency. This work also highlights the limited resolution of most lipidomics platforms for resolving mmBCFA-containing lipids. We found that mmBCFAs are incorporated into diverse lipid species by cultured adipocytes, including ether lipids, TAGs, and phospholipids. However, more extensive and focused approaches are needed to fully characterize their fates within different tissues.</p><p id="P25">Using <sup>13</sup>C labeled leucine and valine chow, we observed that HFD feeding suppressed BCAA catabolism, resulting in decreased mmBCFA synthesis. This result is consistent with transcriptional and other flux-based measurements that indicate downregulation of this pathway in mouse models of obesity and diabetic patients<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup>. In fact, mmBCFAs correlate negatively with metabolic disease biomarkers such as C-reactive protein and insulin resistance in patients<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. This contrasts with levels of BCAAs and their downstream catabolic intermediates, which increase in the plasma of insulin resistant patients<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup>. However, BCAA levels did not increase in our model of diet-induced obesity, and thus mmBCFA levels did not correlate with BCAA levels as might be expected. This is presumably due to the adipose specific origin of these FAs, as BCAAs are widely catabolized in energetically demanding tissues such as muscle, liver, heart and brain which are not significant sources of mmBCFAs. Furthermore, BCAA turnover and abundance is much greater than that of mmBCFAs. Therefore, while mmBCFA synthesis is impacted by BCAA catabolic flux, differential mmBCFA production is unlikely to be a primary driver of BCAA accumulation in T2D patients. Nevertheless, mmBCFAs may be a strong biomarker of adipose tissue lipogenesis and BCAA catabolism, and in contrast to circulating BCAA levels, are not overtly influenced by changes in protein turnover and muscle insulin resistance.</p><p id="P26">The functional consequences of decreased mmBCFA levels are unknown. Despite their abundance in tissues and presence at &#x003bc;M levels in plasma, mmBCFAs have been studied minimally in the context of mammalian biology. mmBCFA-containing lipids play critical roles in the postembryonic growth, neuronal development and foraging behavior of <italic>C. elegans</italic><sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>. In prokaryotes BCFAs influence membrane fluidity, and their abundances change in response to certain stresses<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>. In mammalian biology, previous studies have suggested they influence colon epithelial cell inflammation<sup><xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup> and protect against necrotizing enterocolitis<sup><xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup>. Our insights into the metabolic origins and fates of mmBCFAs suggest other potential functions. Since mmBCFAs are primarily synthesized in adipose tissue, incorporated into TAGs, and increase in plasma during fasting, these lipids may be involved in nutrient sensing and signal to other tissues in the body. However, given the relatively low abundance of mmBCFAs, these FAs are unlikely to contribute significantly to energy storage or substrate oxidation and are more likely to play a role in signaling or membrane structure. Ultimately, understanding the factors that regulate mmBCFA physiology is an essential step in elucidating their function and contribution to the biological importance of the BCAA catabolic pathway.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S12"><title>Materials and reagents</title><p id="P27">Media and sera were purchased from Life Technologies. Glucose and amino acid isotope tracers were purchased from Cambridge Isotopes Inc. Fatty acid standards were purchased from Larodan. All other reagents were purchased form Sigma-Aldrich unless otherwise noted.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Cell culture</title><p id="P28">3T3L1 pre-adipocytes were purchased from the American Type Culture Collection and cultured in high glucose Dulbecco&#x02019;s modified Eagle medium (DMEM) (Life Technologies) supplemented with 10% bovine calf serum (BCS) below 70% confluence. For differentiation, cells were allowed to reach confluence (Day &#x02212;2), 2 days post confluence (Day 0) differentiation was induced with 0.5 mM 3-isobutyl-1-methylxanthine (IBMX), 0.25 &#x003bc;M dexamethasone, 1 &#x003bc;g/ml insulin in DMEM containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS). Media was changed on Day 2 to DMEM + 10% FBS with 1 &#x003bc;g/ml insulin. Day 4, and thereafter DMEM + 10% FBS was used. Cobalamin (500 nM) was supplemented to cultures when noted. Isotope tracing was carried out 7 days post induction of differentiation unless otherwise noted. Cells were incubated in custom DMEM where the metabolite specified was replaced with the <sup>13</sup>C or <sup>2</sup>H labeled version for 24 hours unless otherwise specified. For short chain fatty acid addition experiments, individual short chain fatty acids were added to the media at the indicated concentration for 24 hours after which total fatty acids were extracted as described below. Fatty acids were then calculated as % total fatty acids and normalized to control conditions. For LCMS analysis of [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>5</sub>] valine incorporation into lipids, 3T3L1 cells were incubated in tracer media for 4 days.</p><p id="P29">BAT depots were isolated from the interscapular area of neonate mice as previously described<sup><xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup>. Once cells reached confluency, differentiation was induced by addition of DMEM containing 10% FBS, 20nM insulin, 1nM triiodothyronine, 0.5mM 3-isobutyl-1-methylxanthine, 2-&#x003bc;g/mL dexamethasone, and 0.25mM indomethacin for 2 days and then switched to differentiation media containing 20nM insulin, and 1nM triiodothyronine for 5&#x02013;6 days. Isotope tracing was carried out 7 days post induction of differentiation.</p><p id="P30">Primary human white pre-adipocytes and muscle satellite cells were isolated, propagated and differentiated and then cultured for 24 hours in tracer media as previously described<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>. Weight stable obese subjects undergoing elective laparoscopic gastric bypass via Roux-en-Y for the treatment of obesity were recruited for the study to provide material for pre-adipocyte isolation. Both human skeletal muscle biopsies and material for pre-adipocyte isolation were obtained with approval from the University of California San Diego&#x02019;s Committee on Human Investigation and VA San Diego Medical Center&#x02019;s Institutional Review Board. All donors provided informed written consent after listening to an explanation of the protocol and the study complied with all relevant regulations.</p><p id="P31">All hypoxia experiments were carried out in a Coy hypoxia chamber which allows media changes under hypoxic conditions. ND-646 (1,4-dihydro-1-[(2<italic>R</italic>)-2-(2-methoxyphenyl)-2-[(tetrahydro-2<italic>H</italic>-pyran-4-yl)oxy]ethyl]-a,a,5-trimethyl-6-(2-oxazolyl)-2,4-dioxothieno[2,3-<italic>d</italic>]pyrimidine-3(2<italic>H</italic>)-acetamide) was solubilized in DMSO and added to cells at a final concentration of 100 nM for 24 hours in the presence of tracer.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Lipolysis Assay</title><p id="P32">Differentiated 3T3-L1 adipocytes were washed twice with PBS and incubated with serum-free DMEM containing P/S, 2% FA-free BSA, and 10 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>M isoproterenol for 1hr. 100&#x003bc;L was extracted for GC-MS analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Oil Red O staining</title><p id="P33">A 0.35% (w/v) Oil Red O stock was prepared in isopropanol and filtered through a 0.22 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m filter. Cells were washed with PBS, fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 30 minutes at room temperature, washed 2X in milli-Q water, washed once with 60% isopropanol, and finally stained with 3:2 (stock:water) Oil Red O solution for 30 minutes. Stain solution was removed from cells and cells were washed 4X with milli-Q water before imaging.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Lentiviral production and shRNA KD of Acyl CoA Dehydrogenases</title><p id="P34">Glycerol stocks of TRC2-pLKO.1-puro shRNA (methods table 1), and a non-targeting control construct were purchased from Sigma Aldrich, packaged in HEK293FT cells using the transfection agent Fugene 6 and required packaging plasmids VSV-G, gag/pol, and rev. HEK293FT medium containing lentiviral constructs was collected two days later and filtered (0.45 &#x003bc;m). Polybrene was added to a final concentration of 6 &#x003bc;g/mL. 3T3L1 pre-adipocytes were infected with 0.5 mL of virus-containing medium in a 6-well plate for 4 hours before addition of 2 mL of virus-free medium. After 24 hours of recovery, transduced cells were selected with 3 &#x003bc;g/mL puromycin. Cells were then plated to 12-well plates for differentiation as described above. Puromycin was removed from the medium beginning on Day 0 of differentiation.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Pooled CRISPR/Cas9 KO of <italic>Crat</italic> and <italic>Fasn</italic> in 3T3L1 adipocytes.</title><p id="P35">Fasn, NT and CrAT target sequences (methods table 2) were cloned into the lentiCRISPRv2 plasmid, a gift from Feng Zhang (Addgene plasmid # 52961). For lentivirus production, 2 &#x02013; 2.5 million HEK293FT cells were placed in 10-cm tissue culture plates in 10 ml of DMEM (containing 1% penicillin/streptomycin, 10% FBS). 24 hours later, transfection was performed using Lipofectamine 3000 (Invitrogen) with 1.3 &#x003bc;g VSV.G/PMD2.G, 5.3 &#x003bc;g of lenti-gag/pol/PCMVR8.2 and 4 &#x003bc;g of lentiviral vector. Lentivirus-containing supernatants were harvested 48 and 72 hours later and concentrated using Amicon Ultra-15 centrifugal filters, 100,000 NMWL (Millipore) following manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. 3T3-L1 pre-adipocytes were infected with 10 &#x003bc;L of virus, in 1 ml of medium containing 7.5 &#x003bc;gs of polybrene in a 6-well plate for 4 hours before addition of an extra 1 mL of virus-free medium. After 24 hours of recovery, transduced cells were selected with 3 &#x003bc;g/mL puromycin. Cells were then plated to 12-well plates for differentiation as described above. Puromycin was removed from the medium beginning on Day 0 of differentiation.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>RNA isolation and quantitative RT-PCR</title><p id="P36">Total RNA was purified from cultured cells using Trizol Reagent (Life Technologies) per manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. First-strand cDNA was synthesized from 1 &#x003bc;g of total RNA using iScript Reverse Transcription Supermix for RT-PCR (BioRad Laboratories) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Individual 10 &#x003bc;L SYBR Green real-time PCR reactions consisted of 2 &#x003bc;L of diluted cDNA, 5 &#x003bc;L of SYBR Green Supermix (BioRad), and 1 &#x003bc;L of each 5&#x003bc;M forward and reverse primers. For standardization of quantification, 18S was amplified simultaneously. The PCR was carried out on 96 well plates on a CFX Connect Real time System (Bio-Rad), using a three-stage program provided by the manufacturer: 95&#x000b0;C for 3 min, 40 cycles of 95&#x000b0;C for 10 sec and 60&#x000b0;C for 30 sec. Gene-specific primers used are listed in methods table 3. PCR data for inter-gene comparison was corrected for primer efficiency.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Western blots</title><p id="P37">3T3L1 adipocytes or 100&#x02013;150 mgs of ground eWAT were lysed in ice-cold RIPA buffer with 1&#x000d7; protease inhibitor (Sigma-Aldrich). 30 &#x003bc;g of total protein was separated on a 12% SDS-PAGE gel for BCKDH blots or 20 ugs of total protein was separated on a 4&#x02013;20% SDS-PAGE gel (mini-protean TGX gels, Bio-Rad) for CrAT and FASN blots. The proteins were transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane and immunoblotted with anti-Bckdha (Novus Biologicals NBP1&#x02013;79616) (1:1,000 dilution), anti-Beta-Actin (Cell Signaling 4970S) (1:5,000), anti-GAPDH (Cell signaling 5174S), anti-CrAT (Novus NBP2&#x02013;15999), anti-FASN (Proteintech 10624&#x02013;2-AP). Specific signal was detected with horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody goat anti-rabbit (1:2,500 &#x02013; 1:10,000) using SuperSignal West Pico Chemiluminescent Substrate (Thermo Scientific) and developed using Blue Devil Autoradiography film (Genesee Scientific) or BioRad Chemidoc XRS+.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Animal studies</title><p id="P38">Animal handling and care followed the NIH Guide for Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. The experimental protocols were approved by either the UCSD, Salk or UMMS Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee. C57BL/6J and ob/ob(B6.Cg-Lepob/J) were obtained from Jackson Laboratories.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Mouse fasting study</title><p id="P39">Food was removed from cages containing 12 week old male or female C57BL/6J mice (3&#x02013;4 mice per cage) at 7:00 am. Blood was collected via tail bleed at baseline, 2, 6 12 and 24 hours post removal of food. Mice remained in their original cage with original bedding (non-synthetic shavings) for the duration of the experiment.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title><sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O administration to animals</title><p id="P40">For the comparison of germ free and specific pathogen free mice, male Swiss Webster mice were bred and maintained in sterile semi-flexible isolators and screened for bacterial, viral, and fungal contamination. Age-matched male specific pathogen free mice were used for comparison and obtained from Charles River at 5 weeks of age. Mice were maintained under a 12 hr light/dark cycle and given a standard chow diet ad libitum. At 6 weeks of age, mice were subcutaneously injected with 0.035 mls/g body weight 0.9% NaCl <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O and drinking water was replaced with 8% <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O enriched water. 8 days later, mice were fasted for 6 hours (9 am &#x02013; 3pm) and tissues collected and snap frozen in liquid N<sub>2</sub>.</p><p id="P41">For high fat study, 5-week-old C57BL/6J mice were obtained from Jackson Laboratories and ad lib fed a 45% high fat diet (D12451) or a 10% low fat diet (D12450K) for 15 weeks from 6 weeks of age. Diets were obtained from Research Diets, Inc. 7 &#x02013; 21 days prior to termination, mice were I.P injected with 0.035 mls/g body weight 0.9% NaCl <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O and drinking water was replaced with 8% <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O enriched water. Mice were fasted for 6 hours prior to plasma and tissue collection and samples were immediately snap frozen in liquid N<sub>2</sub>.</p><p id="P42">Thermo-variation experiments were carried out as previously described<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>. Briefly, 10-week-old C57BL/6J mice were simultaneously housed in two rodent incubators (RIT33SD, Powers Scientific) within the Animal Medicine facilities of the UMMS for 4 weeks. One of them had the temperature adjusted to 30&#x000b0;C (thermoneutrality group). Another incubator had its temperature decreased by four degrees weekly until reaching 6&#x000b0;C at which temperature the mice stayed for a week (severe cold group). Room temperature group mice were in a clean room set at 22&#x000b0;C co-housed in the same facility as the mice in rodent incubators. Mouse cages were changed weekly using components pre-adjusted to temperature. Three days prior to termination, mice were intraperitoneally injected with 0.035 mL/g body weight 0.9% NaCl <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O (Sigma, 151882) and drinking water was replaced with 8% <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O enriched water.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Isotope labeled chow study</title><p id="P43">5-week-old C57BL/6J mice were obtained from Jackson Laboratories and ad lib fed a custom 60% kcal high fat diet (TD.160092) or a 20% kcal fat diet (TD. 160091) for 15 weeks from 6 weeks of age. Diets and incorporated isotopes were obtained from Envigo Teklad Diets and Cambridge isotopes respectively. For the final 3 weeks, 25% of the total valine and leucine in the diet was replaced with [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>5</sub>-<sup>15</sup>N]valine and [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub>-<sup>15</sup>N]leucine so that there was 3 g [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>5</sub>-<sup>15</sup>N]valine /100 grams protein and 4 g [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub>-<sup>15</sup>N]leucine/100 grams protein in both diets. Mice were fasted overnight prior to plasma and tissue collection and samples were immediately snap frozen in liquid N<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Tissue pO<sub>2</sub> and organ blood flow in HFD/LFD mice</title><p id="P44">To determine the impact of obesity on tissue pO<sub>2</sub>, blood flow and BCKDHA levels in eWAT, 5-week-old C57BL/6J mice were obtained from Jackson Laboratories and ad lib fed a 60% kcal high fat diet (D12492) or a 10% kcal fat diet (D12450K) from research diets for 8 weeks from 6 weeks of age.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Electrodes for oxygen measurements</title><p id="P45">The oxygen partial pressure was measured using carbon fiber electrodes (Carbostar-1, Kation Scientific; Minneapolis, MN) where the tip of the electrode was coated with 5% Nafion (Sigma; St. Louis, MO) to increase oxygen specificity. The process consisted of three individual Nafion coats. The microelectrodes were polarized at &#x02212;0.8 V relative to a silver-silver chloride reference electrode (Cypress Systems; Lawrence, KS). Oxygen measurements were performed using the two electrodes system (working and reference electrode), and the current generated was measured with a potentiostat and electrometer (Keithley model 610C; Cleveland, OH). The microelectrodes were calibrated at 37&#x000b0;C with 0, 5, 10 and 21% oxygen gases (Airgas; Los Angeles, CA). Tissues were superfused (0.1 mL/min) with physiological Krebs salt solution and the tissue was maintained at 35&#x02013;37&#x000b0;C by the heated Krebs solution. The solution was spread on the tissue as a thin film, drained into a platter, and drawn off by suction. The solution was equilibrated with 95% N<sub>2</sub> and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, which maintained the superfusate at a pH of 7.4 and minimized O<sub>2</sub> delivery to the tissue from the atmosphere. Oxygen measurements were made by penetrating the tissue with the microelectrode tip. The reference electrode was placed in the bath, and the microelectrode was placed in a shielded holder and advanced towards the measurement site with a micromanipulator. A long-working distance X10 Leitz objective was used to direct the electrode to the measurement site. Before measurements, the electrode tip was immersed in the supernatant suffusion solution and the current was registered. The supernatant suffusion solution was set as 0 mmHg reference point. Upon introduction into the tissue, the microelectrodes responded with a time constant that is estimated to be of the order of 10 sec. A stable reading is obtained within 30 seconds, and upon reaching the current plateau value, the electrode is extracted from the tissue and the tip maintained within the suffusing saline solution.</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>Organ Blood Flow Distribution</title><p id="P46">The fluorescent-labeled microsphere (FLM) method was used to determine organ blood flow. Briefly, fluorescent microspheres (Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR), 15 &#x003bc;m in diameter with a single color (green, yellow, red or scarlet) were suspended in saline and injected over a short 10 second period (100 &#x003bc;L) at the time point of interest. At the end of the protocol, animals were euthanized with a lethal dose of sodium pentobarbital, and eight vital tissues were harvested. The tissues were digested in 1N KOH in separate containers for 24 hrs and then filtered. Fluorescent dye extraction was accomplished using Cellosolve (Fisher Scientific Co., Pittsburg, PA), and the number of FLMs was quantified as a function of the florescent signal at each specific FluoSphere wavelength (LS50B, Perkin-Elmer Corp., Norwalk, CT) <sup><xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>NAFL/NASH patient sample collection</title><p id="P47">16 subjects undergoing diagnostic liver biopsy for suspected NAFLD were recruited by the NAFLD Research Center at the University of California&#x02013;San Diego. Subjects were carefully screened and excluded for liver diseases other than NAFLD and secondary causes of hepatic steatosis<sup><xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup>. Subjects drank 50 mL of 70% <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O three times per day for 4 days, followed by twice a day until the date of liver biopsy, for a total period of 3&#x02013;5 weeks. Plasma was collected weekly from the start of heavy water labeling until the time of biopsy. All procedures used in this study were approved by the University of California&#x02013;San Diego Human Research Protections Program. Subjects provided written informed consent, and Declaration of Helsinki protocols were followed.</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>GC/MS analysis of fatty acids and polar metabolites</title><p id="P48">For cell culture, polar metabolites and fatty acids were extracted using methanol/water/chloroform and analyzed as previously described<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. For tissue and plasma, metabolites and total fatty acids were extracted from tissues and plasma using a Folch-based methanol/chloroform/saline extraction at a ratio of 1:2:1 with inclusion of [<sup>2</sup>H<sub>31</sub>] palmitate and norvaline as lipid and polar internal standards respectively. Briefly, 250 &#x003bc;l MeOH, 500 &#x003bc;ls CHCL3, 250 &#x003bc;ls saline and fatty acid isotope internal standards were added to weighed pre-ground tissue. This was vortexed for 10 minutes followed by centrifugation at 10,000 g for 5 minutes. Polar metabolites were derivatized in 2% (w/v) methoxyamine hydrochloride (Thermo Scientific) in pyridine and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 60 minutes. Samples were then silylated with N-tertbutyldimethylsilyl-N-methyltrifluoroacetamide (MTBSTFA) with 1% tert-butyldimethylchlorosilane (tBDMS) (Regis Technologies) at 37&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02013;45 minutes. Polar derivatives were analyzed by GC-MS using a DB-35MS column (30m x 0.25 mm i.d. x 0.25 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m, Agilent J&#x00026;W Scientific) installed in an Agilent 7890A gas chromatograph (GC) interfaced with an Agilent 5975C mass spectrometer (MS). The lower chloroform phase was dried and then derivitised to form fatty acid methyl esters(FAMES) via addition of 500 &#x003bc;ls 2% H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> in MeOH and incubation at 50&#x000b0;C for 2 hours. FAMES were extracted via addition of 100 &#x003bc;l saturated salt solution and 500 &#x003bc;l hexane and these were analyzed using a Select FAME column (100m x 0.25mm i.d.) installed in an Aglient 7890A GC interfaced with an Agilent 5975C MS using the following temperature program: 80 &#x000b0;C initial, increase by 20 &#x000b0;C/min to 170 &#x000b0;C, increase by 1 &#x000b0;C/min to 204 &#x000b0;C, then 20 &#x000b0;C/min to 250 &#x000b0;C and hold for 10 min. The % isotopologue distribution of each fatty acid and polar metabolite was determined and corrected for natural abundance using in-house algorithms adapted from Fernandez et al<sup><xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup>. The metabolite ion fragments used are summarized in methods table 4. Mole percent enrichment (MPE) was calculated via the following equation:
<disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math display="block" id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mstyle mathsize="140%" displaystyle="true"><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <italic>n</italic> is the number of carbon atoms in the metabolite and M<sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the relative abundance of the <italic>i</italic>th mass isotopologue. Molar enrichment was determined by multiplying the MPE by the abundance.</p><p id="P49">YSI (yellow springs instrument) was used to quantify glucose, lactate, glutamine and glutamate in cell culture media.</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title>Isotopomer spectral analysis.</title><p id="P50">The contribution of oxPPP derived NADPH to lipogenesis using the [3-<sup>2</sup>H] glucose tracer was determined via isotopomer spectral analysis (ISA) using INCA as previously described<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. The ISA compares a measured fatty acid isotopomer distribution (determined by integrating metabolite ion fragments of fatty acids summarized in methods table 3) to one that is simulated using a reaction network for palmitate synthesis whereby 14 NADPH molecules are consumed to form one palmitate molecule. Models were also generated for mmBCFA and OCFA synthesis whereby 12 NADPH molecules are consumed to form one branched or odd chain fatty acid(methods table 5 and 6). Parameters for the relative enrichment of the lipogenic NADPH pool from a given [<sup>2</sup>H] tracer and the percentage of fatty acids that are <italic>de novo</italic> synthesized are extracted from a best fit model using INCA 4.6 metabolic flux analysis software package<sup><xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup>. The 95% confidence intervals for both parameters were estimated by evaluating the sensitivity of the sum of squared residuals between measured and simulated fatty acid mass isotopomer distributions to small flux variations.</p></sec><sec id="S30"><title>GC/MS analysis of short chain fatty acids.</title><p id="P51">Cecal content was weighed, and 2&#x003bc;l of water was added per mg of cecum. The sample was vortexed for 5 minutes followed by centrifugation at 18,000 g for 5 minutes at 10&#x000b0;C. The resultant cecal water was used for SCFA analysis, and the cecal pellet was dried overnight at 60&#x000b0;C to obtain the dry weight.</p><p id="P52">For cecal SCFA quantification, 50 &#x003bc;l of cecal water was added to a 2 ml eppendorf microcentrifuge tube, followed by 150 &#x003bc;l water, 10 &#x003bc;l 5 mM 2-ethylbutyrate, 30 &#x003bc;l 10 mM sodium acetate-d3, 50 &#x003bc;l 1-propanol and 50 &#x003bc;l pyridine. The tube was placed on ice for 5 minutes followed by addition of 100 &#x003bc;l 1M NaOH and 30 &#x003bc;l methylchloroformate. The sample was then vortexed for 20 seconds followed by addition of 300 &#x003bc;l MTBE and vortexed for another 20 seconds followed by centrifugation at 10,000 g for 5 minutes at 4&#x000b0;C. 100 &#x003bc;l of the upper phase was then transferred in duplicate to GC vials for analysis. Samples were analyzed by GC-MS using a DB-35MS column (30m &#x000d7; 0.25 mm i.d. &#x000d7; 0.25 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m, Agilent J&#x00026;W Scientific) installed in an Agilent 7890B gas chromatograph (GC) interfaced with an Agilent 5977B mass spectrometer (MS) using the following temperature program: 50 &#x000b0;C initial with a hold time of 0.8 minutes, followed by an increase of 25 &#x000b0;C/min to 120 &#x000b0;C and then an increase of 100 &#x000b0;C/min to 280 &#x000b0;C. Samples were injected using split mode(25 ml/min split flow) and the mass spectrometer was operated in scan mode between 50 &#x02013; 150 AMU. Acetate was quantified from the internal acetate isotope standard and all other SCFAs were quantified from a standard curve extracted in parallel.</p><p id="P53">The isotopologue distributions of acetate and isovalerate were obtained via diethyl ether extraction and TBDMS derivatization of cecal water. Briefly, 10 &#x003bc;l concentrated HCL (37%) and 1ml Et<sub>2</sub>O was added to 100 &#x003bc;l cecal water followed by 10 minutes of vortexing and centrifugation at 18,000g at 15&#x000b0;C for 5 minutes. The upper phase was added to a new tube and the Et<sub>2</sub>O extraction step was repeated. 250 &#x003bc;l of the extract was aliquoted in triplicate to GC vials and 25 &#x003bc;ls MTBSTFA + 1% tBDMS was added followed by incubation at room temperature for 1 hour prior to GCMS analysis with the following temperature program: 80 &#x000b0;C initial with a hold time of 0.8 minutes, followed by an increase of 15 &#x000b0;C/min to 150 &#x000b0;C with a hold time of 2 minutes, then an increase by 50 &#x000b0;C/min to 280 &#x000b0;C. Samples were injected using split mode (25 ml/min split flow) and the mass spectrometer was operated in scan mode between 50 &#x02013; 500 AMU.</p></sec><sec id="S31"><title>Plasma <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O enrichment analysis</title><p id="P54">The <sup>2</sup>H labeling of water from samples or standards was determined via deuterium acetone exchange. 5 &#x003bc;l of sample or standard was reacted with 4 &#x003bc;l of 10N NaOH and 4 &#x003bc;l of a 5% (v/v) solution of acetone in acetonitrile for 24 hours. Acetone was extracted by the addition of 600 ul chloroform and 0.5 g Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> followed by vigorous mixing. 100 &#x003bc;l of the chloroform was then transferred to a GC/MS vial. Acetone was measured using an Agilent DB-35MS column (30 m 3 0.25 mm i.d. x 0.25 &#x003bc;m, Agilent J&#x00026;W Scientific) installed in an Agilent 7890A gas chromatograph (GC) interfaced with an Agilent 5975C mass spectrometer (MS) with the following temperature program: 60 &#x000b0;C initial, increase by 20 &#x000b0;C/min to 100 &#x000b0;C, increase by 50 &#x000b0;C/min to 220 &#x000b0;C, and hold for 1 min. The split ratio was 40:1 with a helium flow of 1 ml/min. Acetone eluted at approximately 1.5 min. The mass spectrometer was operated in the electron impact mode (70 eV). The mass ions 58 and 59 were integrated and the % M1 (m/z 59) calculated. Known standards were used to generate a standard curve and plasma % enrichment was determined from this. All samples were analyzed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="S32"><title><bold><italic>In vivo de novo</italic> lipogenesis calculations</bold>.</title><p id="P55">Calculation of the fraction of newly synthesized fatty acids (FNS) was based on the method described by Lee et al.<sup><xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup>, where FNS is described by the following equation:
<disp-formula id="FD2"><mml:math display="block" id="M2" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
Where ME is the average number of deuterium atoms incorporated per molecule (ME =1 &#x000d7; <italic>m</italic>1 + 2 &#x000d7; <italic>m</italic>2 +3 x <italic>m</italic>3 &#x02026; ), p is the deuterium enrichment in water and n is the maximum number of hydrogen atoms from water incorporated per molecule. N was determined using the equation:
<disp-formula id="FD3"><mml:math display="block" id="M3" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
As describd by Lee et al <sup><xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup> where q is the fraction of hydrogen atoms and p + q = 1. The molar amount of newly synthesized fatty acids (MNS) was determined by:
MNS = FNS x total fatty acid amount (nmoles/mg tissue).</p></sec><sec id="S33"><title>LC/MS lipidomic analysis</title><p id="P56">Lipid extraction was carried out using a Folch-based methanol/chloroform/saline extraction at a ratio of 1:2:1 with the inclusion of C12:0 dodecylglycerol and hexadecanoic acid-d<sub>31</sub> as internal standards. The methanol phase was washed a second time with chloroform after addition of 1 &#x003bc;l formic acid. Metabolite separation was achieved with a Luna reverse-phase C5 column (50 &#x000d7; 4.6 mm, with 5-&#x003bc;m-diameter particles; Phenomenex). Mobile phase A was composed of a 95:5 ratio of water:methanol, and mobile phase B consisted of isopropanol, methanol, and water in a 60:35:5 ratio. Solvent modifiers 0.1% formic acid with 5 mM ammonium formate and 0.1% ammonium hydroxide were used to assist ion formation and to improve the LC resolution in both positive and negative ionization modes, respectively. The flow rate for each run started at 0.1 mL/min for 5 min to alleviate backpressure associated with injecting chloroform. The gradient started at 0% B and increased linearly to 100% B over the course of 45 min with a flow rate of 0.4 mL/min, followed by an isocratic gradient of 100% B for 17 min at 0.5 mL/min, before equilibrating for 8 min at 0% B with a flow rate of 0.5 mL/min. MS analysis was performed with an electrospray ionization (ESI) source on an Agilent 6430 QQQ LC-MS/MS. The capillary voltage was set to 3.0 kV, and the fragmentor voltage was set to 100 V. The drying gas temperature was 350 &#x000b0;C, the drying gas flow rate was 10 L/min, and the nebulizer pressure was 35 psi. Representative lipids were quantified by SRM of the transition from precursor to product ions at associated optimized collision energies as previously described<sup><xref rid="R58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup>. Briefly, for the SRM transitions where the transition of parent masses to the loss of the headgroup (e.g. loss of phosphocholine from phosphatidylcholine) is monitored, the acyl chain specificities were determined from previously described procedures<sup><xref rid="R58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup>. For phospholipids such as PCs and PEs, the fatty acid acyl chain composition was determined from phospholipids using a mobile phase containing both ammonium hydroxide and formic acid and monitored the fatty acid fragmentations from [M-H+HCO2H] m/z at 40 V collision energy in negative ionization mode. For other phospholipids such as PAs and PIs, the fatty acid fragmentations from [M-H] m/z at 40 V collision energy in negative ionization mode in mobile phase containing just ammonium hydroxide were monitored. The identifying ion and the M+4(mass increment of 4) ion of each lipid was monitored and relative abundance was determined by integrating the area under the curve followed by normalization to internal standard values. Significant incorporation of U<sup>13</sup>C valine into lipids was determined by comparing the relative abundance of the M+4 ion of each lipid species targeted in [U<sup>13</sup>C<sub>5</sub>]valine traced cells versus cells that had no tracer added (no trace) via fold change differences and students t-test. Percentage enrichment of each lipid species was determined via:
<disp-formula id="FD4"><mml:math display="block" id="M4" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>%</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mprescripts/><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>13</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mprescripts/><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>13</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mprescripts/><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mprescripts/><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mmultiscripts><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
Where M<sub>4</sub> is the M+4 abundance of each lipid, M<sub>0</sub> is the identifying ion abundance and <sup>13</sup>C and <sup>12</sup>C denote cells cultured in [U<sup>13</sup>C<sub>5</sub>]valine and <sup>12</sup>C valine respectively.</p></sec><sec id="S34"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="P57">All results shown as mean &#x000b1; SEM. <italic>P</italic> values were calculated using Student two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test unless otherwise specified; *, <italic>P</italic> value between 0.01 and 0.05; **, <italic>P</italic> value between 0.001 and 0.01; ***, <italic>P</italic> value &#x0003c;0.001. T-tests were carried out in GraphPad Prism, version 7. Errors associated with ISA of lipogenesis are 95% confidence intervals determined via sensitivity analysis. All cell culture experiments were replicated at least 3 independent times.</p></sec><sec id="S35"><title>Data Availability.</title><p id="P58">The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>1</label><media xlink:href="NIHMS1502614-supplement-1.pdf" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d36e1878" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S36"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="P59">This work was supported, in part, by US National Institutes of Health (NIH) grants R01CA188652 (C.M.M.), NIH R01CA172667 (D.K.N), P01-HL110900 (PC) and R01-HL126945 (PC), a Searle Scholar Award (C.M.M.), a Camille and Henry Dreyfus Teacher-Scholar Award (C.M.M.), an NSF CAREER Award (#1454425 to C.M.M.), and an Ajinomoto Innovation Alliance Program Grant (C.M.M). The project was funded (in part) by a seed grant made available through the UC San Diego Larsson-Rosenquist Foundation Mother-Milk-Infant Center of Research Excellence (M.W). J.S.G. is supported by AHA award 18CDA34080527. This material is the result of work supported with resources and the use of facilities at the VA San Diego Medical Center. The contents do not represent the views of the U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs or the United States Government. We would like to thank Dr. Mari Gantner for helping with primary brown adipose tissue isolation and culture.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><p id="P60">Competing interests</p><p id="P61">The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></fn><fn id="FN2"><p id="P62">Author contributions</p><p id="P63">M.W. and C.M.M. conceived and designed the study. C.R.G. carried out knock down and analysis of ACAD enzymes and assisted with design and execution of all 3T3L1 experiments; L.S.R. and D.K.N. carried out lipidomic analysis of <sup>13</sup>C traced adipocytes; and J.M., Y.M.L. and J.S.A. provided germ-free and SPF samples. T.P.C and S.A.P isolated and cultured human primary cells. N.M. and J.M.G. assisted with GC/MS analysis of <italic>in vivo</italic> samples; J.D.H. carried out gene expression analysis of tissue samples, J.S.G and D.A.G. carried out D<sub>2</sub>O thermo-variation experiment in mice. P.C. carried out <italic>in vivo</italic> oxygen tension and arterial blood flow studies in mice. M.W. performed all other experiments. R.L designed and executed the clinical study of NAFL and NASH patients. M.W. and C.M.M. wrote the paper with help from all authors.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Newgard</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>A branched-chain amino acid-related metabolic signature that differentiates obese and lean humans and contributes to insulin resistance</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19356713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Metabolite profiles and the risk of developing diabetes</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>448</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21423183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tonjes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>BCAT1 promotes cell proliferation through amino acid catabolism in gliomas carrying wild-type IDH1</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>901</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23793099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Overmyer</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Maximal oxidative capacity during exercise is associated with skeletal muscle fuel selection and dynamic changes in mitochondrial protein acetylation</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>468</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25738461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>She</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peroni</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>
<article-title>Adipose tissue branched chain amino acid (BCAA) metabolism modulates circulating BCAA levels</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>285</volume>, <fpage>11348</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20093359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Crown</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marze</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Antoniewicz</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<article-title>Catabolism of Branched Chain Amino Acids Contributes Significantly to Synthesis of Odd-Chain and Even-Chain Fatty Acids in 3T3-L1 Adipocytes</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>e0145850</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26710334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Branched-chain amino acid catabolism fuels adipocyte differentiation and lipogenesis</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26571352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ran-Ressler</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Brenna</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<article-title>Branched-chain fatty acid content of foods and estimated intake in the USA</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source>
<volume>112</volume>, <fpage>565</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24830474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>West</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Koulman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<article-title>A review of odd-chain fatty acid metabolism and the role of pentadecanoic Acid (c15:0) and heptadecanoic Acid (c17:0) in health and disease</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>2425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25647578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mercier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dominguez-Cuevas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Errington</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<article-title>Crucial role for membrane fluidity in proliferation of primitive cells</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22832271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kniazeva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sewell</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Lipid-TORC1 Pathway Promotes Neuronal Development and Foraging Behavior under Both Fed and Fasted Conditions in C. elegans</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>260</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25892013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Kneebone</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<article-title>Fatty acid composition of human colostrum and mature breast milk</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>252</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage> (<year>1981</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7211726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grigor</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dunckley</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Purves</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>
<article-title>The synthesis of the branched-chain fatty acids of rat skin surface lipid</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>218</volume>, <fpage>389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage> (<year>1970</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5499196</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ran-Ressler</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Devapatla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Brenna</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>
<article-title>Branched chain fatty acids are constituents of the normal healthy newborn gastrointestinal tract</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Res</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18614964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Adipose tissue monomethyl branched-chain fatty acids and insulin sensitivity: Effects of obesity and weight loss</article-title>. <source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25328153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mika</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>A comprehensive study of serum odd- and branched-chain fatty acids in patients with excess weight</article-title>. <source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1669</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27355152</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lackey</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Regulation of adipose branched-chain amino acid catabolism enzyme expression and cross-adipose amino acid flux in human obesity</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source>
<volume>304</volume>, <fpage>E1175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23512805</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kishimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hignite</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Biermann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<article-title>Branched-chain and odd-numbered fatty acids and aldehydes in the nervous system of a patient with deranged vitamin B 12 metabolism</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage> (<year>1973</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4701555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>RU</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Inhibition of acetyl-CoA carboxylase suppresses fatty acid synthesis and tumor growth of non-small-cell lung cancer in preclinical models</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1108</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1119</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27643638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hiltunen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Mitochondrial fatty acid synthesis type II: more than just fatty acids</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>284</volume>, <fpage>9011</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19028688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Tracing compartmentalized NADPH metabolism in the cytosol and mitochondria of mammalian cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24882210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Horning</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karmen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Vagelos</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
<article-title>Fatty acid synthesis in adipose tissue. II. Enzymatic synthesis of branched chain and odd-numbered fatty acids</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>236</volume>, <fpage>669</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage> (<year>1961</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13715907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oku</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Chinen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<article-title>Precursor role of branched-chain amino acids in the biosynthesis of iso and anteiso fatty acids in rat skin</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1214</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage> (<year>1994</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7918610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Human fetal intestinal epithelial cells metabolize and incorporate branched chain fatty acids in a structure specific manner</article-title>. <source>Prostaglandins Leukot Essent Fatty Acids</source>
<volume>116</volume>, <fpage>32</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28088292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Obayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Estrogen controls branched-chain amino acid catabolism in female rats</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>
<volume>134</volume>, <fpage>2628</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15465758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kaneda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<article-title>Iso- and anteiso-fatty acids in bacteria: biosynthesis, function, and taxonomic significance</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>288</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage> (<year>1991</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1886522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Macfarlane</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beatty</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<article-title>Estimation of short-chain fatty acid production from protein by human intestinal bacteria based on branched-chain fatty acid measurements</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiology Ecology</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage> (<year>1992</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Previs</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>New methodologies for studying lipid synthesis and turnover: looking backwards to enable moving forwards</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1842</volume>, <fpage>402</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23707557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abdelmagid</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Comprehensive profiling of plasma fatty acid concentrations in young healthy Canadian adults</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>e0116195</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25675440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sailer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Increased plasma citrulline in mice marks diet-induced obesity and may predict the development of the metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e63950</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23691124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Odd Chain Fatty Acids; New Insights of the Relationship Between the Gut Microbiota, Dietary Intake, Biosynthesis and Glucose Intolerance</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>44845</fpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28332596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eissing</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>De novo lipogenesis in human fat and liver is linked to ChREBP-beta and metabolic health</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>1528</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23443556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>A high-fat diet suppresses de novo lipogenesis and desaturation but not elongation and triglyceride synthesis in mice</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>2541</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25271296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sanchez-Gurmaches</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Brown Fat AKT2 Is a Cold-Induced Kinase that Stimulates ChREBP-Mediated De Novo Lipogenesis to Optimize Fuel Storage and Thermogenesis</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>209</lpage> e6 (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29153407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Violante</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Substrate specificity of human carnitine acetyltransferase: Implications for fatty acid and branched-chain amino acid metabolism</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1832</volume>, <fpage>773</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23485643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Initial quantitative proteomic map of 28 mouse tissues using the SILAC mouse</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23436904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trayhurn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>
<article-title>Hypoxia in adipose tissue: a basis for the dysregulation of tissue function in obesity?</article-title>
<source>Br J Nutr</source>
<volume>100</volume>, <fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18397542</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Robciuc</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>VEGFB/VEGFR1-Induced Expansion of Adipose Vasculature Counteracts Obesity and Related Metabolic Complications</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>712</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27076080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<article-title>Hypoxia is a potential risk factor for chronic inflammation and adiponectin reduction in adipose tissue of ob/ob and dietary obese mice</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source>
<volume>293</volume>, <fpage>E1118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17666485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mayers</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Tissue of origin dictates branched-chain amino acid metabolism in mutant Kras-driven cancers</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>353</volume>, <fpage>1161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27609895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>A branched-chain amino acid metabolite drives vascular fatty acid transport and causes insulin resistance</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>421</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26950361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>SIRT4 Is a Lysine Deacylase that Controls Leucine Metabolism and Insulin Secretion</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>838</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>855 e15</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28380376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hellerstein</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Neese</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<article-title>Model for measuring absolute rates of hepatic de novo lipogenesis and reesterification of free fatty acids</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol</source>
<volume>265</volume>, <fpage>E814</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage> (<year>1993</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8238508</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Brain insulin lowers circulating BCAA levels by inducing hepatic BCAA catabolism</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>898</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>909</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25307860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seiler</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Carnitine Acetyltransferase Mitigates Metabolic Inertia and Muscle Fatigue during Exercise</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26154055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>The Acetyl Group Buffering Action of Carnitine Acetyltransferase Offsets Macronutrient-Induced Lysine Acetylation of Mitochondrial Proteins</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26748706</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mardinoglu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Integration of clinical data with a genome-scale metabolic model of the human adipocyte</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>649</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23511207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kniazeva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Euler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<article-title>A branched-chain fatty acid is involved in post-embryonic growth control in parallel to the insulin receptor pathway and its biosynthesis is feedback-regulated in C. elegans</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>2102</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18676815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>BCFA suppresses LPS induced IL-8 mRNA expression in human intestinal epithelial cells</article-title>. <source>Prostaglandins Leukot Essent Fatty Acids</source>
<volume>116</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28088291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ran-Ressler</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Branched chain fatty acids reduce the incidence of necrotizing enterocolitis and alter gastrointestinal microbial ecology in a neonatal rat model</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e29032</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22194981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gantner</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hazen</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eury</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Kralli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<article-title>Complementary Roles of Estrogen-Related Receptors in Brown Adipocyte Thermogenic Function</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source>
<volume>157</volume>, <fpage>4770</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4781</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27763777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vacanti</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Regulation of substrate utilization by the mitochondrial pyruvate carrier</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source>
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25458843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cabrales</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>
<article-title>Plasma viscosity regulates systemic and microvascular perfusion during acute extreme anemic conditions</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol</source>
<volume>291</volume>, <fpage>H2445</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Decaris</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>Identifying nonalcoholic fatty liver disease patients with active fibrosis by measuring extracellular matrix remodeling rates in tissue and blood</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<volume>65</volume>, <fpage>78</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27706836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Des Rosiers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Previs</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>David</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Brunengraber</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<article-title>Correction of 13C mass isotopomer distributions for natural stable isotope abundance</article-title>. <source>J Mass Spectrom</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage> (<year>1996</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8799277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<article-title>INCA: a computational platform for isotopically non-stationary metabolic flux analysis</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>1333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24413674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>In vivo measurement of fatty acids and cholesterol synthesis using D2O and mass isotopomer analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol</source>
<volume>266</volume>, <fpage>E699</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>708</lpage> (<year>1994</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8203508</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Louie</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
<article-title>GSTP1 Is a Driver of Triple-Negative Breast Cancer Cell Metabolism and Pathogenicity</article-title>. <source>Cell Chem Biol</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27185638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Mammalian adipocytes synthesize mmBCFAs via fatty acid synthase.</title><p id="P64"><bold>a</bold>. mmBCFA abundance in differentiating 3T3L1 adipocytes. <bold>b</bold>. mmBCFA abundance in 3T3L1 adipocytes differentiated for 7 days +/&#x02212; 500 nM B12. Two-tailed students <italic>t</italic>-test was performed on three cellular replicates (p=0.000019) with no adjustment for multiple comparisons. <bold>c</bold>. Atom-transition map demonstrating isotope incorporation into <italic>de novo</italic> synthesized fatty acids from [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub>]glucose. Closed circles indicate <sup>13</sup>C carbon. <bold>d</bold>. Isotopologue distribution of iso-C16:0 from [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub>]glucose traced 3T3L1 cells. <bold>e.</bold> % enrichment from [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub>]isoleucine-derived acetyl-CoA (M1-M2 only) in 3T3L1 adipocytes +/&#x02212; 100 nM ND646 for 24 hours. <bold>f</bold>. Atom-transition map depicting transfer of isotope [3-<sup>2</sup>H]glucose through glycolysis, the pentose phosphate pathway and reductive biosynthesis. Open circles indicate carbon and small red circles indicate deuterium label from [3-<sup>2</sup>H]glucose. <bold>g</bold>. Contribution from [3-<sup>2</sup>H]glucose labelled NADPH to fatty acid de novo synthesis determined via ISA. 3T3L1 adipocytes cultured in tracer for 72 hours. <bold>h</bold>, Iso-C16:0 levels as % total FA in pooled CRISPR/Cas9 FASN KO 3T3L1 adipocytes following addition of isobutyrate for 24 hours. <bold>i.</bold> Relative abundances of mmBCFAs and C16:0 in differentiated 3T3L1s following addition of isobutyrate for 24 hours. Two-tailed students <italic>t</italic>-test was performed on three cellular replicates for each comparison with no adjustment for multiple comparisons. All data are presented as means &#x000b1; SEM with dot plots overlaid except for <bold>g</bold>, where 95% confidence intervals from ISA model are shown. All data are representative of three cellular replicates, and each experiment was repeated 3 independent times with the exception of <bold>h</bold>, where two separate infections were carried out. The same result was obtained in each independent experiment. *p&#x0003c;0.05, **p&#x0003c;0.01, ***p&#x0003c;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-1502614-f0001"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>BCAA catabolic intermediates drive mmBCFA synthesis.</title><p id="P65"><bold>a.</bold> Pathway depicting BCAA catabolism and mmBCFA synthesis. <bold>b-d</bold>. Isotopologue distributions of <bold>b</bold>, iso-C16:0 from [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>5</sub>]valine <bold>c</bold>, iso-C17:0 from [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub>]leucine and <bold>d</bold>, anteiso-C17:0 from [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>6</sub>]isoleucine. Representative data from three cell replicates in <bold>b-d</bold>. <bold>e-g</bold>. Relative abundance of <bold>e</bold>, iso-C16:0 <bold>f</bold>, iso-C17:0 and <bold>g</bold>, anteiso-C17:0 following knock down of ACAD enzymes. Representative data from six cell replicates in <bold>e-g. h.</bold> Relative mRNA expression. Representative data shown from three cell replicates. All experiments are carried out in 3T3L1 adipocytes. All experiments were repeated 3 independent times with similar results. Data are presented as means &#x000b1; SEM with dot plots overlaid (<bold>b-d, h</bold>) or box (25<sup>th</sup> to 75<sup>th</sup> percentile with median line) and whiskers (min to max values) (<bold>e-g</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-1502614-f0002"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>mmBCFAs are <italic>de novo</italic> synthesized <italic>in vivo</italic> a-b.</title><p id="P66">Abundance of <bold>a</bold>, iso-C16:0, and <bold>b</bold>, iso-C17:0, in various tissues from C57BL/6J male (n=6) and female mice (n=6). <bold>c</bold>. Plasma concentration of total hydrolyzed mmBCFAs from C57BL/6J male mice (n=8) following removal of food at time 0 (7 am) and sampled at 2hrs, 6hrs, 12hrs and 24hrs. <bold>d</bold>. Incorporation of <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O into newly synthesized fatty acids. <bold>e-f</bold>. Fractional synthesis of fatty acids in <bold>e</bold>, iWAT, and <bold>f</bold>, BAT of germ free (n=6) and SPF mice (n=6). <bold>g-h</bold>. Amount of newly synthesized fatty acids present in <bold>g</bold>, iWAT and <bold>h</bold>, BAT of germ free (n=6) and SPF mice (n=6). <bold>i</bold>. Deuterium enrichment of plasma FAs in NAFLD patients (n=16) normalized to the area under the curve of plasma <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O levels from day 0 to day 21 for each patient. Two-tailed students <italic>t</italic>-test was performed for each comparison in this figure with no adjustment for multiple comparisons. Data are presented as means &#x000b1; SEM (<bold>c</bold>), means &#x000b1; SD with dot plots overlaid (<bold>i</bold>), or box (25<sup>th</sup> to 75<sup>th</sup> percentile with median line) and whiskers (min to max values) (<bold>a</bold>-<bold>b</bold>,<bold>e</bold>-<bold>h</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-1502614-f0003"/></fig><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>BCAA flux to mmBCFAs is decreased by diet-induced obesity.</title><p id="P67"><bold>a</bold>. Relative abundances of FAs in iWAT from C57BL/6J mice fed HFD (n=4) or LFD (n=5) for 15 weeks. <bold>b</bold>. Total FAs abundances in plasma from C57BL/6J mice fed HFD (n=8) or LFD (n=8) for 15 weeks. <bold>c-f</bold>, <sup>13</sup>C enrichment in specified metabolite from HFD or LFD with 25% of valine and leucine supplied as [U<sup>13</sup>C,<sup>15</sup>N]isotope.<bold>c</bold>. Citrate % <sup>13</sup>C enrichment. N=8 for all comparisons except LFD iWAT (n=7), eWAT (n=7), BAT (n=7), heart (n=5) and HFD iWAT (n=4), BAT (n=7), heart (n=4). <bold>d</bold>. <sup>13</sup>C molar enrichment of C16:0. N=8 for all comparisons except LFD eWAT (n=7), heart (n=5) and HFD iWAT (n=7). <bold>e</bold>. Isotopologue distribution of iso-C16:0 from [U-<sup>13</sup>C<sub>5</sub>]valine (HFD n=8, LFD n=8). <bold>f</bold>. <sup>13</sup>C molar enrichment of iso-C16:0. N=8 for all comparisons except HFD iWAT (n=7), liver (n=5) and brain (n=6). Two-tailed students <italic>t</italic>-test was performed for each comparison in this figure with no adjustment for multiple comparisons. Data are presented as means &#x000b1; SEM with dot plot overlaid (<bold>a-d, f</bold>) or box (25<sup>th</sup> to 75<sup>th</sup> percentile with median line) and whiskers (min to max values) (<bold>e</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-1502614-f0004"/></fig><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><title>Adipose tissue mmBCFA synthesis is facilitated by CrAT a-b.</title><p id="P68">Fold difference in the levels of newly synthesized FAs present in <bold>a</bold>, liver and <bold>b</bold>, iWAT. LFD (n=6) and HFD (n=4) for all comparisons in <bold>a-b</bold>. <bold>c</bold>. <italic>De novo</italic> lipogenic turnover of iso-C16:0 across the primary lipogenic tissues. <bold>d</bold>. <italic>De novo</italic> lipogenic turnover of C16:0 across the primary lipogenic tissues. LFD (n=6) and HFD (n=4) for all comparisons in <bold>c-d</bold> except LFD BAT iso C16:0. P values indicate intra-tissue comparison between HFD and LFD. <bold>e</bold>. Amount of newly synthesized FAs in BAT of mice exposed to thermoneutral (30&#x000b0;C), room temperature (22&#x000b0;C), or acclimatized to severe cold (6&#x000b0;C) over 1 month, (n=6 per group). <bold>f</bold>. <italic>Crat</italic> expression relative to liver in tissues from male C57BL/6J mice (n=4). <bold>g</bold>. relative abundance of total FAs in pooled CRISPR/Cas9 <italic>Crat</italic> KO 3T3L1 adipocytes. Representative data from three cell replicates. Three independent infections have been carried out with the same result. Data is presented as box (25<sup>th</sup> to 75<sup>th</sup> percentile with median line) and whiskers (min to max values) (<bold>a</bold>-<bold>f</bold>) or means &#x000b1; SEM with dot plots overlaid (<bold>g</bold>). Two-tailed students <italic>t</italic>-test was performed for each comparison in this figure with no adjustment for multiple comparisons. *p&#x0003c;0.05, **p&#x0003c;0.01, ***p&#x0003c;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-1502614-f0005"/></fig><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><title>Hypoxia suppresses BCAA catabolism and mmBCFA synthesis in adipocytes.</title><p id="P69"><bold>a</bold>. Volcano plot of changes in metabolite abundance in 3T3L1 cells exposed to hypoxia (1% O<sub>2</sub>) or normoxia for 48 hours. 12 cell replicates. <bold>b</bold>. Glucose and amino acid uptake by 3T3L1 cells in hypoxia (1%) or normoxia. 14 cell replicates for lactate and glucose, 6 cell replicates for glutamine and glutamate, 3 cell replicates for leucine, isoleucine and valine. Two-tailed students <italic>t</italic>-test was performed for each comparison in <bold>a</bold> and <bold>b</bold> with no adjustment for multiple comparisons. <bold>c</bold>. Mole percent enrichment (MPE) of TCA intermediates from [U-<sup>13</sup>C] BCAAs in 3T3L1s following 24 hours of tracing in hypoxia (1%) or normoxia. <bold>d</bold>. Relative contribution of different substrates to lipogenic acetyl-CoA in 3T3L1s as determined by ISA following 24 hours of tracing in hypoxia (1%) or normoxia. <bold>e</bold>. % of each FA newly synthesized over 24 hours in hypoxia (1%) or normoxia. Three cell replicates are shown in <bold>c-e</bold>. All experiments in figure have been repeated 3 independent times with the same results. Data are presented as means &#x000b1; SEM with dot plots overlaid with exception of <bold>b</bold> where data is presented as box (25<sup>th</sup> to 75<sup>th</sup> percentile with median line) and whiskers (min to max values) and <bold>d</bold>-<bold>e</bold>, mean +/&#x02212; 95% confidence interval.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-1502614-f0006"/></fig></floats-group></article>