<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Perhaps the most extensively studied stilbene is resveratrol, existing as two cis-trans isomers (
 <bold>33</bold> and 
 <bold>34</bold>), 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-03846-f008">Figure 8</xref>. It is a constituent of red grapes and wines, and in recent decades, it has received considerable research attention as a molecule with alleged antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activity, the ability to inhibit platelet aggregation and to afford protection against cancer and cardiovascular problems. Additionally, targeting cancer stem cells (CSCs) in colorectal cancer (CRC) enhances CRC chemosensitivity to chemotherapeutic agents such as 5-fluorouracil, increases apoptosis and supresses migration and metastasis [
 <xref rid="B88-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Dietary sources of resveratrol include wild blueberries, mulberries, and raspberries and peanuts. Commercial resveratrol is obtained from Japanese knotweed (
 <italic>Reynoutria japonica</italic>; Polygonaceae) and is sold as a dietary supplement. Despite its popularity with the public and the scientific community, as well as its reputation as a miracle molecule offering tremendous benefits to human health and well-being, it still has not been accepted as an effective therapeutic agent in medical practice in the U.S. Though showing promise in in vitro studies and animal models, resveratrol has failed to provide any significant therapeutic advantage over placebo in human clinical trials of cancer, cardiovascular disorders, metabolic diseases including diabetes and obesity, nor was it shown to have positive effects on longevity [
 <xref rid="B91-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="B92-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,
 <xref rid="B93-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>,
 <xref rid="B94-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. With regard to antioxidant activity, various studies have pointed out that resveratrol behaves as a strong pro-oxidant in vivo [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B95-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Other problems that hinder its clinical use is its poor water solubility and high rate of metabolism and excretion [
 <xref rid="B96-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Because of the low bioavailability, some studies utilized high doses of resveratrol, which resulted in significant side-effects, including diarrhoea, nausea and weight loss [
 <xref rid="B97-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,
 <xref rid="B98-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. To make things worse, resveratrol has been flagged as a pan-assay interference compound (PAIN) (compare with curcumin) that can produce false positive results in many different laboratory assays [
 <xref rid="B99-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. Analogues of resveratrol with better bioavailability are now in the process of development and clinical testing [
 <xref rid="B100-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. One current research focus for resveratrol is its ability to reduce secondary damage in stroke and traumatic CNS injury [
 <xref rid="B101-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>], to slow down cognitive impairment in Alzheimer’s disease [
 <xref rid="B97-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>], and preventive in skin cancer [
 <xref rid="B102-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. Nevertheless, the results are still preliminary.
</p>
