<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In some cases, the hazardous components in the oil have not been identified yet. For instance, carrot (
 <italic>Daucus carota</italic> L.) seed oil has GRAS status; however, it may interfere with gestation and should be avoided altogether during pregnancy and breastfeeding. It is worth mentioning that the wild carrot plant is reputed as a contraceptive agent. Dong and colleagues have reported that carrot seed oil caused antigestational effects in rats and mice [
 <xref rid="B212-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">212</xref>]. Subcutaneous injection of carrot seed EO (2.5–5 mL/kg) to female rats and mice inhibited implantation and prevented progesterone synthesis [
 <xref rid="B213-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>]. Another example is oregano (
 <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> L.) oil [
 <xref rid="B53-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Although oregano oil has a GRAS status, it is embryotoxic. Orally delivered 
 <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> EO to pregnant mice (about 150 mg/kg for two weeks) caused an increase in the rate of embryonic cell death [
 <xref rid="B202-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">202</xref>]. Additionally, zedoary (
 <italic>Curcuma zedoaria</italic> (Christm.) Roscoe) oil has a GRAS status but its consumption can interfere with gestation and can induce abortion [
 <xref rid="B22-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. There was obvious embryotoxicity for zedoary EO ex vivo and reproductive toxicity in animal and developmental experiments [
 <xref rid="B14-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B174-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>]. In addition, the oil was anti-angiogenic in mice [
 <xref rid="B174-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>], suggesting a strong link between its anti-angiogenic and embryotoxic effects [
 <xref rid="B14-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Chinese zedoary EO (i.p., 300 mg/kg) prevented implantation in a dose-dependent manner in female rats on gestational days 7–9 and prevented about 77% of pregnancies. When administered intra-vaginally to female rabbits at 60 or 400 mg/kg/day on gestational days 5–9 and 2–4, a steam-distilled zedoary EO prevented 16% and 100% of pregnancies, respectively [
 <xref rid="B22-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>C. zedoaria</italic> rhizome (10 g/kg/day for 20 days) demonstrated reproductive toxicity in pregnant mice [
 <xref rid="B214-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>]. The embryotoxic effect of zedoary EO was attributed to its sesquiterpenoids, which can block VEGF-mediated angiogenesis [
 <xref rid="B14-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Nevertheless, there is no direct evidence to link any of the oil components to its antifertility effect. Moreover, zedoary rhizome decoctions and ethanol extracts also have antifertility effects [
 <xref rid="B215-ijms-22-02380" ref-type="bibr">215</xref>].
</p>
