<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">Electrospinning is a simple and reliable technique for preparing nanofibers and can be used for a variety of polymer materials. The resulting nanofibers have a smooth surface and controlled morphology
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup>. Coaxial electrospinning can produce micro/nano fibers with a core-shell structure and highly different compositions, which is an improvement over simple electrospinning
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>. The nanofiber particles created by electrospinning and coaxial electrospinning are ideal for many applications such as biosensors, enzyme immobilization, drug delivery, scaffold tissue engineering, wound healing, and so on
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>. The difference is that casting involves the application of a polymer solution on a substrate and then removal of the solvent to cause molecular orientation of the polymer molecules, resulting in film formation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>
 </sup>. However, studies on the characterization of nanoparticles polymer films fabricated by different methods, especially coaxial electrospinning have been scarce. As a biopolymer, we selected gelatin obtained from flounder, which has been FDA approved. 
 <italic class="italic">Paralichthys orbignyanus</italic>, also known as the flounder, is an economically important fish that lives in temperate water and rich in polyunsaturated fatty acids. Current research on flounders has mainly focused on farming, breeding and rough machining
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup>. A large amount of waste materials, such as fish skin and bones, are left during the processing of flounder, especially the bones, which account for about 40% of the whole fish. Therefore, flounder bones were used as the material from which to extract and purify gelatin by the hot-water extraction method.
</p>
