<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">Edible films used in drug and food packaging are biodegradable, naturally renewable and edible biopolymers. Polysaccharides and proteins are used in various fields as a basic excellent macromolecule substance. The typical combination gelatin-chitosan (GC) biocomposite membrane is a type of “green packaging” material with excellent development potential that has been studied by some researchers
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>. Gelatin molecules are rich in biological functional groups such as carboxyl, hydroxyl, and amino groups that have excellent biocompatibility and are potential film-forming materials. Chitosan is the only natural polysaccharide with a large amount of basic aminopolysaccharide, which is non-toxic, degradable, bacteriostatic, and biocompatible and has good film forming properties
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup>. In recent years, to change the performance and characterization of GC films, functional ingredients such as inorganic salts, phenolic compounds, rosmarinic acid and ginger essential oils have been studied by some researchers
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>. However, docosahexaenoic acid (DHA) combined with polysaccharides-proteins has not been studied in recent reports. DHA is a major substance in the growth and maintenance of nervous system cells and an important component of the brain and retina
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>. Supplementing ω-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids can effectively reduce some risk of disease in the long term. The scientific novelty of the work is that we found that fish oil full of ω-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids combined with protein to form the emulsions but seldom films
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, we selected DHA algal oil powder as the core material and functional ingredient, combined with coaxial electrospinning and other processes to prepare membrane materials with good biocompatibility and safety and then to compare their structure and physicochemical properties; we hope the result can be used in the food packaging and biomedical fields.
</p>
