<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The DWH oil spill occurred in 2010, when the use of high-throughput sequencing was on the rise. The new techniques of microbial ecology were comprehensively applied after the event to reveal the impacts of the oil spill on bacterial communities and the responses of different bacterial phyla (Gutierrez, 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). 454 pyrosequencing of the 16S rRNA gene was the first NGS technique applied in this event (Bælum et al., 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), providing information on the succession of bacterial communities. The results, based on the NGS data, specifically showed the increase in the bacterial phyla 
 <italic>Colwelliaceae</italic> and 
 <italic>Oceanospirillales</italic>, which was consistent with the results from 16S rRNA gene-based clone library and PhyloChip (Hazen et al., 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Redmond and Valentine, 
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). The results were based on the analysis of 148,276 quality-filtered reads from 16 samples, whereas the first study after the spill which applied 16S rRNA gene based clone library only generated 250 high qualitied sequences from three samples (Hazen et al., 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The great amount of sequencing could produce more useful information for revealing the bacterial responses to the oil spill. Illumina sequencing was also used in later studies (Mason et al., 
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2014b</xref>; Simister et al., 
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). For instance, by analyzing massive amounts of data generated by Illumina sequencing, Simister et al. (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) found that the dominant bacteria in both sediment and floc samples were 
 <italic>Proteobacteria</italic> (55–64%). They also found that the bacterial composition of the floc samples (mostly aerobic or facultative aerobic phylotypes including 
 <italic>Rhizobiales, Rhodobacterales, Sphingomonadales, Rickettsiales, Alteromonadales</italic>, and 
 <italic>Pseudomonadales</italic>) was different from those in the sediment samples (aforementioned aerobic species and anaerobic phylotypes such as 
 <italic>Desulfobacterales, Desulfuromonadales</italic>, and 
 <italic>Desulfarculales</italic>).
</p>
