<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this equation, observed mortality was the toxicity observed experimentally in combinations of plant oils and natural pyrethrins at either specific dose of plant essential oils (2 and 10 µg/insect). Expected mortality was the additive sum of the observed mortality for natural pyrethrins alone and each plant essential oil alone. Values &gt; 20 represent synergistic mixtures, −20 ≤ values ≤ 20 represent additive mixtures and values &lt; −20 represent mixtures that are antagonistic. An LD
 <sub>25</sub> of natural pyrethrins was used alone or in combination with discrete doses of plant essential oils to calculate co-toxicity values. LD
 <sub>50</sub> and LD
 <sub>25</sub> values for natural pyrethrins were derived from Probit analysis (Finney et al. 1952 [
 <xref rid="B17-insects-12-00154" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]), using a PROC Probit calculation with a control correction option (OPTC) (to account for control mortality) performed in SAS 9.4 (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, NC, USA). After synergistic combinations were identified using the co-toxicity factor method, conventional synergism ratios (LD
 <sub>50</sub> of natural pyrethrins alone ÷ LD
 <sub>50</sub> of natural pyrethrins + a sublethal dose of essential oil) were calculated to evaluate the degree of synergism produced. These experiments were done for comparison and to further evaluate the performance of the co-toxicity factor method outlined by Mansour et al. 1966 [
 <xref rid="B10-insects-12-00154" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. To compare effects at discrete doses to one another or between those and control, an ANOVA (α = 0.05) with a Tukey’s post-test was used with an α value of 0.05. For synergism assessments at discrete doses of plant essential oils, natural pyrethrins were applied in every cohort to obtain a relevant percentage mortality for the LD
 <sub>25</sub> of natural pyrethrins for each cohort. As the response to natural pyrethrins differed slightly in every cohort, this approach ensured that cohort bias was accounted for in all comparisons in the analysis. As a result, the responses for natural pyrethrins alone and plant essential oils alone were adequately taken into account in the co-toxicity calculations for each combination of oil and natural pyrethrins using the aforementioned equation.
</p>
