<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="ab005">
 <p>People use medicinal plants as diet, and for treatment of infectious and noninfectious diseases and they use brief procedures like frying and cooking to do so. Medicinal plants; 
  <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic>, 
  <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic>, and 
  <italic>Lepidium sativum</italic> which is believed to have active components that help to treat and manage various diseases were investigated for their antibacterial activities against 
  <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
  <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhi, 
  <italic>Streptococcus agalactiae</italic> and 
  <italic>Shigella boydii</italic>. Solvent methanol and aqueous were used for extraction of crudes by means of maceration. Susceptibility testing was determined by using disc diffusion method and Minimum inhibitory concentration was determined by broth dilution method. Heat treated plant material activity against test pathogen was aimed to identify resistance capacity of plant material at different interval of time and temperature. All plant extracts under study was active against all tested pathogen after exposure to 45 °C for 30 min. The antibacterial activities of the non-heat-treated extracts of 
  <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic> were relatively low; the results of this study show that extracts of 
  <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic> have better residual antibacterial activities. Methanol extracts of all plant leaves showed highest activity as compared to the aqueous extracts. This is probably assigning the choice of extraction solvent for extracting desired active phytochemical from plants. Many of the people in the study area were illiterate and they did not have awareness about the ways use of medicinal plants. They use the medicinal plants by cooking and frying for different purposes. In the main, plant material can be affected as the temperature of treatment is increases with respect to various times of exposures.
 </p>
</abstract>
