<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since it has been well known that hypertriglyceridemia is one of the most important factors for CVD development, a strong effort has gone into prevention strategies including a phytochemical diet. Additionally, studies showed that daily drinking of MO tea may ameliorate metabolic parameters through reduction of serum lipid concentration and lipid peroxidation. Although the lipid-lowering mechanism of lemon balm remains unclear, it is proposed that the presence of quercetin is responsible for this pharmacological effect (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Jun et al., 2012</xref>). In addition, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Bolkent et al. (2005)</xref> reported that besides the reduction of total cholesterol (TC), MOE also possesses the ability to increase glutathione (GSH) levels in the liver tissue. However, the hypolipidemic effects of MOE are likely related to its powerful antioxidant properties due to lemon balm containing phenolic compounds, as the most important antioxidant agents (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">Zarei et al., 2015</xref>). It is assumed that the presence of RA, a derivate of phenylpropanoid, is associated with its antioxidant properties that are up to 10 times stronger than the antioxidant action of vitamin C (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">Shakeri et al., 2016</xref>). Furthermore, lemon balm extract acts as a potential scavenger of both synthetic and natural free radicals during their early or later stages of formation (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Pereira et al., 2009</xref>). Compounds of MO possess the ability to bind to acetylcholine, as well as inhibit enzyme acetylcholinesterase, which in turn leads to improved cognitive function such as memory (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">Rostami et al., 2010</xref>). Finally, the researchers stand out that MOE prevents diseases that are related to oxidative stress including diabetes, CVDs, or neurodegenerative disorders such as Parkinson and Alzheimer diseases (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Pereira et al., 2009</xref>). Daily intake of MO at low doses improves glucose tolerance and adjusted gene expression that is involved in hepatic gluconeogenesis. All together, these mechanisms contribute to the hypoglycemic properties of this herb (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Chung et al., 2010</xref>). When it comes to anxiolytic effects of MOE, the results of several studies implicate that lower doses of aqueous extract have anxiolytic properties; whereas applied in higher doses, it has a sedative effect (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">Zarei et al., 2015</xref>). In some European countries, this herb is traditionally used for relaxation, especially when a disturbance occurs in the first stage of sleep. Also, it is found that MOE can reduce agitation, as well as muscle tone in patients with Alzheimer disease (
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">Soulimani et al., 1991</xref>). Traditionally, use of lemon balm in mentally ill patients results in significant improvement in irritability, insomnia, headaches, and heart disease (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2005</xref>). All of these beneficial effects can be attributed to the presence of significant amounts of rosmarinic, oleanolic, ursolic acid, and triterpenoids in the herb, assuming that all of these active principles can inhibit γ-aminobutyric acid (GABA) transport activity and increase the level of this neurotransmitter in the brain (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Awad et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Ibarra et al., 2010</xref>).
</p>
