<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>GA is mediated by the deposition of MSU crystals in the joints of patients with hyperuricemia [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Our study found that MSU induced rat paw thickness and reached a peak at 24 h and then gradually decreased, which is in accordance with the study of Dhanasekar et al. [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Besides, MSU resulted in enlarged joint space, inflammatory cell infiltration, and cartilage erosion. The above results indicate the successful establishment of the GA rat model. Moreover, It is generally agreed that MSU induces the generation of some proinflammatory mediators (such as TNF-
 <italic>α</italic>, IL-1
 <italic>β</italic>, IL-6, and IL-18) and can activate proinflammatory pathways in chondrocytes and synoviocytes [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. We demonstrated that GA increases these levels in serum of rats, which was in line with the above finding. In addition, the interplay of MSU and macrophages in the joints results in NLRP3 activation, which triggers the cleavage of pro-caspase-1 to caspase-1 [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Caspase-1 cleaves pro-IL-1
 <italic>β</italic> to generate active IL-1
 <italic>β</italic>, which is the most important inflammatory downstream mediator in GA [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Also, neutrophil elastase, a granule serine protease, hydrolytically degrades connective tissue components including elastin and proteoglycans, as well as collagen [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Infiltration of neutrophil has been reported to cut precursor IL-1
 <italic>β</italic>, facilitating more neutrophils to invade and aggravate the joint, which released excessive elastase to lead to tissue damage [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Dhanasekar and Rasool [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] demonstrated that morin, a bioflavonol, inhibited MSU crystal-induced inflammation in an animal model of GA with regard to NLRP3 inflammasome and inflammatory factors. In the current study, our findings that ZSD decreased articular elastase activity and the protein levels of NLRP3 and cleaved caspase-1, as well as IL-1
 <italic>β</italic>, demonstrated that ZSD possessed anti-inflammatory property, which was similar to the previous report [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
