<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Artificial defoliation has been employed extensively as a method of simulating herbivore attack 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-FerreroSerrano1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Richards1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-BallinaGmez1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> and has recently been used to simulate biological agents to control invasive plants 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Callaway1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Walling1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Watt1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Although artificial defoliation does not always elicit the same results as true herbivory, it can allow researchers to control the amount of defoliation precisely 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Callaway1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. We used defoliation to mimic the herbivory that plants are likely to encounter in nature. A factorial combination of defoliation intensities (0%, 25%, 50%, 75% or 100%) and competition (with or without) were applied to treat invasive 
 <italic>Mikania</italic>. A total of 10 treatments were used in this experiment, and 5 replicates were used for each treatment, amounting to 50 pots. For the experiment without competition, an individual 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> plant was transplanted into each pot; for the competition treatment, an individual 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> plant and one 
 <italic>Coix</italic> plant of similar size were transplanted together into each pot with a distance of 15 cm between them. The pots were irrigated with tap water twice daily and fertilised with 50% Hoagland's nutrient solution once per week 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-BacilioJimnez1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Bamboo sticks (1 m long) were inserted into the soil near 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> to allow the plant to climb. Three weeks after transplantation, 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> plants of similar size were chosen for defoliation. Herbivory by 
 <italic>A. thalia pyrrha</italic> on 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> can remove all of the leaves 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. To simulate a realistic intensity of herbivory, five intensities were included in this experiment: (1) 0% defoliation, (2) 25% defoliation, (3) 50% defoliation, (4) 75% defoliation, and (5) 100% defoliation. These treatments constituted removing 0%∼45% of the total above-ground biomass at the time of clipping to simulate zero to moderate aboveground herbivory 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Callaway2" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. The defoliation of 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> was performed by removing each leaf with scissors, leaving the petiole attached to the stem.
</p>
