<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Branches with leaves of 
   <span class="italic">G</span>. 
   <span class="italic">rosmarinifolia</span> were collected in February 2017 from plants located in the following site: “Raffo Rosso, Monte Cuccio, and Vallone Sagana” (38°11’07”N 13°16’05” E—Sicily—Palermo). The matrices were placed in paper bags and kept at 4 ± 1 °C for 24 hours before the hydrodistillation. A voucher specimen (N° MS 120/2017) was deposited at the Herbarium of the University of Palermo. No specific permits were required for the described location and for the collection of plant material. The plant species used in the present study is not endangered or protected.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oil isolation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Branches with leaves (64 g) were hand-cut into small pieces (~ 2 cm) and then hydrodistillated for 3 hours in a Clevenger-type apparatus, using 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-pentane as collection solvent. The oil was dried by anhydrous sodium sulphate, filtered and stored at 4 °C until its chemical analysis and pharmacological tests. The essential oil yield was 49.8 mg (0.08%).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The GC analysis was performed in an Agilent 7000C GC system, fitted with a fused silica Agilent HP-5MS capillary column (30 m x 0.25 mm i.d.; 0.25 μm film thickness), coupled to an Agilent triple quadrupole Mass Selective Detector MSD 5973; ionization voltage 70 eV; electron multiplier energy 2000 V; transfer line temperature, 295 °C. Helium was the carrier gas (1 mL min
   <span class="sup">-1</span>). The other GC analysis was performed in a Shimadzu QP 2010 plus, single quadrupole GC/MS system, fitted with a Supelcowax 10 capillary column (30 m x 0.25 mm i.d.; 0.25 μm film thickness); ionization voltage 70 eV; transfer line temperature, 280 °C. Helium was the carrier gas (1 mL min
   <span class="sup">-1</span>). For both columns, the temperature was initially kept at 40 °C for 5 min, then gradually increased to 250°C at 2°C min
   <span class="sup">-1</span> rate, held for 15 min and finally raised to 270 °C at 10 °C min
   <span class="sup">-1</span>. One μL of diluted samples (1/100 v/v, in 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-hexane) was injected at 250 °C automatically and in the splitless mode; transfer line temperature, 295 °C.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identification of compounds</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identification of compounds was carried out using NIST 11, Wiley 9, FFNSC 2, and Adams [
   <a rid="pone.0196947.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196947.ref013">13</a>] databases. These identifications were confirmed by Linear Retention Indices (LRI) with those available in literature by SciFinder database. Some of the compounds were also confirmed by comparison of mass spectra and retention times with standard compounds available in laboratory. The retention indices were determined in relation to a homologous series of 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes (C
   <sub>8</sub>-C
   <sub>30</sub>) injected under the same operating conditions. Component relative concentrations were calculated based on GC peak areas without using correction factors.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec007" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cell growth assays</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hepatocellular carcinoma cell lines (HA22T/VGH, HepG2, Hep3B) and triple negative breast cancer cell lines (SUM 149, MDA-MB-231) were used. The human hepatocellular carcinoma cell line HA22T/VGH was kindly provided by Professor Massimo Levrero (Laboratory of Gene Expression, Fondazione Andrea Cesalpino, University of Rome “La Sapienza”, Rome, Italy). HepG2 (ATCC
   <span class="sup">®</span>: HB-8065
   <span class="sup">™</span>) and Hep3B (ATCC
   <span class="sup">®</span>: HB-8064
   <span class="sup">™</span>) cells were obtained from the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC, Rockville, MD, USA). All the above cell lines were authenticated by short tandem repeat profiling (BMR Genomics, Padua, Italy). The human breast cancer cell lines MDA-MB-231 (ATCC
   <span class="sup">®</span>: HTB-26
   <span class="sup">™</span>—Rockville, MD, USA) and SUM149 (SUM149PT—Asterand Bioscience Detroit, MI) were kindly provided by Dr. Elda Tagliabue (Molecular Targeting Unit, Department of Experimental Oncology and Molecular Medicine, Fondazione Institute of Hospitalization and Scientific Care, National Cancer Institute, Milan, Italy) and were authenticated using the short tandem repeat profiling method in their Institute facility.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cells were seeded at 2 × 10
   <span class="sup">4</span> cells/well onto 96-well plates and incubated overnight at 37 °C. After obtaining the cells, the first passage carried out was assigned passage number 1. Cells with a narrow range of passage number (4–6) were routinely tested for Mycoplasma contamination were used for all experiments.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At time 0, the medium was replaced with fresh complete medium supplemented of essential at the indicated concentrations. Following 72 h of treatment, 16 μL of a commercial solution obtained from Promega Corporation (Madison, WI, USA) containing 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-5-(3-carboxy methoxyphenyl)-2-(4-sulphophenyl)-2H-tetrazolium (MTS) and phenazine ethosulfate were added. The plates were incubated in a humidified atmosphere at 37 °C in 5% CO
   <sub>2</sub> for 2 h, and the bioreduction of MTS dye was evaluated by measuring the absorbance of each well at 490 nm using a microplate absorbance reader (iMark Microplate Reader; Bio-Rad Laboratories, Inc., Hercules, CA, USA). Cell growth inhibition was expressed as a percentage (mean ± SD) of the absorbance of the control cells.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec008" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anti- and pro-oxidant activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To evaluate antioxidant activity, we have used DPPH Assay. The antiradical efficiency of the sample was evaluated by the DPPH stable radical method [
   <a rid="pone.0196947.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196947.ref014">14</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0196947.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196947.ref015">15</a>]. 100 μL of sample, the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">G</span>. 
   <span class="italic">rosmarinifolia</span> at different concentrations, was added to aliquots (3.9 mL) of a solution made up with DPPH (4.8 mg) in MeOH (200 mL), and the mixture was incubated for 1 h at room temperature in the dark. Then the absorbance was measured at 517 nm using a UV-VIS spectrophotometer. The initial concentration of DPPH was approximately 60 μM. Lower absorbance values of reaction mixture indicate higher free radical scavenging activity. The results were plotted as the percentage of absorbance disappearance at 517 nm [(1—A/A0) × 100] against the amount of sample divided by the initial concentration of DPPH. Each point was acquired in triplicate. ED
   <sub>50</sub> corresponds to micrograms of fraction able to consume half the amount of free radical divided by micromoles of initial DPPH. The results were expressed as antiradical capacity (ARC), which is the inverse of ED
   <sub>50</sub>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trolox (6-hydroxy-2,5,7,8-tetramethyl-chroman-2-carboxylic acid) curve was used as the positive control.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pro-oxidant activity was examined by cell counting, adding N-acetyl-L-cysteine (NAC), an antioxidant molecule, 1 h before essential oil. Data were expressed as mean ± standard deviation (SD) of at least three different experiments performed in duplicate. All the chemicals were supplied by Sigma Aldrich srl, Milan, Italy.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec009" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results of biological assays are given as means ± standard deviation. Statistical analysis was carried out by analysis of variance (one-way ANOVA) followed by Tukey’s test. Statistica ver. 10 (StatSoft Inc. 2011) was used as software for the analyses.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
