<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The findings evidenced the selective long-term cytotoxicity of the antioxidant-rich 
 <italic>T. bentzoë</italic> leaf extract against HepG2 cells. This plant, which is also used traditionally in the mitigation of asthma, hemorrhages, diarrhea, and sexually transmissible diseases, amongst others, has also shown some in vitro anticancer activities against HepG2 cells. The cytotoxic nature of 
 <italic>T. bentzoë</italic> leaf extract against cancerous cells indicated that the 
 <italic>T. bentzoë</italic> leaf has the potential to be repurposed in the mitigation of cancer as part of traditional medicine. The results so far generated support the hypothesis that 
 <italic>T. bentzoë</italic> extract induces apoptosis/necrosis cell death in HepG2 cells via the degradation of cellular genetic material and the subsequent arrest of the cell cycle’s progression in the G0/G1 phase. Overall, the MTT-guided fractionation of the crude extract and spectroscopic analyses allowed the characterization of 10 phenolic compounds, including punicalagin, ellagic acid, gallic acid and methyl gallate, that are known to have established 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> anticancer properties. However, the contribution of the other non-identified phytoconstituents cannot be excluded, and thus further evaluation of the identified components is warranted alongside the crude extract. The metabolite profiling of the leaf extract may be envizaged in future studies. Taking into consideration the guidelines of the US national cancer institute as well as the selectivity index observed in this study, 
 <italic>T. bentzoë</italic> leaf extract has been revealed as a promising candidate that can be exploited in the search for novel anticancer agents. The current study provided base line data for more in-depth investigations of the chemotherapeutic potential of 
 <italic>T. bentzoë</italic> plant extracts. Further mechanistic investigation, directed towards delineating the molecular mechanisms via which the purified bioactive entities target the aberrant signaling pathways involved in carcinogenesis, is needed to fuel 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies. Future animal studies and ideally human clinical trials are warranted to establish the physiological doses for human administration.
</p>
