<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">The genus 
  <italic class="italic">Cyphostemma</italic> (Planch.) Alston (Vitaceae) includes about 150 species distributed in eastern and southern Africa and Madagascar. Some species are used in traditional medicine and their biological activities, including antiproliferative effects against cancer cell lines, have been demonstrated. To date no investigations on 
  <italic class="italic">Cyphostemma</italic> essential oils have been carried out. Essential oils, which play important roles in plant defenses have been demonstrated to be active in the treatment of several human diseases and to enhance bioavability of other drugs. The aim of this paper was to identify the chemical composition of the essential oil of the leaves of 
  <italic class="italic">Cyphostemma juttae</italic> (Dinter &amp; Gilg) Desc. and to verify some biological activities on two triple negative breast cancer cell lines (MDA-MB-231, SUM 149), characterized by the over-expression of the transcription factor NF-κB. In the essential oil, obtained by hydrodistillation and analysed by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry, 39 compounds were detected and with phytol (30%) dominating the chemical composition. 
  <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">juttae</italic> essential oil reduced cell growth and showed a pro-oxidant activity in both cell lines. Moreover, 
  <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">juttae</italic> essential oil caused a substantial decrease of NF-κB activation and consequently a significant reduction of some NF-κB target genes. The present study shows for the first time the cytotoxic properties of 
  <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">juttae</italic> essential oil and highlight its availability to interfere with NF-κB pathway, suggesting a potential therapeutic use in triple negative breast cancers (TNBCs) of this essential oil.
 </p>
</abstract>
