<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">People’s interest in natural compounds rather than synthetic ones is growing considerably [
 <xref rid="B12-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>], especially because they are regarded as safe with no side effects and possess a variety of therapeutic actions [
 <xref rid="B13-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Indeed, natural products such as vegetable oils with antioxidant potential can help the organism to modify the oxidative state in imbalance conditions [
 <xref rid="B14-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. In addition, plant essential oils exhibit low mammalian toxicity and can affect the reproduction, growth rate, and behavior of insects [
 <xref rid="B16-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Lantana montevidensis</italic> Briq., popularly known as “chumbinho” in Brazil, is used to treat rheumatism, bronchitis, and gastric disorders [
 <xref rid="B21-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Studies carried out with the leaf extract or leaf essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">L. montevidensis</italic> demonstrated their antibacterial activities and their potential to modulate antibiotics drugs used in clinical infections [
 <xref rid="B22-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. In addition, leaf extract of 
 <italic class="italic">L. montevidensis</italic> was shown to exhibit antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B9-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>], while flavonoids from its leaves were reported to exert antiproliferative activity against gastric adenocarcinoma, human uterus carcinoma, and murine melanoma cells, in vitro [
 <xref rid="B21-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>].
</p>
