<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <p id="Par1" class="p">
  <italic class="italic">Origanum vulgare</italic> L. (Lamiaceae) is a widespread flavoring culinary and medicinal herb. The present study aimed at investigating the antimicrobial activity of 
  <italic class="italic">Origanum vulgare</italic> (OV) essential oil (EO) through illustrating its biostatic, biocidal and the dynamics of the biocidal activity against 11 different microorganisms. GC/MS of OV EO allowed the identification of 32 compounds representing 99.94% of the oil. The two major identified compounds were terpinen-4-ol (38.35%) and 
  <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-sabinene hydrate (10.06%). Different methods were employed to illustrate the biostatic activity of OV EO. Results of the biostatic studies on OV EO using agar and broth dilution methods showed that 
  <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (
  <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic>) was the most sensitive organism; with a Minimum inhibitor concentration (MIC) 1.18 mg/ml. Agar diffusion method showed that the highest activity was observed against 
  <italic class="italic">Bordetella bronchiseptica</italic> (
  <italic class="italic">Br. bronchiseptica</italic>), 
  <italic class="italic">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> (
  <italic class="italic">S. cerevisiae</italic>), 
  <italic class="italic">Bacillus subtilis</italic> (
  <italic class="italic">B. subtilus</italic>) and 
  <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> (
  <italic class="italic">S. epidermidis</italic>) with inhibition zones 38 ± 1.5, 29.5 ± 0.8, 26.9 ± 0.9 and 26.9 ± 1.1 mm, respectively. Studying the dynamics of 1% v/v OV essential oil emulsion over a period of 6 h revealed that 
  <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> (
  <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic>)
  <italic class="italic">, B. subtilis, S. epidermidis</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">S. cerevisiae</italic> had the fastest response. Also increasing concentrations of OV oil emulsion increased the rate of cell killing and the duration of growth lag phase increased correspondingly. These data indicated that OV EO produces a concentration and time-dependent antimicrobial activity.
 </p>
</abstract>
