<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In each of the groups, five rats with average food consumption, i.e., those with the highest and lowest values were eliminated, were used in microarray analyses. The extraction of hepatic RNA and sample preparation for the DNA microarray analysis were conducted according to a previous study [
 <xref rid="pone.0210950.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]; after the normalization of raw signals, positive genes were selected and analyzed using a principal component analysis (PCA). Each sample was applied to one microarray chip (Rat Genome 230_2.0 GeneChip, Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA). Microarray data were normalized using the SuperNORM data processing service (Skylight Biotech Inc.), and gene expression in each group was estimated [
 <xref rid="pone.0210950.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0210950.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. To cancel interference by noise, positive genes were selected prior to PCA. The significance of dietary factors was statistically tested by a two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) that was applied to the factors, Perfect Match (PM) cell sensitivity and dietary group effect [
 <xref rid="pone.0210950.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. The level of significance used for the selection was 0.01. The magnitude of the difference was estimated by taking trimmed means among differences calculated for PM data; in comparisons between CS and other diets, genes with Δz scores of more or less than 0.2 were selected. This magnitude corresponded to a 1.41-fold difference. A total of 4871 out of 31042 genes in the microarray satisfied the criteria for significance and differences (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210950.s008" class="xref">S3 Table</xref>). The selected genes and the groups of samples formed a matrix of multivariate data. The relationships between the genes and differences among the groups were further assessed using PCA [
 <xref rid="pone.0210950.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. The appearance frequency of key words, supplied for each gene by the manufacturer, was tested using a binominal distribution model. Among genes with absolute values that were larger than 0.1 in PC1 or 0.05 in PC2, words with 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-values less than 0.0005 and appearing in more than four genes were selected. Microarray data have been deposited into the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) public repository, accession code GSE66371.
</p>
