<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par46" class="p">On the other hand, differences in the relative intensities of soluble compounds in INS and PB feeds were greater. The insect meal tested contained high quantities of low molecular weight compounds (see molecular weight profile in Online Resource 5). This seems in agreement with the higher relative intensities of several free amino acids found in the INS feed than in the PB feed. Feeding high levels of low molecular weight compounds to carnivorous fish such as salmon or trout has been shown to increase growth (Hevroy et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">2005</xref>; Aksnes et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">2006</xref>). A similar positive impact on growth was also observed with insect meal in the present study performed in rainbow trout. It is known that free amino acids and small peptides are absorbed specifically and more rapidly than the bolus of amino acids produced by protein digestion, especially in juveniles (Oliva-Teles et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">1999</xref>; Lundquist and Artursson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">2016</xref>; Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">2017</xref>). Furthermore, amino acids, especially branched-chain amino acids, are known as signaling molecules. Together with insulin, branched-chain amino acids, especially leucine, contribute to the activation of the TOR signaling pathway, which regulates protein translation and metabolism (Seiliez et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">2008</xref>; Laplante and Sabatini 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">2012</xref>; Zhang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" class="xref">2017</xref>). As the highest relative intensities of free branched-chain amino acids were found in INS feeds, which exhibited the best growth performances, our results support the hypothesis that the positive impact on growth with INS feedstuff may be due to enhanced protein synthesis under amino acid stimulation.
</p>
