<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous studies have shown that H2O2 is an important reactive oxygen species (ROS) which could induce oxidative damage through the interaction with iron. The berry extract and ginsenoside Re of PQR have high cardioprotective effects against oxidative stress. Phenolic acids such as caffeic acid and chlorogenic acid in PQR fruit could up-regulate the ability of myocardial cells to metabolize H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> in a dose-dependent manner and reduce the oxidative damage of cardiomyocytes induced by H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>. It has protective effect on myocardial oxidative stress. However, the specific mechanism is not clarified (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Mehendale et al., 2006</xref>). Rb1 has the activity of scavenging DPPH and hydroxyl radical, and can inhibit the increase of JNK phosphorylation (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), reduce the expression of P-JNK, and improve the cell survival rate after H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> exposure to play a protective role on myocardial oxidative stress (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2012</xref>). PQR could also significantly inhibit the upregulation of extracellular matrix protein and vasoactive factor caused by oxidative stress, and reduce the mRNA expression of cardiac natriuretic factor and brain natriuretic factor, so as to prevent the biochemical and functional changes of heart caused by diabetes (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">Sen et al., 2013b</xref>). Zhu et al. have shown that 
 <italic>Panax quinquefolium</italic> can significantly inhibit oxidative stress, balance the ratio of Bcl-2/Bax, and inhibit the activation of Caspase-3 (
 <xref rid="B171" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2013</xref>). In addition, it could also significantly increase the phosphorylation of Akt and eNOS protein levels in ischemia-reperfusion myocardial cells, and significantly reduce the infarct area and myocardial cell apoptosis in mice to improve myocardial infarction (
 <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2011</xref>). And PQR saponin could significantly increase the survival rate of neonatal rat ventricular myocytes induced by hypoxia reperfusion, down regulate lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) leakage, slow down early cell apoptosis, increase energy production (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05), and increase the expression of glucose transporter 4 (GLUT4) and fatty acid translocation enzyme/cluster 36 differentiation (FAT/CD36) on cell membrane (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) (
 <xref rid="B148" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
