<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Solid lipid micro- and nanoparticles, also called Lipospheres, are drug-loaded solid lipid spheres decorated with phospholipids and surfactants, used to deliver active agents [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Lipospheres are prepared by a melt process in which the lipid and the drug are melted and mixed with a hot buffer containing the phospholipids and surfactants, then homogenized to create a uniform emulsion. Upon rapid cooling a dispersion is formed. Alternatively, the drug, lipid, phospholipid, and surfactants can be dissolved in an organic solvent and evaporated in a large flak to form a thin film. Upon addition of a warm buffer and homogenization, a lipid suspension is obtained. Lipospheres have been prepared for extended delivery of local anesthetics, vaccines, antibiotics, insect repellent, cosmetic agents, etc. [
 <xref rid="B22-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. An in-situ formulation called Pro-Nanodispersion Lipospheres (PNL) spontaneously forms nanoparticles upon addition to aqueous media. PNL are designed to improve the oral bioavailability of cyclosporin and cannabinoids [
 <xref rid="B21-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Upon contact with GI (gastrointestinal) fluids, the oily formulation loaded into soft gelatin capsules immediately forms lipid nanoparticles of 30 nm to significantly improve the oral bioavailability of Cyslosporin [
 <xref rid="B21-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Similar formulations to improve oral delivery of cannabinoids are under clinical development [
 <xref rid="B23-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Lipospheres, PNL, or Solid Lipid Nanoparticles (SLN) have potential applications in the delivery of water insoluble active agents by different routes of administration for improved bioavailability. Many bioactive ingredients, nutrients, and other food additives, including fatty acids, vitamins, polyphenols, aromas, and preservatives are highly hydrophobic materials. Absorption into the small intestine increases when an edible lipid is added, thereby promoting solubilization and transportation of lipophilic agents [
 <xref rid="B28-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. For these reasons micro- and nanoparticles produced from different lipid systems as transporters have been studied extensively. The presence of lipids can instantaneously increase the dispersibility of hydrophobic additives leading to improved absorption, and thus to increased bioavailability. The difference between solid lipid particles and oil-in-water (o/w) emulsions is that their lipid carrier is composed of a solid lipid (solid at room temperature) [
 <xref rid="B29-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The added active materials (core) remain incorporated inside a solid lipid phase, usually stabilized by surfactant molecules [
 <xref rid="B30-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The solid state of Solid Lipid Microparticles (SLM) provides clear advantages over the liquid state, encouraging increasing interest in their development. Lipid microparticles can be an advantageous alternative to polymeric particles in light of several visible advantages of this delivering system. Amongst them are the facility of large-scale production, relatively low cost, and low toxicity. In addition to solubilization and better dispersion of the active ingredient, SLM can provide extended release of active agent, to mask the undesirable taste and protect against degradation inside the GI tract [
 <xref rid="B31-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Many lipid materials are suitable for food applications, including fatty acids and fatty alcohols, waxes, and triglycerides. Usually, the solid lipids used in the microencapsulation process have a melting point from 50° to 85 °C [
 <xref rid="B32-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Lipid transporters have exceptional properties that widely used in emulsification, film formation, and encapsulation of active compounds thereby providing many potential applications in the food industry [
 <xref rid="B33-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Polar lipids, such as biocompatible phospholipids, are good surface-active compounds suitable for the stabilization, protection, and controlled release of active compounds [
 <xref rid="B34-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Therefore, lipid-based encapsulation techniques can certainly offer a number of important benefits as a shield system for sensitive food bioactives.
</p>
