<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The majority of the identified fatty acids in the oils recovered from by-products of 
 <italic class="italic">Malus</italic> spp. were found in bound forms, in the form of di- and triglycerides, and fatty acid alkyl esters (from 446.5 to 810.4 mg mL
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>). Only small amounts of less stable free fatty acids were found, varying in the range of 3.0–26.5 mg mL
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>. The oils recovered from by-products of 
 <italic class="italic">Malus</italic> spp., especially 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. Bernu prieks, followed by 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. cv. “Ola”, and 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. × 
 <italic class="italic">Soulardii</italic> are rich in Ts. A relatively high amount of δ-T was found in 
 <italic class="italic">M.</italic> Bernu prieks apples with a concentration of 21.5 mg mL
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>. This amount was 13.45- and 19.94-fold higher than reported earlier for 
 <italic class="italic">Jatropha curcas</italic> L. and 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. × 
 <italic class="italic">domestica</italic> Borkh oil, respectively. In total, 11 compounds including five phytosterols and six triterpenes were identified and quantified in the tested pomace oils. β-Sitosterol was the prevalent compound found in all tested pomace oils with a percentage distribution of 10.3–94.5%. Among the analyzed triterpenes, lupeol was found to be the dominant compounds in 
 <italic class="italic">M.</italic> crab apples, varying in the range of 0.1–66.3%. Thus far, this is the first report providing the evidence on the presence of dietary lupeol in the 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. crab apples. Moreover, the amount of lupeol reported here are 99-, 16-, and 2-fold higher than observed earlier for olive fruit, aloe leaves, and ginseng oil, respectively. The concentration of total carotenoids was found to be higher in oil recovered from the pomace of yellow crab apple Berzukroga dzeltenais, while the lowest in oil extracted from the pomace of Bernu prieks apple, corresponding to 14.5 and 5.1 mg mL
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, respectively. The results of scavenging capacity assay using the DPPH
 <sup class="sup">•</sup> radicals did not show correlation between the total bound FAs (R
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.2191), tocopherols (R
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.0086) or carotenoids (R
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.2306) in apple pomace oils, which suggests that radical scavenging (DPPH
 <sup class="sup">•</sup>) with each compound is an independent process, the overall success of which depends predominantly on the chemical structure of a particular biologically active compound, rather than on the concentration. The only pomace oil from 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. cv. “Ola” showed an inhibition of both Gram-positive and Gram-negative test cultures, while, to a lesser extent, the ability to inhibit only Gram-negative pathogenic bacteria was attributed to pomace oil from 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. Berzukroga dzeltenais.
</p>
