<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several plants contain α- and β-pinene (
 <bold>30</bold>, 
 <bold>31</bold>), which are related to herbal, turpentine or pine forest odour [
 <xref rid="B73-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-02473-f006">Figure 6</xref>). Considerable amounts of α-pinene compound can be found in 
 <italic>Helianthus tuberosus</italic> L. through GC-MS analysis, i.e., 25% of all substances in hydrodistilate (unpublished results). This perennial plant from the Asteraceae Dum family until now was studied only as a valued plant in the functional food and alcohol industry (tubers with a high content of inulin) and cultivated for energetic purposes (vast amounts of annual aboveground biomass with a satisfying calorific value of 15.93 MJ∙kg
 <sup>–1</sup>) [
 <xref rid="B74-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Pure α-pinene is easily obtained from turpentine oil. It is a starting material for further synthesis of borneol and camphor (67). Another fragrant compound can also be extracted from 
 <italic>H. tuberosus</italic>, and there is β-bisabolene 
 <bold>32</bold>, which have balsamic odour, and that plant contains significant amounts of these constituents in leaves, 40% 
 <italic>w</italic>/
 <italic>w</italic> (unpublished results) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-02473-f006">Figure 6</xref>). Yeo et al. [
 <xref rid="B75-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] stated that β-bisabolene exhibited selective cytotoxic activity for mouse cells and human breast cancer cells, and Kusuhara et al. [
 <xref rid="B76-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>] proved that α-pinene is responsible for inhibiting tumour growth in mice. Moreover, α-pinene and β-bisabolene are both included as a flavouring substances specified Annex I to Regulation (EC) No 1334/2008 of the European Parliament and of the Council regarding food additives (in force) [
 <xref rid="B77-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>].
</p>
