<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Visitors to dental offices know the characteristic clove scent that accompanies them during dental procedures in the mouth. A substance belonging to the phenol group eugenol 
 <bold>14</bold> is responsible for this intense aroma (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-02473-f005">Figure 5</xref>). Eugenol exhibits antiseptic properties. It can be obtained from cinnamon leaf oil or clove oil. The content of eugenol in clove oil reaches 81% and, taking into account the fact that the production of clove oil reaches 100,000 tons per year, chemical synthesis is not profitable [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Clove oil is used in blackberry, cherry and smoke flavour composition in the food industry [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Moreover eugenol is used in perfumery for the creation of clove, carnation, oriental and spicy notes. In addition to its fragrance properties, eugenol has been tested for its antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory, anti-cancer and anti-stress properties. Detailed information on this can be found in a review article published by Khalil et al. [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Another source of intense aroma in the five spice powder is cinnamon. The best known species are Ceylon cinnamon (
 <italic>Cinnamomum verum</italic> J.Presl) and cassia (
 <italic>C. casia</italic>). The compound responsible for the smell in both cases is cinnamaldehyde 
 <bold>15</bold> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-02473-f005">Figure 5</xref>). Cassia essential oil typically contains 85% cinnamaldehyde and is used for flavouring cola drinks and a component of cherry, vanilla and nut flavours [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Production of 
 <italic>E</italic>-cinnamaldehyde is mainly based on steam distillation of the oil from the bark of the genus 
 <italic>Cinnamomum</italic> e.g., 
 <italic>C. zeylanicum</italic> Blume, where the content of this aldehyde reaches 97%. The leaves of the same tree are a rich source of eugenol [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Cinnamaldehyde has been used as a food additive for over 100 years because of its tantalizing smell. It is used to flavour bread, cakes, puddings and drinks. Thus far, it is considered a safe food additive. Some studies indicate that this compound is nephrotoxic, at least in rats [
 <xref rid="B56-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Another representative in our gallery of aromatic food additives is safrole 
 <bold>16</bold>, a compound with a Janus face (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-02473-f005">Figure 5</xref>). This is an example of a sudden end to long-term use of a compound that was considered safe. It occurs, inter alia, in the North American plant 
 <italic>Sassafras albidum</italic> (Nutt.) Nees, from which the essential oil is obtained by steam distillation. Until 1960, safrole was used to flavour root beer, various soft drinks, chewing gums and toothpaste. It owed its popularity to the aroma that was referred to as the fragrance of a ‘candy store’. After 1960, it was found to be weakly hepatocarcinogenic and banned as a food additive [
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. To make matters worse, safrole is a precursor to the synthesis of psychedelic substances, e.g., MDMA. On the other hand, safrole is applied in the synthesis of valuable compounds used in perfumery and for pesticide formulations.
</p>
