<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Substituted and/or fused bicyclic pyrimidine-containing scaffolds are privileged structures in medicinal chemistry with diverse bioactivities and success stories reported including the development of anticancer, anti-inflammatory, antiviral and antibacterial pyrimidine-based chemical entities
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5–13</sup>
 </xref>. Starting from fused-pyrimidine scaffolds known in anticancer agents, such as lapatinib (
 <bold>1</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>), TAK285 (
 <bold>2</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>), compound 
 <bold>3</bold> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>), our team has identified 5-amino-4-pyrimidinol hit compound 
 <bold>4</bold> out of a small library. This library was originally developed by decomposing the ring fused to the pyrimidine ring while maintaining the relative positions of the other substituents (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>)
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref>. While screening the reported generated library for anticancer activity, we have noticed that the derivatives having a chloro substituent at the 2-position of the pyrimidine core possessed slightly enhanced antiproliferative activity; yet they lacked EGFR inhibitory activity. Additionally, among unfused anticancer pyrimidines, literature reports promoted 2,4-diarylpyrimidine derivatives, such as WZ4002 (
 <bold>5</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>), to have excellent antiproliferative activity
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref>. Consequently, we thought of using hit compound 
 <bold>4</bold> as a starting point to design hybrid compounds combining the pharmacophoric features of both hit compound 
 <bold>4</bold> and the 2-amino-4-pyrimidinol-based 2,4-diarylpyrimidine derivatives. Thus, in addition to the 4-phenoxy feature shared by both hit compound 
 <bold>4</bold> and WZ4002, the offspring molecules (
 <bold>6</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>) would also inherit the 5-benzamide feature from hit compound 
 <bold>4</bold> and the 2-anilino feature from WZ4002. Noteworthy, some recently reported non-ATP-competitive DAPK1, ATP-competitive CSF1R kinases dual inhibitors for the treatment of the neurodegenerative tauopathies possess similar structures to this design rationale even though they were designed via different approach and for a different therapeutic purpose
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref>. Therefore, reprofiling the bioactivity of such compounds against cancer cells was strongly encouraged. Reprofiling i.e. repurposing or repositioning is a powerful tool of modern medicinal chemistry that offers many advantages and resulted in several successful outcomes
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>17–20</sup>
 </xref>.
</p>
