<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another prominent challenge will now be to progress from elegant proof-of-principles of microbial synthesis of alkaloid derivatives to more systematic explorations of the derivative space surrounding MIAs and BIAs and expanding these capabilities to include diversification of other natural product scaffolds. General approaches for achieving this will include (i) feeding of substrate analogs, (ii) pathway modification, and (iii) addition of enzymes, as recently reviewed by 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Cravens et al. (2019)</xref> For these non-mutually exclusive approaches to successfully produce sufficient yields for bioactivity testing of new drug leads, a number of challenges will have to be overcome. Chief among these, improving our ability to reliably engineer enzyme specificity and promiscuity would exponentially speed progress toward improved analog turnover. New computational methods designed to support protein design, such as the online webtool FuncLib (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Khersonsky et al., 2018</xref>), may also aid this process. However, these approaches will also require new high-resolution structures to be published in many cases. Conversely, structure-agnostic methodologies, such as directed evolution, have already been highly successful at engineering enzyme specificities, but are limited by our ability to screen the variants (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Payne et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Andorfer et al., 2016</xref>). New biosensors targeting analogs of alkaloid precursors or intermediates may address this and help to improve analog turnover at pathway bottlenecks (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Ellefson et al., 2018</xref>). Additionally, the large datasets generated by truly high throughput technologies open the door to the application of big data techniques such as machine learning, which has recently been used to successfully guide “semi-rational” protein engineering (
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Saito et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B127" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2019</xref>). Bioprospecting for promiscuous homologs may also prove fruitful. In the case of MIAs, the identification of two naturally occurring chlorinated alkaloids suggests that evolution may have already provided halo-tolerant enzymes and that screening alkaloid-producing plants native to halogen-rich habitats (e.g., coastal and volcanic soils) may save a significant amount of protein engineering (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Al-Khdhairawi et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B135" ref-type="bibr">Zeng et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
