<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="ab005">
 <p>Ethnobotanical and phytochemical studies are useful to discover new drugs. Phytochemical screening is an important step in the detection of the bioactive components existing in medicinal plants that are used in traditional medicine. Very few phytochemical studies investigating medicinal plants used in traditional medicine exist in Saudi Arabia. Eighty-five medicinal plants used in traditional medicine in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia are investigated here for the first time. This research aims to screen of 85 medicinal plants used in traditional medicine in Jeddah for the presence of secondary metabolites, and to answer the following question: Is the ethnomedicinal importance of medicinal plants used in Jeddah conform to their secondary metabolite content. Ethnobotanical fieldwork took place in Jeddah from August 2018 to September 2019. Eighty-five different plant species belonging to 37 families were identified. Screening of 85 medicinal plants was performed for the presence of alkaloids, glycosides, flavonoids, tannins, saponins and resins using standard methods. The most commonly distributed phytochemical compounds among medicinal plants used were glycosides (82%; 70 species), tannins (68%; 58 species), alkaloids (56%; 48 species), saponins (52%, 44 species) and flavonoids (35%; 30 species). On the other hand, the least commonly distributed compounds were resins (31%; 26 species). All the six groups of secondary metabolites were found in seeds of 
  <italic>Cuminum cyminum</italic> L., 
  <italic>Pimpinella anisum</italic> L. and 
  <italic>Trigonella foenum-graecum</italic> L. It can be said that the ethnomedicinal importance of these 85 medicinal plants used in Jeddah conform to their secondary metabolite content. More research should be carried out on the quantitative analysis of phytochemicals in these 85 medicinal plants used in traditional medicine in Jeddah. Furthermore, there is a need to focus phytochemical screening on ethnobotanical studies to complete research into traditional medicine which leads to the discovery of new drugs.
 </p>
</abstract>
