<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The most important and most common medicinal plant species used by the healers was 
 <italic>Rothmannia wittii</italic> Craib (Bremek.) (Rubiaceae) as demonstrated by its high use value index of 1.75. The healers used this species in a decoction to treat failing lactation in postpartum women, as a tonic, and to treat muscle pain. This species is a widely used Thai medicinal plant called “Muk Mor” in Thai language. It is otherwise used for treatment of venereal disease and to treat fever [
 <xref rid="B58-plants-09-01177" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], and as an anti-inflammatory agent [
 <xref rid="B59-plants-09-01177" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. The second most used plant was 
 <italic>Tinospora crispa</italic> (L.) Hook. f. and Thomson (Menispermaceae; UV = 1.5), which is also used in other parts of Thailand and in the Philippines as a stem extract to treat jaundice, cholera, malaria, fevers, stomach trouble, indigestion, diarrhea, and infections by worms in children [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-09-01177" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-plants-09-01177" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Furthermore, traditional healers in Malaysia, Guyana, Bangladesh, and India use this plant to treat diabetes [
 <xref rid="B60-plants-09-01177" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. In a study of the same ethnic group as in this study in Nakhon Phanom, the most used medicinal plant was 
 <italic>Crinum asiaticum</italic> L. var. 
 <italic>asiaticum</italic> (Amaryllidaceae). There, it was used to treat injuries [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-09-01177" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] but this species was not even recorded in our study, which demonstrates how the use of medicinal plants is often very local and the property of only a few healers. The difference in traditional knowledge in each region possibly depends on their history and the time their community was settled, or by the experiences and activities in their daily lives [
 <xref rid="B51-plants-09-01177" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-plants-09-01177" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].
</p>
