<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8" class="p">Well-established methods of physico-chemical pretreatment are concentrated or diluted acid treatment, the latter often combined with steam explosion, and alkaline treatment including ammonia-fibre expansion (AFEX). The pretreatments target different structures of the lignocellulosic material. Acid pretreatments mainly hydrolyse polysaccharides by breaking glycosidic linkages. Hydrolysis of crystalline cellulose is slower than that of amorphous hemicellulose; therefore, during acid pretreatment, hemicellulose is often degraded to sugar monomers, while cellulose is still present in polymeric form. Removal of hemicellulose is increasing the surface and opening pores for subsequent enzymatic treatment (Rabemanolontsoa and Saka 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" class="xref">2016</xref>; Satlewal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">2017</xref>). Steam explosion disrupts the structure of lignocellulose due to the expansion of moisture during pressure release. Additionally, glycosidic bounds are hydrolysed due to acetic acid that is released from hemicellulose (Jacquet et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">2012</xref>). Alkaline treatment hydrolyses linkages between polysaccharides and lignin, removes lignin and reduces crystallinity (Rabemanolontsoa and Saka 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" class="xref">2016</xref>; Satlewal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">2017</xref>). All methods have advantages and disadvantages regarding the extent to which sugar monomers are released, energy demand and production of fermentation inhibitors. High silica content may cause high shearing forces, scaling or fouling of equipment (Satlewal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">2017</xref>). Silica had also an inhibitory effect on cellulolytic enzymes, due to non-productive adsorption of cellulase (Talukder et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" class="xref">2017</xref>). Fermentation inhibitors are formed as side products of physico-thermal pretreatment. Under acid pretreatment, sugar dehydration results in the formation of 2-furaldehyde (furfural) from pentoses and hydroxymethyl furfural (HMF) from hexoses (Brandenburg et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">2018</xref>; Jönsson and Martín 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2016</xref>). At severe pretreatment conditions, furaldehydes are further degraded to levulinic and formic acids. Moreover, acetic acid is released due to hydrolysis of the acetyl groups of hemicelluloses. A number of aromatic compounds can also be present in acid hydrolysate, most of them originating from lignin degradation (Jönsson and Martín 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2016</xref>). During alkaline pretreatment, less inhibitors are generated compared to acid pretreatment. Sugars can be converted to organic acids, including saccharinic acid, lactic and formic acids and a variety of dihydroxy and dicarboxylic acids (Jönsson and Martín 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2016</xref>; Satlewal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">2017</xref>).
</p>
