<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There were many studies, which reflected the usefulness of furanodiene in combinational therapy to combat various cancer cells. Xu et al. studied the antiproliferation activity of furanodiene on lung cancer cells A549, NIH-H1299, and 95-D and studied its usefulness in combination therapy with paclitaxel. This study observed the inhibition of colony formation in 95-D cells and A549 cells and that it facilitated upregulation of protein expression levels of binding immunoglobulin (BIP), mRNA and C/EBP homologous protein (CHOP), as well as its accumulation in the nucleus, inducing endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress. Further, they studied that furanodiene efficiently causes cell metastasis in 95-D lung cancer cell, by activating the signaling molecules and regulating G1 cell cycle arrest, thereafter inducing apoptosis and autophagy. This autophagy was involved in the enhancement of the expression of light chain3-II (LC3-II) in the protein level. Due to this, downregulation of the protein levels of full PARP surviving, Bcl-2 and pro-caspase 7 and upregulation of cleaved PARP, affected the signaling molecules that promote apoptosis. It was also seen that furanodiene inhibited cell proliferation in a concentration-dependent manner as well as caused blockage of cell cycle progression in G1phase by downregulating the protein levels of cyclin D1 and CDK6 and upregulating those of p27 and p21 in 95-D cells [
 <xref rid="B81-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>]. Zhong et al. also studied the combined effects of tamoxifen (TAM) and furanodiene in human breast cancer cell in vitro. This research showed that the enhancement of growth inhibitory and pro-apoptosis behavior of furanodiene, enhanced the pro-apoptosis and growth inhibitory activity of tamoxifen. This activity induced cell cycle arrest via mitochondrial-caspase dependent, PARPg-independent and CDKs-cyclin signaling pathway in human breast cancer cells without affecting the cytotoxicity of Tamoxifen [
 <xref rid="B82-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>]. Furanodiene, when treated on breast cancer cell lines MCF-7 and MDA-MB-231 suppressed proliferation and increased the lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) release in a dose-dependent manner. It also depolarized mitochondrial membrane potential, chromatin condensation, and DNA fragmentation bringing cell cycle arrest at G0/G1 phase. Furanodiene, when injected intraperitoneally in mice, witnessed tumor suppression in a dose-dependent manner in vivo [
 <xref rid="B83-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>]. Zhong et al. research showed that furanodiene is a promising agent for treating chemo resistant breast cancer cell. They studied that when doxorubicin-resistant breast cancer cells (MCF-7/DOXR) are treated with furanodiene, showed an alteration in mitochondrial function as well as the levels of ATP are reduced causing apoptotic cell death. In these cells, the phosphorylation of AMPK and AMPK pathway, ATP citrate luase (ACLY), 3-glycogen synthase kinase (GSK)–3β and AICAR (5-aminoimidazole-4-carboxamide-1-β-4-ribofuranoside, acadesine), an AMPK activator, augmented by furanodiene by induction of anticancer activity [
 <xref rid="B84-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biomolecules-09-00013-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>C). Further, a study explained the combination therapy with furanodiene and doxorubicin, by inference of cell migration and cell invasion, when taken in a non-toxic concentration, in highly metastatic breast cancer MDA-MB-231 cell in vitro. This combination showed downregulation of integrin αV, and β-catenin expression, and inhibited the phosphorylation of paxillin, FAC (focal adhesion kinase), p85, Akt and decreased the MMP-9. Additionally, it reflected no influence on the expression levels of neural Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome protein (N-WASP), cdc42, RhoA and α/β tubulin. Thereby, the effects of doxorubicin on the tubulin cytoskeleton remained unaltered. Hence, proved that furanodiene is highly beneficial when combined with doxorubicin on cancerous breast cells [
 <xref rid="B85-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>]. Hence, the advantage of furanodiene is that it can be used alone or in combination for different types of cancer and drug resistant cancers. These extensive studies provide a pathway for furanodiene to be established as a therapeutically effective natural compound for cancer treatment.
</p>
