<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several previous studies have reported the potential 
 <italic>Agave americana</italic> to be used in the management of a range of disorders. A study by Thaker VS and Maharshi AR showed that 80% methanolic extracts of five species of Agave plant, including 
 <italic>Agave americana</italic>, had an inhibitory effect on the hyphal growth of common pathogenic fungi.
 <xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> The presence of saponin-based components with antifungal activity against conidial germination of 
 <italic>A. brassicae</italic> in the leaf extracts of 
 <italic>Agave americana</italic> was reported by Guleria S and Kumar A.
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> In another study, Santos et al identified significant antifungal activity of hydroethanolic extracts of 
 <italic>A. sisalana</italic> leaves against 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>.
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Bouaziz et al formulated a method to extract insoluble fibers from 
 <italic>Agave americana</italic>, which can be used to treat and prevent a range of disorders, including colon cancer, constipation, diabetes, and coronary heart disease.
 <xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> The ability of 
 <italic>Agave fourcroydes</italic> powder to increase the growth performance and serum concentration of IgG in rabbits when used as a dietary supplement was also reported.
 <xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> The potential antioxidant and cytotoxic activity of 
 <italic>A. sisalana</italic> and antioxidant and the antibacterial activities of six other Agave species have been identified earlier.
 <xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Another study by Alcázar et al reported that steroidal saponins from 
 <italic>Agave durangensis</italic> had a strong growth inhibitory effect on two yeast strains, 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> and 
 <italic>K. marxianus</italic>.
 <xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> The beneficial physiometabolic effect was observed in Wistar rats upon their exposure to fructans extracted from 
 <italic>Agave salmiana</italic>.
 <xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> In this study, we evaluated the in vitro antibacterial activity of leaf extracts of 
 <italic>Agave americana</italic> against 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Klebsiella pneumoniae, Salmonella species</italic>, and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>.
</p>
