<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As the solute is purified, the compound is identified through its structure and molecular weight. Some of the techniques used to determine the structure of the pure compound responsible for its biological activity are nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), gas chromatography-mass spectrophotometry (GC-MS), high-resolution electrospray ionization mass spectrophotometry (HRESIMS), Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FT-IR), and circular dichroism (CD). Each one has its advantage over the other but they help each other in understanding more about the discovered compound. NMR is used to give an idea about the physical, chemical, and biological property of the compound through the identification of carbon present in the compound while MS is used to identify, quantify, elucidate the structure, and determine the molecular weight of the unknown compound [
 <xref rid="B142-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. Mass spectrometry is an analytical tool that can give qualitative and quantitative data about the analyte and it has several types. One of these is HRESIMS which is a robust technique that can analyze the minute volume of samples that are non-volatile and thermally stable compounds. It is used when conventional techniques cannot analyze the given sample while GC-MS is a combination of two techniques making it a powerful tool in the analysis of a certain compound [
 <xref rid="B143-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. Gas chromatography separates the individual components while mass spectrometry characterizes the components. On the other hand, FTIR is a tool to identify the functional groups and the structure of the molecule in a given extract [
 <xref rid="B142-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. Finally, the CD is absorption spectroscopy that uses circularly polarized light to determine the chirality of a given compound [
 <xref rid="B144-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. Therefore, there is no single process in doing natural product research. The process always depends on the characteristic of the compound to be discovered.
</p>
