<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ROS burst is one of the earliest host defense responses to pathogen infections [
 <xref rid="B51-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. ROS production in infected cells can be measured using different detection methods. The commonly used DAB staining method [
 <xref rid="B52-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] destroys cell organelles, making it difficult to preserve the actual ROS accumulation pattern in living cells [
 <xref rid="B20-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], but showed evenly distributed ROS within the dead cell (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-06196-f002">Figure 2</xref>A). We found that incompatible rice–
 <italic>P. oryzae</italic> interactions produced much higher ROS levels than compatible interactions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-06196-f002">Figure 2</xref>B). CM-H
 <sub>2</sub>DCFDA staining in living rice cells revealed that a large amount of ROS uniquely accumulated around invasive hyphae only during incompatible interactions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-06196-f002">Figure 2</xref>A). During incompatible rice–
 <italic>P. oryzae</italic> interactions, ROS accumulation around invasive hyphae appears from 12 h after inoculation and continues for 36 h, disappearing when HR cell death occurs [
 <xref rid="B20-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Inhibition of OsRBOHB enzyme activity with DPI treatment significantly reduced ROS accumulation, with the ROS focal accumulation disappearing around invasive hyphae (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-06196-f004">Figure 4</xref>). DPI negatively affects plant development and defense responses by suppressing RBOH-mediated ROS generation. Dosage-dependent DPI treatment during incompatible interactions gradually reduced the total ROS level and focal accumulation (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-21-06196">Figure S3C</xref>). In the interaction between Lettuce cells and 
 <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv 
 <italic>phaseolicola</italic>, highly localized accumulation of ROS caused localized membrane damage at sites of bacterial attachment, and DPI treatment reduced ROS quantity in lettuce cells [
 <xref rid="B54-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].
</p>
