<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Actin polymerization contributes to the modification of calcium channel activity and NADPH oxidase function [
 <xref rid="B55-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Plant NADPH oxidases are localized at the plasma membrane and endometrium via vesicle trafficking along actin microfilaments under normal conditions and salinity stress [
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Plant pathogen infection causes dynamic actin microfilament rearrangements at the site of cellular invasion [
 <xref rid="B60-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Cytochalasin interferes with actin microfilament polymerization by inhibiting the rate of elongation, and acts on cytoplasmic streaming in plant cells [
 <xref rid="B64-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] and suppresses HR cell death by avirulent 
 <italic>P. oryzae</italic> [
 <xref rid="B20-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. It has high affinity binding to the barbed of F-actin to prevent the monomer addition [
 <xref rid="B65-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. It also inhibited F-actin assembly in bundles and meshwork, and NOX2 subunit localization was disrupted in the region of actin clearance [
 <xref rid="B71-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. In the present study, the actin polymerization inhibitor Cyt A [
 <xref rid="B72-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] helped to establish the compatibility and colonization of avirulent 
 <italic>P. oryzae</italic> in rice cells (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-06196-f005">Figure 5</xref>A,B). Cyt A abolished ROS focal accumulation and restored the expression of pathogen effector BAS4. However, the ROS quantity in infected rice cells decreased only slightly after Cyt A treatment (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-06196-f005">Figure 5</xref>C). This suggests that Cyt A does not directly inhibit the enzyme activity of OsRBOHB already present in the plasma membrane, but rather interrupt the distribution of newly synthesized OsRBOHB due to actin microfilament reorganization [
 <xref rid="B43-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], so that the immune response cannot effectively occur at infection sites. Activity levels of Cytochalasins can be a little bit different depending on diverse biological properties even though their activities are basically similar. Cyt A also has antimicrobial activity that inhibits 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> and 
 <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> growth and blocks ferric ion accumulation around the infection sites in wheat [
 <xref rid="B74-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. In this paper, when rice cultivar HY was inoculated with 
 <italic>P. oryzae</italic> avirulent race INA168, Cyt A showed more stable suppression on HR cell death.
</p>
