<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on the data presented in this study, we propose the hypothesis of ROS focal accumulation–mediated suppression of 
 <italic>P. oryzae</italic> effector BAS4 expression during incompatible rice–
 <italic>P. oryzae</italic> interactions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-06196-f006">Figure 6</xref>). OsRBOHB proteins are evenly distributed throughout the rice plasma membrane under pathogen-free normal conditions, but abundant OsRBOHB proteins are localized surrounding invasive hyphae during avirulent pathogen infection (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-06196-f001">Figure 1</xref>B). This re-distribution of OsRBOHB enables the formation of strong ROS focal accumulation within a very limited space at the site of 
 <italic>P. oryzae</italic> infection. ROS focal accumulation can inhibit invasive hyphal growth and 
 <italic>P. oryzae</italic> effector BAS4 expression. By contrast, OsRBOHB localization is not altered at the infection site of compatible interactions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-06196-f001">Figure 1</xref>B), and ROS focal accumulation is blocked, effectors were successfully expressed and secreted into rice cells to inhibits rice targets associated with ROS production and other plant immune mechanisms [
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-21-06196" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. If DPI inhibits OsRBOHB activity or Cyt A inhibits OsRBOHB re-distribution in incompatible interactions, ROS focal accumulation disappears and pathogens successfully colonize rice cells (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-06196-f004">Figure 4</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-06196-f005">Figure 5</xref>). These combined results suggest that the formation of ROS focal accumulation can be an effective plant immune mechanism to inhibit some effectors including BAS4 expression and secretion from invasive hyphae during the invasion of 
 <italic>P. oryzae</italic>. We hypothesize that plants can protect themselves from pathogen infection by strategically accumulating ROS, thereby blocking pathogen effector secretion. These results will improve our understanding of how plants maintain immunity during the co-evolution of plants and pathogens.
</p>
