<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110" class="p">Essential oils have also been shown to regulate the relaxation and contraction of the gut, and thereby to influence the transit of digesta and the resultant interaction between feed and the endogenous enzymes in the gut. The essential oils (cineol, methyl-eugenol and terpineol) of 
 <italic class="italic">Croton nepetaefolius</italic> were myorelaxant and antispasmodic, and were capable of stimulating intestinal transit possibly due to decreased luminal resistance to propulsion of intestinal digesta (
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Magalhães et al., 1998</xref>). Both 
 <italic class="italic">Manuka</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Kanuka</italic> oils (tea-tree oils) were shown to have spasmolytic action, but 
 <italic class="italic">Kanuka</italic> had a strong initial spasmogenic action, which might be related to the difference in their chemical compositions (sesquiterpenens vs. monoterpenens; 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lis-Balchin and Hart, 1998</xref>). The backstage mechanisms might relate to terpenes being well recognized as novel compounds targeting voltage-gated ion channels (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">de Araújo et al., 2011</xref>). The essential oils from 
 <italic class="italic">Ferula heuffelii</italic> inhibited spontaneous contraction of isolated rat ileum dose-dependently possibly by blocking voltage Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> channels or by opening K
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> channels (
 <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pavlović et al., 2012</xref>). Blocking calcium channels seemed to be of higher significance for 
 <italic class="italic">Agathosma betulina</italic> essential oils than 
 <italic class="italic">Agathosma crenulata</italic> regarding their initial spasmogenic action followed by a spasmolytic action on the guinea-pig ileum (
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lis-Balchin et al., 2001</xref>).
</p>
