<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="Materials and Methods" id="sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2-1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study design</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The DS database comparison process was comprised of four phases: Phase1 - the selection of DS databases to be incorporated into our study; Phase2 - a top-down, systematic review of these databases to understand essential data elements required for DS representation; Phase3 - the generation of a preliminary model that could be employed to represent each DS concept in a consistent, precise, and holistic fashion; Phase4 - a comparison of data elements coverage across the selected databases. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1-2840637" href="#f1-2840637">Figure 1</a> illustrates the phases and corresponding criteria.
  </p>
  <sec id="sec2-1-1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phase1 - Database selection</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We selected five electronic, evidence based DS resources at primarily two levels of representation: ingredient level (i.e., Dietary Supplement Ingredient Database (DSID), Natural Medicine (NM), Dietary Natural Health Products Ingredients Database (NHPID) and product level (i.e., Dietary Supplement Label Database (DSLD) and Licensed Natural Health Products Database (LNHPD)). Each of these databases were built exclusively for DS representation and created/maintained by either government from USA (DSID, DSLD) or Canada (NHPID, LNHPD), and/or healthcare professionals (NM-USA). More standardized drug terminological systems with some representation of DS were excluded from our preliminary study to be evaluated as the next step.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2-1-2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phase2 - Review of databases</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A comprehensive, systematic review of the databases was performed by three co-authors: RR (health informaticist/physician), RZ (health informaticist), and TA (pharmacist/physician/health informaticist), by studying guidelines associated with each database and real time searching of a common DS as a representative example. The proposed LanguaL DS structured vocabulary (LanguaL™ DS) 
    <span class="sup">
     <a rid="r17-2840637" ref-type="bibr" href="#r17-2840637">17</a>
    </span> thesaurus for DS was also reviewed in order to get additional contextual knowledge of what currently exists under drugs and DS vocabulary domain. LanguaL vocabulary is formulated by the US Federal Dietary Supplement Ingredient Database (DSID) 
    <span class="italic">ad hoc</span> Working Group. In addition, a well-established and widely employed drug compendium, the American Hospital Formulary Service (AHSF) Drug Information (DI) Essentials 
    <span class="sup">
     <a rid="r18-2840637" ref-type="bibr" href="#r18-2840637">18</a>
    </span>, was also reviewed. AHFS DI essentials is created by the American Society of Health-System Pharmacists (ASHP) 
    <span class="sup">
     <a rid="r19-2840637" ref-type="bibr" href="#r19-2840637">19</a>
    </span>, an evidence based foundation for safe and effective drug therapy.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2-1-3" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phase3 - Data element model generation</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A comprehensive list of data elements to be used as a standard check-list was generated based on LanguaL code (food) &amp; AHFSA (drugs) after an iterative process comprising an extensive review of DS and drug databases (both as controlled vocabularies, monographs or free text), their respective guidelines, and discussion among experts (RR, RZ, TA, JB). These data elements are defined in 
    <a rid="t1-2840637" ref-type="table" href="#t1-2840637">Table 1</a>. It was found during this process that some data elements, while not explicitly present in a given database, are indeed expressed indirectly. For example, while none of the databases have a “lexicon variant” data element, alternate spellings for ingredients could be discovered by finding multiple synonymous entries that are spelled differently, e.g., “Ginkgo” and “Gingko”. Thus, a new facet, lexicon variant, could be created to explicitly express this concept. The model was further strengthened by including valuable inputs from experts, a team of informaticists, physicians and pharmacists (RZ, RR, TA, JB, GM, SP). The resulting data elements are all those deemed essential for comprehensive representation of DS.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2-4" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phase4 - Data elements coverage comparison</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During this phase, the five selected databases were first qualitatively evaluated and compared for presences of essential data elements employing the above model as a check-list. Information pertaining to specific data elements was considered present if it existed in the controlled vocabularies (CV), monographs (M) or free text. We have also reported how DS should be represented comprehensively (by obtaining data from multiple resources) through two representative examples, Ginseng and Fish oil, cross checked with the model. A single variant of each example was employed for initial comparison.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the quantitative evaluation, facets were first mapped to the data elements in 
    <a rid="t1-2840637" ref-type="table" href="#t1-2840637">Table 1</a> by a physician and health informaticist (RR). A coverage analysis was performed (JV) over the mapped facets, shown as the percentage of database entries having a non-null value. We use this evaluation to estimate the completeness of values for each data element for ingredients and products within each of these databases. Multiple facets in the source databases often map to a single data element in our schema. A given DS was considered to have data for a given ontology attribute if one or more of the corresponding facets in its source database was non-null.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
