<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There is an opportunity to use silicones as coupling agents or adhesion promotors in metallurgical processing. Silicones form strong intermolecular interactions and chemical bonds with inorganic materials, such as glass, silica, alumina, talc, clay, mica, aluminium, iron, titanium oxide, zinc oxide, iron oxide, graphite, carbon black and calcium carbonate, showing improved wettability, compatibility, heat resistance up to 315 °C, weatherability and moisture resistance [
 <xref rid="B32-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. Silicones, composed of a Si–O linkage, have a high bond energy of 444 kJ·mol
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>. The Si–C bond has a bond energy of 318 kJ·mol
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, slightly lower than a C–C bond, while the Si–Si bond is weak (193 kJ·mol
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>). An Si–H bond (bond energy of 320 kJ·mol
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) is more reactive than the C–H bond of hydrocarbons (bond energy of 416 kJ·mol
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>). The Si–O bonds in silicones are strongly polarised, compared to C–O bonds in organic polymers, with stronger intermolecular interactions [
 <xref rid="B33-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. The epoxy-metal oxide bond strength is ≈140 kJ·mol
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> compared to that of siloxane-metal oxide (≈450 kJ·mol
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>). The Si–O bond in silicones can replace the metal–oxygen–hydrogen bond or even the carbon–oxygen–metal bond easily through strong surface bonds [
 <xref rid="B34-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>] resulting in a dense cross-linked network that is interwoven with terminal chemical functionality. The bond energy of such an interaction in a glass-silanol system (Si–O–Si) is ≈450 kJ·mol
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>. Bond strengths at the interface are listed in 
 <xref rid="materials-12-00655-t008" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 8</xref> [
 <xref rid="B35-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Silicones show increased wetting with the transition metal oxides, e.g., iron ore (iron oxide) compared to the carbon-based polymers, and increased mechanical strength. Iron oxides render the silicones with increased thermal stability at elevated temperatures [
 <xref rid="B36-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. 
</p>
