<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As mentioned above, for 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> susceptibility testing, conidia or spores are used as inocula. For 
 <italic>M. mycetomatis</italic>, the most common causative agent of eumycetoma, only sporulates in very rare circumstances and sterile hyphae are usually obtained.
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> Therefore, to use conidia as a starting point is not feasible. For that reason, an alternative approach for generating a starting inoculum was needed. To assess the effect of the nature of the starting inoculum on the MIC, conidia and hyphal fragments were compared.
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>–</sup>
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref> Two different approaches have been reported in the literature to generate hyphal fragments direct from a colony. The first is to generate hyphal fragments via sonication,
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> the second is by rubbing the fungal colony with a sterile scalpel or transfer tip.
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref> When hyphal fragments were generated from 
 <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> by sonication and used as a starting inoculum (70–80% transmission at 660 nm) in the CLSI antifungal susceptibility assay, similar MICs for amphotericin B and voriconazole were obtained compared with the conidia starting inoculum (5×10
 <sup>4</sup> cfu/ml).
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> The MICs for itraconazole were one dilution step higher.
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> When hyphal fragments were generated by rubbing the fungal colony and used as a starting inoculum (2–5×10
 <sup>4</sup> cfu/ml) in the EUCAST-based antifungal susceptibility assay, again similar MICs for amphotericin B, posaconazole and voriconazole were obtained.
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref> This was not only demonstrated for 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic>, but also for species of 
 <italic>Absidia</italic>
 <italic>, Acremonium</italic>, 
 <italic>Emericella</italic>, 
 <italic>Fusarium</italic>, 
 <italic>Microsporum</italic>, 
 <italic>Mucor</italic>, 
 <italic>Paecilomyces</italic>, 
 <italic>Rhizomucor</italic>, 
 <italic>Rhizopus</italic>, 
 <italic>Scedosporium</italic>, 
 <italic>Trichoderma</italic> and 
 <italic>Trichophyton</italic>.
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref> Therefore hyphal fragments seem a good substitute for conidia. In contrast, when hyphal clumps instead of hyphal fragments were used as a starting inoculum, a significant increase in 50% minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC50) from 1 µg/ml (conidia) to 8 µg/ml (hyphal clumps) was noted for amphotericin B and from 0.5–1 µg/ml (conidia) to &gt;16 µg/ml (hyphal clumps) for the azoles.
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> This indicated that only MICs obtained for hyphal fragments were comparable to those obtained with conidia, not those obtained with fungal clumps. The manner in which hyphal fragments were generated seemed less important as long as the same cfu/ml or density was used. Therefore, for mycetoma agents, hyphal fragments are currently generated by sonication.
</p>
