<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">
 <italic>Nigella sativa </italic> L. is an annual plant belonging to the Ranunculaceae family that grows to the height of 60–70 cm. Its leaves are gray-green with thread-like cuttings, its flowers are colored white to blue, and its fruits are in the form of follicles containing numerous black and aromatic seeds. The seeds contain 40% fixed oil and about 1.4% essential oil and are medicinally used as carminative, cathartic, milk-promoter, anti-constipation, and sexual promoter in men. Although it is a wild species, it is cultivated in some parts of Europe, Eastern Asia, and some regions of Iran
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>. The biofertilizer Azotobarvar-1 (containing nitrogen-fixing bacteria from the genus 
 <italic>Azotobacter</italic>) is a voluntary molecular nitrogen fixer that is capable of synthesizing biologically active compounds in the root zone including nicotinic acid, pantothenic acid, biotin, vitamin B, auxins, and gibberellins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>. These compounds are involved in root system development and influence crop yields and soil characteristics by improving water and nutrient uptake and nitrogen (N) biofixation. 
 <italic>Azotobacter</italic> can also produce plant anti-pathogenic compounds and is involved in disease control
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. Phosphate biofertilizer Barvar-2 contains two phosphate solubilizing bacteria from 
 <italic>Bacillus</italic> and 
 <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> species that secrete organic acids and acid phosphatase, thereby converting insoluble P content of soil (especially in calcium-rich regions) into the soluble forms that are absorbable by plants
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. Biofertilizers, indeed, contain various free-living microorganisms
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>
 </sup>, that can convert macronutrients from unavailable into available forms by biological processes and improve root system development and seed germination
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
