<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The provincial standards relating to the Tibetan, the Xinjiang Uygur, the Inner Mongolia, the Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region, Qinghai, Sichuan, and Yunnan and Guizhou provinces also apply to the regulation of the quality of ethnic medicines in China [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The academy group and enterprise standards are also applicable to the quality of ethnomedicine. The 28 DPMs identified in the survey include 101 traditional medicines with quality standards listed in the 
 <italic>Chinese Pharmacopoeia</italic> (2015 edition). The quality standards of 30 traditional medicines are listed in the Standards for Chinese medicinal materials in Yunnan Province (SYNP) or other provincial quality standards (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). Four herbal medicines including 
 <italic>Aristolochia chuii</italic> Wu (Dabaijie), 
 <italic>Michelia mahan</italic> C. Y. Wu (Mahan), 
 <italic>Asparagus officinalis</italic> L. (Xiaobaibu), and leaf and stem of 
 <italic>Vitex trifolia</italic> L. do not have applicable quality standards or are out of date. The 73 YPMs identified in the survey included 182 traditional medicines with quality standards in the 
 <italic>Chinese Pharmacopoeia</italic> (2015 edition). The quality standards of 88 traditional medicines are included in the SYNP or other provincial pharmacopoeias. Eleven herbal medicines have no applicable quality standards or are out of date, including the root of 
 <italic>Rosa odorata</italic> (Andr.) Sweet var. gigantea (Crép.) Rhed. Et Wils. (Gugongguo), 
 <italic>Fibraurea recisa</italic> Pierre (Dahuangteng), 
 <italic>Dolichos falcata</italic> Klein (Damayao), 
 <italic>Cyanotis arachnoidea</italic> G. B. Clarke (Lushuicao), 
 <italic>Bulbophyllum reptans</italic> (Lindl.) Lindl. (Xiaolvji), 
 <italic>Adenophora bulleyana</italic> Diels (Shashen), 
 <italic>Cynoglossum officinale</italic> L. (Daotihu), 
 <italic>Crepis lignea</italic> (Vant.) Babc. (Wanzhangsheng), 
 <italic>Cymbopogon distans</italic> (Nees) Wats. (Yunxiangcao), and Ziheche and extract of 
 <italic>Hemsleya chinensis Cogn</italic>. ex Forbes et Hemsl (Xuedan extract). More information is provided in Tables 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supplementary-material-1">S3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supplementary-material-1">S4</xref>.
</p>
