<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Nanofibrillated cellulose, obtained by mechanical disintegration from native plant fibers, is a cellulosic derivative used as a novel packaging material [
 <xref rid="B126-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">126</xref>]. However, its major drawback is its vulnerability to microbe attacks, such as from cellulose-consuming fungi, for instance [
 <xref rid="B127-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">127</xref>]. It is known that most of the bacterial cell walls are negatively charged; therefore, and as mentioned above, an interesting option to develop intrinsic antimicrobial materials is the use of quaternary ammonium compounds, molecules, or polymers [
 <xref rid="B128-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">128</xref>]. Indeed, it has been demonstrated that these compounds could interact electrostatically with the negatively charged bacteria cell wall, causing a disruption of the membrane and posterior death [
 <xref rid="B6-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B129-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">129</xref>,
 <xref rid="B130-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">130</xref>]. With this in mind, Littunen et al. [
 <xref rid="B127-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">127</xref>] proposed the chemical incorporation of quaternary ammonium compounds into nanofibrillated cellulose (NFC) to impart an antimicrobial property. For that, the authors developed two types of cationized and nanofibrillated cellulose via redox-initiated graft copolymerization with a [2-(methacryloyloxy)ethyl]trimethylammonium chloride (DMQ) monomer to obtain nanofibrillated cellulose grafted poly[2-(methacryloyloxy)ethyl]trimethylammonium chloride (NFC-PDMQ), and by etherification with a quaternary ammonium compound (NFCQ). They evaluated the antimicrobial activity of unmodified NFC and both NFCQ and NFC-PDMQ against three potential human pathogens: 
 <italic class="italic">Micrococcus luteus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> bacteria, and 
 <italic class="italic">Candida oleophila</italic> yeast. As expected, unmodified NFC did not show pathogen growth inhibition. As the authors stated, the cationized sample NFCQ showed a strong broad-spectrum antimicrobial effect at a high concentration (2000 µg/mL). In contrast, the polymer-grafted NFC-PDMQ showed moderate antibacterial activity but a strong antifungal response. In addition, NFCQ was notably more efficient against the Gram-negative than the Gram-positive bacteria, but NFC-PDMQ exhibited consistent activity. A cytotoxicity test was also performed for both systems and confirmed the lack of toxicity.
</p>
