<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">The quest for further environmental and toxicological healthy and more suitable and efficient pesticides has been intensified by various demands. Thus, in plants, an evident solution was tried and found. Secondary metabolites from terrestrial plants have gained much interest in contemporary times as alternative sources for novel biopesticides. The traditional usage of these herbs and species by the indigenes of different regions of the world as antimicrobial and pesticides resources are well known (
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Dalziel, 1937</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Ayensu, 1978</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Bello et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>). Possibly, the earliest record shows that tobacco (
 <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>) is employed as pesticides. Decoction from the Tobacco leaves are employed to destroy aphids, this leads to the discovery of Nicotine, an alkaloid and a plant from Japan, the plantcRoh-ten with its scientific name referred to as 
 <italic>Rhododendron Hortense</italic>. Rotenone was isolated as the bioactive compound; it is used from early times as pesticides. Plants are large reservoir of secondary metabolites largely untapped or under-tapped for use as pesticide (
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Feyisa et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">Waziri, 2015</xref>). This review portrays and abridges the botanical description, folklore uses and the economic impact of 
 <italic>B. verticillata</italic> but emphases on its biological activity i.e. antimicrobial effects. The review assert that since this plant has a significant antimicrobial activity hence this activity can be drawn against plant-parasitic nematodes. Its significant antimicrobial activity can be channel against root-knot nematodes. Highlight of its phytochemistry was clearly stated because these are the secondary metabolites responsible for the antimicrobial effects hence the proposed nematicidal ability. Its resistance ability attest to the fact that it can be pursue further as a plant-based herbicide.
</p>
