<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Surfactants are amphiphilic molecules, which occur in numerous products of daily life in food, cosmetics and pharmaceuticals (Šabeder et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>; Marchant and Banat, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). Fatty acid sugar esters (a.k.a. glycolipids) are a class of surfactants, based on a sugar moiety and a fatty acid tail. Compared to other surfactant classes, they are commonly biodegradable, non-toxic and environmentally friendly being very mild and skin-friendly at the same time (Chang and Shaw, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). Synthesis of sugar esters can be performed by chemical processes as well as by microbial or enzymatic conversions (Ducret et al., 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1996</xref>). However, only enzymatic synthesis enables sustainable production of tailor-made sugar esters. Enzymatic synthesis of fatty acid sugar esters based on sugar and fatty acids or their respective esters is often catalyzed by esterases or lipases in reaction media of low water activity (Pöhnlein et al., 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Under these conditions, the hydrolytic activity of both enzyme classes is reversed and ester bonds are formed between the hydroxyl group of a sugar molecule and the carboxyl group of the fatty acid (Zaks and Klibanov, 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1985</xref>; Klibanov, 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1989</xref>). Esterification of sugar and fatty acid can take place in different reaction media, e.g., certain organic solvents, ionic liquids or deep eutectic solvents (DES). DES offer several advantages, as non-flammable, cheap, biodegradable and easy to produce. In general, DES consists of a mixture of a quaternary ammonium or phosphonium salt and a hydrogen bond donor. By interaction of both components the melting point of the mixture is strongly decreased resulting in a solution which is often liquid at room temperature (Abbott et al., 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>; Durand et al., 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>; Tang and Row, 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Since it was shown by Gorke et al. (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>), that hydrolases like esterases and lipases show high activity in deep eutectic solvents consisting of the ammonium salts choline chloride (CC) or ethylammonium chloride with different hydrogen bond donors, many other successful enzymatic reactions in DES were reported (Xu et al., 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>).
</p>
