<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In a previous study it was shown, that various sugars can act simultaneously as hydrogen bond donor for the DES formation, and as substrate for the enzymatic sugar ester production (Siebenhaller et al., 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Further, it was shown, that fatty acid vinyl esters with different chain length are suitable acyl chains. Siebenhaller et al. (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>) demonstrated that it is possible to use a cellulose fiber hydrolysate from beech wood as a sugar resource for both, enzymatic reaction and DES component, to synthesize sugar esters with a fossil-oil based fatty acid tail. To increase sustainability of the product, a renewable source for fatty acids or fatty acid esters like plant oil or microbial oil (“single cell oil,” SCO) can be used. In contrast to plant oils, microbial lipids can be produced independent from season, climate and location; they do not require arable land and a wide range of carbon sources, e.g., waste streams from food industry or renewable carbon sources, can be used for their production (Ochsenreither et al., 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). SCOs are produced by oleaginous microorganisms (bacteria, yeast, microalgae or filamentous fungi) which are able to accumulate 20–80% lipid per dry biomass in the stationary growth phase under nutrient limitations, e.g., nitrogen or phosphate, and coincident excess of carbon source (Ratledge, 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>). The basidiomycetous yeast 
 <italic class="italic">Cryptococcus curvatus</italic> belongs to one of the best studied oleaginous microorganisms. Under optimized conditions, 
 <italic class="italic">C. curvatus</italic> accumulates up to 60% lipid per dry biomass (Ratledge, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1991</xref>). Previous studies showed that 
 <italic class="italic">C. curvatus</italic> can utilize waste streams from industry, e.g., distillery or brewery waste, to produce SCO (Gonzales-Garcia et al., 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Ryu et al., 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Additionally, some hydrolysates, such as dilute sulfuric acid hydrolysates of wheat straw (with emphasis on acetate utilization) (Yu et al., 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) and alkaline-pretreated corn stover hydrolysate (resulting in ~30% (w/w) lipid content) (Gong et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) have been used as a substrate.
</p>
