<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the first test the suspension and culture medium were prepared as is described in the ISO 22196 (ISO 22196: Plastics—measurement of antibacterial activity on plastics and other non-porous surfaces (2011)). The test strains were incubated for 24 h at 37 °C. The antimicrobial testing method consisted of placing a drop of a suspension, of either 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> (ATCC 8739) or 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (ATCC 6538), onto the surface of the tested material (with a surface area of 5 cm × 5 cm). Each tested sample was prepared in a separate sterile vessel, with the test surface facing upwards. Then 0.4 mL of the test inoculum was dropped onto the tested surface. The test inoculum was covered with a piece of film (with a surface area 4 cm × 4 cm), which did not have anti-bacterial properties (neutral film), and was pressed mildly onto the film so that the test inoculum spread to the periphery. Half of the untreated specimens were processed instantly after inoculation, by adding 10 mL of Soybean Casein Lecithin Polysorbate Medium (SCDLP) broth (ISO 22196) to the vessel containing the test specimen. After this, the sum of viable bacterial cells was assessed. This obtained amount was used to evaluate the recovery rate of the bacteria from the investigated test specimens. After the inoculation of the specimen and the application of the cover film, the lid of the vessel was changed. After a 24 h incubation period, at 35 °C, the bacterial suspension was released from the coverslip-test sample and the sum of the viable bacterial cells that had survived was determined. The log values were the mean of 3 parallel samples (for each film type). The log reduction was the difference between the growth obtained with a neutral film (Stomacher bag) and the growth obtained with an active treated film. Sometimes a reduction, rather than growth, was observed with the neutral film, because of the low pH of the free lactic acid containing the PLA.
</p>
