<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In 2016, Taddeo and coworkers demonstrated for the first time in the literature the occurrence of 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin from something not belonging to the vegetable kingdom [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In their investigation devoted to comparing the efficiency of different extraction methodologies of selected prenylated and unprenylated coumarins and cinnamic acid derivatives from dry raw Italian propolis followed by quantification by HPLC analysis, it was shown that 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin could be easily extracted with good yields from this food matrix using several techniques such as maceration with pure ethanol (126.68 µg/g of dry propolis), ultrasonication with a 7:3 ethanol/water mixture (181.29 µg/g), and in the presence of β-cyclodextrin (β-CD) as an auxiliary agent either in water (1.5 
 <italic>w/w</italic>, 172.35 µg/g) or by far most efficiently in olive oil (295.84 µg/g) as the solvent. For raw propolis the latter has been seen as the most effective extraction route. The better extraction yields recorded with β-CD may be explained by the tight interaction of the 3,3-dimethylallyoxy side chain with the lipophilic environment represented by the inner cavity of the cyclic polysaccharide, as already evidenced by Tanaka and coworkers in 2010 [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Enforcing this hypothesis is the experimental knowledge that umbelliferon, the unprenylated parent coumarin of 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin, has been extracted in very low quantities under the same experimental conditions, while maceration with ethanol provides nearly equal concentration values. This study also indicated for the first time that a bee product like propolis could be regarded as an additional natural source of 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin and biologically active oxyprenylated phenylpropanoids in general. It suggested that the beneficial effects of propolis for human health can be also ascribed to less abundant phytochemicals, like those just mentioned, that could biologically act in synergy with major products typically found in great quantities in propolis like flavonoids and phenolic acids. For example, the reported neuroprotective properties of propolis [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] could be also ascribed to the presence of 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin, known to exert such effects both in vitro and in vivo [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The paper by Taddeo and coworkers can also be considered as a great stimulus to continue the search of such secondary metabolites in other bee-derived preparations such ashoney, pollen, royal jelly, and bee wax. Indeed, this kind of investigation would be unprecedented in the literature in widening the current knowledge on the chemical composition of healthy bee products.
</p>
