<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Formulation Descriptions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on traditional
  <span class="italic"> quilombola</span> medicinal use information, formulations containing
  <span class="italic"> breu</span> essential oils were developed and evaluated for their antinociceptive and sedative activities. The final concentration of essential oil in the formulations (0.1 g/mL) was established based on the amount of
  <span class="italic"> breu</span> used in burning and inhalation by
  <span class="italic"> quilombolas</span> [
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>] as well as the mean yield of essential oil in the
  <span class="italic"> breu</span> samples [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>]. Although the traditional mode of use of
  <span class="italic"> breu</span> by the
  <span class="italic"> quilombola</span> communities involves burning and subsequent inhalation of the smoke produced, the chamber developed for this study does not foresee this procedure.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All of the formulations presented a clear and monophasic aspect, with a slightly yellowish color and a characteristic scent, indicating that solutions with molecular dispersion were obtained [
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>, 
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>]. Because they were extemporaneous formulations, it was necessary to disperse them in water before nebulization, generating a heterogeneous system known as a liquid-liquid dispersion. This probably occurs because the excess water makes the medium quite polar, preventing the apolar components of the essential oil from remaining in the solution [
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>, 
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>]. Despite the heterogeneous nature of the solution in the formulation cup, the compressed air injected by the nebulizer generates a vortex that guarantees homogeneous air nebulization inside the chamber [
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
