<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Formulation Descriptions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on traditional
   <span class="italic"> quilombola</span> medicinal use information, formulations containing
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> essential oils were developed and evaluated for their antinociceptive and sedative activities. The final concentration of essential oil in the formulations (0.1 g/mL) was established based on the amount of
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> used in burning and inhalation by
   <span class="italic"> quilombolas</span> [
   <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>] as well as the mean yield of essential oil in the
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> samples [
   <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>]. Although the traditional mode of use of
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> by the
   <span class="italic"> quilombola</span> communities involves burning and subsequent inhalation of the smoke produced, the chamber developed for this study does not foresee this procedure.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All of the formulations presented a clear and monophasic aspect, with a slightly yellowish color and a characteristic scent, indicating that solutions with molecular dispersion were obtained [
   <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>, 
   <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>]. Because they were extemporaneous formulations, it was necessary to disperse them in water before nebulization, generating a heterogeneous system known as a liquid-liquid dispersion. This probably occurs because the excess water makes the medium quite polar, preventing the apolar components of the essential oil from remaining in the solution [
   <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>, 
   <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>]. Despite the heterogeneous nature of the solution in the formulation cup, the compressed air injected by the nebulizer generates a vortex that guarantees homogeneous air nebulization inside the chamber [
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Chemical Analysis of the Air Nebulized inside the Chamber</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chemical composition of the volatiles produced during operation of the nebulizing chamber was analyzed by static head space sampling of the chamber air by a sampling port. In this chamber, the animal holders have an air output (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1(a)</a>, 10) that can be sealed by a plastic screw cap. These outputs are opened during the tests, forcing the intake air to leave the chamber thought them since they are the only exits from the chamber [
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>]. The main components in each essential oil formulation,
   <span class="bold"> A</span>–
   <span class="bold">E,</span> were quantified in the nebulized air and are shown in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>. The chemical composition of each
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> essential oil present in the formulations is described in Da Silva et al. [
   <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>]. Compared to the individual composition of the essential oils observed in a previous study [
   <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>], the composition of each nebulized formulation was quite similar to that of the original essential oils. In all formulations, the major components were present and at higher concentrations than the other components. A mixture of 
   <span class="italic">δ</span>-3-carene/isosylvestrene was the major component of the head space air from Formulation “
   <span class="bold">A</span>” (58.96% in the first minute and 56.4% after 15 min), which was prepared with the BBIM, BBPIR, BBIR
   <sub>1</sub>, and BBIR
   <sub>2</sub> essential oils (61.45% mean in the original oils);
   <span class="italic"> p</span>-cymene was found at 20.6% (first minute) and 22.5% (after 15 min) in the head space air of Formulation “
   <span class="bold">B</span>”, prepared with the BBIR
   <sub>3</sub> and WBB1 essential oils (32.7% mean in the original oils);
   <span class="italic"> p</span>-cymene (27.9% in the first minute and 23.4% after 15 min) and a high concentration of sesquiterpenes were the major compounds in the nebulized air from Formulation “
   <span class="bold">C</span>”, prepared with the BBTF1 and BBTF2 essential oils (11.45% mean of 
   <span class="italic">p</span>-cymene in the original essential oils); a mixture of limonene/
   <span class="italic">β</span>-phellandrene (33.4% in the first minute and 6.4% after 15 min) and 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-terpineol (15.4% in the first minute and 68.9% after 15 min) was detected as the major component in the head space air of Formulation “
   <span class="bold">D</span>”, prepared with the WBB
   <sub>2</sub> essential oil (41.1% limonene/
   <span class="italic">β</span>-phellandrene mix and 30.9%  
   <span class="italic">α</span>-terpineol in the original essential oil). Finally, 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-pinene was found at 68.8% (first minute) and 49.2% (after 15 min) in the head space of Formulation “
   <span class="bold">E</span>”, prepared with the WBIG essential oil, which contained 57.7%  
   <span class="italic">α</span>-pinene in its original composition. From 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>, it can be seen that, in the first minute, lower molecular weight components (monoterpene hydrocarbons) were detected at higher relative percent concentrations, as expected. This is why 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-pinene was detected at a higher relative percentage in Formulation E in the first minute (68.8%) than in the original essential oil (57.7%). By the fifteenth minute, the relative percent concentrations of the monoterpene hydrocarbons decayed while concentrations of the oxygenated monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes increased. This suggests that initially mice receive a dose that is rich in monoterpenes, which are lighter and probably more easily dispersed in the nebulized droplets. As the formulation is depleted, it is heavier and more difficult to disperse components that are nebulized, increasing their concentration inside the chamber. This is clearly seen in Formulation
   <span class="bold"> D</span>, in which the major compounds in the first minute are a mixture of 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-phellandrene-limonene (monoterpene hydrocarbons), which are replaced by 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-terpineol (oxygenated monoterpene) as the major volatile compound of the air sample collected at the second time point (15 min).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Hot Plate Test</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The hot plate test was employed to assess antinociceptive activity. In the hot plate test, the response to pain stimuli is relayed to the supraspinal reflex mediated by 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>
   <sub>1</sub> and 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>
   <sub>2</sub> opioid receptors [
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>]. This test was developed by Woolfe &amp; Macdonald in 1944 [
   <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>] and improved by many other researchers, such as Eddy et al. [
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>] and O'Callaghan and Holtzman [
   <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>]. In all of these cases, antinociceptive activity is characterized by an increased tolerance to pain by the animal when in contact with a heated plate.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">None of the mice that inhaled any of the tested formulations showed a significant increase in response time compared to animals that inhaled compressed air or vehicle, indicating the absence of antinociceptive activity (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a> and 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>). This result is in accordance with previous work from Rao and coworkers [
   <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>], who reported that oral administration of
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> essential oil obtained from
   <span class="italic"> P. heptaphyllum</span> did not result in antinociceptive activity in the hot plate test.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Formalin-Induced Licking Test</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Intraplantar administration of formalin produces nociception, which is characterized by two distinct phases [
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>]. The early phase (neurogenic phase) occurs in the first five minutes and is associated with direct chemical stimulus of the afferent fibers, mainly C-fibers [
   <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>, 
   <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>], with activation of TRPA1 channels [
   <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>], and reflects centrally mediated pain. The late phase (inflammatory phase) occurs between 15 and 30 minutes after formalin injection and is mediated by the release of a combination of inflammatory mediators and sensitization of central nociceptive neurons [
   <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>, 
   <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>, 
   <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">37</a>]. It is well-known that centrally acting drugs, such as opioids, inhibit nociception in both phases, while peripheral-acting drugs, such as acetylsalicylic acid, inhibit only the second phase [
   <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>, 
   <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">38</a>]. In addition, the activity of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs is also observed in the second phase [
   <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>, 
   <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>, 
   <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3</a> and 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a> show the results of the five formulations on the formalin test. The vehicle did not produce significant inhibition of the licking response in the early or the late phase. The results obtained from inhalation of the nebulized formulations were compared with those obtained from inhalation of the vehicle. Formulation B reduced the licking time significantly only in the early phase (36.9%), suggesting possible central pain inhibition. Formulation D suppressed the licking time significantly only in the late phase (37.9%), indicating possible peripheral antinociception by decreasing tonic inflammatory pain. Only Formulation E significantly suppressed the licking time in both the early phase (46.8%) and late phase (60.2%), indicating that it is effective on both tonic inflammatory and central pain.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because the pain mechanisms assessed using the hot plate and formalin tests are different, it is common for substances to be active in only one of the models. This was observed with the oral administration of
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> essential oil, which resulted in antinociceptive activity in both the capsaicin and formalin (only in the second phase) tests and none in the hot plate test [
   <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>]. This was also observed in the present study, as well as in others [
   <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">39</a>, 
   <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>]. The active substances present in all of these studies probably do not have affinity with opioid receptors, as they are inactive in the hot plate test.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The activity shown by formulations B, D, and E is related to their essential oil compositions since the compressed air (control group), vehicle (vehicle group), and Formulations A and C did not present a decrease in the licking time in either phase. Thus, the predominant presence of monoterpenes (
   <span class="italic">α</span>-pinene,
   <span class="italic"> p</span>-cymene, 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-phellandrene, limonene, and 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-pinene) in the fraction of nebulized and inhaled air of Formulations B, D, and E (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>) may be related to the antinociceptive activity. In addition, the fraction of nebulized and inhaled air of Formulation E also had a high concentration of 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-terpineol (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>), a potent analgesic that acts on both central and peripheral pain [
   <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>]. Interesting results regarding the antinociceptive activity of these monoterpenes administered by different pathways can be found in the literature. When administered intraperitoneally in mice, limonene presents antinociceptive activity in acetic acid and formalin (mainly in the second phase) tests without sedative properties [
   <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">42</a>]. Additionally,
   <span class="italic"> p</span>-cymene injected intraperitoneally in mice presented orofacial antinociceptive activity in formalin, capsaicin, and glutamate tests, without sedative properties [
   <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">43</a>]. Similarly, 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-phellandrene [
   <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">39</a>] and 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-pinene [
   <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>] also showed antinociceptive properties in different models. These data suggest that the combination of these components in the formulations is a crucial factor in the observed antinociceptive activity.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to antinociceptive properties, these monoterpenes present anti-inflammatory activity. Limonene, for example, in addition to being the major component of essential oils from
   <span class="italic"> Citrus</span> species with anti-inflammatory activity when administered orally also had the same effect when tested alone [
   <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">45</a>]. Bergamot essential oil is rich in limonene and 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-pinene, which are mainly responsible for the anti-inflammatory activity of Bergamot in the carrageenan test [
   <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">46</a>]. 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-Pinene is also a major component in
   <span class="italic"> Chenopodium album </span>L. [
   <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">47</a>] and
   <span class="italic"> Ugni myricoides</span> [
   <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">48</a>] leaf essential oils, which have anti-inflammatory properties against TPA and carrageenan, respectively. This monoterpene is involved in immunologic activation and inflammatory intermediate synthesis inhibition, which are important for the pharmacological properties of many essential oils [
   <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">49</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The different tested
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> formulations significantly decreased the duration of the licking time in both phases of pain responses in the formalin-induced licking model. One possible explanation for this effect is that
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> may act by decreasing the release of inflammatory mediators or exert direct effects on different receptors present in the paw, such as bradykinin, serotonin, or opioid receptors, thus reducing the licking response.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. Rota-Rod Test</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rota-rod test is a safe and efficient test to assess an animal's motor coordination and balance. It has been employed to directly measure the influence of essential oils and their components on the central nervous system [
   <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">50</a>, 
   <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>]. Another advantage of the rota-rod test is that it allows distinguishing analgesic or anti-inflammatory effects from possible sedative effects since nonspecific muscle relaxation effects may reduce motor coordination and mask the mice's response to nociception [
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although
   <span class="italic"> quilombolas</span> reported mild drowsiness and relaxation after burning and inhalation of the
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> oleoresin [
   <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>], all of the tested animals remained conscious and no visible effects on their behavior were observed from
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> formulation inhalation. The amount of alcohol in the formulation did not appear to affect the behavior of the animals since administration of the vehicle alone (which contains alcohol) did not generate any behavioral changes. Although it is well-known that several monoterpenes can induce seizures [
   <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">52</a>], we did not observe this effect in the tested mice.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">None of the formulations with essential oils presented sedative or motor coordination depressant effects after nebulization and inhalation since the number of animal falls was quite reduced (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab5" href="#tab5">Table 5</a>). However, it should be taken into account that the
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> formulations evaluated in the present study only contained the volatile fractions (essential oils) and that
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> was not submitted to combustion. Burning of an oleoresin, as is usually done in the traditional use, may induce changes in the chemical composition, as pyrolysis may occur. This effect was not evaluated here. However, during the traditional mode of use, burning occurs slowly and at least some of the volatile compounds pass to the vapor phase by evaporation due to the heating flux, before pyrolysis, similar to cigarette burning, for example. Therefore, both the original compounds and pyrolysis products might be present in the smoke inhaled during traditional use. Nevertheless, the absence of sedative or motor coordination depressant effect is a satisfactory result since it demonstrates that any of the observed anti-inflammatory or antinociceptive effects are associated with a depressor effect above the central nervous system. Other essential oils, such as
   <span class="italic"> Chrysopogon zizanioides</span> [
   <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">39</a>] and
   <span class="italic"> Croton sanderianus</span> [
   <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>], also have antinociceptive and anti-inflammatory activity without sedative properties. Myrcene and linalool, which are components of the
   <span class="italic"> breu</span> essential oil, have sedative and motor system depressant activities at high concentrations [
   <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">53</a>, 
   <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">54</a>]. However, it appears that their concentrations in the nebulized and inhaled air fractions were not enough to trigger such effects.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
