<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">Atherosclerosis is characterized by the accumulation of lipid-rich plaques in the arterial wall. Its pathogenesis is very complicated and has not yet been fully elucidated. It is known that dyslipidemia is a major factor in atherosclerosis. Several different Hermansky–Pudlak syndrome (HPS) mutant mice have been shown either anti-atherosclerotic or atherogenic phenotypes, which may be mainly attributed to corresponding lipid perturbation. To explore the effects of different HPS proteins on lipid metabolism and plasma lipid composition, we analyzed the plasma lipid profiles of three HPS mutant mice, 
  <italic class="italic">pa</italic> (
  <italic class="italic">Hps9</italic>
  <sup class="sup">−/−</sup>), 
  <italic class="italic">ru</italic> (
  <italic class="italic">Hps6</italic>
  <sup class="sup">−/−</sup>), 
  <italic class="italic">ep</italic> (
  <italic class="italic">Hps1</italic>
  <sup class="sup">−/−</sup>), and wild-type (WT) mice. In 
  <italic class="italic">pa</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">ru</italic> mice, some pro-atherosclerotic lipids, e.g. ceramide (Cer) and diacylglycerol (DAG), were down-regulated whereas triacylglycerol (TAG) containing docosahexaenoic acid (DHA) (22:6) fatty acyl was up-regulated when compared with WT mice. Several pro-atherosclerotic lipids including phosphatidic acid (PA), lysophosphatidylserine (LPS), sphingomyelin (SM), and cholesterol (Cho) were up-regulated in 
  <italic class="italic">ep</italic> mice compared with WT mice. The lipid droplets in hepatocytes showed corresponding changes in these mutants. Our data suggest that the 
  <italic class="italic">pa</italic> mutant resembles the 
  <italic class="italic">ru</italic> mutant in its anti-atherosclerotic effects, but the 
  <italic class="italic">ep</italic> mutant has an atherogenic effect. Our findings may provide clues to explain why different HPS mutant mice exhibit distinct anti-atherosclerotic or atherogenic effects after being exposed to high-cholesterol diets.
 </p>
</abstract>
