<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Ethnobiology and Ethnomedicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1746-4269</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">386</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-020-00386-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Filling the gaps: ethnobotanical study of the Garrigues district, an arid zone in Catalonia (NE Iberian Peninsula)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Gras</surname><given-names>Airy</given-names></name><address><email>airy.gras@ibb.csic.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>Joan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garnatje</surname><given-names>Teresa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.507630.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2107 4293</institution-id><institution>Institut Bot&#x000e0;nic de Barcelona (IBB; CSIC-Ajuntament de Barcelona), </institution></institution-wrap>Passeig del Migdia s.n., Parc de Montju&#x000ef;c, 08038 Barcelona, Catalonia Spain </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5841.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 0247</institution-id><institution>Laboratori de Bot&#x000e0;nica (UB) - Unitat associada al CSIC, Facultat de Farm&#x000e0;cia i Ci&#x000e8;ncies de l&#x02019;Alimentaci&#x000f3;, Institut de Recerca de la Biodiversitat &#x02013; IRBio, </institution><institution>Universitat de Barcelona, </institution></institution-wrap>Av. Joan XXIII 27-31, 08028 Barcelona, Catalonia Spain </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.425916.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2195 5891</institution-id><institution>Institut d&#x02019;Estudis Catalans, </institution></institution-wrap>C. del Carme 47, 08001 Barcelona, Catalonia Spain </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>34</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">This study has focused on the Garrigues district, one of the most arid regions in Catalonia (NE Iberian Peninsula), which, in general terms, has remained unexplored from the ethnobotanical point of view. This area, of 22,243 inhabitants, comprises 33 municipalities distributed across 1123.12&#x02009;km<sup>2</sup>. The natural vegetation is dominated by holm oak forests and maquis called &#x02018;garriga&#x02019;, the latter giving its name to the district. During the last few decades, this landscape has been transformed by agricultural activities, nowadays in recession. The main aim of this work was to collect and analyse the ethnoflora of this area in order to fill a gap in the ethnobotanical knowledge in Catalonia.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">The followed methodology was based on semi-structured interviews. The obtained data have been qualitatively and quantitatively analysed and compared with other available ones.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Data were gathered from 68 interviews involving 101 informants, whose ages range from 24 to 94, the mean being 73.07. The number of taxa reported in this study was 420, belonging to 99 botanical families. The interviewed informants referred 4715 use reports (UR) of 346 useful taxa, 1741 (36.93) of them corresponding to medicinal uses, 1705 (36.16%) to food uses, and 1269 (26.91%) to other uses. This study has inventoried, apart from individual plant uses, 260 plant mixtures, of which 98 are medicinal and 162 food. In the present study, 849 vernacular names with 116 phonetic variants have been collected, as well, for 410 taxa. The informant consensus factor (F<sub>IC</sub>) obtained for our interviewees is 0.93, and the ethnobotanicity index is 23.47% for the studied area. Apart from plants belonging to the typical Catalan, Iberian or European ethnofloras, the present work contributes information on some plants from semiarid or arid regions, such as <italic>Artemisia herba-alba</italic> and <italic>Plantago albicans</italic>, much rarer in the ethnobotany of the quoted areas.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">The results of this study reveal the persistence of ethnobotanical knowledge in the prospected area and the importance of filling the existing gaps in the ethnofloristic sampling of the Catalan territories. The almost complete dataset, now including some arid territories, will allow us to carry out a global analysis and to provide an accurate overview.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Arid zones</kwd><kwd>Catalonia</kwd><kwd>Ethnobotany</kwd><kwd>Ethnopharmacology</kwd><kwd>Food uses</kwd><kwd>Garrigues</kwd><kwd>Iberian Peninsula</kwd><kwd>Medicinal uses</kwd><kwd>Plant uses</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100002809</institution-id><institution>Generalitat de Catalunya</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2017SGR001116</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>Joan</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100010770</institution-id><institution>Institut d'Estudis Catalans</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>PRO2017-S02VALLES</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>Joan</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Spanish Government</institution></funding-source><award-id>CSO2014-59704-P</award-id><award-id>CGL2017-84297-R</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Garnatje</surname><given-names>Teresa</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100005774</institution-id><institution>Universitat de Barcelona</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Predoctoral grant</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Gras</surname><given-names>Airy</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">One hundred twenty-four years after ethnobotany&#x02019;s first definition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], Catalonia finds itself among the well-studied territories at the level of traditional knowledge on plant biodiversity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Mountainous regions have been extensively sampled from the beginning of the practice of this science in our country [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], drawing an almost complete ethnobotanical map of the Catalan part of the Pyrenean mountain range [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Also profusely investigated is the coast and the two mountain ranges (littoral and prelittoral) that stretch along the coastline, from the area just north of Cap de Creus to Terres de l&#x02019;Ebre in the south [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], basically constituting the Catalanidic territory from the physiographic point of view [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], and plateaus and basins of central Catalonia, in the Auso-Segarric physiographic territory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Apart from a few areas in the Pyrenees and the Ebro delta and its neighbouring territories, Catalan ethnobotanical prospection presents a significant gap in the Western plains. This area has a continental Mediterranean climate, with high thermic contrasts between warm and cold periods, and significantly dry, with almost five arid or perarid months per year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The soil is generally calcareous and, not rarely, saline or gypseous [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. These territories, roughly coincidental with the Sicoric physiographic territory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], are the only semiarid or arid lands in Catalonia, where some elements of steppe flora are present [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">Although the arid zones have not attracted the interest of researchers as much as mountain or tropical areas, since, a priori, they are considered less rich and diverse compared to the zones with more exuberant vegetation, the arid Iberian lands have been studied in depth from the botanical point of view by the pioneering work of Bol&#x000f2;s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] and Braun-Blanquet and Bol&#x000f2;s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Some examples of botanical studies focused on flora and vegetation, carried out in areas close to the Garrigues district, may be found at Masclans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], Bold&#x000fa; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], Recasens and Conesa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], Recasens et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], Sol&#x000e9;-Senan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], and the references contained in these papers. Concerning useful plants, the classical approach for arid lands has been the study of economic plants that could be grown or exploited in these areas for landscape protection and, mostly, agricultural and livestock raising activities (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]). Ethnobotanical studies have also been carried out in arid and semiarid areas all around the world (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]), including the Iberian Peninsula [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], although to date, none has yet been performed in Catalonia.</p><p id="Par7">The studied area, belonging to an arid region, is the Garrigues district (in Catalan &#x02018;comarca&#x02019;), located in west Catalonia, NE Iberian Peninsula (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Our study has focused on the Garrigues <italic>sensu lato</italic>, also including nine municipalities that had previously been located in the Garrigues district but currently belong to Segri&#x000e0; district and are known as historical Garrigues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Map of the study area showing the location of Catalonia within Europe, the Garrigues district within Catalonia and the municipalities of the Garrigues <italic>sensu lato.</italic> The municipalities on the right of the red line correspond to the Garrigues <italic>sensu stricto</italic> and those on the left side, to historical Garrigues</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2020_386_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">The Garrigues <italic>sensu lato</italic> has an altitude range from 201&#x02009;m&#x02009;a.s.l., in the locality of Sarroca de Lleida, to 1021&#x02009;m&#x02009;a.s.l., in Punta del Curull (Serra de la Llena, el Vilosell). The climate is low altitude continental Mediterranean, considered arid or semiarid, with a rainfall of about 333&#x02009;mm/year. Winters are very cold and summers are very hot, with an annual mean of 14.4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with minimum and maximum temperatures of &#x02212;&#x02009;6.8 &#x000b0;C and 37.3&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">There are fundamental climax plant communities in the studied area. A kind of holm oak forest called &#x02018;carrascar&#x02019; in Catalan language (<italic>Quercetum rotundifoliae</italic>) dominates a large part of the Garrigues district. A portion of the Garrigues, including the so-called historical (belonging to Segri&#x000e0; district) is more arid and dominated by a maquis (<italic>Rhamno lycioidis-Quercetum cocciferae</italic>) called &#x02018;garriga&#x02019; (plural &#x02018;garrigues&#x02019;) in the Catalan language, which gives its name to the district. The part called Garrigues Altes (Serra de la Llena) is dominated by another type of holm oak tree forest (<italic>Viburno tini-Quercetum ilicis</italic>) called &#x02018;alzinar&#x02019; in the Catalan language [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. These climax communities are to a large extent degraded, and the landscape is far from the pure one of the plant formations quoted. Time and human action model a landscape fruit of the transformation of the natural vegetation by agricultural activities. In some cases, agriculture is currently in recession, and the abandoned fields will evolve again in terms of landscape.</p><p id="Par10">The &#x02018;carrascar&#x02019; forest degradation gives a &#x02018;garriga&#x02019; poor in species and other formations such as <italic>Rosmarino officinalis-Linetum suffruticosi</italic>, <italic>Genisto-Cistetum clusii</italic>, <italic>Ruto angustifolii-Brachypodietum retusi</italic> or <italic>Salsolo vermiculatae-Artemisietum herbae-albae</italic>, this in part depending on the salinity and aridity of each area. In parallel, degradation of the maquis leads to the aforementioned communities plus <italic>Delphinio gracilis-Lygeetum sparti</italic>. Finally, &#x02018;alzinar&#x02019; forest degradation gives rise to shrub or herbaceous formations such as <italic>Erico multiflorae-Thymelaeetum tinctoriae</italic> or <italic>Phlomido angustifolii-Brachypodietum retusi</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p><p id="Par11">The study area is composed of 33 municipalities and comprises 1123.12&#x02009;km<sup>2</sup> and 22,243 inhabitants, representing a density of 19.80 inhabitants/km<sup>2</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. It is a very depopulated territory with an ageing population, 26.44% being over 65. The overageing index (quotient between the number of people aged 85&#x02009;years and over and the number of people aged 65 and over, expressed as a percentage) is 21.59%, and the ageing index (quotient between the number of people aged 65&#x02009;years and over and the number of young people under 15&#x02009;years of age, expressed as a percentage) is 218.91% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. These data reflect a rather discouraging situation of the district in terms of population and highlight the importance of this study, since traditional biodiversity knowledge, in Western countries traditionally safeguarded to a considerable extent by old people, could fail to be transmitted, due to the lack or scarcity of young generations.</p><p id="Par12">Economically, the Garrigues district can be defined as a rural area based on agriculture and livestock activities. Cereals, fruit and olive trees are the predominant crops, and poultry and pig farms, the main livestock. According to the agrarian register of 2009, the agricultural area occupies 60,745&#x02009;ha and represents 54% of the district [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p><p id="Par13">Between the second half of the eighteenth century and the end of the nineteenth century, a big agricultural expansion occurred in the studied area, coincidental with a significant increase in the population. This caused the brushwood clearing of difficult, abrupt zones covered by natural vegetation in order to become convenient for agricultural uses, originating a typical terrace structure. In 1865, the Urgell canal was opened, which brought water to northwest district municipalities (Arbeca, les Borges Blanques, Puiggr&#x000f2;s, Juneda and, in part, Castelldans), allowing the diversification of crops: olive and almond trees, cereals in the dry farming lands, and alfalfa and maize in the irrigated lands [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Nowadays, the Urgell canal is not the only one, since, with the construction of the Segarra-Garrigues canal (2002&#x02013;2030), the areas of possible irrigation are increasing, although the latter canal is not yet being used at 100% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">Even though western Catalonia arid lands have been the object of a relatively abundant number of botanical investigations, mostly centred on flora and vegetation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], the ethnobotanical background in the studied area is poor and could be described as practically inexistent. Just some ethnographic works have been done in the district, but not specifically focused on plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. As for the neighbouring areas, only the Segarra district, not far from the Garrigues, but belonging to another physiographic territory, as above commented, has been studied from the ethnobotanical point of view [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p><p id="Par15">The main aims of the present research are (i) to contribute towards filling a gap in the ethnobotanical knowledge map of Catalonia, (ii) to collect plant uses and their vernacular names in a depopulated arid or semiarid rural area, (iii) to analyse the ethnoflora in order to detect specific useful taxa of arid or semiarid areas and (iv) to establish some comparisons with other studied areas.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Material and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Fieldwork methods</title><p id="Par16">The fieldwork method used was semi-structured interviews [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], always taking into account ethical principles of the International Society of Ethnobiology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] and with the oral informed consent of the informants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Interviews were carried out from May 2015 to July 2017 and were developed in the Catalan language, common to interviewers and interviewees. All information was digitalised, transcribed and introduced into our database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gestio.etnobotanica.cat">www.gestio.etnobotanica.cat</ext-link>) which contains all ethnobotanical data (on medicinal, food and other uses) collected by our research group.</p><p id="Par17">The plant taxa cited by the informants were identified using the Flora Manual dels Pa&#x000ef;sos Catalans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. For systematic and nomenclatural aspects, we follow this quoted flora of the Catalan language area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] for specific and infraspecific levels, and APG IV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] for families. The herbarium vouchers have been deposited in the herbarium BCN (Centre de Documentaci&#x000f3; de Biodiversitat Vegetal, Universitat de Barcelona).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Data analyses</title><p id="Par18">The analyses were carried out with Excel (Microsoft Excel 2007) program. To analyse the results, we have used the use report (hereinafter, UR), i.e. the report of the use of one taxon by an informant, as the unit of measurement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p><p id="Par19">With the aim of assessing the state of ethnobotanical knowledge in the studied area, the following indices were calculated. The informant consensus factor (F<sub>IC</sub>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>], which is the ratio of the number of UR minus the number of used taxa to the number of UR minus one, is more reliable when closer to 1. The ethnobotanicity index (EI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>], which is the quotient between the number of plants used (only taking into account the native plants) and the total number of plants that constitute the flora of the territory, is expressed as a percentage. For this purpose, we have considered the plants present in the 10 &#x000d7; 10&#x02009;km UTM squares corresponding to the studied area in the Banc de Dades de Biodiversitat de Catalunya [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. The index of medicinal importance (MI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>] was also calculated, dividing the total use reports for a specific use category by the number of taxa possessing this use.</p><p id="Par20">We calculated the number of medicinal plants used per informant (MP/I), per inhabitant (MP/H), and per unit of area (MP/km<sup>2</sup>), in order to compare the results with other territories from which this information is provided only for this kind of useful plants.</p><p id="Par21">For preparations with more than one plant, we obtained the recently proposed index of taxon usefulness in mixtures (ITUM) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>], which is the quotient between the number of reports of one taxon in mixtures and its total citations, whether simple or complex presentation. This index indicates the exclusiveness of taxa in mixtures when the value is one or closer to one.</p><p id="Par22">Finally, for the vernacular names, we calculated the ethnophytonymy index [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], i.e. the percentage of taxa present in the flora that have folk names; the allochtonous ethnophytonymy index proposed by Carri&#x000f3; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>] assesses the rate between taxa having a vernacular name in non-Catalan languages (even for those taxa also having some Catalan names) and the total number of collected taxa; and the linguistic diversity index in phytonymy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>], i.e. the mean number of folk names for the plants recorded in the ethnofloristic prospection, computes the rate between the number of vernacular names and their taxa to evaluate the linguistic richness of a territory independently of its flora.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Validation in the literature</title><p id="Par23">To confirm the reported specific uses by participants in the study, we additionally reviewed the literature to carry out a pharmacological validation of most reported plants, those with three or more reports for a particular use, using monographs from official sources and encyclopaedic bibliography on phytotherapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Characteristics of the interviewees</title><p id="Par24">Data were gathered from 68 interviews to 101 informants. The interviewees&#x02019; ages range from 24 to 94, and the mean age is 73.07; 59.41% of them were, men and the remaining 40.59% were women, which is not common in Catalan ethnobotanical studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. This deficit could be explained by the exodus of women to the cities, to work or to study, whereas men remained in the district. Nowadays, the Garrigues population has 1000 more men than women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. The informants were born in the studied area or have been living there a very significant part of their lives, and most of them are professionally related to agricultural and livestock raising activities.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Plant taxa, botanical families and use reports</title><p id="Par25">The number of taxa reported in this study was 420 (belonging to 99 botanical families), 25 of them have only been determined at the generic level and 46 presenting infraspecific category. In some cases, we are facing ethnotaxa, when all the species included in a genus are used indistinctly or when the informants were not able to distinguish them. The complete dataset of the recorded useful plants in the studied area is available in the <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Supplementary material</xref>.</p><p id="Par26">The five best-represented families are Asteraceae (11.43%), Lamiaceae (7.38%), Fabaceae (7.14%), Rosaceae (5.71%) and Poaceae (5.00%). Two reasons could explain these results: on the one side, these families are large in terms of the number of species, and on the other, they are common in the Mediterranean landscape. We highlight the fifth place of the Poaceae in the UR ranking, insignificant in other ethnobotanical studies in Catalan regions. Some genera of this family are largely cultivated as cereal in the Garrigues and thus are well known and appreciated by local people. In addition, other genera belonging to the same family that grow wild there are typical of the arid and steppe regions, not only in the studied area. In agreement with the last assertion, this family occupies the first place in the ranking in an ethnobotanical prospection in a semiarid zone in Ethiopia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>].</p><p id="Par27">The interviewed informants refer 4715 use reports (UR) of 346 useful taxa, 1741 (36.93) of them corresponding to medicinal uses, 1705 (36.16%) to food uses, and 1269 (26.91%) to other uses. The numbers show that a proportional sampling effort has been made for the three categories.</p><p id="Par28">This first ethnobotanical approach to an arid or semiarid zone contributes 41 new taxa (9.76%) not mentioned before as useful in Catalonia (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), one of them, <italic>Moricandia arvensis</italic> (L.) DC., being exclusive to the Sicoric physiographic territory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In addition, among the 420 taxa mentioned, we find species with climatic and geographical affinities not common in previously studied territories: Mediterranean-Saharian connection species like <italic>Atriplex halimus</italic> L. or <italic>Salsola vermiculata</italic> L.; Iberian (European)-Pontian connection plants such as <italic>Salsola soda</italic> L.; Mediterraneo-Turanian connection taxa such as <italic>Artemisia herba-alba</italic> Asso or <italic>Stipa parviflora</italic> Desf.; Mediterranean plants of arid areas like <italic>Lygeum spartum</italic> L. or <italic>Plantago albicans</italic> L.; Iberian-Magrebian plants such as <italic>Ononis tridentata</italic> L. or <italic>Retama sphaerocarpa</italic> (L.) Boiss.; and typical Iberian endemics of these dry areas, such as <italic>Dictamnus hispanicus</italic> Webb ex Willk. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>New contributions from the studied area to the ethnoflora of Catalonia</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Taxon, family and herbarium voucher</th><th>Vernacular names (in Catalan if there is no another indication)</th><th>Medicinal use</th><th>Food use</th><th>Other use</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>Antirrhinum barrelieri</italic> Boreau subsp. <italic>litigiosum</italic> (Pau) O.Bol&#x000f2;s et Vigo (Plantaginaceae) BCN 150372</td><td>Esquitxag&#x000f3;s, gallets, sabateta de la Mare de D&#x000e9;u</td><td/><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Artemisia herba-alba</italic> Asso (Asteraceae) BCN 129018</td><td>Botja, botja pudenta, espernallac bord, espernallac mascle</td><td>x</td><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Asphodelus cerasiferus</italic> Gay (Asphodelaceae) BCN 125419</td><td>Albi&#x000f3;, bironer</td><td>x</td><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Bupleurum fruticosum</italic> L. (Apiaceae) BCN 156605</td><td>Matabou</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Carlina corymbosa</italic> L. subsp. <italic>hispanica</italic> (Lam.) O.Bol&#x000f2;s et J.Vigo (Asteraceae) BCN 125418</td><td>Assotacristos</td><td/><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Centaurea paniculata</italic> L. subsp. <italic>leucophaea</italic> (Jord.) Briq. (Asteraceae) BCN 140160</td><td>Trencacaps</td><td/><td>x</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Coronilla juncea</italic> L. (Fabaceae) BCN 150377</td><td>Herba del cascat</td><td>x</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Coronilla minima</italic> L. subsp. <italic>lotoides</italic> (Koch) Nyman (Fabaceae) BCN 125401</td><td>Espernallac, herba del cascat</td><td>x</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Coronilla valentina</italic> L. subsp. <italic>glauca</italic> (L.) Batt. in Batt. et Trab. (Fabaceae) BCN 140154</td><td/><td/><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Crataegus azarolus</italic> L. (Rosaceae) BCN 96759</td><td>Agret, atzeroler</td><td>x</td><td>x</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Cynoglossum cheirifolium</italic> L. (Boraginaceae) BCN 156570</td><td>Besneula</td><td>x</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Cytinus hypocistis</italic> (L.) L. (Cytinaceae) BCN 140178</td><td>Arnetes de mel, pinyetes, popetes, regineta, tenalletes de mel</td><td/><td>x</td><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ephedra distachya</italic> L. (Ephedraceae) BCN 150358</td><td>Efedra</td><td>x</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Helianthemum syriacum</italic> (Jacq.) Dum.Cours. (Cistaceae) BCN 125478</td><td>Romer blanc</td><td>x</td><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Jasminum fruticans</italic> L. (Oleaceae) BCN 125492</td><td>Gessam&#x000ed;</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Kochia scoparia</italic> (L.) Schrad. (Amaranthaceae) BCN 140172</td><td>Mirambell</td><td/><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Lavatera maritima</italic> Gouan (Malvaceae) BCN 14355</td><td>Malva marina</td><td>x</td><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Limodorum abortivum</italic> (L.) Swartz (Orchidaceae) BCN 51622</td><td>Orqu&#x000ed;dia de color rosa</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Limonium hibericum</italic> Erben (Plumbaginaceae) BCN 96755</td><td/><td/><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Lonicera implexa</italic> Ait. subsp. <italic>implexa</italic> (Caprifoliaceae) BCN 125512</td><td>Lligabosc</td><td>x</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Moricandia arvensis</italic> (L.) DC. (Brassicaceae) BCN 140180</td><td>Collej&#x000f3;n (Spanish), espinac de frare</td><td/><td>x</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Oenothera biennis</italic> L. (Onagraceae) BCN 81537</td><td>Onagra (Spanish)</td><td>x</td><td>x</td><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Oxalis pes-caprae</italic> L. (Oxalidaceae) BCN 95553</td><td>Caramelets, vinagrera</td><td/><td>x</td><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Peucedanum officinale</italic> L. subsp. <italic>stenocarpum</italic> (Boiss. et Reut.) F.Q. (Apiaceae) BCN 99150</td><td>Cua de porc, fonoll de porc</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Phlomis lychnitis</italic> L. (Lamiaceae) BCN 156590</td><td>Candelera</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Plantago albicans</italic> L. (Plantaginaceae) BCN 125521</td><td>Herbafam</td><td>x</td><td>x</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Pyrus spinosa</italic> Forsk. (Rosaceae) BCN 103045</td><td>Saramenya (fruit), saramenyera</td><td/><td>x</td><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Reseda luteola</italic> L. (Resedaceae) BCN 100866</td><td>Gualda (Spanish), reseda (Spanish)</td><td/><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Rhamnus lycioides</italic> L. (Rhamnaceae) BCN 150374</td><td>Corniol</td><td>x</td><td>x</td><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Salix viminalis</italic> L. (Salicaceae) BCN 65531</td><td>Vimen, vimenera</td><td>x</td><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Salsola kali</italic> L. (Amaranthaceae) BCN 150378</td><td>Espantallops, parnella borda, trotamon</td><td>x</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Salsola soda</italic> L. (Amaranthaceae) BCN 42984</td><td>Parnella</td><td>x</td><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Salsola vermiculata</italic> L. (Amaranthaceae) BCN 125398</td><td>Salada, siscall</td><td/><td>x</td><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scorzonera laciniata</italic> L. (Asteraceae) BCN 125490</td><td>Barballa</td><td/><td>x</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Sideritis scordioides</italic> L. (Lamiaceae) BCN 125397</td><td>Esparbonella, herba de Sant Antoni, planta de la pulmonia</td><td>x</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Sideritis spinulosa</italic> Barnades ex Asso (Lamiaceae) BCN 140155</td><td>Herba de la llanceta, herba de la pulmonia, herba del miracle</td><td>x</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Stipa offneri</italic> Breistr. (Poaceae) BCN 140524</td><td>Llambra</td><td/><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Stipa parviflora</italic> Desf. (Poaceae) BCN 125386</td><td>Bitxella, bitzell, pelaguer</td><td/><td/><td>x</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tanacetum corymbosum</italic> (L.) Schultz Bip. subsp. <italic>corymbosum</italic> (Asteraceae) BCN 125389</td><td>Herba de Santa Maria</td><td/><td>x</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Teucrium polium</italic> L. subsp. <italic>capitatum</italic> (L.) Arcang. (Lamiaceae) BCN 140518</td><td>Tim&#x000f3; mascle</td><td>x</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Viscum album</italic> L. subsp. <italic>austriacum</italic> (Wiesb.) Vollmann (Santalaceae) BCN 125518</td><td>Vesc, vesquera, visquerc&#x000ed;, xoca</td><td>x</td><td>x</td><td>x</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>General quantitative ethnobotany</title><p id="Par29">With a view to assessing the state of ethnobotanical general knowledge in the studied area, we calculated the informant consensus factor (F<sub>IC</sub>) obtained for our interviewees (0.93), although we have also calculated the F<sub>IC</sub> for medicinal information (0.89) in order to be able to compare it with other territories. It occupies a position in the upper part of the range of the values obtained for other Catalan language studied areas (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Quantitative ethnobotany indexes in other territories in Catalonia</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Territory</th><th>F<sub>IC</sub></th><th>EI</th><th>MP/informant</th><th>MP/inhabitant</th><th>MP/km<sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Alt Empord&#x000e0; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]</td><td>0.91</td><td>25.90</td><td>1.88</td><td>0.28 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></td><td>0.25</td></tr><tr><td>Cerdanya [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]</td><td>0.93</td><td>_</td><td>1.11</td><td>0.82 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></td><td>0.23</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Garrigues</italic> (this paper)</td><td><italic>0.89</italic></td><td><italic>23.47</italic></td><td><italic>1.94</italic></td><td><italic>0.88 &#x000d7; 10</italic><sup><italic>&#x02212;2</italic></sup></td><td><italic>0.17</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Giron&#x000e8;s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]</td><td>0.86</td><td>22.56</td><td>2.40</td><td>1.29 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></td><td>0.73</td></tr><tr><td>Montseny [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]</td><td>0.91</td><td>23.20</td><td>1.95</td><td>0.44 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></td><td>0.42</td></tr><tr><td>Pallars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]</td><td>0.87</td><td>29.19</td><td>1.66</td><td>2.32 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></td><td>0.16</td></tr><tr><td>Ripoll&#x000e8;s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]</td><td>0.96</td><td>28.60</td><td>1.73</td><td>1.10 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></td><td>0.29</td></tr><tr><td>Segarra [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>3.17</td><td>0.54 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup></td><td>0.13</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>F<sub>IC</sub> informant consensus factor for medicinal information, EI ethnobotanicity index, MP number of medicinal plants</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par30">The ethnobotanicity index (EI), calculated not taking into account the 41 taxa of allochthonous plants recorded (those not present in Bol&#x000f2;s et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]), is 23.47% for the studied area; this roughly means that between one fifth and one quarter of the plants of the area have been claimed as useful by the informants. The Garrigues EI is very close to Montseny and Giron&#x000e8;s values, and slightly lower than in other Catalan language studied areas (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Medicinal uses</title><p id="Par31">The total number of taxa employed for medicinal purpose was 196. Of the 1741 UR, 94.26% have been destined to human medicine, 4.02% to veterinary and 1.72% to both human and veterinary medicines (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Supplementary material</xref>).</p><p id="Par32">The number of medicinal plants used per informant is 1.94, value comprised between those found in Alt Empord&#x000e0; and Montseny (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). A much higher value was obtained for the Segarra district, an area close to the Garrigues. However, this difference must be interpreted with caution, because it may be a bias partially due to the number of the informants interviewed (29 compared to 101). Medicinal plants per habitant are 0.88 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, a value similar to those recorded in Cerdanya or Ripoll&#x000e8;s (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Finally, medicinal plants per area are 0.17, a value near the one of Pallars, and lower than in other studied areas, like Montseny or Alt Empord&#x000e0; (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par33"><italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. is the most cited taxon, followed by <italic>Olea europaea</italic> L. subsp. <italic>europaea</italic> var. <italic>europaea</italic>, and <italic>Matricaria recutita</italic> L. and <italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> L. subsp. <italic>angustifolia</italic> (Pers.) Cout. The top twenty taxa and their main medicinal uses with three or more UR (according to the reliability criterion of Le Grand &#x00026; Wondergem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>] and Johns et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]) are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. Some of these taxa, either wild plants like <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> and <italic>Sambucus nigra</italic> L. or cultivated ones such as <italic>Matricaria recutita</italic> or <italic>Allium sativum</italic> L., are among the most cited in other Catalan territories [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The top twenty taxa and their main medicinal uses with three or more UR</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Taxon, family and herbarium voucher</th><th>Used part</th><th>Uses with UR &#x02265; 3</th><th>Pharmaceutical form</th><th>Total UR</th><th>Total UR (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. (Lamiaceae) BCN 96764</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Anticatarrhal<sup>1,2,5</sup>; buccal anti-inflammatory; buccal antiseptic<sup>3,5</sup>; expectorant<sup>1,2,3,5</sup>; external antiseptic<sup>3,5</sup>; intestinal anti-inflammatory<sup>2,5</sup>; ocular antiseptic<sup>5</sup>. Pharyngeal anti-inflammatory<sup>5</sup>; salutiferous<sup>3,5</sup>; stomachic<sup>2,3,5</sup>; vulnerary<sup>3,5</sup></td><td>Aerosol, bath, collutorium, gargarism, tisane</td><td>155</td><td>8.90</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Olea europaea</italic> L. subsp. <italic>europaea</italic> var. <italic>europaea</italic> (Oleaceae) BCN 125505</td><td>Fruit, leaf</td><td>Analgesic, antihelminthic, antihypertensive<sup>3,5</sup>, antipyrotic, for earache, laxative<sup>3</sup></td><td>Direct use, embrocation, liniment, tisane</td><td>89</td><td>5.11</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Matricaria recutita</italic> L. (Asteraceae) BCN 140183</td><td>Inflorescence</td><td>Antibacterial<sup>3,5</sup>; antidismenorrhoeal<sup>5</sup>; digestive<sup>2,3,4,5</sup>; intestinal anti-inflammatory<sup>1,2,3,4,5</sup>; ocular antiseptic<sup>5</sup></td><td>Bath, tisane</td><td>81</td><td>4.65</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> L. subsp. <italic>angustifolia</italic> (Pers.) Cout. (Rutaceae) BCN 140153</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Abortive<sup>3,5,+</sup>; antiasthmatic<sup>5</sup>; antineoplastic<sup>5</sup>; postpartum coadjuvant*; for sprains<sup>5</sup>; repellent</td><td>Direct use, tisane, unknown</td><td>81</td><td>4.65</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Santolina chamaecyparissus</italic> L. subsp. <italic>squarrosa</italic> (DC.) Nyman (Asteraceae) BCN 96763</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Antalgic/antiecchymotic/anti-inflammatory<sup>3,5</sup>; anti-edematous; anti-inflammatory<sup>3,5</sup>; anti-ulcerate<sup>3</sup>; buccal antiseptic<sup>+</sup>; cicatrizing; for sprains; vulnerary<sup>+</sup></td><td>Bath, collutorium</td><td>69</td><td>3.96</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Jasonia saxatilis</italic> (Lam.) Guss. (Asteraceae) BCN 125409</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Anticatarrhal<sup>3</sup>; antihypertensive<sup>3</sup>; renal lithotriptic</td><td>Tisane</td><td>47</td><td>2.70</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Lippia triphylla</italic> (L&#x02019;H&#x000e9;r.) O. Kuntze (Verbenaceae) BCN 125394</td><td>Leaf</td><td>Antidismenorreic; intestinal anti-inflammatory<sup>3</sup>; digestive<sup>3,5</sup>; tranquilizer<sup>3,5</sup></td><td>Tisane</td><td>37</td><td>2.13</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Malva sylvestris</italic> L. (Malvaceae) BCN 125508</td><td>Aerial part, flower, leaf</td><td>Anticatarrhal<sup>1,2</sup>; antineoplastic; antitussive<sup>1,2</sup>; intestinal anti-inflammatory<sup>1</sup>; laxative; resolutive</td><td>Poultice, tisane, unknown</td><td>37</td><td>2.13</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. (Vitaceae) BCN 150353</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Anti-inflammatory/muscular pain; pharyngeal anti-inflammatory; for sprains</td><td>Bath, direct use, poultice</td><td>36</td><td>2.07</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L. (Lamiaceae) BCN 156603</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Anticatarrhal<sup>5</sup>; antihypertensive</td><td>Tisane</td><td>33</td><td>1.90</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Allium sativum</italic> L. (Amaryllidaceae) BCN 29832</td><td>Bulb</td><td>Against bee bites<sup>5</sup>; analgesic<sup>5</sup>; antibacterian<sup>3,5</sup>; antihelminthic<sup>3,5</sup>; for earache<sup>5</sup>; for warts<sup>5</sup>; salutiferous<sup>3,5</sup></td><td>Direct use, poultice</td><td>32</td><td>1.84</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Sambucus nigra</italic> L. (Adoxaceae) BCN 96771</td><td>Inflorescence</td><td>Anticatarrhal<sup>1,2,5</sup>; ocular antiseptic</td><td>Bath, tisane</td><td>30</td><td>1.72</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Juglans regia</italic> L. (Juglandaceae) BCN 150364</td><td>Leaf</td><td>Cicatrizing<sup>3</sup>; resolutive</td><td>Bath</td><td>28</td><td>1.61</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Dictamnus hispanicus</italic> Webb ex Willk. (Rutaceae) BCN 125519</td><td>Aerial part, leaf</td><td>Abortive; antihypertensive</td><td>Tisane</td><td>27</td><td>1.55</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Eryngium campestre</italic> L. (Apiaceae) BCN 125407</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Antiophidian; for rash</td><td>Direct use</td><td>27</td><td>1.55</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Equisetum ramosissimum</italic> Desf. (Equisetaceae) BCN 29982</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Antihypertensive; diuretic</td><td>Tisane</td><td>26</td><td>1.49</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Euphorbia</italic> sp. (Euphorbiaceae)</td><td>Latex</td><td>For warts</td><td>Direct use</td><td>25</td><td>1.44</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Salvia officinalis</italic> L. subsp. <italic>lavandulifolia</italic> (Vahl) Gams (Lamiaceae) BCN 96762</td><td>Leaf</td><td>Antihypertensive<sup>5</sup>; hematocathartic</td><td>Tisane</td><td>25</td><td>1.44</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Hypericum perforatum</italic> L. (Clusiaceae) BCN 96760</td><td>Flower</td><td>Antalgic/antiecchymotic/anti-inflammatory<sup>4,5</sup>; for skin disorders</td><td>Liniment</td><td>24</td><td>1.38</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Satureja fruticosa</italic> (L.) Briq. subsp. <italic>fruticosa</italic> (Lamiaceae) BCN 125387</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Digestive<sup>3,5</sup>; intestinal anti-inflammatory<sup>3,5</sup></td><td>Tisane</td><td>24</td><td>1.38</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The number of UR is the total number, not only the UR according to uses with three or more use reports. Uses with no sign are addressed only to humans, those marked with an asterisk (*) only to animals, and those with a plus sign (+) are common to both. Validation uses: <sup>1</sup>EMA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>], <sup>2</sup>ESCOP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>], <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://3fitoterapia.net"><sup>3</sup>Fitoterapia.net</ext-link> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>], <sup>4</sup>Blumenthal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>], and <sup>5</sup>Duke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par34">Conversely, other species like <italic>Jasonia saxatilis</italic> (Lam.) Guss., <italic>Santolina chamaecyparissus</italic> L. subsp. <italic>squarrosa</italic> (DC.) Nyman or <italic>Dictamnus hispanicus</italic> Webb ex Willk., commonly growing and frequently reported in the present studied area, are not the most common in top positions in other territories, where they are less abundant or not present. This fact reflects the well-confirmed idea that the closer to civilization a plant grows, the more it is used by local people [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>].</p><p id="Par35">The medicinal taxa recorded belong to 68 families. In this category, Lamiaceae is the most reported with 18.78%, followed by Asteraceae (17.06%) and, far from them, Rutaceae (6.49%). These results are close to those recorded in other ethnofloristic works conducted in Mediterranean areas, where predominating families Asteraceae, Lamiaceae and Rosaceae occupy first places [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. The relevant presence of Rutaceae has its explanation in the specific use of their main species reported, <italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> subsp. <italic>angustifolia</italic> for abortive use (in both animals and humans) and postpartum coadjuvant (in animals) and <italic>Dictamnus hispanicus</italic> for antihypertensive use.</p><p id="Par36">Plant parts most commonly used for remedies preparation are the aerial part with 45.78% including young, sterile, flowering, and fructified aerial parts; these organs are followed by leaves (17%). These results agree with those in other Catalan language areas such as Segarra [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] and Pallars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], the first one closer and not very different in the climate to the Garrigues and the second one farther and with mountain (including high mountain) conditions.</p><p id="Par37">The most treated troubles, representing 58.53% of the total, are addressed to digestive system and nutritional disorders, skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders, circulatory system and blood disorders and respiratory system disorders (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). If we analyse the reports for specific medicinal use, antihypertensive (8.10%), anticatharral (7.01%), intestinal anti-inflammatory (4.77%), antialgic/anti-ecchymotic/anti-inflammatory (3.79%) and ocular antiseptic (3.73%) are the most reported.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Systems and disorders addressed with medicinal plants in the area studied. Abbreviations: DN, digestive system and nutritional disorders; SS, skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders; CB, circulatory system and blood disorders; R, respiratory system disorders; MT, musculoskeletal system disorders and traumas; G, genitourinary system disorders; S, sensory system disorders; II, infections and infestations; PBP, pregnancy, birth, and puerperal disorders; PI, pain and inflammations; UNK, unknown; TR, tonic and restorative; NM, nervous system and mental disorders; P, poisoning; EM, endocrine system and metabolic disorders; IN, immune system disorders and neoplasia</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2020_386_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par38">Thirty plant taxa have been reported as antihypertensive in the Garrigues district, occupying the first position among the most cited plants for specific disorders. The plants used to lower blood pressure are commonly quoted in other ethnobotanical studies in Catalonia, but in no one case they occupy the first position [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par39">The index of medicinal importance is useful to evaluate the real importance of the use, as a specific use can be cited for a few or many species and this may change the relevance of the information. This index was calculated for 20 of 134 medicinal use categories (those most reported), and the results for the uses that have a ratio higher than 4 are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The seven medicinal specific categories with an index of medicinal importance (MI) higher than 4</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2020_386_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par40">Regarding the pharmaceutical form, tisane, including decoction and infusion, represents 39.06% of the total forms reported, followed by bath (16.03%) and direct use (internal or external) (14.65%). Among the thirty pharmaceutical forms employed, the simplest ones predominate over others; other more complex ones, such as poultice or essence, are also used but in low frequency.</p><sec id="Sec11"><title>Pharmacological validation</title><p id="Par41">To confirm the top twenty taxa (excepting <italic>Euphorbia</italic>, only determined at the genus level) and their main medicinal uses with three or more use reports, we reviewed the literature (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Seventy-seven uses of these 19 taxa are coincidental with those recorded in the literature set consulted. For an important percentage, 59.74%, of the ethnobotanical uses, we validated the information with at least one of the sources checked. By far, Duke&#x02019;s CRC handbook of medicinal herbs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>] with 48.05% of validated uses and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fitoterapia.net">Fitoterapia.net</ext-link> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>] with 33.77% were the most inclusive, systematic and detailed works analysed. The traditional uses confirmed in this literature, which is often used in drug register processes, may be considered as the most consolidated, with a view to introducing new products onto the market. Whereas the roughly 40% of the ethnobotanical uses (all of them reliable in terms of the number of three or more use reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]) not found in the literature set should be the object of further phytochemical and/or pharmacological investigation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Food uses</title><p id="Par42">In the studied region, 168 taxa consumed as food were detected, 52.98% of them being cultivated and the remaining 47.02% wild. Of the 1705 use reports, 91.79% have been consumed by humans, 8.03% by animals and 0.18% by both humans and animals (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Supplementary material</xref>). The number of food plants cited per informant is 1.66.</p><p id="Par43">The five most cited species are <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic>, <italic>Papaver rhoeas</italic> L., <italic>Rubus ulmifolius</italic> Schott, <italic>Olea europaea</italic> subsp. <italic>europaea</italic> var. <italic>europaea</italic> and <italic>Prunus dulcis</italic> (Mill.) Weeb. The first three plants are wild and typical in the studied area: The aerial part of <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> is used as a condiment, the young leaves of <italic>Papaver rhoeas</italic> consumed as salad and the fruit of <italic>Rubus ulmifolius</italic> is either eaten fresh or cooked with sugar, to make jam, the three uses being quite common. <italic>Olea europaea</italic> subsp. <italic>europaea</italic> var. <italic>europaea</italic> and <italic>Prunus dulcis</italic> are the main crops in the studied area, where they are largely cultivated (ca. 19,276 and 645&#x02009;ha, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]), and this explains their high number of use reports. The fundamental role of oil in the Mediterranean cuisine together with the numerous recipes for the preparation and preservation of olives explain the high number of citations of the olive tree. The high number of UR of the almond tree could be interpreted in the same sense. This species, widely distributed in the Mediterranean area, has been cited for the consumption of its ripe seeds, raw or toasted, but also for the complete unripe fruit, named green almonds, which are usually eaten either directly or pickled. The top-ranked twenty species and their principal mode of consumption are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>.
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The top twenty taxa and their main food uses with three or more UR</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Taxon, family and herbarium voucher</th><th>Used part</th><th>Uses with UR &#x02265; 3</th><th>Total UR</th><th>Total UR (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. (Lamiaceae) BCN 96764</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Boiled in water, condiment</td><td>74</td><td>4.34</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Papaver rhoeas</italic> L. (Papaveraceae) BCN 125507</td><td>Aerial part, leaf</td><td>Raw</td><td>69</td><td>4.05</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Rubus ulmifolius</italic> Schott (Rosaceae) BCN 156557</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Cooked with sugar, high-grade alcoholic beverage, raw</td><td>69</td><td>4.05</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Olea europaea</italic> L. subsp. <italic>europaea</italic> var. <italic>europaea</italic> (Oleaceae) BCN 125505</td><td>Fruit, leaf</td><td>Air-dried*, macerated in water, preserved in oil, preserved in vinegar</td><td>65</td><td>3.81</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Prunus dulcis</italic> (Mill.) Weeb. (Rosaceae) BCN 125495</td><td>Fruit, seed</td><td>Air-dried, cooked with oil, cooked with sugar, milk-based beverage, preserved in vinegar, raw, toasted, water-based beverage</td><td>65</td><td>3.81</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Satureja montana</italic> L. (Lamiaceae) BCN 125403</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Condiment</td><td>56</td><td>3.28</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Sonchus oleraceus</italic> L. (Asteraceae) BCN 125509</td><td>Leaf</td><td>Raw</td><td>52</td><td>3.05</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Arbutus unedo</italic> L. (Ericaceae) BCN 96768</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Cooked with sugar, raw</td><td>50</td><td>2.93</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus carica</italic> L. (Moraceae) BCN 150361</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Air-dried, high-grade alcoholic beverage, raw</td><td>49</td><td>2.87</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Celtis australis</italic> L. (Cannabaceae) BCN 125477</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Raw</td><td>48</td><td>2.82</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L. (Lamiaceae) BCN 156603</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Condiment</td><td>45</td><td>2.64</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cydonia oblonga</italic> Mill. (Rosaceae) BCN 150356</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Cooked with sugar</td><td>38</td><td>2.23</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Sorbus domestica</italic> L. (Rosaceae) BCN 150384</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Air-dried, raw</td><td>37</td><td>2.17</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Foeniculum vulgare</italic> Mill. subsp. <italic>piperitum</italic> (Ucria) Cout. (Apiaceae) BCN 125404</td><td>Aerial part, fruit</td><td>Boiled in water, condiment, raw</td><td>34</td><td>1.99</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Malva sylvestris</italic> L. (Malvaceae) BCN 125508</td><td>Flower, fruit</td><td>Raw</td><td>34</td><td>1.99</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> L. subsp. <italic>maritima</italic> (L.) Arcang. (Amaranthaceae) BCN 156567</td><td>Leaf</td><td>Boiled in water, raw</td><td>33</td><td>1.94</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Silybum marianum</italic> (L.) Gaertn. (Asteraceae) BCN 125516</td><td>Inflorescence</td><td>Raw</td><td>33</td><td>1.94</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Silene vulgaris</italic> (Moench) Garcke (Caryophyllaceae) BCN 96770</td><td>Leaf</td><td>Boiled in water, cooked with oil, raw</td><td>31</td><td>1.82</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> L. (Solanaceae) BCN 29952</td><td>Fruit</td><td>Cooked with sugar, preserved</td><td>31</td><td>1.82</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Laurus nobilis</italic> L. (Lauraceae) BCN 150355</td><td>Leaf</td><td>Condiment</td><td>30</td><td>1.76</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The number of UR is the total number, not only the UR according to uses with three or more use reports. Uses with no sign are for humans and those marked with an asterisk (*) are for animals</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par44">The most consumed parts of these plants are the fruits or infructescences, with 47.98% of the total, and, significantly lower, aerial parts (22.35%) and leaves (18.83%). The explanation is the extensive use of olives and almonds, but also of wild or marginal fruits such as <italic>Rubus ulmifolius</italic>, <italic>Celtis australis</italic> L., <italic>Pyrus spinosa</italic> Forsk., <italic>Sorbus domestica</italic> L., <italic>Crataegus azarolus</italic> L. and <italic>C. monogyna</italic> Jacq. Fruits are popular for consumption around the world. To quote similar climatic areas to the one considered, in arid zones of India, the relevance is remarked of local fruits in people&#x02019;s nutrition, confirmed by composition analyses, even though they are somewhat undervalued and underutilised when compared with commercial exotic fruits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>].</p><p id="Par45">The most common mode of consumption is fresh (43.11%) and as a condiment (16.07%). Fresh consumption includes raw salads like <italic>Eruca vesicaria</italic> (L.) Cav. subsp. <italic>sativa&#x000a0;(Mill.) Thell. in Hegi</italic>, <italic>Papaver rhoeas</italic>, <italic>Sonchus oleraceus</italic> L., <italic>Samolus valerandi</italic> L., the above-mentioned edible fruits or more uncommon products like the fresh inflorescence of <italic>Silybum marianum</italic> (L.) Gaertn. This last mentioned plant is not so frequently eaten, but its preparation and consumption are comparable to that of another plant of the same family, <italic>Carlina acanthifolia</italic> All., very popular in mountain regions<italic>.</italic> Condiments are mostly used to flavour different types of cooked meat and snails, among others, and, as we have mentioned previously, to preserve, and also to flavour, the olives.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Medicinal and food mixtures</title><p id="Par46">This study has inventoried, apart from individual plant uses, 260 plant mixtures, of which 98 (37.69%) are medicinal and 162 (62.31%) food (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Supplementary material</xref>).</p><p id="Par47">Sixty-one taxa are employed in medicinal mixtures, and the mean of species reported for mixture is 2.67. The most reported species are <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic>, present in 10.69% of mixtures; <italic>Olea europaea</italic> subsp. <italic>europaea</italic> var. <italic>europaea</italic> (6.87%); and <italic>Pinus halepensis</italic> Mill. (5.34%).</p><p id="Par48">The index of taxon usefulness in mixtures was calculated taking into account all the taxa with three or more use reports in mixtures, thereby using the same criteria as in the simple presentation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. The results in medicinal mixtures show there are two taxa reported only in mixtures, <italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic> (Mill.) Hill and <italic>Apium graveolens</italic> L., with the maximum ITUM value of one, and another one, <italic>Citrus limon</italic> (L.) Burm., with a high value (0.92).</p><p id="Par49">These medicinal mixtures are used to treat, principally, respiratory disorders (29.59%), circulatory system and blood disorders (17.35%) and immune system disorders (11.22%). The most common pharmaceutical form does not change in respect to individual plants, tisane being reported in half of the mixtures, followed by poultice (14.29%). The informant consensus factor (F<sub>IC</sub>) for medicinal mixtures data is 0.77, a value between Giron&#x000e8;s district (0.56) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and the study carried out in two Catalan territories (Alt Empord&#x000e0; and Ripoll&#x000e8;s) (0.85) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>].</p><p id="Par50">In food mixtures, 78 taxa are reported. The mean number of species reported for food mixtures is 3.59, and the most cited species are <italic>Allium sativum</italic> (5.16%), <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> (4.65%), <italic>Juglans regia</italic> L. and <italic>Satureja montana</italic> L. (4.48%, for both).</p><p id="Par51">The number of taxa only reported in food mixtures is higher than the number of taxa in the medicinal ones. The analysis carried out shows seven taxa with a maximum value (ITUM = 1), indicating their use only in mixtures. Most of them are spices like <italic>Cinnamomum verum</italic> J.Presl, <italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L., <italic>Illicium verum</italic> Hook.f., <italic>Myristica fragrans</italic> Houtt., <italic>Piper nigrum</italic> L. or <italic>Syzygium aromaticum</italic> (L.) Merr. et Perry, but also <italic>Hyssopus officinalis</italic> L. These high ITUM values could be explained by the fact that all of these taxa are used as a seasoning and they are rarely used alone.</p><p id="Par52">Condiment is the main use reported (45.06%), followed by high-grade alcoholic beverage (12.35%). Analysing in more details the condiment use, we have counted 43 recipes regarding seasoning olives, and this means 26.54% of the total of the mixtures. The relevant percentage of high-grade alcoholic beverage uses is mostly due to the importance of the traditional liqueur called <italic>ratafia</italic>. Finally, the informant consensus factor (F<sub>IC</sub>) for food mixtures is 0.87. Even if this value is not comparable with other studies, because to date, scarce attention has been paid to food mixtures in comparison with medicinal ones it suggests, its maximum value being 1, a solid information fact of popular knowledge on plant combinations with food use.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Other uses</title><p id="Par53">This category includes non-medicinal and non-food uses. Nowadays, these uses are the most vulnerable. On the one hand, the application of this melting pot with numerous use subcategories seems not as necessary as in the past, and the traditional work has been mechanised, or many objects for home use are currently acquired in supermarkets. On the other hand, unlike plants with medicinal and food uses, traditional knowledge of plants with other uses has not been much investigated. Serving as good examples, pharmaceutical companies are interested in the chemical compounds of some of the plants traditionally used as medicine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>], and leading chefs are looking for new ingredients to incorporate new flavours and textures in their dishes and wild food plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]; conversely, domestic uses and handicraft products are minimal at a general level in business terms.</p><p id="Par54">Nevertheless, although most of them have almost disappeared and others remain in a residual condition, specific research to analyse this kind of uses is still important. Not least, they are highly considered by their practitioners and have a cultural relevance and may even imply some economic revenues to local people [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>] or generate new market opportunities in a world where people are increasingly concerned about the environment and try to reduce plastics and other waste.</p><p id="Par55">In our study, we have collected 1269 UR concerning 184 taxa (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Supplementary material</xref>). The number of plants cited for other uses (as stated, all but medicinal and food) per informant is 1.82. Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> shows the top twenty species in this field and their principal uses (with three or more use reports). The five most reported species are <italic>Arundo donax</italic> L., mostly indicated for their use in home gardens and, in general, in agricultural management; <italic>Olea europaea</italic> subsp. <italic>europaea</italic> var. <italic>europaea</italic>, to elaborate handmade soap from the used oil or to bring a piece of aerial part of the olive tree to bless during Palm Sunday; <italic>Celtis australis</italic> for the elaboration of forks; <italic>Dorycnium pentaphyllum</italic> Scop. for broom elaboration; and <italic>Helichrysum stoechas</italic> (L.) Moench for decorative use.
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>The top twenty taxa and their main other uses with three or more UR</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Taxon, family and herbarium voucher</th><th>Used part</th><th>Uses with UR &#x02265; 3</th><th>Total UR</th><th>Total UR (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>Arundo donax</italic> L. (Poaceae) BCN 156562</td><td>Inflorescence, stem, whole plant</td><td>Agrosilvopastoral management, basketry, domestic, ludic, unclassified</td><td>79</td><td>6.23</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Olea europaea</italic> L. subsp. <italic>europaea</italic> var. <italic>europaea</italic> (Oleaceae) BCN 125505</td><td>Aerial part, ash, fruit, stem</td><td>Cane elaboration, domestic, fuel obtention, magic and religious beliefs and practices</td><td>75</td><td>5.91</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Celtis australis</italic> L. (Cannabaceae) BCN 125477</td><td>Seed, stem</td><td>Agrosilvopastoral management, cane elaboration, ludic</td><td>72</td><td>5.67</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Dorycnium pentaphyllum</italic> Scop. (Fabaceae) BCN 125504</td><td>Aerial part, flower</td><td>Broom elaboration, honey obtention</td><td>52</td><td>4.10</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Helichrysum stoechas</italic> (L.) Moench (Asteraceae) BCN 96758</td><td>Aerial part, inflorescence</td><td>Air freshener, bouquet elaboration, broom elaboration, honey obtention, magic and religious beliefs and practices</td><td>49</td><td>3.86</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Genista scorpius</italic> (L.) DC. in Lam. et DC. (Fabaceae) BCN 156592</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Domestic, for pig slaughter, fuel obtention, unclassified</td><td>47</td><td>3.70</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Mantisalca salmantica</italic> (L.) Briq. et Cavill. (Asteraceae) BCN 125420</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Broom elaboration</td><td>34</td><td>2.68</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Typha latifolia</italic> L. (Typhaceae) BCN 31314</td><td>Aerial part, leaf</td><td>Agrosilvopastoral management, bouquet elaboration, unclassified</td><td>33</td><td>2.60</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Viscum album</italic> L. subsp. <italic>austriacum</italic> (Wiesb.) Vollm. (Santalaceae) BCN 125518</td><td>Aerial part, stem</td><td>For hunting, magic and religious beliefs and practices, recollection for selling</td><td>32</td><td>2.52</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Prunus dulcis</italic> (Mill.) Weeb. (Rosaceae) BCN 125495</td><td>Ash, flower, stem</td><td>Domestic, fuel obtaining, honey obtention</td><td>31</td><td>2.44</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Lygeum spartum</italic> L. (Poaceae) BCN 125497</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Agrosilvopastoral management, rope elaboration, shoe elaboration</td><td>28</td><td>2.21</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Lavandula latifolia</italic> Medic. (Lamiaceae) BCN 96766</td><td>Aerial part, whole plant</td><td>Air freshener, bouquet elaboration, cosmetic, for gardening</td><td>24</td><td>1.89</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Pinus halepensis</italic> Mill. (Pinaceae) BCN 150381</td><td>Ash, stem, whole plant</td><td>Domestic, folk oral literature, fuel obtention</td><td>24</td><td>1.89</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L. (Lamiaceae) BCN 156603</td><td>Aerial part, flower</td><td>Cosmetic, smoking, honey obtention</td><td>24</td><td>1.89</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Sorbus domestica</italic> L. (Rosaceae) BCN 150384</td><td>Fruit, stem, whole plant</td><td>Folk oral literature, unclassified</td><td>23</td><td>1.81</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Urtica urens</italic> L. (Urticaceae) BCN 150351</td><td>Aerial part</td><td>Agrosilvopastoral management</td><td>22</td><td>1.73</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Linum tenuifolium</italic> L. subsp. <italic>suffruticosum</italic> (L.) Litard. (Linaceae) BCN 125496</td><td>Whole plant</td><td>Folk oral literature</td><td>20</td><td>1.58</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Quercus coccifera</italic> L. (Fagaceae) BCN 150369</td><td>Aerial part, stem</td><td>Domestic, cane elaboration, fuel obtention</td><td>20</td><td>1.58</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic> L. (Anacardiaceae) BCN 125514</td><td>Aerial part, fruit</td><td>For hunting, repellent</td><td>18</td><td>1.42</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Aphyllanthes monspeliensis</italic> L. (Asparagaceae) BCN 125510</td><td>Root, whole plant</td><td>Domestic, recollection for selling, unclassified</td><td>16</td><td>1.26</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The number of UR is the total number, not only the UR according to uses with three or more use reports</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par56">The aerial part and stems represent almost a third part of all reports. The first one, the most cited, is represented by 50.83%, and the second one, almost by a quarter (21.99%).</p><p id="Par57">If we split data into subcategories, agrosilvopastoral management (11.74%), domestic (8.67%), magic or religious beliefs and practices (8.35%) and broom elaboration (8.20%) are the most reported. The first three categories are general and group a variety of uses, which explains the first positions. Broom elaboration is a very specific use, quoted by almost all our informants and a wide diversity of taxa. Up to 11 species are reported for this use. <italic>Dorycnium pentaphyllum</italic> and <italic>Mantisalca salmantica</italic> (L.) Briq. et Cavill. are the most valued, specifically used to sweep the threshing floor after selecting cereal or legume grains, and the street near home (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Other species reported are <italic>Arundo donax</italic>, <italic>Chamaerops humilis</italic> L., <italic>Erica multiflora</italic> L., <italic>Kochia scoparia</italic> (L.) Schrad., <italic>Lygeum spartum</italic>, <italic>Phoenix dactylifera</italic> L., <italic>Retama sphaerocarpa</italic>, <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L. and <italic>Spartium junceum</italic> L. Some of these brooms continue, to some extent, to be used nowadays and renewed when necessary. Furthermore, even if, as already stated, these uses are, in general, declining, some utilisations, such as ritual (for instance in Christmas or Palm Sunday), folk oral literature (e.g. proverbs) or handicraft basketry, persist in the studied territory, as they do in other Catalan language territories [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>] and in other Mediterranean areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>].
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>A moment of broom elaboration process with <italic>Dorycnium pentaphyllum</italic> Scop. and some freshly produced brooms of this species and <italic>Mantisalca salmantica</italic> (L.) Briq. et Cavill.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2020_386_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Vernacular names</title><p id="Par58">In the present study, 849 vernacular names with 116 phonetic variants have been collected for 410 taxa. Fifty-four of these taxa do not have medicinal, food or other uses associated, 36 of them with other observations and 18 only with a popular name. Ten taxa have been mentioned by the informant without any popular name; in these few cases, the informant did not know or could not remember the name of a plant. Out of the 849 names, 79 are in the Spanish language, two in French and one in English, all the rest being in Catalan. The most cited taxon in terms of folk name (apart from cultivated plants with races, see later) is <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic>, which has been reported 90 times with the popular name <italic>tim&#x000f3;</italic> and 17 as <italic>farigola</italic>, the second name (belonging to the so-called eastern Catalan dialect) not typical in the area (speaking western Catalan dialect), but known by many informants as used in other Catalan language variants. The same happens with <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic>&#x02019; names, with &#x02018;romer&#x02019; (75 UR) as the typical in the district and &#x02018;roman&#x000ed;&#x02019; (5 UR) also known from other dialects.</p><p id="Par59">The ethnophytonymy index for vernacular names shows a value close to the classical ethnobotany index 21.80%; this indicating that most of the plants have at least one vernacular name in the Catalan language.</p><p id="Par60">The allochthonous ethnophytonymy index is 18.05%, between Giron&#x000e8;s (4.7%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and Mallorca (27.8%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>] values. The reason for this quite high value in a rural district is the origin of one of the interviewees, who is from Germany but has lived in the Garrigues district for a long time, although she only speaks Spanish, not Catalan.</p><p id="Par61">The linguistic diversity index in phytonymy, calculated to value the linguistic richness of a territory independently of its flora, reaches a value of 1.98 for taxa with only Catalan language names and 2.07 for all taxa.</p><p id="Par62">Finally, we want to mention the interesting case of a certain number of plant names that have gender adjectives although they are not dioecious taxa. Some plants are named based on other taxa&#x02019;s names with the addition of &#x02018;mascle&#x02019; (male) or &#x02018;femella&#x02019; (female), irrespective of their sexual condition. As already stated, &#x02018;tim&#x000f3;&#x02019; is the typical name for <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic>; based on this, <italic>Teucrium</italic> gr. <italic>polium</italic> (belonging to the same family as <italic>Thymus</italic>) and <italic>Coris monspeliensis</italic> subsp. <italic>monspeliensis</italic> (from another family) are termed &#x02018;tim&#x000f3; mascle&#x02019;. <italic>Santolina chamaecyparissus</italic> subsp. <italic>squarrosa</italic> is named &#x02018;espernallac&#x02019; or &#x02018;espernallac femella&#x02019;, whereas <italic>Artemisia-herba-alba</italic> is known as &#x02018;espernallac mascle&#x02019;; in this case, people commenting that the former species produces flowers and the latter does not (in fact, <italic>Artemisia</italic> capitula and flowers are much smaller and less visible than those of <italic>Santolina</italic>).</p><p id="Par63">The Garrigues being an important agricultural area, it is not surprising that some cultivated plants bear a high number of names due to the races present in the area or known by the informants. This is the reason for which <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. (with 15 folk names) is the taxon with the highest number of popular names. This also happens with <italic>Olea europaea</italic> subsp. <italic>europaea</italic> var. <italic>europaea</italic> (13 names), with the added value, at a local level, that one of the villages of the district (Arbeca) gives the name to a very well-known olive race (&#x02018;arbequina&#x02019;), highly appreciated for both fruit consumption and oil elaboration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]. Finally, the same applies to <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L. (14 names). The first wild plant species in the ranking of common names is <italic>Helichrysum stoechas</italic> (11 names), followed by <italic>Crataegus monogyna</italic> and <italic>Silybum marianum</italic> (both with nine names).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par64">This first study in the Western plains has revealed the importance of prospecting the arid or semiarid areas of Catalonia. Traditional knowledge is persisting in the district, as the results confirm, in terms of high values of the number of useful (medicinal, food or with other applications) taxa, number of popular phytonyms, ethnobotanicity index and informant consensus factor. The persistence of traditional knowledge is comparable to that existing in other Catalan areas regarding medicinal, food and even other plant uses (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]), which is of interest to confirm in this first study focused on an arid land. Indeed, most ethnofloristic parameters fall within the general corpus of Catalan, Iberian and European ethnobotany, but some particularities arise. The climatic and soil characters, together with the agricultural condition of the territory, give rise to the Poaceae among the five top families recorded in the number of taxa known and used. The characteristics of the territory bring considerable relevance to plants with semiarid or arid, and steppe, affinities, which are rarely reported in other places of the above-quoted areas. This is why this paper contributes 41 novelties of taxa to the Catalan ethnoflora, irrespective of it having been quite profusely studied. With the present work, the ethnofloristic gap in the arid Catalan lands is at least partly filled. Apart from the fact that some specific prospections are still needed, this may be seen as the first step towards starting work with all available ethnobotanical data in the country in order to perform meta-analytic studies. In its turn, these studies should provide the basis for comparisons at higher levels, such as Iberian and Mediterranean.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec17"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13002_2020_386_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1.</bold> Supplementary information.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1186/s13002-020-00386-0.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank all the people who participated as informants in this work, who are, in fact, true collaborators, for sharing their time and knowledge. Samuel Pyke (Botanical Garden of Barcelona) is acknowledged for his revision of the English language. Joan Veny (Institut d&#x02019;Estudis Catalans) is thanked for his help on correctly treating plant folk names and their variants. We also thank Pere Barnola (Flora Catalana), Pep Vicens and&#x000a0;Josep Vigo (Universitat de Barcelona) and, again, Samuel Pyke for their assistance in some plant determinations. We acknowledge the support of the publication fee by the CSIC Open Access Publication Support Initiative through its Unit of Information Resources for Research (URICI).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>The subject and its reach have been designed by the three authors. AG performed the fieldwork in the studied area, with the assistance in some cases of the other two authors. AG and TG carried out the statistical analyses. AG wrote the first draft of the manuscript. Finally, the three authors jointly prepared and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was supported by projects 2017SGR001116 from the Generalitat de Catalunya (Catalan Government), PRO2017-S02VALLES and PRO2020-S02VALLES&#x000a0;from the Institut d&#x02019;Estudis Catalans (IEC, Catalan Academy of Sciences and Humanities) and CSO2014-59704-P and CGL2017-84297-R from the Spanish Government. AG received a predoctoral grant of the Universitat de Barcelona (APIF 2015-2018).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All data are available in the <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Supplementary information</xref>.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par65">All the authors agree with the manuscript and consent to participate in it. Concerning the informants, they gave the informed consent (see the &#x02018;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Material and Methods</xref>&#x02019; section).</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par66">The authors give their consent for the publication of this manuscript.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par67">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harshberger</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purposes of ethno-botany</article-title><source>Bot. Gaz.</source><year>1896</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/327316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Etnobot&#x000e0;nica: persones, plantes, cultura i benestar. Aspectes generals, i situaci&#x000f3; i perspectives als Pa&#x000ef;sos Catalans</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>Institut d&#x02019;Estudis Catalans</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Barcelona</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Muntan&#x000e9; J. Aportaci&#x000f3; al coneixement de l&#x02019;etnobot&#x000e0;nica de Cerdanya. Universitat de Barcelona. PhD thesis. 1991.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Muntan&#x000e9; J. Etnobot&#x000e0;nica, etnofarm&#x000e0;cia i tradicions populars de la Catalunya septentrional (Capcir, Cerdanya i Conflent). Universitat de Barcelona. PhD thesis. 2005.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Agelet A. Estudis d&#x02019;etnobot&#x000e0;nica farmac&#x000e8;utica al Pallars. Universitat de Barcelona. PhD thesis. 1999.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rigat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnatje</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estudis etnobot&#x000e0;nics a la comarca del Ripoll&#x000e8;s (Pirineu, Catalunya, pen&#x000ed;nsula Ib&#x000e8;rica)</article-title><source>Collect. Bot.</source><year>2017</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>e003</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3989/collectbot.2017.v36.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aldea</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnatje</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Estudi etnobot&#x000e0;nic ena Val d&#x02019;Aran. Saben&#x000e7;a populara e patrimoni naturau e culturau</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>Barcelona</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Universitat de Barcelona Edicions</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnatje</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldea</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Ambrosio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Altimiras</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Parada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Etnobot&#x000e0;nica del Pirineu catal&#x000e0;: estat actual i propostes de futur</article-title><source>Ibix</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>47</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bonet M&#x000c0;. Estudis etnobot&#x000e0;nics a la vall del Tenes (Vall&#x000e8;s Oriental). Universitat de Barcelona. Master thesis. 1991.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Selga A. Estudis etnobot&#x000e0;nics a les Guilleries. Universitat de Barcelona. Master thesis. 1998.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bonet M&#x000c0;. Estudi etnobot&#x000e0;nic del Montseny. Universitat de Barcelona. PhD thesis. 2001.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bonet M&#x000c0;, Rold&#x000e1;n M, Camprub&#x000ed; J, Vall&#x000e8;s J. Etnobot&#x000e0;nica de Gallecs. Plantes i cultura popular al Baix Vall&#x000e8;s. Mollet del Vall&#x000e8;s: Centre d&#x02019;Estudis Molletans; 2008.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Parada M. Estudi etnobot&#x000e0;nic de l&#x02019;Alt Empord&#x000e0;. Universitat de Barcelona. PhD thesis. 2007.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Usos i cultura popular de les plantes a les Gavarres</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Consorci de les Gavarres</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Monells</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Batet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cartany&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Castells</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pi&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Salat</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><source>Etnobot&#x000e0;nica a les muntanyes de Prades</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Centre d&#x02019;Hist&#x000f2;ria Natural de la Conca de Barber&#x000e0;</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Montblanc</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Talavera M. La recuperaci&#x000f3; dels coneixements tradicionals relatius a la biodiversitat com a eina de desenvolupament de nous cultius amb esp&#x000e8;cies silvestres, i acceptaci&#x000f3; per part dels consumidors dels productes elaborats amb esp&#x000e8;cies silvestres i varietats tradicionals. Estudi etnobot&#x000e0;nic de la comarca de l&#x02019;Anoia, tradicionals. Universitat de Barcelona. PhD thesis. 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Serrasolses</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnatje</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional knowledge in semi-rural close to industrial areas: ethnobotanical studies in western Giron&#x000e8;s (Catalonia, Iberian Peninsula)</article-title><source>J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed.</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-019-0295-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30940210?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30940210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bol&#x000f2;s O de, Vigo J. Flora dels Pa&#x000ef;sos Catalans, vol. 1. Ed. Barcino: Barcelona; 1984.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bol&#x000f2;s O de. Corologia de la flora dels Pa&#x000ef;sos Catalans. Volum introductori. Chorology of the flora of Catalan Countries. Introductory volume. Barcelona: Institut d&#x02019;Estudis Catalans; 1985.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Raja D. Estudis etnobot&#x000e0;nics a la comarca de la Segarra. Universitat de Barcelona. MSc thesis. 1995.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Riba O, Bol&#x000f2;s O de, Panareda JM, Nuet J, Gos&#x000e0;lbez J. Geografia f&#x000ed;sica dels Pa&#x000ef;sos Catalans. Barcelona: Ketres editora; 1976.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bol&#x000f2;s O de, Vigo J, Masalles RM, Ninot JM. Flora manual dels Pa&#x000ef;sos Catalans. 3rd ed. Ed. P&#x000f2;rtic: Barcelona; 2005.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bol&#x000f2;s O de. Algunas consideraciones sobre las especies esteparias en la Pen&#x000ed;nsula Ib&#x000e9;rica. Anales Inst. Bot. Cavanilles. 1951;10:445&#x02013;53.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Braun-Blanquet J, Bol&#x000f2;s O de. Les groupements v&#x000e9;g&#x000e9;taux du bassin moyen de l&#x02019;Ebre et leur dynamisme. Zaragoza: Estaci&#x000f3;n Experimental de Aula Dei (CSIC), 2 vols; 1958.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masclans</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><source>Flora del Segri&#x000e0; i l&#x02019;Urgell a la Plana Occidental Catalana</source><year>1966</year><publisher-loc>Institut d&#x02019;Estudis Catalans</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Barcelona</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bold&#x000fa; A. Estudio flor&#x000ed;stico y fitogeogr&#x000e1;fico de la zona comprendida entre los montes de Prades y el r&#x000ed;o Segre. Universitat de Barcelona. PhD thesis. 1975.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Recasens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribuci&#x000f3; al coneixement de la flora catalana occidental, III</article-title><source>Butll. Inst. Catalana Hist. Nat</source><year>1991</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>74</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Recasens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>El grupo corol&#x000f3;gico mediterr&#x000e1;neo est&#x000e9;pico en la mitad oriental de la Depresi&#x000f3;n del Ebro como exponente de su riqueza flor&#x000ed;stica</article-title><source>Ecolog&#x000ed;a</source><year>2001</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>100</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sol&#x000e9;-Senan XO, Ju&#x000e1;rez-Escario A, Garc&#x000ed;a C, Pedrol J, Conesa JA. Contribuci&#x000f3; del patrimoni biol&#x000f2;gic municipal al Segri&#x000e0;: flora d&#x02019;afinitat est&#x000e8;pica dels secans. Shikar: Revista del Centre d&#x02019;Estudis Comarcals del Segri&#x000e0;, 2014; 1:119-124.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickens</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><source>Plants for arid lands. Proceedings of the Kew International Conference on Economic Plants for Arid Lands held in the Jodrell Laboratory, Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, England, 23&#x02013;27 July 1984</source><year>1984</year><publisher-loc>Kew</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Royal Botanic Gardens</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>TAS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucena</surname><given-names>RFP</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alencar</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How ethnobotany can aid biodiversity conservation: reflections on investigations in the semi-arid region of NE Brazil</article-title><source>Biodivers. Conserv.</source><year>2009</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10531-008-9463-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ladio</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human ecology, ethnobotany and traditional practices in rural populations inhabiting the Monte region: resilience and ecological knowledge</article-title><source>J. Arid Environ.</source><year>2009</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaridenv.2008.02.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhattarai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Quave</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of medicinal plants in the trans-Himalayan arid zone of Mustang district, Nepal</article-title><source>J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-6-14</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20370901?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20370901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wariss</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmat</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayt</surname><given-names>MQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Anjum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukhtar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparative ethno-botanical study of Cholistan (an arid area) and Pothwar (a semi-arid area) of Pakistan for traditional medicines</article-title><source>J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed.</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>31</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-015-0018-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25925727?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25925727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Oliveira Campos LZ. de, Albuquerque UP, Peroni N, Ara&#x000fa;jo EL. Do socioeconomic characteristics explain the knowledge and use of native food plants in semiarid environments in Northeastern Brazil. J. Arid Environ. 2015; 115:53-61. DOI:10.1016/j.jaridenv.2015.01.002.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miara</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bendif</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ait Hammou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixidor-Toneu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants used by nomadic peoples in the Algerian steppe</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>219</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2018.03.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29548971?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29548971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mart&#x000ed;nez-Lirola MJ, Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Tejero MR, Molero-Mesa J. Ethnobotanical resources in the province of Almer&#x000ed;a, Spain: Campos de N&#x000ed;jar. Econ. Bot. 1996; 50(1):40-56. DOI:10.1007/BF02862112.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguado</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>La formaci&#x000f3; hist&#x000f2;rica de les Garrigues: comarca natural, circumscripci&#x000f3; administrativa i ens local</article-title><source>IV Trobada d&#x02019;estudiosos de la comarca de les Garrigues</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Les Borges Blanques</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Consell comarcal de les Garrigues</publisher-name><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>106</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Servei Meteorol&#x000f2;gic de Catalunya, Generalitat de Catalunya. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.meteo.cat">www.meteo.cat</ext-link>. Accessed 15 June 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayoral</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedrol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Recasens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>El paisatge vegetal dels espais d&#x02019;inter&#x000e8;s natural de Lleida: &#x000e0;rea meridional</source><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>Institut d&#x02019;Estudis Ilerdencs</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lleida</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IDESCAT. Institut d&#x02019;Estad&#x000ed;stica de Catalunya. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.idescat.cat">http://www.idescat.cat</ext-link>. Accessed 15 June 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Reguant F, Sisquella M, Lletj&#x000f3;s R. Canal Segarra-Garrigues, una eina de futur. DARP [Departament d&#x02019;Agricultura, Ramaderia, Pesca i Alimentaci&#x000f3;], Generalitat de Catalunya; 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Font</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Los estudios bot&#x000e1;nicos en la provincia de L&#x000e9;rida</source><year>1944</year><publisher-loc>Intituto de Estudios Ilerdenses</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lleida</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bellmunt J. Fets, costums i llegendes. Barcelona: Pag&#x000e8;s editors, 3 vols; 1987.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gabernet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Clap&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Arbeca, pels camins de la mem&#x000f2;ria</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>Ajuntament d&#x02019;Arbeca</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Arbeca</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arest&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salom&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><source>Retrobant lo passat</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Diari de Ponent, S.A.</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lleida</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pujadas</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Comas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Roca</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Etnografia</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Barcelona</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Universitat Oberta de Catalunya</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">International Society of Ethnobiology. International Society of Ethnobiology Code of Ethics (with 2008 additions). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ethnobiology.net/code-of-ethics">http://ethnobiology.net/code-of-ethics</ext-link>. Accessed 15 June 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Politics, culture, and governance in the development of prior informed consent in indigenous communities</article-title><source>Curr. Anthropol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>47</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/497670</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23576816?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23576816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">APG [Angiosperm Phylogeny Group] IV. An update of the Angiosperm Phylogeny Group classification for the orders and families of flowering plants: APG IV. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 2016; 181:1-20. DOI:10.1111/boj.12385.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vandebroek</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Damme</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Puyelde</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>De Kimpe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of health conditions treated with traditional and biomedical health care in a Quechua community in rural Bolivia</article-title><source>J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed.</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-4-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18194568?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18194568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trotter</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Etkin</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Informant consensus: a new approach for identifying potentially effective medicinal plants</article-title><source>Plants in indigenous medicine and diet, behavioural approaches</source><year>1986</year><publisher-loc>Bredford Hills</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Redgrave Publishing Company</publisher-name><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>112</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Port&#x000e8;res R. Cours d&#x02019;Ethno-botanique et Ethno-zoologie (1969&#x02013;1970). Volume I, Ethno-botanique g&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;rale. Paris: Mus&#x000e9;um National d&#x02019;Histoire Naturelle (Laboratoire d&#x02019;Ethno-botanique et Ethno-zoologie), Facult&#x000e9; des Lettres (Institut d&#x02019;Ethnologie); 1970.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">BDBC. Banc de dades de Biodiversitat de Catalunya. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biodiver.bio.ub.es/biocat/index.jsp">http://biodiver.bio.ub.es/biocat/index.jsp</ext-link>. Accessed 30 June 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carri&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotany of medicinal plants used in Eastern Mallorca (Balearic Islands, Mediterranean Sea)</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>1021</fpage><lpage>1040</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2012.03.049</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22783553?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22783553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Parada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnatje</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Folk medicinal plant mixtures: establishing a protocol for further studies</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>2018</volume><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2017.12.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonet</surname><given-names>M&#x000c0;</given-names></name><name><surname>Parada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Selga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on pharmaceutical ethnobotany in the regions of L&#x02019;Alt Emporda and Les Guilleries (Catalonia, Iberian Peninsula)</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>68</volume><issue>1-3</issue><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-8741(99)00083-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10624874?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10624874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Carri&#x000f3; E. Contribuci&#x000f3; a l&#x02019;etnobot&#x000e0;nica de Mallorca. La biodiversitat vegetal i la seva gesti&#x000f3; en una illa mediterr&#x000e0;nia. Universitat de Barcelona. PhD thesis. 2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bonet M&#x000c0;, Vall&#x000e8;s J. Plantes, remeis i cultura popular del Montseny: Etnobot&#x000e0;nica d&#x02019;una reserva de la biosfera. Granollers; Figueres: Museu de Ci&#x000e8;ncies Naturals de Granollers; Brau; 2006.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Blumenthal M. The ABC clinical guide to herbs. Austin: American Botanical Council; 2003.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duke</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><source>CRC Handbook of medicinal herbs</source><year>2003</year><edition>2</edition><publisher-loc>Austin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Botanical Council</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">EMA (European Medicines Agency). European Union herbal monographs. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ema.europa.eu/en">https://www.ema.europa.eu/en</ext-link>. Accessed 20 March 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ESCOP (European Scientific Cooperative on Phytotherapy). The scientific foundation for herbal medicinal products. ESCOP Monographs. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://escop.com/">https://escop.com/</ext-link>. Accessed 20 March 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fitoterapia.net">Fitoterapia.net</ext-link>. Vadem&#x000e9;cum de Fitoterapia. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fitoterapia.net/">https://www.fitoterapia.net/</ext-link>. Accessed March 20, 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gemedo-Dalle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maass</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Isselstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant biodiversity and ethnobotany of Borana pastoralists in southern Oromia</article-title><source>Ethiopia. Econ. Bot.</source><year>2015</year><volume>59</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1663/0013-0001(2005)059[0043:PBAEOB]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Le Grand A, Wondergem PA. Les phytoth&#x000e9;rapies anti-infectieuses de la f&#x000f4;ret-savane, S&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;gal, Afrique Occidentale. Un inventaire. J. Ethnopharmacol. 1987; 21:109-125. DOI:10.1016/0378-8741(87)90122-X.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokwaro</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimanani</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbal remedies of the Luo of Siaya district, Kenya: establishing quantitative criteria for consensus</article-title><source>Econ. Bot.</source><year>1990</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03183922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Tejero</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Casares-Porcel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Rojas</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramiro-Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Molero-Mesa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieroni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giusti</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Censorii</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>de Pasquale</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Della</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Paraskeva-Hadijchambi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadijchambi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Houmani</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Demerdash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>ElZayat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hmamouchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Johrig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants in the Mediterranean area: synthesis of the results of the project Rubia</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2007.11.045</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18242025?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18242025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rathore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutrient content of important fruit trees from arid zone of Rajasthan</article-title><source>J. Hortic. For.</source><year>2009</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>108</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000e4;ger</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ethnopharmacology</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Daeschler D. Jean-Paul Jeunet: Jura. Pontarlier: &#x000c9;ditions du Belv&#x000e9;d&#x000e8;re; 2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnatje</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carri&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beyond food and medicine, but necessary for life, too. Other folk plant uses in several territories of Catalonia and the Balearic Islands</article-title><source>J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>23</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-016-0097-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27316670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27316670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guarrera</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Handicrafts, handlooms and dye plants in the Italian folk traditions</article-title><source>Indian J. Tradit. Knowl.</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>69</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fajardo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Verde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ob&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Leopold</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional craft techniques of sparto grass (<italic>Stipa tenacissima</italic> L.) in Spain. Econ</article-title><source>Bot.</source><year>2015</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12231-015-9323-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tard&#x000ed;o</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo de Santayana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aceituno</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inventario espa&#x000f1;ol de los conocimientos tradicionales relativos a la biodiversidad agr&#x000ed;cola</article-title><source>Vol. 1: Introducci&#x000f3;n, metodolog&#x000ed;a y fichas</source><year>2018</year><publisher-loc>Madrid</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Ministerio de Agricultura, Pesca y Alimentaci&#x000f3;n</publisher-name></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>