<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Cardiotoxicity as an off-target effect of doxorubicin therapy is a major limiting factor for its clinical use as a choice cytotoxic agent. Seeds of 
  <italic>Irvingia gabonensis</italic> have been reported to possess both nutritional and medicinal values which include antidiabetic, weight losing, antihyperlipidemic, and antioxidative effects. Protective effects of 
  <italic>Irvingia gabonensis</italic> ethanol seed extract (
  <italic>IGESE</italic>) was investigated in doxorubicin (DOX)-mediated cardiotoxicity induced with single intraperitoneal injection of 15 mg/kg of DOX following the oral pretreatments of Wistar rats with 100-400 mg/kg/day of 
  <italic>IGESE</italic> for 10 days, using serum cardiac enzyme markers (cardiac troponin I (cTI) and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH)), cardiac tissue oxidative stress markers (catalase (CAT), malonyldialdehyde (MDA), superoxide dismutase (SOD), glutathione-S-transferase (GST), glutathione peroxidase (GSH-Px), and reduced glutathione (GSH)), and cardiac histopathology endpoints. In addition, both qualitative and quantitative analyses to determine IGESE's secondary metabolites profile and its 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> antioxidant activities were also conducted. Results revealed that serum cTnI and LDH were significantly elevated by the DOX treatment. Similarly, activities of tissue SOD, CAT, GST, and GSH levels were profoundly reduced, while GPx activity and MDA levels were profoundly increased by DOX treatment. These biochemical changes were associated with microthrombi formation in the DOX-treated cardiac tissues on histological examination. However, oral pretreatments with 100-400 mg/kg/day of 
  <italic>IGESE</italic> dissolved in 5% DMSO in distilled water significantly attenuated increases in the serum cTnI and LDH, prevented significant alterations in the serum lipid profile and the tissue activities and levels of oxidative stress markers while improving cardiovascular disease risk indices and DOX-induced histopathological lesions. The 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> antioxidant studies showed 
  <italic>IGESE</italic> to have good antioxidant profile and contained 56 major secondary metabolites prominent among which are 
  <italic>γ</italic>-sitosterol, Phytol, neophytadiene, stigmasterol, vitamin E, hexadecanoic acid and its ethyl ester, Phytyl palmitate, campesterol, lupeol, and squalene. Overall, both the 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
  <italic>in vivo</italic> findings indicate that 
  <italic>IGESE</italic> may be a promising prophylactic cardioprotective agent against DOX-induced cardiotoxicity, at least in part mediated via 
  <italic>IGESE</italic>'s antioxidant and free radical scavenging and antithrombotic mechanisms.
 </p>
</abstract>
