<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The selected pasture species had a significant suppressive effect on parthenium weed growth and biomass production. The variable performance of the two mixtures could be attributed to the growth and suppressive effects of individual species present in each mixture. For instance, the presence of siratro and Buffel grass in the second plant mixture contributed towards the effectiveness of this mixture in reducing the abundance of parthenium weed as both species have been reported to grow vigorously and suppress parthenium weed individually [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-09-01587" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Moreover, these species were found to be tolerant to the allelopathic effects of parthenium weed [
 <xref rid="B36-plants-09-01587" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-plants-09-01587" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Siratro could play an important role in the suppression of parthenium weed growth through its twining and prostrate growth habit, creating an enveloping canopy that would shade the early growth of the weed. The formation of an early canopy has been indicative of species that could successfully suppress the growth of parthenium weed [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-01587" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Rapid growth and attainment of height and branching or tillering, are some of the morphological and physiological characters of grassland plants that have also been positively correlated with the ability to suppress parthenium weed growth [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-09-01587" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and would thus explain the successful suppression of mixture two. In addition, Queensland bluegrass, the only native species that established well in this plant mixture (
 <xref rid="plants-09-01587-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), could also play a decisive role in reducing the abundance of parthenium weed as it has been shown to suppress parthenium weed by as much as 50% when in monoculture in the field [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-09-01587" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Therefore, this species may have played a role in this trial as well.
</p>
