<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Most non-native invasive plants are distributed across a wide range of latitudes in their invaded ranges, and thus might experience varying biotic interactions, especially during range expansion [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Biotic factors, such as native pathogens and herbivores or native competitors, play an important role in non-native plant invasions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Several theories incorporating biotic interactions, such as the Enemy Release Hypothesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and the Biotic Resistance Hypothesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], have been developed to explain plant invasions. Integrating these theories with the Latitudinal Biotic Interaction Hypothesis can provide a foundation for understanding the spatial heterogeneity of plant invasions and the underlying causes. If latitudinal variation in the biotic interactions of native plants differs from that of invasive plants, then large-scale heterogeneity in the strength of enemy release or biotic resistance could affect plant invasions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Latitudinal variation in invasive plant-above-ground herbivore interactions and the possible causes (such as local adaptation, phenotypic plasticity or apparent competition) have recently received attention [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. For instance, in North America, herbivores on the native genotype 
 <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> decrease with latitude, but no latitudinal pattern exists for the invasive genotype, potentially resulting in decreasing enemy release intensity and increasing biotic resistance intensity with latitude for the invasive genotype [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. More generally, differences in selection pressures for native and invasive plants and the length of time that each group is present at a location may cause evolutionary differences that lead to non-parallel gradients with increasingly intense plant–soil biota interactions at lower latitudes for native plants but not invasive plants. It remains unclear how plant–soil biota interactions and their indirect effects on above-ground plant–herbivore interactions change with latitude for closely related native and invasive plants.
</p>
