<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="s2001">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Cyclophosphamide is an alkylating antineoplastic agent and its major limitation is injury to normal tissue, leading to multiple organ toxicity, including kidney, heart, liver and reproductive toxicity. 
   <italic>Croton macrostachyus</italic> (Euphorbiaceae) has been used in Ethiopian traditional medicine to manage renal diseases.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2002">
  <title>Objective</title>
  <p>The present study aims to assess the protective effect of the stem bark extract and solvent fractions of 
   <italic>Croton macrostachyus</italic> on cyclophosphamide-induced nephrotoxicity in rats.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2003">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>Nephrotoxicity was induced using cyclophosphamide 200 mg/kg i.p injection on the first day of the experiment. The negative control groups were administered with cyclophosphamide alone (200 mg/kg, i.p.). The crude extracts were administered at three dose levels (100, 200, and 400 mg/kg), while aqueous and ethyl acetate fractions were given at two dose levels (100 and 200 mg/kg). Excepting the normal control, all groups were subjected to cyclophosphamide toxicity on the first day.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2004">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>Treatment with crude extract 100 mg/kg and ethyl acetate fraction significantly decreased kidney-to-body weight ratio (P &lt; 0.001). In addition, treatment with 
   <italic>Croton macrostachyus</italic> crude extract and solvent fractions significantly decreased serum blood urea nitrogen (BUN) level (P &lt; 0.001). Treatment with 100 and 200 mg/kg of ethyl acetate fraction significantly decreased serum creatinine level. Histopathological results confirmed the protective effect of the crude extract and solvent fractions of 
   <italic>Croton macrostachyus</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2005">
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p>Croton macrostachyus possesses nephroprotective activities and it could be a possible source of treatment for cyclophosphamide-induced nephrotoxicity.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
