<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The review by 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2019.00697" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Grynkiewicz and Demchuk</ext-link> discussed new perspectives for fisetin, a naturally occurring flavonol, which has distinct antioxidant properties along with a plethora of other plant polyphenols. In particular, they described the potential applications and demand for fisetin in healthcare, methods for its preparation, and its suitability for pharmaceutical use. 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2020.00363" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Wang, Song et al.</ext-link> reviewed the phytochemical, structural modification, and relevant bioactivities, such as anticancer, lipid-regulating, anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, antiviral, and diuretic activities of triterpenoids, especially those obtained from 
 <italic>Alisma</italic> species and their derivatives. 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2020.00301" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Harada et al.</ext-link> summarized the chemistry and neurotrophic activities of (–)-talaumidin and its derivatives. They achieved the first enantioselective total synthesis of (–)-talaumidin 
 <italic>via</italic> a flexible and reliable synthetic pathway involving an Evans asymmetric aldol reaction, as well as stereo-controlled hydroboration and Friedel-Crafts arylation, to construct the four contiguous chiral centers on the tetrahydrofuran ring. To investigate the structure-activity relationships, a systematic synthesis of all diastereomers and syntheses of several related derivatives was reported along with an evaluation of neurite outgrowth promotion and neuroprotection in primary cultured rat cortical neurons and in nerve growth factor-differentiated PC12 cells. Candidates including (–)-talaumidin for the regeneration of mouse optic nerves 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> were discovered. 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2020.00187" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Nakamura et al.</ext-link> developed a practical and reproducible method for total synthesis of hydroxy-α-sanshool, α-sanshool, and spilanthol, which is a characteristic polyunsaturated fatty acid amide obtained from 
 <italic>Zanthoxylum</italic> species. Notably, a highly selective Wittig reaction using a newly synthesized phosphonium salt with low deliquescence and long-term stability created the desired 
 <italic>Z</italic>-form polyenes. This improved methodology was shown to be applicable to the efficient synthesis of other sanshool derivatives. Regarding the structure determination of novel naturally occurring compounds from traditional medicinal plants, four picrotoxane-type sesquiterpenes, dendroterpene A–D, were isolated from the stems of 
 <italic>Dendrobium nobile</italic> (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2019.10.3389/fchem.2019.00812" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Wang, Chen et al.</ext-link>). Six highly oxidized lanostane- and cycloartane-type triterpenes, xuetongalactones A–F, were obtained from the stems of 
 <italic>Kadsura heteroclita</italic> (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2019.00935" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Shehla et al.</ext-link>). Six new limonoids, dictamlinonol A, dictamlimonoside B, and dictamlimonols C–F, were isolated from the root bark of 
 <italic>Dictamnus dasycarpus</italic> (
 <italic>Cortex Dictamni</italic>) (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2020.00073" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Chen et al.</ext-link>). Three new geranylated coumarins, kayeassamin I and mammeasins E and F, were obtained from the flowers of 
 <italic>Mammea siamensis</italic> (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2020.00199" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Morikawa et al.</ext-link>). Five new cyclic organosulfer compounds, foliogarlic disulfanes A
 <sub>1</sub>-A
 <sub>3</sub> and foliogarlic trisulfanes A
 <sub>1</sub> and A
 <sub>2</sub>, were isolated from the leaves of 
 <italic>Allium sativa</italic> (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2020.00282" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Fukaya et al.</ext-link>). Their structures, including the stereochemistry, were elucidated by NMR, MS, X-ray diffraction, and electronic circular dichroism spectroscopic analyses. Various bio-functional activities including; α-glucosidase inhibitory (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2019.00812" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Wang, Chen et al.</ext-link>), cytotoxicic (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2019.00812" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Wang, Chen et al.</ext-link>; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2019.00935" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Shehla et al.</ext-link>), anti-inflammatory (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2019.00935" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Shehla et al.</ext-link>; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2020.00073" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Chen et al.</ext-link>), and 5α-reductase inhibitory activities (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2020.00199" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Morikawa et al.</ext-link>) were also reported. A limonoid fraxinellon was a noteworthy compound obtained as a main constituent of 
 <italic>Cortex Dictamni</italic> in a yield of ~0.15% with remarkable anti-inflammatory activity. Fraxinellon inhibited lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-induced nitric oxide production and reduced the LPS-induced expression of inducible nitric oxide synthase and cyclooxigenase-2 at the mRNA and protein levels in a dose-dependent manner by regulating the nuclear factor kappa-light-chain-enhancer of activated B cells in RAW 264.7 macrophage-like cells (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2020.00073" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Chen et al.</ext-link>). In addition, a geranylated coumarin surangin C obtained from 
 <italic>M. siamemsis</italic> flowers exhibited 5α-reductase inhibitory activity (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 5.9 μM). Although the intensity of the 5α-reductase inhibitory activity of these coumarins is moderate compared to the positive control with a steroid skeleton finasteride (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.12 μM), there are few reports of 5α-reductase inhibitors with non-steroidal skeletons. These active coumarins may therefore be useful candidates for seed compounds of new non-steroidal 5α-reductase inhibitors (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fchem.2020.00199" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Morikawa et al.</ext-link>).
</p>
