<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0030" class="p">Oil reservoirs are extreme environments for microbial life [
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>] characterized by high toxicity, hydrophobicity and low water activity, as well as high temperature, salinity, and pressure [
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Nevertheless, oil reservoirs offer a broad range of niches for a multitude of bacteria and archaea, such as sulfate-, nitrate-, and iron-reducers, fermenters, acetogens, and methanogens [
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. The microbial degradation of oil results in a higher fraction of bitumen and eventually leads to the deterioration of the world’s oil resources. Since oil is still one of the most important resources for industry and energy [
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>], it is crucial to gain insights into the microbiology of oil reservoirs. Over the past decades, numerous reviews on oil microbiology have investigated the extent of biodegradation, the effect of microbes on oil quality, oil production methods and enhanced oil recovery (EOR) [
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[5]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[6]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[7]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[8]</xref>], as well as their taxonomical and functional composition and the impact of environmental factors on microbes [
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. However, due to the lack of undisturbed samples, our knowledge of microbial ecology in oil reservoirs is still limited [
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>].
</p>
