<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To increase nematicidal efficacy, Soliman et al. prepared and compared AgNPs obtained using 
 <italic>A. judaica</italic> extracts in different solvents (petroleum ether, ethyl acetate, ethanol) with AgNPs obtained using the essential oil and AgNPs prepared using a reference pesticide and compared the extracts. LC
 <sub>50</sub> values showed that all types of nanoparticles were more toxic to the second juvenile stage of 
 <italic>Meloidogyne incognita</italic> than the extracts. Comparing the activity of AgNPs obtained using the reference pesticide and those obtained using the extracts or the essential oil, respectively, proved that the NPs obtained using the reference pesticide had the highest inhibitory effect. As for AgNPs obtained from 
 <italic>A. judaica</italic>, their activity increased up to 3-fold, being influenced by the extraction solvent (AgNPs obtained using petroleum ether extract&gt; AgNPs obtained using ethyl acetate extract&gt; AgNPs obtained using essential oil&gt; AgNPs obtained using ethanol extract). Regarding the inhibition of egg hatchability by extracts and AgNPs, the results were similar, with NPs having a better activity compared to extracts, and among the NPs, the best results being obtained when using petroleum ether as solvent. The explanation could lay in the chemical composition of 
 <italic>A. judaica</italic> extracts and of AgNPs. The chemical analysis revealed that the major components of the petroleum ether extract were 6-octadecanoic acid, n-hexadecanoic acid, 1,3-dimethylbenzene (m-Xylene), bis (2-ethylhexyl)phthalate, octacosane, 9,11-dimethyl-6H-indolo-quinline, nonacosane, cyclohexanol,3-ethenyl-3-methyl-2(1-methylethenyl)-6(1-methylethyl), and cyclohexanol-3-ethenyl-3-methyl-2-(1-methylethenyl)-6-(1-methylethyl, while for the corresponding NPs, the major compounds were 4-trimethyl-yciclo-hept-’-en-3′-yl]-3-buten-2-one, berkheyaradulene, β-caryophyllene, and allo-aromadendrene, which were found to be 20 to 30-fold increased [
 <xref rid="B217-molecules-26-03061" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>].
</p>
