<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10" class="p">In the last years, resin-based products have been explored as feed components to improve and maintain intestinal health of broilers [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>]. While the integrity of the chicken gut is of key importance in broiler health and performance, challenges that affect epithelial integrity are continuously encountered (coccidia, bacterial pathogens such as 
 <italic class="italic">Clostridium perfringens</italic>, feed antigens and mycotoxins, amongst others) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>]. Loss of intestinal mucosal integrity leads to intestinal inflammation, as antigens will initiate a cascade of molecular events that lead to pro-inflammatory cytokine expression. The intestinal microbial composition is also crucial in, either or not, maintaining gut homeostasis. Given the anti-microbial and anti-inflammatory properties of resin, potential beneficial effects in the avian gut may be expected. Indeed, inclusion of a resin-based product in the diet of broiler chickens significantly increased broiler performance when birds were under 
 <italic class="italic">C. perfringens</italic> challenge [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>]. Furthermore, even under unchallenged conditions broiler performance was increased by inclusion of resin-based products in a commercial diet supplemented with or without chemical coccidiostats [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>]. However, little is known about the mechanism by which these resin-based products influence broiler performance. The described benefits do not seem to be associated with the feed type [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>]. Moreover, the potential effect on broiler microbiota remains unclear. Unfortunately, all broiler studies described so far used a resin-based product containing a combination of resin-specific tall oil fatty acids (~90%) and resin acids (~8%). As both the tall oil fatty acids fraction as well as the resin acids fraction of these resin-based products can have an effect on bird performance, it is still unclear whether one or the other fraction, or the combination, is essential to gain the observed results.
</p>
