<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Vet World</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Vet World</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Veterinary World</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0972-8988</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2231-0916</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Veterinary World</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6303501</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14202/vetworld.2018.1539-1550</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Yields, chemical composition, and antimicrobial activity of two Algerian essential oils against 40 avian multidrug-resistant <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mansouri</surname><given-names>Narimene</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aoun</surname><given-names>Leila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dalichaouche</surname><given-names>Nabila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hadri</surname><given-names>Douniazed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Laboratory Research of Epidemiologic Monitoring, Health, Production, Reproduction, Experimentation and Cellular Therapy of Domestic and Wild Animals, Department of Veterinary Medicine, University of Chadli Bendjedid, El-Tarf, Algeria</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Regional Veterinary Laboratory of El-Tarf, National Institute of Veterinary Medicine, Minister of Agriculture, Algeria</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Veterinary Medicine, University of Chadli Bendjedid, El-Tarf, Algeria</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Narimene Mansouri, e-mail: <email xlink:href="avinanou@gmail.com">avinanou@gmail.com</email><bold>Co-authors:</bold> LA: <email xlink:href="aoun_vet@yahoo.fr">aoun_vet@yahoo.fr</email>, ND: <email xlink:href="nabila_dalichaouche@yahoo.fr">nabila_dalichaouche@yahoo.fr</email>, DH: <email xlink:href="bigmantaraie21@gmail.com">bigmantaraie21@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1539</fpage><lpage>1550</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; Mansouri, <italic>et al</italic>.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->Open Access. This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Aim:</title><p>The aim of this study is to investigate, <italic>in vitro</italic>, a possible antibacterial activity of Algerian essential oils (EOs) of Thyme (<italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L.) and that of Coriander (<italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L.) against multidrug-resistant avian <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains and this in a perspective of their future use as a substitute for antibiotics (ATBs).</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>In addition to the reference strain of <italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC 25922, 40 strains of avian <italic>E. coli</italic> have been isolated (24 strains of broilers and 16 of turkeys), their antimicrobial resistance profile was determined by antibiogram tests against 21 ATBs whereupon they were subjected to the action of two Algerian EOs; the EO of Thyme (<italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L.) and that of Coriander (<italic>C. sativum</italic> L.), which oils were extracted by hydrodistillation and analyzed by Gas Chromatography coupled to Mass Spectrometry (GC-MS) and this for the determination of their chemical composition. The antibacterial activity, resulting in zones of inhibition, was evaluated by carrying out, in triplicate, aromatograms for both pure EO and that which has been diluted to 15% in Dimethyl Sulfoxide (DMSO), while the minimum inhibitory concentrations (MIC) of the two EOs were highlighted by the method of liquid macrodilution.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>Antibiogram performance demonstrated an alarming state of antimicrobial resistance, the multidrug resistance rate was estimated at 100% for the broilers chicken strains and at 81.25% for strains isolated from turkeys, hydrodistillation allowed to obtained EOs with yields estimated at 1.22&#x000b1;0.26% for Thyme EO and 0.23&#x000b1;0.15% for the essence of Coriander, the GC-MS analysis identified 19 main compounds and showed that the majority chemical components were Carvacrol (73.03%) for Thyme volatile oil and Linalool (60.91%) for Coriander EO, aromatograms and the determination of MIC concluded that the EO of Thyme showed a greater antibacterial activity with an average of the zones of inhibition estimated at 26.75&#x000b1;0.426 mm and MIC ranging from 0.07 to 0.93 mg/ml against an average of the inhibition zones evaluated at 17.05&#x000b1;0.383 mm and MICs evaluated between 0.6 and 10 mg/ml for the EO of Coriander.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>In aviculture, these results seem to be very promising in the case where we think about the replacement of ATBs by EOs, <italic>in vivo</italic> studies would be very interesting to confirm or invalidate this hypothesis.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Avian <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></kwd><kwd>antimicrobial resistance</kwd><kwd>essential oils</kwd><kwd>antibacterial activity</kwd><kwd><italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L</kwd><kwd><italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>Introduction</title><p>In veterinary medicine and particularly in poultry farming, antimicrobial resistance is a real public health problem; the anarchic use of antibiotics (ATBs) has led to the development of bacteria with an alarming profile of resistance [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In Algeria, as in the majority of developing countries, the poultry sector is one of the most prosperous sectors, and white meat is the most consumed meat, so any selection of ATB resistance will inevitably affect the health of Algerian consumers [<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>In recent years, the number of scientific articles relating to aromatherapy and demonstrating its benefits has increased [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], that is why we naturally have opted, in our study, for the use of two essential oils (EOs) that of Thyme (<italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L.) and Coriander (<italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L.). These aromatic and medicinal plants are widely used, and their benefits have been recognized since Antiquity [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In fact, Thyme, widespread in Algeria, constitute an important remedy used since centuries and identified as a good source of bioactive compounds possessing significant antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties, potentially effective in prevention and treatment of pathological conditions [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], but what prompted us the most to choose it is its reputation of antibacterial molecule, especially against Enterobacteria, one of the most important bacteria in avian pathology [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Coriander, another aromatic plant common in the Mediterranean basin, also has EOs known for their antifungal, insecticides, and antibacterial effects [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Following this observation, our approach was to think about a new substances that could have, <italic>in vitro</italic>, the same antibacterial effect as that of ATBs, while having the advantage of avoiding the selection of new resistant bacteria, which is why, we thought to an ancient cure, namely aromatic plants and especially their EOs [<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Our approach was, therefore, to look for the antibacterial action of these EO to remedy the evolution of antimicrobial resistance, thus providing consumers with healthy foodstuffs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Ethical approval</title><p>Ethical approval was not required in this study since no live animals were used in the experiment. Samples were collected from dead animals.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Plant material</title><p>Dried aerial parts (stems, leaves, and flowers) for Thyme EO and ground seeds for Coriander EO were purchased from a herbalist in the city of El-Tarf (Northeastern Algeria), these plants come from the summer harvest (Flowering season) of the year 2015 in the region of Djelfa located in the central part of Northern Algeria which is a region characterized by a semi-arid climate.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Extraction and isolation of EOs</title><p>Extraction of the EOs was carried out by hydrodistillation using the Deryng apparatus which is the Polish version of the Clevenger apparatus [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], several distillations were carried out by boiling 100 g of dried aerial parts of Thyme in 1 L of distilled water [<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and 30 g of ground Coriander in 500 ml of distilled water during 3 h, the yield of EO was determined in relation to the dry matter [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. After decanting and drying of the oils over anhydrous sodium sulfate, they were stored at 4&#x000b0;C in amber glass tubes and the dark until analysis [<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry (GC-MS) analysis</title><p>The chemical composition analysis of EOs of Thyme (<italic>T. vulgaris</italic>) and that of Coriander (<italic>C. sativum</italic> L.) was performed in Algiers in the Center for Scientific and Technical Research in Physical and Chemical Analysis (CRAPC EXPERTISE SPA) using g a Hewlett Packard Agilent 6890 GC equipped with an HP-5MS capillary column (30 m * 0.25 mm, film thickness 0.25 &#x003bc;m). The steady state temperature was started at 60 &#x000b0;C for 8 min and then gradually increased (2 &#x000b0;C/min) to 250 &#x000b0; C for 10 min. This device was coupled to a Hewlett Packard Agilent 5973 MS detector recorded in 70 eV electron ionization with 30 to 550 sweep with a solvent delay of 3.5 min, ion source at 230 &#x000b0;C and interface temperature at 280 &#x000b0;C. The temperature of the injector was fixed to 250&#x000b0;C with a split ratio of 50:1 and 0.2 &#x000b5;l of injected volume. Helium was used as the carrier gas at a flow rate of 0.5 ml/. The percentage of each constituent of the oil was determined by area peaks, the EOs components were identified by comparison with literature data and the profiles from the Wiley 7.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Bacterial strains</title><p>In our study, the bacteria we worked on were represented by 40 multidrug-resistant strains of avian <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (24 strains from broiler chicken and 16 from turkey) isolated from animals reared in the Eastern region of Algeria and this from feces, livers, and intestines of birds with diarrhea. These samples were restored in buffered peptone water for 18-24 h at 37&#x000b0;C, then, using a sterile platinum loop, a drop from the previously inoculated broth was seeded onto Hektoen agar plates for 24 h at 37&#x000b0;C. Identification of <italic>E. coli</italic> isolates was performed according to morphological characters of colonies and results of their biochemical tests obtained using commercial biochemical test kits (bioM&#x000e9;rieux API, France). We also worked on a reference strain of <italic>E. coli</italic> (ATCC 25922) provided by the Regional Veterinary Laboratory of El-Tarf.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Evaluation of resistance phenotypes of E. coli avian strains</title><p>The resistance profile of isolated strains was studied by performing antibiograms (antimicrobial susceptibility testing) according to the recommendations of the Antibiogram Committee of the French Society of Microbiology (CA-SFM - Veterinary Antibiograms - version 2017). These antibiograms were carried out against 21 ATBs belonging to 6 ATB families (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table-1</xref>) and for each group of antibiograms performed, internal quality control was done with the <italic>E. coli</italic> reference strain (ATCC 25922), and this for ensuring the validity of the results of the antibiograms obtained [<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table-1</label><caption><p>Families of antibiotics used.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibiotic family</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subfamily</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Molecule</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concentration</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disc initials</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Aminoglycosides</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gentamicin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 &#x000b5;g</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GM</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neomycin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 UI</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NEO</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="10" valign="top" colspan="1">Beta-lactams</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aminopenicillins</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amoxicillin/clavulanic acid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(20/10 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMC</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ampicillin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMP</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbapenems</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ertapenem</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETP</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Imipenem</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMI</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cephalosporins first generation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cephalothin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(30 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CF</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cephalosporins second generation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefoxitin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(30 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FOX</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cephalosporins third generation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefotaxime</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(30 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTX</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceftazidime</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(30 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAZ</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceftiofur</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(30 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XNL</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceftriaxone</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(30 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRO</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Quinolones</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cephalosporins fourth generation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefepime</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(30 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEP</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monobactams</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aztreonam</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(30 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">first generation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nalidixic acid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(30 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluoroquinolones second generation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciprofloxacin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIP</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluoroquinolones third generation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Danofloxacin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DAN</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrofloxacin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENR</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polymyxins</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polypeptide</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colistin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(50 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetracyclines</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetracycline</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(30 UI)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TE</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trimethoprim/sulfonamides</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trimethoprim/Sulfamethoxazole</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.25/23.75 &#x000b5;g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SXT</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Disc diffusion assay</title><p>This method, also called aromatogram, is based on a technique used in medical bacteriology which is the antibiogram, the only difference is the replacement of ATBs with aromatic extracts, the EO will diffuse from the soaked disc within the agar and determine a concentration gradient [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. For this, a bacterial suspension of density equivalent to 0.5 MacFarland is prepared and diluted 1/100, in the meantime, 20 ml of Mueller-Hinton agar medium are prepared and poured into a Petri dish where 2 ml of inoculum are poured, after impregnation of 5 min, the excess inoculum is removed by suction. On the surface of each box, three sterile 6 mm diameter filter paper disks (bioM&#x000e9;rieux) are deposited. Two tests are carried out: A disc soaked with 15 &#x003bc;l of EO and the second one with 15 &#x003bc;l of EO supplemented with 15% of Dimethyl Sulfoxide (DMSO). A negative control is carried out with 15 &#x003bc;l of sterile distilled water in the presence of 15% of DMSO. The dishes are left for 1 h at room temperature, then inverted and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 18-24 h [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The bacteria will grow on the entire surface of the agar except where they meet a concentration of EO sufficient to inhibit their growth. At the outlet of the stove, the absence of bacterial growth results in a translucent halo around the disc and the diameter of the inhibition zone (IZ) is measured and expressed in millimeters (mm). The larger the diameter, the more the strain is sensitive to EO [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Each test was performed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Determination of Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC)</title><p>In this step, we drew on the work of Dr. Guinoiseau using the method of liquid macrodilution for the determination of MICs, and this method consists of inoculating, by a standardized inoculum and a decreasing concentration range in EO. After incubation, observation of the range gives access to the MIC [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], which corresponds to the lowest concentration of active ingredient capable of inhibiting any bacterial growth at 24 h [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec1-3"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Yields and organoleptic properties</title><p>Extraction by several hydrodistillations of the two plants allowed to obtain different yields. Indeed, the EO of <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L., characterized by a liquid appearance, a light brown color, a strong and a spicy aromatic odor, expressed a yield estimated at 1.22&#x000b1;0.26%, while the EO of <italic>C. sativum</italic> L., which was characterized by its mobile liquid appearance, pale yellow, and its camphorous odor, displayed, as for her, a much lower yield evaluated at 0.23&#x000b1;0.15%. <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table-2</xref> compares the yields we obtained with several other studies [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>-<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], carried out on the same plants, in Algeria, Maghreb, Africa, and other regions of the world.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table-2</label><caption><p>Comparison of the yields obtained with the data from the literature.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="5" valign="top" colspan="1">EO</th><th align="center" colspan="5s" rowspan="1">Yields</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="3" valign="top" colspan="1">Present study (%)</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Literature data (%)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Algerian studies</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maghrebian studies</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">African studies</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other studies</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T&#x003bd;EO</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22&#x000b1;0.26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45-2.7 [16,17]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-3.6 [18-20]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55-1 [21,22]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83-4 [23-25]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<italic>s</italic>EO</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23&#x000b1;0.15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44-0.70 [26]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 [27]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31-0.8 [28,29]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15-2.1 [30-33]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>EO=Essential oil, T&#x003bd;EO=<italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. Essential oil, <italic>CsEO=Coriandrum sativum</italic> L. Essential oil</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The results illustrated in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table-2</xref> demonstrate a certain variability in the yields obtained in the various studies conducted [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>-<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]; indeed, these differences could be explained by several factors such as environmental factors as demonstrated by Krol and Kieltyka-Dadasiewicz [<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] who emphasized that the weather conditions and harvested time have a significant effect on the herb yield, in the same context, Jordan <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] gave a relationship between the production of volatile oils and the climate by stating that EO production is favored in areas with a low thermicity index. Other studies examining the influence of plant maturity on their EO yield have shown that higher yields have been recorded on advanced mature plants [<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Hazzoumi <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], when to them, have highlighted a negative correlation between the water content in plant leaves and their EO yields, while other authors have attributed the difference of these yields to the plant drying time [<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] and to the means of EO extraction, Indeed, it has been proven, especially by Akram <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], where EO extraction was done by two different methods, a supercritical fluid extraction (SCFE) and hydrodistillation, that the yield of the EO differs according to the extraction technique. The comparison between these two methods revealed the superiority of the yields obtained by SCFE compared to the hydrodistillation process. While Zheljazkov <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] emphasized the duration of hydrodistillation by demonstrating that the low EO yield obtained in the short distillation time (DT) has been increased with increasing of this DT, the extraction temperature and the flow rate can also be incriminate [<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Other parameters such as growing region [<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], geographical variations, and origin of cultivars also appear to be behind the variations in these yields [<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Chemical composition of the EOs</title><p>The GC-MS analysis of the essences studied gave the following results (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table-3</xref>), for Thyme EO (<italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L.), 14 compounds, representing 95.58% of all the constituents detected, were identified. This EO was characterized by its high content of phenols (74.40%). Indeed, among the 7 main constituents of this aroma, the main compound was Carvacrol (73.03%) which is a powerful phenol sought in EOs for its antibacterial action, which molecule was followed by p-cymen (9.99%), &#x003b2;-caryophyllene (3.63%) and &#x003b3;-terpinene (3.02%), which together with p-cymen represent the two precursors of Carvacol [<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], note that Thymol, another potent phenol is present but in small quantities (1.14%). For Coriander EO (<italic>C. sativum</italic>), GC-MS analysis revealed 19 molecules representing 93.51% of the total components; the main molecule was Linalool (60.91%), followed by Eugenol (8.95%) and Aceteugenol (6.70%). The chemical analysis of these essences allowed, therefore, highlighting 2 different chemotypes (CT), the CT Carvacrol for the EO of Thyme and Linalool CT for EO of Coriander.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table-3</label><caption><p>Chemical composition of the essential oils studied (<italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. and <italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L.).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" valign="top" colspan="1">Compounds</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" valign="top" colspan="1">RT (min)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">% Content</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T&#x003bd;EO</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<italic>s</italic>EO</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Pinene</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.142</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camphene</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.879</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-Pinene</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.610</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-Myrcene</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.477</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Terpinene</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.124</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-Cymene</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.570</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;-Terpinene</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.546</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalool</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.313</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camphor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.311</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Borneol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.906</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Terpineol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.743</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decanal</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.578</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geraniol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.246</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thymol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.055</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carvacrol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.371</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.03</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eugenol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.197</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geranyl acetate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.593</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trans (&#x003b2;) caryophyllene</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.543</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aceteugenol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.376</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemical group</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.95</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Monoterpene hydrocarbons (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Phenols (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">01.58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Oxygenated monoterpenes (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">03.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Sesquiterpenes hydrocarbons (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">09.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Others (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>RT=Retention time, T&#x003bd;EO=<italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. Essential oil, C<italic>s</italic>EO=<italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L. Essential oil</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>By analyzing our results and comparing them with other studies (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table-4</xref>) [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>-<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], we can make the following observations; concerning the EO of Thyme, the majority components are the same as we obtained but with different levels allowing to have other CT. Indeed, apart Sidali <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], who worked on <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. from Northwest Algeria and whose results attributed, as for us, their EO to the Carvacrol CT, the other studies presented other CT. The study carried in Algeria (North Center) [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and on the same plant, displayed an EO belonging to the Linalool CT in Morocco [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], in Italy [<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] and in Iran [<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], have highlighted an EO with Thymol CT. In Romania, another CT, the &#x003b3;-terpinene one, has been reported [<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Note that in the literature, for the EO of <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L., there are up to 20 different CTs [<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table-4</label><caption><p>Comparison of the chemical compositions obtained with the data from the literature.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. Essential Oil</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Origin</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major components</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Our study</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carvacrol (73.03), <italic>p</italic>-Cymen (9.99), Caryophyllene (3.6), &#x003b3;-Terpinene (3.02), Linalool (1.17), Thymol (1.14)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Algeria (Northwest)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carvacrol (55.2), &#x003b3;-Terpinene (12.6), <italic>p</italic>-Cymen (9.3), Linalool (3.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Algeria (North Center)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalool (82.88), Thymol (4.92), Linalyl acetate (2.43), Cymene (2.08)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morocco</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thymol (35.8), Carvacrol (18.6), <italic>p</italic>-Cymen (14.1), &#x003b3;-Terpinene (12.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thymol (43.68), <italic>p</italic>-Cymen (18.5), Carvacrol (5.5), &#x003b3;-Terpinene (4.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thymol (40.02), Carvacrol (18.31), <italic>p</italic>-Cymen (16.78), Linalool (4.84)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Romania</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;-Terpinene (68.41), Thymol (24.72), Caryophyllene (5.50)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic></bold> L. Essential Oil</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Origin</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Major components</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>References</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Our study</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalool (60.91), Eugenol (8.95), Aceteugenol (6.70),&#x003b3;-Terpinene (3.25)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Algeria (Northwest)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalool (63.50), Camphor (2.69), Geraniol (1.79), Limonene (0.29)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egypt (North)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalool (59.6), Ethyl hexanoic acid (4.9), Sabinene,(4.36) &#x003b1;-Thujene (3.32)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalool (77.07), Geraniol (5.24), Caryophyllene (3.16), Camphor (2.60)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syria</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalool (73.92), Geranyl acetate (4.43), o-Cymen (2.39)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egypt (Center)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalool (70.93), Linalool acetate (4.78), -Pinene (4.17), <italic>p</italic>-Cymen (3.63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>As for the EO of <italic>C. sativum</italic> L., the result that we obtained is corroborated by several other studies carried out in Algeria (Northwest) [<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], Egypt (North and Center) [<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], Italy [<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], and Syria [<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], thus affirming the belonging to the Linalool CT. The variations reported in the compositions of the EO studied can be explained by intrinsic plant factors and extrinsic one [<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]; these factors can be divided into three groups; genotype, ecological, and technological factors [<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>-<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. instead of [<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>-<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], in fact, Pirbalouti [<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], during his work, indicated that the components of EOs varied with the plant genotype, El-Zaeddi <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], when to them, have rather questioned the stage of maturity of the plant, while Lu&#x000ed;s <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] have instead focused on the geographical origin of the plant; however, the environmental factor is also important. Indeed, Atti-Santos <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], working on the effect of the seasonal variation of the chemical composition of the EO of <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> from South Brazil, found that the main component, namely Thymol, over the 9 months of harvesting period, was found to vary from 35.5% to 52.4%, concluding that as regard to the harvest time, EO was richer in oxygenated compounds in spring season. Other authors have attributed the difference in the chemical composition of EO to the conditions in which the plants will grow, thus calling into question the temperature, photoperiod, rainfall, and hygrometry [<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>-<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], abiotic stress such as salinity and water stress [<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], agronomical practices [<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>], and even spatial distribution of the plants. Indeed, De Falco <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], in addition to incriminating the state of the plant before extraction (fresh or dried), demonstrated an EO rich in Sabinene from plants grown in single rows, while plants grown in double rows were richer in Ocimene. Finally, other factors, influencing the composition of EO, can be mentioned such as the period and conditions of storage [<xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], the duration of drying of the plant, as well as the extraction duration [<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2-11"><title>ATBs resistance of E. coli avian strains</title><p>The results of ATB resistance of <italic>E. coli</italic> strains are presented in <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table-5</xref>; for the broiler chicken strains, antibiograms showed a very high and very disturbing antimicrobial resistance profile. Indeed, of the 21 ATBs tested, a total resistance (100%), combining the intermediate and resistant antibiogram results (I+R), has been reported to 8 molecules; amoxicillin/clavulanic acid (AMC), ampicillin (AMP), ceftazidime (CAZ), which is a cephalosporin third generation, nalidixic acid (NA), danofloxacin (DAN), enrofloxacin (ENR), tetracycline (TE), and trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole (SXT), these strains showed also a significant resistance (I+R) to colistin (CS) (95.83%), ciprofloxacin (CIP) (87.5%) and neomycin (NEO) (75%); note that the cefepime (FEP), cephalosporin fourth generation, is the only ATB for which no antimicrobial resistance has been reported (0%), but what also attracted our attention is the presence of a resistance to two molecules belonging to the carbapenem family, namely ertapenem (ETP) and imipenem (IMI), evaluated respectively at 8.33 and 4.16%. although this resistance is minimal, it is very worrying as this class of ATB ranked as critically important by World Health, is used in hospitals as a treatment of last intention [<xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Unfortunately, the result we obtained is corroborated by several other studies conducted in Algeria; this is the case of Halfaoui <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] who worked on different organs of broilers with colibacillosis lesions in central Algeria. This study isolated 156 strains of <italic>E. coli</italic> with a high level of resistance to TE (94.12%), flumequine (FLM): 91.5%, SXT (88.89%), ENR (86.27%), NA (85.62%), AMP (83.01%) and doxycycline (DO): 75.81%. Another study, conducted on ATB resistance of avian Enterobacteriaceae in Western Algeria by Ahmed <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], found that <italic>E. coli</italic> strains presented a high levels of resistance to FLM (94%), TE, and amoxicillin with the same rate estimated at 92%, SXT (91%), ENR (86%), NA (84%), and cephalothin (CF) with 80% of resistance; a second study, conducted in another region of the West region of Algeria, also revealed high antimicrobial resistance levels for <italic>E. coli</italic> from broilers with up to 90.35%, 79.82%, 70.17%, 92.10%, and 62.28%, respectively, for TE, ENR, SXT, AMC, and ceftiofur (XNL) [<xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Other similar results were recorded on <italic>E. coli</italic> strains from broiler in other countries; Abd El Tawab <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] showed <italic>E. coli</italic> strains with total resistance (100%) to AMC and significant resistance to 2 other ATB which are DO and erythromycin (ERY) with, respectively, rates estimated at 90% and 60% in Egypt; Manishimwe <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>] reported a prevalence of ATB resistance (I+R) from <italic>E. coli</italic> isolates to ERY, rifampicin, and DO estimated, respectively, at 100, 98.8, and 98.3% in Rwanda, while Wasyl <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>] estimated at 54.5% the resistance of <italic>E. coli</italic> to cephalosporin in Poland; these genes were also noted in strains from broilers originated from Belgium and Germany.</p><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table-5</label><caption><p>Antibiograms results of avian <italic>E. coli</italic> strains.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibiotics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Resistance BS (I+R)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Resistance TS (I+R)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NEO</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMC</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMP</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ETP</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMI</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CF</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FOX</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTX</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAZ</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XNL</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRO</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEP</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIP</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DAN</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENR</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TE</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SXT</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of multi-resistant isolates</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.25</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>ATB=Antibiotics, BS=Broiler strains, (I+R)=Intermediate+resistant, TS=Turkey strains, GM=Gentamicin, NEO=Neomycin, AMC=Amoxicillin/clavulanic acid, AMP=Ampicillin, ETP=Ertapenem, IMI=Imipenem, CF=Cephalothin, FOX=Cefoxitin, CTX=Cefotaxime, CAZ=Ceftazidime, XNL=Ceftiofur, CRO=Ceftriaxone, FEP=Cefepime, AT=Aztreonam, NA=Nalidixic acid, CIP=Ciprofloxacin, DAN=Danofloxacin, ENR=Enrofloxacin, CS=Colistin, TE=Tetracycline, SXT=Trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole, <italic>E. coli=Escherichia coli</italic></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>However, our results differ completely from those obtained in France and expressed in the annual report of the year 2016 of the network RESAPATH (French surveillance network for antimicrobial resistance in pathogenic bacteria of animal origin) in collaboration with ANSES (French agency for food, environmental, and occupational health safety), in fact, this network reported that the resistance to TE in clinical <italic>E. coli</italic> broiler strains has been continuously decreasing from 81% in 2010 to 44% in 2016. The same thing was found for XNL, where its resistance decreased from 22% in 2010 to 2.4% in 2016, and this network also reported a sensitivity of these <italic>E. coli</italic> strains with regard to ENR (92%), DAN (87%), AMC (85%), SXT (69%), and NA (53%) [<xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Regarding the CS, apart from the study carried out by Bodering <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] where the resistance rate of <italic>E. coli</italic> isolated at CS was estimated at 100%, the majority of the other studies showed resistance rates at the CS that did not exceed 16% [<xref rid="ref72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,<xref rid="ref73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], or even a total sensitivity to this molecule for some studies [<xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].</p><p>In the case of strains isolated from turkeys, the finding is a significant antimicrobial resistance but less than that of broilers; in fact, a state of resistance (I + R) evaluated at 100%, has been demonstrated for a single molecule (CS) which, according to a study by Messai [<xref rid="ref74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>], is the first molecule to be used in Algeria in the Poultry farming during digestive infections. These bacteria also showed an estimated resistance of 87.5% against 4 molecules (AMC, NA, DAN and ENR) followed closely by a resistance rate evaluated at 81.25% recorded against four other molecules (NEO, AMP, CAZ and TE). The CIP, SXT, CF, and the cefoxitin came after with, respectively, posted rates at 75, 68.75, 56.25, and 50%. For the three ATB (IMI, ceftriaxone, and aztreonam), no antimicrobial resistance was reported (0%). We would like to point out that for these strains of turkey, the state of non-sensitivity to an ATB of the Carbapenem family, namely, ETP (6.25%) as well as the presence of resistance against a fourth-generation Cephalosporin, the FEP (6.25%), the only ATB, as previously mentioned, for which no resistance has been recorded in <italic>E. coli</italic> from broiler chicken, is a real public health problem, especially considering that turkey farming in Algeria is a very recent sector compared to broiler farming.</p><p>Gosling <italic>et a</italic>l. [<xref rid="ref75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>], working on CIP resistance in <italic>E. col</italic>i isolated from turkeys, recorded a rate of multi-resistant isolates estimated at 88.1% with resistances, 100% for both CIP and NA, 94.4% for TE, and 84.9% for AMP in Great Britain; the only result that does not agree with ours is the sensitivity of these strains to AMC (92.8%).</p><p>Our results are completely contradictory with those highlighted in France by the RESAPATH network which is a report of a decline in antimicrobial resistance and an increase in the sensitivity of <italic>E. coli</italic> strains from turkey meat to ATB; indeed, a significant increase in the proportion of susceptible isolates to CS was observed in all animal species what suggest that the spread of CS-resistant <italic>E. coli</italic> that is pathogenic for animals is under control; for TE, the sensitivity increased from 17% in 2010 to 58% in 2016, and the same thing for FLM which went from 66% in 2010 to 78% in 2016; this network also has a sensitivity state estimated at 99% for the NEO, 97% for the CF, 95% for the ENR, and 85% for the AMC [<xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. These results contradictory to ours could be explained by the rational use of the ATB, the respect of the rules of breeding allowing to minimize the diseases and, at the same time, the use of ATB and an awareness of all the actors of the poultry sector (breeder, veterinarians, and state institutions) as to the need to preserve the existing ATB capital.</p><p>The results of antimicrobial resistance we got and which are quite disturbing can be explained by several factors; the increased and uncontrolled use of ATB, sometimes by the breeder himself, who is not, under any circumstances, entitled to perform correct antibiotic therapy. Indeed, nowadays, the large availability of avian ATB on the Algerian market with affordable prices (generic drugs) facilitates the access of these molecules to breeders [<xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. The use of ATB as a preventive measure as growth promoters can also be incriminating, the non-respect of the rules of breeding such as increased density, bad hygiene, bad aeration, and the non-installation of footbath leads the appearance of pathologies involving repeated ATB therapies, in which antibiotherapy is carried out without using antibiograms in most of the time [<xref rid="ref75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Other factors, mentioned by Mateo [<xref rid="ref76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], may also influence the occurrence of resistance in poultry farms such as the decrease in the availability of ATB (poor dilution, degradation by biocides, and plugging pipettes), the decrease in consumption ATB (poor ATB taste, low number of water points, and lameness), and decreased absorption of ATB (enteritis). This phenomenon of antibioresistance can, also, be explained by the diversity of the mechanisms of resistance of bacteria [<xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2-12"><title>Antimicrobial activity of the EOs</title><p>As can be seen in Tables-<xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">6</xref> and <xref rid="T7" ref-type="table">7</xref>, the two EOs tested showed antibacterial activity against the strains tested; however, it was found that the essence of Thyme (<italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L.) had a much greater antibacterial activity than EO of Coriander (<italic>C. sativum</italic> L.). The average of the IZ recorded for the pure EO of Thyme on all the avian strains studied was estimated at 26.75&#x000b1;0.426 mm (ranging from 18.66&#x000b1;0.152 mm for the smallest IZ to 39.33&#x000b1;0.585 mm for the largest one) with CMIs ranging from 0.07 to 0.93 mg/ml; for this EO, it is noted that there is no variation between the average of the IZ of pure and diluted EO, and the same thing was observed by comparing the average of the IZ of broiler strains and those of turkeys.</p><table-wrap id="T6" position="float"><label>Table-6</label><caption><p>Antibacterial activity of the essential oils studied.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="5" valign="top" colspan="1"><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains</th><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Broiler chicken strains (average of disc diameter of inhibition (mm)&#x000b1;standard deviation)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L.</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L.</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEO</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DEO</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEO</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DEO</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.00&#x000b1;1.053</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.43&#x000b1;0.461</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.50&#x000b1;0.500</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.73&#x000b1;0.288</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.50&#x000b1;0.556</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.70&#x000b1;0.346</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.00&#x000b1;0.200</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.56&#x000b1;0.585</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.00&#x000b1;0.866</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.40&#x000b1;0.435</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.10&#x000b1;0.953</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.33&#x000b1;1.154</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.66&#x000b1;1.154</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.56&#x000b1;0.750</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.83&#x000b1;0.115</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.33&#x000b1;0.585</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.46&#x000b1;0.057</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.33&#x000b1;0.750</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.56&#x000b1;0.513</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.00&#x000b1;0.300</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.33&#x000b1;0.577</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.26&#x000b1;0.404</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.00&#x000b1;1.000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.53&#x000b1;0.635</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.50&#x000b1;0.916</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.00&#x000b1;0.173</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.70&#x000b1;0.264</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.00&#x000b1;0.200</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.53&#x000b1;0.808</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.66&#x000b1;0.665</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.80&#x000b1;0.346</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.43&#x000b1;0.378</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.36&#x000b1;0.550</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.00&#x000b1;0.100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.93&#x000b1;0.057</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.10&#x000b1;0.264</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.23&#x000b1;0.351</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.66&#x000b1;1.527</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00&#x000b1;0.173</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.70&#x000b1;0.519</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.00&#x000b1;0.173</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.56&#x000b1;0.288</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.53&#x000b1;0.404</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.80&#x000b1;0.173</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.66&#x000b1;0.152</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.53&#x000b1;0.923</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.80&#x000b1;0.346</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.76&#x000b1;0.404</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.83&#x000b1;0.115</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.90&#x000b1;1.000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.80&#x000b1;0.200</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.73&#x000b1;0.152</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.66&#x000b1;0.115</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.00&#x000b1;0.100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.50&#x000b1;0.556</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.36&#x000b1;0.550</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.00&#x000b1;0.100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.56&#x000b1;0.577</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.40&#x000b1;0.519</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.80&#x000b1;0.173</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.33&#x000b1;0.981</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.00&#x000b1;0.500</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.46&#x000b1;0.503</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.00&#x000b1;1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.26&#x000b1;0.057</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.86&#x000b1;0.251</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.00&#x000b1;1.000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.40&#x000b1;0.529</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.63&#x000b1;0.981</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.60&#x000b1;0.435</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.00&#x000b1;0.200</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.70&#x000b1;0.100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.00&#x000b1;0.200</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.80&#x000b1;0.100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.00&#x000b1;0.800</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.83&#x000b1;0.288</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.06&#x000b1;0.115</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.03&#x000b1;0.896</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.60&#x000b1;0.608</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.96&#x000b1;1.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.00&#x000b1;0.173</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.26&#x000b1;1.137</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.00&#x000b1;0.200</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.63&#x000b1;0.378</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.53&#x000b1;0.550</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.00&#x000b1;0.100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.00&#x000b1;0.264</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.00&#x000b1;0.100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.00&#x000b1;0.100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00&#x000b1;1.000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">09.83&#x000b1;0.288</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">09.63&#x000b1;0.550</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.76&#x000b1;0.611</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.13&#x000b1;1.021</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.73&#x000b1;0.461</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00&#x000b1;0.100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O.A.DDI-BCS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.72&#x000b1;0.471</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.51&#x000b1;0.589</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.21&#x000b1;0.438</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.71&#x000b1;0.444</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" valign="top" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Turkey strains (average of disc diameter of inhibition (mm)&#x000b1;standard deviation)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L.</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold><italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L.</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></td><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PEO</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>DEO</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PEO</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>DEO</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.00&#x000b1;0.888</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.33&#x000b1;0.665</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.00&#x000b1;0.173</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.00&#x000b1;0.458</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.63&#x000b1;0.378</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.50&#x000b1;0.896</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.66&#x000b1;0.550</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.60&#x000b1;0.608</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.40&#x000b1;0.360</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.66&#x000b1;0.896</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.63&#x000b1;0.873</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.00&#x000b1;0.100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.00&#x000b1;0.264</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.73&#x000b1;0.115</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.36&#x000b1;0.550</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.70&#x000b1;0.264</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.36&#x000b1;1.184</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.70&#x000b1;1.212</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.00&#x000b1;0.781</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.76&#x000b1;0.404</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.00&#x000b1;0.173</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.60&#x000b1;0.360</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.73&#x000b1;0.251</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.00&#x000b1;0.500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.16&#x000b1;0.152</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.23&#x000b1;0.709</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.50&#x000b1;0.556</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.00&#x000b1;0.866</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.33&#x000b1;0.585</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.00&#x000b1;0.173</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.00&#x000b1;0.458</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.30&#x000b1;0.458</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.46&#x000b1;0.416</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.53&#x000b1;0.461</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.63&#x000b1;0.321</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.23&#x000b1;0.305</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.86&#x000b1;0.230</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.00&#x000b1;0.400</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.73&#x000b1;0.251</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.70&#x000b1;0.624</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.00&#x000b1;0.100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.33&#x000b1;0.493</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.43&#x000b1;0.152</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.40&#x000b1;0.519</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.63&#x000b1;0.321</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.76&#x000b1;0.723</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.56&#x000b1;0.378</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.96&#x000b1;1.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.00&#x000b1;0.100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.00&#x000b1;0.100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.03&#x000b1;0.152</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00&#x000b1;0.100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.36&#x000b1;0.550</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.83&#x000b1;0.288</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.00&#x000b1;0.173</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.00&#x000b1;0.300</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.00&#x000b1;0.100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.00&#x000b1;0.754</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.63&#x000b1;0.404</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.56&#x000b1;0.585</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.66&#x000b1;0.305</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.33&#x000b1;0.152</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.00&#x000b1;0.100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.00&#x000b1;0.264</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O.A.DDI-TS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.80&#x000b1;0.382</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.78&#x000b1;0.496</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.05&#x000b1;0.383</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.57&#x000b1;0.461</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O.A.DDI-AS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.75&#x000b1;0.426</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.65&#x000b1;0.542</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.55&#x000b1;0.416</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.14&#x000b1;0.434</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCC 25922</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.60&#x000b1;0.200</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.36&#x000b1;0.208</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.33&#x000b1;0.513</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.10&#x000b1;0.173</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>PEO=Pure essential oil, DEO=Dilute essential oil in 15% of DMSO, O.A.DDI-BCS=Overall average disc diameter of inhibition for broiler chicken strains, O.A.DDI-TS=Overall average disc diameter of inhibition for turkey strains, O.A.DDI-AS=Overall average disc diameter of inhibition for all strains, DMSO=Dimethyl sulfoxide</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T7" position="float"><label>Table-7</label><caption><p>MICs of the essential oils studied.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">MIC of broiler chicken strains (mg/ml)</th></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> strains</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC T&#x003bd;EO</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC C<italic>s</italic>EO</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>MIC of turkey strains (mg/ml)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>E. coli</italic> strains</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIC T&#x003bd;EO</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIC C<italic>s</italic>EO</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCC 25922</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>MIC=Minimum inhibition concentration, T&#x003bd;EO=<italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. essential oil, C<italic>s</italic>EO=<italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L. essential oil, <italic>E. coli=Escherichia coli</italic></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>After the Thyme EO, we found, with an average of IZ estimated at 17.05&#x000b1;0.383 mm (ranging from 9.63&#x000b1;0.550 mm for the smallest zone of inhibition to 36.00&#x000b1;0.458 mm for the largest one) and MICs evaluated between 0.6 and 10 mg/ml, the EO of Coriander. The aromatograms of this EO, on all avian strains studied, expressed different results between pure and diluted EO, with an estimated difference of 2.4 mm in favor of pure EO, a difference was also noticed between the broiler and turkey strains; in fact, turkey strains displayed, for both pure and diluted EO, an average of IZ larger, with a difference of almost 1mm, compared to the broiler chicken strains. Regarding the ATCC 25922, it expressed the same result regarding the sensitivity to the EOs used; Thyme EO in the first position with a MIC estimate at 0.16 mg/ml, followed by Coriander EO which the MIC had posted at 2.5 mg/ml. The IZ was greater in pure EO for the two EOs studied; in fact, for Thyme EO, a significant difference was highlighted between an IZ of 30.60&#x000b1;0.200 mm for pure EO versus 21.36&#x000b1;0.208 mm for diluted EO, for Coriander EO, a smaller gap has been registered between an IZ of 17.33&#x000b1;0.513 mm for pure EO against 16.10&#x000b1;0.173 mm for diluted EO, this result could be explained by an antagonism between the dispersant (DMSO) and these EO [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>In the literature, several other studies have expressed results comparable to those we obtained regarding the antibacterial activity of Thyme EO [<xref rid="ref77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>-<xref rid="ref79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>] and Coriander EO [<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="ref80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] to <italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC 25922 and or multidrug-resistant <italic>E. coli</italic> strains. That said, in Egypt, a study by El-Shenawy <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="ref81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>], rather revealed an antibacterial activity of Coriander EO (IZ=20 mm) greater than that we have found, and this contradictory result can be explained by the use of different bacterial strains of <italic>E. coli</italic>, different methods for MIC determination [<xref rid="ref82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>], the composition of EO, functional groups present in active component and their synergistic interactions, varietal differences, the test method used as well as culture conditions (type and volume of broth, temperature, time of incubation, concentration, and age of inoculums) [<xref rid="ref83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>-<xref rid="ref85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>].</p><p>In sum, it can be concluded that the antimicrobial properties of EO are essentially connected to their chemical composition; the highest antibacterial activity is demonstrated by phenolic compounds such as Carvacrol, Thymol, and Eugenol [<xref rid="ref86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,<xref rid="ref87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. This would strongly explain the results we obtained; indeed, the most significant antibacterial activity reported was the one with the highest phenol levels, namely Thyme EO and its 74.40% phenolic compounds mainly represented by Carvacrol (73.03%). The mechanism of action of Carvacrol and Thymol, each on their side or in synergy, involves the disruption of the cell membrane and escape of cytoplasmic contents [<xref rid="ref88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. In <italic>E. coli</italic>, Carvacrol and Thymol provoke the depolarization and disintegration of the external membrane, liberating lipopolysaccharides and increasing the permeability of the cytoplasmic membrane [<xref rid="ref89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,<xref rid="ref90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Other studies, explaining even more the results we have obtained, rapported that, in addition to the ratio in which the main active constituents are present, the interactions between these and the minor constituents can also affect the antibacterial activity of EO; this is the case of <italic>p</italic>-cymen (whose level in Thyme were 9.99 %) which is not an efficient antimicrobial agent when used alone, but with Carvacrol and Thymol, it can potentiate the action of the EO to promoting the cytoplasmic membrane expansion and facilitating the antimicrobial action of these monoterpene phenols [<xref rid="ref90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,<xref rid="ref91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>].</p><p>As for Coriander EO, its antibacterial activity was reported by several authors [<xref rid="ref92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,<xref rid="ref93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>], this antibacterial activity can be explained by its chemical composition whose major component proved to be Linalool (60.91%) and its complex interactions with different individual components [<xref rid="ref94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>-<xref rid="ref96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>], the antibacterial activity in question would be due to disrupting bacterial cell walls, inhibiting bacterial enzyme activity and suppressing translation of certain regulatory gene products [<xref rid="ref92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. More recently, a new antimicrobial peptide, namely &#x0201c;plantaricin CS&#x0201d; with broad antibacterial activity was isolated from the coriander leaf extract [<xref rid="ref97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-4"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The present study has unfortunately confirmed the presence of an alarming ATB resistance, in Algeria, against <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> in poultry farming, it has also demonstrated, <italic>in vitro</italic>, the antimicrobial action of two EOs, the EO of Thyme and that of Coriander, with a more pronounced antibacterial activity for Thyme EO, the results obtained are promising, <italic>in vivo</italic> study is necessary to validate the possibility of the use of EOs instead of ATBs.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-5"><title>Authors&#x02019; Contributions</title><p>NM performed the fieldwork, collected the samples, isolated avian <italic>E. coli</italic> strains and determined their antimicrobial resistance profile, DH performed the aromatograms and highlighted the MICs, ND supervised the laboratory work, and LA read and approved the final manuscript. All authors have read and approved the final manuscript version.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors wish to thank the veterinarians who have contributed to this work by collecting samples; they also thank all the staff of the Regional Veterinary Laboratory of El-Tarf (LVR el-Tarf) and more specifically the Director of LVR El-Tarf: Mr. Houner and the staff of the food hygiene service. The research was funded by the first author (Narimene Mansouri) and the Laboratory Research of Epidemiologic monitoring, Health, Production, Reproduction, Experimentation and Cellular Therapy of Domestic and Wild Animals, Department of Veterinary Medicine, University of Chadli Bendjedid, El-Tarf, Algeria.</p></ack><sec id="sec1-6"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Economou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gousia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Agriculture and food animals as a source of antimicrobial-resistant bacteria</article-title><source>Infect. Drug Resist</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25878509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alloui</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennoune</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Poultry production in Algeria: Current situation and future prospects</article-title><source>World's Poult. Sci. J</source><year>2013</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>619</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fontanay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mougenot</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Duva</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of antibacterial properties of essential oils and/or of their major components</article-title><source>Hegel</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>118</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dauqan</surname><given-names>E.M.A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdullah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal and functional values of thyme (<italic>Thymus vulgaris L</italic>) Herb</article-title><source>J. Appl. Biol. Biotech</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dehimi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Speciale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saija</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahamna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Raciti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cimino</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cristani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties of Algerian <italic>Thymelaea microphylla</italic></article-title><source>Coss. And Dur. Extracts. Pharm. Mag</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><issue>47</issue><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>210</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prasanth</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravi</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Varsha</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Satyam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review on <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> traditional uses and pharmacological properties</article-title><source>Med. Aromat. Plants</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>164</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nia</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Frah</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Azoui</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insecticidal activity of three plants extracts against <italic>Myzus persicae</italic>(Sulzer, 1776) and their phytochemical screening</article-title><source>Acta Agric. Slov</source><year>2015</year><volume>105</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>267</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radaelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Weidlich</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoehne</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Flach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Costa</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ethur</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activities of six essential oils commonly used as condiments in Brazil against <italic>Clostridium perfringens</italic></article-title><source>Braz. J. Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>47</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26991289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tullio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oils and their antimicrobial activity</article-title><source>Int. J. Clin. Med. Micobiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>1</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>110</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huzar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dzi&#x00119;cio&#x00142;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wodnicka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d6;r&#x000fc;n</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00130;&#x000e7;&#x000f6;z</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000c7;i&#x000e7;ek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of hydrodistillation conditions on yield and composition of coriander (<italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L.) Essential oil</article-title><source>Pol. J. Food Nutr Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>68</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>249</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Golparvar</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadipanah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of harvest time on yield and quality of <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. Essential oil in Isfahan Province, Iran</article-title><source>Agric. Conspec. Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>79</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>118</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kulpa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wesolowska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Paula</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micropropagation and composition of essentials oils in garden thyme (<italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Not. Bot. Horti Agrobo</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>532</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>CA-SFM</collab><source>Veterinary Antibiogram of the Antibiogram Committee of the French Society of Microbiology</source><year>2015</year><date-in-citation>Last accessed on 10-02-2018</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.draaf.occitanie.agriculture.gouv.fr/IMG/pdf/casfm_vet2017_id_doc=271__cle023963.pdf">http://www.draaf.occitanie.agriculture.gouv.fr/IMG/pdf/casfm_vet2017_id_doc=271__cle023963.pdf</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boukhatem</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferhat</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kameli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saidi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Taibi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Djamel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential application of thyme (<italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L.) Essential oil as antibacterial drug in aromatherapy</article-title><source>Int. J. Innov. Appl. Stud</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1418</fpage><lpage>1431</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guinoiseau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterials from Essential Oils: Fractionation, Identification and Mode of Action</article-title><source>Doctoral thesis, University of Corsica-Pasquale Paoli, France; 2010</source><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sidali</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Brada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauconnier</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Lognay</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and antimicrobial activity of <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> essential oils from North Algeria</article-title><source>Phyto. Chem. Bio. Sub. J</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>161</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouguerra</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tine-Djebbar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Algerian <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> essential oil: Chemical composition and larvicidal activity against the mosquito <italic>Culex pipiens</italic></article-title><source>Int. J. Mosq. Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imelouane</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Amhamdi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wathelet</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ankit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khedid</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>El Bachiri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and antimicrobial activity of essential oil of thyme (<italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic>) from Eastern Morocco</article-title><source>Int. J. Agric. Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>208</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemrhari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zouhair</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>El Kahkahi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Elidrissi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Amchrouk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Elhourri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and differentiation of essential oils of Morocco's different varieties of thyme</article-title><source>Glob. J. Pure Appl. Chem. Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zantar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>El Garrouj</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chabi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Laglaoui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassani</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of harvest time on yield, chemical composition, antimicrobial and antioxidant activities of <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> and <italic>Mentha pulegium</italic> essential oils</article-title><source>Eur. J. Med. Plants</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>77</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oraby</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Borollosy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oils from some Egyptian aromatic plants as an antimicrobial agent and for prevention of potato virus Y transmission by aphids</article-title><source>Ann. Appl. Stat</source><year>2013</year><volume>58</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>103</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tchoumbougnang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jazet</surname><given-names>DPM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sameza</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Nkouaya</surname><given-names>MEG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiako</surname><given-names>FGB</given-names></name><name><surname>Amvam</surname><given-names>Z.P.H</given-names></name><name><surname>Menut</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Larvicidal activity against <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> Giles and chemical composition of essential oils from four plants cultivated in Cameroon</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Agron. Soc. Environ</source><year>2009</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nezhadali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nabavi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajabian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Akbarpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pourali</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Amini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical variation of leaf essential oil at different stages of plant growth and <italic>in vitro</italic> antibacterial activity of <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> Lamiaceae, from Iran</article-title><source>Beni-Seuf Univ. J. Appl. Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>92</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alizadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oil constituents, phenolic content and antioxidant activity in Iranian and British <italic>Thymus vulgaris L</italic></article-title><source>Int. J. Agri. Crop Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>318</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abu-Darwish</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oils yield and heavy metals content of some aromatic medicinal plants grown in Ash-Shoubak region, South of Jordan</article-title><source>Adv. Environ. Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>301</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ouis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical and Biological Study of Essential Oils of Coriander, Fennel and Parsley</article-title><source>Doctoral Thesis in Organic Chemistry</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>Algeria</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Oran 1</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Msaada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben Ta&#x000e2;rit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosni</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tammar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettaieb</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Limam</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Marzouk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of different extraction methods for the determination of essential oils and related compounds from coriander (<italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Acta Chim. Slov</source><year>2012</year><volume>59</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24061362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahba</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flavoring compounds of essential oil isolated from agriculture waste of coriander (<italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic>) Plant</article-title><source>J. Mater. Environ. Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>82</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elhassan</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of essential oils from fruits of umbelliferous crop cultivated in Sudan II <italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L. (Coriander) and <italic>Foeniculum vulgare</italic> Mill (Fennel)</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Phytochem</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>116</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizanur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashraful</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Samsun</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Aklima</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Atique</surname><given-names>U.A.K.M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.S.H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative studies on physicochemical properties and GC-MS analysis of essential oil of the three varieties of <italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> Linn</article-title><source>IJHNM</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Serio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaves-L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzarrino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Amato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo Sterzo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Paparella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of essential oils obtained from Abruzzo autochthonous plants: Antioxidant and antimicrobial activities assessment for food application</article-title><source>Foods</source><year>2018</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>19</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joujeh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kattaa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Naseh</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Joujeh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oil composition of coriander (<italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L.) fruits</article-title><source>Int. J. Comp. Soc</source><year>2018</year><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>L.F</given-names></name><name><surname>;Alloisio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornara</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>De Feo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> and <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> essential oils: Chemical composition and activity on central nervous system</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1999</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krol</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieltyka-Dadasiewicz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yield and herb quality of thymus (<italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L.) depending on harvest time</article-title><source>Turk. J. Field Crops</source><year>2015</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lax</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rota</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Loran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sotomayor</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of bioclimatic area on the essential oil composition and antibacterial activity of <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L</article-title><source>Food Control</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>468</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hazzoumi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Moustakime</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Amrani</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation in Yield and Composition of Essential Oil in <italic>Pelargonium sp</italic> During the Vegetative Stage, International Conference on Chemical, Environmental and Biological Sciences (CEBS-2015)</article-title><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>Dubai, United Arab Emirates</publisher-loc><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>135</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ndiaye</surname><given-names>EHB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gueye</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndiaye</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Diop</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Diop</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauconnier</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Lognay</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition of essential oils and hydrosols of three <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> species from Senegal <italic>Eucalyptus alba</italic> Renv <italic>Eucalyptus camaldulensis</italic> Dehnh and <italic>Eucalyptus tereticornis</italic> Hook</article-title><source>Am. J. Essent. Oils Nat. Prod</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akram</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Younis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ameer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Farooq</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanif</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative efficacy of various essential oil extraction techniques on oil yield and quality of <italic>Jasminum sambac</italic> L</article-title><source>Sci. Int</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>95</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheljazkov</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name><name><surname>Astatkie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlegel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrodistillation extraction time effect on essential oil yield, composition and bioactivity of coriander oil</article-title><source>J. Oleo Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>63</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>857</fpage><lpage>865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25132088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mhemdi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kechaou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fages</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Supercritical tuneable process for the selective extraction of fats and essential oil from coriander seeds</article-title><source>J. Food Eng</source><year>2011</year><volume>105</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>616</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anwar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Saari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physicochemical composition of hydrodistilled essential oil from coriander (<italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L.) seeds cultivated in Pakistan</article-title><source>J. Med. Plants Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>3537</fpage><lpage>3544</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crocoll</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Degenhardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Route to Thymol and Carvacrol Formation: CYP71D178-D182 from Oregano, Thyme and Marjoram</article-title><source>10<sup>th</sup> International Symposium on Cytochrome P450 Biodiversity and Biotechnology</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>MA, USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Woods Hole</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouyahya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guaouguaou</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakri</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacological activities and medicinal properties of endemic Moroccan medicinal plant <italic>Origanum compactum</italic>(Benth) and their main compounds</article-title><source>Asian Pac. J. Trop. Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>628</fpage><lpage>640</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nemati</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Barzegar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Khosravinezhad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Talebi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Reza</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and antioxidant activity of Shirazi <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> essential oil</article-title><source>Adv. Herb. Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumalan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Danciu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Obistioiu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Negrea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Poiana</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rus</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Radulov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehelean</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergistic antifungal, allelopathic and antiproliferative potential of <italic>Salvia officinalis</italic> L and <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. Essential oils</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2018</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>185</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fikry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Naser</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Salama</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and antimicrobial activity of the essential oils of selected apiaceous fruits</article-title><source>Future J. Pharm. Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>92</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Satyal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mc Feeters</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Setzer</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oil characterization of <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> from various geographical locations</article-title><source>Foods</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>70</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moghaddam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Omidbiagi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sefidkon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition of the essential oil of <italic>Tagetes minuta</italic> L</article-title><source>J. Essent. Oil Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Asmari</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Athar</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Faraidy</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Almuhaiza</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition of essential oil of <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> collected from Saudi Arabian market</article-title><source>Asian Pac. J. Trop. Biomed</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>150</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Senatore</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Monte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>De Martino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Grulova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Scognamiglio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Snoussi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Feo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on chemical composition, antimicrobial and antioxidant activities of five <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. Essential oils</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2015</year><volume>20</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>12016</fpage><lpage>12028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26140436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suraci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Postorino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Roccotelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Agosteo</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oil chemical composition and antifungal effects on <italic>Sclerotium cepivorum</italic> of <italic>Thymus capitatus</italic> wild populations from Calabria, Southern Italy</article-title><source>Rev. Bras. Farmacogn Braz. J. Pharm</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>248</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pirbalouti</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity in chemical composition and yield of essential oil from two Iranian landraces of sweet Basil</article-title><source>Genetika</source><year>2014</year><volume>46</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>426</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Zaeddi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Tom&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cal&#x000ed;n-S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burl&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbonell-Barrachina</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volatile composition of essential oils from different aromatic herbs grown in Mediterranean regions of Spain</article-title><source>Foods</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>41</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu&#x000ed;s</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Domingues</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical profiling and evaluation of antioxidant and anti-microbial properties of selected commercial essential oils: A comparative study</article-title><source>Medicines</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><issue>36</issue><fpage>36</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atti-Santos</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauletti</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciro</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pansera</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Agostini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Atti</surname><given-names>S.L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moyna</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physico-chemical evaluation of <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L. Essential oils</article-title><source>Braz. Arch. Biol. Technol</source><year>2005</year><volume>48</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1035</fpage><lpage>1039</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sriti</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachrouch</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Msaada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Aouini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boushih</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Abderraba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Limam</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mediouni</surname><given-names>B.J.J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and insecticidal activity of essential oil from coriander fruit against <italic>Tribolium castaenum Sitophilus oryzae</italic> and <italic>Lasioderma serricorne</italic></article-title><source>Int. J. Food Prop</source><year>2018</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>2833</fpage><lpage>2845</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Misharina</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of the duration and conditions of storage on the composition of the essential oil from coriander seeds</article-title><source>Appl. Biochem. Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>37</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>622</fpage><lpage>628</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>De La Fuente</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenardis</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coriander essential oil composition from two genotypes grown in different environmental conditions</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>50</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2870</fpage><lpage>2877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11982413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naghdi</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdollahi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehrafarin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghorbanpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolyat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Qaderi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghiaci</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview on two valuable natural and bioactive compounds, thymol and carvacrol, in medicinal plants</article-title><source>J. Med. Plants</source><year>2017</year><volume>16</volume><issue>63</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Falco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Roscigno</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mignola</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Taglialatela-Scafati</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Senatore</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and biological activity of essential oils of <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> L. Subsp <italic>Vulgare</italic> L. under different growth conditions</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2013</year><volume>18</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>14948</fpage><lpage>14960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24304588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehdizadeh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirbalouti</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Moghaddam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Storage stability of essential oil of cumin (<italic>Cuminum cyminum</italic> L.) as a function of temperature</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Prop</source><year>2017</year><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1742</fpage><lpage>1750</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhushan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Khurana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagaraju</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Antibiotic Resistance in Poultry Environment: Spread of Resistance from Poultry Farm to Agricultural Field</source><year>2017</year><publisher-loc>New Delhi, India</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Centre for Science and Environment</publisher-name><fpage>10</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halfaoui</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Menoueri</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bendali</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serogrouping and antibiotic resistance of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> isolated from broiler chicken with colibacillosis in center of Algeria</article-title><source>Vet. World</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>830</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28831231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulaya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouzidc</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Benameurd</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial resistance of enterobacteria isolates in Western Algeria</article-title><source>J. Appl. Environ. Biol. Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>145</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benameura</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Guemourb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammoudic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoudia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggad</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Humbletf</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Saegermang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial resistance of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> isolated from Chickens in West of Algeria</article-title><source>Int. J. Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>370</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abd El Tawab</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Abd El Aal</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>El Mazied</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Morsy</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of <italic>E. coli</italic> in broiler chickens in winter and summer seasons by application of PCR with its antibiogram pattern</article-title><source>Benha Vet. Med. J</source><year>2015</year><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>128</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manishimwe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Buhire</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Uyisunze</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Turikumwenayo</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tukei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of antibiotic resistant <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in different poultry farming systems in the Eastern Province and Kigali City of Rwanda</article-title><source>Rev. Elev. Med. Vet. Pays Trop</source><year>2017</year><volume>70</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>19</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wasyl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavaco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Aarestrup</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and characterization of cephalosporin resistance in nonpathogenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> from food-producing animals slaughtered in Poland</article-title><source>Microbial. Drug Resist</source><year>2012</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>82</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anses</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>R&#x000e9;seau D'&#x000e9;pid&#x000e9;miosurveillance de L'antibior&#x000e9;sistance des Bact&#x000e9;ries Pathog&#x000e8;nes Animales</source><year>2011</year><date-in-citation>Last accessed on 29-04-2018</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>France</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Bilan 2010, Lyon et Ploufragan-Plouzan&#x000e9;</publisher-name><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><comment>ISSN 2114-6411. Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.resapath.anses.fr">https://www.resapath.anses.fr</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anses</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>R&#x000e9;seau D'&#x000e9;pid&#x000e9;miosurveillance de L'antibior&#x000e9;sistance des Bact&#x000e9;ries Pathog&#x000e8;nes Animales</source><year>2016</year><date-in-citation>Last accessed on 29-04-2018</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>France</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Bilan 2016, Lyon et Ploufragan-Plouzan&#x000e9;</publisher-name><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><comment>ISSN 2268-6355. Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.resapath.anses.fr">https://www.resapath.anses.fr</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bodering</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndoutamia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngandol</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngakou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of antibiotics and resistance profile of isolated <italic>Salmonella</italic> spp. and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains from poultry exploitations in cities of N'Djamena and Doba in Chad</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Chem. Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1669</fpage><lpage>1684</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibior&#x000e9;sistance des Ent&#x000e9;robact&#x000e9;ries D'origine Aviaire</article-title><source>Doctoral Thesis in life Sciences Option Microbiology</source><year>2017</year><publisher-loc>Mascara, Algeria</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Universit&#x000e9;Mustapha Stambouli</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zoubair</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Benguedour</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aboussaleh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeghari</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Aouane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berrid</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Abouchouaib</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sbaibi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic resistance profile of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> of Avain origin: Broiler case in the region of grand Casablanca-Morocco</article-title><source>Am. J. Innov. Res, Appl. Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>54</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analyse Critique des Pratiques de L'antibioth&#x000e9;rapie en Elevages Avicoles</article-title><source>Graduation of Magister in Veterinary Medicine, Option Pathology, Specialty Poultry and Avian Pathology</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Constantine, Algeria</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University Mentouri</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gosling</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Clouting</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ciprofloxacin resistance in <italic>E. coli</italic> isolated from Turkeys in Great Britain</article-title><source>Avian Pathol</source><year>2012</year><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22845325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mateo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution &#x000e0;L'&#x000e9;tude de L'usage des Antibiotiques en Fili&#x000e8;res Aviaires et aux Cons&#x000e9;quences de cet Usage en Mati&#x000e9;re D'antibior&#x000e9;sistance</article-title><source>Graduation Thesis to Obtain the Rank of Veterinary Doctor</source><year>2016</year><publisher-loc>Lyon 1, France</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University Claude-Bernard</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merazi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammadi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial activity of some medicinal plants used as an avian therapy in Algeria</article-title><source>Am. J. Microbiol. Biotechnol</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>114</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mourad</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Rahman</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Elaasser</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Safwat</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity of certain medicinal plant and their essential oils on the isolated bacteria from UTI patients</article-title><source>Int. J. Adv. Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1510</fpage><lpage>1530</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borug&#x00103;</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Jianu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mi&#x0015f;c&#x00103;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gole&#x00163;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruia</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Horhat</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> essential oil: Chemical composition and antimicrobial activity</article-title><source>J. Med. Life</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25870697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000d6;zkinali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sener</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;r</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;ney</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Olgun</surname><given-names>&#x000c7;</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity and chemical composition of coriander and galangal essential oil</article-title><source>Indian J, Pharm. Educ</source><year>2017</year><volume>51</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>224</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref81"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Shenawy</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baghdadi</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Hosseiny</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity of plants essential oils against some epidemiologically relevant food-borne pathogens</article-title><source>Open Public Health J</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mith</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dure</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Delcenserie</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhiri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Daube</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Clinquart</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activities of commercial essential oils and their components against food-borne pathogens and food spoilage bacteria</article-title><source>Food Sci. Nutr</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25473498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holley</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improvement in shelf-life and safety of perishable foods by plant essential oils and smoke antimicrobials</article-title><source>Food Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>22</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>292</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref84"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seow</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuk</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant essential oils as active antimicrobial agents</article-title><source>Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr</source><year>2014</year><volume>54</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24261536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref85"><label>85</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dorman</surname><given-names>H.J.D</given-names></name><name><surname>Deans</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial agents from plants: Antibacterial activity of plant volatile oils</article-title><source>J. Appl. Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>88</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10736000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref86"><label>86</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sienkiewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00141;ysakowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pastuszka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bienias</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalczyk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The potential of use basil and rosemary essential oils as effective antibacterial agents</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2013</year><volume>18</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>9334</fpage><lpage>9351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23921795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref87"><label>87</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalemba</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunicka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial and antifungal properties of essential oils</article-title><source>Curr. Med. Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>10</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>813</fpage><lpage>829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12678685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref88"><label>88</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>RJW</given-names></name><name><surname>Skandamis</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Coote</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nychas</surname><given-names>G.J.E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A study of the minimum inhibitory concentration and mode of action of oregano essential oil, thymol and carvacrol</article-title><source>J. Appl. Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>91</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11556910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref89"><label>89</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oils: Their antibacterial properties and potential applications in foods - A review</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>94</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15246235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref90"><label>90</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarrazin</surname><given-names>SLF</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Raposo</surname><given-names>JDA</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>JKR</given-names></name><name><surname>Salimena</surname><given-names>FRG</given-names></name><name><surname>Maia</surname><given-names>J.G.S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mour&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>R.H.V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial action against foodborne microorganisms and antioxidant activity of carvacrol-rich oil from <italic>Lippia origanoides</italic> Kunth</article-title><source>Lipids Health Dis</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26552874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref91"><label>91</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ultee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennik</surname><given-names>M.H.J</given-names></name><name><surname>Moezelaar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The phenolic hydroxyl group of carvacrol is essential for action against the food-borne pathogen <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic></article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>68</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1561</fpage><lpage>1568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11916669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref92"><label>92</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name><surname>Freire</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kook</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial effect of linalool and a-terpineol against periodontopathic and cariogenic bacteria</article-title><source>Anaerobe</source><year>2012</year><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22537719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref93"><label>93</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantore</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Iacobellis</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>De Marco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Capasso</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Senatore</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity of <italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L. and <italic>Foeniculum vulgare</italic> Miller Var. Vulgare (Miller) essential oils</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>52</volume><issue>26</issue><fpage>7862</fpage><lpage>7866</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15612768</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref94"><label>94</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Telci</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dayisoylu</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Digrak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Demirtas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Alma</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of bioactivity of linalool-rich essential oils from <italic>Ocimum basilucum</italic> and <italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> varieties</article-title><source>Nat. Prod. Commun</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>969</fpage><lpage>974</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20614837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref95"><label>95</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delaquis</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazza</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of individual and mixed fractions of dill, cilantro, coriander and eucalyptus essential oils</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>74</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11929164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref96"><label>96</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Queiroz</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Domingues</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coriander (<italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L.) essential oil: Its antibacterial activity and mode of action evaluated by flow cytometry</article-title><source>J. Med. Microbiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>60</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1479</fpage><lpage>1486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21862758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref97"><label>97</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laribi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>M'Hamdi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettaieb</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coriander (<italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> L.) and its bioactive constituents</article-title><source>Fitoterapia</source><year>2015</year><volume>103</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25776008</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>