<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since ancient times, mint-based preparations have also been known to affect cognition and emotion, and have been used as restorative agents to enable to regain vigor. The oldest record on the effect that mints have on the central nervous system is attributed to Aretaeus of Cappadocia (fl. 2nd century), who advised that epileptics should take walks among acrid and aromatic herbs, such as mint and pennyroyal [
 <xref rid="B134-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. Pliny also wrote about the use of watermint to control epileptic seizure, besides it helping with hangovers [
 <xref rid="B17-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. For the latter, Marcus Terentius Varro (116 BC–27 BC), a roman scholar and writer, advised hanging garlands of pennyroyal in one’s chambers [
 <xref rid="B17-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In contrast, in the 
 <italic>Hippocratic Corpus</italic> it is written that mint should be avoided by epileptics because of its ‘pungent nature’ [
 <xref rid="B135-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>] There are also several records about using mints to treat headaches. Paulus Aegineta treated throbbing headaches and those resulting from heat exposure with pennyroyal and watermint [
 <xref rid="B33-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Galen wrote about a head compress, previously recorded by Asklepiades, but probably attributed to Nikomedes IV of Bithunia, which contained ‘sulfurwort (hog-fennel), rue, mint and other herbs in rose oil’ [
 <xref rid="B31-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Finally, some attempts have been made to use mints for psychiatric disorders. Galen also wrote about hysteria, and, among his treatments, he administered a mixture of plants, such as mint, hellebore, laudanum, belladonna extract, and valerian [
 <xref rid="B136-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>]. In Trota’s work, 
 <italic>Potio Sancti Pauli</italic>, which included horsemint, was given to treat several nervous states, including ‘epileptics, cataleptics and analeptics’ [
 <xref rid="B40-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Centuries later, Rev. Townsend tried peppermint essential oil, without much success, to treat hysterical fits [
 <xref rid="B50-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], as did John Quincy (d. 1722), the English apothecary and medical writer, with pennyroyal water [
 <xref rid="B137-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>].
</p>
