<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the present study, the administration of 4% DSS in drinking water led to the development of symptoms of ulcerative colitis (bloody diarrhea, weight loss, and shortening of the length of the colon) in all the mice in the group untreated; moreover, mice having received DSS and untreated also presented a higher DAI score and a histopathological score compared to normal mice. In this study, we showed that Combretin A and B inhibited experimental colitis, resulting in an overall attenuation of DAI inflammation, including colon length and changes in body weight. Oral administration of 4% DSS in mice causes acute colitis. Animals have shown a variety of clinical symptoms of inflammatory bowel disease, including diarrhea, bloody stools, and weight loss. A disease activity index score was used as a reliable tool to assess the extent of gastrointestinal disease in experimental DSS-induced colitis. At the end of the experimental period, clinical symptoms were more pronounced. Prednisolone used in this study as the reference drug exerts its anti-inflammatory and immunosuppressive effect by inducing the gene expression of annexin therefore which have the main function the inhibition of the phospholipase A2 enzyme with the consequence of suppressing the synthesis of prostaglandins and leukotrienes by the arachidonic acid. Prednisolone can also act on macrophages and monocytes by blocking the synthesis and release of many proinflammatory cytokines (interleukin 1 (IL-1), interleukin 6 (IL-6), and tumor necrosis factor-
 <italic>α</italic> (TNF-
 <italic>α</italic>)) [
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. In the study, prednisolone significantly reduced all the symptoms of DSS-induced colitis. However, mice treated with Combretin A and B significantly improved the clinical score, suggesting a protective effect of these compounds in this model of colitis. Histological scores indicate that treatment with Combretin A and B reduced the damage to the mucous membranes. Ultimately, the results obtained indicate that treatment with Combretin A and B effectively attenuates established colonic inflammation and has a pronounced protective effect against colitis induced by DSS in mice.
</p>
