<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig4" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Figure 4</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Wound healing, immunophenotyping, MMP9 and TIMP-1 production of scar tissue on 10
   <sup class="sup">th</sup> day after wounding in IL-10
   <sup class="sup">−/−</sup> mice and IL-10
   <sup class="sup">−/−</sup> supplemented daily with EPA-rich oil. (
   <bold class="bold">A</bold>) Wound area percentages during the experimental period in IL-10
   <sup class="sup">−/−</sup> mice (blue line) and IL-10
   <sup class="sup">−/−</sup> mice supplemented daily with EPA-rich oil (red line) (n = 5–7 animals/group). Values are expressed as mean ± SEM. The comparison between the groups was made through two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Bonferroni post-test. (
   <bold class="bold">B</bold>) Percentage of positive M2 macrophages (CD45
   <sup class="sup">+</sup>F4/80
   <sup class="sup">+</sup>CD206
   <sup class="sup">+</sup>), were quantified by flow cytometry in scar tissue harvested 10 days after wound induction. Values are expressed as mean ± SD (n = 3–4 animals/group). The comparison between the groups was made through 
   <italic class="italic">t</italic> Test and Mann Whitney posttest. (
   <bold class="bold">C</bold>) MMP9 and TIMP-1 quantification of scar tissue collected 10 days after wound induction. Values are expressed as mean ± SD (n = 5–8 animals/group). *p &lt; 0.05 indicates significant differences in relation to control and 
   <sup class="sup">#</sup>p &lt; 0.05 indicates significant differences in relation to IL-10
   <sup class="sup">−/−</sup>. (
   <bold class="bold">D</bold>) Representative photomicrographs of skin stained with picrosirius and hematoxylin. The examination without (left) and with (right) polarized light revealed the organization and heterogeneity of collagen fiber orientation, squamous stratified epithelium (asterisk) and bulbs of the hair follicles (black arrowhead) and sebaceous glands (white arrowhead) in 21
   <sup class="sup">st</sup> day after lesion induction (n = 2–5 animals/group). Scale bar = 50 µm.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_45508_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e911" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
