<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0050">In the present investigation, as larvicides essential oil of 
 <italic>M. piperita</italic> (leaves), 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulb), 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> (leaves), 
 <italic>O. sanctum</italic> (leaves), 
 <italic>C. grandis</italic> (peels) and 
 <italic>C. grandis</italic> (leaves) are found to be highly effective against the target species. However, treated larvae are found to be moderately responsive to the oil of 
 <italic>C. aurantifolia</italic> (leaves), 
 <italic>C. linearis</italic> (leaves), 
 <italic>A. marmelos</italic> (leaves), 
 <italic>E. maculata</italic> (leaves), 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> (leaves) and 
 <italic>L. alba</italic> (leaves). Treated adults are found as highly responsive toward the oils of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs), 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> (peels), 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs), 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels), 
 <italic>E. maculata</italic> (leaves) respectively but with higher LD50 dose in comparison to larvae. The result of the current study revealed that in some cases, the same plant essential oil acted differently against the different developmental stages of the same target species, 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic>. These differential toxic effects might be due to their difference in the levels of penetration and persistence in different life stages of 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Sarma et al., 2019</xref>). However, in some other cases, the same plant oil is found effective against both the larval and adult stages and therefore such oils can be applied to control this mosquito species irrespective of their developmental stages. In the present investigation, the larval and adult stages of the target species are found to be vulnerable to 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs) oil. The larvicidal activity of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs) oil is in conformity with the findings of 
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Muturi et al. (2018)</xref> where they observed biocidal activity of the garlic oil against 
 <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> and mentioned the constituent compound, allyl disulfide as the responsible factor. It seems that garlic oil is comparatively less volatile because it contains constituent molecules having higher weight with thiol groups than commonly occurring terpene compounds of other essential oils and thereby strongly affecting every developmental stage of the target species due to its high persistence
 <bold>.</bold> Like 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs) oil, 
 <italic>E. maculata</italic> (leaves) oil is also found toxic against larvae and adults of the target species. The reported major constituents of the 
 <italic>E. maculata</italic> (leaves) oil are eucalyptol and eudesmol which are individually found to be effective against 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> in earlier studies (
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Sarma et al., 2019</xref>) and the same compounds may be responsible for the biocidal activity of the oil against the life stages of 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic> in the present case. In our previous study, we have reported 
 <italic>C. grandis</italic> (peels) oil as potent larvicide for the first time against 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic>, where eudesmol, nootkatone etc. are found as the major constituent compounds which may be the possible factors for its toxicity against larvae (
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Mahanta et al., 2017</xref>). Besides these, 
 <italic>C. grandis</italic> (leaves) and 
 <italic>C. aurantifolia</italic> (leaves) oils are also found as effective larvicides in the current study. Two of the selected plant oils namely 
 <italic>M. piperita</italic> (leaves) and 
 <italic>O. sanctum</italic> (leaves) oils are found efficient only against the larval stage of the target species. The presence of aromatic rings and both the endocyclic and exocyclic double bonds in its constituent profiles [limonene and carvone in 
 <italic>M. piperita</italic> (leaves) and eugenol and methyl eugenol in 
 <italic>O. sanctum</italic> (leaves)] may play the pivotal role for the larvicidal effect (
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Sarma et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Pandey et al., 2013</xref>). Moreover, the 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> (leaves) oil is found as a strong larvicidal agent with LC50 value of 22.18 ppm against 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic> for the first time in our investigation. Earlier it was reported as potent ovicide and larvicide against 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> and 
 <italic>Anopheles</italic> mosquitoes respectively (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Dosoky and Setzer, 2018</xref>). Sabinene, beta-ocimene, gamma-terpinene, beta pinene etc. are some of the reported major constituents of this oil which may be responsible for the strong larvicidal activity of the plant oil (
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Paoli et al., 2016</xref>). Moreover, 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil is also found as an adulticide for the first time in our investigation which may be due to the activity of its constituent compounds like limonene, linalool, pinene etc (
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Ivoke et al., 2013</xref>). In addition to 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs) and 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oils, 
 <italic>A. marmelos</italic> (leaves) and 
 <italic>C. aurantifolia</italic> (peels) oils are also found to act as adulticides but with relatively higher LD50 dose in comparison to their early life stage.
</p>
