<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0065">In the current study, after applying the prepared binary mixtures, we observed synergistic interaction with a high percentage of observed larval mortality in most of the cases. A total of 83 numbers of mixtures are found to act synergistically against the treated larvae. Interestingly, 100% observed mortality is recorded in case of 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> (leaves) oil-based binary mixtures-treated larvae. It is for the first time we have reported the 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> (leaves) oil as a strong candidate against the larval stage of the filarial vector. The major as well as the minor compounds present in this essential oil may act cumulatively to induce the activity of the other plant oils present in the mixture. The possible explanation for the increased toxicity of binary mixtures would be that one candidate might have interfered with the enzymatic detoxification of the second one, thereby enhancing its total toxicity (
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Perumalsamy et al., 2012</xref>). The garlic oil-based combinations are also found to have synergistic interaction against the larval stage of the target species. The variety of major constituent compounds like sulfur compounds (from the garlic oil), monoterpenes or monoterpenoides (limonene, carvone, eugenol, nootkatone etc. from 
 <italic>Citrus</italic>, 
 <italic>Mentha</italic>, 
 <italic>Ocimum</italic> oils) may share different mode of action and thereby increasing its final lethal activities (
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Pavela, 2015</xref>). At 1:1 volume ratio, out of 21 numbers, only two combinations i.e. 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ 
 <italic>M. piperita</italic> (leaves) and 
 <italic>O. sanctum</italic> (leaves)+ 
 <italic>M. piperita</italic> (leaves) are found to act antagonistically which may be due to the same mode of actions of the constituent compounds present in the candidate oils. Such kind of antagonism can be supported by the findings of 
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Sarma et al. (2019)</xref> where they mentioned the antagonistic interaction between carvone [one of the major constituents of 
 <italic>M. piperita</italic> (leaves) oil] and the sulfur compound [one of the major constituents of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs) oil]. However, the antagonistic effect observed in case of 
 <italic>O. sanctum</italic> (leaves)+ 
 <italic>M. piperita</italic> (leaves) mixture treated larvae has a disagreement with the results reported in their investigations as the mixtures of eugenol [one of the constituents of 
 <italic>O. sanctum</italic> (leaves) oil] with carvone as well as limonene have manifested synergism against the larval stages of 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic>. The antagonistic interaction may be due to the involvement of some other minor constituent compounds present in 
 <italic>O. sanctum</italic> (leaves) and 
 <italic>M. piperita</italic> (leaves) plant essential oils. In other volume ratios of these two combinations whenever the amount of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> and 
 <italic>O. sanctum</italic> oils are increased, the mixtures have shown synergistic activities. From this an assertion could be made that the 
 <italic>Mentha</italic> oil is not so effective in combination though it is found to be the most effective one when tested alone. Finally, the most effective binary combination proposed in the current study against the larval stage is 1:1 volume ratio of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> (leaves). The co-activity of the monoterpenes [major constituents of 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> (leaves) oil and organosulfur compounds major constituents of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs) oil] may lead to the synergy in the larval stages of 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic>.
</p>
