<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0070">The susceptibility status of the adult stage of 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic> towards the prepared binary mixtures is also studied in the present investigation. Most of the combinations of 1:1 volume ratio has shown synergistic effect except the mixtures of essential oil of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ 
 <italic>A. marmelos</italic> (leaves); 
 <italic>A. marmelos</italic> (leaves)+ 
 <italic>E. maculata</italic> (leaves) and 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels)+ 
 <italic>E. maculata</italic> (leaves). Similarly, at 1:3 volume ratio, when the volume of 
 <italic>E. maculata</italic> (leaves) oil is increased upto three times than its original LC10 concentration, 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> (peels)+ 
 <italic>E. maculata</italic> (leaves) mixture is found to possess synergism. However, 
 <italic>A. marmelos</italic> (leaves)+ 
 <italic>E. maculata</italic> (leaves) mixture is not able to act synergistically despite the testing of its different volume ratios against the adult individuals. The synergistic interaction with 100% observed mortality is recorded in case of the mixture of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil mixture. However, 1:3 and 3:1 volume ratios of these mixtures are found to show no effect. From such findings, a conclusion can be drawn that the mixtures may act synergistically at an optimum volume ratio of the particular essential oil present in the mixture. Below or above the volume range, they may lose their synergistic interaction. Moreover, the mixture of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ 
 <italic>E. maculata</italic> (leaves) and 
 <italic>A. marmelos</italic> (leaves)+ 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil mixtures are also found to act synergistically only at 1:1 volume ratio. These oils may act at different target sites for which synergism occurs. The minor compounds may also interact due to which synergistic effect is observed even at the LC10/LD10 concentration/dose. Some of the 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil-based combinations like 1:1 volume ratio of 
 <italic>A. marmelos</italic> (leaves)+ 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) and 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil mixtures are found to possess synergism. The co-toxicity of different major constituents viz. sulfur compounds from 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs), limonene from 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil, beta-terpinyl acetate from 
 <italic>A. marmelos</italic> (leaves) oil with different mode of actions may be the possible reason for their synergistic interaction. Against the adult stage, 1:1 volume ratio of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil mixture is considered as the most effective combination.
</p>
