<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0080">In the current study, GC-MS analysis is carried out to highlight the constituent profile of the two most effective binary mixtures i.e. 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulb) + 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> (leaves) and 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs) + 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels). The nature and the structure of the constituent compounds like the presence of hydrocarbon chains besides a phenyl ring, and exocyclic double bonds are some of the responsible factors for the efficacy of essential oil constituents (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Benelli et al., 2017a</xref>). Here, the constituent profile has shown the presence of diallyl trisulfide, diallyldisulfide, beta citronellol, ocimene as probable major compounds in 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs) + 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) combination. Again, in the mixture of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs) + 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> (leaves), probable major constituents are diallyldisulfide, citronellal, diallyltrisulfide, caryophyllene oxide, linalool. 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Deng et al. (2020)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Sarma et al. (2019)</xref> proposed the chemical composition of 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> and 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> essential oil where they found some of the compounds similar (like ocimene, linalool, citronellal, caryophyllene oxide for 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> and diallyldisulfide, diallyltrisulfide for 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> respectively) to our findings in this investigation. Most of the probable major constituents of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs) + 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> (leaves) oil mixture viz. sulfur compounds, citronellal, linalool is found to possess no effect in binary combinations as proposed by 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Pavela (2015)</xref>. Therefore, it is important to mention that other major compounds of this particular mixture viz. caryophyllene oxide may be responsible for its synergistic effect along with some other minor constituents. Moreover, caryophyllene oxide is already reported as a larvicidal compound by some of the authors against mosquitoes (
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Hung et al., 2019</xref>). One of the major compounds of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs) + 
 <italic>C. paradisi</italic> (leaves) combination, linalool was found to exhibit less larvicidal activity against 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic> which was established by 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Benelli et al. (2017b)</xref>. They stated that the insecticidal activity of an essential oil depends not only on its main molecules, but it is an interaction among all the constituent components. Here in the present case, linalool may act as a synergist whenever present in mixture with some other compounds against 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic> larvae. Moreover, the major constituent compounds present in the 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs) + 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) mixture like sulfur compounds, citronellol, ocimene, terpinyl acetate are already found to be reported to possess insecticidal activities against different pests including mosquitoes (
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Chu et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Bossou et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">Tabari et al., 2017</xref>). In these combinations, if we consider the area percentages of the constituents, sulfur compounds and monoterpenes occupy maximum areas and therefore an assumption can be made that the presence of these two types of constituent compounds may be responsible for their synergistic interaction even at a low concentration against 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic>.
</p>
