<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">
 <italic>Glycyrrhiza uralensis</italic> Fisch. is one of the most important medicinal plants in China because of its commercial value and patronage. Wild 
 <italic>Glycyrrhiza uralensis</italic> Fisch. resources usually grow in arid, semiarid and saline regions and therefore have the ability to adapt to saline conditions. Due to excessive excavation and habitat destruction in recent years, wild resources of Chinese herbal medicines are very limited in nature. Overharvesting has gradually exhausted wild resources, and cultivated 
 <italic>G. uralensis</italic> has become an alternative source
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. However, practices and studies have indicated that the salt tolerance of cultivated 
 <italic>G. uralensis</italic> is lower than that of wild plants
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>G. uralensis</italic> cultivation is widely distributed in arid and semiarid desert steppes and edges and loess of hilly regions and environments
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. The growth and development of the plant is inhibited by the inherent soil salinity associated with these areas. Enhancing the salt tolerance of 
 <italic>G. uralensis</italic> in artificial cultivation systems remains a challenge that calls for urgent solutions. Considering the vital role of C and N metabolism in the plant stress response and management, this research seeks to elucidate the effect of Si on the contents of C and N metabolites, activities, and key enzymes (GS, NR, SS, and SPS) under NaCl stress and comprehensively analyze their relationship to C and N metabolism. This research also seeks to explore the role of Si in the metabolic pathways underlying salt-tolerance mechanisms to provide a scientific basis for the salt tolerance of 
 <italic>G. uralensis</italic> under artificial cultivation with high growth and yield components for sustainable development.
</p>
