<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the family Brassicaceae, both floral (Deng and Hu 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1995</xref>; Davis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1986</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1998</xref>) and extrafloral (Mathur et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2013</xref>) nectaries have been reported. Floral nectaries are outgrowths of the receptacle located between the sepals and stamens in the region of filament bases (Frei 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1955</xref>; Fahn 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1979a</xref>). As a result, floral insect visitors collecting nectar often inadvertently pick up and disperse pollen. Floral nectaries of crucifers vary in their morphology, size and distribution. There are four nectary types based on number and distribution of the organs: (1) annular—a continuous zone of nectarial tissue around the receptacle, e.g. 
 <italic>Dentaria</italic> sp. and 
 <italic>Sisymbrium loeselii</italic>; (2) two-nectary type—two opposing nectaries at the flower base, e.g. 
 <italic>Hesperis matronalis</italic> and 
 <italic>Matthiola bicornis</italic>; (3) four-nectary type—made up of two pairs of nectaries classified as lateral (associated with the short stamens) and median (external to the long stamens) as in 
 <italic>Brassica</italic>, 
 <italic>Sinapis</italic> and 
 <italic>Raphanus</italic>; and (4) eight-nectary type—two pairs of lateral and two pairs of median nectaries, e.g. 
 <italic>Lobularia maritima</italic> (Norris 1941, cit. in Davis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1996</xref>; Clemente Muñoz and Hernández Bermejo 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1978</xref>; Davis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1998</xref>). The pairs of lateral and median nectaries vary with respect to their secretory activity as well as vascularization (Davis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1986</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1998</xref>). In general, the lateral nectaries produce most of a flower’s nectar and total nectar carbohydrates (Eisikowitch 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">1981</xref>; Davis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1986</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1996</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1998</xref>; Masierowska 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2003</xref>). Brassicaceae nectaries are composed of three types of tissues: (1) epidermal tissue, (2) parenchyma and (3) vascular tissue. The vascular tissue is composed of phloem alone (e.g. Frei 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1955</xref>, Fahn 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1979a</xref>, Davis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1986</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1998</xref>). Modified stomata are the way of nectar exudation (Davis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1998</xref>, Masierowska 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2003</xref>).
</p>
