<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Initiatives have been taken in the USA to promote the acquisition of fresh fruit and vegetables from farmers markets and urban agriculture/horticulture initiatives such as the San Francisco Urban Agriculture Alliance (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sfuaa.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.sfuaa.org/</ext-link>). The diversity of products grown through such initiatives is important for their commercial success, but also key to diets being able to supply all of the health-protecting compounds that plants can provide in the diet. Similar initiatives are being championed in developing countries stimulated by the promotion of cultivation and consumption of a diverse selection of indigenous fruit and vegetables. A good example is the promotion of traditional greens in Kenya which have gained significant popularity over the past 5 years and are more nutritious than introduced greens such as kale, being richer in vitamins (A, C, E, folate), calcium and soluble fibre (
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cernansky, 2015</xref>). In an ideal situation we would be able to compare the relative benefits of consuming local greens such as African nightshade (
 <italic class="italic">Solanum scabrum</italic>) to introduced greens such as kale (
 <italic class="italic">Brassica oleracea</italic>) using local, nutritional information. Currently, there is access to nutrient composition data, for example through the USDA Food Composition Databases (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ndb.nal.usda.gov/ndb/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://ndb.nal.usda.gov/ndb/</ext-link>) or McCance and Widdowson’s The Composition of Foods integrated dataset and those for other European countries, accessible through the EUROFir Hub (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eurofir.org/food-information/food-composition-databases-2" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.eurofir.org/food-information/food-composition-databases-2</ext-link>). However, information is often limited to major global commodity products and does not include local or indigenous crop varieties. Access to such databases is also often subject to a subscription, making use by the interested consumer practically impossible.
</p>
