<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Fan et al. [
 <xref rid="B89-molecules-24-02055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>] studied the effects of different carbon nanopowders on the thermal conductivity and energy storage performance of paraffin-based nanocomposite phase-change energy storage materials. These include long and short MWCNTs, carbon nanofibers, and graphene nanoplatelets (GNPs). The reported the use of planar graphene nanoflakes (GNPs) to overcome the low-thermal interface resistance of paraffin-based PCMs. Among the four types of carbon fillers, the relative performance of GNPs was increased by 164% at a load of 5 wt% due to the two-dimensional (2D) planar structure, which reduced the thermal interface resistance of the filler/substrate. Xiang et al. [
 <xref rid="B95-molecules-24-02055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>] investigated the thermal and electrical conductivities of GNP nanocomposites with two sizes and aspect ratios of peeled graphite nanoplates mixed with paraffin wax. They found that when the aspect ratio of the nanoplates was large and their orientation was good, the interface density of the nano-filler was low, and the thermal conductivity and thermal stability of the nanocomposite could be increased. The paraffin wax and exfoliated graphite nanoplates (xGNPs) interacted through van der Waals forces. Discrete singular convolution (DSC) analysis of paraffin nanocomposites with low xGNP concentrations demonstrated that the two peaks corresponding to the melting and crystallization enthalpy of the paraffin wax were not considerably affected by the addition of xGNP particles. In addition, the thermal and chemical inertness of xGNP and the interaction of the xGNP particles with the surrounding matrix enhanced the overall stability of the composite PCM. Comparing the effects of xGNP and graphene on the thermophysical properties of PCM composites, it was found that the graphene-containing composites had lower electroosmotic flow thresholds, and the paraffin conductivity was much higher than that of xGNP-containing composites. However, the thermal conductivity was lower [
 <xref rid="B94-molecules-24-02055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>].
</p>
