<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0125">At present, the emergence of synthetic oral anti-diabetic inhibitors has improved the performance in the management of DM, and its multifaceted complications as well as susceptibility to infections. But the regular use of these inhibitors comes with diluted effects. The present study revealed a protective efficacy of 
 <italic>P. granatum</italic> fruits peel extracts against chronic hyperglycemia-induced oxidative stress linked to DM, thereby suggesting an approach to ameliorate its potential burden through the antioxidant application. In the antioxidant traits, aqueous and ethanolic extracts showed varied ranges of DPPH scavenging activities. The present findings agreed with the reports of 
 <xref rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr">Venkatadri et al. (2017)</xref> who illustrated pronounced degradation of DPPH at disparate concentrations of the extracts. However, this investigation uncovered that aqueous extract elicited the potent antioxidant activity, linking the fact that active phytochemicals of 
 <italic>P. granatum</italic> fruits peel are readily dissolved in an aqueous medium. Plants rich in phytoconstituents, such as alkaloids, saponins, flavonoids, and phenols have been marked to protect the human body from free radicals, improves the normal metabolism of aerobic cells, and confer strong antioxidant defence mechanisms (
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Oboh et al., 2014</xref>). In this investigation, the DPPH degrading potential of aqueous extract suggests the availability of many hydroxyl groups in the structure of saponins as contained in the aqueous extract than ethanolic, acetone, chloroform, and petroleum ether extracts responsible for the enhancement of antioxidant activity in DM (
 <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Elekofehinti, 2015</xref>). Hydrogen peroxide deactivates enzymes by the oxidation of essential thiol (-SH) groups and reacts with Fe
 <sup>2+</sup> similar to Cu
 <sup>2+</sup> ions for forming hydroxyl radicals (
 <xref rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr">Venkatadri et al., 2017</xref>). In this study, 
 <italic>P. granatum</italic> peel extracts showed moderate scavenging of H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> which might be due to glycosides found in the extracts.
</p>
