<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mutagenicity assay was performed following the plate incorporation method with the histidine-requiring 
 <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> mutant TA98 and TA100 strains purchased by Molecular Toxicology Inc. (Boone, NC, USA; moltox.com). All strains (100 µL per plate of fresh overnight cultures) were checked with and without the addition of 0.5 mL of a 5% S9 exogenous metabolic activator (S9 mix). The lyophilized post-mitochondrial supernatant S9 mix (Aroclor 1254-induced, Sprague–Dawley male rat liver in 0.154 M KCl solution), commonly used for the activation of pro-mutagens to mutagenic metabolites (Molecular Toxicology, Inc., Boone, NC, USA) was stored at −80 °C before use. The concentration tested for all the samples were 5, 10, 20, 50, and 100 µL/plate of a stock solution 50 mg/mL. An amount of 0.5 mL of phosphate buffer or S9 mix for assays with metabolic activation was added to 2 mL molten top agar (0.6% agar, 0.6% NaCl, 0.5 mM L-histidine/biotin solution) at 46 °C, together with 0.1 mL of each sample solution at different concentrations, and 0.1 mL of fully-grown culture of the appropriate tester strain. The ingredients were thoroughly mixed and poured onto minimal glucose agar plates (1.5% agar in 2% Vogel–Bonner medium E with 5% glucose solution). DMSO was used as a negative control (100 µL/plate). Positive controls were prepared as follows: 2-aminoanthracene (2 µg/plate) for both strains with metabolic activation a 2-nitrofluorene (2 µg/plate) and sodium azide (2 µg/plate) for TA98 and TA100 without metabolic activator, respectively. The plates were incubated at 37 °C for 72 h and then the his+ revertants were checked and counted using a Colony Counter 560 Suntex (Antibioticos, Italy). A sample was considered mutagenic when the observed number of colonies was at least twofold over the spontaneous level of revertants [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-00084" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. All determinations were made in triplicate.
</p>
