<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As introduced in 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot3-molecules-24-00363" class="xref">Section 3.3</xref>. Characterization, the mass of every DSC sample was controlled at 5ߝ10 mg, which was much less than the mass of PCM used in the industry. Note that the sample amount, heating rate, sample compositions would interfere in the DSC signal [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. In order to avoid the influence of small sample amount on PCM solidification temperature measurement, the measurement of T-history or cooling curve was widely used to determine the supercooling degree of PCM samples [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-24-00363" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. Therefore, the crystallization properties of the mixture samples in this work were characterized by measuring their cooling curves. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-00363-f011" class="xref">Figure 11</xref> shows a schematic diagram of the experimental setup, which consists of a thermostatic silicone oil bath box and a thermal energy storage (TES) unit. The silicone-oil bath could control the temperature automatically with an accuracy of ±0.01 °C. And the TES unit used a cylindrical glass container with an inner diameter of 25 mm, a wall thickness of 1 mm and a length of 200 mm to place the sample. As shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-00363-f011" class="xref">Figure 11</xref>, a K-type thermocouple was placed at the center of the cylindrical glass container to monitor the temperature change of each sample with a measurement error of ±0.1°C. Moreover, the test points were at the same depth (20 mm away from bottom of the container) in different tests, to make sure the effects of input heat flux from top and bottom on them were identical. On the other hand, two-third of the volume of the container was filled with the test sample, and the remaining space was left to adapt to the thermal expansion of the PCM. During the measurement, the TES unit was put into the oil bath and heated/cooled with the following program. Firstly, the oil was heated at a rate of 1 °C/min from the room temperature to the specified temperature (80 °C for mixtures, 105 °C for NH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>Al(SO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>)
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·12H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O/KAl(SO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>)
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·12H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O and 135 °C for MgCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·6H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O). Secondly, the thermostatic silicone oil bath box was maintained at the specified temperature for 2 h until the samples completely melted. Finally, the oil was cooled down to 30 °C at a rate of 1 °C/min. At the same time, temperature data in the experiment was collected using a data logger (Agilent 34970A, Santa Clara, CA, USA).
</p>
