<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As shown, for this oil, phenylpropanoids form the backbone of the characterized compounds. The richness of 
 <italic>P. cubeba</italic> fruit’s essential oil on phenylpropanoids, which are chemically a group of compounds derived from the carbon skeleton of phenylalanine, implicated in plant defense, structural support, and the survival of plants, have been widely reported for their anticonvulsant, analgesic, antidiabetic, and anti-inflammatory potential [
 <xref rid="B24-plants-09-01534" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Furthermore, they have shown application in the food, pharmaceuticals, cosmetics, textiles, biofuel, and sensors [
 <xref rid="B24-plants-09-01534" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Macchia et al. [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-01534" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] have indicated that methyl eugenol is formed through cyclic acid pathways, with phenylalanine as precursor; however, eugenol will be formed under a few reaction stages. Eugenol is then converted easily to methyl eugenol via a methyl donor from sadenosylmethionine (SAM) and enzymatic activity from O-methyltransferase (OMT) [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-09-01534" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Binu et al. [
 <xref rid="B27-plants-09-01534" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] showed that treatment with eugenol improved the peroxidation of the membrane and restored normal heart rate. Also, histological examination of the cardiac segments has confirmed the beneficial role of eugenol against arsenic-induced oxidative damage. Eugenol has been reported to possess a large spectrum of activity, including antitumor, anti-inflammatory, analgesic, antibacterial, antifungal, anesthetic, and antipyretic potency [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-09-01534" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-plants-09-01534" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-09-01534" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-plants-09-01534" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-plants-09-01534" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-plants-09-01534" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-plants-09-01534" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].
</p>
