<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Mediterranean diet is characterised by high intake of non-refined grains, legumes, and a large diversity of fresh vegetables and fruits daily; yogurt and milk are consumed only a few times per week; there is reduced intake of fish and seafood, eggs, white meat and high fat dairy products (a few times per week); red meat is consumed only a few times per month; alcohol intake is also minimised; dietary lipids are mainly derived from olive oil [
 <xref rid="B277-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">277</xref>]. Epidemiological studies and randomized clinical trials have shown that consumption of a Mediterranean diet bestows protective effects against several diseases, including obesity, diabetes, hypertension, cardiovascular disease, stroke, numerous cancers, allergic diseases, as well as Parkinson’s and Alzheimer’s disease (recently reviewed by Tosti et al. [
 <xref rid="B278-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">278</xref>]). Based on evidence to date, Tosti et al. [
 <xref rid="B278-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">278</xref>] concluded that the health benefits of the Mediterranean diet are due to its lipid-lowering effects, protection provided against inflammation, oxidative stress and platelet aggregation, modulation of growth factors and hormones involved in cancer pathogenesis, inhibition of nutrient sensing pathways by specific amino acid restriction and gut microbiota metabolites which influence host metabolic health. Indeed, the accumulating evidence suggests that the Mediterranean diet modulates gut microbiota composition and functionality resulting in microbiome and metabolome which differs from that of the Western diet and reduces risk of disease. For example, consumption of the Mediterranean diet for one year by obese men (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 20) significantly decreased the genera 
 <italic class="italic">Prevotella</italic> and increased 
 <italic class="italic">Roseburia</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Oscillospira</italic> [
 <xref rid="B279-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">279</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Roseburia</italic> is a known butyrate-producer with immune maintenance and anti-inflammatory properties [
 <xref rid="B280-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">280</xref>] and 
 <italic class="italic">Oscillospira</italic> is positively associated with leanness and health [
 <xref rid="B281-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">281</xref>]. Long-term consumption of the diet also increased the abundance of 
 <italic class="italic">Parabacteroides distasonis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B279-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">279</xref>], a strain recently shown to block colon tumor formation in high fat diet-fed azoxymethane-treated mice [
 <xref rid="B282-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">282</xref>]. Faecal metabolite changes linked to amino acid, peptide and sphingolipid metabolism were reported on the Mediterranean diet and an improvement in insulin sensitivity was noted [
 <xref rid="B279-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">279</xref>]. The same group investigated the effect of chronic consumption of the Mediterranean diet for 2 years in obese patients with severe metabolic disease (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 33), obese patients without metabolic dysfunction (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 32) and non-obese subjects (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 41) [
 <xref rid="B283-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">283</xref>]. Obese patients with severe metabolic disease showed a marked dysbiosis in their gut microbiota which was reversed following consumption of the Mediterranean diet; furthermore, there was a significant reduction in plasma triglyceride levels and a trend for glucose depletion in the same group. In this case, consumption of the Mediterranean diet for two years increased the abundance of 
 <italic class="italic">Bacteroides</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Prevotella</italic> which make up the Bacteriodetes phylum, which has previously been reported to be reduced in obese people [
 <xref rid="B228-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">228</xref>]. In addition, genera with saccharolytic activity, including 
 <italic class="italic">Faecalibacterium</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Roseburia</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ruminococcus</italic> were also increased. Interestingly, such changes were not observed for non-obese individuals or obese individuals without metabolic syndrome. De Filippis et al. [
 <xref rid="B284-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">284</xref>] reported that adherence to the Mediterranean diet in a cohort of Italian individuals (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 153) was associated with increased levels of faecal SCFAs which correlated with enrichment of members of Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes. In contrast, low adherence to the diet (particularly observed in omnivores) was associated with increased levels of urinary TMAO which correlated with L-
 <italic class="italic">Ruminococcus</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">Ruminococcus</italic> genus assigned to 
 <italic class="italic">Lachnospiraceae</italic> family). Interestingly, the mucin-degrading bacterium 
 <italic class="italic">Ruminococcus torques</italic> has been shown to be increased in transgenic mice representative of Crohn’s disease and receiving a high fat/high sugar Western diet [
 <xref rid="B285-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">285</xref>]. These mice had decreased mucus layer thickness and increased intestinal permeability. Higher adherence to the Mediterranean diet in a Spanish cohort (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 74) was also associated with higher levels of 
 <italic class="italic">Clostridium</italic> cluster XVIa and 
 <italic class="italic">F. prausnitzii</italic> [
 <xref rid="B286-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">286</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Clostridium</italic> cluster XVIa contains the 
 <italic class="italic">Blautia coccoides</italic> group which are known butyrate producers [
 <xref rid="B287-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">287</xref>], are involved in secondary bile acid production [
 <xref rid="B288-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">288</xref>], as well as in the formation of T-regulatory cells [
 <xref rid="B289-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">289</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">F. prausnitzii</italic> is now recognised as one of the most abundant butyrate producers in the human gut microbiota and has anti-inflammatory properties [
 <xref rid="B194-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">194</xref>]. Interestingly, Mitsou et al. [
 <xref rid="B290-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">290</xref>] reported that fast food consumption in an adult population resulted in a microbiota with suppressed representation of 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> and butyrate-producing bacteria while adherence to the Mediterranean diet led to lower faecal 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> counts, a higher 
 <italic class="italic">Bifidobacterium</italic>: 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> ratio and greater molar ratio of acetate (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 120). The study also reported increased levels and prevalence of 
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic> due to the Mediterranean diet which the authors suggest could be linked to the ingestion of foodstuffs that are carriers of yeast. Overall, the studies presented here strongly indicate that increased SCFA production as a result of gut microbiota modulation on the Mediterranean diet plays a key role in its beneficial health effects. 
</p>
