<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">
 <italic>Megachile</italic> (
 <italic>Callomegachile) sculpturalis</italic> Smith, 1853, one of hundreds of species amongst 
 <italic>Megachile</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], is the first translocated bee species to become established in Europe. 
 <italic>Megachile sculpturalis</italic> is a protandric wild bee with an active season from June to mid-September in Europe [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Males body size ranges between 12 and 22 mm, and females between 20 and 28 mm. Both sexes are characterized by their narrow body, bright orange hairy thorax hair and dusky wings (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. 
 <italic>Megachile sculpturalis</italic> is a cavity-nesting wild bee using preexisting holes in wood. The species naturally occurs in East-Asia (Japan, China, South-Korea and Taiwan), but was first established outside its native range in the eastern USA around 1994, and is now considered as invasive species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Although it is classified as a pollen generalist, this polylectic species presents a strong preference for pollen of 
 <italic>Styphnolobium japonicum</italic> and 
 <italic>Ligustrum</italic> sp. in Europe. Both plants are native to Asia and often used as ornamental plants in human habitats [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The bee species shows aggressive behavior towards the local bee fauna from time to time, and events of direct evictions have been observed in the US and in Europe [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. A recent study detected a negative correlation between its presences in trap nests and the emergence of native bee species raising the question of the magnitude of the impact of 
 <italic>M. sculpturalis</italic> on the local bee populations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].
</p>
