<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">
 <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> is a wonder plant with over 500 chemical entities (Radwan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">2009</xref>) including over 100 phytocannabinoids and 120 terpenes (Calvi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2018</xref>), of which less than 30 biosyntheses have been characterized (Booth and Bohlmann 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2019</xref>). Phytocannabinoids are divided into 10 subclasses, i.e., cannabigerol, cannabichromene, cannabidiol, (−)-
 <italic>trans</italic>-Δ
 <sup>9</sup>-tetrahydrocannabinol, cannabicyclol, cannabielsoin, cannabinol, cannabitriol, and miscellaneous (Brenneisen 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>). There has been also a new phytocannabinoid identified which is called Δ9-tetrahydrocannabiphorol (Δ9-THCP) (Citti et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2019</xref>). Recently, the molecular pharmacology of the seven most phytocannabinoids (namely Δ9-tetrahydrocannabinol, Δ9-tetrahydrocannabivarin, cannabinol, cannabidiol, cannabidivarin, cannabigerol, and cannabichromene) was investigated thoroughly (Turner et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2017</xref>), and 14 cannabinoids, 47 terpenoids, 3 sterols, and 7 flavonoids have been profiled in Cannabis flowers, leaves, stem barks, and roots for medicinal purposes (Jin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2020</xref>). Moreover, the medicinal effects of 
 <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> are exploited within the treatment of epilepsy, pain, anxiety, depression, sleep disorders, nausea related to cancer treatment, and psychotic conditions, and it has antiglaucoma, antiemetic, antiobesity, and anticancer properties (Andre et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2016</xref>, Barrales-Cureño et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2020</xref>, Corroon and Phillips 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2018</xref>). In addition, the government of Canada recognizes 
 <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> as an effective treatment for over two dozen conditions (Health Canada 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2018</xref>). It is noteworthy that the scientific interest in 
 <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> was renewed in the early 1990s with the outline of cannabinoid receptors and therefore the identification of an endogenous cannabinoid system in the nervous system of humans (Zuardi 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138">2006</xref>) wherein the pharmacological mechanisms of Cannabis metabolites would guide advances in therapies and changes in public health approaches (Russo and Marcu 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">2017</xref>).
</p>
