<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">The lactobacilli use glycogen from exfoliated epithelial cells, which is converted to lactic and fatty acids. Additionally, these bacteria are able to produce other bactericidal products including hydrogen peroxide, bacteriocins, bacteriocin-like products, and surfactants that help in preventing infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Products from various 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> spp. have been shown to inhibit or reduce adherence of urogenital pathogens via competitive exclusion of the host receptor(s) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Phukan, Brooks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] described the discovery of an aggregation promoting factor APF-2 from the vaginal strain 
 <italic>L. gasseri</italic> ATCC 9857 that inhibits 
 <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> adherence to human vaginal ectocervical cells. Hinderfeld, Phukan [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] showed that 
 <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> and CST-IV associated-bacteria are correlated with 
 <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], can enhance paracellular permeability of the cervicovaginal epithelium by dysregulating tight junctions, and affect proinflammatory cytokines such as interleukin-6 (IL-6) and tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α). Valadkhani et al. indicated the protective role of 
 <italic>Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> in 
 <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> infection using healthy human vaginal cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Restoration of the vaginal microflora by both oral and vaginal delivery of prebiotics, probiotics, and/or synbiotics have been attempted for bacterial vaginosis, as well as for 
 <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> infection, with varying degrees of success dependent on strain(s) used, duration of treatment, route of delivery, and whether in combination with traditional drugs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. This is therefore a potential strategy that could be investigated alongside the natural products that we will describe herein.
</p>
