<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Parasites &#x00026; Vectors</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1756-3305</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8220678</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4830</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-021-04830-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Acaricidal activity of <italic>Cinnamomum cassia</italic> (Chinese cinnamon) against the tick <italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> is linked to its content of (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nwanade</surname><given-names>Chuks F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Tianhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiaoyu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Can</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Zhijun</given-names></name><address><email>yuzhijun@hebtu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Jingze</given-names></name><address><email>liujingze@hebtu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.256884.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0605 1239</institution-id><institution>Hebei Key Laboratory of Animal Physiology, Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, College of Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Hebei Normal University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shijiazhuang, 050024 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.488206.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 4912 1751</institution-id><institution>Department of Biochemistry and Biology, Basic Medical College, </institution><institution>Hebei University of Chinese Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Shijiazhuang, 050200 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>330</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The tick <italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> (Neumann) is a well-known vector of numerous pathogens of veterinary and medical importance. Various control strategies, including the use of synthetic pesticides, have been developed to control this tick species. However, demand for effective and safe alternative pesticides is increasing due to the adverse effects associated with the intensive and injudicious use of synthetic pesticides, which include undesirable effects on non-target species and environmental pollution. Hence, the acaricidal activity of the extract and the essential oil of <italic>Cinnamomum cassia</italic> (Chinese cinnamon) and their major components, and the underlying mechanisms of this activity, were evaluated against unfed larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">The components of the extract and essential oil of <italic>C. cassia</italic> were determined by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry, and their larvicidal and nymphicidal activity were evaluated using the larval and nymphal packet test. The underlying detoxification mechanism was elucidated by targeting<italic> in vivo</italic> esterase and monooxygenase activity, and the toxicological effect was assessed on non-target <italic>Tenebrio molitor</italic> and <italic>Harmonia axyridis</italic> by topical application in open Petri dishes.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">(<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde was the predominant component of the extract (50.79%) and essential oil (89.95%). The 50% lethal concentration (LC<sub>50</sub>) for larvae and nymphs treated with the extract was 11.56 and 49.18&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively. The essential oil, (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde and fenvalerate exhibited acaricidal activity, with LC<sub>50</sub> values of 3.81, 3.15, and 0.14&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively, against the larvae, and 21.31, 16.93, and 1.89&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively, against the nymphs. (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde significantly increased esterase and monooxygenase activity in both larvae and nymphs. Unlike fenvalerate, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde did not cause mortality of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> or <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic> adults.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">This study demonstrates that <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde have the potential to be developed into botanical-based larvicidal and nymphicidal agents for tick control.</p></sec><sec><title>Graphical abstract</title><p id="Par100"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="13071_2021_4830_Figa_HTML" id="MO9"/></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Cinnamomum cassia</italic></kwd><kwd>Extract</kwd><kwd>Essential oil</kwd><kwd>(<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde</kwd><kwd><italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic></kwd><kwd>Non-target organism</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>32070494</award-id><award-id>32071510</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Zhijun</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Jingze</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Youth Top Talent Support Program of Hebei Province</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003787</institution-id><institution>Natural Science Foundation of Hebei Province</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>C2019205064</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Zhijun</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Financial Assistance for the Introduction of Overseas Researchers</institution></funding-source><award-id>C20190350</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Zhijun</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>High-level talent support project of Hebei Province</institution></funding-source><award-id>A201901031</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Zhijun</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Science Foundation of Hebei Normal University</institution></funding-source><award-id>L2018J04</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Zhijun</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5">The long-horned tick <italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> Neumann (Acari: Ixodidae) is an obligate hematophagous ectoparasite native to East Asian countries, and was recently found to be established in several states of the USA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In recent years, control of this tick has attracted much attention because of its ability to acquire and transmit numerous zoonotic pathogens, including severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In addition, it is a major pest of livestock in Australia and New Zealand, and infestation, which can cause exsanguination, can lead to economic losses related to reduced growth and production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Various control strategies, including the use of synthetic pesticides, have been developed to control tick species including <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. However, the demand for effective and safe alternative pesticides is increasing due to the adverse effects, including environmental pollution and undesirable effects on non-target species, associated with the intensive and injudicious use of synthetic pesticides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Plant-based products including essential oils and extracts provide good alternatives because they are effective against a wide variety of pests and have little or no toxicity against non-target species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. <italic>Cinnamomum</italic> (Lauraceae) is among the plant genera with promising insecticidal activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. This genus is composed of about 250 species, including the economically important <italic>Cinnamomum cassia</italic> Presl [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par6"><italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> is an evergreen aromatic plant species native to tropical and subtropical regions including China [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. It is an important material in Chinese traditional medicine for the treatment of various ailments such as dysmenorrhea and menoxenia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> also has numerous pharmacological properties that are of great importance to the food and pharmaceutical industries. For example, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil has been demonstrated to be an effective natural antibacterial agent against Shiga toxin-producing <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, an important foodborne pathogen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Another potential industrial application of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> is as an antioxidant agent because of its radical scavenging ability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> has several other important pharmacological properties, including anticholesterol and antidiabetes activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Despite its medicinal uses and potential for use in industry, its potential for application in tick management has scarcely been examined.</p><p id="Par7">In the present study, the extract and essential oil of <italic>C. cassia</italic> bark, and their major component, (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde, which were characterized by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry, and the (synthetic) pyrethroid, fenvalerate, were evaluated<italic> in vitro</italic> against unfed larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic>. The larvae and nymphs are important immature stages of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> as they have been implicated as vectors of tick-borne pathogens, including <italic>Rickettsia rickettsii</italic>, the agent of Rocky Mountain spotted fever [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Therefore, they are considered strategic targets in tick control programs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Furthermore, to elucidate their possible detoxification mechanisms, the effects of the essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde [with low 50% lethal concentration (LC<sub>50</sub>) values in the<italic> in vitro</italic> test] on the biochemical parameters of larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> were tested by targeting<italic> in vivo</italic> esterase and monooxygenase activity. In ticks, esterase and monooxygenase are common detoxification enzymes against xenobiotic compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Finally, to evaluate their environmental safety, the toxicological effects of the essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde were evaluated on the following non-target terrestrial invertebrates: <italic>Tenebrio molitor</italic> (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae), a beneficial insect of ecological and nutritional importance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]; and <italic>Harmonia axyridis</italic> (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae), a biocontrol agent of aphids, scales and other phytophagous pests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Preparation of extracts and source of essential oil</title><p id="Par8">The bark of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> was obtained commercially in September 2019, from Yulin, Guangxi, China (22.625248&#x000b0;N, 110.18473&#x000b0;E), and identified in the Herbarium of College of Life Sciences, Hebei Normal University, Shijiazhuang, China, from voucher specimen 20,006,001. The dried and pulverized bark of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> was macerated with 100% methanol, as described by Rawa et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The supernatants were collected using a Buchner funnel. The resulting filtrates were dried under reduced pressure at 40&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C using a vacuum rotary evaporator. Extracts were stored at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in an airtight brown bottle until tested for acaricidal activity. <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> bark essential oil [Generally Regarded as Safe for human consumption (US Food and Drug Administration)] was obtained from a local supplier (Yu Cheng product workshop) in Chaozhou, Guangdong, China. This supplier extracts essential oils on a small scale by hydrodistillation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Determination of the components of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> extract and essential oil</title><p id="Par9">Components of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> extract and essential oil were determined on a gas chromatography-mass spectrometer (model 7890A-5975C; Agilent Technologies, USA). Chromatographic separation was achieved using a DB-5MS capillary column (30&#x000a0;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m). The carrier gas was helium at 1&#x000a0;mL/min flow rate, and the spilt ratio 10:1. The temperature conditions were 60&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 2&#x000a0;min, increased to 150&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min, and finally to 280&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min. The mass spectrometer was bombarded with an electron impact ionization source, and the electron energy was 70&#x000a0;eV. The inlet temperature was 280&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and the ion source temperature was 230&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The mass scanning range was 40&#x02013;550&#x000a0;m/z. Compounds were identified using the Standard Reference Database of the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Chemicals</title><p id="Par10">Analytical grade methanol was purchased from Baishi Chemicals (Tianjin, China). (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde (98%; lot no. I1918074), a clear yellow liquid, was purchased from Aladdin Biochemical (Shanghai, China). Fenvalerate (Hubei Danongren Biological Technology), used as a sample synthetic (commercial) acaricide, was purchased from a local market. Esterase, monooxygenase, and protein assay kits were purchased from Shanghai Enzyme-linked Biotechnology (Shanghai, China).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Test organisms</title><p id="Par11">Unfed adult ticks of <italic>H. longicornis</italic> were collected from vegetation by tick dragging at Xiaowutai National Nature Reserve Area (40&#x000b0;03&#x02032;03&#x02033;N, 115&#x000b0;23&#x02032;15&#x02033;E), Zhangjiakou, Hebei Province, China. Unfed adult ticks were placed on the ears of New Zealand white rabbits and the resulting engorged females were maintained in an incubator [26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, 85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5% relative humidity (RH), 16:8&#x000a0;h (light:dark; L:D) photoperiod] for oviposition. The larvae that hatched during a period of 14&#x000a0;days and the nymphs that molted during a period of 14&#x000a0;days were used for subsequent tests.</p><p id="Par12"><italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> larvae were collected from a commercial breeder in Zhengzhou, Henan, China. They were first reared to the pupal and then to the adult stage on a diet of wheat bran and potato slices in plastic containers (18&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;11&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;11&#x000a0;cm), as described by George et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], under laboratory conditions [25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, 70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5% RH, 16:8-h photoperiod (L:D)]. Adults 6&#x02013;10&#x000a0;days after eclosion, and larvae (&#x0003e;&#x02009;15&#x000a0;mm), were used in this study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic> larvae were commercially obtained (Jiangsu, China), and reared according to Benelli et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Larvae were fed aphids <italic>ad libitum</italic> and maintained in an incubator [25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, 70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5% RH, 16:8-h photoperiod (L:D)], and the resulting adults (3&#x02013;7&#x000a0;days old) were used in this study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Acaricidal activity</title><p id="Par13">Acaricidal activity against the larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> was determined using larval and nymphal packet tests. First, the bark extract of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic>, essential oil of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic>, and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde were diluted with 70% methanol. There is little or no toxicity of 70% methanol when it is used as a solvent in the packet test<italic> in vitro</italic> (filter papers soaked with the test compounds were allowed to dry before use in a closed packet containing ticks) [see details of the larval packet test (LPT) below]. In addition, previous studies have shown that analytical grade methanol (undiluted) has little or no toxicity against tick species, and it has been suggested as a suitable solvent for dissolving plant extracts when testing acaricidal activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Then a range finding test was carried out to determine the appropriate test concentrations. For larvae, five concentrations were used, ranging from 5.00 to 20.00&#x000a0;mg/mL for the extract, 2.75&#x02013;5.00&#x000a0;mg/mL for the essential oil, 2.75&#x02013;3.70&#x000a0;mg/mL for (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde, and 0.025&#x02013;0.750&#x000a0;mg/mL for fenvalerate. For nymphs, five to six concentrations were used, ranging from 40.00 to 60.00&#x000a0;mg/mL for the extract, 10.00&#x02013;30.00&#x000a0;mg/mL for the essential oil, 5.00&#x02013;30.00&#x000a0;mg/mL for (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde, and 0.38&#x02013;4.50&#x000a0;mg/mL for fenvalerate.</p><p id="Par14">The LPT was carried out according to the<italic> in vitro</italic> test recommended by the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], as described by Godara et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Briefly, filter papers (7.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;9.0&#x000a0;cm, Whatman No. 1; Whatman, Maidstone, UK) were soaked with 1&#x000a0;mL of the dilutions. The treated filter papers were allowed to dry and were then folded into packets and sealed on the side with clips. One hundred larvae were introduced into each packet before sealing the top of with clips. The packets containing the larvae were kept in an incubator (26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and 85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5% RH). After 24&#x000a0;h, the packets were examined for larval mortality. Distilled water and 70% methanol served as the negative control group, and fenvalerate diluted with distilled water, as specified on the product label, served as the positive control. Each treatment and control group was replicated four times. A similar LPT was used for unfed nymphs, with ten nymphs placed into each packet; each treatment and the negative control group (distilled water and 70% methanol) and positive control group (fenvalerate) was replicated five times.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Effect (LC<sub>50</sub>) on non-target <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic></title><p id="Par15">The essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> were selected due to their low LC<sub>50</sub> values against unfed larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> (Figs. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Adults of <italic>T. molitor</italic> were exposed to LC<sub>50</sub> of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil (3.81 and 21.31&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively, for larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic>) and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde (3.15 and 16.93&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively) (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) using the method described by Pedersen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Exposure was performed by topical application in open Petri dishes (diameter, 9&#x000a0;cm). Briefly, the abdomen was held with a soft tweezer, causing the beetle to lower its head, which exposed the soft part between the pronotum and elytra. Each adult received a 1-&#x000b5;L droplet of the test solutions using a micropipette (Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany). Likewise, larvae received a 1-&#x000b5;L droplet of the test solutions in the area that was proportionally equal in proximity to the head. Adults and larvae of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> exposed to LC<sub>50</sub> of fenvalerate (0.14 and 1.89&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively, for larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic>), as estimated in the toxicity bioassay, were used as a positive control. Negative control groups included adults and larvae exposed to 70% methanol and distilled water. Treated adults and larvae were transferred to clean Petri dishes (ten beetles per dish), and fed with wheat bran and potato slices. All dishes were maintained in the incubator [25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, 70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5% RH, 16:8-h photoperiod (L:D)]. The numbers of dead larvae and adults of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> were determined 48&#x000a0;h after treatment. <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> that did not respond to the probe were considered dead. Each treatment and control group was replicated five times.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Concentration&#x02013;response curves of <italic>Haemaphysalis</italic>
<italic>longicornis</italic> larvae.<italic> Solid lines</italic> represent the estimated mean.<italic> Dotted lines</italic> represent 95% confidence intervals (<italic>CI</italic>; lower and upper) around the mean. <italic>LC</italic><sub><italic>50</italic></sub> Lethal concentration required to kill 50% of the population at 24&#x000a0;h</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2021_4830_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Concentration&#x02013;response curves of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> nymphs.<italic> Solid lines</italic> represent the estimated mean.<italic> Dotted lines</italic> represent 95% CI around the mean. For abbreviations, see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2021_4830_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Effect (LC<sub>50</sub>) on non-target <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic></title><p id="Par16">The effects of the LC<sub>50</sub> for larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil (3.81 and 21.31&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively) and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde (3.15 and 16.93&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively) on adult <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic> were assessed by using a minor modification of the method described by Youn et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. In the present study, 1&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L of the test solutions was topically applied to adults at the junction between the pronotum and elytron using a micropipette (Eppendorf). Adults of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic> exposed to LC<sub>50</sub> of fenvalerate for larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> (0.14 and 1.89&#x000a0;mg/mL) were used as positive controls. Negative control groups included adults exposed to 70% methanol and distilled water. Treated adults were transferred to clean Petri dishes (ten adults per dish), fed with <italic>Metopolophium dirhodum,</italic> and maintained in an incubator [25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, 70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5% RH, 16:8-h photoperiod (L:D)]. The number of dead <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic> was determined 48&#x000a0;h after treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], with adults that did not respond to a probe considered dead. Each treatment and the control groups were replicated five times.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Biochemical analysis</title><p id="Par17">The<italic> in vivo</italic> enzyme activities were measured for unfed larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> exposed to LC<sub>50</sub> of the essential oil (3.81 and 21.31&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively) and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde (3.15 and 16.93&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively) (Figs. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Larvae and nymphs exposed to LC<sub>50</sub> of fenvalerate (0.14 and 1.89&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively) (Figs. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) were used as a positive control. Negative control groups included larvae and nymphs exposed to 70% methanol and distilled water. The essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde were selected due to their low LC<sub>50</sub> values against unfed larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> (Figs. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). About 20&#x000a0;mg of the larvae and nymphs that survived after treatments in the packet assays was homogenized in 400 &#x000b5;L pre-cooled phosphate-buffered solution (0.1&#x000a0;M, pH 7.2). The homogenate was centrifuged at 3000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x000a0;min. The resulting supernatant was removed and used for esterase and monooxygenase assays using the corresponding ELISA kit (Shanghai Enzyme-linked Biotechnology), and for the protein assay using bicinchoninic acid protein assay kit (Shanghai Enzyme-linked Biotechnology), following the manufacturer's instructions. For each tested concentration and control group, there were three replicates.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p id="Par18">Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS software (v20.0; IBM, Armonk, NY). The normality of residuals was first verified using the Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk test. Then, ANOVA and Tukey&#x02019;s test were used to determine the significance of the data of the biochemical analyses. Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis and Student-Newman-Keuls post hoc test were used to determine the significance of the percentage mortality of the non-target species. Mortality of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> larvae in the negative control (70% methanol only) was below 5%, thus no correction of mortality was necessary [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. LC<sub>50</sub> were determined by performing a probit analysis on the tick mortality data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] using SPSS (v20.0) and MedCalc (v19.6.4; MedCalc, Ostend, Belgium) software.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Chemical composition</title><p id="Par19">In the <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> extract, a total of 14 compounds representing 97.39% of the total extract were identified. The major constituent of this extract was (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde (50.79%). The percentage compositions of the remaining 13 compounds ranged from 0.97 to 15.83% (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil, 16 compounds were identified, accounting for 97.11% of the total composition. Specifically, the major constituent was (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde (89.95%). The percentage abundance of the remaining 15 compounds ranged from 0.13 to 1.68% (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The compounds obtained from the bark extract and essential oil of <italic>Cinnamomum cassia</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">S/N</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Retention time</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Area %</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Compounds</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Area %</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Retention time</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Extract</th><th align="left">Essential oil</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">6.748</td><td align="left">11.99</td><td align="left">3-Methoxy-3-phenylpropanal</td><td align="left">Tetrahydro-2-furanol</td><td align="left">0.42</td><td align="left">3.230</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">6.951</td><td align="left"><italic>50.79</italic></td><td align="left">(<italic>E</italic>)-<italic>cinnamaldehyde</italic></td><td align="left">Butyrolactone</td><td align="left">0.16</td><td align="left">4.999</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">7.582</td><td align="left">2.83</td><td align="left">Copaene</td><td align="left">2-Furanmethanol</td><td align="left">1.39</td><td align="left">5.124</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">8.016</td><td align="left">1.78</td><td align="left">Cinnamyl acetate</td><td align="left">Benzaldehyde</td><td align="left">0.26</td><td align="left">5.688</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">8.183</td><td align="left">15.83</td><td align="left">(<italic>E</italic>)-2-hydroxycinnamic acid</td><td align="left">(<italic>Z</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde</td><td align="left">0.52</td><td align="left">8.240</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">8.431</td><td align="left">2.53</td><td align="left"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Muurolene</td><td align="left">(<italic>E</italic>)-<italic>cinnamaldehyde</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>89.95</italic></td><td align="left">8.809</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">8.559</td><td align="left">3.16</td><td align="left"><italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-Cadinene</td><td align="left">Copaene</td><td align="left">0.18</td><td align="left">9.433</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">8.601</td><td align="left">1.21</td><td align="left"><italic>Cis</italic>-calamenene</td><td align="left"><italic>Trans</italic>-cinnamic acid</td><td align="left">1.09</td><td align="left">9.777</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">8.642</td><td align="left">1.83</td><td align="left">2-Methoxycinnamaldehyde</td><td align="left">Cinnamyl ester</td><td align="left">0.40</td><td align="left">9.842</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">8.671</td><td align="left">0.97</td><td align="left">Cubenene</td><td align="left">Coumarin</td><td align="left">0.33</td><td align="left">9.919</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">9.399</td><td align="left">1.14</td><td align="left">Syringaldehyde</td><td align="left"><italic>&#x003b3;</italic>-Muurolene</td><td align="left">0.15</td><td align="left">10.092</td></tr><tr><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">9.399</td><td align="left">1.14</td><td align="left"><italic>T</italic>-muurolol</td><td align="left">Cadina-1(10),4-diene</td><td align="left">0.13</td><td align="left">10.353</td></tr><tr><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">11.013</td><td align="left">1.03</td><td align="left">Palmitic acid</td><td align="left">2-Methoxycinnamaldehyde</td><td align="left">1.68</td><td align="left">10.430</td></tr><tr><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">11.876</td><td align="left">1.16</td><td align="left">Linoleic acid</td><td align="left">Benzene</td><td align="left">0.18</td><td align="left">10.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left">15</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">2-Methyl-1-naphthalenol</td><td align="left">0.14</td><td align="left">10.727</td></tr><tr><td align="left">16</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">1-Phenyl-hexa-1,5-dione</td><td align="left">0.13</td><td align="left">11.071</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>S</italic>/<italic>N</italic> Signal-to-noise ratio</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par20">The presence of (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde as the predominant component in the extract and essential oil from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> bark in the present study is in accordance with results reported in other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. However, the chemical composition of the extract and essential oil from <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> bark is affected by many factors including methods of extraction, and the different agroecological conditions during the growth and development of the plant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. As a result, several species of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> have been reported with different percent contents of (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. For example, in the study of Deng et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde was the predominant component and accounted for about 72.23% of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> bark essential oil. In a recent study, Liang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] found that (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde (62.96%) was a major component of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> bark extract. In addition, in other species of <italic>Cinnamomum</italic>, (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde is also a major component, and accounted for about 66.43% of <italic>Cinnamomum</italic>
<italic>zeylanicum</italic> bark essential oil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. In the present study, the percent content of (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde in the essential oil (89.95%) was higher than in the extract (50.79%). A possible explanation for variation in the percent content of (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde may be the different methods used for the extraction of the extract and essential oil. Variation in the percent content of (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde can also be due to the geographical origin of the <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> and the method used for the extraction of the extract and essential oil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Acaricidal activity, effect (LC<sub>50</sub>) on non-target species, and biochemical activity</title><p id="Par21">The acaricidal activity was evaluated by the packet test for unfed larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic>. After treatment of unfed larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> for 24&#x000a0;h, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil, with LC<sub>50</sub> values of 3.81 and 21.31&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively, and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde, with LC<sub>50</sub> values of 3.15 and 16.93&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively, exhibited greater acaricidal activity compared with <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> extract, with LC<sub>50</sub> values of 11.56 and 49.18&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively (Figs. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). However, the efficacy of the essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde was lower compared with that of fenvalerate (synthetic acaricide), with LC<sub>50</sub> values of 0.14 and 1.89&#x000a0;mg/mL against the larvae and nymphs, respectively (Figs. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Despite these results, <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde can be considered as potential candidates for the development of larvicidal and nymphicidal agents for tick control. This conclusion is justified from a toxicological and a mechanistic perspective. For instance, from a toxicological point of view, it is important not only to assess the efficacy of new plant-based pesticides on target species but also to estimate any effect on non-target species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Herein, we evaluated the effect of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde on the mortality of non-target species, i.e. <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> and <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic>. <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> is presently being promoted as a beneficial insect, as it is capable of degrading polystyrene and plastic waste, and may play an important role in litter decomposition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In addition, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> larvae are often used as pet food, and offer a promising alternative protein source for human and animal nutrition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Besides this, predatory behavior of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> on ticks has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic> is a biocontrol agent of pests including aphids, scales, and other phytophagous pests, and plays an important role in regulating the populations of these pests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Topical application of the essential oil (tested concentration: LC<sub>50</sub> 3.81 and 21.31&#x000a0;mg/mL for unfed larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic>) or (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde (tested concentration: LC<sub>50</sub> 3.15 and 16.93&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively) did not cause mortality in <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> or <italic>Harmonia</italic>
<italic>axyridis</italic> adults (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A, B), which may indicate that these compounds are environmentally safe. Generally, essential oils and their active compound(s) are not toxic to non-target organisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], in accordance with our results. For example, essential oil from <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> did not cause any significant mortality in <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic> larvae or adults, and had no adverse effect on <italic>Eisenia fetida</italic> earthworm adults [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Mortality (%) of <italic>Tenebrio</italic>
<italic>molitor</italic> (<bold>A</bold>) and <italic>Harmonia</italic>
<italic>axyridis</italic> (<bold>B</bold>). The fenvalerate LC<sub>50</sub> values were estimated for the larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> by the packet test. Data are presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5).<italic> Different letters</italic> indicate significant difference (Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis/Student-Newman-Keuls, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). For abbreviations, see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2021_4830_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par22">However, topical application of fenvalerate (tested concentration: LC<sub>50</sub> 1.89&#x000a0;mg/mL for the nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic>) resulted in significant mortality in adult <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> [18.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.35;<italic> F</italic><sub>(4,20)</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;15.444, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.000] and <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic> [8.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.74;<italic> F</italic><sub>(4,20)</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.952, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.003] when compared with the control (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A, B), which indicates that fenvalerate may inhibit their performance as beneficial organisms and biocontrol agents. Furthermore, there was no mortality in the larvae of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> treated with fenvalerate (tested concentrations: LC<sub>50</sub> 0.14 and LC<sub>50</sub> 1.89&#x000a0;mg/mL, for larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic>) during the 48-h observation period, thus these data were omitted from all calculations and comparisons. Pedersen et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] found that <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> adults were more sensitive to exposure to the pyrethroid &#x003b1;-cypermethrin than their larvae. It is possible that the size of an insect and its structure may affect the amount of a chemical that enters its body [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Generally, synthetic insecticides including pyrethroids have a negative effect on non-target species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. For example, treatment with &#x003b1;-cypermethrin at 1.6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>&#x000a0;mL/L caused about 50% mortality in non-target <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic> adults [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par23">It is important to note that the results of the non-target assay should be interpreted with caution, given the different experimental designs, including the non-uniform methods (LPT verse topical application) used to assess toxicity on the target and non-target species, which may have caused <italic>Haemaphysalis</italic>
<italic>longicornis</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> and <italic>Harmonia</italic>
<italic>axyridis</italic> to react differently to the test substances. Moreover, the toxicity of a substance usually depends on the amount acquired by the test organism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Thus, the lack of toxicity of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde in non-target <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> and <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic> could have been due to their exposure to lower concentrations than the ticks, as a result of the different<italic> in vitro</italic> assays used. However, our observations in this study are significant in that they provide an indication of the potential effects of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde on non-target <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> and <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic>, and provide the basis for the design of future studies which will take into account, among other factors, the disparities between the experimental designs used in this present study.</p><p id="Par24">Elucidating the underlying detoxification mechanism can provide important clues for the development of botanical-based acaricides. In the present study, both the essential oil of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde significantly affected the activities of detoxification enzymes in ticks, including those of esterase and monooxygenase. For example, in contrast to the fenvalerate treatment, esterase activity was significantly increased in larvae [Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A;<italic> F</italic><sub>(4,10)</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17.549, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.000] and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> [Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B;<italic> F</italic><sub>(4,10)</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;39.363, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.000] exposed to (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde (tested concentration: LC<sub>50</sub> 3.15 and 16.93&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively) when compared with the control. Likewise, esterase activity significantly increased when the nymphs were exposed to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil (tested concentration: LC<sub>50</sub> 21.31&#x000a0;mg/mL) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B). On the other hand, similar to the effects of fenvalerate, monooxygenase activity was significantly increased in the larvae [Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>C;<italic> F</italic><sub>(4,10)</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;22.346, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.000] and nymphs [Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D;<italic> F</italic><sub>(4,10)</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;33.181, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.000] after treatment with LC<sub>50</sub> of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde. Esterase and monooxygenase are involved in the metabolic detoxification of pesticides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. In ticks, they play an important role in the development of resistance to synthetic acaricides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. For example, resistance to synthetic pyrethroids was found to be significantly correlated with increase esterase and monooxygenase activities in <italic>Rhipicephalus microplus</italic>&#x000a0;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. It has also been demonstrated that the inhibition of detoxification enzymes, including esterase, led to an increase in the mortality of a resistant strain of <italic>R. microplus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The increased expression of esterase and monooxygenase in the present study may indicate their involvement in the detoxification response against <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde. However, additional studies are needed to test different times of exposure, since esterase and monooxygenase activities may decrease with time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], and to explore the contribution of other metabolic enzymes such as acetylcholinesterase and glutathione S-transferases to defense mechanisms. It is important to note that the total protein content of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> after treatment with <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil, (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde and fenvalerate ranged from 0.98 to 1.05&#x000a0;mg/mL for the larvae and 0.96&#x02013;1.13&#x000a0;mg/mL for the nymphs, and treatment with the essential oil, (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde and fenvalerate did not induce significant changes in the total protein of either.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>
<bold>A&#x02013;D</bold> Esterase and monooxygenase activities of larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis.</italic> Data are presented as the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3).<italic> Different letters</italic> indicate a significant difference (Tukey&#x02019;s test, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001).<italic> EO</italic> Essential oil</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2021_4830_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par25">In addition, based on the present results, the efficacy of <italic>C. cassia</italic> essential oil in terms of LC<sub>50</sub> values, i.e. lower concentrations compared with those of the extract (Figs. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), may be attributed to the high percent content of the main component, (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde. (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde is the key component of <italic>C. cassia</italic> bark responsible for its insecticidal and acaricidal activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. When tested as a pure compound, (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde was effective against the larvae and nymphs of <italic>Rhipicephalus sanguineus</italic>, with 100% mortality at 2.55 and 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L/mL, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. A similar observation was recorded for the larvae of <italic>Amblyomma cajennense</italic> at a (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde concentration of 5.0&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L/mL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Likewise, (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde was effective with 100% mortality at a concentration of 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L/mL against <italic>R</italic>. <italic>microplus</italic> and <italic>Dermacentor nitens</italic> larvae [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Acaricidal activity of (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde was also observed against the larvae of <italic>Amblyomma sculptum</italic> (LC<sub>50</sub> 1.40&#x000a0;mg/mL) and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>nitens</italic> (LC<sub>50</sub> 1.68&#x000a0;mg/mL) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Besides its efficacy against ticks, (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde was found to be an efficient mosquito larvicidal against <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>, <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> and <italic>Armigeres subalbatus</italic>, with LC<sub>50</sub> values below 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p><p id="Par26">Compared with other essential oils, for example, essential oil of <italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic> (LC<sub>50</sub> values of 28.06 and 28.18&#x000a0;mg/mL for larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic>, respectively) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> bark essential oil tested in this study showed greater acaricidal activity against the larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic>. The insecticidal activity of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil has also been reported for other target species, e.g. against the nymphs of <italic>Ricania</italic> sp., with an LC<sub>50</sub> value of 37.66&#x000a0;mg/mL after exposure for 72&#x000a0;h [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. In addition, the insecticidal activity of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> extract has been reported for pests of stored products including <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic> and <italic>Lasioderma serricorne</italic>, with LD<sub>50</sub> values of 3.96 and 23.89&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/adult, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. To our knowledge, the present study is the first report on the acaricidal activity of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> extract and essential oil against vector ticks. The essential oils obtained from other species of <italic>Cinnamomum</italic> have also been studied against tick species. For example, the larvicidal activity of <italic>Cinnamomum</italic>
<italic>zeylanicum</italic> essential oil was evaluated against <italic>R</italic>. <italic>microplus</italic> larvae, with an LC<sub>50</sub> of 0.086% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Apart from acaricidal activity, <italic>Cinnamomum</italic>
<italic>verum</italic> essential oil was found to exhibit larvicidal activity against fourth-instar <italic>Cx. quinquefasciatus</italic> (LC<sub>50</sub> 40.7 &#x003bc;L/L) and adulticidal (LC<sub>50</sub> 42&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/adult) activity against <italic>Musca domestica</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par27">Cinnamon oil is considered safe by the US Food and Drug Administration and is exempted from toxicity data requirements by the US Environmental Protection Agency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. However, there are potential safety concerns regarding cinnamaldehyde. For example, cinnamaldehyde at certain exposure concentrations reduces adenosine triphosphate levels and disrupts mitochondrial function in human bronchial epithelial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Thus, during<italic> in vivo</italic> and/or field trials of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> products, concentration&#x02013;response curves should be determined. These can be used to identify lethal and non-lethal concentrations for ticks and mammalian hosts. Additionally, application of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> products directly to the host may provide better protection from tick infestation, since hosts can be kept in enclosures to protect them against environmental factors including weather conditions that could interfere with the efficacy of the applied products [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Natural product-based acaricides are sensitive to environmental factors, thus, they do not persist for long in the environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par28">The <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> products tested in the present study, especially the essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde, exhibited good acaricidal activity against larvae and nymphs of <italic>Haemaphysalis</italic>
<italic>longicornis</italic>, whereas no toxic effect was found against the terrestrial invertebrates <italic>T</italic>. <italic>molitor</italic> and <italic>Harmonia</italic>
<italic>axyridis</italic>, which suggests that they may not be harmful to non-target terrestrial invertebrates when used as acaricides. The defense response of the larvae and nymphs of <italic>H</italic>. <italic>longicornis</italic> to <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde may be partly related to the increased synthesis of esterase and monooxygenase. In addition, the acaricidal activity of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> essential oil or extract is likely related to the biochemical activity of (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde, i.e. the increased expression of esterase and monooxygenase activity. However, the molecular mechanism underlying the acaricidal activity of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>cassia</italic> warrants further exploration, and future studies on its effects on other non-target species such as soil-dwelling (earthworms) and aquatic organisms are imperative.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Chuks F. Nwanade acknowledges support from the China Scholarship Council. The authors would like to thank Dr. Abolfazl Masoudi for his technical input.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>CFN, ZY, and JL designed the project. ZY identified the tick species. CFN and CW performed the plant extractions. CFN, MW, and XZ performed the bioassay. CFN and TW wrote the draft manuscript. ZY and JL critically revised the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (32070494, 32071510), the Youth Top Talent Support Program of Hebei Province to ZY, the Natural Science Foundation of Hebei Province (C2019205064), Financial Assistance for the Introduction of Overseas Researchers (C20190350), the High-level Talent Support Project of Hebei Province (A201901031) and the Science Foundation of Hebei Normal University (L2018J04).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The data used and analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes><title>Animal welfare statement</title><p>The experimental protocols in this study fully complied with the animal protection law of the People&#x02019;s Republic of China, and were approved by the Animal Ethics Committee of Hebei Normal University (protocol no. 157031).</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par30">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pritt</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> is in the United States and biting humans: where do we go from here?</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/ciz451</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31150050?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31150050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZT</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> ticks as reservoir and vector of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome virus in China</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1770</fpage><lpage>1776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2110.150126</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26402039?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26402039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tick-borne pathogens and the vector potential of ticks in China</article-title><source>Parasites Vectors</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>24</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-014-0628-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25586007?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25586007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>ACG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biology, ecology and distribution of the tick, <italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> Neumann (Acari: Ixodidae) in New Zealand</article-title><source>N Z Vet J</source><year>2016</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00480169.2015.1035769</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25849758?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25849758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the acaricidal activity of 63 commercialized pesticides against <italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae)</article-title><source>Entomol Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>330</fpage><lpage>336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1748-5967.12367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pisa</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Amaral-Rogers</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Belzunces</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonmatin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of neonicotinoids and fipronil on non-target invertebrates</article-title><source>Environ Sci Pollut Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-014-3471-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavela</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oils from <italic>Foeniculum vulgare</italic> Miller as a safe environmental insecticide against the aphid <italic>Myzus persicae</italic> Sulzer</article-title><source>Environ Sci Pollut Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>10904</fpage><lpage>10910</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-018-1398-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavela</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Drenaggi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Desneux</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Maggi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytol, (<italic>E</italic>)-nerolidol and spathulenol from <italic>Stevia rebaudiana</italic> leaf essential oil as effective and eco-friendly botanical insecticides against <italic>Metopolophium dirhodum</italic></article-title><source>Ind Crops Prod</source><year>2020</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>112844</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2020.112844</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavela</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Giordani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Casettari</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Curzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappellacci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acute and sub-lethal toxicity of eight essential oils of commercial interest against the filariasis mosquito <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> and the housefly <italic>Musca domestica</italic></article-title><source>Ind Crops Prod</source><year>2018</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>668</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2017.12.062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sriramavaratharajan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Murugan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the leaf essential oils of an endemic species <italic>Cinnamomum perrottetii</italic> from Western Ghats</article-title><source>India Nat Prod Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1085</fpage><lpage>1087</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14786419.2015.1095746</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26453373?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26453373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Cinnamomum cassia</italic> Presl: a review of its traditional uses, phytochemistry, pharmacology and toxicology</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2019</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>3473</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules24193473</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6804248?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6804248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitory effect of <italic>Cinnamomum cassia</italic> oil on non-O157 Shiga toxin-producing <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Food Control</source><year>2014</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>374</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2014.05.050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity of various parts of <italic>Cinnamomum cassia</italic> extracted with different extraction methods</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>7294</fpage><lpage>7304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules17067294</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22695234?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22695234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamidpour</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamidpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamidpour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahlari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cinnamon from the selection of traditional applications to its novel effects on the inhibition of angiogenesis in cancer cells and prevention of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease, and a series of functions such as antioxidant, anticholesterol, antidiabetes, antibacterial, antifungal, nematicidal, acaracidal, and repellent activities</article-title><source>J Tradit Complement Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtcme.2014.11.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26151013?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26151013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Snellgrove</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartzer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Krapiunaya</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The ability of the invasive Asian longhorned tick <italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae) to acquire and transmit <italic>Rickettsia rickettsii</italic> (Rickettsiales: Rickettsiaceae), the agent of Rocky Mountain spotted fever, under laboratory conditions</article-title><source>J Med Entomol</source><year>2020</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>1635</fpage><lpage>1639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jme/tjaa076</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32338290?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32338290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adenubi</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name><name><surname>McGaw</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eloff</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Naidoo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> bioassays used in evaluating plant extracts for tick repellent and acaricidal properties: a critical review</article-title><source>Vet Parasitol</source><year>2018</year><volume>254</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2018.03.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29657003?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29657003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Delmonte</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Novato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Daemon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilela</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acaricidal activity of essential oil of <italic>Syzygium aromaticum</italic>, hydrolate and eugenol formulated or free on larvae and engorged females of <italic>Rhipicephalus microplus</italic></article-title><source>Med Vet Entomol</source><year>2018</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mve.12259</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28833280?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28833280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaud&#x000ea;ncio</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name><name><surname>Klafke</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tunholi-Alves</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>da Fonseca</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Activity of carboxylesterases, glutathione-<italic>S</italic>-transferase and monooxygenase on <italic>Rhipicephalus microplus</italic> exposed to fluazuron</article-title><source>Parasitol Int</source><year>2017</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.parint.2017.04.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28435029?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28435029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparagano</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Port</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Okello</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiel</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repellence of plant essential oils to <italic>Dermanyssus gallinae</italic> and toxicity to the non-target invertebrate <italic>Tenebrio molitor</italic></article-title><source>Vet Parasitol</source><year>2009</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2009.02.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19264408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19264408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vigneron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jehan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigaud</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Moret</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immune defenses of a beneficial pest: the mealworm beetle <italic>Tenebrio molitor</italic></article-title><source>Front Physiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>138</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2019.00138</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30914960?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30914960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omkar</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecology and biological control application of multicoloured Asian ladybird, <italic>Harmonia axyridis</italic>: a review</article-title><source>Biocontrol Sci Technol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09583150500335350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rawa</surname><given-names>MSA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Murugaiyah</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahab</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-cholinesterase potential of diverse botanical families from Malaysia: evaluation of crude extracts and fractions from liquid-liquid extraction and acid-base fractionation</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2019</year><volume>245</volume><fpage>112160</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2019.112160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31419500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyling</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name><surname>Fredensborg</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cedergreen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in life stage sensitivity of the beetle <italic>Tenebrio molitor</italic> towards a pyrethroid insecticide explained by stage-specific variations in uptake, elimination and activity of detoxifying enzymes</article-title><source>Pestic Biochem Phys</source><year>2020</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pestbp.2019.09.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravindran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Juliet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunil</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Amithamol</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Toxic effects of various solvents against <italic>Rhipicephalus</italic> (<italic>Boophilus</italic>) <italic>annulatus</italic></article-title><source>Ticks Tick-Borne Dis</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2011.04.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21890070?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21890070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations</collab></person-group><article-title>Module 1. Ticks: acaricides resistance: diagnosis management and prevention</article-title><source>Guidelines resistance management and integrated parasite control in ruminants</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Rome</publisher-loc><publisher-name>FAO Animal Production and Health Division</publisher-name><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>77</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Parveen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Katoch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Katoch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acaricidal activity of extract of <italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic> against <italic>Rhipicephalus sanguineus</italic> of dogs</article-title><source>Parasitol Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-013-3704-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24288053?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24288053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Youn</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxicity of greenhouse pesticides to multicolored Asian lady beetles, <italic>Harmonia axyridis</italic> (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae)</article-title><source>Biol Control</source><year>2003</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1049-9644(03)00098-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finney</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Probit analysis</source><year>1971</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of essential oils from cassia bark and cassia twig samples by GC-MS combined with multivariate data analysis</article-title><source>Food Anal Methods</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1840</fpage><lpage>1847</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12161-014-9821-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical compound identification and antibacterial activity evaluation of cinnamon extracts obtained by subcritical<italic> n</italic>-butane and ethanol extraction</article-title><source>Food Sci Nutr</source><year>2019</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>2186</fpage><lpage>2193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.1065</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31289667?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31289667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>HNH</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Adukwu</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro antifungal activity of <italic>Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic> bark and leaf essential oils against <italic>Candida albicans</italic> and <italic>Candida auris</italic></article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2020</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>8911</fpage><lpage>8924</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-020-10829-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32880694?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32880694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samish</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alekseev</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arthropods as predators of ticks (Ixodoidea)</article-title><source>J Med Entomol</source><year>2001</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0022-2585-38.1.1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11268678?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11268678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and larvicidal activity against <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes of essential oils from <italic>Arisaema fargesii</italic></article-title><source>Pest Manage Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>534</fpage><lpage>542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ps.5542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fular</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Upadhaya</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shakya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Standardization of tick specific biochemical tools for estimation of esterases, monooxygenases and glutathione<italic> S</italic>-transferase for characterization of acaricide resistance</article-title><source>Pestic Biochem Phys</source><year>2020</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pestbp.2020.01.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Gall</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Klafke</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detoxification mechanisms involved in ivermectin resistance in the cattle tick, <italic>Rhipicephalus</italic> (<italic>Boophilus</italic>) <italic>microplus</italic></article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>12401</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-30907-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30120322?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30120322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acaricidal and insecticidal responses of <italic>Cinnamomum cassia</italic> oils and main constituents</article-title><source>Appl Biol Chem</source><year>2018</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13765-018-0402-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senra</surname><given-names>TOS</given-names></name><name><surname>Calmon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zering&#x000f3;ta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>CMO</given-names></name><name><surname>Maturano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigation of activity of monoterpenes and phenylpropanoids against immature stages of <italic>Amblyomma cajennense</italic> and <italic>Rhipicephalus sanguineus</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae)</article-title><source>Parasitol Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>3471</fpage><lpage>3476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-013-3527-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23842886?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23842886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senra</surname><given-names>TOS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zering&#x000f3;ta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>CMO</given-names></name><name><surname>Calmon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Maturano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessment of the acaricidal activity of carvacrol, (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde, trans-anethole, and linalool on larvae of <italic>Rhipicephalus microplus</italic> and <italic>Dermacentor nitens</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae)</article-title><source>Parasitol Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>1461</fpage><lpage>1466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-013-3289-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23354938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Novato</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name><name><surname>de Monteiro</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Maturano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Senra</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the combined effect of thymol, carvacrol and (<italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde on <italic>Amblyomma sculptum</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae) and <italic>Dermacentor nitens</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae) larvae</article-title><source>Vet Parasitol</source><year>2015</year><volume>212</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2015.08.021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26346899?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26346899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsui</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insecticidal activities of leaf essential oils from <italic>Cinnamomum osmophloeum</italic> against three mosquito species</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2009</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2008.02.030</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18396039?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18396039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agwunobi</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of the essential oil from <italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic> on mortality and morphology of the tick <italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae)</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>2020</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-020-00485-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32246382?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32246382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insecticidal activities of their components derived from the essential oils of <italic>Cinnamomum</italic> sp. barks and against <italic>Ricania</italic> sp. (Homoptera: Ricaniidae), a newly recorded pest</article-title><source>Pest Manage Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>2000</fpage><lpage>2004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ps.4627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Supercritical carbon dioxide extract of <italic>Cinnamomum</italic><italic> cassia</italic> bark: toxicity and repellency against two stored-product beetle species</article-title><source>Environ Sci Pollut Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>22236</fpage><lpage>22243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-018-2342-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rath</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> assessment of synergistic combinations of essential oils against <italic>Rhipicephalus</italic> (<italic>Boophilus</italic>) <italic>microplus</italic> Canestrini (Acari: Ixodidae)</article-title><source>Exp Parasitol</source><year>2019</year><volume>201</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exppara.2019.04.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31034814?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31034814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clapp</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavrich</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>van Heusden</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarowski</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaspers</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cinnamaldehyde in flavored e-cigarette liquids temporarily suppresses bronchial epithelial cell ciliary motility by dysregulation of mitochondrial function</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>316</volume><fpage>470</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajplung.00304.2018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corr&#x000ea;a</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Felippelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A comparison of three different methodologies for evaluating <italic>Rhipicephalus</italic> (<italic>Boophilus</italic>) <italic>microplus</italic> susceptibility to topical spray compounds</article-title><source>Vet Parasitol</source><year>2015</year><volume>207</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2014.11.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25468670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25468670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for personal protective measures to reduce human contact with blacklegged ticks and for environmentally based control methods to suppress host-seeking blacklegged ticks and reduce infection with Lyme disease spirochetes in tick vectors and rodent reservoirs</article-title><source>J Med Entomol</source><year>2016</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1063</fpage><lpage>1092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jme/tjw103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27439616?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27439616</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>