<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several plant species with medicinal importance have already been explored; however, there are many unexplored higher plant species. In the search of such species, the present study was conducted, where 
 <italic>Fernandoa adenophylla</italic> was explored scientifically. 
 <italic>F. adenophylla</italic> is a member of the family 
 <italic>Bignoniacea</italic>, which is dispersed in Africa and Southeast Asia.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>
 </sup> This species is also known as Ziron, Dhopa-phali, Mostanphul, Karen wood, and Lotum-poh.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>F. adenophylla</italic> has been used in the folkloric system for the treatment of constipation (Bangladesh), haemorrhoids (Bangladesh), and snake bites (India) as well as skin disorders in Thailand.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>
 </sup> Traditionally, this plant is used by local people for the treatment of premature ejaculation, nocturnal emission, diabetes, amenorrhoea, microbial infections, sepsis, and other skin diseases.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>
 </sup> The different extracts of 
 <italic>F. adenophylla</italic> have been documented to have various pharmacological effects, including antihypertensive, leishmanicidal antifungal, antibacterial, and anti-TB properties.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>
 </sup> Plants contain different phytochemicals, such as β-amyrin, lapachol, α-lapchone adenophylone, dehydro-α-lapchone, dehydro-iso-α-lapchone, dilapachone, tecomoquinone-I, and β-sitosterol.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>
 </sup> All species of 
 <italic>Bignoniacea</italic> contain lapachol in relatively large amounts. Lapachol and its derivatives have been reported to have a wide variety of biological activities, including anti-inflammatory, antimalarial, antiendemic, antiulcer, anticarcinogenic, antiabscess, viricidal, and termiticical activities.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>
 </sup> The chemical constituents including peshawaraquinone, indanone derivatives, lapachol, and α-lapachol have been documented for phosphodiesterase 1 and anti-inflammatory properties. Based on medicinal importance, this study was designed to investigate the antinociceptive effects, muscle coordination, and molecular docking of peshawaraquinone isolated from 
 <italic>F. adenophylla.</italic>
</p>
