<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Molecular docking of standard drugs and bioactives from medicinal plants with receptor molecules was performed using AutoDock Vina (Trott &amp; Olson, 
 <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The catalytic site of SARS-CoV-2 M
 <sup>pro</sup> (His41 and Cys145), receptor binding motif of S-protein (Leu455, Phe486, Glu493 and Ser494) and hotspot binding residues of ACE2 receptor (Lys31 and Lys353) were chosen as binding sites for docking analysis (Jin et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Lan et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Shang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Veeramachaneni et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Yan et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Grid box was generated using ADT with dimensions relative to the ligands (XYZ) with a resolution of 1 Å. The prepared ligand and receptor files were submitted to AutoDock Vina (Trott &amp; Olson, 
 <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Each docking calculations were repeated three times using different seeds and retaining the remaining values as default. Final protein-ligand interactive models were chosen based on the binding affinity as well as the molecular contacts. The hydrogen bond (H-bond), hydrophobic contacts were calculated using LigPlot+ (Laskowski &amp; Swindells, 
 <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). The binding energy (BE) for each ligand-receptor docked complexes was obtained, and 2D conformations were generated using LigPlot+. Further, the inhibition constant (Ki) for standard drugs and medicinal plant bioactives with SARS-CoV-2 protein targets was determined using the following equation (Onawole et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). 
 <disp-formula id="M0001">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="TBSD_A_1842246_M0001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="d2e1274">
    <mrow>
     <mtext>Ki</mtext>
     <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
     <mn>1</mn>
     <msup>
      <mrow>
       <mn>0</mn>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
       <mtext>Binding</mtext>
       <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
       <mtext>energy</mtext>
       <mo>/</mo>
       <mn>1.366</mn>
       <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
      </mrow>
     </msup>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
