<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another significant group of bioactive compounds are phenylpropanoids, which are naturally synthesized by plants. However, research has shown that endophytes also produce phenylpropanoids. These compounds belong to the largest group of secondary metabolites that possess an aromatic ring with a 3-carbon propene tail, thus resulting in a C6-C3 carbon skeleton. These compounds are from the amino acids phenylalanine and tyrosine [
 <xref rid="B66-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. In cancerous cells, phenylpropanoids prevent overexpression of histone deacetylase (HDAC), thus inhibiting the cell cycle and inducing apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B66-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Phenylpropanoid derivatives possessing antimicrobial activities have been extracted from the endophytic fungus 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp. (ZJ-68), associated with mangrove [
 <xref rid="B67-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. In another study, fusarubin and anhydrofusarubin isolated from 
 <italic>Cladosporium</italic> species inhibited cell growth and induced apoptosis of human cancer cell lines HL-60, U937, and Jurkat [
 <xref rid="B68-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Although both compounds significantly increased apoptosis of these cancerous cells with increase in concentrations, fusarubin significantly decreased the percentage of cells in the S phase while increasing those in the G2/M phase [
 <xref rid="B68-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. On the contrary, anhydrofusarubin increased the percentage of cells in the G0/G1 phase but decreased those in the S and G2/M phases [
 <xref rid="B68-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. These findings provide a valid basis for the need to focus on investigations aimed at constantly assessing the potential of endophytic fungi to produce bioactive compounds, given the evidence that they have an array of metabolites, such as alkaloids, macrolides, terpenoids, flavonoids, glycosides, xanthones, isocoumarins, quinones, phenylpropanoids, aliphatic metabolites, and lactones, with powerful anticancer properties [
 <xref rid="B69-microorganisms-08-01934" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Nonetheless, only a small proportion of endophytes have been investigated so far, thus requiring more research in the niche area. 
</p>
