<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par50" class="p">Simultaneously, phytochemical diversity drives plant–insect community diversity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>]. Lavender-visiting insects, including herbivores, natural enemies and pollinators, were investigated for the first time along with the maturity of lavender inflorescence. Mounting evidence has highlighted the role of volatile terpenoids in communication between plants and insects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>]. The flower buds of lavender emerge in early April at north of China, when the weather is dry and rainless and aphids multiply quickly. Besides lavender, many other plants, such as mint (
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> × 
 <italic class="italic">piperita</italic>), peach tree 
 <italic class="italic">(Amygdalus persica</italic>), pepper (
 <italic class="italic">Zanthoxylum bungeanum</italic>) and 
 <italic class="italic">Hemistepta lyrata</italic>, were attacked heavily during this period of time. Our study showed that (+)-R-limonene and 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-trans-ocimene are the two highest compounds in the EOs of FB0, and can get rid of aphids in Y-tube bioassay. Previous studies have reported that monoterpenes such as limonene, linalool or ocimene, are usually released within 24 h after attack and plants overexpressed genes encoding linalool, limonene, cymene and ocimene-related synthetases exhibit higher activity in inhibiting infestation of aphids [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>]. Transcriptomic dynamics over various developmental stages revealed that 
 <italic class="italic">LIMS</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">BOS</italic> expressed strongly in tender and succulent FB0 sample, which is one of prospective host of aphids. Therefore, we supposed that the original bud of FB0 could release some specific volatiles (limonene, 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-ocimene and 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-pinene etc.) to defend aphids, resulting that the lavender can prevent further damage caused by herbivores and get through this key developmental stage. In addition to the direct defence by plants themselves, predatory insects attracted by lavender such as ladybirds, lacewings, spiders, and hoverflies may contribute to eliminating the aphids. Many reports have demonstrated that an array of volatiles, referred to as herbivore-induced plant volatiles, are produced when plants encounter aggressive insects, resulting in the attraction of natural enemies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>]. Taken together, the development of lavender inflorescences and associated volatiles may play an important role in structuring plant-associated insect communities to accommodate survival and the evolutionary ‘arms race’.
</p>
