<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0125">
 <italic>A. moschata</italic> is a medicinal plant, which has been traditionally used in ethnomedicine to treat various digestive disorders in humans and animals. For this plant, 
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Vitalini et al. (2016)</xref> showed a broad spectrum of antimicrobial activity against some food pathogen bacteria, such as 
 <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic>, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aereus</italic>, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic>, and 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>. The present study aimed to evaluate the effects of the main pure compounds of 
 <italic>A. moschata</italic> essential oil and the essential oil on in vitro rumen fermentation and the microbiome. To the best of our knowledge, the role of 
 <italic>A. moschata</italic> essential oil in modifying rumen metabolism and enhancing nutrient utilization by animals has never been investigated. The main compounds of 
 <italic>A. moschata</italic> essential oil are BOR, CAM, and EUCA. Interestingly, these compounds gave promising results for lower enteric CH
 <sub>4</sub> production in short-time in vitro incubations without decreasing SCFA production (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Joch et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). In Exp. 1 (48 h of incubation), the GP and SCFA did not decrease with the additives, whereas in Exp. 2 (9 d of incubation), the addition of EUCA decreased SCFA production, which is possibly related to lower digestibility of the diet supplemented with EUCA. The difference between the 2 experiments might be due to several reasons, such as different doses used, the different donor animals, and the possible adaptation of rumen bacteria to the additives. The selected compounds were oxygenated monoterpenes, which degrade little in the rumen; for example, 
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Malecky et al. (2012)</xref> showed that after 24 h of incubation with the caprine rumen inoculum, oxygen-containing terpenes were less degraded than linear and monocyclic terpenes. Hence, it can be speculated that in the short trial (Exp. 1), the additives were slowly degraded, whereas in Exp. 2, the rumen microbiome was probably more adapted to the additives. Similarly, 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Cardozo et al. (2004)</xref>, using a continuous fermenter, observed a different SCFA profile due to essential oil supplementations at 2 d of fermentation, whereas these differences disappeared at longer fermentation lengths (e.g., 6 d) due to rumen microbial adaptation.
</p>
