<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Criteria of a clear driver of changes were only partially met for 
 <italic>I. glandulifera</italic> in the present study. If the species was a clear driver, planted 
 <italic>I. glandulifera</italic> should establish and clearly suppress natives, while removal would lead to recovery of the native vegetation (Bauer, 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Didham et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; MacDougall &amp; Turkington, 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>)⁠. In the present study, planted 
 <italic>I. glandulifera</italic> reached similar, but slightly smaller sizes than naturally growing ones. Establishment and growth of 
 <italic>I. glandulifera</italic> were lower in alder forests than in meadows. Thus, 
 <italic>I. glandulifer</italic>a growth was slightly restricted by resident vegetation and native plant species α‐diversity was not affected at all. Species composition, vegetation height, 
 <italic>U. dioica</italic> total biomass, and 
 <italic>U. dioica</italic> cover differed among invaded and uninvaded plots. However, they were not subsequently affected by removal and planting of 
 <italic>I. glandulifera</italic>. On the one hand, this can indicate that differences between invaded and uninvaded plots were not caused by 
 <italic>I. glandulifera</italic> but are due to other factors, such as habitat conditions or disturbances. If these factors already differed between plots before 
 <italic>I. glandulifera</italic> invasion, they themselves could be one reason for the invasion success at a particular patch. In this case, only comparing invaded and uninvaded patches observationally could lead to the false conclusion that 
 <italic>I. glandulifera</italic> has a negative impact on native vegetation. On the other hand, a response of the native vegetation to the 
 <italic>I. glandulifera</italic> manipulations indicating a causal effect could take longer time than the study duration of one season (Cockel et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Rusterholz et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Also between‐year variations could obscure long‐term effects. However, the manipulations affected total native biomass and performance of 
 <italic>U. dioica</italic>, the response of which is faster and more sensitive in comparison with diversity measures. This indicates a fast competitive and allelopathic effect on the growth of neighboring plants as known for the annual 
 <italic>I. glandulifera</italic> from the seedling stage onwards (Bieberich et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Gruntman et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Another limitation of this experimental study design is that the removal and planting of any other plant species could have the same effect as the removal and planting of 
 <italic>I. glandulifera</italic>, and thus the results might not be specific to 
 <italic>I. glandulifera</italic>. However, results of the present study are corroborated by a previous observational study within the same sites, which underpins that 
 <italic>I. glandulifera</italic> has no impact on α‐diversity, species composition, and vegetation height, but on abundance of 
 <italic>U. dioica</italic> (Bieberich et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). We suggest that continuing the manipulations for more than one season may lead to a change of total abundance of 
 <italic>U. dioica</italic> as a consequence of the reduced growth of individual plants.
</p>
