<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There is an urgent need for new antimicrobial ingredients specifically targeting oral pathogens such as 
 <italic class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus cereus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> sp. Despite the availability of robust preservatives food spoilage and poisoning caused by microorganisms remains a problem that has not yet been brought under adequate control. Natural preservatives as an alternative to the artificial ones are therefore needed to achieve sufficiently long shelf-life of foods and a high degree of safety with respect to foodborne pathogenic microorganisms. Several studies have been performed to investigate whether classical hop extracts, supercritical hop extracts or extracts obtained by isomerization of supercritical hop extracts, could be used as antimicrobial agents against foodborne pathogens and also against microorganisms capable of causing food spoilage due to the high content of phenolic phytoalexins, e.g., flavonoids. Screening of plant extracts and their constituents has a well-established history for searching novel anti-infective agents effective against cariogenic and periodontal bacteria [
 <xref rid="B39-nutrients-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Nowadays, plant antiseptics are incorporated into a whole range of oral products. The substances responsible for this activity are mainly the hop acids, which are classified as α-acids (humulones), β-acids (lupulones), and their oxidation products. These substances consist of a mixture of homologous compounds [
 <xref rid="B20-nutrients-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Residues attained in the process of hops extraction, which comprises a waste product from the brewing industry, may be used as a cheap source of natural compounds with dual functions (as an antioxidant and antimicrobial agent) of wide application.
</p>
