<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <p>The present study investigated the effects of hot water extracts of 22 medicinal plants used traditionally to treat diabetes on Dipeptidyl peptidase-IV (DPP-IV) activity both 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
  <italic>in vivo</italic> in high-fat fed (HFF) obese-diabetic rats. Fluorometric assay was employed to determine the DPP-IV activity. For 
  <italic>in vivo</italic> studies, HFF obese-diabetic rats were fasted for 6 h and blood was sampled at different times before and after the oral administration of the glucose alone (18 mmol/kg body weight) or with either of the four most active plant extracts (250 mg/5 ml/kg, body weight) or established DPP-IV inhibitors (10 μmol/5 ml/kg). DPP-IV inhibitors: sitagliptin, vildagliptin and diprotin A, decreased enzyme activity by a maximum of 95–99% (
  <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001). Among the 22 natural anti-diabetic plants tested, 
  <italic>Anogeissus</italic>
  <italic>Latifolia</italic> exhibited the most significant (
  <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001) inhibitory activity (96 ± 1%) with IC
  <sub>50</sub> and IC
  <sub>25</sub> values of 754 and 590 μg/ml. Maximum inhibitory effects of other extracts: 
  <italic>Aegle marmelos, Mangifera indica, Chloropsis cochinchinensis, Trigonella foenum-graecum</italic> and 
  <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic> were (44 ±7%; 38 ± 4%; 31±1%; 28±2%; 27±2%, respectively). A maximum of 45% inhibition was observed with &gt;25 μM concentrations of selected phytochemicals (rutin). 
  <italic>A.</italic>
  <italic>latifolia, A. marmelos, T. foenum-graecum</italic> and 
  <italic>M. indica</italic> extracts improved glucose tolerance, insulin release, reduced DPP-IV activity and increased circulating active GLP-1 in HFF obese-diabetic rats (
  <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05–0.001). These results suggest that ingestion of selected natural anti-diabetic plants, in particular 
  <italic>A. latifolia, A. marmelos, T. foenum-graecum</italic> and 
  <italic>M. indica</italic> can substantially inhibit DPP-IV and improve glucose homeostasis, thereby providing a useful therapeutic approach for the treatment of T2DM.
 </p>
</abstract>
