<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observations of Fungal Morphology and Ultrastructure</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The action mechanism of CEO was determined using transmission electron microscopy (TEM) according to a previous study with minor modifications (
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">Bozzola and Russell, 1999</a>). Seven-day-old 
  <span class="italic">C. acutatum</span> exposed to 0, MFC and 2MFC of CEO were cultivated in the dark at 25°C for 2 days. The mycelia was harvested from PDA with 10 mL of SDW and softly scraping the colonies with a sterile L-shaped glass rod. The mycelium suspension was centrifuged at 7000 
  <span class="italic">g</span> for 15 min to obtain mycelia. The small segments measuring 5 × 5 mm were excised at the margin of the mycelium colony. Then, the segments were promptly placed in vials containing 2.5% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 mol/L phosphate buffer saline (PBS) (pH 7.2) at 4°C and fixed overnight. The fixed samples were rinsed with the same buffer three times for 10 min. Afterward, the samples were dehydrated in a graded series of ethanol (70, 80, 90, 95, and 100%, 
  <span class="italic">v/v</span>) for 20 min in each alcohol dilution. The last step was performed for 30 min thrice. The dehydrated specimens were then embedded and polymerized in Spurr’s resin at 65°C for 72 h. Ultrathin sections (approximately 50 nm in thickness) were hand trimmed with a diamond knife using an MT-X Ultratome for TEM observations (H-600, Hitachi Co. Ltd., Tokyo, Japan).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Membrane integrity was determined using fluorescent microscope (FSM) according to a previous study with minor modifications (
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">Liu et al., 2010</a>). 
  <span class="italic">C. acutatum</span> was treated with the MFC of CEO as described previously. PDA plates without CEO were served as negative controls. Mycelia were collected after incubation for 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 days in the dark at 25°C, and washed with cold PBS (0.05 mol/L, pH 7.0) to remove residual medium, respectively. Mycelia were then fixed by cold ethanol (70%, 
  <span class="italic">v/v</span>) at 4°C for 1 h. After removal of ethanol, and the mycelia were washed twice with PBS. Then the mycelia were stained with 50 μg/mL propidium iodide for 20 min at 4°C in the dark. Mycelia were collected by centrifugation (4000 ×
  <span class="italic">g</span> for 10 min), and washed twice with PBS to remove residual dye. Samples were observed with the E200 Nikon Eclipse microscope (Nikon Co., Tokyo, Japan). Fields of view from each cover slip were chosen randomly, and each treatment was replicated thrice and the experiment was repeated thrice. The number of spores in bright-field was defined as the total number, and membrane integrity (MI) was calculated as:
 </p>
 <div id="E3" class="disp-formula" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="M3" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <span class="mtext">MI</span>
    <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
    <span class="mi">%</span>
    <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
    <span class="mo">=</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mo">[</span>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">1</span>
      <span class="mo">−</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mo">(</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="mfrac">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mtext">number of stained spores</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mtext">number of total spores</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">)</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">]</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">×</span>
    <span class="mn">100</span>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
