<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par53">Most of the identified phytochemicals in 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> seed oil have previously been reported to show antidiabetic, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, anticancer, antimicrobial, anti-arthritic, anticonvulsant, antiulcer, antihypertensive, anti-nociceptive, hepatoprotective, cytotoxic, antimycomicrobial, antiparasitic, and analgesic activities (Marques et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2019</xref>; Caboni et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2012</xref>; Begum et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2016</xref>; Lang and Buchbauer 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2012</xref>; Balamurugan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2013</xref>; Muniyan and Gurunathan 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2016</xref>; Saeed et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2012</xref>; Zhao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2018</xref>; Adeoye-Isijola et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2018</xref>; Wu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2017</xref>; Chavan et al. 2009; Yimer et al. 2019; Hadi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2016</xref>; Engels and Brinkmann 2017). These compounds showed varying degrees of binding on the SARS-CoV-2 protein targets (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), as revealed by the change in Gibb’s free energy values (ΔG) (Duru and Duru 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2020</xref>). The FDA emergency approved drug Remdesivir (Williamson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2020</xref>), administered on adults and children with suspected or confirmed cases of COVID-19, was used as a control to identify compounds with good binding affinities for the studied COVID-19 proteins. Caryophyllene oxide had the best binding affinities on 3CLpro (− 6.0 kcal/mol), NSP3 (− 6.3 kcal/mol), NSP9 (− 6.3 kcal/mol), and RDRP (− 6.9 kcal/mol) targets. The compound α-bergamotene gave the best binding affinity on RPIA (5.7 kcal/mol), while β-bisabolene displayed an excellent binding affinity on the ACE2 protein target. These values were very close to those obtained using the antiviral control drug. The binding affinity of β-bisabolene (− 8.0 kcal/mol) was almost similar to Remdesivir (− 8.1 kcal/mol) on the ACE2 target. This observation is an indication that β-bisabolene could prevent the interaction of the spike glycoprotein of the virus with the ACE2 protein of the human host cell, thereby preventing infection of the host.
</p>
