<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par62">Sphingosine kinases (SphKs) play an important role in the production of sphingosine-1-phosphate (S1P). For blocking SphK dependent angiogenesis probably needed inhibition of both isoforms of SphK. Gustin et al., identified a new series of SphK inhibitors by structure-based approach. New synthesized compounds can be inhibited both isoforms of SphK (SphK1/SphK2) and specific- SphK1. Human SphK1/2 biochemical assay and WM266-4 cell assay was performed for synthesized compounds. The activity of compound 
 <bold>71a</bold> and 
 <bold>71b</bold> was determined against SphK1, SphK2 with IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.02, 0.1 µM for 
 <bold>71a</bold> and IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.003, 0.04 µM for 
 <bold>71b</bold> and against WM266-4 cell (EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.09 µM for 
 <bold>71a</bold> and EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.36 µM for 
 <bold>71b</bold>). Then, in biochemical assays, compound 
 <bold>71b</bold> showed more potent than 
 <bold>71a</bold>. Pharmacokinetic parameters were evaluated for both compounds in rat, for example, moderate clearance obtained for them. Compound 
 <bold>71a</bold> exhibited reasonable bioavailability in mice and with having good pharmacokinetic properties, showed high selectivity against SphKs. In compound 
 <bold>71a</bold>, IC
 <sub>50</sub> values for murine SphK and murine SphK2 obtained 0.07 and &gt;10 µM and in compound 
 <bold>71b</bold>, IC
 <sub>50</sub> values determined 0.02 and &gt;10 µM. The pharmacodynamic assay was also assessed for compound 
 <bold>71a</bold> and investigated the circulating levels of S1P and levels of 
 <bold>71a</bold> in plasma. According to the SAR studies, (2 R, 4 S)-2-(hydroxymethyl) piperidin-4-ol moiety as a critical structure formed hydrogen bonds with Asp81 and Asp178. A hydrogen bond made between the oxygen of the piperidine hydroxymethyl and the carboxyl of Asp178 and the oxygen of the 4-hydroxy piperidine and the carboxyl of Asp81 interacted with together by H-binding. A polar pocket including Asp81 and Asp178 filled using the piperidine. An excess methyl group in the 4- position of the piperidine reduced about tenfold potency. Two chlorine atoms on phenyl group were set in a hydrophobic pocket. The van der Waals interaction was made between the 
 <italic>meta</italic>-chlorine and Met306, Leu261, and Leu268. The 
 <italic>para</italic>-chlorine seen to form van der Waals interactions with Phe288, His311, and Leu319 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig15" ref-type="fig">15</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>].
</p>
