<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>
  <underline>Purpose:</underline> Reflecting the extended scope of the valid EMA regulation, this analysis intends to contribute to the knowledge about risk for participants in first-in-human (FiH) multiple-dose studies. 
  <underline>Materials and methods:</underline> All FiH multiple-dose studies in healthy subjects performed by the Bayer Department of Clinical Pharmacology, Cardiovascular, between 2006 and 2019 were analyzed. Study reports were reviewed for study designs, demographics, treatment-emergent adverse events (TEAEs), and safety laboratory results above the 1.5-fold of the upper limit of normal (aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), creatine kinase (CK), amylase, lipase, glutamate dehydrogenase (GLDH), gamma glutamyl transpeptidase (GGT), total bilirubin, and creatinine in serum), and data were analyzed. 
  <underline>Results:</underline> 12 out of 16 studies were included. Indications for development were cardiovascular (7), pulmonary (3), kidney (1), and hematological (1) diseases. 496 healthy male subjects (mean age 33.8 years, mean BMI of 24.7 kg/m
  <sup>2</sup>) received treatment (370 active, 126 placebo). 293 subjects had at least 1 TEAE (59.1%): 231 (62.4%) after active treatment and 126 (49.2%) after placebo. Subjects with a maximum TEAE intensity of moderate did not differ between active and placebo. The only severe TEAE was unrelated to the study, the only serious TEAE on active treatment was not considered drug-related. Subjects had a significantly higher relative risk on active treatment versus placebo to experience an overall TEAE. No relevant differences between active and placebo for the analyzed laboratory increases were seen. 
  <underline>Conclusion:</underline> Subjects were not exposed to an undue risk in the analyzed studies. Adverse events and laboratory value increases occur frequently under placebo treatment. The results can help in the risk stratification for and interpretation of other phase I studies. 
 </p>
</abstract>
