<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010" class="p">Extraction by the steam explosion is a relatively new and developing method that in through self-evaporation results in the displacement of a large part of the volatile molecules in the plant (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Meng and Ragauskas, 2014</xref>). This process is based on the volatility of fugacious compounds where, the raw materials are exposed to saturated vapor for a short period of time, which varies by product type. Extraction of citrus essential oil performed by hydro-distillation with ambient pressure is traditionally used. Today, citrus fruit is extensively grown from temperate to tropical zones within the northern and southern. In the processing of citrus, the peels remain as a waste. One of the products from citrus peel is essential oil that is aromatic liquids characterized by an odor and produced by citrus peels (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Guenther, 1948</xref>). Essential oil Citrus is intensively collected in oil glands of the peel (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Boussaada et al., 2007</xref>), accounting for about 1–3% fresh weight on average (
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Njoroge et al., 2005</xref>). Essential oil Citrus is a complex combination of natural ingredients that can contain compounds with different concentrations and has significant applications in the pharmaceutical and food industries. Due to the attention of various industries to this valuable product, the presence of the essential substance of limonene (the major combination of essential oils in orange peel), which has antimicrobial, antioxidant, biological properties and herbal fragrance (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bauer et al., 2008</xref>). Recently, Citrus essential oil has been acknowledged no longer handiest for its fragrant features however additionally for its physiological homes, along with chemo-prevention in opposition to most cancers and aromatherapy consequences (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dorman and Deans, 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Murthy et al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
