<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pomegranate is a source of bioactive compounds, present both in the fruit (peel and arils), and in the leaves and bark [
 <xref rid="B72-plants-09-01214" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Ozgen et al. [
 <xref rid="B73-plants-09-01214" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] affirm that pomegranate is a fruit rich in phenolic antioxidants, specifically anthocyanins, but their content varies between varieties, or sub-species. The fruit has a large number of flavonoids, it is estimated that about 0.2% to 1% of the weight of the fruit represent this group of compounds, of which about 30% of all the anthocyanidins are in the peel [
 <xref rid="B74-plants-09-01214" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Pomegranate juice has a high content of polyphenols, significant amounts of ellagic acid, caffeic acid, chlorogenic acid, coumaric acid, catechins, ferulic acid and a large list of anthocyanins [
 <xref rid="B75-plants-09-01214" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. The literature indicates that pomegranate contains 124 different compounds and that among these phytochemicals, high molecular weight polyphenols (such as ellagitannins and punicalagin) are likely to mediate most of the fruit’s protective effects against harmful agents [
 <xref rid="B75-plants-09-01214" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. In the peel, almost 48 phenolic compounds have been identified [
 <xref rid="B76-plants-09-01214" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Some authors identified and quantified phenolic compounds with more than 50 varieties of pomegranate fruits, using high-performance liquid chromatography with electrospray ionization and mass spectrometry (HPLC-DAD-ESI/MS
 <sup>n</sup>), they concluded that ellagitannins were the most abundant compounds in all the investigated samples (mesocarp, peel, arils, juices), and all the varieties had ellagitannins and anthocyanins [
 <xref rid="B77-plants-09-01214" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-plants-09-01214" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. All these data were taken from studies in 
 <italic>P. granatum</italic> L. It can be hypothesized that these compounds are also present in 
 <italic>P. protopunica</italic> Balf., however there is a large information gap in this regard. Hundreds of studies have been conducted in which the antioxidant capacity and total phenols of 
 <italic>P. granatum</italic> L. are evaluated, however, for 
 <italic>P. protopunica</italic> Balf., the scenario is different. It is curious that there are not enough published studies of the content of total phenols and antioxidant effect of 
 <italic>P. protopunica</italic> Balf. Nor did we find studies of the nutrimental and chemical composition of the fruit. This may be due in the first place to the isolation of the species, and also due to the difficulty in obtaining government permits, as it originates from a declared a World Heritage Site. Perhaps there are unpublished works.
</p>
