<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the main purpose of our study was not to investigate the added value of patient involvement in medicines R&amp;D as such, our respondent outcomes overlap with earlier findings from others in this regard (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). In general, stakeholders share a sense of urgency and express an overall interest with respect to patient involvement in medicines R&amp;D. They furthermore share a strong wish for capacity and capability building and agree that a Dutch version of the EUPATI training program could meet the needs that arise from such a wish. Stakeholders expect EUPATI to be a relevant and high-quality training program and thereby to contribute to an increase in the pool of patient experts available for patient involvement activities. It is believed that in addition to their valuable experiences as a patient, substantial knowledge of terminology, and the complex process of development of medicinal products is necessary for patients to be equal partners in the dialogue with stakeholders (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). By focusing on both technical knowledge and relevant skills in general, not only will the quality of the outcomes of the engagement activity benefit (e.g., the patient's advice), but so will the engagement process as such. Klingmann et al. (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) have already stated that if patients can obtain knowledge through education, multiple impactful roles in the medicine development process come within reach. Training may also be beneficial for restoring the power balance between patients and professionals from other stakeholder groups. According to Abma (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), patients need to develop a strong, self-conscious position before they are ready to participate and enter into a dialogue with researchers about their agenda. As well as concrete output from trained patient representatives, as graduates of a particular cohort, stakeholders also believe that a Dutch EUPATI course will indirectly add to the incentive for patient involvement in the Netherlands in general. As such, this is in line with previous observations that a combined effort of governmental organizations, the academic world, patient organizations, health foundations, and the pharmaceutical industry to share knowledge and resources in order to address the challenges of pharmaceutical innovation will be beneficial for all (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Internationally, the PARADIGM consortium is currently investigating the return on investment of patient involvement initiatives and metrics for quantitative and qualitative assessment. The initial publications from this consortium suggest a key role for education and empowerment in evaluating benefits and costs (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).
</p>
