<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The prevalence of LAB in cereal ecosystems and their contribution to the improvement of this particular fermentation processes could be due to their biochemical and metabolic characteristics (
 <xref rid="B248" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">248</xref>). Studies of enzymes, like phytases involved in nutritional aspects in determined ecosystems, are important for the understanding of particular traits of LAB that are relevant for their right exploitation as starters (
 <xref rid="B249" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">249</xref>). The PA contained in gluten free flours can be reduced by lactic acid fermentation, directly by LAB phytase activity or indirectly providing the optimal conditions to the endogenous phytase activity (
 <xref rid="B250" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">250</xref>). Several studies were carried out on different aspects of LAB phytases in cereals fermentation (
 <xref rid="B129" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">129</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">130</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B163" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">163</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B238" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">238</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B251" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">251</xref>–
 <xref rid="B253" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">253</xref>), nevertheless, there are only few reports of these enzymes in autochthonous LAB isolated from pseudocereals. Carrizo et al. (
 <xref rid="B166" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">166</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">167</xref>) reported high phytase activities in LAB strains isolated from quinoa and amaranth (grains and sourdough), such as 
 <italic class="italic">E. durans</italic> CRL 2122 (1,041 ± 48 U/mL), 
 <italic class="italic">E. mundtii</italic> CRL 2007 (957 ± 25 U/ml) and 
 <italic class="italic">L. plantarum</italic> CRL 2106 (730 ± 25 U/mL), among other. Afterwards, the minerals bioavailability present in pasta made with quinoa flour as a dietary matrix and fermented by selected LAB producing phytase was evaluated in an animal model. The animal group fed with the bio-enriched pasta fermented by LAB (
 <italic class="italic">L. plantarum</italic> CRL 2107 + CRL 1964) showed higher concentrations of minerals (P, Ca
 <sup class="sup">+2</sup>, Fe
 <sup class="sup">+2</sup>, and Mg
 <sup class="sup">+2</sup>) with respect to control animal group (
 <xref rid="B218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">218</xref>). Also, Rizzello et al. (
 <xref rid="B186" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">186</xref>) reported that the use of quinoa sourdough with autochthonous LAB (
 <italic class="italic">L. plantarum</italic> T6B10 and 
 <italic class="italic">L. rossiae</italic> T0A16) increased phytase activity during the fermentation respect to non-fermented flour. The results confirmed that quinoa fermented with selected starters had a phytase activity ca. 2.75- times higher than raw quinoa flour.
</p>
