<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">Hydrodistillation method is the best method to purify and quantify the essential oil from plant and it also one of the universally approved method (
 <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Rajivgandhi et al., 2020a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Rajivgandhi et al., 2020b</xref>). Briefly, the collected leaves were dried after surface sterilization with D·H
 <sub>2</sub>O and maintained 15 days in dark condition. The dried plant leaves were ground by using master and pestle for nice powder. The nice thin content of the plant powder was performed to hydrodistillation 12 h in Clevenger’s apparatus. After 12 h, the essential oil was collected and separated the organic and aqueous phase. Finally, the organic phase of was dried over using sodium anhydrous sulphate and stored at 4 °C for further use. After, the crude essential oil powder was mixed into methanol (99%) to dissolve the powder. Consequently, the sample was analyzed by using HRLC-MS (Model 6745, Agilent Technology, CA, America) for complete analysis of the powder content including phytochemical compounds, proteins, amino acids, nutrients and bioactive compounds. The HRLC-MS was connected with DB-5 colomn 925 × 0.22 mm), the film thickness was used as o. 30 µm. The software was fitted by turbo mass gold mass spectrometer. The injector temperature was maintained at 240 °C. The temperatures of 40 °C and 240 °C were set initially and finally respectively. The injected volume and helium carrier gas was designed as 1 mL and 1 mL /m respectively. The solution of methanol was used for analysis. In addition, the 100 K Pa of pressure, 70 eV of energy, 1000 rate of decomposition and 0.50 range of decomposition were set. After successful completion of program, the instrument was run and allowed 4 h for complete analysis. After completion of the program, the available chemical constituents of the compounds were noted. The resulted chemical constituents were compared with Wiley library database of the Bharathidasan University NIST and confirm the available compounds.
</p>
