<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A 100 mm silicon wafer was cleaned with a Piranha solution and subsequently rinsed with DI water. Afterwards it was bathed in 1% hydrofluoric acid for 1 min and rinsed again with DI water. The wafer was then heated for 20 min at 200°C for dehydration. The silicon-SU-8 mould contained two stacked layers of photoresist. The first layer of SU-8 2002 of 4.5 μm (micro resist technology GmbH, Germany) photoresist was spincoated onto the wafer. Therefore, 1.5 mL of resist was applied and spincoated at 3800 rpm for 35 s. Then the wafer was softbaked at 65°C for 3 min followed by 3 min at 95°C. The photomask containing the cultivation chamber geometries (cultivation chambers) was aligned with the wafer at vacuum contact mode using a mask aligner (MA/BA Gen4 Pro Serie mit MO-Exposure Optic, SUSS MicroTec Lithography GmbH, Germany) and exposed to 350 nm 400 nm light with 700 mJ/cm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>. Afterwards post exposure baking was performed (3 min at 65°C and 3 min at 95°C). The wafer was placed in SU-8 developer for 1 min and transferred into a second container with fresh SU-8 developer for a few seconds. Then the wafer was rinsed in isopropanol to remove any SU-8 developer residue and dried using nitrogen gas flow. Afterwards a hard bake was performed for 10 min at 150°C. The second SU-8 layer of 10 μm SU-8 was spincoated onto the wafer at 2600 rpm for 35 s. The coated wafer was softbaked for 3.5 min at 65°C and 3 min at 95°C. The second layer photomask incorporating the geometries for the medium supply channels was aligned in the mask aligner with the first layer mask and exposed to 350 nm 400 nm light with 800 mJ/cm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> in vacuum contact mode. Afterwards, a SU-8 post exposure bake was performed on a hotplate for 3 min at 65°C and 3 min at 95°C. The wafer was again placed in SU-8 developer for 45 s and transferred into a second container with fresh SU-8 developer for 60 s. To remove any SU-8 developer residue the wafer was rinsed 20 s with isopropanol and dried with nitrogen gas. Finally, a hard bake was performed for 6 h at 150°C. The finished wafer was used as master mould for PDMS moulding. To validate the structure heights profilometer measurements (Dektak 150, Veeco, USA) were made. Finally, the accuracy of the structures was controlled optically using a microscope.
</p>
