<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Various hydrogel formulations with 
 <italic>Chlorella vulgaris</italic> extracts were prepared and tested in vivo on Swiss albino mice with induced skin injuries; an antibacterial gel was used as reference [
 <xref rid="B157-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>]. The extracts were characterized in terms of phytochemical profile, exhibiting triterpenes among the active compounds; their topical application revealed pro-healing and anti-inflammatory properties with no atopic or allergic side effects even at high concentrations. Chitosan-gelatin hydrogel films were designed for the entrapment of lupeol, aiming to obtain an ideal wound dressing; in vitro assays revealed a sustained release of lupeol, antioxidant properties as well as lack of toxicity thus qualifying the hydrogel films as promising wound healing formulations [
 <xref rid="B158-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. A hydrogel was prepared by tosylating β-cyclodextrin and grafting the product on polyethyleneimine, followed by cross linkage with silk fibroin; the hydrogel was loaded with 
 <italic>Centella asiatica</italic> extract and hydrocortisone and reduced significantly the wound healing time of pressure sores [
 <xref rid="B159-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>]. 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> extract, containing a triterpene mixture, was complexed with hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin and formulated as topical spray which showed high efficacy in the treatment of excision wounds inflicted on rats [
 <xref rid="B160-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>]. An asiaticoside-rich fraction was separated from an extract obtained using the 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> aerial part and then formulated as hydrogel based on polyvinylalcohol and polyethylene glycol through the freeze-thaw method; the hydrogel was assessed in vivo on rabbits with induced skin injuries by means of the incision model [
 <xref rid="B161-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. Experimental results showed that the tested hydrogel accelerated the healing process even compared to commercial creams used as reference while no irritation phenomena were reported.
</p>
