<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Description</italic>. 
 <italic>Sclerotia</italic> globose, subglobose, oval to irregularly shaped, up to 28 cm long and 22 cm wide, weighing up to 20 kg; when fresh, outer crust reddish brown, inner context white and corky; outer crust becomes hard corky and inner context becomes fragile when dry. 
 <italic>Basidiocarp</italic> annual, resupinate, soft corky and without odor or taste when fresh, hard corky to fragile when dry, up to 20 cm long, 10 cm wide, 5.5 mm thick at center. 
 <italic>Margin</italic> thin, usually pores extend to the very edge. 
 <italic>Pore surface</italic> cream to ash gray when fresh, becoming pinkish buff to cinnamon buff when dry, not glancing; pores round, angular or sinuous, 1–2 per mm; dissepiments thick, slightly lacerate to distinctly dentate. 
 <italic>Subiculum</italic> cinnamon buff, hard corky, up to 1.5 mm; 
 <italic>tubes</italic> hard corky to fragile, buff, up to 4 mm long. 
 <italic>Hyphal system</italic> dimitic in all parts, generative hyphae with simple septa, skeletal hyphae dominant, all hyphae IKI–, CB–, weakly inflated in KOH. 
 <italic>Subicular hyphal structure</italic> homogeneous, hyphae strongly interwoven; generative hyphae occasionally present, hyaline, thin-walled, occasionally branched, frequently simple septate, 4–6 μm in diam.; 
 <italic>skeletal hyphae</italic> dominant, hyaline, thick-walled with a distinct wide lumen, usually flexuous, frequently branched, occasionally simple septate, 6–12 μm in diam. 
 <italic>Tramal generative hyphae</italic> frequent, hyaline, thin-walled, occasionally branched, frequently simple septate, 3–5 μm in diam.; 
 <italic>tramal skeletal hyphae</italic> frequent, hyaline, thick-walled with a wide lumen, flexuous, occasionally frequently branched and simple septate, 4–8 μm in diam. 
 <italic>Cystidia</italic> and cystidioles absent; 
 <italic>basidia</italic> clavate, with four sterigmata and a simple basal septum, 25–32 × 7–8 μm, basidioles in shape similar to basidia but slightly smaller. 
 <italic>Basidiospores</italic> oblong-ellipsoid to cylindrical, tapering at apiculus, hyaline, thin-walled, IKI–, CB–, (6–)7–9.6(−11) × (2.5–)2.9–4(−4.1) μm, L = 8.24 μm, W = 3.2 μm, Q = 2.49–2.66 (
 <italic>n</italic> = 90/3). 
 <italic>Rot type</italic> brown.
</p>
