<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">In this study, we measured the potential of recycling three readily available organic waste streams in Nairobi, Kenya, and arguably also in other megacities in the developing world, and their influence on the nutritional quality of BSFL as a proposed alternative protein source for livestock feed. As the quality of livestock feed is mainly measured in the concentrations of CP present in the feed’s dry matter, we conducted a proximate analysis applying the standard methods described by the Association of Official Analytical Chemist
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>
 </sup> using a nitrogen-to-protein conversion factor of 4.76
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>
 </sup> and obtained significantly high values of CP, surpassing those of soybean meal and other commonly used plant proteins in livestock feeds such as canola, cottonseed and sunflower meal
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup>. The CP values we obtained in our study ranged between 33 and 41% which is slightly lower than the range of values (39 to 43%) reported by Spranghers and colleagues
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup> for BSFL reared on various organic waste streams. Moreover, Nguyen and colleagues
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup> reported a CP value of 39% for BSFL reared on fruits and vegetables waste while Sheppard and colleagues
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup> reported 42% CP for BSFL reared on chicken manure. However, the previously mentioned CP values were obtained using the Kjeldahl standard nitrogen-to-protein conversion factor of 6.25 while the values we reported were obtained using the conversion factor of 4.76. The total nitrogen content in insects in general and BSF in specific contain nitrogen originating from both protein and non-protein sources such as chitin. Hence, separating non protein from protein nitrogen was necessary in order to obtain accurate crude protein content and to avoid over estimated values that were previously reported using the standard conversion factor
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>. When calculated using the standard nitrogen-to-protein conversion factor of 6.25, the range of CP values we obtained from this study (39 to 54%) surpassed the range of values previously reported in literature
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup>. Our results were closer to that obtained by Caligiani and colleagues
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup> and Janssen and colleagues
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>
 </sup> who both used a nitrogen-to-protein conversion factor of 4.76. Similarly, the EE content we found in BSFL was higher than those reported from full fat soybean meal
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup> and commercially available fishmeal
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>
 </sup>. Newton and colleagues
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup> and St-Hilaire and colleagues
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>
 </sup> reported even higher EE values in BSFL than we found in our study. Previous studies reported an influence of the rearing substrate on the EE content. For instance, Nguyen and colleagues
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup> reported higher EE content for larvae reared on fish and liver in comparison to chicken feed. However, there was no apparent influence of the rearing substrates on the EE content of BSFL in our study.
</p>
