<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Each one of the isolated 
 <italic>M. fruticosa serpyllifolia</italic> VOs was dissolved in DMSO (100%) at a concentration of 50 mg/mL. The prepared 
 <italic>M. fruticosa serpyllifolia</italic> VO solutions were filter sterilized and then were serially microdiluted (2-fold) eleven times in sterile nutrient broth. In 96-well plates, the dilution processes were carried out under aseptic conditions. In the microwells that were assigned to evaluate the antibacterial activities of the extracted 
 <italic>M. fruticosa serpyllifolia</italic> VOs, the concentration of these oils ranged from 0.024 to 25 mg/mL. On the other hand, the concentrations of these essential oils in the microwells assigned to evaluate their antifungal activities ranged from 8.467∗10
 <sup>−3</sup> to 16.666 mg/mL. In these plates, microwell number 11 contained essential oil-free nutrient broth, which was used as a positive control for microbial growth. In addition, the microwell number 12 contained essential oil-free nutrient broth that was left uninoculated with any of the test microbes. This well was used as a negative control for microbial growth. Microwell numbers 1 to 11 were inoculated aseptically with the test microbes. At the time of inoculation, the final concentrations of microbial cells were about 2.5 × 10
 <sup>5</sup> and 0.333–1.666 × 10
 <sup>3</sup> colony-forming unit (CFU)/mL for the tested bacterial pathogens and 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, respectively. Each of the included microbes in this study was examined in duplicate for being inhibited by the 
 <italic>M. fruticosa serpyllifolia</italic> essential oils. At 35°C, all the inoculated plates were incubated and the incubation period lasted for about 16-20 hours for the plates inoculated with the test bacterial strains and for about 48 hours for the plates inoculated with 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic>. The lowest concentration of 
 <italic>M. fruticosa serpyllifolia</italic> essential oils, at which there was no visible microbial growth in that microwell, was observed.
</p>
