<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> species are documented with ethnobotanical used against infectious diseases/ailments such as conjunctivitis, diarrhea, dysentery, pneumonia, flu, and sore throats, sexually transmitted diseases, urinary infections, among others (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Eloff et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">Maulik and Katiyar, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">Maulik and Talwar, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Cock, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Afshari et al., 2016</xref>). This has led to some studies as an effort to elucidate their antimicrobial mechanisms and antimicrobial spectrum. Some efforts are being made to evaluate the potential antimicrobial properties of 
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> sp. extracts. The report by 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Akter et al. (2019)</xref>, evaluates the antimicrobial capacity of 
 <italic>Terminalia ferdinandiana</italic> Exell. extracts in food preservation. The authors prepared the extracts with methanol, ethanol, acetone, hexane, and distilled water, by accelerated solvent extraction from freeze-dried powders of barks, fruits, and leaves of 
 <italic>T. ferdinandiana</italic> Exell, and tested them against some of the most common foodborne microorganisms by the disc diffusion assay. The authors found that methanol extracts showed a broad spectrum of antibacterial activity against the gram-positive 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus, Bacillus cereus, Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, and the gram-negative bacteria 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>. Also, the authors determined that the minimum inhibitory concentration and minimum bactericidal concentration values of extracts of 
 <italic>T. ferdinandiana</italic> Exell ranged from 1–3 mg/mL, 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>, 
 <italic>B. cereus</italic>, and methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> were the most sensitive bacteria against 
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> sp. extracts; on this subject, ethanol and acetone extracts showed the most potent antibacterial inhibitory activity. The authors argue that intriguingly, the extracts with the highest antioxidant activity (methanol and water extracts) were not the ones with the highest antibacterial activity, which may indicate that the compounds that may be differentially found in each type of extracts (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Akter et al., 2019</xref>).
</p>
