<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">
  <italic class="italic">Sapindus mukorossi</italic> seed oil is commonly used as a source for biodiesel fuel. Its phytochemical composition is similar to the extracted oil from 
  <italic class="italic">Sapindus trifoliatus</italic> seeds, which exhibit beneficial effects for skin wound healing. Since 
  <italic class="italic">S. mukorossi</italic> seed shows no cyanogenic property, it could be a potential candidate for the treatment of skin wounds. Thus, we evaluated the effectiveness of 
  <italic class="italic">S. mukorossi</italic> seed oil in the treatment of skin wounds. We characterized and quantified the fatty acids and unsaponifiable fractions (including β-sitosterol and δ-tocopherol) contained in 
  <italic class="italic">S. mukorossi</italic> seed-extracted oil by GC-MS and HPLC, respectively. Cell proliferation and migratory ability were evaluated by cell viability and scratch experiments using CCD-966SK cells treated with 
  <italic class="italic">S. mukorossi</italic> oil. The anti-inflammatory effects of the oil were evaluated by measuring the nitric oxide (NO) production in lipopolysaccharide-treated RAW 264.7 cells. Antimicrobial activity tests were performed with 
  <italic class="italic">Propionibacterium acnes</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and 
  <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic> using a modified Japanese Industrial Standard procedure. Uniform artificial wounds were created on the dorsum of rats. The wounds were treated with a carboxymethyl cellulose (CMC)/hyaluronic acid (HA)/sodium alginate (SA) hydrogel for releasing the 
  <italic class="italic">S. mukorossi</italic> seed oil. The wound sizes were measured photographically for 12 days and were compared to wounds covered with analogous membranes containing a saline solution. Our results showed that the 
  <italic class="italic">S. mukorossi</italic> seed oil used in this study contains abundant monounsaturated fatty acids, β-sitosterol, and δ-tocopherol. In the in vitro tests, 
  <italic class="italic">S. mukorossi</italic> seed oil prompted cell proliferation and migration capability. Additionally, the oil had significant anti-inflammatory and anti-microbial activities. In the in vivo animal experiments, 
  <italic class="italic">S. mukorossi</italic> seed oil-treated wounds revealed acceleration of sequential skin wound healing events after two days of healing. The size of oil-treated wound decreased to half the size of the untreated control after eight days of healing. The results suggest that 
  <italic class="italic">S. mukorossi</italic> seed oil could be a potential source for promoting skin wound healing.
 </p>
</abstract>
