<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec23" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CNB oil exposure increases 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> sensitivity to cell wall disrupting agents
 </div>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to determine whether cell wall integrity was compromised by CNB, RSY150 were exposed to cell wall perturbing agents CR and CFW at 1/2 MIC and 1/4 MIC. Higher sensitivity, reflecting compromised cell wall integrity, was observed in CNB treated cells in comparison to control (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>a) at 1/2 MIC, progressively decreasing to 1/4 MIC (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>b). As positive controls, we analyzed mutants lacking genes related to cell wall integrity and to wall organization and biogenesis for their sensitivity to CNB oil treatment. The mutants tested had the following knockouts: 
  <span class="italic">VPS28</span>, a VPS factor required for vacuolar protein sorting; 
  <span class="italic">CRH11</span>, encoding a GPI-anchored cell wall transglycosylase; 
  <span class="italic">SSU81</span>, encoding a function involved in oxidative stress, cell wall biogenesis, and morphogenesis; and 
  <span class="italic">DFG5</span>, encoding an N-linked mannoprotein of the cell wall and membrane. All these mutants exhibit generalized sensitivity to CNB oil, with lower MIC than the wild type strain (CaSS1), further verifying an impact of CNB on cell wall integrity (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>c). The associated MIC decreased two-fold, from 125 μg/mL to 61.5 μg/mL, for all mutants.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>CNB treated RSY150 
     <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> exhibit a cell wall stress response. Logarithmic phase RSY150 cells were treated with 1/2 and 1/4 MIC CNB oil or without oil for 24 h. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Treated and control cells at 10
     <span class="sup">5</span>, 10
     <span class="sup">4</span> and 10
     <span class="sup">3</span> CFU were spotted on YNB complete media agar containing CFW and CR and examined after 2 days. Treated cells showed greater sensitivity to cell wall stressors. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> The number of colonies on the CR and CFW plates show a dose dependent effect that decreases as a function of oil concentration. The 1/2 MIC CNB oil was more effective than 1/4 MIC, with a significant difference ** between 1/2 MIC oil treatment compared to untreated controls (p &lt; 0.05). The cell count was normalized with treated cells grown on YNB media agar only. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Wild type background strain (CaSS1) and cell wall defective mutants (
     <span class="italic">SSU81, CRH, DFG</span> and 
     <span class="italic">VPS</span>) were exposed to a twofold increasing dilution of CNB oil in a MIC assay, showing overall sensitivity to the CNB oil and indicating a moderate cell wall stress response
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40694_2018_46_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
