<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The virus, known as coronavirus, a single RNA-stranded virus, belongs to the 
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic> family. The RNA is encapsulated in the membrane, and the virion contains phosphorylated nucleocapsid protein and RNA. By interacting with the angiotensin-converting-enzyme-2 (ACE2) receptor, the virus enters the host and causes severe respiratory tract infection (RTI) in humans. Viral proteases have been well documented as potential approved drug targets for several infections, including hepatitis C virus (HCV) and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Recent studies from Liu and his group documented the presence of the main protease (M
 <sup>pro</sup>) enzyme in SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Homology modeling with SARS-CoV M
 <sup>pro</sup> has delineated about a 96% structural similarity with SARS-CoV M
 <sup>pro</sup> [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Due to the structural similarity with the M
 <sup>pro</sup> from other coronaviruses, SARS-CoV-2 M
 <sup>pro</sup> can be considered to be a prospective target for drug discovery for COVID-19 treatment. SARS-CoV-2 M
 <sup>pro</sup> cleaves the overlapping pp1a and pp1b polyproteins through proteolytic cleavage, which is considered to be a critical step for viral replication [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Additionally, the functioning of replication-essential enzymes, for instance, RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp), nsp13 are also dependent on the proteolytic release [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Consequently, SARS-CoV-2 M
 <sup>pro</sup> is responsible for inhibiting SARS-CoV-2 replication. Therefore, targeting this specific enzyme will lead towards potential therapeutic advantages in drug discovery for this dangerous virus.
</p>
