<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the present study, we tried to identify the role of some isolated phytochemicals from a medicinal plant, known as 
 <italic>Tinospora crispa</italic> Miers., a member of the Menispermaceae family, for the treatment of COVID-19 using computational biology techniques. The plant is locally known as Gulancha [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. It is indigenous to Bangladesh, Eastern China, India, and Malaysia. Our previous work also confirmed the hepatoprotective, antinociceptive, anxiolytic, antidepressant, and antipyretic activities of plant extract and fractions of 
 <italic>T. crispa</italic> [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Moreover, the ethnobotanical role of the plant has already been documented, primarily as a tonic, a blood purifier, and for stomach disorders [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Importantly, the plant exhibited significant antimalarial attributes in combination with pyrimethamine, which corroborates the findings from recent studies providing evidence for the use of the antimalarial drug chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine to combat against SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In addition, one study reported the antiviral activity of 
 <italic>T. crispa</italic> along with other traditional herbs delineated antiviral activity against fish pathogenic viruses, including infectious hematopoietic necrosis virus, infectious pancreatic necrosis virus, 
 <italic>Oncorhynchus masou</italic> virus [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The active components from another species of 
 <italic>Tinospora</italic> (
 <italic>T. cordifolia</italic>) has been shown to represent not only antiviral activity but also protease inhibitor activity [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-25-03936" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Therefore, this study rationalizes the role of screened compounds of 
 <italic>T. crispa</italic> to combat SARS-CoV-2.
</p>
