<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Egg yolk is an excellent dietary source of choline, lutein and zeaxanthin. Choline is not an essential nutrient in humans, but dietary deficiency can cause various diseases such as fatty liver, increased lymphocyte apoptosis, and DNA and muscle damages in humans [
 <xref rid="b9-ajas-18-0738" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="b10-ajas-18-0738" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Lutein in egg yolk lipids has been identified as a carotenoid that accumulates in the macular region of the human retina and plays an important role in the prevention of age-related macular degeneration that causes blindness [
 <xref rid="b11-ajas-18-0738" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="b13-ajas-18-0738" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Liu et al [
 <xref rid="b14-ajas-18-0738" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] reported that lutein and zeaxanthin supplementation improved visual performance of age-related macular degeneration patients in a dose-response manner. One egg yolk contains between 300 and 500 μg of xanthophylls [
 <xref rid="b15-ajas-18-0738" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>], and lutein and zeaxanthin in egg are highly bioavailable because they are dispersed in lipid matrix such as triglycerol, phospholipids, and cholesterol [
 <xref rid="b16-ajas-18-0738" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Egg yolk contains high levels of long-chain omega-3 fatty acids such as eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA) because of its high phospholipids content. Neuringer et al [
 <xref rid="b17-ajas-18-0738" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>] and Innis [
 <xref rid="b18-ajas-18-0738" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] reported that infants who do not get enough omega-3 fatty acids from their mothers during pregnancy are at risk for developing vision and nerve problems. Since eggs are an excellent source of high-quality protein and other essential nutrients, the addition of dried egg white and/or yolk can improve the nutritional value of a non-dairy creamer analogs/mimics greatly. When dried egg white and yolk are used together, the improvement of nutritional value will be greater than using egg white alone because egg yolk contains high levels of essential fatty acids, phospholipids, choline, lutein, and minerals, which are important nutrients for infants and growing babies.
</p>
