<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Yellow mealworm (
 <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic>), a member of the family Tenebrionidae, is one of the most promising insect species suitable for mass production because it is easy to breed and feed [
 <xref rid="B7-animals-09-00187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-animals-09-00187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Mealworm larvae fed on plant by-product diets grow well [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-09-00187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] and have a short life cycle: the egg stage lasts 3 to 9 days, the larval stage lasts 26 to 76 days, and the pupal stage lasts 5 to 17 days [
 <xref rid="B16-animals-09-00187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Larvae of 
 <italic class="italic">T. molitor</italic> are rich in protein and unsaturated fat, and processed 
 <italic class="italic">T. molitor</italic> larvae meal has been tested as a replacement of FM in the diet of several aquatic species. For instance, the inclusion of 
 <italic class="italic">T. molitor</italic> larvae meal in the diet of gilthead seabream (
 <italic class="italic">Sparus aurata</italic>) at 25% and 50%, which represented a 33% and 74% replacement of FM, showed no negative effects on fish growth performance [
 <xref rid="B17-animals-09-00187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Moreover, the 33% FM substitution resulted in optimal weight gain, feed conversion ratio (FCR), and protein efficiency ratio (PER), while the coefficients of apparent digestibility decreased as IM inclusion level increased [
 <xref rid="B17-animals-09-00187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Another study showed that up to 40% of FM could be replaced by IM from yellow mealworm larvae (17% incorporation level) in diets of African catfish (
 <italic class="italic">Clarias gariepinus</italic>) without affecting growth performance or FCR [
 <xref rid="B18-animals-09-00187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Juvenile rockfish (
 <italic class="italic">Sebastes schlegeli</italic>) showed no adverse health and growth performances when up to 38% of the FM in its diet was replaced by IM from mealworm larvae (32% incorporation level) [
 <xref rid="B19-animals-09-00187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Belforti et al. revealed that rainbow trout (
 <italic class="italic">Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>) fed diets in which 33% or 66% of the FM was replaced with mealworm IM (25% and 50% incorporation level, respectively) showed no differences on fish growth, but the replacement significantly improved FCR and fish survival [
 <xref rid="B14-animals-09-00187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. It is, however, important to note that most studies addressing FM replacement with IM use whole dried insect larvae, which contain a relatively high-fat level [
 <xref rid="B20-animals-09-00187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. IM usually shows an excellent composition of essential amino acids, but a low-quality fatty acid profile [
 <xref rid="B2-animals-09-00187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Defattening IM is a method that can improve its palatability and nutrient digestibility, thereby making it a more suitable and protein-rich ingredient for fish diets [
 <xref rid="B2-animals-09-00187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Nonetheless, the effect of replacing FM with insect protein meal (IPM) from defatted mealworm on fish performance is still poorly investigated [
 <xref rid="B2-animals-09-00187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>].
</p>
