<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ginger essential oil (GEO), produced in tropical and subtropical countries such as India and China, is extracted from 
 <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic>. It is one of the most commonly used spices worldwide, especially in Asian countries, because of its potent antifungal, antimicrobial, and antioxidant activities. The flavor of ginger makes it an excellent condiment and appetizer that is popular in food items. Khaledian et al. evaluated the effects of electrospinning of cellulose nanofiber (CNF) integrated with ginger essential oil (GEO) and citric acid (CA) on the chemical, microbial, and sensory characteristics of barbecued chicken meat [
 <xref rid="B251-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">251</xref>]. Microbial analysis observed that CNF-GEO-CA showed the highest activity against the main microbes involved in chicken-meat spoilage, such as 
 <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> species, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> species, total aerobic psychotropic bacteria, lactic acid bacteria, and fungi (yeasts and molds) compared to control and CNF treatments [
 <xref rid="B239-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">239</xref>,
 <xref rid="B252-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">252</xref>,
 <xref rid="B253-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">253</xref>,
 <xref rid="B254-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">254</xref>]. The microbiological test carried out in this study revealed that the GEO could be considered an effective antimicrobial agent. It enhanced chicken meat’s shelf life by lowering the number of microorganisms present on it [
 <xref rid="B255-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">255</xref>,
 <xref rid="B256-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">256</xref>,
 <xref rid="B257-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">257</xref>]. The GEO antimicrobial efficacy improved when checked on the ready-to-cook chicken after introducing CA and GEO into CNF. This was attributable to CA’s uninterrupted entrance into the bacterial cell, which acidified the cell membrane, denatured the cell’s protein, inhibited metabolic reactions, and eventually caused bacteria to die [
 <xref rid="B258-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">258</xref>,
 <xref rid="B259-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">259</xref>]. Furthermore, these substances remained high over time because of the continuous release of these antimicrobials by the polymer matrix into the food surface to suppress microbial growth [
 <xref rid="B260-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">260</xref>]. The sensory analysis evaluated that color, taste, odor, and overall acceptability of chicken meat were enhanced by wrapping it with CNF containing GEO and CA during the storage.
</p>
