<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Applications of lignin include those related to fillers, binders, dispersants, or polymeric surfactants, and only around 5% of over 70 million ton annual production of lignin is used for commercial applications.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref105" class="xref">105</xref>
 </sup> The potential use of lignin for coatings and stabilizer of emulsions has been demonstrated,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref77" class="xref">77</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref81" class="xref">81</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref82" class="xref">82</xref>
 </sup> while colloidal lignin particles have been used for coatings,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref106" class="xref">106</xref>
 </sup> for loading of active compounds, as a template for functional polymeric capsules,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup> or for Pickering emulsions.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup> The surface activity of lignin is an attractive property that benefits the stabilization of multiphase systems, including Pickering templates for microcapsules and nanoparticles, organic carriers for inorganic particles, emulsion with gas-switchable features, and tunable emulsion, among others. Our proposed aerosol flow system for high-throughput and high-yield production of lignin nano- and microparticles is relevant because of the tunable size, hydrophilicity, and various surface morphologies that can be achieved (
 <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig" class="xref">8</xref>
 </xref>a, left).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup> Such lignin particles comprising given sizes have been studied as far as their evaporation-induced self-assembly, to form particulate coatings with segregated structures, which were also followed by modeling (
 <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig" class="xref">8</xref>
 </xref>a, middle frames).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref106" class="xref">106</xref>
 </sup> The effect on emulsion stability of lignin particle size and concentration in the aqueous phase was studied in surfactant-free emulsification.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup> An example was kerosene-in-water emulsions that were obtained by using given concentrations (0.1–0.6%) of Kraft lignin particles with varied average size (from ∼350 to 1000 nm). An illustration of the adsorbed particles at the oil/water interface is included in 
 <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig" class="xref">8</xref>
 </xref>a, right. We also synthesized lignin supracolloids from W/O microemulsions and found them effective for the stabilization of Pickering emulsions.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref83" class="xref">83</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
