<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Biofilm is a surface attached microbial communities embedded in an extracellular matrix derived from cells and environment.
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> Biofilms are more resistant to physical and chemical stresses compared to their planktonic counterpart as biofilms exhibit various mechanisms to neutralise those external stresses. Extracellular biofilm matrix acts as a physical or chemical barrier for diffusion of antimicrobial agents into the biofilm. Further, with the limited availability of nutrients, the biofilm community shifts towards slow or no growth status from exponential growth. All above factors and induction of a biofilm phenotype and quorum sensing contribute to high resistance to antimicrobial agents of a biofilm.
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>32</sup>
 </xref> Since the resistance of biofilms to available antimicrobial strategies is becoming more widespread, more studies should be carried out in order to invent novel, non-toxic, inexpensive and effective treatment options specially by controlling the virulence of the pathogen effectively. In the current study, efficacy of 
 <italic>C. verum</italic> leaf EO as a potential phytomedicinal agent was evaluated on forming 
 <italic>Candida</italic> biofilms. 
 <italic>C. verum</italic> EO exhibited a potential antibiofilm effect on forming biofilms of 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> (ATCC MYA-2876), 
 <italic>C. tropicalis</italic> (ATCC 750) and 
 <italic>C. dubliniensis</italic> (ATCC MYA-646) test strains. Concentrations required to reduce the biofilm development by 50% (Compared to negative control) were 0.15, 0.35 and 0.2 mg/mL for three test strains respectively. And the MTC (concentrations of EO required to completely cease the biofilm development) was 1.0 mg/mL for all test strains. Importantly, these MTC values are lower than MIC and MFC values of test strains which indicates the high potency of killing of forming biofilms of 
 <italic>C. verum</italic> EO though biofilms are considered as more resistant microbial communities than its planktonic counterpart. These data suggest the potential action of 
 <italic>C. verum</italic> oil on interrupting the normal process of formation of 
 <italic>Candida</italic> biofilms.
</p>
