<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0115">Freezing and crystallization processes are interconnected. These are characterized by nucleation and then crystallization 
 <xref rid="b0685" ref-type="bibr">[137]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0760" ref-type="bibr">[152]</xref>. Conventional cooling is quicker when applying ultrasound, and offers uniform seeding, resulting in shorter dwelling time. The final crystal size decreases by the seeds and thus do not harm the cells 
 <xref rid="b0815" ref-type="bibr">[163]</xref>. An accelerated cooling can be achieved by improving heat transfer 
 <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0485" ref-type="bibr">[97]</xref>. Ultrasonic cavitation occurs, which serves as nuclei for crystal formation or disruption of the present initial nuclei. Finer ice crystals are formed between the beginning of crystallization and ice formation which reduces the freezing time 
 <xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. Even so, it reduces cell structure destruction. In ultrasound assisted freezing, the freezing process can be speed up because of the mass transfer, increase in heat and nucleation initiation 
 <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. Primary and secondary nucleation is the two major phases of ultrasound nucleation. Primary nucleation occurs when nucleation temperature which is less than the required freezing temperature, is reached. This step goes along with the release of latent heat in excess amounts. The high pressure generated by ultrasound (act as a driving force for nucleation) is recorded and result in the reduction of degree of supercooling 
 <xref rid="b0450" ref-type="bibr">[90]</xref>. When the size of the bubbles exceeds the critical threshold, which is required for nucleation then the bubbles produced by cavitation act as a nucleated nuclei. Microstreaming and eddies can result from the movement of stable cavitation bubbles, thus improving the transfer of mass and heat which resulting in nucleation. Cavitation bubbles and microflow induces shear force due to collapsing. More nucleation sites are produced when ultrasound shatter the dendrites of present ice into pieces 
 <xref rid="b0340" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref>.
</p>
