<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0410">According to TCM, the adverse reactions of AR are mainly manifested in “dryness”. The “dryness” of AR is not only a pharmacological action for treating diseases but also a factor causing adverse reactions. Unprocessed AR has strong “dryness” and is easy to consume Yin fluid. The adverse reactions include impairment of spleen Yin, dysfunction of spleen in transportation, distress in the epigastrium, mouth parching and tongue scorching, and constipation. Therefore, Yixue Rumen indicated AR to “mistakenly take blood consumption, yin fail to nourish the body, hyperactive the fire due to yin deficiency”. After processing, the “dryness” of AR is slowed down, and it could eliminate dampness and activate spleen and stomach by entering the middle Jiao. Taking AR orally does not cause swelling and could eliminate dampness blocking and abdominal distention. In the case of Yin deficiency and heat injury to the body, the “dryness” of AR is particularly prominent. Therefore, Bencao Jingshu recorded that “AR should not be taken for diseases that belong to Yin deficiency, blood deficiency, essence deficiency, tidal fever, dry mouth and lips, cough and spit, spitting blood, sore nose and throat, and constipation, stagnation and Qi deficiency in the liver and kidney.” Bencao Zheng also recorded that “those who have a deficiency of internal heat and Yin and loose sweating on the surface should not take AR.” The “dryness” of AR is related to its volatile oil. The Compendium of Materia Medica (Bencao Gangmu) recorded, “because of the dryness of AR, processing would be taken that its oil is soaked in glutinous rice swill, and it is used for slicing and baking.” The results showed that the volatile oil content of AR decreased after being fried with bran and rice swill (
 <xref rid="bib142" ref-type="bibr">Zhao, 2009</xref>). Whether AR should be processed to reduce the content of the essential oil in clinical medication should be based on the needs of the disease. For instance, raw AR is suitable for cold syndrome and cold dampness arthralgia, while processed AR is suitable for dampness resistance and middle Jiao and flaccidity syndrome. In addition, the deficiency of the element body Yin should be used with caution. Studies on modern toxicology and pharmacology of AR verified the safety profiles in different animal models. Following administration of ethanolic 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> extract at the high dose level (5000 mg/kg body weight) in rats and mice, no significant toxicity was observed except for gastric stimulation and central nervous system inhibition symptoms (diminished response to touch and balance and decreased alertness and motor ability) (
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">Plengsuriyakarn et al., 2012</xref>). It is important however for the knowledge of potential deleterious effects of 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> on cardiovascular system. The antiplatelet aggregation of 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> is possibly mediated through suppression of collagen-induced signaling pathway which is upstream of the release of thromboxane A2 from platelets (
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Nasu et al., 2009</xref>). Care should be taken when using 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> extract or its active constituents in patients with platelet disorders or coagulopathy. The results of acute and subacute toxicity tests in rats and mice indicated that 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> was safe at a wide range of dose levels (1000–5000 mg/kg body weight) (
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Koonrungsesomboon et al., 2014</xref>). An observational study conducted in China showed a safety profile of Fufang Cangzhu Tang, a Chinese herbal formula containing 15 g of AR decocted into 300 mL of liquor and separately administered orally two times a day for 8 weeks in 32 senile patients with obesity or overweight complicated with impaired glucose tolerance (
 <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Shi et al., 2006</xref>). In addition, animal experiments showed that the volatile oil of AR has a sedative effect in small dose, hyperreflexia in spinal cord, and inhibition effect in large dose, which eventually leads to respiratory paralysis and death (
 <xref rid="bib116" ref-type="bibr">Wu, 1999</xref>). Its main inhibitory components are β-eucalyptol and atractylol, thus, it is harmful to organisms. Therefore, AR should be used with caution in patients with nervous system diseases because of its various effects on the nervous system. Meanwhile, it can discharge sodium and potassium; thus, electrolyte balance should be given attention in long-term applications. Several clinical studies of AR have been conducted in patients with different diseases/symptoms by using AR in various formulations (
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2008</xref>). Atractyloside (ATR) is a diterpenoid glycoside and occurs naturally in Asteraceae plants (
 <italic>A. macrocephala</italic>, 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> and 
 <italic>Xanthium sibiricum</italic>), many of which are used in foods and ethnomedicines. The toxicity of ATR has caused fatal renal proximal tubule necrosis and/or centrilobular hepatic necrosis in man and farm animals. And the degradation of ATR is a way to increase pharmaceutical safety for the Chinese medicinal industries (
 <xref rid="bib146" ref-type="bibr">Zhu, 2012</xref>). However, no clinical study using AR extract or its main components alone has been conducted, signifying the need for further clinical trials to prove its clinical efficacy and safety for the human body. Although clinical research directly supporting its safety in the human body is lacking, the available information showed no serious adverse event.
</p>
