<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Concentration-mortality bioassays (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Silva et al., 2013</xref>) were conducted to estimate the lethal concentration (LC) of the essential oil extracted from four 
 <italic>Vitex</italic> species (
 <italic>V. capitata, V. megapotamica, V. gardneriana</italic>, and 
 <italic>V. rufescens</italic>) to adult coconut mites (
 <italic>A. guerreronis</italic>). A preliminary bioassay was performed using a wide concentration range where the no observed adverse effect level (NOAEL) and the concentration able to kill 100% of 
 <italic>A. guerreronis</italic> were determined. Afterward, four concentrations within this range were used to generate a concentration response curve as follows: oil was sprayed onto perianth disks (1 cm diameter) of young coconut fruits placed in Petri dishes containing agar at 5%. Spraying of the oils was performed at a pressure of 34 kPa (0.34 bar) with a 9.3-ml spray rate using a Potter Tower device (Burkard, Rickmansworth, United Kingdom) (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira et al., 2017</xref>). Sprayed perianth disks were allowed to dry for 20 min before 20 adult 
 <italic>A. guerreronis</italic> were placed onto each disk. Control disks were sprayed with acetone, which was also used to dissolve and dilute the oils for all concentrations. Petri dishes were individually maintained in an incubator at 26°C and 70% relative humidity for 24 h. Eight replicates (wells) for each oil concentration were used. Harmfulness of the commercial acaricide abamectin (Vertimec 18 EC
 <sup>TM</sup>; 18 g a.i./L, at field dosage 75 mL/100 L) to 
 <italic>A. guerreronis</italic> was evaluated as a way of toxicity comparison (20 replicates were performed and control disks were sprayed with distilled water). Mite mortality was assessed after 24 h of exposure and concentration-mortality curves were estimated by Probit analysis using the PROC PROBIT procedure in SAS (version 9.4, Cary, NC, United States). The likelihood ratio chi-square goodness-of-fit was applied to evaluate whether the data adequately conformed to the PROBIT model (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Robertson et al., 2007</xref>).
</p>
