<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Eight phenolic glycosides compounds—tachioside, isotachioside, koaburaside, 2,6-dimethoxy-4-hydroxyphenyl-1-O-beta-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucopyranoside, 4,6-dihydroxy-2-methoxyphenyl-1-O-beta-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucopyranoside, a mixture of erigeside C and salidroside, and 6-hydroxyphenyl)-1-O-beta-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucopyranoside—isolated from the stem extracts of LO (LOSE) showed anti-allergic inflammatory activities. Among the eight compounds, koaburaside, (6-hydroxyphenyl)-1-O-beta-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucopyranoside and 2,6-dimethoxy-4-hydroxyphenyl-1-O-beta-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucopyranoside suppressed the release of histamine from mast cells as compared with gallic acid, which was used as a positive control. In particular, (6-hydroxyphenyl)-1-O-beta-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucopyranoside attenuated the gene expressions of the pro-inflammatory cytokines TNF-α and IL-6 in human mast cells [
 <xref rid="B60-plants-09-01765" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Similarly, seven neolignans, including one new compound linderin A isolated from LOSE, were investigated for their anti-allergic inflammatory effects on human mast HMC-1 cells. Other lignans investigated were (+)-xanthoxyol, pluviatilol, actiforin, (+)-syringaresinol, (+)-(7S,8R,8′R)-acuminatolide and (+)-9′-O-trans-feruloyl-5,5′-dimethoxylariciresinol. All compounds except (+)-xanthoxyol and (+)-syringaresinol inhibited the release of histamine, whereas linderin A and actiforin suppressed the expressions of TNF-α and IL-6 pro-inflammatory cytokines [
 <xref rid="B62-plants-09-01765" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. In another study, (+)-syringaresinol, one of the constituents of LOSE, was reported to possess an anti-inflammatory effect on carrageenan-induced hind paw oedema in mice. Moreover, treatment with (+)-syringaresinol successfully inhibited the protein expression of iNOS, COX-2 and NF-κB and mRNA expression of iNOS, COX-2, TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL-6. It also reduced LPS-induced the release of NO, PGE2, TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL-6 in a dose-dependent manner [
 <xref rid="B65-plants-09-01765" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. These results demonstrate that compounds isolated from LO show strong anti-allergic and anti-inflammatory activity and can, therefore, be further developed into effective therapeutic agents with modification.
</p>
