<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40" class="p">A number of physiological changes are observed when microalgae are subjected to nutrient deprivation. During stress, the cell machinery will try to minimize the protein synthesis due to non-availability of nitrogen by shutting down the protein biosynthesis and degrading the protein pool to amino acids to get energy for survival as well as to assimilate carbon as storage molecules. Under nutrient-deprived condition, the total chlorophyll content decreased as the days of starvation progressed. Under nitrogen-deprived condition, the chlorophyll content was severely deteriorated within 2 to 4 days of starvation, while phosphorous- and sulphur-starved cells showed a slow decrease. Chlorophyll reduced to almost half within 2 days of nitrogen starvation (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>b). This is a very common phenomenon observed under nitrogen stress among other strains too. The protein content did show variable response to different stress conditions. Under nitrogen deprivation, rapid lowering in protein content is observed. The cell machinery tries to cope up with nitrogen unavailability by cutting down on protein synthesis and degrading the protein pool to amino acids to get energy for survival as well as to divert carbon towards storage molecules. Phosphorous- and sulphur-starved cells also showed a slow decline in the protein content, but the initial impact on protein machinery was not as severe as nitrogen starvation Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>c). A sharp increase in carbohydrates in nitrogen-starved cells was observed on the second day, where the carbohydrate content was doubled, which later decreased substantially. This initial response might be attributed to the formation of carbohydrates as energy storage molecule in the case of extreme nitrogen limitation, which later provides carbon skeleton for lipid biosynthesis as storage molecules under prolonged starvation. The increase in carbohydrate content in phosphorous- and sulphur-starved cells was observed after day 4, and the lipid accumulation was observed late as compared to nitrogen-starved cells (Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>c, 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>a). These observations suggest that the microalgae initially store carbohydrates energy reserves to overcome the initial stress and then utilize the same for energy generation when they are subjected to severe macronutrient limitation. This has been reported in various microalgae, where some accumulate starch under nutrient depletion condition, others accumulate lipids, or an initial starch accumulation followed by lipid accumulation over prolonged stress is observed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">65</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" class="xref">69</xref>]. In conclusion, adverse effects in molecular profiles of biomolecules (such as total chlorophyll, proteins and carbohydrates) were seen during N- and S- conditions with hampered cell growth (biomass), whereas P- stress seems to have a limited effect.
</p>
