<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par41" class="p">Under optimal conditions, photosynthesis and electron transport chain produce ATP and NADPH which is utilized as energy currency during cell division [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">70</xref>]. Hence, the optimal ratio of reduced and oxidized metabolites is maintained, whereas during nutrient deprivation the pool of NADP+ and ADP depletes as photosynthesis continuously produces NADPH and ATP which remains under-utilized [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>]. Biosynthesis of fatty acid consumes NADPH and ATP; hence, the increased fatty acid synthesis helps the cells to maintain the balance of required electron acceptors (NADP+). During nutrient limitation, an increase in the lipid content has been demonstrated in several microalgal species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">71</xref>]. Nitrogen is an essential requirement for protein synthesis as well as photosynthesis, but under nitrogen-limiting conditions most of the carbon fixed in photosynthesis is channelized towards the production of lipids and/or carbohydrates. Several studies have demonstrated that nitrogen deprivation leads to higher accumulation of lipids in various microalgal strains [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" class="xref">72</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">73</xref>]. Upon removal of nitrogen, 
 <italic class="italic">Nannochloropsis</italic> sp. and 
 <italic class="italic">Neochloris oleoabundans</italic> increased their lipid content to onefold and twofold, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" class="xref">74</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" class="xref">75</xref>]. A number of cellular metabolic processes such as photosynthesis, signal transduction, energy transport system require phosphorous as the main component, and hence, the deficiency of this major element also results in accumulation of lipids [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" class="xref">76</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" class="xref">78</xref>]. Similar studies showed increase in lipid accumulation to more than 50% of dry weight (dw) under P- limitation in 
 <italic class="italic">Scenedesmus</italic> sp. LX1 belonging to 
 <italic class="italic">Scenedesmaceae</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" class="xref">79</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" class="xref">80</xref>]. In our present investigation, FAME content in 
 <italic class="italic">P. kessleri</italic> was highest in N- cells, whereas in P- cells the same has been compensated by the better growth rate. This observation was unique as the cells were able to produce lipids without compromising growth and the mechanism is still to be exploited. Further investigation can provide us with novel insights for enhancement of lipids among specific strains without negotiating growth. However, the FAME profiling depicting the saturation and unsaturation levels was more promising in the case of N- cells. Nitrogen-deprived cells had a high level of SFAs and MUFAs, while PUFAs levels are decreased (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>b). This profile is more suitable in terms of biodiesel as the amount of polyunsaturation affects overall properties of biodiesel. Lower PUFA level is mainly helpful in lowering ignition delay, increasing stability against oxidation and lowering NOx emission [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" class="xref">81</xref>], whereas in P- cells the PUFA content was higher than SFAs and MUFAs in 
 <italic class="italic">P. kessleri</italic>.
</p>
