<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par43" class="p">Citric acid positively regulates acetyl-CoA-carboxylase which is the enzyme for the first committed step towards FA biosynthesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" class="xref">94</xref>]. Citric acid is an intermediate of Calvin cycle; when transported from mitochondria to cytoplasm, it breaks down into oxaloacetic acid and acetyl-CoA diverting flux towards FA biosynthesis. Increased citrate may act as an acetyl-CoA carrier for fatty acid synthesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" class="xref">95</xref>]. In 
 <italic class="italic">Nannochloropsis salina</italic>, kinetic profiles and activity studies showed that this Eustigmatophyceae strain is able to convert sugar via citrate cycle towards lipids [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" class="xref">96</xref>] and the exogenous supply of citrate showed increased fatty acid biosynthesis in 
 <italic class="italic">Chlamydomonas</italic> sp. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">85</xref>]. Upregulated citrate may provide acetyl-CoA in cytoplasm which can further be utilized to produce FA molecules. Citric acid was highly upregulated in both N- and P- cells. Similarly, 2-ketoglutaric acid has also emerged as a master regulator in essential pathways. Like citric acid, it is also a cataplerotic molecule, enhancing to provide synthesis and regulation of other molecules desired by the cells. It was found to be interacting with the regulator of acetyl-CoA carboxylase enzyme (ACCase), thus relieving ACCase for fatty acid biosynthesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>]. 2-Ketoglutaric acid was also found to increase in nitrogen stress, providing backbone for nitrogen assimilation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" class="xref">97</xref>]. Amino acid degradation may also lead to accumulation of 2-ketoglutarate, which can be further converted back to citrate for FA synthesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" class="xref">98</xref>].
</p>
