<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Here we show biological invasions decrease the diversity of environmental microbiomes. While several studies have investigated the effects of species invasions on environmental microbiomes, we still lack a generalized consensus across different environmental microbiomes and systems. Previous studies have found that invasive species increased environmental microbial diversity [
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], while others reported a decrease [
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. However, the majority of studies did not analyze the microbial diversity, as they used techniques that did not allow for such analysis, or reported no changes [
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Within the studies included in our analysis, invasion by feral pigs decreased soil microbial diversity, while invasion by 
 <italic>Artemisia rothrockii</italic> increased soil microbial diversity. The remaining three studies in our analysis reported no effects of biological invasions on environmental microbiome diversity. Our analysis was constrained in terms of sampled environment (soil) and invasive organism (plants), and an expanded dataset would be beneficial to generalize our results. Microbial diversity is tied to the function of microbiomes, and changes in diversity can reflect changes in function [
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Changes in microbial diversity and function do not always have the same direction [
 <xref rid="pone.0240996.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>], which might explain the discrepancy between our results and other studies. While we observed a relatively small reduction of the Shannon diversity index in invaded environments compared to non-invaded environment, this matches with the changes we observed in terms of community composition.
</p>
