<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Animals</div>
 <sec id="sec2.5.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.1. Animals and Care</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 48 adult male Wistar rats (200 ± 20 g) were purchased from the Beijing Vital River Laboratory Animal Technology Co., Ltd. (Certificate: SCXK (Beijing) 2012-0001). All rats were housed in conventional cages in a temperature (22°C–24°C) and light-controlled (12-hour light- dark cycle) room for 7 days [
   <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>] with standard rat chow and water ad libitum [
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>]. The experimental protocol was approved by the local Animal Care Committee at the Beijing University of Chinese Medicine. All the experimental procedures were carried out in accordance with the international guidelines for the care and use of laboratory animals.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.5.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.2. Grouping of Animal</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The animals were randomly divided into 4 groups, with 12 rats in each group. The groups were the control group, the fatigue group, the essential oil mixture (EOM) group, and the peppermint essential oil (PEO) group. The EOM and PEO groups were, respectively, nebulized with a mixture of essential oils and peppermint oil (0.4 ml/kg of body mass of each kind of oil) mixed with 2 ml of distilled water, according to the method validated by Chen et al. [
   <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>]. The control group and fatigue group were nebulized with an equal volume of distilled water. All groups were nebulized 10 minutes after the end of swimming to exhaustion.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.5.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.3. Rat Fatigue Model</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Loaded swimming to exhaustion was selected as the fatigue model and evaluation index. Xiaoming et al. [
   <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>] noted that swimming has more advantages than other exercises such as the treadmill because training is not required since rodents have a natural swimming ability, and they would try to struggle to avoid drowning even when fatigue is extreme, assuring a high level of performance.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After 7 days acclimation, the weight loaded swimming to exhaustion was carried out as described by Chi et al. [
   <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>] with slight modifications. All of the rats were removed from the fatigue group, EOM group, and PEO group for the swimming to exhaustion in a pool (length 65 cm, width 50 cm, depth 50 cm, water depth 30 cm, and temperature 25 ± 1°C). A lead block (10% of body weight) was attached to the tail root of the swimming rat [
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>]. The rats were determined to be exhausted when they failed to rise to the surface to breathe after 7 s [
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>]. The rats in the control group were normally raised without any treatment until the end of the experiment. Swimming to exhaustion started at 5 p.m. every day for three days. All rats were fasted 12 hours before bleeding.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
