<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While dealing with plant-derived phenolics, it should be kept in mind that over 80,000 different types of phenolics with wide range of chemical structures have been found in plant kingdom (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Dai and Mumper, 2010</xref>). This plant must have a large number of phenolic compounds but only a very small fraction was identified by GC–MS. Possibly, due to limitations of the analysis of non-derivatized polar organics by GC–MS, relatively polar plant phenolics such as the derivatives of benzoic acid (gallic acid), and the derivatives of cinnamic acid (coumaric acid, caffeic acid and ferulic acids) that were detected by HPLC remained undetected in GC–MS. It may be mentioned here that gallic acid and catechin have antioxidant and anticancer properties (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Dai and Mumper, 2010</xref>) while caffeic acid was reported to reduce the acute immune and inflammatory response (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 1988</xref>). Besides, rutin has antioxidant, antihypertensive, antiviral and antiplatelet properties (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Ganeshpurkara and Salujaa 2017</xref>) while ferulic acid is a strong antioxidant (
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">Srinivasan et al., 2007</xref>). Apart from significant antioxidant potential (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Gramza et al., 2005</xref>), gallic acid has also been shown to possess antimicrobial activity against human pathogens (
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Corynobacterium accolans, Candida albicans</italic>) as well as plant pathogen (
 <italic>Erwinia carotovora</italic>) (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Fogliani et al., 2005</xref>). Other studies have reported cytotoxic activity of gallic acid (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Kaur et al., 2005</xref>). Again, since gallic acid can act as a nucleophile, it can therefore scavenge electrophilic mutagens (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Hour et al., 1999</xref>). Molecules detected by HPLC like gallic acid (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Badhani et al., 2015</xref>), ferulic acid (
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">Srinivasan et al., 2007</xref>), and rutin were reported to possess strong antioxidant activity (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Al-Rejaie et al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
