<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous studies had reported insecticidal and mosquito larvicidal activities of inland halophytes (
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr">Thangam and Kathiresan, 1991</xref>) including some mangroves of Indian Sundarbans (
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">Suresh et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Balakrishnan et al., 2016</xref>). Apart from the observed insecticidal and mosquitocidal activities in solvent extract of 
 <italic>S. monoica,</italic> presence of many phytochemicals (4-Carene, eicosane, eicosane, 2-methyl, methyl ester of carbamic acid, and pinane) with reports of insecticidal and mosquitocidal properties have been registered (
 <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). So, 
 <italic>S. monoica</italic> can be included in the growing list of plants with significant mosquito larvicidal activity for the production of insect and mosquito repellents. In addition to the antimicrobial and insecticidal properties, nearly monotypic species distribution of the plant made us curious to know about allelochemic property of the plant, which has not been reported so far. Allelopathic compounds of plants are secondary compounds that exert stimulatory, neutral, or inhibitory activity to the receiving target plant or plant organ. As seeds are an important plant organ and most sensitive to allelochemicals, seed germination is the most widely used bioassay for allelopathic studies. As expected, a significant dose-dependent phytotoxic activity of the polar extracts of the plant was observed toward tomato seeds (as representative glycophyte) and Amaranthus (as widely known weed), establishing the herbicidal and weedicidal potential of the mangrove associate. Our finding of the allelopathic potential of the plant was supported by the detection of various phytochemicals like furfural, 2-furanmethanol, 2,4-di-tert-butylphenol, 2-methoxy-4-vinylphenol, diphenyl ether etc (
 <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), reported to have herbicidal activity. A high amount of saponin is related to the haemolytic property i.e., lysis of normal and red blood cells (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Gauthier et al., 2009</xref>), but antihaemolysis assay detected the significant presence of anti-haemolytic property in the polar solvent extract of the plant, which was again supported by the identification of the relevant anti-inflammatory compounds by GC–MS (
 <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Apart from above, phytol and 7,9-di-tert-butyl-1-oxaspiro (4,5)deca-6,9-diene-2,8-dione, 3,7,11,15-tetramethyl-2-hexadecene found in this study, had also been reported as diuretic agents (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Duke, 1992</xref>). In addition, GC–MS data also showed the presence of probable hepatoprotective molecules as well as antitumor and anticancer or cancer preventive biomolecules (
 <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). From the above comprehensive biochemical, functional and chemometric studies, it became clear that the plant 
 <italic>S. monoica</italic> is a wonderful phytomedicinal plant and has got a rich reservoir of structurally diverse molecules of therapeutic importance.
</p>
