<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Microb Cell Fact</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Microb. Cell Fact</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Microbial Cell Factories</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1475-2859</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6240951</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1026</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12934-018-1026-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Triauxic growth of an oleaginous red yeast <italic>Rhodosporidium toruloides</italic> on waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019; for enhanced and concomitant lipid and &#x003b2;-carotene production</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>Gunjan</given-names></name><address><email>gunjan.sngh15@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>Sweta</given-names></name><address><email>swetariteshsinha@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name><address><email>kkbandyopadhyay@amity.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><address><email>lawrence@cvm.msstate.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3893-658X</contrib-id><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>Debarati</given-names></name><address><phone>91(0) - 120-4392645</phone><email>dpaul@amity.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1805 0217</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.444644.2</institution-id><institution>Amity Institute of Biotechnology, </institution><institution>Amity University, </institution></institution-wrap>Sec 125, Noida, Uttar Pradesh 201313 India </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0816 8287</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.260120.7</institution-id><institution>Basic Sciences, College of Veterinary Medicine, </institution><institution>Mississippi State University, </institution></institution-wrap>Mississippi State, MS 39762 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>182</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Vegetable &#x02018;mandi&#x02019; (road-side vegetable market) waste was converted to a suitable fermentation medium for cultivation of oleaginous yeast <italic>Rhodosporidium toruloides</italic> by steaming under pressure. This cultivation medium derived from waste was found to be a comparatively better source of nutrients than standard culture media because it provided more than one type of usable carbon source(s) to yeast.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">HPLC results showed that the extract contained glucose, xylose and glycerol along with other carbon sources, allowing triauxic growth pattern with preferably usage of glucose, xylose and glycerol resulting in enhanced growth, lipid and carotenoid production. Presence of saturated and unsaturated fatty acid methyl esters (FAMEs) (C<sub>14-20</sub>) in the lipid profile showed that the lipid may be transesterified for biodiesel production.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par3">Upscaling these experiments to fermenter scale for the production of lipids and biodiesel and other industrially useful products would lead to waste management along with the production of value added commodities. The technique is thus environment friendly and gives good return upon investment.<graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="12934_2018_1026_Figa_HTML" id="MO6"/></p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12934-018-1026-4) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>R. toruloides</italic></kwd><kwd>Oleaginous yeast</kwd><kwd>Waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019;</kwd><kwd>Triauxic</kwd><kwd>Lipid</kwd><kwd>Carotenoids</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001407</institution-id><institution>Department of Biotechnology , Ministry of Science and Technology</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>BT/PR7122/PBD/26/369/2012</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>Debarati</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par11">Rising concerns on elevated energy prices and environmental deterioration has led to a search for environment-friendly alternatives to traditional energy fuels, and in this aspect, biodiesel has proved to be one of the most promising potential substitutes. In biodiesel, the content of hydrocarbons responsible for pollution is in very low amounts. The net emission of carbon dioxide was 0% when pure biodiesel is used, as compared to 15.65% emission in a 20% blended-biodiesel sample [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Biodiesel is also less corrosive, easier to transport or store than conventional petroleum and is hence considered as a clean and renewable alternative. European Union (EU) data showed that EU accounts for 53% of the world&#x02019;s biodiesel production in 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. It has been projected by the International Energy agency that by 2050, biofuels will be able to meet at least a quarter of world&#x02019;s fuel demand [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. This implies that there is an immense boost for evolving biofuels as an alternate energy resource. Various feedstock can be used to produce biodiesel including oil extracted from plants or animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], however, plant based or animal based oils contest for water and land, otherwise utilized for farming practices. They also compete with food which is undersupplied to some third world nations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. To address the above issues, microbial oil is now being considered as a feed for its low cost and environment friendly processing during biodiesel production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Microbial oils exhibit several advantages over vegetable oils, due to the short doubling times exhibited by microbes and the growth is less impacted by spatial and temporal factors and readily responds to scale up as required [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par12">Oleaginous yeasts, such as <italic>R. toruloides</italic> that accumulate lipids up to 50% of their body weight, have been reported to grow on various cheap carbon sources including industrial effluents, and are invaluable sources of triacylglycerides (TAG&#x02019;s). Yeasts have advantages over algae and molds due to faster growth rate and can be easily cultivated on large scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. A study by Cheirsilp et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] in Southern Thailand, shows that effluents from natural rubber, palm oil and biodiesel processing industries, contain high amounts of organic load contributing to significant chemical oxygen demand (COD). Other waste material i.e. serum latex from the rubber latex concentrate industry, crude glycerol from biodiesel plant and molasses from sugarcane plant; all potentially serve as carbon-rich substrate for growing oleaginous yeast strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Palm oil mill effluent (rich in minerals and vitamins) is another waste medium, effectively used for growing oleaginous yeasts such as <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In India, rich agricultural resources lead to the generation of&#x02009;~&#x02009;50 MT of vegetable and fruit waste per annum, which may be considered for utilizing and growing microorganisms for biofuels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Production of yeast-oil using agro-industrial waste [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], food waste/municipal wastewater as feedstock have been cited as &#x02018;promising techniques&#x02019; for producing alternate energy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] and is considered as a valuable feedstock for yeast-oil.</p><p id="Par13">The fatty acids mostly accumulated are palmitic acids (C16:0), stearic acid (C18:0), linoleic acid (C81:2), linolenic acid (C18:3), etc. amongst other FAMEs compounds and such combinations of long chain FAMEs are similar to vegetable oils and preferred for biodiesel production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Red yeasts also produce carotenoids that are active as anti-cancer agents, as singlet oxygen foragers, as resistant reaction stimulants and furthermore as additives for makeup [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The application of chemical synthetic methods to prepare carotenoid compounds as food additives have been strictly regulated, leading to increased interests on finding biotechnological solutions. Several strains such as <italic>Rhodosporidium</italic>, <italic>Phaffia</italic>, <italic>Cystofilobasidium</italic>, etc. are known to produce carotenoids, amongst which <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-carotene, torulene, torularhodin are the main components found in <italic>Rhodosporidium</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">In this study, we have successfully cultivated <italic>R. toruloides</italic> using waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019; obtained by steaming fruit peels and inedible/discarded parts of vegetables e.g. cauliflower stubs, pea pods, etc. which are generally discarded and pollute vegetable markets (mandis) in India. The lab scale biorefinery has been developed to convert waste material to useful bio-products such as biodiesel and carotenoids, with zero discharge. The FAMEs obtained from <italic>R. toruloides</italic> included mixtures of long chain fatty acids e.g. linoleic, oleic acid, and palmitic acid that have potentials in soap and cosmetics industry apart from being important components of biodiesel. Carotenoids extracted from <italic>R. toruloides</italic> showed the presence of a mixture of various components (&#x003b2;-carotene, torularhodin, torulene, etc.), &#x003b2;-carotene being the major component [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par15">This bioprocess described in this study can be potentially used in future for cultivating various industrially important microbes that are capable of utilizing more than one carbon source present in the culture medium. The study also suggests an economical method for utilization of different types of waste particularly from &#x02018;mandis&#x02019; that otherwise contaminate market places and give off foul odour by decomposing and facilitating rapid proliferation of house flies, roaches, etc.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Microorganism and cultivation</title><p id="Par16"><italic>Rhodosporidium toruloides</italic> (ATCC 204091) obtained from the College of Veterinary Medicine, Mississippi State University, USA was used for all experiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The yeast was grown and maintained on culture plates containing minimal media (MM): glucose 5&#x000a0;g/L; di-sodium hydrogen phosphate dehydrate 6&#x000a0;g/L; sodium chloride 5&#x000a0;g/L; potassium dihydrogen phosphate 3&#x000a0;g/L; ammonium chloride 2&#x000a0;g/L; magnesium sulphate 0.1&#x000a0;g/L; yeast extract 2&#x000a0;g/L; agar 1.6% (w/v); pH 5.5 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Preparation of waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019;</title><p id="Par17">Inedible matter (composed of peels of orange, sweet lemon, banana, mango, pea pods and stubs of cauliflower/cabbage) obtained from &#x02018;mandis&#x02019;, juice shops and various cafeterias, was utilized for obtaining culture medium for <italic>R. toruloides.</italic> The collected waste material was shredded; 30&#x000a0;g of it was steamed in 100&#x000a0;mL water for 15&#x000a0;min to prepare an &#x02018;extract&#x02019; that would be used as fermentation medium, hence called waste extract (WE) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Seasonal variations in sugar content in WE was observed and so while preparing it each time, the C/N ratio was maintained at 30:1 to minimize this variation and also methods related to WE preparation and pretreatment were standardized and have been reported previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The various types of &#x02018;mandi&#x02019; waste (orange/pea/mango/papaya peels; cauliflower/cabbage stubs) were analyzed individually for carbon (C) and nitrogen (N) content (data not shown). Peels with higher C content were added with those having appropriate N content to maintain the standardized C/N ratio of 30:1 in the resultant WE. C was determined by phenol sulphuric acid test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], DNS for reducing sugar [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] and N by Kjeldahl method. After autoclaving, nutritional analysis of dried waste was done at Central Laboratory for Soil and Plant Analysis, Division of Soil Science and Agricultural Chemistry, ICAR-Indian Agricultural Research Institute, New Delhi (India).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019; preparation using <bold>a</bold> peels and stubs of fruits and vegetables; <bold>b</bold> distilled water added with measured amount of waste; <bold>c</bold> autoclaved; <bold>d</bold> filtered using muslin cloth; <bold>e</bold> filtered waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019; for fermentation medium; <bold>f</bold> waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019; as fermentation medium and <bold>g</bold> yeast grown in shake flasks containing waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019;</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12934_2018_1026_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Cultivation of <italic>R. toruloides</italic></title><p id="Par18">A 48&#x000a0;h old seed culture (log phase) having optimal density (OD<sub>600</sub>) in the range of 0.6&#x02013;0.8 was used to inoculate a 50&#x000a0;mL WE. Samples were collected at every 6&#x02013;12&#x000a0;h interval for determination of OD (600&#x000a0;nm), dry and wet cell weight, total sugar [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] and reducing sugar [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] of the medium; lipid content and &#x003b2;-carotene content of the biomass. The cells were harvested by centrifugation using pre-weighed tubes, at 4000&#x000a0;rpm for 10&#x000a0;min; supernatant was discarded and harvested cells were weighed (wet cell weight) and then dried in oven at 80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02013;2&#x000a0;h, till dry and final weight of centrifuge tubes containing cells were obtained (~&#x02009;20% of wet weight). This is the dry cell weight (DCW) and is expressed in (g/L). DCW&#x02009;=&#x02009;(W<sub>2</sub>&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;W<sub>1</sub>)/V<sub>1</sub>; where: W<sub>2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;weight of tube containing dried cells, W<sub>1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;weight of empty tube and V<sub>1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;Volume of culture [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Biomass was assessed by absorbance (OD 600&#x000a0;nm) and DCW of pellet. These parameters were further used to calculate kinetic parameters such as t<sub>d</sub> (doubling time), t<sub>g</sub> (generation time) and &#x000b5; (specific growth).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Analytical methods</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Determination of lipid content</title><p id="Par19">Extraction of lipid was done following the protocol of Bligh and Dyer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The cells (100&#x02013;1000&#x000a0;mg) were harvested by centrifugation at 10,000&#x000a0;rpm for 10&#x000a0;min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, washed once with distilled water and the dry pellet weight was recorded (W). The dry pellet was resuspended in 3.75&#x000a0;ml of chloroform/methanol (2:1, v/v solution) and vortexed for 15&#x000a0;min, followed by 1.25&#x000a0;ml of chloroform and 1.25&#x000a0;ml of 1&#x000a0;M NaCl, with vortexing at every step.</p><p id="Par20">The mixture was centrifuged at 3000&#x000a0;rpm for 15&#x000a0;min to separate the aqueous and organic phase. The organic lower phase was transferred to a weighed vial and dried till organic phase evaporated. The weight of the vial was again recorded (W2).</p><p id="Par21">Therefore, lipid content from dry cell biomass was calculated as:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{Lipid content }}\left( {{\text{g}}/{\text{L}}} \right) \, = \frac{{{\text{Lipid weight in weighed vial }}\left( {\text{g}} \right) \, {-}{\text{ empty weighed vial }}\left( {\text{g}} \right)}}{{{\text{Grown in sample Volume }}\left( {\text{L}} \right)}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Lipid content</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Lipid weight in weighed vial</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/><mml:mtext>empty weighed vial</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Grown in sample Volume</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12934_2018_1026_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{Lipid content }}\left( \% \right) \, = \frac{{{\text{Lipid content }}\left( {{\text{g}}/{\text{L}}} \right)}}{{{\text{Dry cell weight }}\left( {{\text{g}}/{\text{L}}} \right)}} \times { 1}00$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Lipid content</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Lipid content</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Dry cell weight</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12934_2018_1026_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="Equc"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\text{Lipid Productivity }} = \frac{{{\text{lipid concentration}}({\text{g}}/{\text{L}})}}{{{\text{Fermentation time }}\left( {\text{hrs}} \right)}}[{\text{unit}} - {\text{g}}/{\text{L}}/{\text{h}}]$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Lipid Productivity</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lipid concentration</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Fermentation time</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mtext>hrs</mml:mtext></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>unit</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12934_2018_1026_Article_Equc.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Transesterification and FAME analysis</title><p id="Par22">Transesterification of 0.15&#x000a0;g lipid (extracted from pelleted cells) was performed in a glass tube using 2&#x000a0;mL <italic>n</italic>-Hexane and 1&#x000a0;mL 2&#x000a0;M methanolic-KOH. The tubes were capped and vigorously shaken for 30&#x000a0;s and then incubated for 20&#x000a0;min at 70&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. After cooling to room temperature 1.2&#x000a0;ml of 1&#x000a0;M HCl was added with gentle stirring and 1&#x000a0;ml of <italic>n</italic>-hexane was added and the mixture was allowed to stand for separation of phases. The upper yellow phase containing the FAMEs was transferred into the glass vial for further identification using gas chromatography (GC).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Gas chromatography</title><p id="Par23">Gas chromatography was done to quantify and identify individual components present in transesterified samples. It was performed on a Rastech gas chromatography model 2806 (Delhi, India) equipped with 30&#x000a0;m long (film thickness 0.25 um; internal diameter 0.25&#x000a0;mm) GC column EC&#x02122;<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (Grace Davison Discovery Sciences) containing dimethyl polysiloxane as the stationary phase and a flame ionization detector with Winchrom (IndTech Instruments) acquisition software, under the following conditions: carrier gas N<sub>2</sub> flow 1&#x000a0;mL/min, column pressure 2.05&#x000a0;bar, initial oven temperature was maintained at 200&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min and then elevated to 280&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C at 10 C min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, injector temperature 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, detector temperature 275&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with 2&#x000a0;kg/cc air flow. Identification and quantification of methyl esters were based on the comparison of retention times and peak areas of commercial standards, sample volume used was 0.2&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L (diluted with hexane).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>GC-mass spectrographic analysis</title><p id="Par24">Methyl esters of fatty acids were analyzed by a Gas Chromatography&#x02013;Mass spectrometry on a Shimadzu GCMS&#x02014;QP 2010 Plus (Shimadzu, Japan) fitted with a SP&#x02013;2560 capillary column (100&#x000a0;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x000a0;mm i.d). The temperatures of injection and detector ports were set at 260&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The oven temperature programmed was initially at 140&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min, then rose at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C/minute to 240&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and finally held at 240&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min. The carrier gas was nitrogen with a total flow rate of 16.3&#x000a0;mL/min. MS conditions: Ionization voltage was 70&#x000a0;eV; ion source temperature was 270&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and mass range was 30&#x02013;700 mass units. The individual peaks were identified by comparing their retention indices with standard chromatogram and their mass spectra with NIST/Wiley library of mass spectral database.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Carotenoid extraction</title><p id="Par25">Carotenoids were extracted using a modified method of Kim and Park [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Cells were collected by centrifugation, washed and treated with DMSO, incubated at 50&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;h and the process was repeated till all the carotenoids were extracted in DMSO. The carotenoids were then extracted in the hexane phase by liquid&#x02013;liquid extraction. The OD of the supernatant was determined at 450&#x000a0;nm against hexane using a Systronics UV&#x02013;Vis spectrophotometer 117. Quantification was done using standard curve of &#x003b2;-carotene (prepared in hexane). &#x003b2;-carotene was quantified as it is present as one of the components of yeast carotenoids. All statistical calculations were done using <italic>MEDCALC Software bvba</italic> statistical software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.medcalc.org">www.medcalc.org</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>HPLC analysis</title><p id="Par26">For detection of different carbon sources such as glucose, xylose, glycerol, arabinose etc. in the WE, HPLC was performed using 5&#x000a0;mM H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> in Milliq water as mobile phase in a HPLC column AMINEX HPX-87H, 300X7.8MM that is specially designed for ethanol and organic acids estimation. The flow rate was maintained at 0.5&#x000a0;mL/min. HPLC analysis was used to determine the presence of various sugars in the WE and changes in their concentration after fermentation.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Cell Growth and glucose utilization of <italic>R. toruloides</italic> grown in &#x02018;extracts&#x02019; made from waste(s)</title><p id="Par27">Nutritional analysis of the waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019; (WE) showed the presence of 30% carbon, 1% nitrogen, 0.18% phosphorus and 0.56% potassium. <italic>R.toruloides</italic> showed a triauxic growth pattern when grown on WE but not when grown in minimal medium (MM) containing glucose as the only carbon source (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, b). The total sugar content of WE at the beginning of the experiment (0&#x000a0;h reading) was&#x02009;~&#x02009;20&#x000a0;g/L (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b), comprising of 48.55% glucose, 30.9% xylose and 20.4% glycerol apart from smaller amounts of arabinose, xylitol, etc. as determined by HPLC analyses. Various agro-industrial residues, such as monosodium glutamate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], methanol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], molasses/crude glycerol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], soluble starch [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] have been reported as growth media for producing lipid by various oleaginous microorganisms (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). All of these waste sources showed the presence of a single carbon source; however, WE contained multiple carbon sources, such as arabinose, xylohexose, xylitol, succinate acid etc. with glucose, xylose and glycerol as predominant components. <italic>R. toruloides</italic> efficiently utilized more than one carbon source for growth and lipid formation as also indicated by its growth curve.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Comparative study of growth, lipid and carotenoid production during batch cultivation of&#x000a0;<italic>R. toruloides</italic>&#x000a0;in <bold>a</bold> Minimal medium <bold>b</bold> Waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019;</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12934_2018_1026_Fig2_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Comparative study of lipid production from different strains of oleaginous yeast</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Oleaginous yeast strain</th><th align="left">Carbon source</th><th align="left">Growth medium</th><th align="left">Biomass<break/>(g/l)</th><th align="left">Lipid content (% dcw)</th><th align="left">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Rhodospordium toruloides</italic>
</td><td align="left">Glucose/xylose/glycerol</td><td align="left">Waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019;</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">74.5</td><td align="left">The present work</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Rhodotorula glutinis</italic>
</td><td align="left">Glucose</td><td align="left">Monosodium glutamate (MSG) wastewater</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Candida lipolytica</italic>
</td><td align="left">Methanol</td><td align="left">NA<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">NA<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">4.9</td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic>
</td><td align="left">Molasses and crude glycerol</td><td align="left">YPD</td><td align="left">50 cdw</td><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cryptococcus terricola</italic> JCM 24523</td><td align="left">Soluble starch</td><td align="left">YPD</td><td align="left">4.88</td><td align="left">61.96</td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Rhodosporidium toruloides</italic> AS2.1389</td><td align="left">Wastewater</td><td align="left">YPD</td><td align="left">8.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.23</td><td align="left">43.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.74</td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Rhodotorula glutinis</italic> TR29</td><td align="left">Molasses</td><td align="left">Malt extract broth (MEB)</td><td align="left">16.2</td><td align="left">64.8</td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Yarrowia. lipolytica</italic> B9</td><td align="left">Deproteinized whey</td><td align="left">DWB medium</td><td align="left">7.4</td><td align="left">58</td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>Metschnikowia pulcherrima</italic>
</td><td align="left">Glycerol</td><td align="left">OMP medium</td><td align="left">7.4</td><td align="left">40</td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cryptococcus curvatus</italic> ATCC 20509</td><td align="left">Corn stover</td><td align="left">YPD liquid medium</td><td align="left">27.7</td><td align="left">43.6</td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup> Comparative results were analyzed according to dry cell (W/V)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par28">Analysis of the growth curve of <italic>R. toruloides</italic> using WE as culture medium showed that there was a significant increase in cell mass after 6&#x000a0;h of cultivation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b), whereas in case of MM, the increase was observed after 22&#x000a0;h. The log phase progressed from 6&#x000a0;h to 16&#x000a0;h, followed by a short stationary phase after 24&#x000a0;h and then the second log phase progressed from 30&#x000a0;h to 48&#x000a0;h, followed by a third log phase (~&#x02009;56&#x000a0;h to 72&#x000a0;h). Different growth phases log 1, log 2 and log 3 supported growths at the rate of 0.109/h, 0.043/h and 0.039/h (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). HPLC analysis (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table&#x000a0;S1A) and (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1A) of the cell-free fermentation medium was performed at various time points during growth, to evaluate the utilization of glucose, xylose, glycerol, etc. Results showed that&#x02009;~&#x02009;80% glucose was consumed (10.9&#x000a0;g/L to 2.6&#x000a0;g/L in 24&#x000a0;h) during the initial log phase and preferably used as main carbon source along with slight co-consumption of xylose and glycerol (~&#x02009;5% of each in 24&#x000a0;h). HPLC data and kinetic growth rate variations supports the &#x02018;triauxic&#x02019; mode of growth where the organism preferentially used a particular sugar faster than the others, during the three log phases in WE (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). We observed that during log phase 3, biomass production was enhanced and the productivity was the highest (0.20&#x000a0;g/L/h) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Glycerol and other carbon sources were probably used during the 3<sup>rd</sup> log phase, as they were rapidly consumed toward the end (72 to 80&#x000a0;h). Glucose might have been valuable as a growth initiator but higher productivities were observed during the third log phase, which may be attributed to higher solubility and slower catabolism of glycerol. Between glucose and xylose a diauxic pattern of growth was reported earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] in which one substrate was catabolized preferentially over the other with a lag phase occurring between the growth phases.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Kinetic parameters of <italic>R. toruloides</italic> during growth in minimal medium and waste extract</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Growth Medium</th><th align="left">Growth phase</th><th align="left">Specific growth rate (&#x000b5;)<break/>(h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left">Doubling time (t<sub>d</sub>)<break/>(h)</th><th align="left">Yield (Y<sub>x/s</sub>)</th><th align="left">Yield (Y<sub>p/x</sub>)</th><th align="left">Yield (Y<sub>p/s</sub>)</th><th align="left">Productivity (g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1. Minimal medium</td><td align="left">Log</td><td char="." align="char">0.093</td><td char="." align="char">7.44</td><td char="." align="char">0.91</td><td char="." align="char">0.6</td><td char="." align="char">1.37</td><td char="." align="char">0.110</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2. Waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019;</td><td align="left">Log 1</td><td char="." align="char">0.109</td><td char="." align="char">6.35</td><td char="." align="char">0.41</td><td char="." align="char">0.15</td><td char="." align="char">0.06</td><td char="." align="char">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Log 2</td><td char="." align="char">0.039</td><td char="." align="char">17.63</td><td char="." align="char">0.61</td><td char="." align="char">0.28</td><td char="." align="char">0.17</td><td char="." align="char">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Log 3</td><td char="." align="char">0.043</td><td char="." align="char">15.87</td><td char="." align="char">0.94</td><td char="." align="char">0.74</td><td char="." align="char">0.70</td><td char="." align="char">0.20</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par29">After growing for about 72&#x000a0;h, there was a constant decrease in OD until 96&#x000a0;h, suggesting decrease in cell viability and growth. Yield<sub>(X/S</sub>) was highest during log phase 3 (0.94&#x000a0;g/g) as compared to log phase 1 (0.41&#x000a0;g/g), followed by log phase 2 (0.61&#x000a0;g/g) as it is the preferred carbon source for this strain (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Lipid production by <italic>R. toruloides</italic> grown in extracts made from &#x02018;mandi&#x02019; waste</title><p id="Par30">When grown on WE, initially the lipid content increased significantly, as indicated by lipid saturated cells. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b shows the lipid production profile of <italic>R. toruloides</italic> at different time intervals. Lipid content calculated initially at 22&#x000a0;h was 4.898&#x000a0;g/L i.e. 15.8% of DCW and highest lipid content was 13.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.50&#x000a0;g/L i.e. 74.5% of 18&#x000a0;g/L DCW. Highest lipid content determined in case of MM was 5.76&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.78&#x000a0;g/L i.e. 60% of 9.6&#x000a0;g/L DCW. The significance level (p value) calculated form <italic>t</italic> test was 0.003.</p><p id="Par31">The consumption of carbon source(s), cell growth and lipid production demonstrated adequate utilization of all available growth substrates by <italic>R. toruloides.</italic> Productivity of lipids in WE during triauxic growth was calculated as 0.20&#x000a0;g/L/h in duration of 67&#x000a0;h (as described in the methods). GC and GC&#x02013;MS analysis confirmed the occurrence of long chain fatty acids namely myristic, palmitic, palmitoleic, oleic, stearic and linoleic acid present in various amounts (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The content of oleic acid, lauric acid, stearic and linoleic acid varied when cultivated in MM and WE. As determined by GC&#x02013;MS, cells cultivated in WE showed 44.63% increase in oleic acid and 13.39% in linoleic acid respectively, as compared to cells grown in MM. Stearic, linoleic acid and oleic acid and their uses for making soaps, cosmetics, agricultural chemicals, etc. are depicted in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. The presence of such important products may be made cost effective by standardizing its production on inexpensive nutrient sources such as WE.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>The fatty acids content in the lipid of <italic>R. toruloides</italic> obtained from GC analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Lipid composition</th><th align="left">Fatty acid type</th><th align="left">Content of fatty acid<break/>(%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Lauric acid (C12)</td><td align="left">Saturated fatty acid</td><td align="left">2.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Myristic acid (C14)</td><td align="left">Saturated fatty acid</td><td align="left">4.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Palmitic acid (C16)</td><td align="left">Saturated fatty acid</td><td align="left">13.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Margaric acid (C17)</td><td align="left">Saturated fatty acid</td><td align="left">2.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Oleic acid (C18:1)</td><td align="left">Mono-unsaturated fatty acid</td><td char="." align="char">32.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Linoleic acid (C18:2)</td><td align="left">Poly-unsaturated fatty acid</td><td align="left">22.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Others</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">21.95</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Fatty acid composition (FAMES) as determined by GC&#x02013;MS analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Compound name &#x00026; symbol</th><th align="left">Fatty acid type</th><th align="left">Waste &#x02018;Extract&#x02019;</th><th align="left">Minimal media</th><th align="left">Uses</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">C<sub>12.0</sub><break/>(Lauric acid/dodecanoic acid)</td><td align="left">Saturated fatty acid</td><td char="." align="char">2.02</td><td char="." align="char">3.03</td><td align="left">Long shelf-life, non-toxic, treatment for&#x000a0;acne, production of&#x000a0;soaps&#x000a0;and cosmetics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>14.0</sub><break/>(Myristic acid/&#x000a0;tetradecanoic acid)</td><td align="left">Saturated fatty acid</td><td char="." align="char">4.23</td><td char="." align="char">4.49</td><td align="left">Myristic acid acts as a lipid anchor in biomembranes. The ester&#x000a0;isopropyl myristate is used in cosmetic and topical medicinal preparations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>16.0</sub><break/>(Palmitic acid/hexadecanoic acid)</td><td align="left">Saturated fatty acid</td><td char="." align="char">13.42</td><td char="." align="char">16.27</td><td align="left">Used in production of soaps, cosmetics,&#x000a0;release agents, processed food, natural additive in&#x000a0;organic products. Papiperidone&#x000a0;palmitate used in the treatment of schizophrenia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>16.1</sub> &#x003c9;9c<break/>(Palmitoleic acid/9<italic>Z</italic>)-hexadec-9-enoic acid)</td><td align="left">Omega 7-monounsaturated fatty acid</td><td char="." align="char">12.1</td><td char="." align="char">13.79</td><td align="left">Adhesives and sealant chemicals, Agricultural chemicals (non-pesticidal), Finishing agents, Lubricants and lubricant additives, Surface active agents. Also used as supplements and vitamins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>17.0</sub><break/>(Margaric acid/Heptadecanoic acid)</td><td align="left">Saturated fatty acid</td><td char="." align="char">2.83</td><td char="." align="char">5.50</td><td align="left">Adhesives and sealant chemicals, Finishing agents, lubricants, agricultural chemicals (non-pesticidal), surface active agents, flllers, and solvents</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>17.1</sub> &#x003c9;8c<break/>(cis-10-Heptadecenoic acid methyl ester)</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">0.64</td><td char="." align="char">3.67</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>18.0</sub><break/>(Stearic acid/octadecanoic acid)</td><td align="left">Saturated fatty acid</td><td char="." align="char">9.21</td><td char="." align="char">10.47</td><td align="left">Soaps, cosmetics, detergents, lubricants, softening and release agents. Plaster castings, manufacture of lead-acid batteries, candle-making, used along with simple&#x000a0;sugar or&#x000a0;corn syrup as a hardener in candies, dietary supplements, fireworks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>18.1</sub>&#x003c9;9c<break/>(Oleic acid/cis-9-Octadecenoic acid)</td><td align="left">Monounsaturated omega-9 fatty acid</td><td char="." align="char">32.60</td><td char="." align="char">22.54</td><td align="left">Soap as an emulsifying agent, emollient, excipient&#x000a0;in pharmaceuticals, and as an emulsifying or solubilizing agent in aerosol products, soldering flux in stained glass work for joining lead came [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>18.2</sub><break/>(Linoleic acid/9, 12 Octadecadienoic acid)</td><td align="left">Polyunsaturated omega-6 fatty acid</td><td char="." align="char">22.95</td><td char="." align="char">20.24</td><td align="left">Used in making quick-drying oils, useful in&#x000a0;oil paints and varnishes, beauty products industry. Anti-inflammatory, acne reductive, and moisture retentive properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>&#x003b2;-Carotene production by <italic>R. toruloides</italic> grown in extracts made from &#x02018;mandi&#x02019; waste</title><p id="Par32">In the early growth phase, no carotenoid production was observed in either the WE or MM because it is a secondary metabolite. After 45&#x000a0;h of cultivation, carotenoid production started as the culture reached its stationary phase of growth. Maximum carotenoid production was observed after 72&#x000a0;h and 100&#x000a0;h of growth in WE and MM respectively. &#x003b2;-carotene production was determined as 62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.70&#x000a0;mg/L when cultivated on WE as compared to 57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.18&#x000a0;mg/L on MM. A significance value of 0.0251 (P-value), and 95% Confidence Interval (CI) of the difference was established (MEDCALC Software bvba). Earlier reports showed high carotenoid production (1.10&#x000a0;mg/L &#x003b2;-carotene) from <italic>Rhodotorula glutinis</italic> DBVPG 3853 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], and lower production in brewery waste waters ranging between 0.6 and 1.2&#x000a0;mg/L of total average carotenoid content (&#x0223c;&#x02009;50% &#x003b2;-carotene) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. In this study <italic>R. toruloides</italic> cultivated in WE showed an intermediate production (62&#x000a0;mg/L) when compared with earlier reports.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par33"><italic>Rhodosporidium toruloides</italic> is an important oleaginous yeast known for higher lipid production and value added chemicals as it can grow on glucose, xylose and other sugars found in the hydrolysate of &#x02018;waste&#x02019; biomass including lignocelluloses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p><p id="Par34">Various oleaginous yeast have been cultivated in other inexpensive media to produce lipids, such as <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> was grown in molasses (waste generated by sugarcane industry), oleaginous filamentous fungus <italic>Aspergillus oryzae</italic> in potato processing wastewater (starch as carbon source), <italic>Cunninghamella echinulata</italic> on tomato waste hydrolysate (TWH) media (glucose as carbon) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. In all these cases there is primarily one carbon source (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). WE used in this study contained mixed sugars; glucose, xylose, glycerol etc. which were sequentially utilized by <italic>R. toruloides</italic> to synthesize lipids during triauxic growth. The WE medium is inexpensive as compared to synthetic medium and richer in nutrients as compared to other waste resources (stover, molasses, etc.) and appropriate in terms of techno-economic utility of waste to bio-product.</p><p id="Par35"><italic>Rhodosporidium toruloides</italic> has the potential to produce lipids from &#x02018;mandi&#x02019; waste prepared by steaming inedible parts of fruits and vegetables that otherwise pose serious environmental problem. Various sugars in the hydrolysate (depolymerized by steaming) consisted of glucose and xylose that were sequentially metabolized in order of preference by <italic>R. toruloides.</italic> This pattern of growth was reported earlier in <italic>R. minuta</italic> and in <italic>R. glutinis</italic> where diauxic growth is suggested respectively, with&#x02009;~&#x02009;40% and 36.4% &#x000a0;% lipid accumulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. However, earlier study showed that <italic>T. cutaneum</italic> accumulated 59% lipids by utilizing glucose and xylose simultaneously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], suggesting that utilization of sugars is strain dependent and varies with C/N ratio and that sequential or simultaneous utilization of saccharides do not impact accumulation of lipids (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). When cells are grown in a medium that is deficient in a key nutrient, usually nitrogen, they cease to proliferate due to the lack of biosynthesis of proteins and nucleic acids. The excess carbon substrate however, continues to be assimilated by the cells and converted into storage fat (TAGs, sterols, etc.). This phenomenon is common in filamentous fungi and oleaginous yeast strains. However, if the C/N ratio is higher than 80&#x000a0;g/g NH3+&#x02009;, there is a prolonged nitrogen deficiency, thus altering lipid synthesis and directing the metabolic flux toward the production of products such as citric acid. Comparatively product yield (<italic>Y</italic><sub>P/S</sub>) during batch fermentation at high substrate concentration showed that the increase of glucose concentration resulted in the decrease of product yield due to less cell growth. This phenomenon therefore posed some difficulty for the up scaling lipid production due to high substrate consumption rate in the presence of high C/N ratio (i.e. high concentration of glucose with lower level of nitrogen) due to reduction in biomass production. High cell density cultures via fed batch fermentation provide an alternative to achieve higher product yields.</p><p id="Par36">For the production of biodiesel, saturated fatty acids and monounsaturated fatty acids are more valued over saturated fatty acids e.g., C16:0 and C18:0 which are solid at room temperature and can be difficult to use in cold weather for production of biodiesel. On the other hand, monounsaturated fatty acids have better flow properties as they are liquid at room temperature, and hence preferable for biodiesel (27). There are some more higher-value oleochemical products such as nutritional polyunsaturated fatty acids that have a higher profit margin and may be suggested as economically viable products derived from oleaginous yeasts, as compared to biodiesel and might soon become acceptable to industries dealing in solvents, adhesives, lubricants, or platform chemicals.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par37">&#x02018;Mandi&#x02019; waste is a rich amalgamation of various carbon source(s) utilized in culture medium. <italic>R. toruloides</italic> showed triauxic growth when cultivated in it and consequently accumulated higher amounts of lipids and carotenoids. Our results suggest that this culture medium can support in 24.17% increase in lipid and 8.77% increase in carotenoid production as compared to synthetic minimal medium.</p><p id="Par38">The waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019; also contains the essential mineral salts required for growth of the organism and therefore serves as a complete medium (supplemented fermentation medium) in it. This bioprocess is suitable for waste management, is environment friendly and gives good return upon investment (ROI).</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional file</title><sec id="Sec19"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12934_2018_1026_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Table S1.</bold> HPLC analysis of fermentation medium at various time points. Retention time and area compared with standard area to determine concentrations of glucose, xylose and glycerol (g/L). <bold>Figure S1.</bold> HPLC analysis of waste &#x02018;extract&#x02019; at different time points during the cultivation of <italic>R. toruloides,</italic> to determine the utilization of various carbon sources. Blue box indicates glucose; red indicates xylose and black indicates glycerol.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>WE</term><def><p id="Par4">waste extract</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MM</term><def><p id="Par5">minimal medium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HPLC</term><def><p id="Par6">high performance liquid chromatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OD</term><def><p id="Par7">optimal density</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMSO</term><def><p id="Par8">dimethyl sulpho-oxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FAMES</term><def><p id="Par9">fatty acid methyl esters</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GC-MS</term><def><p id="Par10">gas chromatography-mass spectrometer</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>GS, SS, DP and KKB contributed jointly to all the aspects of the work reported in the manuscript. GS and SS performed most of the experiments and data analysis at the Amity University, Noida (India). DP and KKB co-supervised the research and ML and RP provided useful suggestions. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par39">The funding by Dept. of Biotechnology (Govt of India) is acknowledged by GS and DP. We also thank Dr. Abha Kumari, Mr. TP Pandey, Dr. Suresh Korpole (IMTECH) for necessary help and Dr. Paul (Maharaja Agrasen College, Delhi Univeristy) for her assistance in improving the language. Mr. Kiran Kumar and Dr. Naseem Gaur, ICGEB (Delhi) and Central Laboratory For Soil And Plant Analysis, Division of Soil Science and Agricultural Chemistry, ICAR-IARI, New Delhi are specially acknowledged for their help in HPLC and nutritional analysis facility.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par40">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par41">All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in the main manuscript file.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par42">The authors approved the consent for publishing the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par43">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par44">This study was funded by Dept. of Biotechnology (Govt of India) acknowledged by GS and DP (Grant No. BT/PR7122/PBD/26/369/2012).</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par45">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fjerbaek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Norddahl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of the current state of biodiesel production using enzymatic transesterification</article-title><source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source><year>2009</year><volume>102</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1298</fpage><lpage>1315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bit.22256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19215031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamalampudi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Noda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whole-cell biocatalysts for biodiesel fuel production</article-title><source>Trend Biotechnol</source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>668</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibtech.2008.08.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasudevan</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiesel production&#x02014;current state of the art and challenges</article-title><source>J Ind Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2008</year><volume>35</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>421</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10295-008-0312-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18205018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shalaby EA. Biofuel: sources, extraction and determination. InLiquid, Gaseous and Solid Biofuels-Conversion Techniques 2013. InTech.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kummamuru B. WBA global bioenergy statistics 2017. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://worldbioenergy.org/uploads/WBA%20GBS%202017_hq.pdf">https://worldbioenergy.org/uploads/WBA%20GBS%202017_hq.pdf</ext-link>. 2017;202017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antolin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinaut</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimisation of biodiesel production by sunflower oil transesterification</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2002</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-8524(01)00200-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12056485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalai</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation and characterization of biodiesel from various bio-oils</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2001</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-8524(01)00051-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11554602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeshita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Competitiveness, role, and impact of microalgal biodiesel in the global energy future</article-title><source>Appl Energy</source><year>2011</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>3277</fpage><lpage>3279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apenergy.2011.02.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knothe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving biodiesel fuel properties by modifying fatty ester composition</article-title><source>Energy Environ Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>766</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b903941d</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advancing oleaginous microorganisms to produce lipid via metabolic engineering technology</article-title><source>Prog Lipid Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>52</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plipres.2013.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23685199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ratledge</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial and algal oils: do they have a future for biodiesel or as commodity oils?</article-title><source>Lipid Technol</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lite.200800044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheirsilp</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Louhasakul</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Industrial wastes as a promising renewable source for production of microbial lipid and direct transesterification of the lipid into biodiesel</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2013</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2013.05.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23747444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habib</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusoff</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Phang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ang</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutritional values of chironomid larvae grown in palm oil mill effluent and algal culture</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>1997</year><volume>158</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0044-8486(97)00176-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pea peel waste: a lignocellulosic waste and its utility in cellulose production by Trichoderma reesei under solid state cultivation</article-title><source>Bioresource</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1505</fpage><lpage>1519</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahore</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review on applicability of naturally available adsorbents for the removal of hazardous dyes from aqueous waste</article-title><source>Environ Monit Assess</source><year>2011</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10661-011-1914-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21387170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential of fruit and vegetable wastes as novel biosorbents summarizing the recent studies</article-title><source>Rev Environ Sci Biotechnol</source><year>2012</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11157-012-9297-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspectives of microbial oils for biodiesel production</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2008</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>749</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-008-1625-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18690426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>XA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production technology and influencing factors of microorganism grease</article-title><source>Food Res Dev</source><year>2006</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>47</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sales-Campos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Peghini</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of the modulatory effects of oleic acid in health and disease</article-title><source>Mini Rev Med Chem</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23278117?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23278117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruthi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruthi</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergistic effect of&#x000a0;fermentable and non-fermentable carbon sources enhances TAG accumulation in oleaginous yeast&#x000a0;<italic>Rhodosporidium kratochvilovae</italic>&#x000a0;HIMPA1</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2015</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2015.02.062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25769691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Carnecka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Halienova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Certik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dvorakova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Haronikova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of several waste substrates for carotenoid-rich yeast biomass production</article-title><source>J Environ Manag</source><year>2011</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2011.06.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petrik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Haronikova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kostovova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Breierova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of biomass, carotenoid and other lipid metabolites by several red yeasts strains cultivated on waste glycerol from biofuel production&#x02014;a comparative screening study</article-title><source>Ann Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>1537</fpage><lpage>1551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13213-013-0617-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jawed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Concomitant production of lipids and carotenoids in <italic>Rhodosporidium toruloides</italic> under osmotic stress using response surface methodology</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>1992</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>248</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Magbanua</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Arick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridges</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome sequence of the oleaginous yeast&#x000a0;<italic>Rhodotorula glutinis</italic>&#x000a0;ATCC 204091</article-title><source>Genome Announc</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e00046-14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/genomeA.00046-14</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24526636?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24526636</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Somashekar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inverse relationship between carotenoid and lipid formation in Rhodotorula gracilis according to the C/N ratio of the growth medium</article-title><source>World J Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2000</year><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1008917612616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Libkind</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Arts</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Broock</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid composition of cold-adapted carotenogenic basidiomycetous yeasts</article-title><source>Rev Argent Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19213239?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19213239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeyaseelan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of biodiesel produced by acidic transesterification of lipid extracted from oleaginous yeast <italic>Rhodosporidium toruloides</italic></article-title><source>3 Biotech</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>434</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13205-018-1467-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilles</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebers</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colorimetric method for determination of sugars and related substances</article-title><source>Anal Chem</source><year>1956</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>350</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ac60111a017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of dinitrosalicylic acid reagent for determination of reducing sugar</article-title><source>Anal Chem</source><year>1959</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ac60147a030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nip</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancement of lipid productivity of Rhodosporidium toruloides in distillery wastewater by increasing cell density</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2013</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2013.07.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23948267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sriwongchai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pokethitiyook</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pugkaew</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruatrachue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimization of lipid production in the oleaginous bacterium Rhodococcus erythropolis growing on glycerol as the sole carbon source</article-title><source>Afr J Biotechnol</source><year>2012</year><volume>11</volume><issue>79</issue><fpage>14440</fpage><lpage>14447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5897/AJB12.2376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bligh</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rapid method of total lipid extraction and purification</article-title><source>Can J Biochem Physiol</source><year>1959</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>911</fpage><lpage>917</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/y59-099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13671378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of phenol on &#x00392;-carotene content in total carotenoids production in cultivation of <italic>Rhodotorula glutinis</italic></article-title><source>Korean J Chem Eng</source><year>2004</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02705506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on lipid production by Rhodotorula glutinis fermentation using monosodium glutamate wastewater as culture medium</article-title><source>Bioresour Technol</source><year>2008</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>5923</fpage><lpage>5927</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2007.04.046</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18420404?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18420404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rup&#x0010d;i&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Blagovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mari&#x00107;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell lipids of the <italic>Candida lipolytica</italic> yeast grown on methanol</article-title><source>J Chromatogr A</source><year>1996</year><volume>755</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9673(96)00579-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8997745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rakicka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dulermo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fickers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicaud</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipid production by the oleaginous yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> using industrial by-products under different culture conditions</article-title><source>Biotechnol Biofuels</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>104</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13068-015-0286-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26213570?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26213570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Takashima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Endoh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikukawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Cryptococcus terricola</italic>&#x000a0;is promising oleaginous yeast for biodiesel production from starch through consolidated bioprocessing</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>4776</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep04776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24758986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sargeant</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mardell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saad-Allah</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiffin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Santomauro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuck</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of lipid from depolymerised lignocellulose using the biocontrol yeast, <italic>Rhodotorula minuta</italic>: the fatty acid profile remains stable irrespective of environmental conditions</article-title><source>Eur J Lipid Sci Technol</source><year>2015</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ejlt.201500143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buzzini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An optimization study of carotenoid production by&#x000a0;<italic>Rhodotorula glutinis</italic> DBVPG 3853 from substrates containing concentrated rectified grape must as the sole carbohydrate source</article-title><source>J Ind Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2000</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.jim.2900765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rempp</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Simone</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>William</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilization of Soluble Starch by Oleaginous Red Yeast&#x000a0;<italic>Rhodotorula glutinis</italic></article-title><source>J Sustain Bioenergy Syst</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4236/jsbs.2013.31007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bommareddy</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabra</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Maheshwari</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic network analysis and experimental study of lipid production in <italic>Rhodosporidium toruloides</italic> grown on single and mixed substrates</article-title><source>Microb Cell Fact</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12934-015-0217-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25888986?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25888986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiebe</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Koivuranta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Penttil&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruohonen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipid production in batch and fed-batch cultures of <italic>Rhodosporidium toruloides</italic> from 5 and 6 carbon carbohydrates</article-title><source>BMC Biotechnol</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>26</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6750-12-26</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22646156?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22646156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muniraj</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial lipid production from potato processing wastewater using oleaginous filamentous fungi <italic>Aspergillus oryzae</italic></article-title><source>Water Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>3477</fpage><lpage>3483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2013.03.046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23597680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madonna</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranjitha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayalakshmi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilization of agro waste as carbon sources for high lipid production by <italic>Aspergillus Niger</italic></article-title><source>Int. Chem. Tech.</source><year>2016</year><volume>03</volume><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>639</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>ZK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous utilization of glucose and xylose for lipid production by&#x000a0;<italic>Trichosporon cutaneum</italic></article-title><source>Biotechnol Biofuels</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1754-6834-4-25</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21864398?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21864398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taskin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortucu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aydogan</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Arslan</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipid production from sugar beet molasses under non-aseptic culture conditions using the oleaginous yeast <italic>Rhodotorula glutinis</italic> TR29</article-title><source>Renew Energy</source><year>2016</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.renene.2016.06.060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taskin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saghafian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aydogan</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Arslan</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial lipid production by cold-adapted oleaginous yeast&#x000a0;<italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic>&#x000a0;B9 in non-sterile whey medium</article-title><source>Biofuel Bioprod Bioref</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bbb.1560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santamauro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiffin</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuck</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-cost production by oleaginous yeast cultured in non-sterile conditions using waste resources</article-title><source>Biotechnol Biofuel</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1754-6834-7-34</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>ZK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipid production from corn stover by the oleaginous yeast&#x000a0;<italic>Cryptococcus curvatus</italic></article-title><source>Biotechnol Biofuels</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>158</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13068-13014-10158-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25352914?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25352914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabine</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ralf</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Georg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Udo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alfred</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><source>&#x0201c;Fatty Acids&#x0201d; in Ullmann&#x02019;s. Encyclopedia of Industrial Chemistry</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Weinheim</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley-VCH</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akoh</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><source>Food lipids: chemistry, nutrition and biotechnology</source><year>2008</year><edition>3</edition><publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benoit</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Abplanalp</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Migrenne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefevre</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruciani-Guglielmacci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Palmitic acid mediates hypothalamic insulin resistance by altering PKC-&#x003b8; subcellular localization in rodents</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2009</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>2577</fpage><lpage>2587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI36714</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19726875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Luis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purified palmitoleic acid for the reduction of high-sensitivity C-reactive protein and serum lipids: a double-blinded, randomized, placebo controlled study</article-title><source>J Clin Lipid</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>617</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name><name><surname>Haigh</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Manders</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxide for valve-regulated lead&#x02013;acid batteries</article-title><source>Journal of power sources.</source><year>1998</year><volume>18;73(1)</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-7753(98)00020-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Julien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoeffel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Flick</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oleic acid lung injury in sheep</article-title><source>J Appl Physiol</source><year>1986</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jappl.1986.60.2.433</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Carrasco F. Ingredientes Cosm&#x000e9;ticos, Diccionario de Ingredientes. 4th ed. p. 428, 2009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diezel</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Skanks</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heise</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant oils: topical application and anti-inflammatory effects (croton oil test)</article-title><source>Dermatologische Monatsschrift</source><year>1993</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>173</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peyrat-Maillard</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuvelier</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Berset</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity of phenolic compounds in 2,2&#x02032;-azobis (2-amidinopropane) dihydrochloride (AAPH)-induced oxidation: synergistic and antagonistic effects</article-title><source>J Am Oil Chem Soc</source><year>2003</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>1007</fpage><lpage>1012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11746-003-0812-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Duncan A. The technique of leaded glass, ISBN 0-486-42607-6, p. 77, 2003.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Thomas A. Fats and fatty oils. Ullmann&#x02019;s encyclopedia of industrial chemistry, 2000.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>