<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>OVA sensitization and challenge in an 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> model led to an increase in histamine and OVA-specific IgE titers in sera, increased IL-4 release in nasal lavage and infiltration of inflammatory cells in the epithelium and sub epithelium of the nasal mucosa (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Bahekar et al., 2008</xref>). Oral administration of 
 <italic>Ostericum grosseserratum</italic> (Maxim.) Kitag. methanol extract at doses of 0.5 and 1.0 mg/ml significantly inhibited OVA-specific IgE production in the OVA-sensitized mice (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) as compared to control mice given OVA alone (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al., 2011</xref>). Based on this study, 
 <italic>O. grosseserratum</italic> has shown a strong activity in AR-induced model. Another plant that has exhibited histamine suppression effect was 
 <italic>Artemisia abrotanum</italic> L., prepared as a nasal spray preparation. The use of nasal spray preparation has shown a rapid onset of action and relief of nasal symptoms such as congestion, rhinorrhea, and sneezing within a few minutes of application (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Remberg et al., 2004</xref>). The overall tolerability in all of the twelve patients dealing with a mild to moderate locally appearing stinging sensation was good although it was reported to happen immediately after applying the nasal spray preparation (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Remberg et al., 2004</xref>). The histamine action was proved by the reduction of early AR symptoms deemed to be strongly related to the early phase cycle of AR pathophysiology. The flavonoids were likely the important compounds in this species that inhibited the effects mediated by histamine (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Bergendorff and Sterner, 1995</xref>). This study might have shown a good response on its effect in alleviating the symptoms after its application. However, there was no evidence of histamine inhibition that was clearly explained or well conducted in this particular study.
</p>
