<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In a time of accelerating “green” knowledge in agriculture, more and more scientific papers are devoted to biocidal opportunities for EOS against plant pests. According to plant-plant relations, EOS are studied mainly for their inhibitory effects on seed germination (weed management) [
 <xref rid="B135-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>,
 <xref rid="B136-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>]. However, studies on their foliar application around the world, as well as anti-weed mulch activity, are also performed. Synowiec [
 <xref rid="B137-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>] correlated highly phytotoxity-essential oils (from 
 <italic>Carum carvi</italic> L., 
 <italic>Mentha ×piperita</italic>, 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> plants) with their chemical content, which consists of compounds from the group of oxygen derivatives of monoterpenes (64–95% of content), in particular monoterpenic alcohols, esters and ketones. The laboratory tests showed promising activities of these EOS against weeds, mainly the small-seed ones, i.e., 
 <italic>Amaranthus retroflexus</italic> L. and 
 <italic>Centaurea cyanus</italic> L. The common maize weed, 
 <italic>Echinochloa crus-galli</italic> (L.) P. Beauv. is also susceptible to caraway oil (being an oil-in-water emulsion at a dose of 2.5%) after foliar application [
 <xref rid="B138-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. Laosinwattana et al. [
 <xref rid="B139-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>] found that 
 <italic>Tagetes erecta</italic> L. essential oil completely inhibited seed germination 
 <italic>of that weed</italic> too, due to inhibiting α-amylase activity (at 2 mL·L
 <sup>−1</sup> emulsifiable concentrate of this essential oil), and, with concentrations of 10–80 mL·L
 <sup>−1</sup> post-emergence of foliar application, caused wilted and desiccated leaves of this weed. Interesting examples of Australian flora endemics pretending to be novel essential oil-yielding crops with their anti-pest capabilities are cited by Sadgrove and Jones [
 <xref rid="B140-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>].
</p>
