<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Simple Summary</title>
  <p>The Federal National Organic Program (NOP) guidelines for pest management can be viewed as constraining to certified organic growers giving them a “limited toolbox” relative to non-organic crop production systems. Certifying agencies work with individual growers in setting boundaries for acceptable pest management tactics and enforce compliance for annual certification, but the knowledge required to have a successful insect pest management program can be overwhelming for growers. Traditional grower educational programs are challenged in providing the needed one-on-one training and follow up to ensure growers successfully master current and adopt newly developed pest management tactics. Gaps in the guidelines, such as monitoring, if included, could aid in grower adoption of practices that inform better decision-making and efficacy. This review promotes the idea that these issues can be overcome by utilizing experiential learning programs to educate growers and paid professionals, such as a pest control advisor. If the pest control advisor is a valued partner in the educational and extension process, they can be an effective advocate, educator, mentor, and assessor reaching more growers than education/extension programs alone, thus, achieving the NOP’s philosophical goal of a production system managed to respond to site-specific conditions.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Abstract</title>
  <p>Insect pest management in certified organic production systems presents considerable challenges for growers. The Federal National Organic Program (NOP) guidelines list acceptable tactics, but their effective use requires a considerable knowledgebase in entomology. The range of tactics allowed by the NOP are viewed as limiting by many growers and there are important elements missing from the list such as pest monitoring and identification. Educational programs must consider utilizing instructional methods and additional means of outreach that introduce new pest management tactics that are individualized, regionally appropriate and emphasize grower adoption and collaboration with local professionals. This review describes the challenges and knowledge burden associated with the listed NOP pest management guidelines, provides an educational model that includes an additional level of professional support for enhanced adoption of novel pest management tactics, or refinement of current practices, with a special emphasis on the importance of insect pest population monitoring.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
