<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With the recent approval of PB larvae as a food ingredient by the Ministry of Food and Drug Safety of Korea, the commercial consumption of the PB larvae has increased [
 <xref rid="B12-ijms-22-00679" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. However, little is known about the chemical composition of PB larvae and the pharmacological effects of its components. In previous chemical studies, some compounds have been reported to be present in the ethanol extract of PB larvae, including 5-hydroxyindolin-2-one and (1
 <italic>R</italic>,3
 <italic>S</italic>)-1-methyl-1,2,3,4-tetrahydro-
 <italic>β</italic>-carboline-3-carboxylic acid, which exhibit anti-thrombotic activity [
 <xref rid="B12-ijms-22-00679" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-ijms-22-00679" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-ijms-22-00679" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. As there is no research on the chemical constituents of the water extract of PB larvae, we have, to the best of our knowledge, isolated, identified, and reported for the first time six major components of the PBWE (
 <bold>1</bold>−
 <bold>6</bold>) including four purine derivatives (e.g., adenine, hypoxanthine, adenosine, and inosine), a pyrimidine derivative (uridine), and a benzoic acid. Purines and pyrimidines are heterocyclic aromatic compounds composed of carbon and nitrogen. Their derivatives play crucial roles in organisms as nucleoside/nucleotide precursors that constitute building blocks of DNA and RNA. They are known to have several biological activities such as antimicrobial, antitumor, antiviral, and antiproliferative effects [
 <xref rid="B43-ijms-22-00679" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Of these, uridine (
 <bold>3</bold>) and inosine (
 <bold>5</bold>), two of the major compounds in the PBWE, have been reported to exhibit anticonvulsant and antiepileptic effects by modulating the function of gamma-aminobutyric acid receptors [
 <xref rid="B44-ijms-22-00679" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-ijms-22-00679" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Sodium benzoate, produced by the neutralization of benzoic acid (
 <bold>6</bold>), has also been shown to alleviate seizures in nonketotic hyperglycinemia [
 <xref rid="B46-ijms-22-00679" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. In addition, uridine (
 <bold>3</bold>), inosine (
 <bold>5</bold>), and benzoic acid (
 <bold>6</bold>) have also been reported to have antioxidant activities [
 <xref rid="B47-ijms-22-00679" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-ijms-22-00679" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-ijms-22-00679" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Similarly, in the present study, we confirmed the antioxidant activity of inosine (
 <bold>3</bold>) and benzoic acid (
 <bold>6</bold>) especially among the isolated compounds. Based on the previous and present studies, we further support the idea that the components of the PBWE might present protective effects against TMT-induced seizures and neurodegeneration. However, further studies on the correlation between these components and their neuroprotective effects as well as their underlying mechanism are needed.
</p>
