<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">
   <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L. from Tunisia, popularly known as rosemary, is of a considerable importance for its medicinal uses and aromatic value. The aim of this study was to examine the chemical composition of 
   <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> essential oil (ROEO) and to evaluate its antibiofilm activity on biofilm-forming bacterium and its anticancer activity on cancer cell lines.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2">The chemical composition of 
   <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> essential oil (ROEO) was analyzed by GC-MS and its antibacterial activity was evaluated by micro-dilution method. The antibofilm activity of ROEO was evaluated using the crystal violet test and the cytotoxicity activity was determined by the MTT assay.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par3">In this research, thirty-six compounds were identified in ROEO using GC-MS analyses. The main components were 1,8-cineole (23.56%), camphene (12.78%), camphor (12.55%) and β-pinene (12.3%). The antibacterial activity of ROEO was evaluated by micro-dilution method. The oil exhibited inhibition and bactericidal effect against two strains: 
   <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 9144 and 
   <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> S61. It was found that the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) obtained for 
   <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
   <italic>S. epidermidis</italic> ranged from 1.25 to 2.5 and from 0.312 to 0.625 μl ml
   <sup>−1</sup>, respectively and the minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) were in the order of 5 and 2.5 μl ml
   <sup>−1</sup>, respectively. Furthermore, this oil showed a 
   <italic>S. epidermidis</italic> biofilm inhibition more than 57% at a concentration of 25 μl ml
   <sup>−1</sup>. The eradication of 67% of the established biofilm was observed at a concentration of 50 μl ml
   <sup>−1</sup> of ROEO, whereas the dose of 25 μl ml
   <sup>−1</sup> removed only 38% of preformed biofilm. ROEO strongly inhibited the proliferation of Hela and MCF-7 cells with IC
   <sub>50</sub> values of 0.011 and 0.253 μl ml
   <sup>−1</sup>, respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par4">Our results demonstrate that ROEO could have a potential role in the treatment of diseases related to infection by microorganisms or proliferation of cancer cells.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
