<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Significantly, an inverse relationship between digestibility and interindividual variability has consistently been observed. In others words, when a protein is highly digestible, all individuals display a great capacity to digest the protein, but when the protein is less digestible some of them have a great capacity to digest it while others have a low capacity. This is illustrated in Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, which depicts the individual data of amino acid bioavailability in rats for 
 <sup>15</sup>N goat whey, sunflower isolate and spirulina. These three data sets are directly comparable because they are methodologically uniform. It appears that for spirulina, which has a digestibility 12–15% lower than that of the other two proteins, the data dispersion is dramatically expanded. We observed the same in humans, for instance, concerning zein digestibility, which was the lowest we observed among our intestinal tube studies [
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8
  <sup>▪</sup>
 </xref>]. The SD was 13% (for a mean of 60%), with the lowest individual value being 39% and the highest 82%. This is consistent with a previous observation of rapeseed isolate that contains resistant albumin (napin), with a mean value of 84 ± 8.8% and extreme values of 65 and 90%, as reviewed recently by Walther 
 <italic>et al.</italic>[
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In this review, the authors proposed variations in protease activity and polymorphism of amino acid transporters as putative causes of interindividual variability, but data are lacking to support these hypotheses. The microbiome may also play a role as indirectly suggested by an intervention study in humans where the administration of vancomycin increased faecal energy losses [
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. However, the rationale for a putative role of the large intestine microbiota in amino acid bioavailability is unclear since there is no significant absorption of amino acids in the colon.
</p>
