<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Airborne fungal propagules have been a major focus of epidemiological studies in traditional plant pathology for native plants and crops. For example, most airborne spores come from fungi growing on living or dead plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and their abundance is influenced by multiple abiotic factors, such as temperature [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], humidity [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], rainfall [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], and wind speed [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Scherm &amp; van Bruggen (1995) reported that lesions on source plants infected with an isolate of 
 <italic>Bremia lactucae</italic> sporulated at night and released spores beginning at sunrise [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Plant canopy air, with complex microclimates, thus acts as an important space for dynamic host-pathogen interactions [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Pathogens in the canopy air can infect plants under optimal microclimate conditions and in turn, release their spores into the air to complete their life cycle; meanwhile, the host can change the canopy microclimate to affect pathogen spread and disease development [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Some studies for the monoculture crop also have shown that numbers of conidia collected decreased with increasing height within and above the crop canopy [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Similarly, for the monoculture invasive plant, its canopy air would harbor diverse fungal spores released from leaf spots, which in turn, may infect host itself as well as neighboring species. It should be expected that: (1) The closer to the plant host, the higher diversity and more complicated co-occurring connections of fungi; (2) there are the sharing between fungi in the canopy air of invasive plants and host-associated pathogenic fungi. Currently, there is a total lack of the knowledge of the airborne phytopathogenic fungi surrounding the invasive plants.
</p>
