<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The apical and axillary shoots were collected from the same 
 <italic>M. cordata</italic> individual cultivated in the greenhouse. After washing under water and trimming the leaves, the juvenile shoots as explant donors were disinfected with 70% ethanol for 2 min, followed by 0.2% sodium hypochlorite for 15 min. Once disinfected, the explants were rinsed 5 times in distilled water and dried using sterile filter paper. The explants were then trimmed into 1 cm segments and cultured on MS media [
 <xref rid="B64-plants-09-01665" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] (pH = 5.8) with sucrose (3% 
 <italic>w</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>), agar (0.75% 
 <italic>w</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>), and 1 mg·L
 <sup>−1</sup> benzyl adenine (BA) for sprouting. The antibiotic-containing MS media were either supplemented with 1.0 g·L
 <sup>−1</sup> CTX or 0.6 g·L
 <sup>−1</sup> TIM. The number of initial explants for culture establishment in each set was listed in 
 <xref rid="plants-09-01665-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The cultures were incubated under 16 h light/8 h dark photoperiod at 26 °C for around 6 weeks, after which the sprouting plantlets were selected. The plantlets were subcultured on PGR-free 1/2 MS media containing a corresponding antibiotic reduced to half of the starting concentration for rooting. After 8 weeks of cultivation, the axillary shoots of rooted plantlets from CTX-treated and TIM-treated groups were cut off and subcultured on the 1/2 MS media with 0.3 g·L
 <sup>−1</sup> TIM for 8 weeks of large-scale propagation. After that, the axillary shoots of strong plantlets were cut off again and subcultured in the same way for second-round propagation. Large-scale propagation of the aseptic plantlets would be continued until the number of aseptic leaves met the requirement of DNA extraction. Every time the plantlets were transferring to fresh media, the green leaves were harvested and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen. The leaves were stored at −80 °C freezer until DNA extraction. Around 100 plantlets were successively subcultured for long-term maintenance after sampling. Through the whole period of in vitro culture, the plantlets were discarded once the culture was colonized by bacteria or fungi. A total of 6 of the robust plantlets were acclimatized to the incubation environment for 2 days, and then they were transferred in the soil and sand (1:1) mixture under the same incubation conditions.
</p>
