<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to the widespread use of oregano for aromatic purposes, the medicinal properties of its EO are also important [
 <xref rid="B138-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. The antimicrobial activities of 
 <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> were extensively studied and well documented. Compared to the antibacterial activities, data on their antifungal activities are limited. Different types and varieties of oregano have been the subject of scientific studies. For example, 
 <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> EO was observed to have an inhibitory effect on 
 <italic>Fusarium verticillioides</italic> [
 <xref rid="B113-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. In addition to the commonly known oregano (
 <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic>), 
 <italic>Poliomintha longiflora</italic> (Mexican oregano) was also reported to be a good antifungal agent, which was attributed to its thymol, carvacrol, and 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene contents [
 <xref rid="B114-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. Velluti et al. [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] outlined that oregano EO is one of the most effective EO against fumonisin B
 <sub>1</sub>. Similarly, the mechanism of antiaflatoxigenic action was also directly correlated with the aflatoxin biosynthesis pathway [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Another effective EO against fumonisin B
 <sub>1</sub> and fumonisin B
 <sub>2</sub> was 
 <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> (turmeric) EO, and that inhibitory effect was correlated with the inhibition of fungal growth [
 <xref rid="B97-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. However, there are also studies in which fungal inhibition and toxin production were independent of each other. For instance, there was no correlation between the antiaflatoxigenic and antifungal activity of 
 <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L. EO [
 <xref rid="B65-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Fumonisin B
 <sub>1</sub> inactivation was not achieved at a sufficient level by peppermint EO [
 <xref rid="B131-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]. However, ZEA reduction by mint EO was reported to be in the range of 19.87% to 30.79% [
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Unlike the toxin inhibition activity of mint EO at moderate levels, it exhibits a wide spectrum of antifungal activity. The antifungal activity of 
 <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> L. EO, which was mainly dominated by menthol [
 <xref rid="B109-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>,
 <xref rid="B139-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>], was generally attributed to their major components. However, the contribution of minor components to these biological activities should also be considered. When the susceptibility of 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> species to 
 <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> EO was compared, the lowest MIC values were observed in 
 <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> and 
 <italic>Aspergillus clavatus</italic> within 
 <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic>, 
 <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>, 
 <italic>Aspergillus oryzae</italic>, and 
 <italic>Aspergillus clavatus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B108-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. Different susceptibilities of molds to EOs may be linked to the production of enzymes by the fungus that catalyzes oxidation and thus causes inactivation of the oil [
 <xref rid="B140-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>]. Peppermint (
 <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> L.) EO also had significant levels of antifungal activities against 
 <italic>A. alternaria</italic> and 
 <italic>Penicillium</italic> spp. with an MIC value of 1.50 μg/mL [
 <xref rid="B56-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>].
</p>
