<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It has been reported that the transcript abundance of TPS is positively correlated with the accumulation of terpene (Nieuwenhuizen et al., 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Bustos-Segura et al., 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>; Yu et al., 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). In this study, the two identified SgSTPSs revealed higher expression in H10 compared to L4, suggesting the potential roles of the two genes in determining the terpene amount in 
 <italic class="italic">S. glabra</italic>. In 
 <italic class="italic">S. glabra</italic> oleoresin, the major components of sesquiterpenes are α-copaene (32.26%) and β-caryophyllene (16.33%) (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">1</xref>, Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Here, by a combination of transcriptome and experimental analyses, we identified that SgSTPS1 was mainly responsible for β-caryophyllene sesquiterpene production, while SgSTPS2 was accountable for α-copaene production. Nevertheless, SgSTPS2 is a versatile enzyme that can also produce other sesquiterpenes including ylangene, germacrene, elemene, cadinene, muurolene, and amorphene, all of which were present in 
 <italic class="italic">S. glabra</italic> oleoresin except elemene, which may be a byproduct due to rearrangements of different sesquiterpenes (Agger et al., 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). Therefore, the two SgSTPS enzymatic products matched well with the chemical composition of oleoresin in the 
 <italic class="italic">S. glabra</italic> stem. Furthermore, these results indicated that different sesquiterpene synthases have diversified functionally to produce specific kinds of products. Among the characterized plant β-caryophyllene synthases, SgSTPS1 exhibited the highest amino acid identity (46%) to GhTPS from 
 <italic class="italic">Gossypium hirsutum</italic> (AFQ23183) (Huang et al., 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>), 40% identity to AtTPS from 
 <italic class="italic">A. thaliana</italic> (AAO85539) (Huang et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>), and the lowest identity (35%) to ZmTPS from 
 <italic class="italic">Zea mays</italic> (ABY79207) (Köllner et al., 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>), three of which catalyzed the formation of β-caryophyllene as the major product from FPP. In particular, the product amorphadiene that SgSTPS2 synthesizes from FPP is a precursor of the antimalarial drug artemisinin, which can be used for the production of artemisinic acid. The identified SgSTPS2 shared 42% similarity with amorpha-4,11-diene synthase from 
 <italic class="italic">A. annua</italic> (ABM88787). Furthermore, β-caryophyllene and α-copaene in plant species were found to serve in defense against pathogens or herbivores, and the identified sesquiterpene synthases were involved in the defense response (Huang et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). Therefore, we hypothesize that SgSTPSs may be responsible for the defense response in 
 <italic class="italic">S. glabra</italic>. Further research is needed to investigate the ecological functions of sesquiterpenes and corresponding SgSTPSs.
</p>
