<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">However, dietary fat is not a homogenous macronutrient, since the structure and function of different fatty acids can vary greatly depending on chain length (6 to 24 carbons) and absence or presence of carbon-carbon double bonds [
 <xref rid="B295-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">295</xref>]. Saturated fatty acids (SFAs) have no double bond, monounsaturated fatty acids (MUFAs) contain a single double bond, while polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs) have two or more double bonds. Furthermore, the double bond can be in a 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic> or 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic> configuration depending on whether the hydrogens attached to the carbons in the double bond are on the same side or opposing sides of the molecule, respectively. Trans fats are produced commercially by the partial hydrogenation of unsaturated fats or naturally via biohydrogenation in ruminant animals [
 <xref rid="B303-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">303</xref>]. Studies have shown that different fatty acids exert differential effects on the gut microbiota. For example, a high fat diet rich in saturated fat in the form of palm oil (PUFA: SFA ratio = 0.4) induced higher body weight gain and liver triglyceride content in mice compared with diets rich in polyunsaturated fats (olive oil, PUFA: SFA ratio = 1.1, or safflower oil, PUFA: SFA ratio = 7.8) [
 <xref rid="B304-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">304</xref>]. Interestingly, the overflow of dietary fat to the distal intestine was greater on the palm oil diet compared with the others. Indeed, the high-saturated fat, palm oil diet reduced microbial diversity and increased the Firmicutes: Bacteroidetes ratio which the authors suggest may be due to antimicrobial effects of the saturated fats. A diet high in SFAs derived from milk fat, but not PUFAs derived from safflower oil, promoted expansion of the low abundance sulfite-reducing 
 <italic class="italic">Bil. wadsworthia</italic> in mice which was associated with a pro-inflammatory immune response and increased incidence of colitis in genetically susceptible mice, but not wild type mice [
 <xref rid="B187-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">187</xref>]. Due to their hydrophobicity, milk fats promote taurine-conjugation of hepatic bile acids which increases the availability of organic sulfur for use by bacteria, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Bil. wadsworthia</italic>. In the same study, both the SFA- and PUFA-rich diets reduced microbiota richness compared with a low-fat diet. In this case, the low-fat diet promoted Firmicutes while the two high fat diets resulted in higher abundances of Bacteroidetes and low levels of Firmicutes. Interestingly, mice fed high fat diets derived from milk fat, or lard (both high in SFAs), or safflower oil (high in PUFAs) revealed that all three high fat diets induced dramatic and specific changes to gut microbiota composition which were associated with different host adipose tissue inflammatory/lipogenic profiles [
 <xref rid="B305-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">305</xref>]. Safflower oil is rich in omega-6 PUFAs which are associated with a pro-inflammatory status [
 <xref rid="B306-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">306</xref>]. Indeed, the safflower oil-rich diet resulted in a greater localized, tissue-specific pro-inflammatory effect compared to the milk fat and lard-based diets [
 <xref rid="B305-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">305</xref>]. However, in both milk fat- and safflower oil-fed mice, Tenericutes were decreased, a phylum which has been shown to be reduced under inflammatory conditions [
 <xref rid="B307-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">307</xref>,
 <xref rid="B308-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">308</xref>] and Proteobacteria was increased, of which 
 <italic class="italic">Bil. wadsworthia</italic> is a member. Consumption of extra virgin olive oil (rich in MUFAs and phenolic compounds), refined olive oil (rich in MUFAs but low in phenolic compounds), or butter (rich in SFAs and cholesterol) by mice resulted in differential effects on gut microbiota composition [
 <xref rid="B309-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">309</xref>]. The butter-induced changes resembled those reported for obese individuals while the changes induced by extra virgin olive oil differed most from butter. In a more recent study, the same group investigated the effect of extra virgin olive oil on mouse gut microbiota compared to butter using more in-depth analysis [
 <xref rid="B310-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">310</xref>]. Highest levels of systolic blood pressure were recorded for mice fed butter which correlated positively with 
 <italic class="italic">Desulfovibrio</italic> sequences in faeces, which were significantly higher in mice fed butter compared to olive oil. Interestingly, 
 <italic class="italic">Desulfovibrionaceae</italic> are sulfate reducers, which the authors suggest could be sustained by butter sulfate sources, whereas the authors suggest that the lower levels in the olive oil diet may be due to the higher presence of polyphenols. Olive oil had the lowest plasmatic insulin levels which correlated inversely with 
 <italic class="italic">Desulfovibrio</italic>, and the lowest plasmatic leptin values which correlated inversely with 
 <italic class="italic">Sutterellaceae, Marispirillum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Mucilaginibacter dageonensis</italic> which were significantly higher for olive oil. Mice fed the standard diet had the lowest total cholesterol levels which correlated positively with 
 <italic class="italic">Fusicatenibacter</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Prevotella</italic>, the latter of which has been associated with an improvement in glucose metabolism [
 <xref rid="B311-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">311</xref>] but its relationship with cholesterol is less clear [
 <xref rid="B310-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">310</xref>]. Interestingly, butter was also associated with an increase in 
 <italic class="italic">Alistipes indictintus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Pontibacter lucknowensis</italic> which correlated positively with total cholesterol, ghrelin, insulin, body weight and HDL/LDL. Lam et al. [
 <xref rid="B312-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">312</xref>] reported a rapid increase of hydrogen sulfide-producing bacteria in mice consuming a diet high in saturated fat which was not observed for mice fed high fat diets containing omega-6 or omega-3 PUFAs. In fact, these bacteria remained relatively stable in mice fed omega-6 PUFAs and were mostly reduced in mice fed omega-3 PUFAs. Likewise, Shen et al. [
 <xref rid="B313-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">313</xref>] reported that mice fed a diet high in saturated fat had a greater abundance of three types of sulfidogenic bacteria (
 <italic class="italic">Bil. wadsworthia, Desulfobulbus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Desulfovibrio</italic>) primarily in the colonic mucosa compared to mice fed a low-fat diet after chronic feeding (20 weeks). In addition, high fat feeding increased intestinal inflammation by week 20, which was not observed at week 6. However, by week 6, high fat feeding had impaired the localization of the tight junction protein zonula occludens 1 at the apical area of the ileal epithelium which was also observed at week 20. The authors concluded that chronic high saturated fat feeding may contribute to chronic intestinal inflammation owing to microbial metabolic pathways. In humans at risk of metabolic syndrome, a high saturated fat diet, a high MUFA diet combined with high glycemic index (GI) carbohydrates, or a high MUFA diet combined with low GI carbohydrates caused a decrease in total bacteria and the high saturated fat diet increased faecal SCFA concentrations which the authors suggest could be due to lower absorption in the gut [
 <xref rid="B314-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">314</xref>]. 
</p>
