<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Insects</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individuals of 
   <span class="italic">T. molitor</span> were obtained from the Laboratory of Biological Control of the Institute of Applied Biotechnology to Agriculture (BIOAGRO, Universidade Federal de Viçosa) in Viçosa, Minas Gerais State, Brasil. Adults of 
   <span class="italic">T. molitor</span> were kept in plastic trays (60 cm long × 40 cm wide × 12 cm) and maintained at 25 ± 1 °C, 70 ± 10% RH and 12:12 h L:D photoperiod. These adults were fed 
   <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> with wheat bran (12% protein, 2% lipids, 75% carbohydrates and 11% mineral/sugar), pieces of sugarcane, 
   <span class="italic">Saccharum officinarum</span> (L.) (Poaceae) and chayote 
   <span class="italic">Sechium edule</span> (Jacq.) Swartz (Cucurbitaceae). Sheets of paper were placed on the substrate to prevent the stress from insects and facilitate oviposition. Healthy larvae, pupae and adults of 
   <span class="italic">T. molitor</span> without amputations, apparent malformations or nutritional deficiencies were used in the bioassays.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Garlic essential oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil of garlic, 
   <span class="italic">A. sativum</span> used in this study was commercial sample from Ferquima Industry &amp; Commerce Ltda. (Vargem Grande Paulista, São Paulo State, Brasil), produced in industrial scale by hydrodistillation drag of water vapor
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b55" href="#b55">55</a>. Ferquima Industry &amp; Commerce Ltda is accredited by the Ministry of Agriculture, Livestock and Supply of Brazil and by international organizations according to ISO Guide
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b56" href="#b56">56</a>. This provides Brazilian producers with licenses, and ensures unrestricted access to major world organic product markets.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mortality test</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Garlic essential oil efficacy was determined by calculating the lethal concentrations (LC
   <sub>50</sub>, and LC
   <sub>90</sub>) values under laboratory conditions and conducted in triplicate. Six concentrations of garlic essential oil besides the control (acetone) were adjusted in 1 mL of stock solution (essential oil and acetone): 1, 2, 4, 8, 16 and 32% (w/v). Aliquots were taken from the stock solution and mixed with acetone in 5 mL glass vials. Different concentrations of the garlic essential oil were applied in 1 uL solution on the thorax of larva, pupa and adult of 
   <span class="italic">T. molitor</span>, using a micropipette. For each developmental stage, fifty insects were used per concentration and were placed individually in Petri dishes (Ø 90 mm × 15 mm) with an absorbent paper, fed with chayote and sugarcane 
   <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> (larvae and adults) and maintained in the dark. The number of dead insects was in each cage was counted after essential oil exposure for 48 h after application. Rates were calculated with a correction for natural mortality
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b57" href="#b57">57</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identification of garlic essential oil compounds</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantitative analyses of the garlic essential oil formulation were performed using a gas chromatograph (GC-17A series instrument, Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan) equipped with a flame ionization detector (FID). The following chromatographic conditions were used: a fused silica capillary column (30 m × 0.22 mm) with a DB-5 bonded phase (0.25 μm film thickness); carrier gas N
   <sub>2</sub> at a flow rate of 1.8 mL min
   <span class="sup">−1</span>; injector temperature 220 °C; detector temperature 240 °C; column temperature programmed to begin at 40 °C (remaining isothermal for 2 min) and then to increase at 3 °C min
   <span class="sup">−1</span> to 240 °C (remaining isothermal at 240 °C for 15 min); injection volume 1.0 μL (1%w/v in CH
   <sub>2</sub>Cl
   <sub>2</sub>); split ratio 1:10; column pressure 115 kPa.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The compounds were identified using a gas chromatograph coupled with a mass detector GC/MS (GCMS-QP 5050 A; Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan). The injector and detector temperatures were 220 °C and 300 °C, respectively. The initial column temperature was 40 °C for 3 min, with a programmed temperature increase of 3 °C/min to 300 °C where it was maintained for 25 min. The split mode ratio was 1:10. One microliter of the garlic essential oil containing 1% (w/v in dichloromethane) was injected, helium was used as the carrier gas with a flow rate constant of 1.8 mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span> on the Rtx
   <span class="sup">®</span>-5MS capillary column (30 m, 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm; Bellefonte, USA) using the Crossbond
   <span class="sup">®</span> stationary phase (35% diphenyl-65% dimethyl polysiloxane). Mass spectrometer was programmed to detect masses in the range of 29–450 Da with 70 eV ionization energy. Compounds were identified by comparisons of the mass spectra with those available in the NIST08, NIST11 library and Wiley Spectroteca Data Base (7
   <span class="sup">th</span> edition), and by the Retention indices.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Toxicity of commercial compounds of garlic essential oil in 
   <span class="italic">T. molitor</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diallyl sulfide and diallyl disulfide identified as toxic compounds in garlic essential oil, were obtained commercially. Diallyl sulfide (purity 97.0%) and diallyl disulfide (purity 70%) were purchased from Across Organics (New Jersey, USA). Six different concentrations of the commercial compounds besides the control (acetone) were adjusted in 1 mL of stock solution (treatment and acetone) used to calculate the lethal LC
   <sub>50</sub> and LC
   <sub>90</sub> concentrations: 5, 10, 20, 40, 80, and 160 mg mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. For each treatment, aliquots were taken from the stock solution and mixed with acetone in 5 mL glass vials. Different concentrations of the each treatment were applied in 1 uL solution on the body of larva, pupa and adult of 
   <span class="italic">T. molitor</span>. Individuals were placed in Petri dishes with wheat bran and sugarcane. A total of 50 larvae, 50 pupae, and 50 adults were used for each concentration and mortality was evaluated for 48 h after application to compared with toxicity garlic essential oil, followed by rate corrections according to the Abbott’ formule
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b57" href="#b57">57</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lethal time of toxic compounds and garlic essential oil in 
   <span class="italic">T. molitor</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Toxicity of garlic essential oil and commercially obtained diallyl sulfide and diallyl disulfide at the calculated LC
   <sub>50</sub> and LC
   <sub>90</sub> concentrations were compared. Distilled water was used as a control. The LC
   <sub>50</sub> and LC
   <sub>90</sub> of each compound were applied in larvae, pupae, and adults of 
   <span class="italic">T. molitor</span>. Insects were individualized in Petri dishes with wheat bran and sugarcane. A total of 240 larvae, 240 pupae, and 240 adults were used for each treatment, with a total of four replicates. Mortality was recorded every 6 h for 48 h, and estimated lethal time values for 50% mortality (LT
   <sub>50</sub>) were compared.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Repellency test</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Four Petri dishes (12 × 1.5 cm) were used as an arena, connected to a central board with plastic tubes (diameter 2 cm) at an angle of 45°. The other dishes were distributed around them in equidistant distances and two plates were put together symmetrically opposed. Two hundred and forty individuals (120 larvae and 120 adults) of 
   <span class="italic">T. molitor</span> were released in the central board and the control group received sugarcane and chayote. A total of 5 uL of the estimated LC
   <sub>90</sub> lethal concentration of garlic essential oil and toxic compounds were applied on absorbent filter paper (2 × 2 cm) placed in two opposite plates used as treatment and two opposite ones with 5 uL of distilled water for absorbent filter paper represented the control. Four replicates per treatment and control were evaluated by the number of individuals per plate after 24 hours calculating the repellency index (IR): RI = 
   <span class="italic">2</span> 
   <span class="italic">G</span>/(
   <span class="italic">L</span> + 
   <span class="italic">P</span>), where G is the percentage of insects in the treatment and P is the percentage of insects in control. Treatments were classified as neutral if the index was equal to one (1); repellent, higher than one (1), and; attractive lower than one (1).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respiration rate</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respirometry bioassays were conducted 3 h after the beetles were exposed or not exposed to garlic essential oil and their constituents, as previously detailed. The doses used corresponded to the recorded LC
   <sub>50</sub> of each toxic compound and control consisted of insect treated with distilled water. Carbon dioxide (CO
   <sub>2</sub>) (μL of CO
   <sub>2</sub> h
   <span class="sup">−1</span>/insect) production was measured with a respirometer of the type CO
   <sub>2</sub> Analyzer TR
   <sub>3</sub>C (Sable System International, Las Vegas, USA), using methodology adapted from previous studies
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" href="#b49">49</a>. Respirometers (25 mL) were used, each one holding 3 adults of 
   <span class="italic">T. molitor</span> with mixed sex and connected to a closed system. CO
   <sub>2</sub> production was measured after the insects were acclimated in the chambers for a period of 12 h at a temperature of 27 ± 2 °C. To quantify the CO
   <sub>2</sub> produced inside each chamber, compressed oxygen gas (99.99% pure) was passed through the chamber at a flow of 100 mL min
   <span class="sup">−1</span> for a period of 2 min. This airflow forces all produced CO
   <sub>2</sub> molecules to pass through an infrared reader coupled to the system, which makes a continuous measurement of the CO
   <sub>2</sub> produced by the insects and held inside each chamber. After CO
   <sub>2</sub> measurement, the insects were removed from the chambers and then weighed using an analytical balance (Sartorius BP 210D, Göttingen, Germany). Respiration rate values were not normalized by body mass because this method masks the individual effects of the variables
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b58" href="#b58">58</a>. Six replicates were used for each treatment.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistics</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lethal concentration (LC
   <sub>50</sub> and LC
   <sub>90</sub>) and their confidence limits for garlic essential oil and toxic compounds were determined by logistic regression in dose-response assays based on the concentration Probit-mortality
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b59" href="#b59">59</a> using XLSTAT-PRO (v.7.5) program for Windows
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b60" href="#b60">60</a>. Student’s t test was used for pairwise comparisons regarding lethal time effects in 
   <span class="italic">T. molitor</span> using SAS User software (v. 9.0) for Windows
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b61" href="#b61">61</a>. Repellency data larvae and adults of 
   <span class="italic">T. molitor</span> were transformed using formula 
   <div id="d32e1171" class="inline-formula">
    <span id="d32e1172" xlink:href="srep46406-m1.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div> and analyzed by one-way ANOVA. A Tukey’s Honestly Significant test (HSD) was also used for comparisons of the means in the bioassays at 5% significance level using SAS User software. Respiration rate were subjected to two-way analyses of variance (time × insecticide treatment) and Tukey’s HSD test (P &lt; 0.05) when appropriate (PROC GLM). As the time interval was assessed in different insect samples, they are not pseudoreplicates in time and therefore subject to regular two-way analyses of variance instead of repeated measures analyses of variance using SAS User software.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
