<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Medicinal plants with antimalarial activity considered to be active should reduce parasitemia at least by 30%, which supports the finding of parasite inhibition in the current study.
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> In 4-day suppressive test, the extract of 
 <italic>A. polystachyus</italic> showed significant parasite suppression: 27.64% (p&lt;0.001), 33.67% (p&lt;0.0001), and 49.25 (p&lt;0.0001) at doses of 100, 200 and 400mg/kg/day, respectively. In the curative test, significant (p&lt;0.0001) parasitemia suppression: 33.76%, 39.24%, and 53.59% at 100mg/kg, 200mg/kg and 400mg/kg, respectively. In prophylactic test, 25%, p&lt;0.001; 32.84%, p&lt;0.0001; and 50%, p&lt;0.0001, at 100mg/kg, 200mg/kg, and 400mg/kg doses of the extract, respectively, as compared to the negative control. Secondary metabolites such as terpenoids, flavonoids, saponins, alkaloids, tannins, glycosides, phenols, and anthraquinone have been implicated for their antiprotozoal and antimalarial activities in many pharmacological studies.
 <xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41–44</xref> The current phytochemical screening result revealed that the methanolic extract of 
 <italic>A. polystachyus</italic> leaves possesses phytochemical constituents namely saponins, tannins, terpenoids, phenols, flavonoids, glycosides, steroids, and anthraquinones. Thus, the significant parasitemia suppression detected in the current study could be due to the presence of these phytoconstituents. The present finding is in line with previous similar studies.
 <xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45–47</xref> Furthermore, it has been conveyed that antioxidant activity can inhibit heme polymerization (the unpolymerized heme is very toxic for the 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> species).
 <xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> In the current study, the leaves extract of 
 <italic>A. polystachyus</italic> showed potent antioxidant activity. Hence, the observed antimalarial activity of the extract might be due to the antioxidant activity of 
 <italic>A. polystachyus</italic> leaves extract. In the present study, the percentage suppression was higher in the curative test than in prophylactic test. This may be because of a rapid hepatic metabolism or clearance of the bioactive compounds accountable for ant plasmodial activities because of the administration of the extract initially for 4 days before the inoculation of the parasite. Compared to the standard drug, the extract of 
 <italic>A. polystachyus</italic> showed less antimalarial activity. This could be because of low selectivity, unpurified/crude nature, poor bioavailability, slow absorption, other pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics parameters of the extract of 
 <italic>A. polystachyus</italic>.
</p>
