<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Pluronic F-127 (F-127, Poloxamer 407, PF-127) is a non-ionic surfactant composed of polyoxyethylene-polyoxypropylene copolymers and is a thermoreversible gel [
 <xref rid="B80-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f007" class="xref">Figure 7</xref>A). It forms monomolecular micelles at low concentrations (10
 <sup class="sup">−4</sup>–10
 <sup class="sup">−5</sup>%) and multimolecular aggregates consisting of a hydrophobic central core with hydrophilic polyoxyethylene chains facing the external medium at high concentrations [
 <xref rid="B80-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>] and 20–35% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) F-127 forms a thermoreversible gel, which exists as a liquid at 4 °C and as a solid at room temperature [
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. F-127 was dissolved gently since it easily forms foam, and the pelleted/clumped F-127 polymer was gentle stirred 1–2 times a day in the a cool room until forming a gelling liquid [
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. The process of obtaining a clear viscous liquid of F-127 usually took three days. Crystal samples such as thermolysin, glucose isomerase, lysozyme, and bacteriorhodopsin in LCP crystals were mechanically mixed with cold 35% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) F-127 stock solution using a syringe setup (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f004" class="xref">Figure 4</xref>). Crystal samples embedded in F-127 were derived using an HVE injector with a 100-μm ID capillary. The crystal structures of glucose isomerase, thermolysin, and bacteriorhodopsin-LCP derived from F-127 were determined at resolutions of 2.0 Å, 2.0 Å, and 2.3 Å, respectively, using less than 0.5 mg of protein for each dataset [
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. The diffuse scattering of F-127 was observed at around 2.8–5 Å, with a scattering intensity level similar to that of grease, and wider and stronger than that of other hydrogels [
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. In terms of chemical compatibility, the injection stability of F-127 tolerates only NaCl and low-molecular weight PEG/PPG. The injection medium of F-127 was stable at a final concentration of 0.25 M ammonium sulfate, 2 M NaCl, 25% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) polypropylene glycol 400, 23% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) polyethylene glycol 400, and 7% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) polyethylene glycol 2000 [
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. F-127 preparation was time consuming compared to other delivery media.
</p>
