<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Contemporary work on developing surveillance strategies for invasive species has focused on determining optimal levels of survey effort, sometimes in combination with eradication or other control activities [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Other work has explored optimal survey selection in spatial settings [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] and together in both spatial and temporal domains [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C55" ref-type="bibr">55–57</xref>]. In these studies, the survey manager's main objective may have been to minimize the total expected costs associated with an invader (i.e. the economic value of anticipated host losses plus control and mitigation costs) [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], the expected number of new infestations [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] or the time to first detection of an incipient population [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Instead, the objective may have been to minimize the number of invaded or potentially invaded host plants [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] or maximize the number of uninvaded hosts [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Alternately, the goal may have been to maximize the expected number of detections [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] or minimize the number of survey sites with false negatives (i.e. where surveys failed to find an established population) [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Routinely, the survey planning problems in these studies had budgetary constraints on surveillance and other elements of the management response. Further research examples have adapted portfolio theory — an approach from the finance field that maximizes the return on funds distributed among a diverse set of investment assets [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] — to address a somewhat different optimization objective: to allocate surveillance resources for the earliest possible detection, while also hedging against a highly unlikely but catastrophic outcome, i.e. failure to detect a high-impact invader before it becomes well-established and widespread [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-513C59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].
</p>
