<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coronaviruses are enveloped, positive-sense, single-stranded RNA viruses with large viral genomes. The publication of SARS-CoV-2 genome in January 2020 led to its taxonomic classification into the family 
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic> and genus 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Bats are natural reservoirs of coronaviruses [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The SARS-CoV-2 genome shares 96% nucleotide identity with bat coronavirus RaTG13, which suggests a probable zoonotic transfer to humans via an intermediate animal host [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Prior to SARS-CoV-2 epidemic, there are two precedence of zoonotic transfer of 
 <italic>betacoronaviruses</italic> to humans, namely the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and the middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV), which had also led to outbreaks of severe respiratory disease [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In 2002–2003, SARS-CoV emerged in China and led to 8098 infections and 774 deaths across the world [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Interestingly, the SARS-CoV-2 genome shares ~80% nucleotide identity with SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In 2012, MERS-CoV emerged in Saudi Arabia and led to 2521 infections and 866 deaths that were largely limited to Middle Eastern countries [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Unlike SARS and MERS, the geographic spread of COVID-19 and the ensuing mortality is significantly higher. To date, there are no approved antiviral drugs or vaccines against 
 <italic>betacoronavirus</italic> infections including COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Hence, the current measures to contain COVID-19 include social distancing, aggressive testing, patient isolation, contact tracing and travel restrictions. In present circumstances, an immediate goal of biomedical research is to develop antivirals or anti-COVID therapeutics for SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
</p>
