<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>2′,4′-dihydroxy-6′-methoxy-3′,5′-dimethylchalcone, or DMC (
 <bold>38</bold>), the major compound of 
 <italic>S. nervosum</italic> flower buds, has also become a compound of interest for its potent antidiabetic and antiobesity activities via multiple mechanisms of action. DMC exhibited strong noncompetitive inhibitory effects on pancreatic 
 <italic>α</italic>-amylase (IC
 <sub>50</sub> 43 
 <italic>μ</italic>M) but literally ineffective against intestinal 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase (∼20% inhibition at 200 
 <italic>μ</italic>M). In addition, DMC was also capable of inhibiting glucose transporter 2 (GLUT 2; 54% inhibition at 150 
 <italic>μ</italic>M), which subsequently blocked the reabsorption of glucose in the kidney and therefore indirectly lowered the glycemic level. The authors also tested the protective effects of DMC against H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>-induced insulin reduced secretion in MIN6 cells. As a result, the cellular viability of MIN6 cells with DMC pretreatment showed no significant changes when compared with control [
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. In another study, Hu et al. [
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] studied the insulinotropic effects of DMC on glucotoxicity in RIN-5F 
 <italic>β</italic>-cells. As a result, DMC cotreatment could stimulate insulin secretion from 
 <italic>β</italic>-cells dose-dependently without affecting the physiological insulin secretion. The underlying mechanism was determined through the upregulation of the GLP-1 receptor and the activation of PDX-1, PRE-INS, and GLUT2-GCK signaling pathway. Besides that, DMC also reduced NO production and MCP-1 expression, which indicated the protective effects of DMC against cellular damage and oxidative stress in pancreatic islets [
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. DMC (10 
 <italic>μ</italic>M) also increased glucose uptake in differentiated adipocytes (3T3-L1). Noticeably, at high concentration (10 and 20 
 <italic>μ</italic>M), DMC remarkably suppressed the lipid accumulation in 3T3-L1 cells while at low concentration (2.5 
 <italic>μ</italic>M), DMC stimulated the lipid storage in the same experimental cell line. The authors hypothesized that DMC upregulated the expression PPAR-
 <italic>γ</italic> at a high dose and suppressed at low-dose [
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Luo and Lu [
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] also studied the protective effects of DMC on H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>-induced cell damage in MIN6 (mouse insulinoma) cells. Pretreatment of DMC (12.5 and 25 
 <italic>μ</italic>M) was shown to improve mitochondrial functions by reducing nucleus fragmentation, decreasing the intracellular level of ROS, and preventing the loss of mitochondrial potential [
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].
</p>
