<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par55" class="p">A large number of different TPS and the fact that some TPS produce multiple products are the chief reasons for the variety in terpenes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>]. Linalool synthase isolated from 
 <italic class="italic">C. osmophloeum</italic> were able to generate the S-(+)-linalool from geranyl diphosphate (GPP) and (E)-nerolidol from farnesyl diphosphate (FPP) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>]. In addition, the products of TPS can be further modified by oxidation, peroxidation, methylation and acylation etc., such as by cytochrome P450 dependent monooxygenases and short-chain dehydrogenases/reductases (SDRs) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>]. In the GO enrichment analysis, 124 up-regulated DEGs between the borneol-type and linalool-type profiles were enriched, among these 10 and 17 DEGs were significantly enriched in the terpene synthase activity and oxidoreductase activity term of the DAG, respectively, indicating that terpene synthase activity and oxidoreductase activity were likely to be the terms leading to the differential accumulation of terpenoids in borneol and linalool chemotypes of 
 <italic class="italic">C. camphora</italic>. In addition, 37 unigenes related to pathways of prenyl diphosphat, monoterpenoid, sesquiterpenoid and diterpenoid biosynthesis were identified in the current study. Mono-, sesqui−/tri-, and di-TPS have been synthesized by the activities of geranyl diphosphate synthase (GPS), farnesyl diphosphate synthase (FPPS) and geranylgeranyl diphosphate synthase (GGPPS) from GPP, FPP and geranylgeranyl diphosphate (GGPP), respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>]. Four GPS, three FPPS and six GGPS have been identified in both borneol and linalool chemotypes but with no difference in expression levels. In addition, a total of seven TPSs including three mono-TPSs, two di-TPSs and sesqui−/tri-TPSs were differentially expressed in the different chemotypes. This suggests that the different expression level of TPS genes in the two chemotypes may be the reason for their accumulation of different terpenoids.
</p>
