<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0380">Atractylenolide I (ATL-I) has an antitumor effect on bladder cancer in vitro and in vivo. The results showed that ATL-I increased the level of p21 and decreased cyclin B1, cyclin-dependent kinase 1 (CDK1), and cell division cycle 25C (Cdc25c) levels and inhibiting bladder cancer cell proliferation. Further study indicated that ATL-I induced G2/M cell cycle arrest. Besides, ATL-I could promote apoptosis by inhibiting PI3K/Akt/mTOR. Animal experiments proved that ATL-I has an inhibitory effect on tumor growth and no obvious toxicity (
 <xref rid="bib141" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2014</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al. (2016)</xref> found that ATL-I could inhibit CML and AML leukemia cell proliferation and growth and induce apoptosis. 
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Fu et al. (2018)</xref> found that ATL-I could inhibit melanoma cell migration by suppressing phospho-janus kinase 2 (p-JAK2), phospho-signal transducer, and activator of transcription 3 (p-STAT3), matrix metalloproteinase-2 (MMP-2) and MMP-9. The clinical study of ATL-I in the treatment of gastric cancer cachexia has been carried out. Atractylenolide II (ATL-II) treatment showed a dose-dependent manner inhibitory effect on p-STAT3, myeloid cell leukemia 1 (Mcl-1) and B-cell lymphoma-extra large (Bcl-xL) in B16 and A375 cells. Among them, STAT3 could promote melanoma. A further animal study showed that ATL-II suppressed STAT3 activation and tumor growth (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Fu et al., 2014</xref>). ATL-II could significantly inhibit cell proliferation, motility and induce apoptosis in a dose and time-dependent manner by modulating Akt/ERK signaling pathway (
 <xref rid="bib103" ref-type="bibr">Tian and Yu, 2017</xref>). Atractylenolide III (ATL-III) possessed antitumor activity on human mast cells stimulated by thymic stromal lymphopoietin (TSLP), human mast cell line-1 (HMC-1) by inhibiting mast cell proliferation, phosphorylated signal transducer, IL-13, and activator of transcription (
 <xref rid="bib130" ref-type="bibr">Yoou et al., 2017</xref>). It was indicated that hinesol inhibited human leukemia HL-60 cells by reducing nuclear fragmentation and DNA fragmentation, activating c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) (
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Masuda et al., 2015</xref>). β-eudesmol had anti-tumor activity in multiple tumor cell models (CCA, Hep-G2, A549, HT29, HeLa, SGC-7901, and BEL-7402, U266 cells) mainly through regulating apoptosis (
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Kotawong et al., 2018</xref>) and growth factors (
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2008</xref>) in a time-and dose-dependent manner (
 <xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr">Srijiwangsa et al., 2018</xref>). Moreover, β-eudesmol (2.5–5 mg/kg) treatment significantly inhibited tumor growth in H22 and S180 mice (
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2008</xref>). Phosphorylation of ERK1/2 and angiogenesis in mice subcutaneous matrix gel plug and mice adjuvant granuloma were inhibited by high concentration of β-eudesmol, suggesting that β-eudesmol can be used as a candidate drug to treat angiogenic diseases (
 <xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr">Tsuneki et al., 2005</xref>). Pongsakorn et al. (2018) investigated cytotoxic interactions between the three major constituents (β-eudesmol, hinesol and atractylodin) of 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic>. Cytotoxic activities against the human CCA cells CL-6 of the dual and triple combinations with different concentration ratios were evaluated by MTT assay. The mixture of the three compounds produced synergistic interaction with combination index values of 0.519 ± 0.10 and 0.65 ± 0.17 (mean ± SD) at the concentrations that inhibit cell growth at the 50% and 90% leveled, respectively.
</p>
