<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Composition of propolis and its plant precursors are not fully known, which is especially apparent in the area of comparative investigation of bee glue and its plant sources. Available data for comparative analysis between bee glue and 
 <italic class="italic">Populus</italic> from temperate climate include research performed using different techniques such as TLC (thin layer chromatography), TLC-MS (thin layer chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry) [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>], GC-MS (gas chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry) after sililation [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>], and UHPLC-MS/MS (ultra-high performance liquid chromatography coupled with tandem mass spectrometry) [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. However, comparative analysis of volatile components remains under-researched [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Moreover, not all aspects of the composition of 
 <italic class="italic">Populus</italic> genus essential oils (EOs) have been studied. According to Jerković and Mastelić [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>], 
 <italic class="italic">P. nigra</italic> L. leaf buds contain mainly oxygenated sesquiterpenoids. As far as we know, the composition of volatile compounds of aspen and other 
 <italic class="italic">Populus</italic> buds is still not properly researched. Available information on 
 <italic class="italic">P. tremula</italic> L. essential oils includes only emission of terpenoids from leaves [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>] and bark [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>].
</p>
