<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0065">Many factors cause immune disorders, including environmental stress and changes in the immune regulators that can lead to many human diseases. Bioactive components can play a vital role in immunity through intrusive with immune cell regulation and pro-inflammatory cytokine synthesis. Recently, a huge number of 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies demonstrated the immunomodulatory part of polyphenols. These studies have shown that people with a specific diet, especially polyphenols-rich ones, are at reduced risk for a variety of diseases (
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Rasouli 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">Yahfoufi 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018
 </xref>). Additionally, polyphenols are developing therapeutic tools for controlling and protecting the body from several autoimmune disorders due to their immunomodulatory effects (
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Khalifa 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Khan 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019
 </xref>). The immune modulation effect of polyphenols is related to the impact on immune cells, pro-inflammatory gene expression, and modulate cytokines production (
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">Yahfoufi 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018
 </xref>). In addition to the antioxidant properties such as reactive oxygen species scavenging of polyphenols and their donations to the rule of inflammatory signing. Polyphenols also showed high-effects in increasing the natural killers in fruits (
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">Yahfoufi 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018
 </xref>). For their effect on the balance between pro and anti-inflammatory cytokine secretion, polyphenols compounds such as catechins and quercetin have been added to various foods. Additionally, numerous flavonoids can inhibit the expression of various pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Comalada 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006
 </xref>). Furthermore, the epigallocatechin gallate and curcumin can induce epigenetic changes in cells. Thus, polyphenols compounds can be efficiently used to control the immune response.
</p>
