<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Simple Summary</title>
  <p class="p">Recently, there has been increasing interest in the use of insects as an alternative sustainable source of protein and fat in animal feed to improve animal production and maintain ecological sustainability. Palm oil is commonly used in broiler chicken nutrition; however, due to the environmental footprint, consumers have formed negative opinions regarding its applications. Therefore, alternatives to palm oil are urgently needed. The present study was conducted to evaluate the effects of 
   <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic> oil as a total replacement for palm oil and poultry fat in broiler chicken diets on chicken performance, nutrient digestibility, pancreatic enzyme activity, various blood parameters and lipid fatty acid compositions of liver and breast muscle tissues. Based on the obtained results, 
   <italic class="italic">T. molitor</italic> oil did not show any adverse impacts on performance and improved the fatty acid profiles of liver and breast muscle tissues. In conclusion, 
   <italic class="italic">T. molitor</italic> oil may be a sustainable alternative to palm oil in broiler chicken nutrition.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Abstract</title>
  <p class="p">This study was conducted to evaluate the effects of 
   <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic> (TM) oil as a total replacement for palm oil and poultry fat in broiler chicken diets on growth performance, nutrient digestibility, pancreatic enzyme activity, selected blood parameters and the lipid fatty acid compositions of liver and breast muscle tissues. A total of 72 seven-day-old female Ross 308 broiler chickens were used. The birds were randomly distributed into three groups with 12 replicates each, using two birds per replicate for 30 days in metabolic cages. The basal diet was supplemented with 5% palm oil, poultry fat or TM oil. There was no effect (
   <italic class="italic">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) caused by the dietary oil replacement on the birds’ performance and apparent nutrient digestibility. Liver size (
   <italic class="italic">p</italic> = 0.033), the concentration of hepatic triglycerides (
   <italic class="italic">p</italic> = 0.049) and total cholesterol (
   <italic class="italic">p</italic> = 0.048) were reduced by TM oil supplementation. Furthermore, TM oil supplementation increased n-3 and n-6 fatty acids (
   <italic class="italic">p</italic> = 0.006; 
   <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, respectively) in breast muscle tissue. In conclusion, the use of TM oil in broiler chickens’ diets did not show any adverse effects on performance, nutrient digestibility and blood biochemical parameters. Moreover, TM oil supplementation improved the fatty acid profiles of liver and breast muscle tissues.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
