<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">As a traditional medicinal herb and valuable natural spice in China, 
  <italic class="italic">Aquilaria sinensis</italic> (Lour.) Gilg has many significant pharmacological effects. Agarwood is the resinous heartwood acquired from wounded 
  <italic class="italic">A. sinensis</italic> trees, and is widely used in pharmaceuticals owing to its excellent medicinal value. In this study, the chemical composition of volatile components and alcohol extracts from different organs of 
  <italic class="italic">A. sinensis</italic> and agarwoods grown in different regions were investigated using GC-MS. The results showed that Vietnam agarwood had the highest moisture content, which was attributed to the local climate, while the fruit and bark of 
  <italic class="italic">A. sinensis</italic> had higher moisture contents than the other organs. The volatile components of 
  <italic class="italic">A. sinensis</italic> organs included 3-ethyl-5-(2-ethylbutyl)-octadecane, oleic acid 3-(octadecyloxy) propyl ester, and docosanoic acid 1,2,3-propanetriyl ester, while the alcohol extracts of 
  <italic class="italic">A. sinensis</italic> organs contained benzoic acid ethyl ester, hexadecanoic acid ethyl ester, oleic acid, and 
  <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hexadecanoic acid. Furthermore, the main active ingredients in agarwood from different habitats were sesquiterpenoids, aromatic species, and chromone compounds. The role of chromone compound 2-phenylethyl-benzopyran as an elicitor and the mechanism of agarwood formation were also investigated. Antioxidant tests showed that essential oils from agarwood and 
  <italic class="italic">A. sinensis</italic> had antioxidant capacities by comparison with butylated hydroxytoluene and vitamin E. An antibacterial activity test showed that the inhibition effect of the essential oil was better against Gram-positive bacteria than against Gram-negative bacteria.
 </p>
</abstract>
