<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plant species not called out in this particular analysis should not be assumed to have no impact. This paper focuses on summarizing only a single component of risk: the impact of nonindigenous aquatic plants to native aquatic plants via competition. Other potentially important components of impact (which are also summarized in GLANSIS products) were excluded from this analysis in an effort to focus on competition alone. For one example, a recent ranking of the highest impact invasive species in the Great Lakes [
 <xref rid="B174-plants-10-00406" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>] included only one aquatic nonindigenous plant, 
 <italic>Myriophyllum spicatum</italic> (Eurasian watermilfoil), which is not among the top impact species when we consider only competition. Eurasian watermilfoil had only a moderate impact score for competition, meaning that its successful establishment has resulted in some noticeable stress or decline in native populations due to its ability to grow in dense stands, allowing it to successfully outcompete other native species for nutrients, sunlight, and space and eventually resulting in a reduction in biodiversity of native plants [
 <xref rid="B128-plants-10-00406" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B175-plants-10-00406" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>]. However, in the broader analysis of diverse and indirect impacts, Eurasian watermilfoil scored higher due to many other documented types of impact (not related to competition [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-10-00406" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-plants-10-00406" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-plants-10-00406" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B152-plants-10-00406" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>,
 <xref rid="B175-plants-10-00406" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>,
 <xref rid="B176-plants-10-00406" ref-type="bibr">176</xref>,
 <xref rid="B177-plants-10-00406" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>,
 <xref rid="B178-plants-10-00406" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>,
 <xref rid="B179-plants-10-00406" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>]).
</p>
