<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is an ethnomedicinal plant originally belonging to the Polygonaceae family. The root, stem, leaf, and metabolites of 
 <italic>Rumex nervosus</italic> (RN) contain essential phytochemical ingredients such as carbohydrates, vitamins, sterols, glycosides, triterpenes, saponins, tannins, and flavonoids, which possess a variety of pharmacological and biological activities and potential applications in medicine [
 <xref rid="B30-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Recent studies show that RN leaf extracts have anti-coccidial and anti-inflammatory activities [
 <xref rid="B34-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. RN has anti-oxidant properties and improves the performance of broiler chickens [
 <xref rid="B35-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. It is used as traditional therapy for several diseases and functions such as an anti-bacterial [
 <xref rid="B29-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and anti-parasitic [
 <xref rid="B36-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] agent. There are pharmacognostical study of RN growing in Yemen reported by [
 <xref rid="B30-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] reported that the ethanolic extract of RN considered as non-toxic up to a dose of 7.1 g/kg b.wt, and have cytotoxic activity with varying degrees of potency against human cancer cell line. In addition, [
 <xref rid="B30-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] reviewed that RN have many traditionally uses and treated multifaceted cases in human such as many inflammatory diseases, wounds, diarrhea, typhus, rabies and skin disorders. As a result, RN as the natural medicinal herb has fewer adverse effects and a lower estimated cost, as opposed to synthetically produced chemical compounds [
 <xref rid="B35-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Diarrhea and vomiting are side effects of RN in children. Thus, contraindication administered for children and the Red teff porridge considered antidotes [
 <xref rid="B37-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The shrubs belonging to the Polygonaceae family may comprise a large amount of oxalic acid. Consuming a large amount of oxalic acid contributes to hyperoxaluria that leads to the calcium oxalate stone formation, and hypocalcemia due to reaction them with plasma calcium and precipitate insoluble calcium oxalate in liver, kidneys, heart, blood vessels, and lungs [
 <xref rid="B38-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. However, to date, there is limited or no evidence of RN leaf powder supplementation of diets used for coccidiosis therapy. Therefore, this study was conducted to evaluate the efficacy of different concentrations of RN leaf powder supplementation used as a dietary anti-coccidial and growth promoter agent in broiler chickens experimentally challenged with 
 <italic>E. tenella</italic>.
</p>
