<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although the antibacterial properties of SAEO have been the target of much attention, the applications of SAEO are limited due to its high volatility, strong smell, and unstable physical and chemical properties [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-23-01126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-23-01126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-23-01126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. The encapsulation techniques based on cyclodextrins (CDs) can solve this problem [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-23-01126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. CDs and its derivatives can encapsulate essential oils and volatile compounds to stabilize their properties, extend their storage capabilities, mask the irritating smell [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-23-01126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>], afford slow release properties [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-23-01126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-23-01126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>] and enhance the antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-23-01126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-23-01126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. In addition, the main components of SAEO are volatile, and encapsulation can regulate their release, because the control of the release rate is the key of prolonging the antimicrobial characteristics of SAEO. Encapsulation of essential oil and its active constituents has been reported by several researchers. In 2014, the inclusion complexes of thymol and thyme essential oil with β-CD were successfully prepared to validate that the complexes exhibited good antibacterial activity [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-23-01126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Furthermore, several researchers successfully encapsulated black pepper essential oil in hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrin (HPCD). The results exhibited a slight decrease in the oxidation resistance of the inclusion complexes, while the antibacterial activity of black pepper oil improved by four-fold against both 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> due to a likely synergistic effect between the wall material and essential oil [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-23-01126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>].
</p>
