<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <bold class="bold">Overview:</bold> Spirulina (classified as 
 <italic class="italic">Arthrospira</italic> sp.) is a microscopic blue-green filamentous alga that floats freely on water media; it grows in fresh water, as well as in alkaline salt water. It is a cyanobacterium belonging to the class, Cyanophyceae, and the order, Oscillatoriales. It is an organism capable of storing different bioactive molecules, among which are the following: (1) Proteins (60%–65% dry weight) with essential amino acids; (2) polyunsaturated fatty acids, such as linoleic acid; (3) vitamins (B12 and E); (4) polysaccharides; (5) minerals (Na, K, Ca, Fe, Mn, and Se); and (6) pigments (chlorophyll, C-phycocyanin, allophycocyanin, β-carotene, lutein, and zeaxanthin). Generally, the content of the compounds varies from species-to-species proportions, but the phytochemicals that are always present in their biomass are C-phycocyanin (with a content of 12.6% in dry spirulina) and high percentages of dietary zeaxanthin [
 <xref rid="B18-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Spirulina is the sole blue-green alga that is commercially cultivated for food use; there are various species, but those of the greatest commercial importance are 
 <italic class="italic">A. maxima</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. platensis</italic> (also known as 
 <italic class="italic">Spirulina maxima</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Spirulina platensis</italic>). Until 1989, these species had belonged to the Spirulina genus and their scientific names, respectively, were 
 <italic class="italic">S. maxima</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. platensis</italic>, both known as “spirulina” [
 <xref rid="B18-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>].
</p>
