<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plant essential oils and extracts have been used for controlling fire ants as mound treatment products. For example, Orange Guard Fire Ant Control (Orange Guard, Inc., Marina, CA, USA) is a product based on citrus peel extract (5.8% d-limonene) and Essentria
 <sup>®</sup> G Granular Insecticide (former EcoEXEMPT™ G Granular Insecticide) is based on eugenol (2.9%) and thyme oil (0.6%) (Central Garden &amp; Pet Company, Schaumburg, IL, USA). Essentria
 <sup>®</sup> IC-3 Insecticide Concentrate is based on rosemary oil (10%), geraniol (5%) and peppermint oil (2%) (Central Garden &amp; Pet Company, Schaumburg, IL, USA). Three experimental citrus oil-based formulations were tested in the field [
 <xref rid="B47-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Since d-limonene and eugenol are the dominant component in citrus peel extracts and clove oil respectively, d-limonene or eugenol are commonly listed as the active ingredients on product labels. However, many minor compounds were identified in these oils/extracts. For example, 54 components were identified in the steam distilled essential oils and 44 in the extracts of orange peels of 12 cultivars of 
 <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> from central-eastern Sicily, Italy [
 <xref rid="B48-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Although in all the cultivars, the main component is d-limonene (73.9–97%), numerous monoterpenes and terpenoids were also found. A total of 23 constituents were identified in clove essential oil [
 <xref rid="B49-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In thyme essential oil, 56 components were identified, and the oxygenated monoterpenes were the most abundant (57.14%) and dominated by geraniol (22.33%), geranyl acetate (19.38%), and linalool (5.49%). Thymol is a dominate phenolic compound in thyme oil (14%) [
 <xref rid="B50-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Thirty-four compounds were tentatively identified in rosemary essential oil, with α-pinene, bornyl acetate, camphene and 1,8-cineole being the major components [
 <xref rid="B51-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Components of peppermint leaf essential oil include menthol, menthone, menthofuran, 1,8-cineole, and menthyl acetate [
 <xref rid="B52-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Minor compounds can play a significant role. For example, LC
 <sub>50</sub> and LC
 <sub>90</sub> values of clove essential oil against mosquitoes, 
 <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic> were significantly lower than those of eugenol, indicating other minor compounds contribute significantly to the toxicity of clove oil [
 <xref rid="B53-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Although essential oil-based control products are available in the market, the data on toxicity of these essential oils and their individual component to fire ant are generally lacking; especially, the contribution of minor compounds to the toxicity of essential oils has not been well studied. Essential oils are produced in over 17,500 plant species [
 <xref rid="B54-insects-11-00758" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. They may become an important source of naturally occurring compounds/mixture that have a potential to be used in fire ant management.
</p>
