<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0150">Palm fat can also be made into a CBS that is comparable to CB. The palm mid-fraction, refined bleached deodorized palm kernel oil and palm stearin are all formed through fractionation of palm fat and have different melting profiles (
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Biswas et al., 2016</xref>). Mixing these different palm fat variations can form a CBS with better properties than using just one of them, especially if they are combined to give compatible physicochemical behaviour to CB (
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Biswas et al., 2016</xref>). It was found that a 14.9/59.6/25.5 (%w/w) blend of palm mid-fraction, refined bleached deodorized palm kernel oil and palm stearin gave crystals with similar morphology to CB (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Biswas et al., 2017a</xref>). However, other properties such as polymorphism and melting profile were different to CB, which could hinder the acceptability of this CBS in alternative chocolate products. A further study used enzymatic interesterification to control the melting range of this palm based CBS and tested the new material by blending it with CB (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Biswas et al., 2017b</xref>). A 5 ​g CBS/100 ​g blend gave no significant difference in the sensory testing to regular chocolate (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Biswas et al., 2017b</xref>). A higher amount of substitution would be preferable for companies who are looking to lower the amount of CB in their products. However, the sensory analysis was significantly different for a 20 ​g CBS/100 ​g blend and it would likely not be accepted by consumers (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Biswas et al., 2017b</xref>). Both the 5 and 20 ​g CBS/100 ​g blend mixtures were found to have similar melting profiles and polymorphism to CB, showing that interesterification and then blending of this CBS with CB can change the crystallization behaviour of the final triglyceride mixture (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Biswas et al., 2018</xref>). These mixtures presented oleic and palmitic fatty acids, especially as 2-oleoyl-1,3-dipalmitoylglycerol (POP), in similar amounts to CB, which could explain their compatibility with CB (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Biswas et al., 2018</xref>). Palm fat has high saturated fatty acids, which could be reduced by using hybrid palm fat stearin, which has less saturated fatty acids than normal palm stearin (
 <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">Ruedas et al., 2020</xref>), this was not tested in a chocolate formulation so it may not provide the solid fat content needed due to its higher unsaturated fatty acid content.
</p>
