<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Considering the Feedlot group as a control, the GPX1 and SOD2 enzyme activities were higher in Lucerne-fed animals and these differences in activity were reflected in the mRNA abundance. We have also seen in the present study that Lucerne feeding substantially increased muscle ALA whereas Feedlot diet substantially increased muscle LA concentrations. One thing we could draw from this is that diet-induced changes in muscle PUFA can alter expression and activity of SOD and(or) GPX antioxidant enzymes in the muscle tissue system. However, whether the altered activity of enzymes initiated the expression of genes or the altered expression of genes initiated the activity of enzymes was not clear, which requires further investigation. Animals and humans have a multi-dynamic defence mechanism regulated by enzymatic and non-enzymatic antioxidants in order to protect their tissues, organelles and individuals from oxidative stress and metabolic disorders [
 <xref rid="B22-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. The latter components have the capability to chelate, scavenge or decompose the damage causing hydroperoxides, transition metals, and other free radical forming substances or prooxidants and therefore protecting the body from adverse changes. Among them, glutathione peroxidase (GPX) and superoxide dismutase (SOD) have been reported as the major enzymatic antioxidants involved in defence mechanism in tissue systems of living organisms [
 <xref rid="B21-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-nutrients-11-00723" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>].
</p>
