<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Studies on disease-mediated competition between invasive and native plant species indicate that infection of invasive plants can contribute to either native plant persistence or recovery [
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. However, in our experiment, inoculation with 
 <italic>Bipolaris</italic> did not modify the effect of 
 <italic>Microstegium</italic> density on the three native species relative to the mock inoculation control, suggesting that competitive effects of 
 <italic>Microstegium</italic> on native species are likely to be consistent in the presence or absence of low levels of disease incidence. Our experimental design captured two components of native species’ competitive ability: their growth in the absence of competition and their biomass responses to changes in 
 <italic>Microstegium</italic> density (i.e., interspecific competition coefficients) [
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. To better characterize the competitive ability of the native species, it is also necessary to estimate their biomass responses to changes in their own density (i.e., intraspecific competition coefficients) [
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Because 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>gigantea</italic> inoculation had unique effects on the growth of the three native species, it may also uniquely affect their per capita impacts on competitor growth, altering their intraspecific competition coefficients. If, however, 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>gigantea</italic> does not affect the intraspecific competition coefficients of the native species, we would expect low levels of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>gigantea</italic> exposure to increase the competitive ability of 
 <italic>Dichanthelium</italic> in interactions with 
 <italic>Microstegium</italic>, decrease the competitive ability of 
 <italic>Elymus</italic>, and to have no effect on the competitive ability of 
 <italic>Eragrostis</italic>, potentially leading to shifts in the relative abundances of native species. Predicting the long-term outcome of disease impacts on native–invasive interactions requires also understanding the invasive species’ competitive ability and niche overlap between the native and invasive species (e.g., overlapping resource requirements or natural enemies) [
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Because the native species are perennial and the invasive species is an annual, studies that examine the effects of disease on aspects of plant fitness other than biomass, for example, annual seed survival and perennial adult survival, are necessary for characterizing the comprehensive impacts of disease on native–invasive plant competition [
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>].
</p>
