<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">Due to the interest of argan oil and with the objective to reduce rural poverty and to conserve the argan forest, women’s cooperatives were created with the support of the Moroccan state and foreign organizations, since the 1990s (Sguenfle and Sadki 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">2018</xref>). Cooperatives have remarkably contributed to local economic development, social status of women and environmental preservation outcomes (Dossa 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2011</xref>). Thus the argan forest constitutes a very important part in household income. Recently, argan oil price has almost quadrupled to reach more than 300 dirhams for a liter (30$) on the local markets and more than 3000 dirhams (300$) per liter in export booming market (Lybbert et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2011</xref>; Aziz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2013</xref>; Le Polain de Waroux 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2013</xref>). Several studies have shown that by 2027, this market will register an annual growth of 10.8% tons of oil produced entirely by women (Lybbert et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2011</xref>; Grand View Research 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2020</xref>). Actually, according to the Moroccan Cooperation Development Office (ODCO), there are more than 400 argan oil cooperatives, 93% of which were created by women and provide regular income for more than 7000 producers. The organization into cooperatives has allowed many women to have bank account and to reinvest in micro-projects like poultry, sheep, and goat farming (Roumane 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">2017</xref>). In addition, this development had a positive impact on the education of girls with a clear increase in enrollment in schools (Lybbert et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2011</xref>). However, it should be noted that the added value of the oil market benefits to educated managers, intermediaries, industry executives, and distributors more than women who produce the oil (Turner 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">2014</xref>; Montanari and Bergh 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2019</xref>). Else, argan woodlands provide various economic opportunities in relationship with ecotourism and local products which can contribute to socioeconomic development of rural communities (Laaribya et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2017</xref>).
</p>
