<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">From the perspective of functional compounds, cold-pressed oils are considered as one of the healthiest chemicals-free products commercially available. Lipophilic phytochemicals present in cold-pressed oils such as phytosterols, squalene, and cholecalciferol have been demonstrated to improve physiological and biological activity in human health. Phytosterols have displayed their abilities to reduce the level of cholesterol in the blood, increase metabolic rates, enhance fat burning, and reduce the incidence of some types of cancers [
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Squalene has some favourable health benefits such as cancer inhibitor, antitumor, antioxidant in the skin, and has been applied in pharmaceutical and cosmetic industries. Cholecalciferol helps regulate and control absorbability of phosphorus and calcium, and, furthermore, it is an effective compound for managing blood sugar levels, thereby controlling diabetic conditions [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In addition, nutritional value of plant oils is also evaluated by the amount of monounsaturated fatty acids (MUFAs) and polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs) [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Oils rich in MUFAs, such as oleic acid (C18:1), had the potential to lower blood cholesterol levels and reduce the aortic accumulation of oxidized LDL without adversely affecting HDL fraction [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. PUFAs are essential for the human health and can only be received from a proper diet. The benefits of linoleic acid (C18:2) have been evidenced for cholesterol and triglyceride lowering effects, anti-inflammation, cardioprotection, antidiabetes, and cancer prevention [
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Meanwhile, linolenic acid (C18:3) has been known for its anti-inflammatory, anti-hypertensive, anti-thrombotic activities, and anticancer activities [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].
</p>
