<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the second experiment, I tested for the effects of fire and grass competition on similarly-sized young trees (about 18 months old) for one month in a greenhouse. I applied the burning technique [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>] in which a blow torch was held about 20 cm from the tree and burned the entire height of each tree on two opposing sides (n = 30 burned trees). The other 30 trees were controls (unburned). I manipulated the presence of grass (
 <italic>Bromus inermis</italic>) using half the burned and half the control trees (n = 15 burned and 15 control). 
 <italic>Bromus inermis</italic> is a weakly to strongly rhizomatous invasive C
 <sub>3</sub> species that is now found in all states of the United States and in Canada [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Grasses were grown for 30 days before the onset of this experiment. The soil used was Promix
 <sup>®</sup> Premier Ultimate Potting Mix. In this second experiment, I measured above- and belowground biomass. For the assessments of storage, I measured total non-structural carbohydrates using a standard protocol [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. All of the analyses were done in a single laboratory because inter-laboratory comparisons have proved problematic in terms of repeatability [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. I also recorded % nitrogen in the trees using a Rapid N Exceed
 <sup>®</sup> Elementar nitrogen analyzer. I recorded tree condition as 1 (poor 
 <underline>~</underline>mostly dead) to 10 (good). There was a significant positive correlation between tree condition and total biomass (r = 0.55, p &lt; 0.001).
</p>
