<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0055">Curcumin and ellagic acid are examples of compounds isolated from plants which are used as food and feed supplements. These compounds prevent metabolism of aflatoxin B
 <sub>1</sub> (AFB
 <sub>1</sub>) and increase the activity of glutathione-S-transferase involved in the detoxification of xenobiotics. They were equally found via Ames assay and in rat and chicken models to protect against mutagenicity induced by AFB
 <sub>1</sub> with 
 <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> strain TA98 and TA100 (
 <xref rid="bib142" ref-type="bibr">Soni et al., 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Gowda et al., 2008</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib138" ref-type="bibr">Smerak et al. (2006a)</xref> studied the effect of curcumin against AFB
 <sub>1</sub> mutagenicity by Ames, 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> micronucleus, comet and chemiluminescence and blastic transformation methods. The results showed that curcumin was able to protect cells against mutagenicity. They also demonstrated a significant reduction in DNA damage through stimulation of DNA repairs. Curcumin has earlier been demonstrated by many authors to exhibit anticarcinogenic, antiproliferative and antimutagenic effects against various mutagens 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">El-Hamss et al., 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Inano and Onoda, 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib121" ref-type="bibr">Polasa et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Hosseini and Hosseinzadeh, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Khan et al., 2019</xref>). Resveratrol is another natural product isolated from grape skin which suppresses the proliferation of many tumour cells such as breast, pancreatic and prostate cancers by inhibiting xenobiotic metabolism and inducing detoxification pathways (
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Farombi, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib149" ref-type="bibr">Thipe et al., 2019</xref>). Studies have showed that this product can protect mycotoxin-induced toxicity in 
 <italic>vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Do et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib144" ref-type="bibr">Sridhar et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib147" ref-type="bibr">Tabeshpour et al., 2018</xref>). Furthermore, 6-gingerol, a natural bioactive compound extracted from ginger was found to possess strong protective effects against PAT-induced genotoxicity in HepG2 cells 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib165" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2011</xref>).
</p>
