<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0070">
 <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Makhuvele et al. (2018a)</xref> investigated the antigenotoxicity of plant extracts against AFB
 <sub>1</sub>-induced genotoxicity. The results showed that most plant extracts from 
 <italic>Artabotrys brachypetalus, Helichrysum petiolare, Hexalobus monopetalus, Friesodielsia obovate, Monanthotaxis caffra, Protea hybrid, Protea roupelliae, Monodora junodis, Uvaria caffra, Xylopia parviflora, Rhoicissus sekhukhuniensis, Podocarpus henkellii, Podocarpus elongatus</italic> and 
 <italic>Agapanthus praecox</italic> had moderate to strong antimutagenic potency in both Vitotox and Ames assays. Ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>Premna integrifolia</italic> leaves demonstrated a protective effect in mice liver against AFB
 <sub>1</sub>-induced toxicity by inhibiting apoptosis and oxidative stress (
 <xref rid="bib137" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2019</xref>). Furthermore, extracts of 
 <italic>Schisandra chinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>Thonninga sanguinea</italic> were shown to possess hepatoprotective effects against AFB
 <sub>1</sub> by enhancing antioxidant and detoxification in rats (
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Gyamfi and Aniya, 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Ip et al., 1999</xref>). Feed additives from South African medicinal plants, 
 <italic>i.e</italic>., 
 <italic>Silybum marianum, Withania somnifera</italic> and 
 <italic>Centella asiatica</italic> were tested and except for 
 <italic>Centella asiatica</italic>, the extracts were found to give partial protection against the growth inhibitory activity of OTA and associated immunosuppression in broiler chicks (
 <xref rid="bib145" ref-type="bibr">Stoev et al., 2019</xref>). The same extracts also showed some hepatoprotective effects on broiler chicks exposed to OTA with extract from 
 <italic>S. marianum</italic> exhibiting nephroprotective effect against OTA toxicity. Very recently, 
 <xref rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr">Nerilo et al. (2020)</xref> evaluated the use of ginger essential oils (GEO) as a fumigant agent for stored maize grains. They reported that GEO was mainly composed of α-zingiberene (23.85%) and geranial (14.16%). Furthermore, their results revealed that 25 and 50 μg/g, respectively, exhibited antifungal activity against 
 <italic>A. flavus</italic> and inhibited AFB
 <sub>1</sub> and AFB
 <sub>2</sub> production. Despite the efficacy of plant extracts and their phytochemicals in the management of toxigenic fungi and their toxins, there are various limitations to the use of phytochemicals and their crude extracts as biofungicides and nutraceuticals. The subsequent section elaborates on these limitations.
</p>
