<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The results obtained from the pH-stat digestion model showed that the FFA release rate in the emulsified PGO that contains a high amount of CLn was significantly lower than the rates observed in SBO, PHY, and IO emulsions in these study conditions (
 <italic class="italic">p &lt;</italic> 0.05). Although the 
 <italic class="italic">d</italic>
 <sub class="sub">32</sub> of the SBO emulsion was significantly smaller than that observed in the other emulsions and the ΔBS(t) rate decreased in the order of SBO (−0.9) &gt; PHY (−1.39) &gt; IO (−1.82) &gt; PGO (−2.12%/h) emulsions, the lowest lipolysis rate from the PGO emulsion seems to be mainly due to the TAG species that are comprised of CLn-CLn-CLn. More specifically, the FFA release rates of PGO (71.8%) were significantly lower than those of SBO (93.8%), IO (92.2%), and PHY (85.4%), when the pH-stat digest model was performed for 10 min. Meanwhile, PHY and IO emulsions did not show a significant difference (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) in their degree of the FFA release rate at 10 min, even though a slightly reduced FFA release rate was observed in the PHY emulsion during the lipolysis reaction. This suggests that the degree of CLn present at which position (i.e., sn-1 and sn-1,3) of the TAG molecules affects lipolysis. In particular, TAG consisting of three molecules of CLn (i.e., CLn-CLn-CLn) is considered to be the most important factor with respect to low lipolysis in this study. For example, PHY contained 24.8% CLn-CLn-CLn; however, PGO (showing the lowest lipolysis rate) consisted of 67.8% of CLn-CLn-CLn. In the pH-stat digest model, there was a lower initial rate of PHY than that of SBO (0% CLn-CLn-CLn) and IO (3.4% CLn-CLn-CLn at most). Nevertheless, the FFA release rate of PHY tended to be low with significant differences, at least up until 5 min of the lipolysis reaction. As expected, PGO containing the highest amount of CLn-CLn-CLn showed the lowest initial rate among them. Therefore, the low lipolysis characteristic of CLn-CLn-CLn may clearly be shown from PGO rather than from PHY. From the results, we conclude that the higher is the CLn-CLn-CLn content, the lower is the lipolysis rate; the order is as follows: SBO ≥ IO ≥ PHY &gt; PGO. Such assumptions can be supported by the following experimental results that were derived by calculating the amount of residual TAG after lipolysis using HPLC-ELSD analysis (Equation (5)), in which CLn-CLn-CLn showed a lower lipolysis rate than any other TAG molecules (i.e., L-L-L, L-L-O, CLn-CLn-P, etc.). In particular, the proposed mathematical model for quantifying individual TAG species suggests that lipolysis rate of CLn-CLn-CLn in PGO sample was 65.3% while those of L-L-L and L-L-O present in SBO sample were 77.1% and 75.5%, respectively. However, there was no significant difference at 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &gt; 0.05 between CLn-CLn-CLn and L-L-L, although they were significant at 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.1. Since the digestive process in the human body is very complex and influenced by many factors, it is hard to say which factor most affects the rate of lipid digestion. Nevertheless, the results from this experiment can be used as a basis for understanding the effect of different compositional fatty acids in TAG molecules on lipid digestion.
</p>
