<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The effect of temperature on antimicrobial activity of
 <italic class="italic"> C. martini </italic>EO was tested according to Shahi and Shahi [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>], using poisoned food technique at concentration of respective MIC of each tested fungal pathogen using Sabouraud dextrose agar as nutrient medium [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Five lots of EO were kept in small brown vials, each containing 5 ml of EO; these were exposed to room temperature of 40, 60, 80, and 100°C in incubator for an hour. Five-day-old fungal culture was punched aseptically with a sterile cork-borer of generally 5 mm diameter. The fungal discs were then put on the gelled agar plate. The agar plates were prepared by impregnating desired concentration of EOs at their respective MIC for each organism at a temperature of 45°C. The plates are then incubated at temperature of 25°C for 7 days. Colony diameter was recorded by measuring the two-opposite circumference of the colony growth. The result was expressed in percentage inhibition of fungal growth by comparing the colony diameter of poisoned plate (EO) and nonpoisoned plate (with distilled water) and calculated using the formula given below:
 <disp-formula id="eq1" class="disp-formula">
  <label class="label">(1)</label>
  <math id="M1" class="math">
   <mtable style="T∞4" class="mtable">
    <mtr class="mtr">
     <mtd class="mtd">
      <mo id="EAAAAAACADCA" class="mo"/>
      <malignmark class="malignmark"/>
      <mtext class="mtext">Percent Growth Inhibition:</mtext>
     </mtd>
    </mtr>
    <mtr class="mtr">
     <mtd class="mtd">
      <maligngroup class="maligngroup"/>
      <malignmark class="malignmark"/>
      <mspace width="10pt" class="mspace"/>
      <mfrac class="mfrac">
       <mrow class="mrow">
        <mtext class="mtext">Growth in Control</mtext>
        <mo class="mo">−</mo>
        <mtext class="mtext">Growth in Test</mtext>
       </mrow>
       <mrow class="mrow">
        <mtext class="mtext">Growth in Control</mtext>
       </mrow>
      </mfrac>
      <mo class="mo">×</mo>
      <mn class="mn">100</mn>
     </mtd>
    </mtr>
   </mtable>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
