<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Diabetes mellitus has developed into one of the debilitating diseases disturbing the health of many people living with cardiovascular diseases in modern times. The root of 
  <italic>Ageratum conyzoides</italic> was investigated for its effects on alloxan-induced diabetic Wistar rats' cardiac tissues. Thirty-two (32) Wistar rats weighing between 180 and 190 g were randomly divided into four groups. The animals in groups B-D were induced with a single dose of 150 mg/kg body weight of alloxan (ALX) intraperitoneally. They were confirmed hyperglycemic after 72 hours of induction and then sustained in hyperglycemic condition for 2 weeks. Animals in groups C and D received AC intervention, as stated above, for four weeks. The body weight of the experimental animals and blood collection for glucose estimation were taken weekly for six weeks using appropriate instruments. Biochemical assays for lipid profile, antioxidant enzymatic, and nonenzymatic markers were carried out. Histopathological changes in the cardiac tissues were also studied. Administration of 150 mg/kg of ALX to experimental rats induced diabetes and significantly reduced the body weights, significantly (
  <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) increased the glucose level, triglyceride (TG), total cholesterol (TC), and low-density lipoprotein (LDL) levels, and decreased the levels of high-density lipoprotein (HDL) and antioxidant enzymatic markers such as catalase (CAT), superoxide dismutase (SOD), and glutathione peroxidase (GPx) while the antioxidant nonenzymatic marker such as malondialdehyde (MDA) level was significantly increased. By contrast, rats given the ethanolic extract root of 
  <italic>A. conyzoides</italic> had significantly (
  <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) increased the body weight gain, whereas the glucose levels significantly (
  <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) improved in treated diabetic rats. This extract also improved the cardiovascular system of the diabetic rats by significantly decreasing TG and LDL levels, significantly (
  <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) increasing the HDL level, significantly reducing the cardiac contents of CAT, SOD, and GPx, and significantly (
  <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) decreasing MDA. Ethanolic extract root of 
  <italic>A. conyzoides</italic> exhibited antihyperglycemic and antihyperlipidemic activities and mitigates damage to the heart from the ALX-induced myocardial toxicity associated with type-1 diabetes.
 </p>
</abstract>
