<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">Much of the research on BS is focused on soil isolates, including the 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus</italic> groups, however, BS production by marine microorganisms is an area relatively unexplored since it is still considered that marine microorganisms are difficult to culture in the laboratory (Stein et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" class="xref">1996</xref>; Walsh and Duffy 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" class="xref">2013</xref>). The global demand for BS has led to a number of academic research groups and manufacturers searching underexploited sources such as bacteria isolated from the marine environment. Recent reports have shown the successful isolation and culture of diverse BS producing microorganisms from marine habitats (Thavasi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" class="xref">2009</xref>). BS production is induced in most marine bacteria in the hydrocarbon polluted environment. Marine bacteria increase hydrocarbon bioavailability by the production of BS which shows surface/emulsification activities and facilitates hydrocarbon degradation (Thavasi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" class="xref">2011</xref>). The marine oil spill from deep water horizon in the Gulf of Mexico caused large volumes of oil spill into the water. Several BS producing marine bacteria became predominant following the spill, including 
 <italic class="italic">Alteromonas</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Halomonas</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Alcanivorax</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Colwellia</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Cycloclasticus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudoalteromonas</italic> (Mapelli and Scoma 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">2017</xref>). A number of other bacteria producing BS including, 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Acinetobacter</italic> were reported in oil contaminated waters worldwide (Gerard et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">1997</xref>; Hentati et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">2016</xref>; Ortega-de la Rosa et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">2018</xref>), although these species are not necessarily restricted to the marine environment.
</p>
