<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Various in vitro regulatory activities of tricin on colon cancer stem cells [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], endothelial cells [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], C2C12 myotubes [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], mesenchymal stem cells [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and dermal fibroblasts [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] have also been reported. In the present study, tricin was shown to inhibit migration of colon cancer cells HT-29 and Colon26-Luc cells at the non-cytotoxic concentrations. In fact, another human colon cancer cell line HCT-116 has also been tested for tricin’s inhibitory effect on viability and migration (data shown in 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-molecules-25-03730">Supplementary Information</xref>). Results showed that the IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of tricin in HCT-116 cells was over 600 μM and the significant inhibition on transwell migration could only be achieved by 50 μM or higher of tricin. Thus, HT-29 cells were used for the further experiments. The phosphorylation of key molecules involved in colorectal cancer progression and metastasis, such as Akt [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], Erk1/2 [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] and NF-κB [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], were down-regulated by tricin in HT-29 colon cancer cells, which the results were in line with previous studies. Shalili et al. showed the anti-inflammatory activity of tricin in hPBMCs which was via modulating the p38MAPK and PI3K/Akt pathways [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Another study demonstrated that tricin could inhibit proliferation and invasion of C6 glioma cells by downregulating focal-adhesion-kinase (FAK) and thus affecting the downstream Akt pathway [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Besides, expression of migration-related proteins, such as integrins, can be evaluated in the future study to illustrate the underlying mechanism of anti-migratory action of tricin.
</p>
