<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We reported a total of 8 compounds, which were isolated and evaluated for scolicidal activity against the protoscoleces. Plants have biologically active compounds in the form of primary and secondary metabolites. Among these, chlorophyll, proteins, and sugars are included in primary, while flavonoids, alkaloids, terpenoids, and phenols are the secondary compounds [
 <xref rid="pone.0240456.ref116" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. These different bio-active compounds work synergistically in combination to produce a pharmacological effect [
 <xref rid="pone.0240456.ref117" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. The efficacy of plant compounds may be attributed to the fact that they inhibit or retard the growth, maturation damage, suppress appetite or reduce procreative ability, which are all the causes of mortality. Moreover, the considerable activity of plants extracts may be due to the additive or synergistic relationship among different major components which can interact with multiple molecular targets in various developmental stages of the parasite [
 <xref rid="pone.0240456.ref118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. Thymol, berberine, and thymoquinone revealed significant 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> scolicidal activity at concentration of 0.1, 0.5, and 1 mg/ml after 5, 10, and 1 minute of exposure [
 <xref rid="pone.0240456.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0240456.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Thymol effects were promising that could be explained by the fact that, it induces shrinkage of the soma region, loss of turgidity, rostellar disorganization, hooks loss, formation of blebs on the tegument, and destruction of microtriches, which finally lead to death of the protoscoleces [
 <xref rid="pone.0240456.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. This could be attributed to the fact that any damage to hooks and blebs formation on the tegument of protoscoleces are generally stress responses which are brought about by different harmful conditions. Moreover, microtriches destruction could affect the absorption of nutrients in protoscoleces and cause starvation and finally death of the larvae [
 <xref rid="pone.0240456.ref119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>].
</p>
