<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Complementary and alternative medicine (CAM) refers to practices of traditional or modern systems that are not considered part of mainstream medicine [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Traditional systems of healing, including Chinese Traditional Medicine (TCM), Ayurveda, Unani medicine, and Iranian Traditional Medicine (ITM) or so-called Persian Medicine, have a theoretical foundation and embrace the indigenous knowledge, skills, and practices of ancient civilizations to maintain health, prevent disease, and treat physical or mental illness. The need for an integrative approach to use both complementary and conventional healthcare is increasingly recognized by many countries and allows safe and effective access to traditional medicines [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. A medical system notable in terms of theory and clinical experience, ITM, is founded on philosophical concepts associated with the four elements [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] (e.g., 
 <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Practiced for thousands of years, ITM is distinctive for world-renowned polymaths such as Rhazes [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] whose book 
 <italic>al-Hawi</italic> (
 <italic>Continiens</italic>) is an encyclopedia of clinical medicine, embracing the views of predecessor physicians from various countries, and Avicenna whose book, 
 <italic>Canon of Medicine</italic>, was a main medical reference in Europe until the 16
 <sup>th</sup> century [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Proficient Iranian physicians continued to revise and complement the body of collected knowledge up to the modern period. An exemplar of the 18
 <sup>th</sup> century, Mohammad Hosein Aghili, is recognized for books on all scopes of ITM including 
 <italic>Kholasat al-Hekmah</italic> (on principles of Iranian medicine), 
 <italic>Mo</italic>'
 <italic>alejaat</italic> (on diseases and their treatment), 
 <italic>Makhzan al-Advieh</italic> (on monotherapy), and 
 <italic>Ghrabadin-e Kabir</italic> (on combination therapy).
</p>
