<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>“Arnica Mexicana” is the common folk name associated with 
 <italic>Heterotheca inuloides</italic>. This plant, belonging to the Asteraceae family, is widely used in flower tea form to treat bruises, rheumatism, inflammation, gastric ulcers, bile duct diseases, cancer and lung diseases [
 <xref rid="B112-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. The anti-inflammatory effect of 
 <italic>Heterotheca inuloides</italic>, as well as antinociceptive properties, have been demonstrated in preclinical models [
 <xref rid="B113-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. The inhibition of COX has been identified as part of its mechanism of action [
 <xref rid="B114-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>], along with the peripheral activation of 5-HT1 receptors [
 <xref rid="B115-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. In agreement with these effects, Rocha-González et al. [
 <xref rid="B116-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>] demonstrated that the antineuropathic actions of 7-hydroxy-3,4-dihydrocadalin (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00865-f001">Figure 1</xref>) involved the activation of serotonergic and opioid receptors, as well as the activation of guanylyl cyclase. An antioxidant effect was also observed. On the other hand, in vitro assays demonstrated the bactericidal, antiparasiti, and cytotoxic activity of 7-hydroxy-3,4-dihydrocadalin, supporting its traditional uses in Mexican culture [
 <xref rid="B117-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. In the last two decades, the information on the pharmacology, toxicology and chemical composition of this plant has increased. Twenty compounds were isolated from dried flowers of 
 <italic>H. inuloides</italic>, demonstrating that the major constituent is the sesquiterpenoid 7-hydroxy-3,4-dihydrocadalin [
 <xref rid="B119-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. In the same study, the authors suggested that 7-hydroxy-3,4-dihydrocadalin can be linked to alterations in body weight, hepatoxicity, nephrotoxicity and death at very high doses [
 <xref rid="B119-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>].
</p>
