<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lentinan, a β-1,3-D-glucan extracted from 
 <italic>Lentinula edodes</italic> or shiitake, is another compound perdmitted in and widely used in Japan for the treatment of cancers, especially gastric cancer, due to its immunomodulatory action. Lentinan is a BRM capable of promoting Th1 response and improving Th1/Th2 balance. In several in vitro studies and in in vivo mice models, the polysaccharide activates dendritic cell function by increasing levels of tumor-infiltrating CD86+ cells, stimulates T and NK cell production, restores the killer/survival cell ratio, increases FcR receptor expression and thus promotes NK cell-mediated tumor cell killing, and increases IL-2 levels. The metabolite also appears to enhance complement-dependent cytotoxicity (CDC) and complement-dependent cell-mediated cytotoxicity via the CR3 receptor, known to be triggered by iC3b in fungal cell walls [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. It can activate downstream signaling pathways, such as MAPK-NFκB and Syk-PKC, through binding to pattern recognition receptors such as TLR2/4/6/9 and Dectin-1, the complement receptor CD11b, and other membrane receptors, with the consequent activation of T cells, NK cells, and macrophages [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. In both in vitro and in vivo studies, it has also been shown to increase the cytotoxic activity of primary macrophages and RAW264.7 cell lines, as well as cytotoxic activity and TNF secretion in macrophages, and cytotoxicity against sarcoma S180 cells by upregulating the proapoptotic protein Bax and downregulating the antiapoptotic protein Bc1–2, thus inducing apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The action of lentinan is also expressed by interfering with cell cycles, as demonstrated in an in vitro study on rat C6 glioma cells [
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The C6 cells’ activity was strongly inhibited in a dose- and time-dependent manner and the induction of apoptosis, cell cycle blockage, an increase in the proportion of cells in G0/G1 phase, and a decrease in those in S-phase were observed.
</p>
