<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">An important component for developing a new, sustainable lure for use in pest control is its field life. Prolonged attractiveness and the lethality reduce the need for frequent labor-intensive and expensive reapplications. In our experiments, lures indeed lost their attractiveness over time, even though ME is the most powerful male lure for tephritid species and known to attract certain species from distances, even at low doses
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. When placed in a competitive setting (in close proximity to each other), trap catch gradually declined with ageing of the lure. A decline in attractiveness of ME lures was also observed in studies with other insect species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. Fresh lures release higher amounts of ME than aged lures and are thus more attractive
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>, as there seems no upper boundary of ME release above which the compound becomes repellent
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>. However, this difference may only be noticeable when traps are sampling from the same local population and thus are ‘competing’ for the same flies (as in our 1-m spaced traps). Indeed, a recent study also indicated that efficacy does not necessarily increase with application density of SPLAT-MAT-ME dollops, and that above a saturation level efficacy of attract-and-kill no longer increases, or even decreases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. The same study also did not find a clear decrease in efficacy of lures of 1-d old and 14-d old lures. This is similar to what we found here, as capture rates of differently aged lures in our 30-m spaced traps experiments showed a consistent decline in capture rates of lures of more than 7 days old. Note also that the longevity of lures measured here may be influenced by climatic factors and thus cannot directly be translated to other climate zones
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>. The results also suggest that, although ME is a powerful attractant, the range of attraction of ME may be less than 30 m. As this is an indirect inference from the data, however, detailed studies are needed to examine the exact range of attraction.
</p>
