<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As well as the reason for its deformities, Pompia botanical classification has been long debated and, to this day, The Plant List (
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.theplantlist.org" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.theplantlist.org</uri>) and The International Plant Names Index (
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.ipni.org" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ipni.org</uri>) do not report any botanical name for this citrus, either as a synonym or as an unresolved name. Although the citrus presence in Sardinia was reported as early as the fifth century b.C., Pompia was first described as an individual and distinct species only in 1837, when Moris reported it as 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus medica monstruosa</italic> [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-24-00908" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. This first classification of this citrus as a citron (
 <italic class="italic">Citrus medica</italic> L.) cultivar, though, has been rejected by Camarda et al. [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-24-00908" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>] on the basis of the evaluation of several factors, i.e., phytochemical, genetic, and morphological analyses. This work lead to the development of a new taxonomical entity defined as 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus limon</italic> var. 
 <italic class="italic">pompia</italic> Camarda var. 
 <italic class="italic">nova</italic>, thus classifying it as a lemon cultivar, rather than a citron one [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-24-00908" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. The proximity of Pompia to 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus limon</italic> (L.) Osbeck and 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus medica</italic> L. was also reported by Mignani et al. [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-24-00908" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. This close relationship was evaluated on the basis of genetic markers, which showed a significant similarity of Pompia to the ‘Zagara Bianca’ lemon and ‘Etrog’ citron genotypes [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-24-00908" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Petretto et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-00908" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>], instead, evaluated the headspace volatile emissions of several citrus samples, classifying Pompia as closer to 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">C. myrtifolia</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">C. sinensis</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">C. paradisi</italic>. Lemon and citron, on the contrary, resulted as the farthest in terms of emitted volatile organic compounds (VOCs) [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-00908" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Curk and Luro [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-00908" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>] analysis of genetic 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> markers classified Pompia as an hybrid of 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus medica</italic> L. and 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus × aurantium</italic> L. [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-00908" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. In a recent work, Deiana et al. [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-24-00908" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>] reported the VOCs emitted in the headspace of polar (ethanolic) extracts of the traditional Pompia candied flavedo (“sa pompìa intrea”). The production process did not influence the volatile emission of the peel, as limonene was found to be as abundant (over 70%) in the head space of this product as in the untreated peels analyzed by Petretto et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-00908" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-24-00908" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>].
</p>
