<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Renewable resources have attracted some research attention as precursors for developing tailored bioactive polymers that are capable of minimizing the rate of bacterial adhesion and biofilm growth in healthcare facilities. Within the therapeutic arsenal of naturally-available alternatives that have been explored, plant secondary metabolites (PSMs), such as essential oils and herb extracts, have revealed relatively powerful broad-spectrum antibacterial activities [
 <xref rid="B15-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Good examples of currently used PSMs are tea tree (
 <italic class="italic">Melaleuca alternifolia</italic>), geranium, zataria, and cinnamon oils that have shown inherent bactericidal performance in their liquid and/or vapor form toward important pathogenic microbes. Due to the presence of a large number of active molecules within a single essential oil or plant extract, their antimicrobial pathway is not fully understood and cannot be attributed to a particular mechanism [
 <xref rid="B17-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. However, the pharmaceutical, cosmetic, and food industries have recently paid great attention to bioactive PSMs, by way of the usage of natural additives as a substitute for synthetic preservatives [
 <xref rid="B18-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Indeed, PSMs are a relatively low-cost renewable resource available in commercial quantities, with limited toxicity, and potentially, different biocidal mechanisms to synthetic antibiotics, which make them an appropriate precursor for “green” functional polymeric materials. On the other hand, using PSMs for surface functionalization through immobilization or synthesis of coatings without loss of functionality is challenging, in part due to the issues with solubility and volatility of these precursors. The plasma-assisted technique overcomes these challenges, allowing the fabrication of a polymerized 3D matrix from renewable precursors with control over its surface properties and chemical functionality. Under appropriate fabrication conditions, plasma-enabled synthesis may help preserve/retain the inherent antimicrobial functionality of PSMs within the solid polymer-like thin films. Plasma polymers of PSMs (PP-PSMs) have several advantages including low cytotoxicity, long-term stability, and a reduced risk of developing microbial resistance. These advantageous properties render PP-PSMs a suitable candidate for bioactive coating applications.
</p>
