<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39">p-Coumaric acid classified as a phytochemical and nutraceutical, presents in vegetables, and fruits, such as cranberry syrups, grape juices, tomatoes, apple, peanuts, carrots, garlic, potatoes, onions, beans, and cereals such as rice maize, oats and wheat, tea, beer and chocolate. p-Coumaric acid and its conjugate have demonstrated several biological activities including antifungal, anti-cancer, antimicrobial, anti-viral, anti-melanogenic, antioxidant, immunomodulatory and anti-inflammatory effects, antiplatelet aggregation, anxiolytic, antipyretic, analgesic, anti-arthritis and antigenotoxicity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR180">180</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR182">182</xref>]. In vitro and in vivo experiments showed that p-coumaric acid attenuated lipopolysaccharide-induced lung inflammation by scavenging ROS production and modulating the oxidative stress under inflammatory conditions in lung injury [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR180">180</xref>]. Moreover, 
 <italic>Adenostemma lavenia</italic> is a permanent medicinal herb belonging to the Compositae family and is widely distributed in the tropical parts of Asia mainly in Taiwan. It is used to treat pulmonary congestion, pneumonia, bacterial infections of the respiratory tract, edema, and inflammation. p-Coumaric acid was found to be the major constituent of this herb. In fact, 
 <italic>Adenostemma lavenia</italic> has been reported to ameliorate acute lung injury through activating AMPK/Nrf2/HO-1 signaling pathway and improving the anti-oxidant response [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR183">183</xref>]. p-Coumaric acid among other compounds extracted from the Himalayan medicinal plants traditionally used to treat bronchitis and related symptoms has demonstrated antiviral activities in vitro against different kinds of human rhinoviruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR184">184</xref>]. Likewise, in vitro research showed that p-coumaric acid among other phenolic acid components extracted from propolis could be effective against Herpes Simplex Virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR185">185</xref>]. Furthermore, a recent docking study has reported that cis-p-Coumaric acid found in coriander, the cis-form of p-coumaric acid, among other natural products may interfere with SARS-CoV-2 attachment to the host cell and can be successfully considered as anti-COVID-19 agents for people with a high risk of cell stress like elders, cancer patients, and front-line medical staff. Similarly, another docking study showed that p-Coumaric acid, Curcumin and their boronic acid derivatives are probable inhibitors of endoribonuclease Nsp15 encoded by Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (MERS-CoV) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR186">186</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR187">187</xref>]. Consequently, p-Coumaric acid and its derivatives may be used as target for an alternative therapy of covid19 and its related pneumonia.
</p>
