<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Understanding species responses to global change will help predict shifts in species distributions as well as aid in conservation planning and management. Climate change varies around the world and concomitant ecological responses are likely to differ by region (
 <xref rid="CIT0077" ref-type="bibr">Walther 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2002
 </xref>). During the past century, average annual global temperatures for land and ocean surfaces have increased at a rate near 0.6 °C/century; however, the trend has been three times greater since 1976, with some of the largest increases in temperature occurring in the high latitudes (
 <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">NOAA Satellite and Information Service 2009</xref>). As the climate changes, most species have been shifting their ranges poleward, or upward on mountains (
 <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Parmesan and Yohe 2003</xref>); however, species vary in their ability to shift their ranges (
 <xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">Sorte 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>). Growing evidence suggests that biotic interactions play key roles in species response to climate change (
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Guo 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2013
 </xref>). Specifically, the study of above- and below-ground biotic interactions are important to consider in relation to plant range expansion with climate change (
 <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">van der Putten 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2016
 </xref>). In a literature review of over 600 papers, 
 <xref rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr">Tylianakis 
  <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)
 </xref> revealed that climate change influences virtually every type of biotic interaction, yet biotic interactions are rarely incorporated into models of organismal response to climate change (
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Gilman 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>). 
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Gilman 
  <italic>et al</italic>. (2010)
 </xref> stressed the importance of assessing the potential effects of novel interactions precipitated by climate change, suggesting that assessing species demographic responses to interactions with species beyond current range boundaries would improve our ability to understand species range-expanding capacities.
</p>
