<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ASLs are mostly discarded or burnt, as they are considered a worthless agricultural waste product. However, ASLs have been commonly used in tropical and subtropical countries such as India, Vietnam, Malaysia, and Laos as a traditional medicine for the treatment of cardiac problems, dysentery, worm infections, fever, fainting, haemorrhage, constipation, and dysuria. Bioactive phytochemicals investigated in different ASL extracts revealed potential biological and pharmacological activities, such as antidiabetic, antioxidant, antimicrobial, antiviral, antiobesity, antidiarrhoeal, and antitumour activities [
 <xref rid="B41-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The phytochemical profile of ASLs can be broadly classified as acetogenins, alkaloids, flavonoids, phenols, saponins, tannins, glycosides, sesquiterpenes, anthocyanins, steroids, diterpenes, terpenoids, quinones, amino acids, and fatty acids [
 <xref rid="B43-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Among them, total phenolic compounds (TPCs), including flavonoids, alkaloids, phenols, saponins, and tannins, are most abundant in ASLs. Epidemiological investigations have proven the role of polyphenolic compounds against various chronic diseases, such as cancer, diabetes, cardiovascular, and neurodegenerative diseases [
 <xref rid="B35-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Polyphenolic compounds regulate various biochemical and physiological processes, namely, enzymatic activity, cell proliferation, signal transduction pathways, and cellular redox potential, to fight against chronic pathologies [
 <xref rid="B47-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. A list of various phytochemicals reported in ASLs is presented in 
 <xref rid="biomolecules-11-00614-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, and the structures are depicted in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biomolecules-11-00614-f003">Figure 3</xref>.
</p>
