<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dietary supplementation of 
 <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> can be used to enhance coccidiosis resistance through increased body weight gain (BWG), decreased lesion score of the gut, and reduced shedding of fecal oocysts [
 <xref rid="B7-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Moreover, a natural product, betaine, can reduce the effects of coccidian challenge [
 <xref rid="B8-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Berberine has been reported to exert a protective effect on chicks’ cecum infected with 
 <italic>E. tenella</italic> [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Mixtures of essential oil (eugenol, thymol, and piperine) and vitamin D
 <sub>3</sub> may be used as an anti-coccidial feed supplement in coccidian-infected broilers [
 <xref rid="B10-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This supplement has a positive effect on the BWG and feed conversion ratio (FCR) of birds due to improved digestibility of nutrients by stimulating digestive enzymes, increasing beneficial microflora, and reducing intestinal lesions caused by coccidial protozoa. Various chemical anti-coccidial drugs such as Amprolium, Monensin, Diclazuril, and Sacox are widely used in the poultry industry and have effective control of avian coccidiosis [
 <xref rid="B11-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Salinomycin is a standard coccidiostat monovalent ionophoric therapeutic drug that disrupts alkali ions gradients across the cell membrane of Eimeriosis across interfering with potassium potential transmembrane and promoting K+ ions efflux from cytoplasm and mitochondria. As a result, Salinomycin acts at the early stages of the parasite life cycle and is most useful as a preventative than a therapeutic drug. Here, Salinomycin used with the diet as preventative or coccidiostat rather than as coccidiocidal drug. The coccidiocidal such as Toltrazuril (Baycox
 <sup>®</sup>) as one of the triazines used during outbreaks due to Toltrazuril acts on intracellular stages of the life cycle that are undergoing schizogony and gamogony leading to control parasite in broilers with just a single 2-day treatment course [
 <xref rid="B12-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. However, the incidence of drug resistance from parasites and the consumers prefer residue-free meats have prompted a number of researchers to suggest and develop alternative agents [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
</p>
