<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The inhibitory activity for α-glucosidase and α-amylase varied depending on the sample and the type of extraction. By comparing the α-glucosidase and α-amylase inhibitory activities of the samples tested, the SW, PWE exhibited the strongest inhibition compared to the positive control, Acarbose. The methanolic extracts of Ceylon Cinnamon have been reported to have the potential to control hyperglycemia 
 <italic>(
  <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Nair, Kavrekar &amp; Mishra, 2013</xref>)
 </italic>. The IC
 <sub>50</sub> values for the α-amylase and α-glucosidase inhibition were 130.55 ± 10.50 µg mL
 <sup>−1</sup> and 140.01 ± 10.08 µg mL
 <sup>−1</sup>, respectively for the 
 <italic>C. zeylanicum</italic> methanol extracts. Comparable α-amylase inhibition has been reported for methanol extract of Cinnamon bark (IC
 <sub>50</sub>: 86.84 µg mL
 <sup>−1</sup>), Cinnamon stick (IC
 <sub>50</sub>: 54.69 µg mL
 <sup>−1</sup>) and the clinical drug, Metformin hydrochloride (53.03 µg mL
 <sup>−1</sup>) (
 <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Wickramasinghe, Peiris &amp; Padumadas, 2018</xref>). According to the findings of 
 <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Wickramasinghe, Peiris &amp; Padumadas (2018)</xref>, a poor α-amylase inhibition was seen in Cinnamon drink (3207.01 µg mL
 <sup>−1</sup>), Cinnamon capsule (2537.49 µg mL
 <sup>−1</sup>), and Cinnamon powder (771.67 µg mL
 <sup>−1</sup>). When compared with previously reported values for methanolic extracts, the PWE and DWE of SW showed better enzyme inhibition (IC
 <sub>50</sub> for the α-glucosidase inhibition; 42 ± 8 µg mL
 <sup>−1</sup> and 116 ± 17 µg mL
 <sup>−1</sup> and IC
 <sub>50</sub> for the α-amylase inhibition; 78 ± 7 µg mL
 <sup>−1</sup> and 132 ± 11 µg mL 
 <sup>−1</sup> respectively). The enzyme inhibition mechanism of Acarbose is well established. Acarbose inhibit the α-glucosidase activity as a competitive inhibitor (
 <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Van de Laar, 2008</xref>). Phytochemicals in plant extracts, in particular phenolics act as non-competitive inhibitors against digestive enzymes. Non-competitive mode of inhibition is better due to the possible multiple side interactions of phenolic compounds with enzyme molecule and also this type of inhibition does not depend on the substrate concentration.
</p>
