<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">Snap-off and corner flow are responsible for disconnection and trapping of hydrocarbons and/or CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. Snap-off occurs when a droplet of non-wetting phase (typically oil or gas) disconnects, leading to the trapping of that phase (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). The basic physics of snap-off was first described by Rayleigh
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>
 </sup>. Flow instabilities arise due to geometrical changes, resulting in differences of capillary pressure. For a jet, as described by Rayleigh
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>
 </sup>, with a given wavelength, regions of constriction develop, leading to higher capillary pressures than adjacent regions. This high capillary pressure causes fluids to flow away from the constriction eventually resulting in the collapse of an interface. For a porous media, a similar situation occurs when an oil droplet spans many pores. The leading and trailing ends of the oil droplet have a given capillary pressure, while the pore throat constriction between pores can result in a larger capillary pressure due to the swelling of a wetting film in the neck region. Hence, the formation of snap-off is also largely dependent on the specific pore geometry, i.e. pore-wall curvature, and pressures in the wetting and nonwetting phases
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>. For a complete water-wet environment (θ = 0), and at capillary-dominated flow regime, snap-off favours a large aspect ratio (pore radius/ throat radius) during an imbibition process, such as water flooding
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup>. In pores of rocks with complex pore geometry, snap-off is controlled by corner flow (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>), which is the advancement of the wetting phase through connected water films that cover the water-wet grains. This mechanism was proposed by Ransohoff, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup> as the quasi-static snap-off criterion, which predicts non-wetting phase snap-off within a smoothly constricted noncircular capillary.
</p>
