<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">Several fabrication methods for geo-material chips have been proposed to produce microfluidics devices that mimic real rock. Song, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup> developed an approach to study acid injection in carbonate formation by etching microfluidics channels into a natural calcite rock, which required multiple pre-processing steps. Song and Kovscek
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup> developed a method to create a functionalised 2D silicon micromodel with pore surfaces coated mainly with kaolinite clay, which allows for the study of fluid–solid interactions. In addition, these authors published another paper describing the use of their functionalised microfluidic platform to study the response of clay to low salinity brine injection
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup>. Other microfluidic device modifications that aid in representing real rock include altering the wettability of the porous network. Lee, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup> developed a novel method termed “Stop-Flow-Lithography (SFL)” to fabricate microfluidics devices with controlled wetting properties in a single lithographic step. They showed immiscible fluid displacement in single pore bodies with varying wetting properties. Porter, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup> developed a novel fabrication method whereby fractures are etched into thin sections of different rock types (shale, sandstone, and siltstone) by a custom-built femtosecond laser direct-write (LDW) system. Similarly, Gerami, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
 </sup> presented a coal geo-material microfluidic chip that was fabricated by etching a fracture pattern into a coal surface using three-dimensional laser micromachining. Wang, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup> demonstrated a novel way to coat a controlled thickness of calcite (CaCO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>) nanocrystal layer onto a simple glass microfluidic channel. This process was achieved by converting the inner surface of the microfluidic silica channels to CaCO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> through numerous chemical surface modifications to functionalise the glass surface to grow a CaCO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> nanocrystal layer. Singh, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup> used another approach to design a microfluidic device of a sandstone rock called “Real Rock Microfluidic Flow Cell” (RRMFC). They mounted a thin section (500 μm) of a sandstone rock between two covers that were bonded via a plasma generator. Lastly, another approach taken by Zhu and Papadopoulos
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup> demonstrated two-phase flow in transparent miniature packed beds with rough grains and analysed the effect of roughness on flow.
</p>
