<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Delphinidin is a member of anthocyanidins which is naturally found in flowers, fruits, vegetables, and grains [
 <xref rid="B80-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>,
 <xref rid="B83-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,
 <xref rid="B84-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. SIRT6 modulation activity of delphinidin has been determined using core histones and estimating the remaining level of H3K9 by Western blot technique, and delphinidin was found to enhance SIRT6 deacetylation [
 <xref rid="B52-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. The structural basis of SIRT6 activation involves delphinidin’s binding to a binding site which is next to a loop near the acetylated peptide substrate binding site of SIRT6 and may cause conformational change of this loop [
 <xref rid="B52-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Delphinidin-3-glycoside is present in the fruits of bog blueberry and has been reported to eliminate ROS, which resulted in the prevention of DNA damage responsible for p53 and Bad (Bcl-2 associated agonist of cell death) activation in UV-B-irradiated human dermal fibroblasts. Henceforth, it is capable of inhibiting skin pigmentation and photoaging [
 <xref rid="B80-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Potent anti-aging action of delphinidin through scavenging of ROS and free radicals has also been reported [
 <xref rid="B80-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B84-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Delphinidin and delphinidin-3- glycoside produced an anti-inflammatory effect through dose-dependent reduction of IL-1
 <italic>β</italic> and suppression of the NF-
 <italic>κ</italic> B pathway in vitro in a mechanistic study carried out by Murakami et al. [
 <xref rid="B81-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Chen et al. reported that delphinidin ceased the proliferation of HER-2 positive breast cancer cells, MDA-MB-453 and BT474, and induced apoptosis and autophagy. In both breast cancer cells, delphinidin induced autophagy through mTOR signaling pathway suppression and AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) signaling pathway stimulation [
 <xref rid="B83-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Significant free radical scavenging activity, anti-proliferative and apoptotic effects of delphinidin on MCF breast cancer cells have also been reported [
 <xref rid="B83-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>].
</p>
