<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Medicinal plants are rich sources of secondary metabolites with various biological properties, including antimicrobial properties [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. 
 <italic>Arbutus pavarii</italic> Pamp, an endemic medicinal plant species known locally as Shmar in Libya, is an evergreen shrub belonging to the Ericaceae family [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In folk medicine, it is used for the treatment of gastritis, renal infections, cancer ailments and kidney diseases [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Previous phytochemical studies on 
 <italic>A. pavarii</italic> showed that this plant contains mainly flavonoids, tannins, glycosides, simple phenolics, triterpenes and sterols [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In addition, it was also reported that 
 <italic>A. pavarii</italic> demonstrated strong antibacterial activity against several pathogenic bacteria [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. However, few studies have focused on determining the effect of 
 <italic>A. pavarii</italic> extracts and its fractions against resistant bacterial strains. Thus, the aim of this study was to evaluate the 
 <italic>A. pavarii</italic> leaf and stem bark extracts against methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA). The anti-MRSA activity of the crude methanolic extract and various solvent fractions were assayed using disc diffusion assay, followed by minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) and minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) determinations, as well as time–kill curve analysis. In addition, the active fraction was subjected to ultrahigh-performance liquid chromatography–mass spectrometry (UHPLC-ESI-MS/MS) analysis for the identification of potential bioactive compounds.
</p>
