<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In 
 <italic>P. carpunya</italic> EO and in the beverage prepared with this species, compounds with medicinal properties, such as those mentioned above, are present; however, compounds that are harmful to human health, such as safrole, are also present. In scientific reports, safrole is considered a human carcinogen based on sufficient evidence of hepatocarcinogenic in rats and mice. The US EPA (United States Environmental Protection Agency) has evaluated the carcinogenicity of safrole and classifies it as possibly carcinogenic to humans (Group B2: the agent (mixture) is possibly carcinogenic to humans). The major toxicities of safrole and isosafrole come from their carcinogenic nature after the oxidation of the allyl side chain and the oxidation of the methylenedioxy group [
 <xref rid="B30-plants-10-00338" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Safrole is oxidized into 1-hydroxysafrole, isosafrole, and dihydrosafrole, which are all carcinogenic (Bogusz, 2008) and have been found to modify DNA covalently [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-10-00338" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The effects of safrole can differ due to the exposure conditions, e.g., short-term vs. chronic toxicity [
 <xref rid="B30-plants-10-00338" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Safrole cannot be used as fragrance ingredient: the International Fragrance Association (IFRA) recommends that the essential oils containing safrole should not be used at levels in which the total concentration exceeds 0.01% in consumer products [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-10-00338" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-plants-10-00338" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The use of natural substances containing safrole is regulated by legal restriction, e.g., in Europe, a maximum concentration of 1 ppm in food and beverages is allowed [
 <xref rid="B33-plants-10-00338" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]; in the USA, it has been prohibited in soft drinks in since 1970s; it is allowed in China (State Food and Drug Administration of China, SFDA of China) in concentrations below 1 mg/L [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-10-00338" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].
</p>
