<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this paper, we report that low concentration of CAA in the growth medium induces changes in the cell morphology of 
 <italic class="italic">D. indicus</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">D. indicus</italic> cells which are rod shaped, form multi-cell chains when grown in complex media such as LB, TSB, and NB or minimal media containing 0.1% CAA. While we are reporting growth medium-dependent morphological alteration in 
 <italic class="italic">D. indicus</italic> for the first time, this phenomena is not new to the Deinococcaceae family. 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chou and Tan (1991)</xref> reported salt-induced morphological changes in 
 <italic class="italic">D. radiodurans</italic> cells. In 
 <italic class="italic">D. radiodurans</italic> increased NaCl concentration decreased the rate of cell separation (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chou and Tan, 1991</xref>). Nutrient concentration-induced morphotypes were also observed in 
 <italic class="italic">D. radiodurans</italic>, and diluted TGY medium led to growth as monomeric and dimeric units (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Joshi and Toleti, 2009</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">D. mumbaiensis</italic> (now known as 
 <italic class="italic">D. ficus</italic>) also displays variable morphology in different nutrient media (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shashidhar and Bandekar, 2006</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">Azotobacter vinelandii</italic> exhibits morphological variability when grown in media containing peptone. In Azotobacter, the formation of branched, giant filamentous cells was due to amino acids, particularly glycine in the medium (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vela and Rosenthal, 1972</xref>). Similarly, our data show that in 
 <italic class="italic">D. indicus</italic> too, presence of CAA in minimal growth medium delayed cell separation resulting in the formation of multi-cell chains. Surprisingly, changes in sodium chloride concentration in the growth medium did not play a role in shape alteration in 
 <italic class="italic">D. indicus</italic> DR1 (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4" class="xref">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>). We also found that the morphological alterations in 
 <italic class="italic">D. indicus</italic> was reversible, as multi-cell chains when transferred back into nutrient-poor media reverted back to rod-shape and no longer exhibited delayed cell separation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" class="xref">Figure 5</xref>). Addition of all 20 amino acids to minimal media caused rod-shaped cells to grow as multi-cell chains (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7" class="xref">Figure 7</xref>). As increasing the concentration of ammonium chloride in M2G medium did not alter cell morphology, it can be concluded that cells are probably responding to increase in amino acids rather than an increase in nitrogen source (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5" class="xref">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>). Our data show that minimal medium, when supplemented with methionine, lysine, aspartate, and threonine, alters cell morphology of 
 <italic class="italic">D. indicus</italic>. In these four amino acids, it was found that methionine and lysine play a more predominant role compared to aspartate and threonine (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7" class="xref">Figure 7</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">Deinococcus</italic> are phylogenetically closely related to extreme thermophiles of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Thermus</italic>. Also, both genera 
 <italic class="italic">Thermus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Deinococcus</italic> have complex cell wall consisting of ornithine-Gly-peptidoglycan (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Embley et al., 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Oyaizu et al., 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Quintela et al., 1999</xref>). Cell wall analysis of 
 <italic class="italic">D. indicus</italic> revealed the presence of ornithine in the cell wall. Ornithine is generated as an intermediate in arginine biosynthesis and in Deinococcus family enzymes involved in AAA pathway for lysine biosynthesis are also involved in arginine biosynthesis (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Miyazaki et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lombo et al., 2004</xref>). It could be predicted that concentration of lysine in the growth medium could be regulating the amount of ornithine in the cell. This notion was supported by our data, as the addition of exogenous ornithine as low as 0.005% in the growth medium was able to recapitulate the multi-cell chain phenotype.
</p>
