<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Furthermore, El-Keredy and Naena [
 <xref rid="B47-animals-11-00093" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] studied the growth of Nile tilapia (
 <italic>Oreochromis niloticus</italic>, initial weight of 20 g) infected with 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> in response to the dietary supplementation of YSE at levels of 0.1, 0.14, and 0.2% for 8 weeks. The fish group fed 0.1% YSE showed the higher growth performance, feed intake (FI), feed efficiency ratio (FER), and protein efficiency ratio (PER); meanwhile, the groups that received high levels of YSE (0.14 and 0.2%) showed no significant alteration compared to the control. The authors demonstrated that high levels of YSE in diets increases the saponin concentration, which negatively affects nutrient absorption; this is in line with the results of Chen et al. [
 <xref rid="B48-animals-11-00093" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] for juvenile Japanese flounder (
 <italic>Paralichthys olivaceus</italic>) a fed lower saponin content (originated from soybean) in their diet, which resulted in increased growth due to the high absorption rate from the intestine that was motivated by the slight permeabilization due to saponins. This would elucidate why a low concentration (&lt;1000 ppm) of saponin-rich plant extracts can exert a favorable influence on fish growth, whilst high levels participate in the development of enteritis. In this context, Bae et al. [
 <xref rid="B49-animals-11-00093" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] reported no significant differences in the growth and feed efficiency between olive flounder (
 <italic>P. olivaceus</italic>, 5.26 ± 0.17 g) that were fed yucca meal for 8 weeks at the level of 1.5 g/kg diet and the control group. Likewise, Tidwell et al. [
 <xref rid="B50-animals-11-00093" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] reported a reduction in body weight and elevation in the FCR of juvenile channel catfish (
 <italic>I. punctatus</italic>) fed YSE at the level of 1.1 g/kg diet.
</p>
