<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another investigation revealed the presence of five novel withanolides such as withasomnilide, somniferanolide, somniferawithanolide, withasomniferanolide, and somniwithanolide in ethanolic extract of stem bark. Further examination showed that epoxy groups are not present in withasomniferanolide, somniferawithanolide, and somniwithanolide (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). Similarly, three new withanolides such as withasomniferol A, withasomniferol B, and withasomniferol C were isolated from ethyl acetate and benzene extracts of roots (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>). 4-Deoxywithaperuvin isolated from alcoholic fruit extract was characterized by spectral analysis and found to contain five hydroxyl moieties (at 5, 6, 14, 17, and 20 positions) (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). Viscosalactone B in the alcoholic extract of the whole plant was investigated as a structural analog of withaferin A having an epoxy group at 6 and 7 positions, double bond at C- 24, and three hydroxyl groups at 3, 4, and 27 positions of carbon skeleton (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>). Withanolide Y was identified as 5α, 6α-epoxy-7α, 17α, 20R-trihydroxy-1-oxo-22R-witha-2, 24-dienolide using single-crystal XRD (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>). Extraction of plant’s root with petroleum ether and acetone was carried out for the isolation of phytochemicals. Various chromatographic and spectroscopic techniques depicted the presence of β-sitosterol and 
 <italic>d</italic>-glycoside (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). Subcritical water extraction of withanolides was conducted for 50 g powder of 
 <italic>W. somnifera</italic>/500 ml of distilled water at 40 °C. The extract was lyophilized and withanolides were separated by soxhlet and high-performance liquid chromatography. Results showed that withanoside IV, 12-Deoxywithastramonolide, withaferin A, and withanolide A were the actual biological contents responsible for various biological activities (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>). Phytochemical extraction of caffeic, ferulic, and benzoic acids along with withaferin A, withanone, and withanolide A was done from methanolic and chloroform extracts of root, stem, and leaves of 
 <italic>W. somnifera</italic> at a concentration of 4.0 g of plant part (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>). Chemical names, structures, and biological activities of essential withanolides are listed in 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. 
</p>
