<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">When more quantitative testing was conducted using the broth microdilution method, all eucalyptus oils showed antimicrobial activity. This is consistent with previous studies, verifying that both eucalyptus oil and 1,8-cineole have activity against a wide range of Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria and yeasts [
 <xref rid="B11-microorganisms-06-00122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-microorganisms-06-00122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. The current study found considerable variation in activity between the different eucalyptus oils, which could be a reflection of differences in their chemical composition. Comparison of the activity of 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus</italic> oils to 1,8-cineole alone confirmed the importance of the other moderate and minor components in 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus</italic> oils in relation to the MIC and MBC/MFC values obtained. Comparison of geometric mean MICs for all oils showed that 
 <italic class="italic">E. globulus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E. polybractea</italic> oils had the lowest values, with a geometric mean of 4.3% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>), and 
 <italic class="italic">E. loxophleba</italic> 1 and 1,8-cineole had the highest values, with geometric means of 7.5% and 7% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>), respectively. These results align with those reported by Cimanga et al. (2002). They showed that oils from 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus deglupta</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus saligna</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus urophylla</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus propinque</italic>, which all contain relatively high percentages of 1,8 cineole (&gt;30%), exhibited similar or lower antimicrobial activity than oils from 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus alba</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus robusta</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus citriodora</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus tereticornis</italic>, which contain low percentages of 1,8-cineole (&lt;10%) [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-06-00122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>].
</p>
