<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It was unexpected that, according to the MIC/MBC values, the Gram-negative bacteria were, broadly speaking, more susceptible to 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus</italic> oils than the Gram-positive bacteria. This susceptibility of Gram-negative bacteria may be due to the presence of certain oil components, such as 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cymene, terpinolene, 1,8-cineole, and cis-geraniol, which can cause the discharge of Gram-negative outer membrane lipopolysaccharide and increase the permeability of the cytoplasmic membrane [
 <xref rid="B34-microorganisms-06-00122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. Of the Gram-negative bacteria, 
 <italic class="italic">A. baumannii</italic> was the most sensitive to the 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus</italic> oils. This result is particularly relevant, given that 
 <italic class="italic">Acinetobacter</italic> spp. are emerging globally as problematic antibiotic-resistant pathogens [
 <xref rid="B35-microorganisms-06-00122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Our results are in agreement with several previous studies that also found 
 <italic class="italic">Acinetobacter</italic> spp. to be relatively more sensitive than other Gram-negative species [
 <xref rid="B22-microorganisms-06-00122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-microorganisms-06-00122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Very few researchers have investigated the potential mechanisms underlying this increased sensitivity; however, it could be due to differences in the outer membrane composition or efflux pumps of 
 <italic class="italic">Acinetobacter</italic> species and 
 <italic class="italic">Enterobacteriaceae</italic> [
 <xref rid="B37-microorganisms-06-00122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-microorganisms-06-00122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Finally, many previous reports on the antimicrobial activity of 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus</italic> oil are difficult to compare with the current study because of differences in the methods used to assess the antimicrobial activity and differences in the chemical composition of the oils.
</p>
