<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p id="Par1" class="p">Cancers and microbial infections are still a major health problem, therefore research on new anticancer and antimicrobial agents ought to be continued. Natural products including essential oils from medicinal plants continue to be an important resource to manage various diseases. Thus, the particular objectives of this study are to investigate the chemical composition, cytotoxic, antimicrobial and antioxidant activities of three 
   <italic class="italic">Plectranthus</italic> species namely 
   <italic class="italic">P. cylindraceus</italic> Hocst. ex Benth., 
   <italic class="italic">P. asirensis</italic> JRI Wood and 
   <italic class="italic">P. barbatus</italic> Andrews grown in Saudi Arabia
   <italic class="italic">.</italic>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2" class="p">The essential oils of the three 
   <italic class="italic">Plectranthus</italic> species were obtained by hydrodistllation and analyzed using GC/FID and GC-MS. The essential oils were further assessed for their cytotoxic, antimicrobial and antioxidant activities. Determination of the cytotoxic activity was carried out against Hela, HepG2 and HT-29 cancer cell lines by utilizing MTT-assay. The antimicrobial activity was assessed against six bacterial and fungal strains by using broth micro-dilution assay. In addition, the antioxidant activity was evaluated utilizing the DPPH and β-Carotene-linoleic acid assays.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p id="Par3" class="p">The GC/FID and GC-MS analysis led to the identification of 59, 60 and 42 compounds representing 89.0% 95.0 and 97.1% of the total essential oils of 
   <italic class="italic">P. cylindraceus, P. asirensis</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">P. barbatus</italic>, respectively. The essential oils were characterized by a high content of oxygenated sesquiterpenes in 
   <italic class="italic">P. cylindraceus</italic>, sesquiterpene hydrocarbons in 
   <italic class="italic">P. asirensis</italic> and monoterpene hydrocarbons in 
   <italic class="italic">P. barbatus</italic> where maaliol (42.8%), β-caryophyllene (13.3%) and α-pinene, (46.2%) were the predominant compounds. Additionally, the oils particularly of 
   <italic class="italic">P. cylindraceus</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">P. barbatus</italic> exhibited remarkable cytotoxic and antimicrobial activities with IC
   <sub class="sub">50</sub>-values between 3.8 and 7.5 μg/mL and MIC-values ranging from 0.137 to 4.40 mg/mL. Moreover, the oils showed moderate to high radical scavenging and antioxidative activities ranging from 52 to 75% at the highest concentration of 1 mg/mL.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par4" class="p">The observed results back the suggestion that these three 
   <italic class="italic">Plectranthus</italic> species represent a promising source of cytotoxic and antimicrobial agents.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
