<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The global bar soap industry is worth approximately US$186 billion. Current trends in consumer preference have shown an increase in demand for the use of natural ingredients in personal skin care and cosmetics products. This has resulted in a steady increase in small- and medium-sized artisan hand-made or homemade soap businesses offering a variety of products with a range of natural ingredients to supply this niche market. Formulation of specialty hand-made natural soap bars by artisan soap makers involves a skillful combination of the ingredients, thoughts, and artistic creativity to produce high-quality soap bars with superior sensory characteristics that resonates with consumers [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. These sensory characteristics include fragrance, color, lather ability, moisturizing capabilities, hardness, skin compatibility, and chemical stability during storage and use [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Of these, aroma (fragrance) and moisturizing capabilities are considered the most influential determinants of consumer preference for natural soap products. Natural soaps are generally defined as alkali salts of fatty acids derived primarily from vegetable or plant oils used as soap feedstock, and contained natural fragrances and/or organic ingredients included as additives. Commercially, natural soaps are manufactured via either a cold or hot saponification process, where triglycerides in fats, oils, and/or free fatty acids used as feedstock are converted in the presence of a base (typically sodium or potassium hydroxide) to form fatty acid salts (soaps), glycerol, and free fatty acids [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Many artisanal soap makers prefer the cold saponification process due to the enhanced aesthetics of the finished product, potential superiority in retaining antioxidants, or the fragrance from essential oils, and creative flexibilities to customize each ingredient including the addition of fresh ingredients, such as fruits and vegetable purees, to obtain a desired end product. Cold saponification uses the heat generated from the combination of the fatty acids (acid) in the melted oils and fats with sodium hydroxide (base) to facilitate the saponification process, which takes 18–24 h to complete, and a further 3–4 weeks to cure the finished soaps [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. The sensory and chemical characteristics of natural soaps are dependent on the manufacturing process, and the chemical composition of the feedstock materials used during formulation. For example, the type and purity of base (alkali) used determines the hardness and solubility of the finished soap. Sodium hydroxide produces harder, more durable soaps, while potassium hydroxide is used to produce soft soap bars or liquid soaps [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Typically, 70–85% of the total contents of natural herbal soap bars are composed of sodium salts of fatty acids (saponified fatty acids) derived from triglycerides or hydrolyzed fatty acids present in the soap feedstock [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. These fatty acids play key roles in the performance of the natural soap, consumer preferences, and the cost of the finished products. Final performance is determined by the carbon chain length, degree of unsaturation (number of double bonds), and distribution and composition of the saponified fatty acids (alkali salts). Saturated fatty acids give light open foams (lather) and a solid, hard consistency, while unsaturated fatty acids provide moisturizing, conditioning, or skin nourishing properties [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. 
</p>
