<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The most commonly used oil sources in natural herbal soaps are mixtures of palm, coconut, olive, rice bran, and sunflower seed oils [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. In some instances, animal fat may be blended with vegetable oils in the final formulation to modulate the soap performance. Vegetable oils tend to be associated with higher quality soaps [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. As such, the use of animal fats is typically replaced with palm or coconut oils to enhance the quality and performance of natural soaps. Vegetable oils tend to be richer in polyunsaturated (C16:3, C18:2, and C18:3) fatty acids, while beef fat (tallow) tends to contain higher levels of long chain (C16:0–C18:0) saturated fatty acids [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Palm and coconut oils, on the other hand contain shorter chain length (C8:0–C14:0) saturated fatty acids. The shorter chain saturated fatty acids in coconut or palm oil increase the lathering profile of the final soap products due to enhanced solubility in water. However, fatty acids with 10 or fewer carbons are less desired because they can confer objectionable odors and irritate the skin. Conversely, longer (C16:0–C18:0) chain length fatty acids enhance the cleansing property of the soap, provide a longer lasting soap, and are devoid of objectionable odors [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. However, the lathering ability is reduced due to decrease solubility in water with the increase in chain length [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Vegetable oils, such as soybean or olive oils, also contain significant levels of long chain saturated fatty acids (C16:0–C18:0), as well as high levels of mono (C18:1) and polyunsaturated (C18:2, C18:3, and C16:3) fatty acids. The solubility and moisturizing capabilities of natural herbals soaps will increase with the degree of unsaturated fatty acids present in the vegetable oils used as soap feedstock [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. However, the double bonds found in unsaturated fatty acids are very susceptible to oxidation, which can occur during saponification, curing, and storage. Oxidation of the double bonds can produce shorter chain fatty acids, aldehydes, ketones, undesirable odors, and discoloration in the soaps, which affects the quality, sensory perception, and shelf life of the final product [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Natural antioxidants in the form of plant extracts are typically added as additives (1–8% of final soap composition) to suppress the oxidation of polyunsaturated fatty acids in natural herbal soaps. These include grape seeds or rosemary extracts, fruits, and vegetable purees. In addition to providing a source of natural antioxidants, these plant extracts are also used as colorants and to add fragrance. A key aesthetic for consumer acceptance of personal cleansing products is fragrance [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. As such, artisanal natural soap manufacturers use a variety of exotic plant-based essential oils as additives to provide added consumer benefits, enhance the sensory perception, as well as modify the performance of their products [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Like the unsaturated fatty acids in the soap, essential oils are also susceptible to oxidation during saponification, storage, or curing. As a result, essential oils used as additives can modulate the odor profile and quality of the product during its lifetime if not properly formulated. Free fatty acids are another important subclass of additives used during the formulation and manufacturing of natural herbal soaps [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. The free fatty acids can exist as unsaponified fatty acids in the final product following saponification and curing. Though the free fatty acids added as additives can decrease the odor and color stability of the final products, they are also known to play an important role in determining soap quality [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. For example, free fatty acids can enhance the fragrance, moisturizing capabilities, foaming, or lather quality. These are important soap quality indices that can influence consumer preference and acceptance [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Thus, the free fatty acid content, though a minor component of the overall soap composition, can have significant influences on the overall quality and sensory characteristics, and in turn, consumer preference or acceptance of natural soaps [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. The right blends of natural fats, oils, and additives (natural plant extracts, free fatty acids, essential oils, and antioxidants) are important factors to consider in the design and manufacture of natural soaps with the ideal physicochemical characteristics and sensory appeal to meet consumer’s demands [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02356" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Many artesian or hand-made soap makers use a combination of cold saponification, essential oils, and plant extracts as additives to manufacture various natural soaps. However, very little is known how the combination of cold saponification and the use of essential oils and plant extracts as additives: (1) how modulating the levels of unsaponified (or free) fatty acids in commercial natural soaps, and (2) how the composition of the unsaponified fatty acids in the manufactured soap influences the soap’s sensory quality and consumer’s perception of the finished products. This is of relevance considering the current global trends show an increase in the number of hand-made specialty natural soap businesses. Many of these businesses are home-based and use an array of additives and essential oils to manufacture their product, but have very little scientific information on how these ingredients can affect the unsaponified fatty acid content, quality, and consumer’s preference or acceptance of their products. We hypothesized that the composition of the feedstock and additives used to manufacture natural herbal soaps following cold saponification will significantly affect the level and composition of free or unsaponified fatty acids in the finished product, and that the unsaponified fatty acids, though a minor component of the soap composition, will have a major influence on the quality, sensory perception, and consumer preference of the final product. This study was designed to test this hypothesis. 
</p>
