<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Antifungals have a broad range of applications but it is difficult to determine the ideal treatment regime because their use can be limited and is often accompanied by side effects. The indiscriminate use of antibiotics has led to an increased resistance to these types of medications (
 <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">De Oliveira Santos et al., 2018</xref>). Accordingly, researchers are exploring therapeutic alternatives, such as the use of plant essential oils or extracts. These have been proven beneficial in the treatment of several diseases due to their phytochemical components that have physiological and therapeutic effects on humans, limited toxicity, and low therapeutic costs (
 <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Abdulrasheed et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-80" ref-type="bibr">Sardi et al., 2013</xref>). The World Health Organization reports indicate that up to 25% of modern medicines used in the United States of America originate from plants. In Africa and Asia, 80% of the population still uses medicinal herbs in their primary health care centers (
 <xref rid="ref-97" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2002</xref>). Moreover, there is documented evidence for the antimicrobial potential of more than 1,340 plants (
 <xref rid="ref-99" ref-type="bibr">Yilar, Bayan &amp; Onaran, 2016</xref>). 
 <italic>Vitex</italic> is one of the largest of the 250 genera in the family Verbenaceae found worldwide (
 <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Ganapaty &amp; Vidyadhar, 2005</xref>). The therapeutic applications of 
 <italic>Vitex agnus-castus</italic> (VA-C) and its safety as a medicinal plant are well stated (
 <xref rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr">Niroumand, Heydarpour &amp; Farzaei, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr">Neves &amp; Da Camara, 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr">Rani &amp; Sharma, 2013</xref>). Previous studies have emphasized the antibacterial activity of the essential oils extracted from the seeds and fruit of VA-C (
 <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Eryigit et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Dervishi-Shengjergji et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Ghannadi et al., 2012</xref>). Other studies have investigated the antimicrobial activity of essential oils extracted from the leaves of VA-C (
 <xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Katiraee et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-95" ref-type="bibr">Ulukanli et al., 2015</xref>). A few studies have demonstrated the antifungal activity of the seed oil (
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Asdadi et al., 2014</xref>). The antifungal potential of VA-C leaves essential oils against plant pathogens (
 <xref rid="ref-99" ref-type="bibr">Yilar, Bayan &amp; Onaran, 2016</xref>). The antibacterial activity of the leaf extract of VA-C has been identified in a few studies (
 <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Ababutain &amp; Alghamdi, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Kalhoro, Farheen &amp; Aqsa, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Arokiyaraj et al., 2009</xref>) as well as the antimicrobial activity of VA-C leaf extract (
 <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Kalhoro, Farheen &amp; Aqsa, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Maltaş et al., 2010</xref>). These studies used only a few bacteria and one 
 <italic>Candida</italic> species (
 <italic>Candida albican</italic>s). 
 <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Keikha et al. (2018)</xref> evaluated the antifungal activity of ethanolic and aqueous lead extracts on 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> strains and they found that the ethanol extract was more effective than the aqueous extract against 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> strains. However, the effect of VA-C leaf extracts of against human 
 <italic>Candida</italic> species has not been well-studied.
</p>
