<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The new model of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> using all occurrences seems to have lower coverage than those proposed by the previous studies [
 <xref rid="B9-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] and compared to those of the global models of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B1-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Interestingly, this study benefited from the availability of more occurrence records in México to update the ecological niche of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in México. Our study observed some limitations in the previous attempts of constructing the ecological niche of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in México [
 <xref rid="B9-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The previous modeling efforts of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in México were associated with some sources of bias in constructing the ecological models, particularly if their available protocol had some limitations that were not suitable for the species, area, and extrapolation zones [
 <xref rid="B51-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. For example, a previous study [
 <xref rid="B53-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] argued that the partial occurrence records are biased by an optimal ecological niche model, therefore, a complete sampling of all the possible occurrences of the species is indispensable. Here, we used a novel improved methodology and allowed different modeling settings [
 <xref rid="B38-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] to construct the species ecological niche models based on calibration and evaluation of our models using a large number of updated variables that previously could not be used. We allowed the optimal parameterization based on the set of environmental variables, features, and multiple regularizations for better construction of the ecological niche model of the Asian tiger mosquito 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>. It is worth mentioning that this methodology has also been applied in the field of vector-borne diseases, such as the 
 <italic>Lutzomyia longipalpis</italic> complex and leishmaniasis vectors [
 <xref rid="B22-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and to infer the distribution of a 
 <italic>Rickettsia parkeri</italic> pathogen transmitted by several tick species in America (personal communications Sokani Sanchez-Montes, UNAM). This study anticipated the potential distribution of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in 2020 and identified areas of strict extrapolation where results should be interpreted with caution [
 <xref rid="B39-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The climatic conditions were surprisingly analogous in calibration and projection areas; therefore, we can have a high degree of certainty in the potential distribution in México. Previous studies [
 <xref rid="B9-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] did not provide any evidence for extrapolation risks and analogous climatic conditions between the different areas they evaluated. An early study [
 <xref rid="B49-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] used the standard deviation as an approximation of the areas where care must be taken in the interpretations of the ecological niche model. Our maps presented an estimate of the uncertainty index based on both the MOP analysis (i.e., analogous versus non-analogous climatic conditions) and a map with the combined standard deviation values as a proxy of the uncertainty in the potential distribution areas. We agree with the previous studies [
 <xref rid="B54-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] regarding the importance of assessing uncertainty indices with the potential distribution map for better interpretations of the prediction maps in the different invasion areas.
</p>
