<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Extracts of the MLs have been utilized for traditional medicines to cure diabetes, bronchitis, diarrhea, asthma, kidney, scabies, respiratory problems, syphilis, and urinary disorders [
 <xref rid="B2-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The most active biological constituent of MLs is mangiferin, followed by phenolic acids, benzophenones, and other antioxidants such as flavonoids, carotenoids, quercetin, isoquercetin, ascorbic acid, and tocopherols. Mangiferin is the main contributor of most of the biological activities of MLs extract. MLs have a great scope of valorization as they are recognized to possess varied phytochemical, biological, and pharmacological properties, viz. anti-microbial, antioxidant, anti-diabetic, anti-tumour, and immunomodulatory effects. ML oil (MLO) contains monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, minor quantities of other analogues, and trace amounts of non-terpenoid hydrocarbons and oxygenated hydrocarbons. The essential oil from MLs also possesses bacteriostatic properties and contains several antimicrobial constituents such as α-gurjunene, trans-caryophyllene, α-humulene, α-selinene, and camphor. The benzophenone derivatives in MLs possess significant 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase inhibitory and immunosuppressive activities. There are several reviews that have been developed to discuss the bioactive compounds and health promoting effect of mango fruit/pulp [
 <xref rid="B4-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], whereas others contain a scattered compilation of literature on mango seeds, MLs, and mango bark [
 <xref rid="B8-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].
</p>
