<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2662-7671</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8010956</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3274</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-021-03274-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antibacterial, anti-inflammatory and antioxidant activities of Mahanintangtong and its constituent herbs, a formula used in Thai traditional medicine for treating pharyngitis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4441-8612</contrib-id><name><surname>Dechayont</surname><given-names>Bhanuz</given-names></name><address><email>Nuzz@hotmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Phuaklee</surname><given-names>Pathompong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chunthorng-Orn</surname><given-names>Jitpisute</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Juckmeta</surname><given-names>Thana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prajuabjinda</surname><given-names>Onmanee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiraratsatit</surname><given-names>Kitrawee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412434.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 1127</institution-id><institution>Department of Applied Thai Traditional Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>Thammasat University, </institution></institution-wrap>Pathum Thani, 12120 Thailand </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412434.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 1127</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Public Health, </institution><institution>Thammasat University, </institution></institution-wrap>Pathum Thani, 12120 Thailand </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>21</volume><elocation-id>105</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Mahanintangtong is listed in the Thailand&#x02019;s National List of Essential Medicines (NLEM). It is used to treat non-specific fevers and illnesses such as pharyngitis and chickenpox. In this study, we investigated the biological activities of the different medicinal plants used in the Mahanintangtong formula.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">The plant materials were extracted by maceration and decoction. Antimicrobial activity, assessed by disc diffusion method, the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC), and minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) were compared with commercially available standard antibiotics. To elucidate the anti-inflammatory mechanisms, inhibition of nitric oxide (NO), tumor necrosis factor &#x003b1; (TNF-&#x003b1;), and interleukin 6 (IL-6) production was tested by Griess and ELISA techniques. Antioxidant activity was measured by ABTS and DPPH scavenging assays.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The extracts with the best antimicrobial activities were carbonized <italic>Tectona grandis</italic> showing against <italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic>, <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, Methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) and <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>. The ethanol extract of <italic>Dracaena loureiroi</italic> wood exhibited the highest NO and IL-6 inhibitory activity with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 9.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.81 and 12.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.30&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL, respectively. The ethanol extract of <italic>Pogostemon cablin</italic> had the highest TNF-&#x003b1; inhibitory with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 10.68&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL. In anti-free radical testing, the ethanol extract of <italic>D. loureiroi</italic> displayed high antioxidant activity by both ABTS and DPPH assays.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">The ethanol extracts from carbonized <italic>T. grandis</italic> and Mahanintangtong showed good antimicrobial activity, especially against <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>, and good anti-inflammatory activity. These findings are relevant to the pathogenesis of pharyngitis and justify additional studies to see if Mahanintangtong could have clinical utility.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic></kwd><kwd>Nitric oxide (NO)</kwd><kwd>Tumor necrosis factor &#x003b1; (TNF-&#x003b1;)</kwd><kwd>Interleukin 6 (IL-6)</kwd><kwd>Thailand National List of essential medicines</kwd><kwd>Pharyngitis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100005790</institution-id><institution>Thammasat University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Thammasat University research grants [grant numbers 2/38/2559, 2016], and Faculty of Medicine, Thammasat University [grant numbers 2-13/2562, 2019]</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Dechayont</surname><given-names>Bhanuz</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par27">Pharyngitis is inflammation of the pharynx that is most often caused by viruses but may also be caused by bacteria, notably, <italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic> (group A Streptococcus [GAS]) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. One of the first defenses against infection is a host-mounted inflammatory response involving a variety of cytokines and chemokines which both trigger and/or enhance the specific inflammatory response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p id="Par28">Inflammation is a complex process that is coordinated by cytokines and immune signalling molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The concept of the immune signalling which induces fever during infection and inflammation has been widely accepted. The well-identified pathways of inflammation are either activated by lipopolysaccharide (LPS) or by key cytokines such as IL-6, IL-1&#x003b2;, TNF-&#x003b1; and others. Other putative endogenous mediators like lipocortin-1 are also involved in fever [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par29">LPS and proinflammatory cytokines can catalyse the formation of small signalling molecules such as nitric oxide (NO), which plays a key role in the pathogenesis of inflammation. NO has an anti-inflammatory effect under normal physiological conditions but it is a pro-inflammatory mediator that induces inflammation due to its over production in acute inflammatory states and physiological stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Therefore, finding the inhibitors which are able to block inflammatory cytokines are important for reducing the inflammatory response.</p><p id="Par30">For treating common bacterial infections like a streptococcal sore throat, penicillin is commonly recommended to decrease symptoms and to prevent subsequent complications and the spread of infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. However, drug side effects and microbial resistance are two reasons for the renewed interest in traditional herbal medicines. The use of plant-based formulations is potentially a viable option for reducing the side effects associated with conventional antibiotic treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] as well as increase the number of compounds that could be used for treating infections or acting synergistically with current therapies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par31">Thailand&#x02019;s National List of Essential Medicines (NLEM), a knowledge repository of Thai traditional herbal medicine, includes information on single herbs and herbal combinations used for treating pharyngitis. The herbal combinations are typically composed of herbs with complimentary properties. Mahanintangtong is a herbal combination described in NLEM for treating non-specific fevers as well as pharyngitis and chickenpox. The formula consists of several herbal plants: carbonized seeds of <italic>Entada rheedii</italic> Spreng, carbonized seeds of <italic>Spondias pinnata</italic> (L.f.) Kurz, carbonized pulp of <italic>Sapindus rarak</italic> DC, carbonized wood of <italic>Calamus caesius</italic> Blume, carbonized wood of <italic>Tectona grandis</italic> L.f., <italic>Dracaena loureiroi</italic> Gagnep, <italic>Myristica fragrans</italic> Houtt, and the leaves of <italic>Pogostemon cablin</italic> (Blanco) Benth, <italic>Tiliacora triandra</italic> (Colebr.), Diels, Chinese ink (Inkstick), and Shell of <italic>Monetaria moneta</italic> (Money cowry) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p><p id="Par32">Previous phytochemical and pharmacological studies have shown that plant extracts have anti-inflammatory properties but no specific work has been done on the Mahanintangtong formula. Therefore, we tested extracts from Mahanintangtong for antibacterial, anti-inflammatory and antioxidant properties.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Chemicals and reagents</title><p id="Par33">All the chemicals and reagents used were of analytical grade. 2, 2&#x02013;Diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH), and butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) were purchased from Fluka, Germany. Acetic acid was purchased from Merck, Germany. 2,2&#x02032;-Azino-bis (3-ethylbenzo-thiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) diammonium salt, 6-hydroxy-2,5,7,8-tetramethylchroman-2-carboxylic acid, potassium persulfate, dimethyl sulfoxide, lipopolysaccharide from <italic>E.coli</italic> O55:B5 (LPS), phosphoric acid, N-(1-Naphthyl) ethylenediamine dihydrochloride, sulfanilamide,3-(4,5-Dimethyl-2-thiazolyl)-2,5-dipheyl-2H-tetrazolium bromide or thiazolyl blue tetrazolium bromide (MTT) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich, USA. Dulbecco&#x02019;s modified eagle medium (DMEM), Foetal bovine serum (FBS), Trypan blue stain 0.4% and Trypsin-EDTA were obtained from Gibco, USA. Hydrochloric acid and isopropanol were obtained from RCI Labscan, Thailand; Phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) was provided by Biochrom, Germany and mouse TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-6 ELISA kits were purchased from ImmunoTools, Germany.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Plant material and preparation of extracts</title><p id="Par34">The plant materials were purchased from a licensed traditional medicine drug store, Charoensuk Osod in Nakorn Pathom, Thailand. The herbal materials were identified and authenticated by Department of Applied Thai Traditional Medicine, Thammasat University. A voucher specimen is kept at the Herbarium of the Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Prince of Songkla University, Thailand. A voucher specimen is shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Then the plant materials were crushed in to small pieces for the extraction process. The formula was prepared from 11 ingredients; its constituents are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Yields (%w/w), plant name, part of plant used, voucher specimen and % in formulation of different components of the Mahanintangtong formula and its constituent herbs </p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Plant name</th><th>Family</th><th>Part used</th><th>Voucher specimen</th><th>Formulation (%wt)</th><th>Extracts type</th><th>% Yield</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Entada rheedii</italic> Spreng. (carbonized)</td><td rowspan="2">Fabaceae</td><td rowspan="2">Seed</td><td rowspan="2">SKP 098/115 05 18 01</td><td rowspan="2">9.71</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>3.96</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>9.46</td></tr><tr><td char="&#x000d7;" align="char" rowspan="2"><italic>Spondias pinnata</italic> (L.f.) Kurz. (carbonized)</td><td rowspan="2">Anacardiaceae</td><td rowspan="2">Seed</td><td rowspan="2">SKP 009 19 16 01</td><td rowspan="2">9.71</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>6.20</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>1.95</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Sapindus rarak</italic> DC. (carbonized)</td><td rowspan="2">Sapindaceae</td><td rowspan="2">Pulp</td><td rowspan="2">SKP 170 19 05 01</td><td rowspan="2">9.71</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>4.64</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>2.98</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Calamus caesius</italic> Blume. (carbonized)</td><td rowspan="2">Arecaceae</td><td rowspan="2">Wood</td><td rowspan="2">SKP 137 03 03 01</td><td rowspan="2">9.71</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>0.58</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>4.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Tectona grandis</italic> L.f. (carbonized)</td><td rowspan="2">Lamiaceae</td><td rowspan="2">Wood</td><td rowspan="2">SKP 095 20 07 01</td><td rowspan="2">9.71</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>0.84</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>0.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Dracaena loureiroi</italic> Gagnep.</td><td rowspan="2">Asparagaceae</td><td rowspan="2">Wood</td><td rowspan="2">SKP 065 04 12 01</td><td rowspan="2">9.71</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>17.79</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>1.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Myristica fragrans</italic> Houtt.</td><td rowspan="2">Myristicaceae</td><td rowspan="2">Wood</td><td rowspan="2">SKP 121 13 06 01</td><td rowspan="2">9.71</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>3.94</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>2.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Pogostemon cablin</italic> (Blanco) Benth.</td><td rowspan="2">Lamiaceae</td><td rowspan="2">Leaves</td><td rowspan="2">SKP 095 16 03 01</td><td rowspan="2">9.71</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>7.47</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>12.70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Tiliacora triandra</italic> Diels</td><td rowspan="2">Menispermaceae</td><td rowspan="2">Leaves</td><td rowspan="2">SKP 114 20 20 01</td><td rowspan="2">9.71</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>3.94</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>6.54</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Chinese ink</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="2">9.71</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>N/A</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>2.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><p><italic>Monetaria moneta</italic></p><p>(Money cowry)</p></td><td rowspan="2">Cypraeidae</td><td rowspan="2">Shell</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="2">2.90</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>N/A</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>0.40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Mahanintangtong formula</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>4.98</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>4.12</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>N/A</italic> Not Applicable</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par35">Seeds of <italic>Entada rheedii</italic> and <italic>Spondias pinnata</italic>, pulp of <italic>Sapindus rarak,</italic> wood of <italic>Calamus caesius</italic> and <italic>Tectona grandis</italic> were carbonized following the Thai Traditional method: heated at 300&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in clay pot for 24&#x02009;h., and, then, as charcoal, for a further 6&#x02009;h, before cooling at room temperature.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Extraction method</title><sec id="Sec6"><title>Maceration method</title><p id="Par36">This followed the method of Dechayont et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. The Mahanintangtong formula and its individual herb components were dried in an oven at 50&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The dried materials (50&#x02009;g) were then extracted three times with 95% ethanol (EtOH) at room temperature (72&#x02009;h) and filtered through Whatman No. 1 filter paper. The extracts were evaporated in a rotary evaporator and vacuum to dryness to give the crude ethanol extract.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Decoction method</title><p id="Par37">Decoction was performed according to the method of Thai traditional medicine. The Mahanintangtong formula and the individual herbs (30&#x02009;g) were boiled in distilled water for 15&#x02009;min, cooled and then reboiled twice more. The aqueous mix was filtered through Whatman No. 1 filter paper and dried using a lyophilizer to give the crude water extract.</p><p id="Par38">The ethanol and water extract yields were calculated as w/w and expressed as percentages (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) and were stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Antimicrobial assay</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Microbial strains</title><p id="Par39">Cultures of the following microorganisms were used in the study: <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 25923; methicillin resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) ATCC 20651, <italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic> ATCC 19615, <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATCC 9097 and <italic>Candida albicans</italic> ATCC 90028.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Disc diffusion method</title><p id="Par40">The agar disc diffusion method was used to determine the antimicrobial activities of the extract, as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Paper discs (6&#x02009;mm diameter) were added to the extracts (conc. 5&#x02009;mg/disc for ethanol extract, and conc. 1&#x02009;mg/disc for water extract). The inoculum density was adjusted to 0.5 of the McFarland standard. Air-dried discs were placed on inoculated Mueller-Hinton agar (MHA) for <italic>S. aureus</italic>, MRSA and <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, MHA with 5% sheep blood for <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> and Sabouraud Dextrose agar (SDA) for <italic>C. albicans</italic>. Positive controls were amoxicillin, ampicillin, gentamicin and vancomycin, each at a concentration of 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/disc. These plates were incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x02009;h for bacteria and at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 48&#x02009;h for <italic>C. albicans</italic>. The zone of inhibition was calculated by measuring the diameter of the inhibition zone. The readings were taken in three different fixed directions in all 3 replicates and the mean value was tabulated.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Determination of the minimal inhibitory concentration <italic>(</italic>MIC<italic>)</italic></title><p id="Par41">The minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) of an antimicrobial agent is the lowest concentration of the antimicrobial agent that inhibits a given bacterial isolate from multiplying and producing visible growth in the test system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Isolated colonies were prepared from 18 to 24&#x02009;h cultures of <italic>S. aureus</italic>, MRSA, <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> and from 36 to 48&#x02009;h cultures of <italic>C. albicans</italic> on an agar plate. Then the inoculum was adjusted with Mueller-Hinton broth (MHB) medium to 0.5 McFarland standard using a densitometer and the cultures were diluted 200 - fold. In sterile 96 - well microtiter plates, 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of a plant extract was diluted 2-fold with broth (10 concentrations). Triplicate samples were used for each test concentration. After incubation for 16&#x02013;18&#x02009;h of <italic>S. aureus</italic>, MRSA, <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> and for 36&#x02013;48&#x02009;h cultures of <italic>C. albicans</italic> at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of resazurin solution was added in each well and incubated for 2&#x02009;h. The lowest concentration value was determined in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Determination of the minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC)</title><p id="Par42">Innocula from the wells that had no visible growth were transferred to the agar plates in quadrants and were incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x02009;h and then examined for bacterial growth. The last quadrant (i.e. with the lowest concentration of plant extract) that showed no growth was taken as the MBC. Values were recorded as mg/ml and all experiments were performed in triplicate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><sec id="Sec13"><title>In vitro assay for anti-inflammatory assay</title></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Cell line</title><p id="Par43">The inhibitory effects of nitric oxide (NO), TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-6 production were evaluated using murine macrophage like RAW 264.7 cells. The RAW 264.7 cell line was cultured in DMEM medium supplemented with 10% heated fetal bovine serum and 50&#x02009;IU/mL penicillin and 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL streptomycin. The cells were detached with trypsin-EDTA and diluted to a suspension in fresh medium.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Assay for NO inhibitory effect</title><p id="Par44">The evaluation of the NO inhibitory activity was performed in a manner similar to that described for cell viability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The cells were seeded at a density of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> cells/well in 96-well microplates and incubated to adhere for 24&#x02009;h at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in a humidified atmosphere containing 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. After that the medium was replaced with fresh medium containing a final concentration at 5&#x02009;ng/mL of LPS. The adherent cells were treated with test samples at six concentrations to give a total volume of 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;L/well and incubated for 24&#x02009;h. Twenty-four hours later, the presence of nitrite was determined in cell culture media using Griess reagent at 570&#x02009;nm. Inhibition (%) was calculated using the following equation and the IC<sub>50</sub> value was calculated graphically using GraphPad 4.0 software in triplicate (Prism, USA).
<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{The}\%\mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{inhibition}=\left(\mathrm{Abs}.\mathrm{Control}-\mathrm{Abs}.\mathrm{Sample}\right)/\mathrm{Abs}.\mathrm{Control}\times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mtext>The</mml:mtext><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mtext>of inhibition</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Abs</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Control</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>Abs</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Sample</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>Abs</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Control</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2021_3274_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-6 inhibitory effect in RAW264.7 cells by ELISA</title><p id="Par45">RAW 264.7 cells were incubated for 24&#x02009;h with 5&#x02009;ng/mL of LPS and various concentrations of extracts. After 24&#x02009;h, supernatants were tested for the production of TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-6 quantified using an ELISA kit (ImmunoTools), following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions; the optical density (OD) at 450&#x02009;nm was determined on a plate reader [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The experiment compared potential with andrographolide as positive control which is a major active compound from the <italic>Andrographis paniculata</italic> plant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Assay for cytotoxicity &#x02013; MTT assay</title><p id="Par46">The cell viability of test sample was performed using the 3-(4,5-dimethyl-2-thiazolyl)-2,5-diphenyl-2H-tetrazolium bromide (MTT) colorimetric method. The RAW 264.7 macrophages were cultured in 96-well plates and allowed to grow at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 24&#x02009;h. Subsequently, the cells were tested with samples at six concentrations and, after 48&#x02009;h, MTT solution (5&#x02009;mg/mL of MTT in PBS) was added to the wells. Following 4&#x02009;h of incubation, the medium was removed and 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of isopropanol containing 0.04&#x02009;M HCl was added to dissolve the formazan production in the cells. The OD of formazan solution was measured with a microplate reader at 570&#x02009;nm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The test simples were considered to be cytotoxic when the OD of the sample-treated group was less than 70% of that in the control (vehicle-treated) group. All determinations were carried out in triplicate. The percentage survival of the cell growth at each extract is calculated as:
<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{The}\%\mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{Survival}=\left(\mathrm{Abs}.\mathrm{Sample}/\mathrm{Abs}.\mathrm{Control}\right)\times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mtext>The</mml:mtext><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mtext>of Survival</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Abs</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Sample</mml:mtext><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>Abs</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Control</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2021_3274_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Antioxidant activity</title><sec id="Sec19"><title>DPPH radical scavenging assay</title><p id="Par47">A stock solution of DPPH solution in absolute EtOH (6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;5</sup>&#x02009;M) was freshly prepared and protected from light [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The herb extracts were prepared in a serial dilution (5 concentrations). The extracts 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;L were individually added and mixed with an equal volume of DPPH solution in 96-well microplates and maintained in the dark at room temperature for 30&#x02009;min. The absorbance was measured at 520&#x02009;nm. The scavenging activity was calculated as a percentage inhibition in the formula (<xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="">3</xref>) below:
<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{The}\%\mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{inhibition}=\left(\mathrm{Abs}.\mathrm{Control}\hbox{-} \mathrm{Abs}.\mathrm{Sample}\right)/\mathrm{Abs}.\mathrm{Control}\times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mtext>The</mml:mtext><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mtext>of inhibition</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Abs</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Control</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02010;</mml:mo><mml:mi>Abs</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Sample</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>Abs</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Control</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2021_3274_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par48">The IC<sub>50</sub> was calculated from a dose-response curve using GraphPad 4.03 software.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>ABTS radical cation decolorization assay</title><p id="Par49">The ABTS reagent was prepared by mixing ABTS 7&#x02009;mM concentration with 2.45&#x02009;mM potassium persulfate in deionized water and left in the dark at room temperature for 12&#x02013;16&#x02009;h [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The mixture reagent was diluted with deionized water to give an absorbance of 0.700&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.020 at 734&#x02009;nm. Serial dilutions of the herbal extracts were made in absolute EtOH for the ethanol extracts and distilled water for the aqueous extracts. ABTS reagent (180&#x02009;&#x003bc;L) was mixed with 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of sample solution at five concentrations and the absorbance was measured after exactly 6&#x02009;min at 734&#x02009;nm in 96-well microplates to determine the scavenging activity. All determinations were carried out in triplicate. The scavenging activity was calculated as a percentage inhibition in the formula (<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref>) below.
<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{The}\ \mathrm{Percentage}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{inhibition}=\left(\mathrm{Abs}.\mathrm{Control}-\mathrm{Abs}.\mathrm{Sample}\right)/\mathrm{Abs}.\mathrm{Control}\times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8" display="block"><mml:mtext>The Percentage of inhibition</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Abs</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Control</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>Abs</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Sample</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>Abs</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Control</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2021_3274_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par50">The IC<sub>50</sub> was calculated from a dose-response curve using GraphPad 4.03 software.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par51">All the experiments were conducted in triplicate. Results are expressed as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error of the mean.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec23"><title>Preparation of extracts</title><p id="Par52">The yield percentages of Mahanintangtong formula and its 11 components are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The maximal extract yield by maceration was the wood of <italic>D. loureiroi</italic> (17.79%) whilst the highest yield by decoction was the leaves of <italic>P. cablin</italic> (12.70%).</p><sec id="Sec24"><title>Antimicrobial assay</title><p id="Par53">The antimicrobial activities of ethanol and water extracts were tested on all the ATCC bacteria and <italic>C. albicans</italic> using the disc diffusion assay, which was assessed by the presence and absence of inhibition zones. The ethanol and water extracts were tested at 5 and 1&#x02009;mg/disc, respectively. In the control tests, DMSO was shown to have no inhibitory effect on any of the bacteria tested. The positive controls were amoxicillin, vancomycin, ampicillin and gentamicin. Based on inhibition zone test results, the ethanol extract of <italic>T. grandis</italic> (carbonized), <italic>S. pinnata</italic> (carbonized), and Mahanintangtong formula produced moderate activity against <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>, <italic>S. aureus</italic> and MRSA (inhibition zone &#x0003e;&#x02009;10&#x02009;mm, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) while all the extracts showed no significant inhibition zones against <italic>C. albicans</italic>.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Antimicrobial activity against five microorganisms of Mahanintangtong formula and its constituent herbs (<italic>n</italic> = 3)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Plant name</th><th rowspan="2">Extracts type</th><th colspan="5">Diameter of inhibition zone (mm.)<sup>*</sup>, MIC (&#x003bc;g/mL)<sup>**</sup>, MBC (&#x003bc;g/mL)<sup>***</sup></th></tr><tr><th><italic>S. pyogenes</italic></th><th><italic>S. aureus</italic></th><th>MRSA</th><th><italic>P. aeruginosa</italic></th><th><italic>C. albicans</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Entada rheedii</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td><p>11.00&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.039<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.039<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>11.33&#x000b1;0.58<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>11.21&#x000b1;1.73<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>1.25<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>1.25<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Spondias pinnata</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td><p>12.67&#x000b1;2.52,</p><p>0.039,</p><p>0.039<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>11.33&#x000b1;0.58,</p><p>0.625,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>12.00&#x000b1;0.00,</p><p>0.625,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>8.33&#x000b1;0.58,</p><p>&#x0003e;5,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0,</p><p>&#x0003e;5,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Sapindus rarak</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td><p>10.33&#x000b1;1.52<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.039<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.039<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>1.25<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>1.25<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>1.25<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Calamus caesius</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.3125<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Tectona grandis</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td><p>13.33&#x000b1;0.58<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.078<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.078<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>13.00+0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>1.25<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>14.33&#x000b1;0.58<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>8.00&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>10.33&#x000b1;1.53<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Dracaena loureiroi</italic></td><td>Ethanol</td><td><p>12.33&#x000b1;0.58<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.156<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.156<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>11.00&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>10.33&#x000b1;0.58<sup>*</sup>, 0.3125<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>1.25<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Myristica fragrans</italic></td><td>Ethanol</td><td><p>10.33&#x000b1;1.15<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.156<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>1.25<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Pogostemon cablin</italic></td><td>Ethanol</td><td><p>10.33&#x000b1;1.15<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.039<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.039<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>10.33&#x000b1;2.52<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>11.67&#x000b1;1.53<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>8.33&#x000b1;1.53<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>1.25<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>1.25<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Tiliacora triandra</italic></td><td>Ethanol</td><td><p>8.33&#x000b1;0.58<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.078<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.078<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>8&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>7&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>1.25<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Chinese ink (Inkstick)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Monetaria moneta</italic> (Money cowry)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Mahanintangtong formula</td><td>Ethanol</td><td><p>10&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.078<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>10&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>10&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.625<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>2.5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>0<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;5<sup>***</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td>Amoxicillin</td><td>NT</td><td><p>35.00&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.016<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.0256<sup>***</sup></p></td><td>NT</td><td>NT</td><td>NT</td><td>NT</td></tr><tr><td>Ampicillin</td><td>NT</td><td>NT</td><td><p>43.00&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.25<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>1.56<sup>***</sup></p></td><td>NT</td><td>NT</td><td>NT</td></tr><tr><td>Gentamicin</td><td>NT</td><td>NT</td><td><p>15.00&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.195<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.195<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>10.00&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;200<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>&#x0003e;200<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>12.00&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.195<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.39<sup>***</sup></p></td><td>NT</td></tr><tr><td>Vancomycin</td><td>NT</td><td><p>15.00&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.39<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>0.39<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>45.00&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.003<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>1.92<sup>***</sup></p></td><td><p>16.00&#x000b1;0.00<sup>*</sup>,</p><p>0.78<sup>**</sup>,</p><p>1.56<sup>***</sup></p></td><td>NT</td><td>NT</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Means of three measurements + SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Amoxicillin, Ampicillin, Gentamicin and Vancomycin were tested at 10 &#x003bc;g/disc. <italic>NT</italic> Not Test, <italic>N/A</italic> Not Applicab</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par54">The MIC and MBC were measured to assess the potency of Mahanintangtong formula and its component extracts using the microdilution assay. These methods confirmed the results obtained by the disc diffusion method. The ethanol extracts were the most active: <italic>E. rheedii</italic> (carbonized), <italic>S. pinnata</italic> (carbonized), <italic>S. rarak</italic> (carbonized) and <italic>P. cablin</italic> extracts inhibited <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> with a MIC and MBC of 0.039&#x02009;mg/mL. All the ethanol and water extracts except Chinese ink and money cowry showed activity against <italic>S. aureus</italic> with MICs and MBCs of 0.625&#x02013;2.5&#x02009;mg/mL, respectively. Although the ethanol extract of <italic>C. caesius</italic> was potent against <italic>S. aureus</italic>, it did not inhibit MRSA. The highest MIC against MRSA was 0.3125&#x02009;mg/mL from ethanol extract of <italic>D. loureiri</italic>. The ethanol extract of <italic>E. rheedii</italic> (carbonized), <italic>T. grandis</italic> (carbonized), <italic>P. cablin</italic> and Mahanintangtong formula (herbal mix) showed the highest MIC and MBC values of 0.625&#x02009;mg/mL against <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. None of the ethanol extracts had inhibitory activity against <italic>C. albicans</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Anti-inflammatory assay</title><p id="Par55">The ethanol extract of <italic>D. loureiroi</italic> exhibited highest NO inhibitory activity with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 9.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.81&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL. The IC<sub>50</sub> for Mahanintangtong formula was higher at 28.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.64&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL.</p><p id="Par56">The ethanol extract of <italic>P. cablin</italic> had the highest inhibitory activity against TNF-&#x003b1; production with an IC<sub>50</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL; values for the wood of <italic>M. fragrans</italic> and carbonized wood of <italic>T. grandis</italic> were 14.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.12&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL and 21.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.40&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL, respectively. IL-6 inhibition was dose-dependent in the range of 1&#x02013;100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL of ethanol extract. <italic>D. loureiroi</italic> had the greatest inhibitory effect with an IC<sub>50</sub> 12.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.30&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Inhibition was less for the aqueous extracts.
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Anti-inflammatory activity by inhibitory effects on NO, TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-6 production in RAW264.7 cells of the Mahanintangtong formula and its constituent herbs (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Plant name</th><th rowspan="2">Extracts type</th><th colspan="3">IC<sub><bold>50</bold></sub>&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM (&#x003bc;g/ml)</th><th>Cytotoxic activity</th></tr><tr><th>NO</th><th>TNF-&#x003b1;</th><th>IL-6</th><th>% Survival (conc. 100 &#x003bc;g/mL)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Entada rheedii</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>79.74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.45</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>73.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Spondias pinnata</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>102.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.72</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>88.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Sapindus rarak</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>66.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.38</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>71.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.09 (conc. 70&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL)</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>95.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Calamus caesius</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>93.97&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.99</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>107.91&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Tectona grandis</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>52.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.58</td><td>21.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.40</td><td>49.38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.44</td><td>97.57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.36</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>97.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Dracaena loureiroi</italic></td><td>Ethanol</td><td>9.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.81</td><td>55.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.47</td><td>12.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.30</td><td>92.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.39</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>98.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Myristica fragrans</italic></td><td>Ethanol</td><td>35.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.22</td><td>14.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.12</td><td>55.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.50</td><td>96.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.68 (conc. 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL)</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>97.97&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Pogostemon cablin</italic></td><td>Ethanol</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>10.68&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td>17.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.78</td><td>95.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.80</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>94.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.43</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Tiliacora triandra</italic></td><td>Ethanol</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>82.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.89</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>96.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;23.11</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>92.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.54</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Chinese ink (Inkstick)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>90.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.62</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Monetaria moneta</italic> (Money cowry)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>93.98&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Mahanintangtong formula</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>28.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.64</td><td>33.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.22</td><td>17.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.65</td><td>88.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.56</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>98.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.74</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Andrographolide</td><td>1.797&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.41</td><td>5.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.48</td><td>9.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.61</td><td>91.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.87</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Means of three measurements &#x000b1; SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). % Survival was tested at 100, 70 or 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL after 24&#x02009;h incubation in RAW 264.7 cells</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Cytotoxicity</title><p id="Par57">At concentrations of 50 and 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL of ethanol and water extracts, there was no effect on cell viability. At all concentrations tested, there was more than 70% of cell viability.</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Antioxidant assay</title><p id="Par58">Several assays have been frequently used to estimate antioxidant activity of crude plant extracts. The most used assays are ABTS and DPPH because they both involve H- or electron-donation to the antioxidant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Moreover, both have excellent stability under certain conditions. High ABTS scavenging activity was seen with the ethanol and water extracts of <italic>D. loureiroi</italic> and the ethanol extract of <italic>T. grandis</italic> as well as the water extract of <italic>S. pinnata</italic> (carbonized) and <italic>E. rheedii</italic> (carbonized). IC<sub>50s</sub> ranged from 8 to 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL compared to the positive controls: Trolox&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL and BHT&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>.). In the DPPH assay, the ethanol extract of <italic>S. pinnata</italic> (carbonized) showed the highest activity with IC<sub>50</sub> of 5.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.90&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL compared to 14.87&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.94 (BHT) and 5.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.20 (Trolox, Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Antioxidant activity of the Mahanintangtong formula and its constituent herbs (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Plant name</th><th rowspan="2">Extracts type</th><th colspan="2">IC<sub><bold>50</bold></sub>&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM (&#x003bc;g/ml)</th></tr><tr><th>ABTS radical-scavenging assay</th><th>DPPH radical-scavenging assay</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Entada rheedii</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>22.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.86</td><td>21.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.72</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>10.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.19</td><td>37.34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.54</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Spondias pinnata</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>14.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.49</td><td>5.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.90</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>10.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.05</td><td>28.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Sapindus rarak</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>94.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.71</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Calamus caesius</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>54.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.75</td><td>58.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.85</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>26.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.16</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Tectona grandis</italic> (carbonized)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>10.13&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.77</td><td>18.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.65</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>24.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.20</td><td>30.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.79</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Dracaena loureiroi</italic></td><td>Ethanol</td><td>8.38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.95</td><td>16.95&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.43</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>10.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.23</td><td>19.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Myristica fragrans</italic></td><td>Ethanol</td><td>49.69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.02</td><td>19.76&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.98</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>24.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.13</td><td>30.99&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Pogostemon cablin</italic></td><td>Ethanol</td><td>63.50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.88</td><td>17.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.15</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>35.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.96</td><td>18.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.72</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Tiliacora triandra</italic></td><td>Ethanol</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>65.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.04</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>79.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.12</td><td>21.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Chinese ink (Inkstick)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Monetaria moneta</italic> (Money cowry)</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>N/A</td><td>N/A</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Mahanintangtong formula</td><td>Ethanol</td><td>14.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.240</td><td>15.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.01</td></tr><tr><td>Water</td><td>34.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.47</td><td>22.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.33</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">BHT</td><td>5.66&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26</td><td>14.87&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.94</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Trolox</td><td>4.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td><td>5.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.20</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Means of three measurements &#x000b1; SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3); BHT and Trolox were used as a positive control for antioxidant activity</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par59">In this, the first study to examine the properties of Mahanintangtong, we have shown that it possesses good anti-inflammatory activity and good antimicrobial activity, especially against <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>, an important cause of illnesses like pharyngitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par60">In Thai traditional medicine, symptoms and diseases are thought to be due to an imbalance of the hot and cold elements in body and the carbonized herbs of the Mahanintangtong formula are used to reduce Pitta (fire element) for illnesses like aphthous stomatitis, measles, chicken pox in children up to 12&#x02009;years old [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Research can substantiate the scientific bases for using traditional medicines and bring to light important compounds that could, with future development, be used in patients. This was the rationale of our study in which we used 6 common ingredients and 5 carbonized herbs i.e. <italic>E. rheedii</italic>, <italic>S. pinnata</italic>, <italic>S. rarak</italic>, <italic>C. caesius</italic>, and <italic>T. grandis</italic>.</p><p id="Par61">The extraction methods and solvents used are important in the processing of the bioactive constituents because plants contain a complex blend of phytochemicals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Decoction and 95% EtOH maceration are standard methods and we used a modification of the Thai traditional maceration method. Extract yields depend on pharmacognosy of the different parts of the plants used. The water extracts from the leaves were double those of the ethanol extracts whereas most of the EtOH extracts from wood were higher than the water extracts. For the seeds, the water extract of carbonized <italic>E. rheedii</italic> and <italic>S. pinnata</italic> seeds was higher and lower than the alcohol extracts, respectively. However, yields of water and ethanol extracts of Mahanintangtong formula were similar.</p><p id="Par62">The ethanol extracts of all herbs and Mahanintangtong had greater antibacterial activity for the gram-positive (+) and gram-negative (&#x02212;) bacteria compared to the water extracts, especially against <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>; the carbonized ethanol extracts had the highest activity. Carbonization is done because it is believed to result in better tolerability but might reduce their efficacy. Never the less, our carbonized ethanol extract retained high anti streptococcal activity. Moreover, the carbonized ethanol extracts of <italic>E. rheedii</italic>, <italic>S. pinnata</italic>, <italic>S. rarak</italic> and <italic>T. grandis</italic> had greater activity against the Gram-positive bacteria compared to <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. Similar results have been reported by Sameh et al., 2019 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] who reported that the essential oil from <italic>S. pinnata</italic> was highly active against MRSA and <italic>S. aureus</italic>. This oil contains sesquiterpenes, &#x003b2;-caryophyllene, oxygenated monoterpenes and &#x003b1;-terpineol are the main constituent and it is noteworthy that &#x003b2;-caryophyllene has been shown to have potent activity against <italic>S. aureus</italic>, <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> with MICs of 3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4 and 7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2&#x02009;&#x003bc;M [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]; &#x003b1;-terpineol also has anti-<italic>S. pyogenes</italic> activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. By contrast, Bitchagno et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] demonstrated that the ethanol extract from the fruit of <italic>T. grandis</italic> showed good activity against the Gram-negative bacteria, especially <italic>E. coli</italic>.</p><p id="Par63">The reduced anti Gram-negative activity in our study is probably due to their hydrophilic cell wall structure which is essentially made up of LPS that is impermeable to hydrophobic oils and so prevents accumulation in their cell membranes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. <italic>C. albicans</italic> was resistant to all extracts and this may be related to the its ability to produce extracellular enzymes that degrade and metabolize substrates on its surface. Therefore, the presence of plant extracts are a source of food to the fungi rather than inhibiting their growth but we also used a low concentration of plant extract which may part explain poor inhibition of <italic>C. albicans</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p><p id="Par64">The ethanol extract of Mahanintangtong formula showed good anti-inflammatory activity by inhibiting the release of NO, TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-6 and supports its use by in Thai traditional medicine. Moreover, previous research demonstrates the anti-inflammatory effect of the roots of <italic>P. cablin</italic>, a key component of Mahanintangtong, by inhibiting TNF-&#x003b1;, IL-1&#x003b2; and IL-6 in rats with experimentally-induced palmar oedema [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The aerial parts of <italic>P. cablin</italic> also inhibited TNF-&#x003b1; in a human promonocytic cell line (U937 cell) and a human colonic adenocarcinoma cell line (HT-29 cells) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. A major component of patchouli oil from <italic>P. cablin</italic> is &#x003b2;-patchoulene that inhibits pro-inflammatory cytokines such as TNF-&#x003b1;, IL-1&#x003b2;, IL6, PGE2 and NO; it also suppresses malondialdehyde, a marker of oxidant stress, and myeloperoxidase, a key enzyme in the respiratory burst of neutrophils [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Patchoulene epoxide which isolated from patchouli oil also inhibits TNF-&#x003b1;, IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-6, PGE2 and NO and downregulates mRNA expression of COX-2 and inducible nitric oxide synthetase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Another important component, the ethanol extract from the bark of <italic>T. grandis</italic>, also inhibits TNF-&#x003b1; in RAW 264.7 cells and immortalized mouse splenic dendritic cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Phytochemicals present in <italic>T. grandis</italic> include naphthoquinone, anthraquinone, monoterpene, diterpene, triterpene, apocarotenoid, phenolic compounds and flavonoids, steroids/saponins, phenylpropanoids and fatty esters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Lapachol, a naphthoquinone, has anti-inflammatory properties in a rat model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] as do the anthraquinones rubiadin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] and obtusifolin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Other research has shown that the methanol extract of <italic>D. loureiroi</italic> has antipyretic properties using the brewer&#x02019;s yeast induced fever method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Taken together, these data show clearly that different key constituents of Mahanintangtong formula possess anti-inflammatory properties and support the use of Mahanintangtong formula in Thai traditional medicine.</p><p id="Par65">We used the DPPH and ABTS<sup>+</sup> assays to assess antioxidant activity of our extracts. Although they share the same mechanism of antioxidant action i.e. electron transfer, DPPH radicals are more suitable for lipophilic antioxidants while ABTS+ radicals can react with both hydrophilic and lipophilic antioxidants. We demonstrated the antioxidant activities of <italic>E. rheedii</italic>, <italic>S. pinnata</italic>, <italic>T. grandis</italic> and <italic>D. loureiroi</italic>, consistent with previous research. Rheediinosides A and B from <italic>E. rheedii</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] and the ethanol extract of <italic>D. loureiroi</italic> have been shown to possess potent antioxidant activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] whilst <italic>S. pinnata</italic> decreased significantly the levels of antioxidant enzymes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] and showed similar antioxidant activity as in our study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p id="Par66">In 1999, the list of herbal medicine in the NLEM was announced. Mahanintangtong is one of herbal formulas on the list. However, there are no scientific reports on the formula. The present study is the first one to emphasize the antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory and antioxidant activities of Mahanintangtong formula extract. We focused on in-vitro pharmacological activity against sore throat. Our findings suggest that the ethanol of Mahanintangtong formula extract could be used to decrease inflammation, and it also showed anti-bactericidal action, especially <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>. This research supports Thai traditional medicine wisdom, and it can promote the use of Mahanintangtong in hospitals and primary health care units. However, both the quality and quantity of herbal raw materials are one of the main challenges for a Thai herbal product industry. This is in contrast with Western medicine that uses chemical drugs. Thus, the variation between different production batches is limited. In our next research, we would like to study the quality control of the chemical constituents of Mahanintangtong formula. Also, the evidence-based in vivo and clinical practice should be studied so that it is possible that the Mahanintangtong will be developed in biofilm formation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par67">This study has brought to light the antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory and antioxidant activities of the Mahanintangtong formula and its constituent herbs. The Mahanintangtong ethanol extract had significant anti <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> activity and significant anti-inflammatory activity that was due to <italic>D. loureiroi</italic>. These results support the use of Mahanintangtong in Thai traditional medicine for minor febrile illnesses and additional development work for possible future clinical use outside of traditional medicine.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ABTS</term><def><p id="Par5">2,2&#x02032;-Azino-bis (3-ethylbenzo-thiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) diammonium salt</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BHT</term><def><p id="Par6">Butylated hydroxytoluene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMEM</term><def><p id="Par7">Dulbecco&#x02019;s modified eagle medium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMSO</term><def><p id="Par8">Dimethylsulfoxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DPPH</term><def><p id="Par9">2, 2 &#x02013;Diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EtOH</term><def><p id="Par10">Ethanol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FBS</term><def><p id="Par11">Fetal bovine serum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HCl</term><def><p id="Par12">Hydrochloric acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IL-6</term><def><p id="Par13">Interleukin 6</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LPS</term><def><p id="Par14">Lipopolysaccharide from <italic>E. coli</italic> O55:B5</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MBC</term><def><p id="Par15">Minimum bactericidal concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MHA</term><def><p id="Par16">Mueller-Hinton agar</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MHB</term><def><p id="Par17">Mueller-Hinton broth</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MIC</term><def><p id="Par18">Minimum Inhibitory Concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MRSA</term><def><p id="Par19">Methicillin resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MTT</term><def><p id="Par20">Thiazolyl blue tetrazolium bromide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NO</term><def><p id="Par21">Nitric oxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OD</term><def><p id="Par22">Optical density</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PBS</term><def><p id="Par23">Phosphate buffer saline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RAW 264.7</term><def><p id="Par24">Mouse macrophage leukemia-like</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SRB</term><def><p id="Par25">Sulphorhodamine B</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TNF-&#x003b1;</term><def><p id="Par26">Tumor necrosis factor &#x003b1;</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>The authors also thank the Faculty of Medicine, Thammasat University for support and provide laboratory facilities. Also, we thank Dr. Bob Taylor for reviewing the manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>BD conceived and designed most of the experiments. PP and JC performed most of the experiments. KJ carried out the anti-inflammatory activity. OP performed data analysis. BD and TJ analyzed the remaining data and wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by Thammasat University research grants [grant numbers 2/38/2559, 2016] for providing logistic support, and Faculty of Medicine, Thammasat University [grant numbers 2&#x02013;13/2562, 2019] for providing financial support and equipment used for biological assays.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par68">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par69">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par70">The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Banerjee S, Ford C. Clinical decision rules and strategies for the diagnosis of group A streptococcal infection: a review of clinical utility and guidelines. Ottawa: Canadian Agency for Drugs and Technologies in Health; 2018.&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30329249/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30329249/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kellum</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissfeld</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yealy</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinsky</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Krichevsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Delude</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Angus</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the inflammatory cytokine response in pneumonia and sepsis: results of the genetic and inflammatory markers of Sepsis (GenIMS) study</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>167</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>1655</fpage><lpage>1663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.167.15.1655</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17698689?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17698689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A calculated response: control of inflammation by the innate immune system</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2008</year><volume>118</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI34431</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18246191?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18246191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endogenous antipyretics</article-title><source>Clin Chim Acta</source><year>2006</year><volume>371</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cca.2006.02.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16549059?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16549059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanna-Jumma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carraretto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Forni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pathophysiological basis and consequences of fever</article-title><source>Crit Care</source><year>2016</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>200</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13054-016-1375-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27411542?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27411542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Omran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Parvathy</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of nitric oxide in inflammatory diseases</article-title><source>Inflammopharmacology.</source><year>2007</year><volume>15</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10787-007-0013-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18236016?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18236016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Agence Francaise de Securite Sanitaire des Produits de Sante</collab></person-group><article-title>Systemic antibiotic treatment in upper and lower respiratory tract infections: official French guidelines</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1162</fpage><lpage>1178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2003.00798.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14686981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elmolla</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhuri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimization of Fenton process for treatment of amoxicillin, ampicillin and cloxacillin antibiotics in aqueous solution</article-title><source>J Hazard Mater</source><year>2009</year><volume>170</volume><issue>2&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>666</fpage><lpage>672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2009.05.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19515483?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19515483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Amyes</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiology and drug resistance mechanisms of fully resistant pathogens</article-title><source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2004.08.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15451497?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15451497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maia</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant-based insect repellents: a review of their efficacy, development and testing</article-title><source>Malar J</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>S11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-10-S1-S11</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21411012?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21411012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luciano-Montalvo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulogne</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavillan-Suarez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A screening for antimicrobial activities of Caribbean herbal remedies</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>126</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6882-13-126</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23731467?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23731467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The Committee of National List of Essential Drugs</collab></person-group><source>National List of Essential Drugs 2012</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Bangkok</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Ministry of Public Health</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dechayont B, Hansakul P, Itharat A. Comparison of antimicrobial, antioxidant activities and total phenolic content of <italic>Antidesma thwaitesianum</italic> fruit extracts by different methods. J Med Assoc Thai. 2012;95(Suppl 1):S147&#x02013;53.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><source>Antibiotics in laboratory medicine</source><year>1996</year><edition>4</edition><publisher-loc>Baltimore</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative assessment of CDS, CLSI disc diffusion and Etest techniques for antimicrobial susceptibility testing of Neisseria gonorrhoeae: a 6-year study</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e000969</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000969</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22761285?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22761285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elshikh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Funston</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resazurin-based 96-well plate microdilution method for the determination of minimum inhibitory concentration of biosurfactants</article-title><source>Biotechnol Lett</source><year>2016</year><volume>38</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1015</fpage><lpage>1019</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10529-016-2079-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26969604?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26969604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dechayont</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Phuaklee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chunthorng-Orn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Poomirat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Juckmeta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Phumlek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokmued</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouncharoen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory, and antioxidant activities of the wood of <italic>Myristica fragrans</italic> Houtt</article-title><source>Int J Geogr Inf Syst</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dechayont</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Itharat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Phuaklee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chunthorng-Orn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Juckmeta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Prommee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuengchamnong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansakul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activities and phytochemical constituents of <italic>Antidesma thwaitesianum</italic> Mull. Arg. Leaf extracts</article-title><source>J Integr Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2095-4964(17)60334-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28659236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28659236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory effect of <italic>Artemisiae annuae</italic> herba in lipopolysaccharide-stimulated RAW 264.7 cells</article-title><source>Pharmacogn Mag</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><fpage>S588</fpage><lpage>S595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0973-1296.139793</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25298679?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25298679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suthisamphat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dechayont</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Phuaklee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Prajuabjinda</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilaichone</surname><given-names>R-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Itharat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokmued</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Prommee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-<italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>, Anti-Inflammatory, Cytotoxic, and Antioxidant Activities of Mace Extracts from <italic>Myristica fragrans</italic></article-title><source>Evid Based Complement Altern Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>7576818</volume><fpage>6</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Re</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Proteggente</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pannala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice-Evans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity applying an improved ABTS radical cation decolorization assay</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>26</volume><issue>9&#x02013;10</issue><fpage>1231</fpage><lpage>1237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0891-5849(98)00315-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10381194?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10381194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gal</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective ABTS radical-scavenging activity of prenylated flavonoids from <italic>Cudrania tricuspidata</italic></article-title><source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source><year>2006</year><volume>70</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1271/bbb.70.427</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16495659?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16495659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Biesbroek</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Trzcinski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogaert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viral and bacterial interactions in the upper respiratory tract</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e1003057</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003057</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23326226?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23326226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><source>Evidence-based validation of herbal medicine</source><year>2015</year><edition>1</edition><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sasidharan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Saravanan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundram</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoga</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extraction, isolation and characterization of bioactive compounds from plants' extracts</article-title><source>Afr J Tradit Complement Altern Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22238476?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22238476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sameh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Sayed</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Labib</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Singab</surname><given-names>ANB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative metabolic profiling of essential oils from <italic>Spondias pinnata</italic> (Linn. F.) Kurz and characterization of their antibacterial activities</article-title><source>Ind Crop Prod</source><year>2019</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2019.05.060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahham</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabana</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahamed</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezzat</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Majid</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Majid</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The anticancer, antioxidant and antimicrobial properties of the Sesquiterpene beta-Caryophyllene from the essential oil of <italic>Aquilaria crassna</italic></article-title><source>Molecules.</source><year>2015</year><volume>20</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>11808</fpage><lpage>11829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules200711808</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26132906?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26132906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oyedemi</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Okoh</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Mabinya</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirochenva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Afolayan</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The proposed mechanism of bactericidal action of eugenol, &#x003b3;-terpineol and g-terpinene against <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, <italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic>, <italic>Proteus vulgaris</italic> and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Afr J Biotechnol</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1280</fpage><lpage>1286</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bitchagno</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sama Fonkeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopa</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity of ethanolic extract and compounds from fruits of <italic>Tectona grandis</italic> (Verbenaceae)</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>265</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-015-0790-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26245866?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26245866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structures of gram-negative cell walls and their derived membrane vesicles</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1999</year><volume>181</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>4725</fpage><lpage>4733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.181.16.4725-4733.1999</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10438737?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10438737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaffin</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Ribot</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Casanova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gozalbo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell wall and secreted proteins of <italic>Candida albicans</italic>: identification, function, and expression</article-title><source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><year>1998</year><volume>62</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.62.1.130-180.1998</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9529890?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9529890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory property of the ethanol extract of the root and rhizome of <italic>Pogostemon cablin</italic> (Blanco) Benth</article-title><source>Sci World J</source><year>2013</year><volume>2013</volume><fpage>434151</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Xian</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ip</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>QF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>XP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory activity of patchouli alcohol isolated from Pogostemonis Herba in animal models</article-title><source>Fitoterapia.</source><year>2011</year><volume>82</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1295</fpage><lpage>1301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2011.09.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21958968?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21958968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory activity of beta-patchoulene isolated from patchouli oil in mice</article-title><source>Eur J Pharmacol</source><year>2016</year><volume>781</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejphar.2016.04.028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27090925?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27090925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liang JL, Wu JZ, Liu YH, et al. Patchoulene epoxide isolated from patchouli oil suppresses acute inflammation through inhibition of NF-kappaB and Downregulation of COX-2/iNOS. Mediat Inflamm. 2017:1089028.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Degbe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Debierre-Grockiego</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tete-Benissan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extracts of <italic>Tectona grandis</italic> and Vernonia amygdalina have anti-toxoplasma and pro-inflammatory properties in vitro</article-title><source>Parasite</source><year>2018</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/parasite/2018014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29533762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vyas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Khandelwal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Tectona grandis</italic> (teak) - a review on its phytochemical and therapeutic potential</article-title><source>Nat Prod Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>33</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>2338</fpage><lpage>2354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14786419.2018.1440217</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29506390?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29506390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Almeida</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva Filho</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiinflammatory action of lapachol</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>1990</year><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-8741(90)90061-W</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2374436?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2374436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zarezadeh A, Mousavi Z, Asgarpanah J, Najafizadeh P. Anti-inflammatory activity of rubiadin in carrageenan induced paw edema method in rat. 2<sup>nd</sup> international congress on biomedicine. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.icbcongress.com/2018/en/prp.php?o=1129&#x00026;st=Anti-inflammatory-Activity-of-Rubiadin-in-Carrageenan-Induced-Paw-Edema-Methodin-Rat">https://www.icbcongress.com/2018/en/prp.php?o=1129&#x00026;st=Anti-inflammatory-Activity-of-Rubiadin-in-Carrageenan-Induced-Paw-Edema-Methodin-Rat</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-allodynic effects of obtusifolin and gluco-obtusifolin against inflammatory and neuropathic pain</article-title><source>Biol Pharm Bull</source><year>2014</year><volume>37</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1606</fpage><lpage>1616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1248/bpb.c14-00307</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25070277?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25070277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reanmongkol</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Subhadhirasakul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouking</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antinociceptive and antipyretic activities of extracts and fractions from <italic>Dracaena loureiri</italic> in experimental animals</article-title><source>Songklanakarin J Sci Technol</source><year>2003</year><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>476</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nzowa</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Barboni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Teponno</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricciutelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupidi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Quassinti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bramucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapondjou</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rheediinosides a and B, two antiproliferative and antioxidant triterpene saponins from <italic>Entada rheedii</italic></article-title><source>Phytochemistry.</source><year>2010</year><volume>71</volume><issue>2&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2009.10.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19896681?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19896681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makchuchit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Itharat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tewtrakul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and nitric oxide inhibition activities of Thai medicinal plants</article-title><source>J Med Assoc Thail</source><year>2010</year><volume>93</volume><issue>Suppl 7</issue><fpage>S227</fpage><lpage>S235</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mujahid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashif</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Badruddeen</surname></name><name><surname>Arif</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protection of hepatotoxicity using Spondias pinnata by prevention of ethanol-induced oxidative stress, DNA-damage and altered biochemical markers in Wistar rats</article-title><source>Integr Med Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.imr.2016.05.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28462128?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28462128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hazra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and free radical scavenging activity of <italic>Spondias pinnata</italic></article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>63</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6882-8-63</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19068130</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>