<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The chemical composition of the four plant samples of 
 <italic class="italic">P. dodecandra</italic> was quite different for both aromas and essential oils. Plant sample P-1 was given the local name ‘Arebi endod’, which indicates that it may be transferred from Arabiya, and may not native to Ethiopia [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-24-00342" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Sample P-1 is monoecious, and its fruit is red and different from local 
 <italic class="italic">P. dodecandra</italic> (sample P-2, green). From both aromas and essential oils, we can also find several common components between this nonnative plant and other three local plants, such as benzaldehyde, sulcatone, β-ionone, phytone and hexa- decanoic acid. Sample P-2 and P-3, collected in the same region, are different in gender, and their usages by local peoples are also different. The leaves of sample P-2 (femal) were widely used as soap, especially for making cotton white, and it was also used as molluscicide for the control of the snails that are the vectors of bilharzias [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-24-00342" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-00342" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-24-00342" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>], but sample P-3 (male) was used for animal abortions and rabies treatment by local peoples [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-00342" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-24-00342" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. The chemical composition of these two samples is more similar than that of the other samples, and nearly 60% of the compounds are the same. Sample P-4 is also male, but different from sample P-3 in the collection place. Sample P-3 was collected around Addis Ababa, in the center of Ethiopia, and sample P-4 was collected around Lake Tana, in northwest Ethiopia. Between the two male samples (P-3 and P-4), fourteen compounds in aromas and nine compounds in essential oils are the same, which were less similar than sample P-2 and P-3.
</p>
