<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">The effectiveness of herbal medicines in the treatment of cancer is well established. Plants have been the source of many established anticancer drugs. Clinically used secondary metabolites in cancer chemotherapy include combretastatins isolated from the Combretaceae plant, 
 <italic>Combretum caffrum</italic> (Eckl. &amp; Zeyh.) Kuntze. [
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], vinblastine and vincristine isolated from Madagascar periwinkle, 
 <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> (L.) G. Don., (Apocynaceae) [
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], camptothecin from 
 <italic>Camptotheca acuminata</italic> Decne (Nyssaceae) [
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], paclitaxel isolated from a tree of the Taxaceae family, 
 <italic>Taxus brevifolia</italic> Spjut [
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], or homoharringtonine isolated from 
 <italic>Cephalotaxus harringtonia</italic> (Knight ex Forbes) K. Koch (Cephalotaxaceae) [
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Regarding the high diversity of phytochemicals in the plant kingdom, medicinal plants still constitute an undeniable source of novel anticancer agents. In the last decade, intensive studies have been performed on the anticancer potential of African medicinal plants. Considering the rapid development of resistance in cancer cell lines to cytotoxic drugs, several botanicals from African flora were successfully screened against multi-drug resistant phenotypes. A number of these botanicals showed a good potential to fight recalcitrant cancers. Some of such cytotoxic plants include 
 <italic>Pachypodanthium staudtii</italic> Engl. &amp; Diels (Annonaceae) [
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], 
 <italic>Albizia adianthifolia</italic> (Schumach.) W. Wight (Fabaceae) [
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], 
 <italic>Dichrostachys cinerea</italic> (L.) Wight &amp; Arn. (Fabaceae) [
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], 
 <italic>Fagara tessmannii</italic> Engl. (Rutaceae) [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], 
 <italic>Withania obtusifolia</italic> L. Dunal (Solanaceae), 
 <italic>Jasonia candicans</italic> (Delile) Botsch. (Asteraceae), 
 <italic>Centaurea lippii</italic> L (Asteraceae) and 
 <italic>Pulicaria undulata</italic> (Forssk.) Hook.f. ex Benth., Oliv. &amp; Hiern (Asteraceae) [
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In the continuation of our research program aimed at discovering new botanicals to combat cancer multidrug resistance (MDR), the present work was designed to assess the cytotoxicity of the dichloromethane-methanol (1:1) extract and fractions from the leaves of 
 <italic>Acacia sieberiana</italic> var Woodii (Fabaceae). This study was extended to the evaluation of possible cellular modes of action of the crude extract (ASL). 
 <italic>Acacia sieberiana</italic> is traditionally used to treat bilharzia, tapeworm, heamorrhage, rheumatism, gonorrhea, syphilis, ophtalmia, stomach-ache, urethral diseases, oedema, and diarrhea [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The rationale of the present study comes to from fact that, there are recommendations that, ethnopharmacological usages such as immune and skin disorders, inflammatory diseases as well as infectious, parasitic and viral diseases should be taken into account when selecting plants that treat cancer; this is because these reflect disease states bearing relevance to cancer or cancer-like symptoms [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Previous phytochemical studies from the leaves of 
 <italic>Acacia sieberiana</italic> harvested from Saudi Arabia afforded seven phenolics, namely 6,7,8-trihydroxy- 3,4′-dimethoxy dihydroflavone, ellagic acid, gallic acid, isoferulic acid, quercetin, kaempferol, quercetin 3-
 <italic>O-β</italic>-
 <sub>D</sub>-glucoside and kaempferol 3-
 <italic>α</italic>-
 <sub>L</sub>-arabinoside [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The cytotoxicity of 
 <italic>Acacia sieberiana</italic> is being reported for the first time.
</p>
