<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Widodo et al. [
 <xref rid="B105-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>] screened various fractions of 
 <italic>A. conyzoides</italic> with different solvents, and out of those, crude ethanolic extract showed agreeable activity against various fungal strains such as 
 <italic>A. niger</italic>, 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>, 
 <italic>M. gypseum</italic>, and 
 <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic>, whilst less activity was reported against bacterial strains such as 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>. A white spike crystalline compound was also isolated successfully from the acetone fraction of 
 <italic>A. conyzoides</italic> leaves, which was characterized as a coumarin, and this derived compound proved its better fungicidal activity (72 h clear inhibition zone) in comparison with the standard miconazole nitrate treatment (24 h inhibition zone) against 
 <italic>A. niger</italic>, launching it as a novel antifungal alternative. Some other authors have also assessed the plant invitro for 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> growth inhibition and supported the extract’s activity against the fungus. Wuyep et al. [
 <xref rid="B88-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>] aimed to evaluate the aqueous and ethanolic extracts of 
 <italic>A. conyzoides</italic> against various strains of 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic>, 
 <italic>A. niger</italic>, 
 <italic>A. fumigatus</italic>, 
 <italic>A. ustus</italic>, 
 <italic>A. terreus</italic>, and 
 <italic>A. tamarii</italic>—strains that are frequently involved in animal and plant fungal diseases. Extracts were assessed quantitatively in vitro with the well diffusion technique, then they were challenged and compared with isolated test standard and controls, respectively. Aqueous extract possessed a higher percentage yield as well as greater antifungal activity in comparison withthe ethanolic extract. The lowest antifungal activity was shown against 
 <italic>A. fumigatus</italic> while the maximum activity was recorded against 
 <italic>A. ustus</italic> and 
 <italic>A. tamarii</italic> with the respective inhibition zones of 8.0 ± 0.1 mm, 20.0 ± 0.6 mm, and 15 ± 0.3 at a concentration of 800 mg/mL. However, in vivo activity of the plant extracts using the standard organisms did not correlate thoroughly with the in vitro tests. Not only could the fungus be controlled by the use of herbal fungicides, but also the carcinogenic and toxic metabolites and aflatoxins released by these fungi could also be controlled, particularly those from 
 <italic>Aspergillus parasiticus</italic> and 
 <italic>A. flavus</italic>. Every year, mycotoxins contaminate almost 25% of the world’s total food commodities. The anti-aflatoxigenic activity of 
 <italic>Ageratum</italic> essential oil was investigated via poisonous-medium method by using different concentrations of the obtained oil, i.e., 1500, 1000, and 500 ppm. The essential oil completely inhibited 
 <italic>A. parasiticus</italic> growth and repressed &gt;84% of the aflatoxin production at the concentrations of 0.75 mg/mL and 0.5 mg/mL, as demonstrated by tandem mass spectrometric analysis. Additionally, the volatiles from 
 <italic>A. conyzoides</italic> green leaf tissue were reported to hold fumigant activity against 
 <italic>A. parasiticus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B106-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>].
</p>
