<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Quotidian plastic materials for food packaging in the market is proffered using a synthetic polymer base like polyproline and polyethylene, which is strenuous to decompose. Based on every day activities of Malaysian households and industries, high amounts of solid waste materials seem to have polluted and harmed the landfill with poison. In the interest of conserving the landfill, while overcoming the solid waste pollution issues, a few groups of individuals. such as researchers, the government, and industrial players [
 <xref rid="B1-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>], came up with several solutions. Starting off, the government promotes the routine of recycling, reducing, and reusing on a daily basis to the community [
 <xref rid="B2-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Industrial players and researchers further focus on recycling plastics to be used as secondary materials and attempts to recycle and convert those materials into synthetic fiber threads and yarns to produce jerseys, shoes, and other textile products [
 <xref rid="B3-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Nonetheless, the main problems are nowhere near solved at this point. The solid waste keeps on continuing its revolution in our daily life. The development of the first environmentally friendly materials consist partly of conventional plastic polyethylene (PE) or polypropylene (PP) and partly of nature’s own material—chalk (40% by weight). Until early 2004, the research growth on producing the bio-based product was expanding throughout the entire globe [
 <xref rid="B4-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. PLA (polylactic acid) films, produced from lactic acid, have shown the highest commercial potential and are now produced on a comparatively large scale. Most bioplastics are produced based on natural biomaterials, such as corn, starch, and soybean [
 <xref rid="B5-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Moreover, other food harvests, for example, cassava, wheat, potato, and sago, have also been transformed into plastic to supplant oil-based plastic [
 <xref rid="B6-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Since those products are food assets for human beings, continuous transformation of those yields into plastic will soon interfere with human sustenance supply by reducing the world’s sustenance assets. In an effort to prevent interference with food assets, other biomaterials should be assessed. Contemporaneous edible films have the potential to substantially reduce the environmental burden due to food packaging and limit moisturization, aroma, and lipid migration between food components [
 <xref rid="B7-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Dealing with the biopolymer materials, it is difficult to avoid fugacious shelf-life issues. Biopolymer, which derives from natural sources, is commonly known for having transitory shelf-life as compared to synthetic biopolymer. Problems and errors may arise during the storage time either for logistic purposes or during transportation of the biopolymer to the industrial consumer. Humidity, temperature, micro-organism, and fungi attack may affect the quality and deteriorate the strength of the biopolymer. Accordingly, this study focuses on producing biofilm with sustainable shelf-life, high quality, low toxicity, and cheap costs, which could provide efficient food chain supply. Therefore, algae are chosen to be used in biopolymer film fabrication. Algae, or seaweed, is an environmental asset that exists in boundless amounts, which can be cultivated naturally. The Agarose chemical structure provides a good support for films. In addition, it is reported that the films, which are made of algae, are transparent, strong, and flexible [
 <xref rid="B2-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. In order to enhance the shelf-life and improve the strength of the algae film, cinnamon extract was used to act as a co-primer and anti-microbial in the film. Based on a previous study, anti-microbial polymer film was able to restrain microbial development, hence, broadening the time span of usability of sustenance [
 <xref rid="B6-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Cinnamaldehyde is an organic compound with the formula of C
 <sub class="sub">6</sub>H
 <sub class="sub">5</sub>CH=CHCHO and occurs naturally as a predominant trans (E) isomer, giving cinnamon its flavor and odor [
 <xref rid="B1-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. It is a type of flavonoid that is naturally synthesized by the shikimate pathway [
 <xref rid="B2-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. This pale yellow, viscous liquid occurs in the bark of cinnamon trees and other species of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Cinnamomum</italic> sp. The essential oil of cinnamon bark contains about 50% cinnamaldehyde [
 <xref rid="B3-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Cinnamaldehyde is also used as a fungicide [
 <xref rid="B8-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Proven effective on over 40 different crops, cinnamaldehyde is typically applied to the root systems of plants [
 <xref rid="B5-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Its low toxicity and well-known properties makes it ideal for agricultural activities. Thus, “cinnamaldehyde” is an effective insecticide, and its scent is also known to repel animals, such as cats and dogs [
 <xref rid="B8-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. It has also been tested as a safe and effective insecticide against mosquito larvae [
 <xref rid="B9-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. At a concentration of 29 ppm, cinnamaldehyde can kill half of Aedes aegypti mosquito larvae within 24 h [
 <xref rid="B10-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. The “trans-cinnamaldehyde” also works as a potent fumigant and practical repellent for adult mosquitos [
 <xref rid="B11-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. By adding cinnamon active chemicals into the packaging system [
 <xref rid="B5-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>], the growth rate of microorganisms in food can be inhibited or reduced. Among other antimicrobials, cinnamaldehyde, which is a major component of cinnamon, also possesses antimicrobial activity and has been utilized in the processing of milk, chicken, and meat [
 <xref rid="B5-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-polymers-11-00004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. The objectives of this study were (1) to assess the suitable percentage loading of cinnamon extract with algae film, and (2) to characterize the effect of cinnamon with the biofilm based on the soil bury test, tensile test, FTIR, and SEM.
</p>
