<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0150">In terms of consumers' health, the evaluation of the compositions of meat fatty acid can be considered as an important parameter in the meat quality. Despite the extensive investigation about the influence of phytogenic products on the production performance of broiler chicks, scarce data are available on the effect of these products on meat compositions. In the current study, the total contents of PUFA in muscle increased in response to the increase of dietary EEO supplementation. The enhanced PUFA amount in the muscle could be because of the amplification of the antioxidant system such as SOD in birds receiving EEO diets, although this requires further investigation. Birds fed different levels of EEO had lower SFA content as well. This decrease should be attributed to a notable reduction in the concentrations of C14:0, C16:0, and C18:0. Some studies have shown that, among the SFA, myristic acid (C14:0) and palmitic acid (C16: 0) can enhance low-density lipoprotein cholesterol content and therefore increase serum cholesterol concentration (
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Rioux et al., 2005</xref>). Hence, dietary SFA have high importance because of their hypercholesterolemic effects, which are associated with coronary artery disease (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Ashayerizadeh et al., 2018</xref>). Also, clinical data strongly support a relationship between coronary heart disease and dietary intake cholesterol and SFA (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2009</xref>). In the current study, the thigh muscle of broilers fed the diet supplemented with 1000 mg/kg EEO had a lower SFA content than that of broilers in the control group. Therefore, the present results show that humans' consumption of these kinds of meats may help reduce the risk of coronary heart disease. In line with our results, 
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hashemipour et al. (2013)</xref> reported that supplementation of phytogenic products (thymol and carvacrol) reduced total SFA contents and increased PUFA and n-6 fatty acid in the serum and thigh muscle and increased MUFA in thigh muscle of broiler chickens. Therefore, considering the hypercholesteremic effects of SFA, the current findings concluded that EEO's dietary supplement might be an effective strategy to reduce the thigh meat SFA concentrations in favor of MUFA and PUFA.
</p>
