<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recently, the poisoning cases are occasionally reported in association with the rising popularity of 
 <italic>Dioscorea</italic> consumption prescriptions in clinical use. Chronic and excessive exposure to 
 <italic>D. bulbifera</italic> tuber has caused liver injury in some patients [
 <xref rid="B339-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">339</xref>]. Also, in vivo and in vitro experimental studies have demonstrated that 
 <italic>D. bulbifera</italic> tuber could induce hepatotoxicity [
 <xref rid="B340-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">340</xref>,
 <xref rid="B341-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">341</xref>], increase relative liver weight and can cause death [
 <xref rid="B214-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>]. It is noteworthy to mention that concentrated herbal preparations of samples of 
 <italic>Dioscorea</italic> species abound, with most of them having little or no information about the exact composition and required dosage, thereby increasing health risks to potential consumers [
 <xref rid="B214-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>]. It thus becomes imperative to establish estimated toxicity values for 
 <italic>Dioscorea</italic> species towards efficient utilization in food based clinical management. In view of this, further investigation is required and there is need for relevant government and donor agencies to invest in initiatives that support this research direction. A promising option is the application of CRISPR-Cas (clustered regulatory interspaced short palindromic repeats-CRISPR-associated) mediated genome editing to remove toxic or antinutritive compounds in yams. This precision breeding technique has the potential to alter one or more pathways or traits in a given cultivar, more efficiently than conventional breeding and without disturbing the complement of traits for which it is preferred. The current outlook for non-transgenic genome edited crops is that they may avoid the heavy regulatory burden placed on transgenic “genetically modified” plants [
 <xref rid="B342-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">342</xref>]. The optimization of protocols for genome editing in yam is well underway [
 <xref rid="B343-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">343</xref>,
 <xref rid="B344-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">344</xref>] and the availability of more and better yam genome assemblies is proceeding apace [
 <xref rid="B344-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">344</xref>,
 <xref rid="B345-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">345</xref>,
 <xref rid="B346-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">346</xref>,
 <xref rid="B347-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">347</xref>]. An understanding of the genetic regulation of desirable nutritional and pharmacological compounds can also be leveraged to increase their amounts, especially with increased variety of possible CRISPR-Cas based manipulations. Genome editing is part of a bright future for scientists working to improve the nutritional quality of yams, while making consumption or clinical use safer.
</p>
