<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In a study of human oocytes using serum-free media, the single-step culture showed improved [
 <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>] or comparable [
 <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>] results in blastocyst formation compared to the sequential culture. In the present study, the blastocyst formation rate of the OM + BSA group was similar to that of the EB + BSA group. This result may have been due to the medium exchange. Fujita 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>] reported that, during culture, embryo-secreted growth factors are essential for embryo development. Ammonia and ROS are generated as byproducts of cellular metabolism and, although a certain level of ROS is beneficial for embryo development, higher levels of ROS and ammonia are not suitable for embryo development 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> [
 <xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. In addition, during culture, it is important to remove some of the old medium and replace it with fresh medium, as fresh medium contains almost all the important ingredients for embryo culture and old medium contains embryo-secreted growth factors. Therefore, we replaced half the old medium with fresh medium for better embryo development. However, the increased stability of alanyl-L-glutamine results in significantly reduced ammonium production with incubation at 37°C [
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Only-One Medium contains alanyl-L-glutamine instead of L-glutamine and therefore the medium does not have to be changed when it is used for human embryo culture. In contrast, Blastocyst Medium contains L-glutamine. As embryos are stressed by medium exchange, embryo development using the Only-One medium may have been better if the medium had not been changed.
</p>
