<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The FRAP assay is a well-known, reliable approach that measures ferric reducing ability in a redox-linked colorimetric reaction that reduces Fe
 <sup>3+</sup> to Fe
 <sup>2+</sup> [
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>–
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. The reflectively high FRAP activity on the basis of IC
 <sub>50</sub> valuation in ethanol extracts of 
 <italic>M. sinensis</italic> flesh and peel and 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> flesh, acetone extracts of 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> flesh and peel, and aqueous extract of 
 <italic>M. sinensis</italic> peel and 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> boiled peel extract can be linked to high flavonoid content such as that seen in the ethanol extracts of 
 <italic>M. sinensis</italic> flesh and peel, acetone extracts of 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> flesh and peel, and 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> boiled peel extract. This confers the flesh and peel of both fruits as natural antioxidant sources and further connotes the contributory role of secondary metabolites of 
 <italic>M. sinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> in disease prevention [
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. The positive correlation between phenolic content and the ABTS activity in 
 <italic>M. sinensis</italic> peel, 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> flesh and peel, FRAP activity of 
 <italic>M. sinensis</italic> peel, and 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> flesh is in conformity with reports of phenolic compounds being related to antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>–
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. However, the general positive and negative correlational patterns indicate an unpredictable correlation between the two pharmacological factors and suggest that none of the polyphenolic constituents contributed exclusively to antioxidant activity, but instead that a combination of the polyphenolic constituents contributed to antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>].
</p>
