<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Edible coatings and films belong to an environmental-friendly technology aimed at enhancing food safety, quality and handling properties by creating a biodegradable semi-permeable barrier protection to water vapor, oxygen and carbon dioxide coming from the external environment. Edible coating is a thin edible substance layer, applied in a liquid form directly on the surface of different food products, mainly fruits and vegetables [
 <xref rid="B1-materials-11-01980" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-materials-11-01980" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-materials-11-01980" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-materials-11-01980" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-materials-11-01980" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Edible films are a thin layer obtained as a solid sheet, which can be applied as a wrapping on the food product. For fresh fruit and vegetables, the creation of a wrong moisture and gas atmosphere may lead to weight loss and respiration rate reductions, with a consequent acceleration of the senescence process and a worsening of the visual gloss of coated commodities. Several studies have identified the necessity to evaluate mechanical (flexibility, tension), thermal, optical (brightness, opacity), wettability and morphological properties of edible films, as it creates a modified atmosphere that influences the gas transfer and further becomes a barrier for aromatic compound transferring [
 <xref rid="B6-materials-11-01980" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-materials-11-01980" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. The above-mentioned characteristics depend on several parameters related to the coating and film composition, such as preparation conditions (solvent, pH, components concentration, temperature) and type of added additives (cross-linking agents, antimicrobials, plasticizers, emulsifiers).
</p>
