<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Scientists who professionally engaged in studying the durability of superhydrophobic materials all face a common confusion, which is the lack of a unified, authoritative, and comprehensive evaluation system. At present, several strategies have been used to test the durability of superhydrophobicity, such as the abrasion test, tape peeling, blade scratching, sand abrasion, water jet tests, ultraviolet radiation, high/low temperature, and acid–base marinating.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19" class="xref">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref61" class="xref">61</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref68" class="xref">68</xref>
 </sup> However, there is no consistency about the test conditions such as types of abradant, applied pressure, velocity, irradiation intensity, and so on. As a result, the lack of standardization always makes comparison of different research results impossible. In addition, how to evaluate the durability of superhydrophobic materials is also an issue. By only using WCA, it is insufficient and unconvincing. If these problems cannot be solved urgently, all current research is blind and unavailing in this field. Therefore, it is necessary and urgent to develop a unified, authoritative, and comprehensive characterization and evaluation system. In addition to developing new test methods, we need to introduce tribology knowledge to analyze, solve and guide the design of bioinspired superhydrophobic materials. The related research is still basically in the blank condition. Then, WCA, SA, advancing/receding contact angle, adhesive force, and integrity of microtopography should all be taken into evaluation systems.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref69" class="xref">69</xref>
 </sup> The best solution is to develop a highly integrated testing system which can test all-around surface wettability. With the aid of an external humidity/temperature control system, gas circuit system, and super-high-speed camera, liquid volatilization and icing processes can be studied via this integrated system in different atmospheres or in vacuum. Ultimately, professional evaluation institutions have to be instituted.
</p>
