<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although medicinal plants such as 
 <italic>Mentha</italic> species are commonly believed to be safe, they are not devoid of side effects that can be severe in some cases. Furthermore, allergic reactions can occur with any natural or synthetic compound in sensitive persons. No chronic toxicity studies in humans are available, therefore toxicity of 
 <italic>Mentha</italic> species are scarcely reported. However, it seems that no adverse effects have been reported after consumption 0.24 mL of pure 
 <italic>M. spicata</italic> essential oil daily for three continuous weeks in two different clinical studies [
 <xref rid="B193-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>,
 <xref rid="B194-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>]. Leaves of 
 <italic>Mentha spicata</italic> are known for its contact allergy such as contact cheilitis caused by its essential oil use as toothpaste flavoring [
 <xref rid="B195-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>]. In addition, MPEO is also associated with adverse effects like vomiting, headaches, flushing, heartburn and nausea [
 <xref rid="B196-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>]. 
 <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> and spearmint tea can deprive the human body of iron and cause anemia if consumed excessively, and carvone and limonene showed to be major allergens [
 <xref rid="B195-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>]. Gürbüz found that pulegone, contained in low concentrations in 
 <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> oil extracts, is hepatotoxic, and Douros et al. also reported the likely liver injury caused by 
 <italic>M. piperita</italic> [
 <xref rid="B197-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>,
 <xref rid="B198-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>]. Other research showed that menthol and pulegone could be toxic compounds; in particular, pulegone and its metabolite menthofuran have been suggested as the hepatotoxic compounds in 
 <italic>Mentha pulegium</italic> and have been also found in smaller quantity in 
 <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> [
 <xref rid="B199-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">199</xref>]. Notably, inhalation of menthol can cause apnea and larygospasm in sensitive patients and indeed has been reported that mentholated preparation can be involved in nausea, anorexia, cardiac problems, ataxia and other CNS symptoms [
 <xref rid="B200-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">200</xref>]. 
 <italic>Mentha spicata</italic> extracts displayed toxicity to neuronal cells when applied at concentrations which are one order of magnitude higher than those effective for radical scavenging [
 <xref rid="B201-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">201</xref>]. The positive correlation between the two aforementioned effects suggests that a higher desirable radical scavenging is associated with a higher undesirable toxicity.
</p>
