<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The sample size was based on the outcome of reduced systolic blood pressure obtained by Perona et al. [
 <xref rid="B16-nutrients-13-00798" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], considering a mean difference of 14 mmHg with a standard deviation of 10 and 8 mmHg for each group. The sample size was calculated with the open license tool at (
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.openepi.com" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.openepi.com</uri> (accessed on 1 February, 2017)) and, as a result, a minimum of seven subjects for each group was obtained, considering a confidence interval of 95% and a statistical power of 80%. Our study included 51 hypertensive patients who were allocated by simple random distribution (1:1) using a freely available website (
 <uri xlink:href="www.randomizer.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.randomizer.org</uri> (accessed on 1 February, 2017)). These patients were followed up in the experimental groups: group supplemented with extra-virgin coconut oil—EVCO; group supplemented with placebo; group supplemented with EVCO plus physical training (EVCO-training); and group supplemented with placebo plus physical training (placebo-training). Six patients did not complete the treatment protocol and were excluded. Two of them were from the EVCO group (one on a physical training protocol and one untrained). The patient in the training group dropped out of the study, and the other patient started pharmacological treatment by decision of the cardiologist on the study team. The remaining four losses were from patients supplemented with the placebo intervention (one from the trained group and three from the untrained group). The patient in the trained group had to move from the study city, and the other three dropped out the study. Considering blood pressure analyzes, two records were excluded (one from the placebo group and one from the EVCO group) because they did not reach more than 80% of the valid measures after 24-hour monitoring. Thus, we had the following experimental groups: EVCO, 
 <italic>n</italic> = 14; Placebo, 
 <italic>n</italic> = 11; EVCO-training, 
 <italic>n</italic> = 11; and Placebo-training, 
 <italic>n</italic> = 9, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nutrients-13-00798-f001">Figure 1</xref>.
</p>
