<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Carvacrol (5-isopropyl-2-methylphenol) (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-23-01061-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>) is a monoterpenic phenol present in the EOs of many plants, especially in the genera 
 <italic class="italic">Origanum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B81-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>]. It is the major constituent of the EO fraction of oregano and thyme. Carvacrol has attracted attention because of its beneficial biological activities, especially analgesic activity. Gonçalves et al. [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>] characterized the constituents of 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus capitatus</italic> EO and evaluated their antinociceptive activity by in vivo and in vitro procedures. The EO of 
 <italic class="italic">T. capitatus</italic> presented 33 components, mainly monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes, and carvacrol (80%) was its major constituent. EO of 
 <italic class="italic">T. capitatus</italic> dose-dependently decreased the CAP amplitude. Such activity was presumably mediated through voltage-gated Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> channels [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. Melo et al. [
 <xref rid="B81-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>] examined the behavioral effects of carvacrol using elevated plus-maze (EPM), open field, rotarod, and barbiturate-induced sleeping time tests in mice. The results indicate that carvacrol had anxiolytic effects in the plus-maze test which are not influenced by the locomotor activity in the open-field test [
 <xref rid="B81-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>]. The mechanism underlying the anesthetic and analgesic effects is based on a reduction in neuronal excitability and voltage-gated Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> channel inhibition in peripheral neurons [
 <xref rid="B79-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>]. The hypothesis of the underlying mechanism was supported by the finding that carvacrol could reduce the total voltage-gated Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> current and tetrodotoxin-resistant (TTX-R) Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> current component in a concentration-dependent manner in isolated dorsal root ganglion neurons [
 <xref rid="B80-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>]. In addition to analgesic activity mediated through the blockade of Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> channels [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>], Trailović et al. [
 <xref rid="B78-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>] tested the effects of different concentrations of carvacrol on isolated tissues of the large pig nematode 
 <italic class="italic">Ascaris suum</italic>. The somatic muscle flaps were used for contraction assays and for electrophysiological investigations. The inhibitory effect of carvacrol on contractions, the inhibition of depolarizations caused by acetylcholine (ACh), and the reduction of conductance changes directly point to an interaction with nicotinic ACh receptors in 
 <italic class="italic">A. suum</italic>.
</p>
