<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">2. Different epidemiological data provide evidence that it is possible to prevent cancer and other chronic diseases, some of which share common pathogenic mechanisms, such as DNA damage, oxidative stress, and chronic inflammation. A complementary strategy is to render organisms more resistant to the mutagens/carcinogens and/or to inhibit the progression of the disease by means of the administration of chemopreventive agents. The latter can act in different stages, such as primary prevention, which is directed toward apparently healthy individuals, with the possibility of inhibiting mutation and the initiation of cancer by activating protector mechanisms in the extracellular as well as the intracellular environment. Also, with secondary prevention, when a premalignant lesion has been detected, and at a certain moment, it is possible to inhibit the progression of the tumor through these same extra- and intracellular mechanisms [
 <xref rid="B7-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B210-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">210</xref>]. Therefore, the concordance issignificant between the results obtained in the genotoxic and/or antigenotoxic assays with respect to the presence of cancer, in which the majority of the studies have been conducted under experimental conditions. For example, Hung Kang et al. (2013) [
 <xref rid="B211-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">211</xref>], employing the micronucleus and comet assay, found more than 90% agreement between invivo positive genotoxic assays with respect to more than 20 carcinogens classified by the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC). In addition, there are data that confirm that the comet assay has a high proportion of positive responses for genotoxic carcinogens in rodents [
 <xref rid="B212-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">212</xref>].Similarly, the application has been suggested of at least three tests and/or the combination of different assays, in vivo as well as in vitro, to obtain reliable results [
 <xref rid="B213-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">213</xref>], as in the case of Kirkland et al. (2005), who found 90% positive results with 553 carcinogens [
 <xref rid="B214-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">214</xref>].
</p>
