<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The originality and novelty of our work is to demonstrate the anticancer effect of PV EO and the potential synergistic combination of its two components, carvacrol and thymol, against myeloid leukemic cell lines. This is the first time that a study has investigated the anticancer effect of PV EO or its cytotoxic effect on normal cells. Our results showed that the 0.01% and 0.02% concentrations of PV EO, which are nontoxic to normal cells, can eradicate all leukemic cells, suggesting that the oil constituents play a dual role in cell viability. At similar concentrations, they can kill cancerous cells, and on the other hand, they are able to protect normal cells from drug toxicity. Recently, we showed that Ptychotis verticillate EO, carvacrol, and thymol have several positive effects on MSCs, which are known to be an important immunotherapeutic cell product [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. By preserving their morphology, sustaining their viability, promoting their proliferation, and protecting them from cytotoxicity and oxidative stress, PV appears to be a promising natural medicinal product for strengthening the therapeutic effects of MSCs [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Several studies have shown that carvacrol or thymol may individually induce, in vitro and in vivo (animal models), cancer cell death through the deregulation of different genes involved in cell proliferation and the apoptosis signaling pathway [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. For leukemic cells, previous studies have shown that both carvacrol and thymol individually showed cytotoxic effects on the HL60 cell line by inducing apoptotic cell death [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, at this time, no published work addressed the effect of the combination of these two molecules on the induction of cancer cell death. Thus, we aimed to investigate the anticancer activity of the combination of carvacrol and thymol in three different leukemic cell lines that are able to partially represent the molecular heterogeneity of AML [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Our results showed a potential synergistic effect of thymol and carvacrol at the different combinations used in the KG1 and HL60 cell lines. Interestingly, for the K562 cell line, which was far less sensitive to individual treatment with carvacrol or thymol, the combination of the two drugs was able to eliminate 70% of K562 cancer cells. The drug concentrations used are toxic to normal cells, but more than 50% of the cells remain alive, even at concentrations that can eliminate all KG1 and HL60 cells and more than 70% of K562-resistant cells. These results show that much of the observed antileukemic effect of PV EO is due to the presence of thymol and carvacrol and that the combination of the two drugs can eliminate even the K562-resistant cells while presenting less toxicity to normal cells. However, the nontoxic effect of EO compared to the combination of carvacrol and thymol (car–thy) in normal cells may be due to the existence of other compounds in EO that protect normal cells from cytotoxicity and oxidative stress. These results prompted us to study the molecular mechanisms involved in this cell death induced by the potential synergistic effect. Our results showed a wide range of annexin+/PI-cells (especially for HL60 cell lines) after carvacrol and thymol treatment associated with the expression of the proapoptotic genes BBC3, GADD45A, TP53, BCL2L11, BAX, CD40, CD40LG, SYCP2, ATP6V1G2, NOL3, TNF, and FASLG. We confirmed by Western blotting that the induction of leukemia cell death is associated with apoptotic pathways, as shown by the strong decrease in procaspase-3 and procaspase-9 in cells treated with the combination of carvacrol and thymol. The GADD45A gene is an indicator of DNA damage and plays a role in drug-induced apoptosis with the involvement of stress-induced MAPK8 [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The DNA damage-induced transcription of this gene is mediated by both p53-dependent and p53-independent mechanisms. Our results showed an increase in TP53 and GADD45A expression after car–thy treatment, suggesting that DNA damage and oxidative stress are involved in car–thy-induced cell death. It was shown that p53 promotes the expression BBC3 (also upregulated in our results), leading to increased intracellular ROS levels and apoptosis induction [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. BBC3-induced apoptosis is directly associated with ROS generation [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Our cell and oxidative stress transcriptomic results confirm the involvement of ROS in car–thy-induced cell death. Indeed, the potential synergistic effect is associated with the underexpression of PRDX3, GSTP1, and SOD2, which provide antioxidant or ROS generation inhibitor functions, as well as the overexpression of TXNRD1, which can serve as an ROS generator [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Our results also showed downregulation of the TGFB gene, which is known to control ROS production directly or by downregulating antioxidative systems [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. It has been demonstrated that reactive oxygen species (ROS) production is also increased by TGF-β downregulation, which triggers Akt inactivation in cancer cell death [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The failure of leukemic cells to resist this potential synergistic effect may be explained by the upregulation of antiapoptotic genes, such as the insulin growth factor 1 receptor (IGF1R). In cancer-resistant cells, the sustained activation of the AKT/mTOR is regulated by the upregulation of IGF1R [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], which plays a determinate role in promoting resistance to PI3K/AKT/mTOR inhibitors. Our Western blot results confirmed this failure to resist to cell death probably due to a decrease in PI3K and p-AKT expression in combination-treated cells compared to untreated cells and cells treated with carvacrol or thymol alone. Furthermore, the overexpression of the proapoptotic gene BCL211 (BIM) could reinforce this resistance failure. Indeed, Locatelli et al. demonstrated the role of BIM in arsenic trioxide-induced ovarian cancer cell death through the activation of caspase-3 and dephosphorylation of p-AKT [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. These results suggest that the potential synergistic effect of car–thy can escape the mechanisms of cell death resistance in part by inhibiting cell proliferation through the PI3K/AKT signaling pathway. In addition, accumulating evidence suggests the interrelation of ROS and endoplasmic reticulum stress (ER) with redox signaling mediators [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. ROS can trigger endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress or vice versa in vivo and in vitro [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Under prolonged and severe ER stress conditions, the unfolded protein response (UPR) can become cytotoxic (including apoptosis) rather than cytoprotective. Interestingly, in our results, car–thy-induced cell death is associated with the upregulation of ATF4, which is one of the UPR-dependent signaling proteins. C/EBP-homologous protein (CHOP) is another important component of the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress response. CHOP knockdown significantly attenuated ER stress-induced apoptosis in hepatocarcinoma cells [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. CHOP and ATF4 cooperate to induce cell death, although how this is achieved is still not completely understood [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Our Western blot results showed an increase in CHOP levels in cells treated with the drug combination and confirmed the implication of ER stress in car–thy-induced leukemic cell death. Together, these results show that the association of carvacrol and thymol induces cell death through apoptotic, oxidative, and reticular stress pathways and suggest that all these mechanisms collaborate to escape cancer cell death resistance. Human cancer treatment strategies ultimately rest on the ability of cancer therapeutics to induce tumor-specific cell death. However, cancer cells, because of their molecular heterogeneity, may present genetic or epigenetic modifications of certain pathways that render them unresponsive to treatment [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The car–thy-induced cell death transcriptomic profile shows the expression of certain antiapoptotic genes as well as the expression of antioxidant genes. In addition, the expression profile of certain genes following the cell death induced by the potential synergistic effect of the two drugs depends on the molecular heterogeneity of the different cell lines; for example, the BBC3, TP53, CD40, ATP6V1G2, and NOL3 genes are significantly upregulated following drug treatment in KG1 and K562 cells, whereas BAX and CFLAR (caspase-8-like) genes are only upregulated in HL60 cells. Our studies of cell death dependence on the caspase pathway and ROS generation showed that cell death induced by the potential synergistic effect of car–thy is independent of both pathways in all the cell lines treated, except for HL60, which shows a strong dependence on the caspase pathway. These results could partly explain the overexpression of Bax and CFLAR in this cell line following treatment and the inability of HL60 to express certain genes that may play a role in both apoptotic and nonapoptotic cell death pathways, such as CD40, TNF, TP53, ATF4, and ATP6V1G2 [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Cell death is often regulated by multiple molecular pathways and mechanisms, including apoptosis, autophagy, and necroptosis. The molecular networks driving these different processes are linked, and one pathway may dynamically evolve to another, particularly during cell treatment with various drugs [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-26-00410" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. To determine the non-apoptotic pathways induced by the car–thy combination, we analyzed the profile of a set of genes involved in autophagy and necrosis. The results showed the overexpression of a set of genes that are involved in both pathways. The comparison of the different lines according to apoptosis dependence did not show a large demarcation between the HL60 line and the other cell lines. However, we observed a significant increase in the expression of some genes, including necrosis genes BMF, DPYSL, and JPH3 and autophagic genes INS and TP53, in only the KG1 and K562 cell lines, in which car–thy-induced cell death is caspase independent. It seems that the inability of car–thy to induce the expression of certain genes that allow the switch between the different pathways in HL60 is one of the causes of the dependence of this line on the caspase pathway. However, this dependence does not seem to be absolute. An extension in car–thy treatment time restores cell death even in the presence of caspase inhibitor. This could be explained by the induction of the expression of a dozen autophagy and necrosis genes in this cell line in response to car–thy.
</p>
