<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The pathogenic fungus used in this experiment was previously isolated from spots on 
 <italic>A. adenophora</italic> leaves, and a phylogenetic analysis of the ITS gene indicated that it was close to 
 <italic>Diaporthe helianthi</italic> (JK58) (see colony morphology in Figure 
 <xref rid="ece37072-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>, with GenBank accession No. JN854227 for the ITS gene). Its pathogenicity (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece37072-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5</xref>) was verified by the method previously described by Gilbert and Webb (
 <xref rid="ece37072-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). Briefly, the pathogenic fungi cultured on potato dextrose agar (PDA, 1,000 ml of distilled water containing 200 g of potato, 10 g of dextrose and 18 g of agar) medium were made into agar disks with a 3‐mm internal diameter punch. A sterile needle was used to lightly wound the underside of the leaf. The agar disk was then attached to the wound and secured with a hairpin. The control group was inoculated with sterile agar disks. The spot area was measured on day 7 after inoculation and then again every 7 days 4 consecutive times. The inoculation experiments consisted of 4 treatments, called Col−P− (no 
 <italic>Colletotrichum</italic>, no pathogen), Col−P+ (no 
 <italic>Colletotrichum</italic>, pathogen), Col+ P− (
 <italic>Colletotrichum</italic>, no pathogen) and Col+ P+ (
 <italic>Colletotrichum</italic>, pathogen). The first five pairs of mature leaves of the seedlings, representing five leaf ages, were inoculated with pathogens, and 9 replicates were inoculated for each leaf age for each treatment. A total of 180 inoculations were carried out. The FIR of 
 <italic>Colletotrichum</italic> sp. was significantly different between Col+ and Col− seedlings (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece37072-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>, FIR(Col−P+) = 3.33%, FIR(Col+ P+) = 28.33%, FIR(Col−P−) = 2.92%, FIR(Col+ P−) = 16.30%), but there was no difference in FIR between leaf ages (L1‐5) (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece37072-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>, FIR(Col−): L1 = 2.08%, L2 = 2.08%, L3 = 3.13%, L4 = 6.25%, L5 = 2.08%; FIR(Col+): L1 = 13.54%, L2 = 29.17%, L3 = 33.33%, L4 = 19.79%, L5 = 15.63%).
</p>
