<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Three decades ago, Dudits et al. [
 <xref rid="B72-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>] suggested that the somatic embryo initiation in vitro was a stress response. Many reports since then underlined the importance of stress factors during SE induction in vitro [
 <xref rid="B10-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Cultured plant tissues experience a variety of stresses as a consequence of in vitro manipulations, including wounding, sterilization, mineral nutrient imbalance in the culture medium composition, PGRs, or subcultures. In response to any of these stresses, the homeostasis between reactive oxygen species (ROS) production and scavenging is disturbed, and ROS are generated in excess, thereby imposing oxidative stress in plant tissue culture. Stresses experienced by cultured tissues may induce a general response, resulting in chromatin remodeling and activation of the embryogenic developmental program [
 <xref rid="B72-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Namely, accumulating evidence revealed that ROS (specifically H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>) may function as signaling molecules that regulate plant growth and development, including cellular proliferation and differentiation [
 <xref rid="B77-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. As a cellular messenger, H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> in proper concentrations has the ability to induce gene expression and protein synthesis, hence triggering activation of embryogenic developmental program and formation of somatic embryos in different plant species [
 <xref rid="B76-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. On the other hand, excessive ROS could severely damage cellular proteins, DNA, and membrane lipids [
 <xref rid="B78-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Thus, ROS overproduction could lead to plant recalcitrance and reduced morphogenetic competence during the in vitro culture [
 <xref rid="B79-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Therefore, maintaining an optimum ROS level in the cell and restoring cell redox balance is important and enables the regulation of various processes [
 <xref rid="B78-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>], including SE induction.
</p>
