<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Abstract</title>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Context:</bold> New antileishmanias are needed because of toxicity, high cost and resistance problems associated with available drugs. 
  <italic class="italic">Nectandra</italic> (Lauraceae) produces several classes of compounds but its essential oil has not previously been reported to have antileishmania activity.
 </p>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Objective:</bold> We evaluated the cytotoxicity and antileishmania activity of essential oils from 
  <italic class="italic">Nectandra amazonum</italic> Nees, 
  <italic class="italic">N. gardneri</italic> Meisn., 
  <italic class="italic">N. hihua</italic> (Ruiz &amp; Pav.) Rohwer and 
  <italic class="italic">N. megapotamica</italic> (Spreng.) Mez.
 </p>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Materials and methods:</bold>
  <italic class="italic">Nectandra</italic> oils were extracted from stem bark/leaves by hydrodistillation and compounds were identified by GC-MS. Oils were tested against 
  <italic class="italic">Leishmania infantum</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">L. amazonensis</italic> intracellular amastigotes and nitric oxide production was evaluated. Cytotoxicity was achieved on NIH/3T3 and J774.A1 cells for the selectivity index (SI).
 </p>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Results and discussion:</bold>
  <italic class="italic">Nectandra gardneri</italic> was active against 
  <italic class="italic">L. infantum</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">L. amazonensis</italic> (IC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> =  2.7 ± 1.3/2.1 ± 1.06 μg/mL) and contained 85.4% sesquiterpenes, of which 58.2% was intermediol. Besides low cytotoxicity (SI &gt;11.3), 
  <italic class="italic">N. gardneri</italic> induced a significant increase in NO production by 
  <italic class="italic">L. infantum</italic>-infected macrophages. 
  <italic class="italic">Nectandra hihua</italic> had the best activity on 
  <italic class="italic">L. infantum</italic> amastigotes (IC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> =  0.2 ± 1.1 μg/mL). This oil was 89.0% sesquiterpenes, with 28.1% bicyclogermacrene. The two specimens of 
  <italic class="italic">N. megapotamica</italic> had different activities on amastigotes. The one richer in sesquiterpenes (49.9%) was active against both species (IC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> =  12.5 ± 1.4/21.3 ± 1.2) and had phenylpropanoid 
  <italic class="italic">E</italic>-asarone as the main compound (42.4%). 
  <italic class="italic">Nectandra amazonum</italic> showed moderate activity on both the species (IC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> =  31.9 ± 2.0/22.1 ± 1.3 μg/mL) and low selectivity (0.9 &lt; SI &gt;2.6), probably due to the major presence of β-caryophyllene (28.5%).
 </p>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Conclusions:</bold> Our data identify compounds that can now be isolated and used for the development of new antileishmanias.
 </p>
</abstract>
