<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">A second type of freezing-created interface that can lead to protein destabilization is caused by the formation of air bubbles during freezing. As a material is frozen, growth of ice crystals results in increase in the concentration of all solutes present in the sample, including dissolved air gasses (predominantly nitrogen and oxygen). As these gasses become more concentrated, air bubbles form, creating additional pathways for surface-related protein instability due to newly formed solution/air interface (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>). The appearance of air bubbles during freezing has been directly observed by optical microscopy (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>) and indirectly by small-angle neutron scattering (SANS) (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>). Protein adsorption onto these freezing-formed air bubbles and protein destabilization due to the additional air/solution interface can therefore be expected, although the relative significance of this potential destabilization mechanism has not been studied. Finally, additional interfaces could also be created in the maximally freeze-concentrated solution when it is cooled below the glass transition temperature, as suggested in a recent study of a model sorbitol–water system (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>). A sorbitol–water mixture with a composition representative of the maximally freeze-concentrated solution was studied by the SANS method. It was reported that cooling of the sample below its calorimetric Tg (glass transition; approx. 210 K) resulted in the development of domains with well-defined and sharp interfaces on the submicrometer length scale, probably as a result of the appearance and growth of microscopic voids in the glassy matrix. Importantly, these interfaces persisted even when the sample was heated back to above its Tg; therefore, these interfaces could represent an additional source of protein surface-related instability during freeze–thaw and freeze–drying/reconstitution.
</p>
