<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22" class="p">In more recent studies, evidence of partially unfolded proteins at ice interfaces has been observed by infrared microscopy (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>). We should note that, while these studies provided convincing evidence that destabilization of protein could be induced by formation of ice, it is not obvious if such destabilization is the result of the direct protein/ice interaction, as other mechanisms can be invoked. For example, it was suggested that the observations of freeze-induced protein destabilization do not necessarily prove that there is a direct ice/protein interaction (
 <italic class="italic">i.e.</italic>, sorption of protein molecules on ice crystals), as the same results could be explained by a partitioning of protein into quasi-liquid layer (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>). The quasi-liquid layer (also known as liquid-like layer) is a thin film of liquid water on the surface of ice crystals, which exists well below the ice melting temperature even in pure water (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>). Estimations of the thickness of the layer vary widely, from a few angstroms to up to a micrometer (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>). Protein molecules in the quasi-liquid layer could be exposed to destabilizing stresses, such as an increased local acidity due to the negative charge on the surface of ice crystals (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>). The ice surface was shown to carry negative charge when in equilibrium with solution at pH values higher than 4; the negative charge is balanced by the elevation in the local concentration of cations, including protons, in the quasi-liquid layer next to the ice surface, with the corresponding increase in the local acidity.
</p>
