<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Absorption of ME/NEs</div>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mostly, absorption of ME/NEs is high in small intestinal lumen rather than in other parts of GIT since it contains biliary lipids (bile salts, phospholipids, and cholesterol). MCTs with amphiphilic nature present in particulate emulsified systems undergo lipolysis at lumen of the intestine into free fatty acids and monoglycerides. These products have the ability to coalesce readily with bile lipids and form micelles. Further, fatty acids of 10–12 carbon atoms and drugs with lop 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 5 passively diffused from the lumen into the systemic circulation by enterocytes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. Fatty acids of more than 10–12 carbon atoms and drugs with log 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &gt; 5 are re-esterified to triglycerides in enterocytes as represented in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>. Cholesterol also undergoes esterification by luminal enzymes into cholesterol esters. The formed triglycerides and cholesterol esters are then covered by a layer of proteins and phospholipids to form chylomicrons, which leaves the cell through exocytosis and enter the lymphatics owing to apparent molar volume increase. Therefore, drugs undergo either portal or lymphatic absorption depending on molecular features and diffusion coefficient of API [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>].
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Steps in intestinal absorption of ME/NEs</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12944_2018_757_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A pH-stat automatic titration unit model demonstrated the lipolysis of ME/NEs and subsequent phases which alters the release profile and fate of a drug in GIT. The further extent of digestion affects release profiles of the drug located in the core of ME/NEs rather than shell [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>]. Carriers of ME/NEs transport the drug present in oil core to mucus layer while the drug available in surfactant shell get separate out as free molecules from carriers and diffuse directly to the epithelium. Though lipophilic compounds readily diffuse across the apical plasma membrane of intestinal epithelium the subsequent passage across the basolateral membrane and into blood are by no means guaranteed [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>]. Thus, ME/NEs facilitate improved transport across the intestinal wall and lead to lowering the effect of protease, an intestinal enzyme and sustained plasma uptake [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>], this attribute was proven to be successful with the sustained release of rhPTH1–34, a peptide drug by opening tight junctions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporters and solute carriers are notable intestinal transporters which regulate the transport of molecules into and out of enterocytes. Cytochrome P-450 3A4 (CYP3A4), multidrug efflux pump and P-glycoprotein (P-gp) are present high levels at villus tip enterocytes of the small intestine. P-gp is ABC transporter and highly expressed on the brush-border membrane of columnar epithelial cells. The efflux transport of particulate emulsified systems into enterocytes is affected by these local transporters. However, efflux inhibition is anticipated with membrane fluidization, induced conformational changes and cholesterol depletion [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>]. PEG 400, Cremophor EL, RH40 and combinatorial surfactants are successful in inhibiting P-gp by forming the micelles during emulsification which can masquerade drug thereby not exposing core drug molecules to the efflux transporters [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cellular surfaces are dominated by negatively charged sulfated proteoglycans that play an important role in cellular proliferation, migration, and motility. Particulate emulsified systems with higher surface charge, bind strongly to the cell membrane with electrostatic interactions between the anionic membrane and cationic nanodroplets, thus increasing the cellular uptake. After adsorption onto the cellular membrane, the uptake occurs possibly via pinocytosis, nonspecific or receptor-mediated endocytosis or phagocytosis [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>]. Absorption of particulate emulsified systems is affected by surface charges (either positive or negative) present on ME/NEs and this phenomenon was evidently demonstrated by griseofulvin emulsions. Therefore, the zeta potential of ME/NEs certainly affects the pharmacokinetics of isotropic systems [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
