<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biochemistry of gastrointestinal tract</div>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mucins, long (200–1000 nm) heterogenous polydispersed filaments of glycosylated proteins are protecting GI mucosa from pH fluctuations, pathogens, mechanical irritation and toxins [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>]. They are categorized into membrane-bound and secretory mucins [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. Majority of mucins are linked with proline, rich in serine and /or threonine glycosylation sites repeated in tandem (named as tandem repeats). These repeated units are widely varied between mucin types in terms of length (5–375 amino acids) and in number (5–395 repeats) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. Each epithelial mucin gene discovered was named as MUC in 1990. Currently, in humans, 20 mucin-type glycoproteins have been assigned to the MUC gene family, as approved by the Human Genome Organization- Gene Nomenclature Committee (HUGO/GNC). MUC1, MUC3A, MUC3B, MUC4, MUC12, MUC13, MUC15, MUC16, MUC17, MUC18, and MUC20 mucins have trans-membrane domains in their C-terminus and thus are type 1 membrane proteins [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. Stomach epithelia contain MUC1, which is present on the apical membranes of parietal cells in fundic glands [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. MUC2 contains four conserved cysteine-rich domains that have sequence similarity to the D-domains of pro-von Willebrand clotting factor expressed in goblet cells of the intestine [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. The other large gel-forming cysteine-rich secretory mucins are MUC5AC, MUC5B, MUC6, and MUC19 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. The MUC 3 gene was essentially expressed in the epithelial cells of small intestine especially in goblet cells and in enterocytes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]. Majorly, MUC 5 AC and MUC 6 gene are expressed in gastric tracts. Mucins affect the absorption of ME/NEs in terms of their biochemical composition, viscosity, diffusivity, dipole moment, zwitterion profiles, ionic strength and interaction with the dispersion medium. Overall, ME/NEs undergo absorption at various sites of GIT such as gastric lumen, stomach, and small intestine as their biomembrane diffusion is proportional to the reciprocal of mucin concentration [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
