<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Components and classification of ME/NEs</div>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oils</div>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oils as carriers firstly meant for hydrophobic drugs to sink, long, medium and short chain triglycerides (LCT, MCT, and SCT) were predominantly used in the preparation of ME/NEs with the rank order of MCTs&gt;LCTs&gt;SCTs [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. Type of oil used in the formulation has a great impact on solubilization, digestion of carrier lipid and drug release with desired characteristics. Principally, LCTs and MCTs are converted into free fatty acids by water dispersion during digestion. Free fatty acids of MCTs are able to migrate rapidly into surrounding medium whereas those produced by LCTs accumulate at the oil-water interface thereby lipase activity is inhibited [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>] Semisynthetic MCT’s are superior over natural MCTs as it was proven in Naringenin nanoemulsions [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>]. Combination of LCT’s and MCTs was also promised with superior emulsifying and dissolution profiles [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. The success of MEs/NEs is affected by molecular and lipid characters of MCT and LCTs such as loading of drug and droplet size, chemical nature, and stability [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>]. As absorption of ME/NEs is governed by Ostwald ripening principle, significant portal absorption of crodomol GTCC, an MCT and lymphatic absorption of corn and canola oils (LCT) were resulted [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Amphiphiles</div>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to typical structural significance, amphiphiles reduce the interfacial tension and impart thermodynamic stability in dispersions. Droplet size of hetero-dispersions is affected by HLB value, type, and concentration of surfactant [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. Surfactants with high HLB (12–18) are suitable candidates for ME/NE’s [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>], since their ability to form smaller droplets within the GI lumen that enables the absorption maxima. In contrast, at higher concentrations, surfactants hamper the absorption process due to increased apparent weight on whole [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Being nonionic, polysorbate is less toxic and unaffected by changes in pH, ionic strength and promotes the formation of ultrafine droplets [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>] whereas, poloxamers display aggregation with Ostwald ripening. But in combination with ionic surfactants, due aggregation of poloxamers is minimized by imparting a positive charge on the surface. A similar principle was noticed in a binary mixture of DDAB and C12E5 DDAB (cationic –nonionic) surfactants which had no obvious effect on droplet structure and size, although it improved the stability of nanoemulsion [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>]. Hence, the nonionic surfactants are considered to be stable in the design of ME/NEs and their subtypes [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. Tween 80, cremophor EL and cremophor RH40 had proven their superiority on digestion and increased absorption by inhibiting the efflux transporters such as p-gp, breast cancer resistance protein and MDR-protein [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>]. A recent success of amphiphiles was portrayed with a combination of Gelucire®, sucrose ester, a non-digestable surfactant. The substitution of the non-digestible surfactants with digestible surfactants, sucrose esters S-1670 and Span® 60, eliminated the digestion lag time with no change in the formation of colloidal structures [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cosurfactants /Cosolvents</div>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Short-to-medium-chain (C3-C8) alcohols such as methanol, ethanol, isopropyl alcohol, carbitol, PEG’s, glycerin, propylene glycol, etc. have the potential to increase the emulsification efficiency by reducing the bending stress at an interface and allow film flexibility to different curvatures for the formation of ME/NE’s. They primarily increase the mobility of hydrocarbon tail and allow greater penetration of oil at the interface [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>]. Transcutol, a cosurfactant has efficiently increased the solubility of paracetamol as a function of temperature over other cosolvents and also combinations [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
