<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The use of hemp fibers as reinforcement for composite materials has risen in the past few years as a result of an increasing demand for the development of biodegradable and recyclable materials. Much attention has been paid in recent decades to composite materials, the components of which, be it matrix or reinforcement, come from nature. The advantages of using green composites lie in both the fibers and the bio-resins being abundantly made by nature, consequently having a low manufacture cost compared to synthetic composites. Moreover, they have relatively good mechanical properties. Hemp fibers can be found in the plant stem, which makes them tough and rigid, an essential requirement for the reinforcement of composite materials. The mechanical properties of hemp fibers are close to those of the glass fibers (see [
 <xref rid="B23-materials-12-01232" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-materials-12-01232" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-01232" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-materials-12-01232" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-materials-12-01232" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]). Nevertheless, the biggest disadvantage is the variability of these properties depending on the weather conditions, the harvest area, or other natural factors. In [
 <xref rid="B28-materials-12-01232" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>], the author explains why the hemp fibers from plants harvested at the beginning of flowering had a stiffness and a tensile strength greater than the fibers of the hemp plant seeds harvested at maturity. In [
 <xref rid="B29-materials-12-01232" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>] it is shown that the fibers of the middle section of the stock had higher mechanical properties than the fibers of the upper and lower sections of the stem. Studies on the mechanical properties of the hemp fibers are described in detail in [
 <xref rid="B30-materials-12-01232" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. Improvement of the mechanical behavior of hemp fibers, as well as different types of treatments, is shown in [
 <xref rid="B31-materials-12-01232" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-materials-12-01232" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>].
</p>
