<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <italic>Ferula</italic> species was first collected by Walter E. Siehe, a German engineer and plant collector [
 <xref rid="B24-plants-10-00102" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], in July 1909 in the northern Adana province of South Anatolia. Siehe identified this species as 
 <italic>Ferula ovina</italic> Boiss. and sent plant specimens to the Herbarium of the Komarov Botanical Institute in Leningrad (LE), USSR, and Herbarium of Royal Botanical Garden, Edinburgh (RBGE), UK. In 1930, during the examination of herbarium specimens at LE, Korovin identified this plant as a new species and named it as 
 <italic>Ferula drudeana</italic>. The first description of 
 <italic>F. drudeana</italic> was published by Korovin without any field observation of this plant in his “Generis Ferula (Tourn.) L. Monographia Illustrata” in 1947 [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-10-00102" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In 1983, we found 
 <italic>F. drudeana</italic> Korovin near Hasan Dağı in the Cappadocia region of Anatolia while collecting 
 <italic>Ferula</italic> specimens for investigation of their biologically active secondary metabolites. The plant voucher was deposited in the Herbarium of the Faculty of Pharmacy of Istanbul University (ISTE 50880) and identified by Dr. E. Tuzlacı. In 2004, 
 <italic>F. drudeana</italic> was also rediscovered where it was originally collected by Siehe in 1909 [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-10-00102" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Although the botanical descriptions of 
 <italic>F. drudeana</italic> have been published by both Korovin and, M. Sağıroğlu and H. Duman [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-10-00102" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-plants-10-00102" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], these descriptions omit macro-morphologic details that provide important clues about the relation of this species to the silphion plant. The roots of wild growing 
 <italic>F. drudeana</italic> were recollected from the Cappadocia region near Hasan Dağı in May 2019 for reinvestigation of its secondary metabolites and herbarium specimen was deposited in the Herbarium of the Faculty of Pharmacy of Istanbul University (ISTE 116411).
</p>
