<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our findings illustrate that foraging rodents, well known to be risk-averse during moonlit nights [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], are also affected by the cover from an invasive plant [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. This result is important because it has implications for granivory and perhaps plant demography in invaded and restored coastal habitats. In central coastal California, Maron and Simms [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] found that rodents limit the establishment and recruitment of 
 <italic>Lupinus arboreus</italic>, a native shrub in their study area. 
 <italic>Lupinus arboreus</italic> is a large, N-fixing shrub, and it influences soil nutrients [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In our study region of northwestern California, 
 <italic>Lupinus arboreus</italic> is a non-native invader [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], so understanding if and how native rodents may be able to help slow its spread—possibly aiding restoration efforts—is a high priority for future research. However, high rates of granivory in habitats with 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic> could also affect native plants—possibly inhibiting restoration. Dangremond et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] found that rodent granivory of an endangered plant, 
 <italic>Lupinus tidestromii</italic>, was higher near 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic>-dominated habitat in coastal dunes of central California, creating apparent competition between 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic> and native plants. Indeed, future research in this system should work toward unraveling the complex trophic links formed by a non-native invasive plant (i.e., 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic>) providing cover favored by native rodents, which likely forage on and potentially limit the recruitment of native and non-native plants, some of which have ecosystem consequences of their own (i.e., 
 <italic>Lupinus arboreus</italic>). The ongoing removal of 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic> in our study region may create unique opportunities for experimental studies of how cover affects rodents and their implications for the overall dune ecology.
</p>
