<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The giving up density of food in a foraging patch is a balance of the benefit (i.e., the food harvest rate) and three costs: the costs of handling and metabolizing the food, the cost of missed opportunities of foraging elsewhere, and the costs of predation risk [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. We believe that the differences we measured in GUD between habitats reflects variation in perceived predation risk because habitat differences in the other costs were likely negligible. We used the same food (shelled sunflower seeds) and sand for all foraging stations, so handling and metabolic costs should have been consistent. Sunflower seeds are energetically very dense, with 560 cal per 100 g of seeds [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], and laboratory trials consistently show they are highly desirable for granivorous rodents and in many cases preferred over wild native seeds (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]). Thus, the sunflower seeds should have diminished and dampened variation in the cost of missed opportunity outside the foraging trays. Also, during our study period (mid-late summer), few plant species have mature seeds in either habitat, and wild foods are relatively rare. Those that are present include the previous year’s 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic> crop. Although we did not measure differences in standing crop of wild seeds between habitats, if any difference existed it would almost certainly be that wild seeds were more available in the 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic>-dominated habitat. If so, this would be a conservative bias, since a higher missed-opportunity cost stemming from more abundant wild foods would raise the GUD in 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic>—the opposite of our observed effect of a significantly lower GUD in 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic>.
</p>
