<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cultivated and wild tomato species produce structural diverse acylsugars, and this diversification is associated with gene duplication and functional diversification of related biosynthetic genes. To provide plants with improved resistance, several breeding strategies have been designed in order to make cultivated tomato able to produce “wild” acylsugars. QTL mapping in recombinant populations has allowed to identify and introgress key genes in cultivated tomato lines [
 <xref rid="B211-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">211</xref>,
 <xref rid="B212-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">212</xref>,
 <xref rid="B213-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>]. As well, major genetic factors behind differences in trichome morphology have been identified by QTL analyses [
 <xref rid="B214-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>]. In parallel, overexpression or gene silencing biotechnological strategies have been used to boost the accumulation of glandular specialized metabolites, with the aim to increase plant protection and yield of bioactive molecules. As an example, R2R3 MYB-dependent auxin signaling pathway TFs, known to participate in hormonally regulated II, V and VI type trichomes formation in tomato leaves, have been used to successfully modulate trichome production [
 <xref rid="B215-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">215</xref>], showing that increased trichomes density improved tomato tolerance to spider mites. Besides 
 <italic>Solanum</italic> species, which are considered a model for trichome studies for their anti-herbivory potential, the overexpression of 
 <italic>AaMYB1</italic> and its orthologue 
 <italic>AtMYB61</italic> TFs was effective in increasing terpene metabolism and trichome development in 
 <italic>A. annua</italic> and 
 <italic>A. thaliana</italic> [
 <xref rid="B216-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">216</xref>]. Implementation of metabolic engineering strategies is already taking advantage of the recent advances in CRISPR/CAS9 technologies, which result particularly promising for precision breeding of trichome complex traits. As an example, Campbell et al. [
 <xref rid="B217-ijms-22-02887" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>] by combining classical genetic approaches (genetic mapping, array comparative genomic hybridization and whole genome sequencing) identified a soybean orthologue of 
 <italic>A. thaliana</italic> CPR5, a necessary gene for proper trichome growth and development, and used a CRISPR/Cas9 functional approach to induce mutations that resulted in an altered trichome phenotype.
</p>
