<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since last several years, various kinds of pharmaceutical drugs including amphotericin B, pentamidine, miltefosine, and paromomycin were involved in the treatment of leishmaniasis. None of the clinically approved drugs could be deliberated as the ultimate source of treatment due to their time-taking process and high toxicity combined with severe adversative effects. In addition, the most often used medicines do not eradicate the parasites entirely from all infected entities (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">De Menezes et al., 2015</xref>). Further, applications of some of these medicines with their limitations are described below:
 <list list-type="simple">
  <list-item>
   <p>• Pentavalent antimonials can be administrated by the intravenous, intramuscular, and intralymphatic routes with the optimum dosage of 20 mg/kg/day (28–30 days) and exhibited 35–95% potentiality. Continuous and excessive use of this drug causes toxicity like nephrotoxicity, hepatotoxicity, severe cardiotoxicity, and pancreatitis (
    <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">De Menezes et al., 2015</xref>)
    <italic>.</italic>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>• Oral administration of miltefosine not only showed inhibitory effects on the growth of 
    <italic>Leishmania</italic> but also affected adversely and created severe infecting symptoms comprising nephrotoxicity, teratogenicity, vomiting and diarrhea, and hepatotoxicity (
    <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">Sundar et al., 2011</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>• Paromomycin, also being used as a therapeutic agent to treat leishmaniasis, reported to show some toxic effects during its treatment phase, like severe nephrotoxicity, hepatotoxicity, and ototoxicity (
    <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Jhingran et al., 2009</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>• Pentamidine with the prime dosage of 3 mg/kg/day can potentially involve in the retardation of 
    <italic>Leishmania</italic> growth with some severe antagonistic effects such as hypotension, elevated rate of hyperglycemia, tachycardia, pancreatic damage, and electrocardiographic changes (
    <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">De Menezes et al., 2015</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
