<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Thai traditional knowledge has a long history, and it is very difficult to find its origin. Traditionally, Thai traditional plant knowledge is communicated from the older generation to the younger orally. It is rarely found in text formats. The old literature, called 
 <italic>Tam Ra O-sod Phra Narai</italic>, records Thai traditional knowledge, describing the medicinal use formularies of King Narai the Great’s reign (Ayutthaya period, 1656–1688). However, we have no evidence that the literature was recorded by the original healers or traditional physicians. Moreover, the literature was revised and published in several versions. In the present period, 
 <italic>Rattanakosin</italic> (1782–present), a number of medicinal plant uses have been recorded in several forms. The old-fashioned notes are 
 <italic>Borassus</italic> palm leaf booklets. Some notes were kept as clans’ secrets and passed to only one, or a few, of their heirs. In the present time, only a few of these ancient texts have been found, and the records mention plant names as local names, and sometimes in the old language. It is difficult to integrate this valuable old Thai traditional knowledge into the modern sciences. In the last few decades, medicinal plants have been popular among Thai people. Hundreds of books about medicinal plants have been published. Some of them mention scientific plant names with uses. However, as scientists, we cannot use them as references in this analysis. Our concerns are as follows: (1) The scientific plant names might be incorrect. Most authors are not botanists, so we cannot trust their plant identification process. In cases where they did not identify the species themselves, it is possible that they just got scientific names by researching the plants’ local names. (2) The sources of the knowledge are unspecified. The literature that specifies only plant descriptions and uses is useless for this study. It is possible that data from many books have the same sources. This will interfere with the study’s results, unexpectedly duplicating data. This study, therefore, focuses on only the sources of the literature that use ethnobotanical methods, explained in [
 <xref rid="B38-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], for collecting data. The literature must provide the study location, scientific plant names (including identification methods), and uses. The ethnomedicinal reports of the gingers were extracted from 62 scientific publications, which were published between 1990 and 2019. The year 1990 was the first year that ethnobotany was introduced into the Thai academic system [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Although Thailand has a long history of taxonomic work, only rarely do herbarium specimen labels describe the uses of plants. Most herbarium specimens with plant use descriptions were prepared by ethnobotanists, and the data were published their works. Therefore, we included only data from ethnobotanical publications, and we ignored herbarium label data so as to avoid data duplication. The references included one book, 26 post-graduate theses, 32 journal articles and 3 scientific reports (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-plants-09-00906">Supplementary Materials</xref>). All these references used ethnobotanical methods to collect data. We avoided duplication by eliminating publications that were done by the same authors in the same place and at the same time. When the results were presented in the students’ thesis, we focused on the data from their thesis, and ignored the use reports from subsequent journal articles based on the same data. An example is the data from the thesis published by Srithi (2012) [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], which was published in parts in three journal articles [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In this case, we only included the data from the thesis. Data cited in a reference that were based on previous references were also eliminated. An example is that some data used in a thesis [
 <xref rid="B43-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] were based on previous reports [
 <xref rid="B44-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], and they were already published in three articles [
 <xref rid="B47-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In this case, we used the data from the oldest reports. We screened the references from the online database of the Thai Library Integrated System [
 <xref rid="B50-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], which collects all theses and academic reports from all higher educational institutions in Thailand. For additional data sources, we searched the Google Scholar, PubMed and Scopus databases. Moreover, we screened the publications in the Thai language from national journals. Therefore, we are confident that the references included in our study cover almost all ethnomedicinal use reports pertaining to gingers during the selected period, and we have made every effort to ensure the data are not repeated in our material. As the vernacular names of Thai plants are problematic and can cause confusion, we excluded all use reports without scientific plant names. In cases where the authors could only identify a plant to a genus (e.g., as 
 <italic>Curcuma</italic> sp., 
 <italic>Alpinia</italic> sp., 
 <italic>Zingiber</italic> sp., etc.), these partly identified species were also excluded from our analysis. Because some references were old, we updated the plants’ scientific names following the World’s Check List of vascular plants.
</p>
