<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mass spectrometric analysis of peptide mixtures was performed in duplicate on a Synapt G2S mass spectrometer (Waters, Manchester, UK) using Masslynx version 4.1, coupled to a nanoAcquity UPLC system (Waters, Manchester, UK) via a NanoLockSpray ion source using a PicoTip Emitter (New Objective, Woburn, MA, USA) as described [
 <xref rid="B41-antioxidants-09-00919" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-antioxidants-09-00919" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Mobile phase A contained 0.1% formic acid in water, and mobile phase B contained 0.1% formic acid in acetonitrile. Peptide solutions containing approx. 70 ng of peptides were supplemented with 40 fmol of Hi3 ClpB_ECOLI standard (Waters, Manchester, UK) for absolute quantitation. Peptides were trapped and desalted using a precolumn (nanoACQUITY UPLC Symmetry C18, 5 µm, 180 µm × 20 mm) (Waters, Manchester, UK) at a flow rate of 10 µL/min for 4 min with 99.9% A. Peptides were separated on an analytical column (ACQUITY UPLC HSS T3, 1.8 µm, 75 µm × 200 mm) (Waters, Manchester, UK) at a flow rate of 300 nL/min using a gradient from 3% to 35% B over 120 min. As a reference compound, 100 fmol/μL [Glu1]-fibrinopeptide B was delivered at 500 nL/min to the reference sprayer of the NanoLockSpray source. The SYNAPT G2S instrument was operated in a data-independent mode [
 <xref rid="B47-antioxidants-09-00919" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], characterized by parallel fragmentation of multiple precursor ions in combination with ion-mobility separation as an additional dimension of separation (referred to as HDMS
 <sup>E</sup>) [
 <xref rid="B48-antioxidants-09-00919" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. By executing alternate scans at low and elevated collision energy (CE) of each 0.5 s, information on precursor and fragment ions, respectively, was acquired. In low-energy MS mode, acquisitions were performed at constant CE of 4 eV, whereas drift time-dependent CE settings were applied in elevated-energy MS mode. The values of drift time-dependent CE settings were used as described [
 <xref rid="B49-antioxidants-09-00919" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Lock spray was acquired once every 30 s for a 1 s period. Mass spectrometric data were stored as raw data files.
</p>
