<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As with the use of any essential oil, there is care about possible allergic reactions or irritation of the skin with the use of lavender. The topical use of lavender is very common in perfumes, cosmetics, and cleaning products [
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>]. It is well reported that lavender has been frequently responsible for dermatitis [
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>, 
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>] and reactions to the sensitivity of other members of the Lamiaceae family [
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>]. It can be evidenced by the topical application of LEO in the highest concentrations, where an absence of anti-inflammatory effect was observed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Lavandula angustifolia</span> Mill. is characteristic of strong fragrance, indicating that there are rich aromatic compounds. The essential oil obtained from the leaves and stem is rich in monoterpene and phenols, and the GC-MS analysis showed that a predominance was due to 1,8-cineole, borneol, and camphor. The total amount of each of them was high, which suggests that the three chemical constituents in
  <span class="italic"> Lavandula angustifolia</span> Mill. leaves may play major roles in the biological activities and pharmacological properties. Another phytochemical study with this plant revealed the presence of the same major constituents of LEO, however, in different concentrations [
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>]. The chemical composition of essential oils may show variations due to geographic conditions, climate, seasonality, and extraction methods [
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>, 
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the literature, there is a great variety of studies demonstrating the activity of essential oils and compounds containing monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes, on the acute inflammatory response and immunomodulatory activity, for example, camphor, estragole, anethole,
  <span class="italic"> Citrus latifolia</span> essential oil, and
  <span class="italic"> Pogostemon cablin</span> essential oil, in models involving leukocyte chemotaxis, edema formation, cellular recruitment, and phagocytosis [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>, 
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>, 
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>–
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the cell viability assay, it was found that LEO in high concentrations (30 and 90 ug/ml) affected cell viability. However, at lower concentrations LEO was not proved to be cytotoxic. Confirming our results, a study reported that the essential oil of lavender has the cytotoxicity dose-dependent manner and can vary with its constituents [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>]. In a study performed by Alnamer et al. [
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>] it was observed that the oral administration of extract of
  <span class="italic"> Lavandula officinalis</span> is not toxic and does not cause significant changes in the body weight. This result indicates that the use in low concentrations can be considered safe.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The present study also evaluated a possible irritative effect of LEO at different concentrations on leukocyte chemotaxis
  <span class="italic"> in vitro</span>. The results showed that LEO did not stimulate the leukocyte chemotaxis, indicating the absence of a leukocyte migration stimulating effect of LEO.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In ear edema induced by croton oil, LEO reduced edema formation, MPO activity, and nitrite levels, but in high concentrations (2.5 mg/ear) this effect is not observed, and LEO did not reduce edema formation but rather presented an irritative response, increasing edema by 16.5% compared to croton oil. Several studies demonstrated that the lavender has an irritating effect after their exposure to the skin [
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>, 
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>]. The constituents present in the essential oil of lavender oxidize when exposed to air and can cause skin irritation [
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>]. Under such conditions, the topical use of lavender in perfumes, cosmetics, and cleaning products should be done with caution.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The croton oil is a phlogistic agent that induces an inflammatory response by activating phospholipase A
  <sub>2</sub> and initiating arachidonic acid metabolites involved in edema and leukocyte migration is associated with alterations in cytokine production and increased production of prostaglandins and leukotrienes [
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>]. Studies demonstrated anti-inflammatory activity of 1,8-cineole (as major constituent of LEO) by inhibition of cytokine production (such as tumor necrosis factor (TNF) and interleukin- (IL-) 1
  <span class="italic">β</span>) and arachidonic acid metabolism [
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>] and decrease of TNF and IL-1
  <span class="italic">β</span> production, nuclear factor kappa B (NF-
  <span class="italic">κ</span>B), and toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4) expression, and MPO activity in lung tissue in LPS-induced acute pulmonary inflammation in mice [
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">37</a>]. It has also been demonstrated that systemic administration of camphor (one of the major constituents of LEO) reduced the edema formation and MPO activity in croton oil-induced ear edema model [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>]. Thus, the anti-inflammatory effect of LEO may be attributable to a single or synergistic effect of its main components.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MPO is an indirect marker of neutrophil infiltration into tissue. Decreases in MPO activity suggest less neutrophil infiltration [
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">38</a>]. Studies with essential oils, monoterpenes, and sesquiterpenes have demonstrated reduction of MPO activity [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>, 
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">39</a>, 
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>]. In our study, the topical application of LEO reduced ear edema induced by croton oil, MPO activity, and NO levels, and a similar effect was observed with dexamethasone (reference drug). Based on our results, we suggest that topical treatment with LEO reduced leukocytes infiltration (observed in MPO activity) and it could be involved in the decrease of the NO production, as observed, and decrease of arachidonic acid metabolites.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nitric oxide (NO) is a signaling molecule that plays a key role in the pathogenesis of inflammation; NO may exhibit an anti-inflammatory effect under normal physiological conditions; however, it may play a proinflammatory role because of its excessive production in abnormal situations. NO has an important role in infection control, leukocyte migration, and cytokine production [
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>, 
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">42</a>]. In our study, topical treatment with LEO reduced NO production. It has been shown that treatment of PC
  <sub>12</sub> cells with LEO reduced the NO, TNF, IL-1
  <span class="italic">β</span>, and IL-6 production in 
  <span class="italic">β</span> amyloid peptide (A 
  <span class="italic">β</span>) induced inflammation [
  <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">43</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The development of the inflammatory response induced by carrageenan is characterized by two different phases: an initial stage (1-2 h) which is dependent on the release of histamine, serotonin, and bradykinin, followed by a later stage (3-4 h) which is primarily maintained by the release of prostanoids and NO in tissue [
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>, 
  <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">45</a>]. It was also observed that, in addition to these mediators, there is an increased production of proinflammatory cytokines, such as TNF, IL-1
  <span class="italic">β</span>, and IL-6 [
  <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">46</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A study demonstrated that 1,8-cineole (a major constituent of LEO) reduced edema formation in carrageenan-induced paw edema model in rats and mice, and the proposed mechanism was the reduction of prostaglandins and proinflammatory cytokines [
  <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">47</a>]. In another study, it was demonstrated that the
  <span class="italic"> Artemisia argyi</span> essential oil (containing camphor and borneol among the main constituents) inhibited edema formation in carrageenan-induced paw edema in rats [
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">48</a>]. Thus, we suggest that anti-inflammatory activity of LEO could be related to 1,8-cineole, borneol, and camphor, found as major constituents of this oil, and also to the other constituents.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our work, LEO at doses of 75 and 100 mg/kg inhibited edema formation already in first phase of carrageenan effect showing similar anti-inflammatory effects to COX antagonist (indomethacin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory, used as reference drug) and only dose of 250 mg/kg LEO treatment inhibited edema formation in the second phase of carrageenan induction with a similar effect to COX-2 selective antagonist (celecoxib, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory, used as reference drug). COX-2, an inducible enzyme found in activated inflammatory cells, plays a crucial role in cytokine production and prostanoid mediator release. The inhibition of COX-2 protein expression has been used to evaluate the anti-inflammatory effects of compounds
  <span class="italic"> in vivo</span> and
  <span class="italic"> in vitro</span> [
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">49</a>, 
  <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">50</a>]. These data show that possibly the mechanism of action of LEO is involved with inactivation of COX in carrageenan-induced paw edema.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additionally, LEO treatment decreased neutrophil infiltration (MPO activity) in a dose-dependent manner and NO production. We suggest that the anti-inflammatory activity of LEO could be, in part, involved with reduced prostanoids, proinflammatory cytokines, and NO production. In addition, the essential oil may be interfering with the production or release of vasoactive amines, such as serotonin and histamine.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also evaluated LEO on dextran-induced paw edema. Dextran is a high molecular weight polysaccharide, which, different to carrageenan, induces anaphylactic reactions characterized by extravasation and formation of edema which can be detected within the first 30 min after induction, due to mastocyte degranulation with release of histamine, serotonin, and other mediators [
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>]. In our work, LEO treatment at doses of 75 and 100 mg/kg reduced paw edema induced by dextran and MPO activity, suggesting decrease of neutrophil infiltration, and a similar effect was observed with promethazine (antihistaminic used as reference drug). This response could be attributable to the release of different autacoids, including histamine. Essential oils can promote the release of histamine and other mediators, acting as irritative agents [
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">52</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">NO is released under basal conditions and its production can be markedly stimulated by bradykinin, acetylcholine, and particularly histamine [
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">53</a>]. The receptor involved in nitric oxide release evoked by histamine must be of the H1, histaminergic subtype [
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">54</a>]. In this model LEO treatment did not show effect on NO production, indicating the LEO mechanism is probably not involved with H1 receptor. It has been demonstrated that
  <span class="italic"> Artemisia iwayomogi</span> extract, containing camphor and borneol (among the main constituents of LEO), inhibited compound 48/80–induced systemic reactions in mice and attenuated histamine release from rat peritoneal mast cells activated by compound 48/80 or IgE [
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">55</a>]. Furthermore, Kim and Cho [
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">56</a>] demonstrated that the essential oil of lavender, applied topically, inhibits histamine release from peritoneal mast cells induced by compound 48-80. Based on our results, we suggest that LEO may inhibit the release of histamine by mast cells.
 </p>
</sec>
