<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results</div>
 <sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Analysis of LEO</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The obtained pale yellow essential oil was dried over sodium sulfate and stored at 4°C in dark vials until tested. The yield of LEO was 0,14% v/w. The chemical composition of LEO was investigated by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS). The results of the GC-MS analysis (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1</a>) showed a predominance of 1,8-cineole (39,8%), endo-borneol (22,6%), and camphor (22,1%). A complete list of the components and their relative abundances are presented in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab1" href="#tab1">Table 1</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Cell Viability</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the cell viability assay, LEO at concentrations of 0.5, 1, 3, 10, 30, and 90 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/ml presented cell viability of 79, 77, 76, 76, 68, and 60%, respectively. Our data indicate that LEO has low cytotoxicity
   <span class="italic"> in vitro</span> at low concentrations, with cell viability greater than 75% up to a concentration of 10 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. 
   <span class="italic">In Vitro</span> Chemotactic Effect of LEO
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The present study evaluated the chemotactic effects of LEO at different concentrations (2, 15, and 150 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/ml) on leukocyte chemotaxis
   <span class="italic"> in vitro</span>. However, LEO did not increase leukocytes chemotaxis in any concentrations when compared to the vehicle (RPMI-1640). The fMLP (10
   <span class="sup">-6 </span>M) (positive control) induced a significant leukocyte migration (data not shown).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Effects of LEO on the Topical Inflammation Induced by Croton Oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The topical effect of LEO on ear edema induced by croton oil was demonstrated. Topical pretreatment with LEO (0.25, 0.5, and 1,0 mg/ear) reduced ear edema induced by croton oil by 59.6, 36.3, and 30.6%, respectively. Topical pretreatment with dexamethasone (0.1 mg/ear) (reference drug) reduced ear edema by 78.7% (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2(a)</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effects of LEO on MPO activity in ears tissues were also demonstrated. The activity of MPO was decreased in the group treated topically with LEO at concentrations of 0.25, 0.5, and 1.0 mg by 62.5%, 58.3, and 21.8%, respectively, compared with the control group. Dexamethasone reduced MPO activity by 82.5% (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2(b)</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The nitrite levels were used as parameters to evaluate the NO production in ears sections after croton oil-induced edema. The nitrite level increased significantly in the edema ear 6 h after croton oil topical application. Pretreatment with LEO (0.125, 0.25, 0.5, 1.0, 2.5, and 5.0 mg/ear) promoted a decrease in the nitrite levels by 80, 76, 80.2, 71.3, 82.3, and 81.3%, respectively. Dexamethasone also reduced nitrite level by 73.2% (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2(c)</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. Carrageenan-Induced Paw Edema in Mice</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The subcutaneous injection of carrageenan in the mouse paw promoted a local inflammatory response with edema peak in 6 h after carrageenan injection. As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4(a)</a>, when compared with positive control group, the treatment with LEO at 75 and 100 mg/kg significantly reduced the development of edema 2, 4, and 6 h after carrageenan injection, and LEO at dose of 75 mg/kg reduced paw edema by 48.7, 37.5, and 40.7%, respectively. At dose of 100 mg/kg, LEO treatment reduced paw edema by 65.7, 56.2, and 42.4%, respectively. The treatment with LEO at dose of 250 mg/kg significantly reduced the development of edema in 4 and 6 h after carrageenan injection by 39.6% and 44.1%, respectively. The treatment with indomethacin (reference drug) reduced the development of edema 2, 4, and 6 h after carrageenan injection by 42.3, 52.5, and 41.3%, respectively, and celecoxib (reference drug) reduced the development of edema 4 and 6 h after carrageenan injection by 40% and 37.18 (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3(a)</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The MPO enzyme activity was evaluated 6 h after edema induction. The treatment with LEO at doses of 75, 100, and 250 mg/kg significantly reduced the activity of MPO in 25%, 50.3%, and 59.4%, respectively, similar to indomethacin (57.1%) (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3(b)</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additionally, the concentration of nitrite levels was evaluated. The treatment with LEO at doses of 75, 100, and 200 mg/kg reduced significantly the nitrite levels by 36.7, 49.4, and 47.6%, respectively, and a similar effect was observed with indomethacin (reference drug) treatment, with 54.3% of reduction (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3(c)</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.6. Dextran-Induced Paw Edema in Mice</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The subcutaneous injection of dextran in the mouse paw caused a local inflammatory response with edema peak in the 1 h after injection. As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4(a)</a>, the treatment with LEO at 75 and 100 mg/kg significantly reduced the edema development in 30, 60, and 120 min after dextran injection, compared with control group. LEO treatment at dose of 75 mg/kg reduced edema by 40, 50, and 48.7%, at times of 30, 60, and 120 min, respectively, and at dose of 100 mg/kg, LEO treatment reduced paw edema by 53.8, 56.2, and 44.6%, respectively. Promethazine (reference drug) reduced the edema development at 30, 60, and 120 min, by 45.4, 60, and 67.9%, respectively (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4(a)</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The LEO treatment at doses of 75 and 100 mg/kg reduced significantly MPO activity by 57.4% and 62%, respectively, similar to effect observed with promethazine (65.1% of reduction). The LEO treatment at 50 and 250 mg/kg did not reduce significantly the MPO activity (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4(b)</a>). LEO treatment did not significantly reduce the nitrite levels in paw edema induced by dextran (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4(c)</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
