<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">Studies in the native and in the invaded range revealed that the effect of encroachment by woody species like 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> on SOC is context-dependent. Jackson et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> and Mureva et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup> found a negative relationship between precipitation and changes in SOC content when grasslands were invaded by woody vegetation, with drier sites gaining and wetter sites losing SOC. Due to the fact that overall losses of SOC at the wetter sites were substantial enough to offset increases in plant biomass carbon, Jackson et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> suggested that assessments relying on carbon stored from woody plant invasions to balance emissions may be incorrect. Our study provides evidence that the effect of 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> encroachment on SOC is also context-dependent. If 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> invades already degraded ecosystems, then it tends to increase SOC, particularly in the top 30 cm. In contrast, if 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> invades pristine or restored grasslands, it is likely to have no or potentially even a negative effect on SOC. Encroachment of grasslands by 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> leads to increased C stored in above-ground plant biomass, but plant biomass C in 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> invaded ecosystems is lower than the SOC pool in the upper 30 cm of the soil and considerably lower than the SOC pool down to 1 m (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>; Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref> online)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, plant biomass C stocks are more vulnerable to loss from fire, biomass harvesting and other disturbances
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. It is noteworthy that the sum of SOC and above-ground C of 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic>-high cover plots does not exceed that of pristine grasslands.
</p>
