<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">FT-IR (Fourier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy) is molecular vibrational spectroscopy that dissects chemical functional groups in the mid-infrared zone between 4000 and 400 cm
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>. The typical functional chemical groups in lipid, protein, and carbohydrate, such as C–H stretching vibration acyl chains, ester C=O stretching band, C=O stretching vibration, N–H bending vibration, C–O and C–O–C stretching band, and so on, have characteristic absorbance in different frequency regions of the mid-infrared zone. Moreover, FT-IR can directly scan the cultured microalgal cells for cellular composition analysis without complex procedures and organic or inorganic reagents which are necessities in the traditional biochemical methods [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-24-01593" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Thus, FT-IR has been a rapid, green, high throughput and cost-effective tool for monitoring and analysis of the microalgal cellular composition [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-24-01593" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-24-01593" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. The lipid content of 
 <italic class="italic">Thraustochytrium</italic> sp., belonging to the 
 <italic class="italic">Thraustochytrids</italic> same as 
 <italic class="italic">Aurantiochytrium</italic> sp., has been analyzed by the FT-IR technology for comparing with the marine oleaginous yeast [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-01593" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. The 
 <italic class="italic">Schizochytrium</italic> sp. cell was pyrolyzed, and the cellular lysates were analyzed by FT-IR method for cellular composition characterization [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-01593" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. The cellular composition of the 
 <italic class="italic">Aurantiochytrium</italic> sp. KRS101, including protein, lipid, carbohydrate, and ash, was been analyzed through FT-IR method [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-24-01593" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. However, the feasibility and reliability of FT-IR method for analyzing cellular composition in 
 <italic class="italic">Aurantiochytrium</italic> sp. have rarely evaluated comparing with the traditional biochemical methods. 
</p>
