<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Pomegranate peel is the dry peel of pomegranate, which accounts for about 30% of the total weight of pomegranate. It has abroad-spectrum antifungal effect and has obvious inhibitory effects on most Gram-negative bacteria, Gram-positive bacteria, fungi and molds. The fungistatic test in vitro showed that the inhibitory effect of ethanol, methanol and water extracts of pomegranate peel [
 <xref rid="B47-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>] on 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum</italic> (isolated from grapefruit, lemon and 
 <italic class="italic">C. sinensis</italic>) was not significantly different from that of the control with chemical fungicide (imazalil). Further study was conducted on the preservation effect of ethanol extracts of pomegranate peel (0.1, 0.5 and 1.0 g/L) on “Eureka” lemon. The ethanol extracts showed excellent preservation effects by being soaked to the fruit for 3 minutes. The study by Maria G. et al. [
 <xref rid="B48-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>] has also shown that in vitro trials revealed the pomegranate peel extract possess a strong fungicidal activity which against germination of conidia of 
 <italic class="italic">Botrytis cinerea</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">P. italicum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum and P. expansum</italic>. Almost complete inhibition of all fungal spore germination was achieved after 20h of incubation with pomegranate peel extract. At concentrations of 1.2 and 12 g/L complete inhibition of infection was achieved in the majority of host pathogen combinations. Mekbib et al. [
 <xref rid="B49-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>] studied the preservation effect of two Ethiopian plants (
 <italic class="italic">Withania somnifera</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Acacia seyal</italic>) methanol extract on “Valencia” 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic>. They can completely prevent the decay of the damaged fruit and reduce the decay rate of the fruit inoculated 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum</italic>, which is not significantly different from the chemical fungicide thiabendazole. 
</p>
