<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Since the appropriate inflammation in the wound area promotes the cell migration and skin tissue repair, the AA precursors, such as omega-6 and omega-9 fatty acids, may be responsible for the healing process because of their role as inflammatory modulators. Cardoso et al. [
 <xref rid="B105-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>] demonstrated that ALA (omega-3), LA (omega-6), and oleic acid (omega-9) modulated skin wound healing at different levels. The omega-9 fatty acid induced faster wound closure than omega-3 and omega-6 fatty acids. The wound treated with oleic acid followed by LA presented less edema compared with the control. Pereira et al. investigated the effect of LA and oleic acid on the inflammatory response of skin wounds and the cytokine release by rat neutrophils [
 <xref rid="B106-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>]. The animals treated with topical LA or oleic acid displayed a 60% greater reduction in the necrotic cell-layer thickness than the control. The number of neutrophils in the wound site was increased by LA (19.3) and oleic acid (24.6) as compared to the control (10.8). Oleic acid could stimulate the production of cytokine-induced neutrophil chemoattractant in inflammation 2 α/β (CINC-2α/β). Rodrigues et al. [
 <xref rid="B107-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">107</xref>] investigated the effect of oral LA (0.22 g/kg) for improving wound healing in streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats. LA reduced the wound area 14 days post-induction. The increased CINC-2α/β, TNF-α, and leukotriene B
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> and the increased leukocyte accumulation and angiogenesis by LA were responsible for the improved wound closure in the early healing phase. Laser ablation on the skin for an aesthetic regimen is often associated with erythema, edema, and crusting. Thirty-four subjects receiving fractional CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> laser treatment were enrolled for topical application of conjugated LA to determine the healing efficacy [
 <xref rid="B108-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">108</xref>]. Conjugated LA showing the ability to stimulate keratinocyte proliferation and epidermal regeneration was practical to reduce edema and itching at day 3 post-irradiation. The skin tolerated the topical conjugated LA well with no increased adverse effects. We summarize the information about the effect of fatty acids in fish oils on cutaneous wounds in 
 <xref rid="marinedrugs-16-00256-t004" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 4</xref>.
</p>
