<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">FAD2s are membrane-bound and contain three conserved histidine boxes (Hisbox 1, Hisbox 2, and Hisbox 3), which are essential to the iron binding and catalysis [
 <xref rid="B16-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. FAD2 is important in regulating the composition of fatty acids in seeds. The mutation of 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2-1A</italic> (S117N) and 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2-1B</italic> (P137R and I143T) genes produce high oleic acid soybeans [
 <xref rid="B7-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. The high oleic acid soybeans were also created by the suppression of 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2-1</italic> gene expression [
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. In peanuts, a MITE insertion into the 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2</italic> gene results in a high-oleate peanut [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. CRISPR/Cas9-mediated genome editing of the gene 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2</italic> in 
 <italic class="italic">B. napus</italic> increased the content of OA [
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Meanwhile, the loss of function mutations, E106K and G303E in BnFAD2-1 and BnFAD2-2, respectively, jointly regulated the high OA trait [
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. Besides the biosynthesis of fatty acids, previous studies have also revealed that 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2</italic> genes are crucial in plant responses to different environmental stresses. For example, the overexpression of the 
 <italic class="italic">PtFAD2</italic> gene in hybrid poplars can increase their freezing tolerance [
 <xref rid="B31-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. Arabidopsis 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2</italic> is required for salt tolerance during seed germination and early seedling growth [
 <xref rid="B4-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. In cotton, 
 <italic class="italic">FAD2</italic> genes play a direct role in adapting to cold stress [
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-20-00849" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. 
</p>
