<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">In this review, we have summarized the effectiveness of some traditional foods (plant, animal, and fungi species), which can consume together with different diets and cultural practices as spices, roots, mushrooms, and fermented food products having significant antiviral and immune-modulating effects against viral infections, including SARS-CoVs (Tables 
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The majority of such foods contain various phytochemical compounds like phenolic, flavonoids, alkaloids, polysaccharides, amino acids etc. and naturally occurring vitamins and minerals (e.g., vitamins C, D, B
 <sub>6</sub>, B
 <sub>12</sub>, A, E, and minerals of zinc, copper, iron, and selenium), which are immune protective and antiviral agents in different pathways (
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">López-Varela et al., 2002</xref>). Indeed, immune systems in the body are vital for confirming protection mechanisms against different ailments and the success of such systems against pathogenic microorganisms, including viruses, make sure the survival of humans. The aforementioned antiviral and immune modulating foods boost the body's specific immunity such as humoral and cell-mediated immunity and trigger various kinds of non-specific immune responses such as macrophages, NK cells, granulocytes, and complement systems, which increase resistance to infections. The activated immune cells increase the output of a variety of immune molecules such as cytokines, IFNs, and chemokines, which are involved in the improvement of immune responses (
 <xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>). Foods that contain glycyrrhizin and other sulphur-containing bioactive compounds such as sulphoxide, proteins and polyphenols promote the function of macrophages, T-lymphocytes, and several cytokines and reduce the formation of IL-12 and TNF-α (
 <xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015</xref>). In case of SARS-CoV-2 immunological studies, a number of immune molecules such as lymphocytes, dendrite and NK cells are exhausted that are very common in chronic viral infections. These findings suggest that the body loses their power to fight against invading pathogens (
 <xref rid="bib114" ref-type="bibr">Weiskopf et al. 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib110" ref-type="bibr">Zhan et al., 2006</xref>). Encouraging news is that early adaptive robust multi-factorial immune responses may ensure better clinical outcomes against SARS-CoV-2 affected patients (
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Thevarajan et al., 2020</xref>). On the other hand, a patient's age, gender, food habit, neuroendocrine-immune regulation and physical status are considered as the key regulating factors of an individual's immune system (
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Li, Genga, Penga, Menga and Lu, 2020</xref>). The mentioned factors play a key role in determining whether an individual is infected with a virus, the duration and severity of the diseases. Therefore, in the early stage as well as during the time of pandemic, the types of food which have significant evaluation against viral infection and immune development might be valuable complementary remedies against viral infections, including COVID-19. The statistics showed that older people are more vulnerable to COVID-19, where the highest death rate (13.4%) was recorded for people having 80 or over age compared to only 1.25% and 0.3% for 50s and 40s people, respectively (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Begley, 2020</xref>). Weak immune systems and pre-existing disease conditions have been attributed to these figures. The literature suggests that food containing potential antiviral as well as immune-modulating effects possess many phytochemical compounds, which have a long history to appear as healing agents against infectious diseases. Glycyrrhizin is the active component of licorice roots that inhibits the replication of SARS associated viruses (
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Cinatl et al., 2003</xref>). Furthermore, like other phytochemicals of food, the compounds of flavonoid groups have antioxidant as well as antiviral properties. They showed anti-corona virus effects by preventing virus entry, inhibiting 3C-like protease (3CLpro) of coronavirus and they are also able to block the enzymatic activity of MERS and SARS-CoV/3CLpro (
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Jo et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Jo et al., 2019</xref>). Moreover, some foods containing bioactive compounds also exhibited very strong antiviral and immune-modulating effects against SARS-CoV-2 homologous enveloped RNA viruses via preventing virus entry, transcription, and translation, replication, blocking viral enzymes, stimulating interferon secretion, and increasing cellular immunity (
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Hayashi et al., 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Luescher-Mattli, 2003</xref>). Therefore, our review demonstrated that selected traditional foods not only boost the body's immune systems and improve the respiratory problems but also progress the overall general health of the people. This could possibly reduce the risk of COVID-19 and initiate a rapid recovery in SARS-CoV-2 infection as like other viral infections. The current pandemic situation of SARS-CoV-2 makes us painfully realize that our ongoing strategies (social distancing, healthy measures, lockdown, quarantine and isolation etc.) to treat this fatal disease are not effective at all. Therefore, taking these traditional foods, which are easily available and consumable in daily diet chart, might play a great role to maintain a healthy immune system and to ensure proper general health. Finally, our reviews recommend people to include these traditional foods in the daily diet chart as a defensive measure in association with other health solutions to ensure protection against viral infections including today's global concern COVID-19 infection and also for keeping up efficient health management.
</p>
