<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Nuptial feeding has been documented in many arthropod mating systems (reviewed by Vahed, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref> and Gwynne, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Perhaps due to its greater burden of proof, the paternal investment hypothesis has rarely been invoked, but the mating effort hypothesis has been well supported in several species of cricket (Gershman, Mitchell, Sakaluk, &amp; Hunt, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Gordon, Gershman, &amp; Sakaluk, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Sakaluk, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>; Warwick, Vahed, Raubenheimer, &amp; Simpson, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Wedell, Tregenza, &amp; Simmons, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Cricket species which participate in nuptial feeding transfer a spermatophore which is composed of two parts: the sperm‐filled ampulla and a gelatinous bulb termed the spermatophylax. Both parts are eaten by the female: first the spermatophylax which covers the ampulla and then the ampulla which remains attached to the female reproductive tract while she is eating the spermatophylax (Warwick et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). It has been hypothesized that the spermatophylax in this cricket acts as a sensory trap through the use of free amino acids, which have been shown to have a phagostimulatory effect in insects (Calatayud et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>) and allow the male to transfer sperm for longer periods of time (Warwick et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Nuptial feeding has also been documented in the spider species 
 <italic class="italic">Pisaura mirabilis</italic> (Stålhandske, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>) and 
 <italic class="italic">Paratrechalea ornata</italic> (Albo &amp; Costa, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). The gifts in these systems are composed of prey items wrapped in silk; males present these gifts to females to increase their chance of mating, but the gifts have no effect on female fecundity or size of eggs, so it appears that these gifts likewise function as sensory traps (Albo &amp; Costa, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Stålhandske, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). While we have some knowledge of the biology of nuptial gifts in spiders, when it comes to the arachnid order Opiliones, commonly known as harvestmen, nuptial gifts remain entirely unexplored territory.
</p>
