<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">North American leiobunine harvestmen (Opiliones: Sclerosomatidae: Leiobuninae), often colloquially referred to as daddy‐longlegs, offer a compelling system for the study of nuptial gifts. These understudied arachnids participate in nuptial feeding via endogenous glandular secretions, but currently, there is no published research on the chemical composition or effects of the secreted substance on the female. Indeed, very little information has been published on reproductive biology in these animals generally; within the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Leiobunum,</italic> the mating behavior of only one species, 
 <italic class="italic">L. vittatum,</italic> has been studied in detail (Fowler‐Finn, Triana, &amp; Miller, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Macías‐Ordóñez, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>). While behavior associated with leiobunine reproduction is largely unexplored territory, the reproductive anatomy in this group has been the topic of several recent phylogenetic and biomechanical studies. Over the last 5 years, Burns, Shultz, and collaborators have documented the evolution of genitalia in this group, uncovering patterns of correlated evolution in male and female genital anatomy strongly suggestive of multiple evolutionary shifts from less antagonistic to more antagonistic interactions between males and females (Burns, Hedin, &amp; Shultz, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Burns &amp; Shultz, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Specifically, Burns et al. (
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) identified two broad categories of male leiobunine genital morphology: sacculate and nonsacculate. Sacculate species have a bilateral pair of cuticular sacs on the distal penis, which contain nuptial secretions produced in accessory glands (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34232-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). To initiate mating, the sacculate male engages in a face‐to‐face embrace, locking his pedipalps behind her second pair of coxae, and transfers a primary nuptial gift directly to the female's mouth. He then quickly withdraws and reorients the distal penis to the opening of the female's pregenital chamber. Copulation begins when the female relaxes her genital operculum and the male inserts the glans into the pregenital chamber. During this time, nuptial gift is issued from the accessory glands, the papillae of which are externalized when the penis is everted (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34232-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). This constitutes a secondary gift the female may gather as copulation proceeds. In nonsacculate species, mating begins in a similar way, but the primary nuptial gift transfer is omitted because penial sacs are not present (Burns et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Therefore, any acquisition of nuptial gift by the female occurs during clasping and manipulation by the male.
</p>
