<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">From the thermogravimetric analysis (TGA) curve, Andrade et al. [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] discovered three mass loss steps for the AgNP-β-CD. The first step referenced to the volatilization of residual water, while the second was related to the decay of β-CD molecules at 314 °C. The third step denoting extremely meager weight loss at 794 °C was ascribed to the deterioration of carbonaceous residues. As reported by Lin et al. [
 <xref rid="B76-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>], during the second stage of weight loss, it became evident that the decay of the CS/cellulose-AgNPs films was initiated at a temperature of 274.2 °C. Cano et al. [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] indicated that the TGA analysis of nano-biocomposites exhibited three degradation stages. The last peak appeared in the range of 550-800 °C and might refer to the oxidative decay of the carbonaceous residue that was produced during the second decomposition stage. Moreover, addition of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs exhibited no obvious influence on the thermal stability of the substances. Cano et al. [
 <xref rid="B78-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>] indicated the augmentation with the silver compound substantially diminished the thermal stability of the starch and PVA fractions contained in the film. Shankar et al. [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] indicated that all the films exhibited several stages of thermal degradation in the TGA curves. They also reported that the films containing ZnO NPs displayed improved thermal stability compared to the native gelatin film. Moreover, NC films exhibiting between three and four thermal decomposition steps were observed by Kadam et al. [
 <xref rid="B64-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. They demonstrated that the existence of degradation residue of NC specimens beyond 650 °C confirmed the presence of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-SiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs (TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> as core and SiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> as shell) in the samples. According to Arfat et al. [
 <xref rid="B90-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>], TGA analyses indicated that the addition of Ag-Cu NPs could enhanced the thermal stability of the NC films.
</p>
