<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As an important oil crop, oil is one of the most important accumulated nutrients in the growth and development process of the fruit of 
 <italic class="italic">Camellia oleifera</italic>. The main component of vegetable oil is triacylglycerol (TAG), which results from glycerol-3-phosphate (G3P) and fatty acid CoA condensation 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>. The glycolytic metabolic pathway is the upstream metabolic pathway of 
 <italic class="italic">Camellia oleifera</italic> fruit oil synthesis; the intermediate product dihydroxyacetone phosphate (DHAP) of the glycolytic pathway is reduced to G3P by glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GPD1) catalyst 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>. The pyruvate dehydrogenase complex converts pyruvate, which is the final product of glycolysis, into acetyl-CoA, then acetyl-CoA is carboxylated by acetyl CoA carboxylase (ACCase) to malonyl-CoA which is the substrate for biological fatty acid synthesis 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>. β-D-fructose-6-phosphate is one of the important intermediates in glycolysis and it has a very wide range of sources. One major source of it is the conversion of L-sorbose-1-phosphate to D-sorbitol-6-phosphate by the reversible catalysis of sorbitol-6-phosphate 2-dehydrogenase, then the reverse catalysis of the sorbitol-6-phosphate 2-dehydrogenase to β-D-fructose-6-phosphate. In this study, we found that miR156 target butanol dehydrogenase was up-regulated (Table 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM0" class="xref">S8</xref> and Table 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM0" class="xref">S9</xref>), which may be involved in increasing the β-D-fructose-6-phosphate to promote glycolysis. In nature, acetyl-CoA carboxylase has two functional forms and each contains the four different components required for activity: biotin carboxylase, biotin carboxyl carrier protein, α- carboxyl transferases and β-carboxyl transferases. One form is heteromeric, in which the all four enzymatic components as individual subunits are combined into a multienzyme complex. The other form is homomeric, whereby all four enzymatic components are concatenated into a single polypeptide, and is the predominant form for 
 <italic class="italic">de novo</italic> fatty acid synthesis 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>. In fruit, miR477 induced the target acetyl-CoA carboxylase carboxyl transferase subunit alpha up-regulated (Table 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM0" class="xref">S8</xref> and Table 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM0" class="xref">S9</xref>), and it may be related to increasing the efficiency of fatty acid synthesis. There are two major biochemical pathways of linoleic acid (LA) to oxidized LA metabolites (OXLAMs) in LA metabolism; they begin with formation of the conjugated hydroperoxydienes 9- hydroperoxyoctadecadienoic acid (9-HPODE) and 13- hydroperoxyoctadecadienoic acid (13-HPODE), which are then rapidly reduced by glutathione-dependent peroxidase to the alcohols 9-hydroxy-octadecadienoic acid (9-HODE) and 13-hydroxy-octadecadienoic acid (13-HODE), respectively. Finally, the 9-HODE and 13-HODE can be converted to the ketones 9-oxo-octadecadienoic acid (9-oxoODE) and 13-oxo-octadecadienoic acid (13-oxoODE) via hydroxy-fatty acid dehydrogenase, respectively. MiR156 targets butanol dehydrogenase up-regulated expression (Table 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM0" class="xref">S8</xref> and Table 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM0" class="xref">S9</xref>) which will be beneficial to the 13-HODE transformed to 13-oxoODE, which may be related to the relative content of LA being decreased in 
 <italic class="italic">Camellia oleifera</italic> fruit during the ripening process 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>.
</p>
