<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par53" class="p">However, the conversion of cholesterol to testosterone in Leydig cells, the cholesterol is done in several stages and is under the action of different enzymes for each [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>]. The free cholesterol tranfer of the extacellular and intracellular medium to the internal mitochondrial membrane is Limiting stage of steroidogenesis and it is mainly mediated by acute steroids-regulators. (StAR) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>]. The physiological action of this protein depends on many internal factors such as PGF levels, COX-2 activity and exogenous factors by the overproduction of free radicals in a complex relationship still poorly understood [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>]. StAR is also susceptible to a variety of pesticides as confirmed by Walsh et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>]. Steroidogenesis involves numerous steps in the synthesis of cholesterol to its transport within steroidogenic tissues and then its metabolism to steroids. Under normal physiological conditions, the collection of cholesterol by steroidogenic cells from free cholesterol circulating in the blood and high density / low density lipoprotein (HDL / LDL). In our previous studies, the administration of malathion at 200 mg / kg / day caused an imbalance in metabolic parameters marked by decreased plasma HDL cholesterol with elevated cholesterol, triglyceride and VLDL-CL levels [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>]. Furthermore, malathion causes a decrease in the transport and use of cholesterol for steroidogenesis which explains this dyslipidemia. In addition, Barlow et al., [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>] established that decreased cholesterol synthesis results in the downregulation of steroidogenesis. On the other hand, the subchronic LSEO co-administration considerably improves dyslipidemia induced by malathion in male mice. In addition, the rate of these parameters has been returned to near normal.
</p>
