<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Various extracts and essential oil obtained from the 
 <italic>A. conyzoides</italic> plant have been screened to identify the molecular mechanisms underlying their antifungal activity or how these compounds target pathogenic microbes. Chief antifungal compounds isolated from 
 <italic>A. conyzoides</italic> were effective against a number of obsessive strains either by precluding cell growth and reproduction or by eradicating the fungal cells directly (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-02933-f004">Figure 4</xref>). In conjunction, these compounds can also proficiently obstruct the discharge of toxic mycotoxins. Inhibition of various fungi by diverse mechanisms also satisfies the requisite aptitude needed for the development of novel anti-resistant antifungals. Khastini et al. [
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] observed that aqueous and ether extracts of 
 <italic>Ageratum</italic> leaves inhibited fungal growth by halting the formation of germ tubes by spores in the presence of the tested fungi, which is crucial for the microorganism’s survival because new hyphae formation can only begin with the germ tubes. Studies substantiating the MOA of precocene II conclude that the compound exhibits its activity either by retarding fungal growth or by stopping the release of mycotoxins such as aflatoxins (B
 <sub>1</sub>, B
 <sub>2</sub>, G
 <sub>1</sub> and G
 <sub>2</sub>) and trichothecenes. Yaguchi et al. [
 <xref rid="B115-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>] suggested that precocene II can inhibit deoxynivalenol biosynthesis, a contaminant released by 
 <italic>F. graminearum</italic> that reduces grain utilization. When analyzed for its mechanism of action, precocene II was found to reduce the mRNA intensities of encoding proteins requisite for deoxynivalenol biosynthesis without inhibiting fungal growth. In their investigations of the fungus 
 <italic>A. flavus</italic>, Nogueira et al. [
 <xref rid="B92-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>] showed that variable concentrations of 
 <italic>A. conyzoides</italic> essential oil checked mycelial growth at different magnitudes. However, at 0.10 μL/mL concentration, aflatoxin B
 <sub>1</sub> production was withdrawn completely. TEM (transmission electron microscopy) analysis revealed ultra-structural deviations in the cytoplasm and cell wall of fungal cells treated with various oil concentrations in comparison with untreated cells. The molecular mechanism involved the destruction and deletion of electron-dense granules (EDGs) from fungal cells, whereas the plasma membrane became villiform and rough and sometimes decoupled with the cell wall. Mitochondrial cristae ridge polarization experienced a decline, which led to disruption of the internal structure of the organelle. Predominantly, mitochondria and plasma membrane swallowed the pathologic alterations and suffered irreversible morphological vicissitudes.
</p>
