<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bioactive compounds from petals have shown antinociceptive, anti-inflammatory [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], cytotoxic, antimicrobial, antioxidant, antidiabetic [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], antiobesity [
 <xref rid="B33-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], antidepressant [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], anticancer, antityrosinase properties, as well as reduce blood pressure and contractility [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Several phenolic compounds from saffron leaves have been identified, showing antibacterial [
 <xref rid="B36-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], anticancer [
 <xref rid="B30-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], antioxidant, and metal ion chelating activities [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Likewise, bioactive constituents in saffron corm, such as proteoglycans, revealed to have a cytolytic effect on human tumor and plant cells and triterpenoid saponins on fungicidal and anticancer activities [
 <xref rid="B30-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Polyphenols showing antibacterial, radical scavenging activity [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], and a mannan-binding lectin [
 <xref rid="B41-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] have also been investigated in saffron corms. The existing experimental analysis aimed to explore the anti-inflammatory, analgesic, anticoagulant, and antidepressant potentials of various extracts of 
 <italic>Crocus sativus</italic> L. in mice by carrageenan-induced paw edema test, hot plate assay, capillary method, and forced swim test, respectively. Up to now, ethanolic extracts of stigma, petals, corms, and leaves of in vivo cultivated saffron have not been previously studied for their nutraceutical properties against analgesia, inflammation, coagulation, and depression.
</p>
