<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The biosphere is microbially rich. However, after nearly 200 years of microbiology discovery research, we still know very little about the microbial diversity around us (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Epstein, 2013</xref>). Most microorganisms in the natural environment are difficult or impossible to obtain pure culture by traditional culture separation methods. Traditionally, microbiologists try to increase the separation of microorganisms by changing the nutrient composition and culture conditions of these classic media (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Achtman and Wagner, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Epstein, 2013</xref>). In this study, to isolate as many endophytes as possible and simulate the artificial environment as much as possible, 20 different media, including oligotrophic media, were used along with the conventionally diluted media. Generally, PDA medium is the most commonly used medium for the isolation of endophytes, in which, potato extract is the main natural complex component that affects the isolation of endophytes, and artificial medium cannot fully match. The potato as a tuber plant was used as a natural medium, therefore, other tuber plants such as lily, sweet potato, yam and carrot were also used as natural medium components for the separation of endophytes in here. However, the above natural medium is sufficiently nutritious, and rapid growth of dominant strains would inhibit the growth of other non-dominant strains, resulting in a decrease in the number and abundance of endophytes. Studies have shown that by reducing the nutrient concentration of traditional medium to prepare the oligotrophic state, and appropriately extending the incubation time, some microorganisms that cannot be separated from the classical medium can be obtained (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Davis et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Epstein, 2013</xref>). Therefore, a variety of oligotrophic media were prepared with 100-fold diluted natural medium and were used in the experiment to isolate the endophytes. The results showed that the separation efficiency of the 100-fold diluted natural medium was higher than that of the original medium, which 100-fold diluted yam medium was the highest.
</p>
