<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A bioassay system was used to evaluate the activity of the three studied EOs using the area preference method [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-10-00829" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. A filter paper disk (Whatman No. 1, 8 cm diameter, area = 54.4 cm
 <sup>2</sup>) was divided into 2 halves, one of which was then treated with 0.5 mL of acetonic solutions of EOs, and the control half was treated with an equal volume of acetone. The four replicates from EOs acetone solutions were tested corresponding to the doses of 0.25, 0.5, and 0.75 mg/cm
 <sup>2</sup> compared with the positive control treatment (malathion, 4 ppm) as chemical control. The treated and control filter paper half were air-dried for about 60 min, allowing solvent evaporation. After that, the paper disc was joined and fixed on the bottom of a Petri dish, and 10 3–7 days old, unsexed adults were then released in the center of both halves. The experiment was maintained at 28 ± 2 °C and 65 ± 5% RH in a dark place. Repellency percentage was recorded at 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5 h depending on the number of insects noticed on both treated and untreated halves. Percentage repellency was calculated by the following equation:
 <disp-formula id="FD1-plants-10-00829">
  <label>(1)</label>
  <math id="mm1">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>Repellence</mi>
     <mo> </mo>
     <mo>(</mo>
     <mo>%</mo>
     <mo>)</mo>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mo> </mo>
     <mfenced>
      <mrow>
       <mi>N</mi>
       <mi>c</mi>
       <mo>−</mo>
       <mi>N</mi>
       <mi>t</mi>
      </mrow>
     </mfenced>
     <mo>/</mo>
     <mfenced>
      <mrow>
       <mi>N</mi>
       <mi>c</mi>
       <mo>+</mo>
       <mi>N</mi>
       <mi>t</mi>
      </mrow>
     </mfenced>
     <mo> </mo>
     <mo>×</mo>
     <mo> </mo>
     <mn>100</mn>
     <mo>,</mo>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <italic>Nc</italic> = the number of insects on the untreated half, and 
 <italic>Nt</italic> = the number of insects on the treated half, after the time exposure.
</p>
