<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Abs1" class="abstract" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been recently recognized that oxidative stress, helminth and microbial infections are the cause of much illness found in the underdeveloped, developing and developed countries. The present study was undertaken to identify the chemical composition, and to assess anthelmintic, antimicrobial and antioxidant effects of 
   <span class="italic">Thymus bovei</span> essential oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chemical composition of the essential oil was analyzed using gas chromatography mass spectrometry (GC-MS). Antimicrobial activity was tested against the selected strains from American Type Culture Collection (ATCC) and clinical isolates such as 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Escherichia coli, Pseudomonas aeruginosa,</span> Methicillin Resistant 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span> using MIC assay. The anthelmintic assay was carried out on adult earthworm (
   <span class="italic">Pheretima posthuma</span>), while antioxidant activity was analyzed using the 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) free radical scavenging method.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trans-geraniol (35.38 %), α-citral (20.37 %) and β-citral (14.76 %) were the major compounds comprising 70.51 % of the essential oil. Our results showed that 
   <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> essential oil exhibited strong anthelmintic activity, even higher than piperazine citrate, the used reference standard, with potential antioxidant activity almost equal to the Trolox standard. Furthermore, 
   <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> essential oil had powerful antibacterial and antifungal activities against the studied pathogens.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> exerted excellent antioxidant, antimicrobial, and anthelmintic activities. Moreover, this study found that 
   <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> volatile oil contains active substances that could potentially be used as natural preservatives in food and pharmaceutical industries, these substances could also be employed for developing new anthelmintic, antimicrobial and antioxidant agents.
  </p>
 </sec>
</div>
