<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> gene (Wuhan‐Hu‐1, NC_045512.2, region 10,055–10,972) which is 918 base pair synthesized in pEXA2 vector was procured from Eurofins Genomics, Japan and was used for sub cloning in protein expression vector since it has been designed with BamHI and XhoI restriction enzyme sites. The digested desired gene insert was purified and ligated to a modified pET‐28a vector between BamHI and XhoI sites. This modified vector contains the sequences coding for PreScission, flag tag, and hexahistidine. The cloned gene in the pET‐28a vector was subjected to protein expression. After analyzing the soluble expressions from various expressing strains of 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, we chose BL‐21DE3 Rosetta RIL cells for expressing the protein. The 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> protein tagged with 6‐histidines at N‐terminal end was expressed using an auto‐induction method of protein production with appropriate antibiotics kanamycin (50 μg/ml) and chloramphenicol (34 μg/ml; Studier, 
 <xref rid="ptr6802-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). The cells were first cultured for 2 hr at +37°C, further grown at +18°C for 18 hr. The cells were harvested by centrifugation, and the pellet was re‐suspended in buffer A (50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 500 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 10 mM Imidazole) containing protease inhibitors 1 mM DTT, 0.5 mM PMSF and DNAseI 0.001 mg/ml with 5 mM MgCl
 <sub>2</sub>. The cells were lysed by adding lysozyme having final concentration 1 mg/ml and disrupted by sonication on ice with 30 s ON and 30 s OFF for 10 min, and the lysate was clarified by centrifugation at 10,000
 <italic>g</italic> for 30 min. The clear lysate was applied onto a Ni‐NTA column pre‐equilibrated with buffer A on ÄKTA™ start FPLC system (GE Healthcare). The column was washed with 100 mL of Buffer A, and 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> protein was eluted with gradient elution 0–500 mM imidazole in buffer A. The fractions were analyzed on SDS‐PAGE for purity. The eluted fractions were pooled, dialyzed, and purified through QFF anion exchange chromatography with a linear gradient of NaCl (0–500 mM). The purified protein was homogeneous with about &gt;95% purity and confirmed with western blot analysis. Fractions containing 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> protein were pooled and cleaved with recombinant Precision protease at +4°C overnight. The overnight cleaved protein was reapplied on the Ni‐NTA column and the unbound sample has been collected. It was concentrated, buffer exchanged (20 mM Tris HCl pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 10% Glycerol, and 1 mM DTT), flash frozen and stored at −80°C for all biochemical and biophysical studies.
</p>
