<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="bullet">
 <list-item>
  <p>Among all plant parts, leaves are widely studied for scolicidal activities, other plant parts should also be investigated for active compounds against CE.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>In future active phytochemicals of plants with high efficiency against 
   <italic>E</italic>. 
   <italic>granulosus</italic> should be investigated separately, that would be helpful to identify and quantify the efficacy of each and every individual compound.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Among the pure compounds isolated from plants reported in this review, thymoquinone showed a remarkable 
   <italic>in vitro</italic> scolicidal activity with a minimum concentration of 1 mg/ml and 1 min of exposure time. However, its toxicity levels and 
   <italic>in vivo</italic> efficacy has not been documented yet. It is highly recommended to further exploit the efficacy of this compound using 
   <italic>in vivo</italic> models and its toxicity levels in the future.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>The mechanisms of action of plant-based compounds should be investigated in order to thoroughly understand and make improvements in the pharmacological and therapeutic properties of these compounds.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Most of the plant’s scolicidal activities have been tested by 
   <italic>in vitro</italic> studies, only few studies reported the 
   <italic>in vivo</italic> efficacy of medicinal plants, it is recommended to explore the 
   <italic>in vivo</italic> biological activities of different plants against 
   <italic>E</italic>. 
   <italic>granulosus</italic> to understand more in-depth scolicidal efficacy.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>The knowledge about the toxicity of the plants reviewed in the article is very scarce, hence, further research should be carried out to exploit the toxicity levels of various plants and their active components.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Most of the medicinal plants and their compounds are evaluated against the common G1 genotype of 
   <italic>E</italic>. 
   <italic>granulosus</italic> focus should be given to other genotypes of 
   <italic>E</italic>. 
   <italic>granulosus</italic> in order to thoroughly understand the efficacy of medicinal plants against other genotypes.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>More focus should be given on parasitocidal rather than parasitotatic (or anti-parasitic) activities of medicinal plants and their constituents.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>More than 68.3% of pharmacological studies are carried out in Iran while the remaining 32.0% in other countries of the world, hence researchers are invited from all over the world to explore the medicinal plants against 
   <italic>E</italic>. 
   <italic>granulosus</italic> for the development of novel and cost effective scolicidal agent to control this zoonotic helminthiasis.
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
