<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to a 2001 World Health Organization (WHO) report, 25% of the world population is suffering from neurological disorders like epilepsy, headache, migraine, madness, insomnia, stress, depression, Alzheimer’s (AD), and Parkinson’s diseases [
 <xref rid="B1-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. AD is a chronic neurodegenerative disease where the deposition of neuronal amyloid along with a deficit of neurotransmitters; acetylcholine (ACh) level occurs, leading to memory dysfunction [
 <xref rid="B2-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Oxidative stress has been pointed to be main factor involved in the pathogenesis of AD. Another predominant reason is the reduction of acetylcholine level in the brain, which is the most notable biochemical change in AD. Acetyl cholinesterase (AChE) and butyryl cholinesterase (BChE) are the key enzymes that causes the degradation of ACh resulting in cholinergic deficits and termination of cholinergic neurotransmission. Thus, the inhibition of cholinesterases is considered to be the base while treating AD and this promising strategy is clinically applied everywhere for treating neurodegenerative diseases and is a rational approach. Inhibition of brain cholinesterases (AChE and BChE) by potential inhibitors reinstates the level of ACh and, thus, plays an important role in the treatment of AD, Dementia, and Parkinson’s disease [
 <xref rid="B3-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and the consequences of cholinesterases inhibition are assessed by observing cholinergically mediated processes such as cognition [
 <xref rid="B4-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Acetylcholine is a key neurotransmitter in the nervous system that interacts with receptors associated with processes of learning and memory. It has been proved that cholinesterase inhibition is a preferable direct receptor agonist therapy that relives ACh deficit and stimulates either nicotinic or muscarinic ACh receptors. Cholinesterases inhibitors like Donepezil are approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the symptomatic treatment of AD. These drugs improve cognitive and neuropsychiatric symptoms. Donepezil is a second-generation cholinesterases inhibitor with a high selectivity in the central nervous system, can reversibly inhibit cholinesterases (AChE and BChE) whereby reducing ACh degradation, thus increase neurotransmitter concentration in the synaptic cleft that prolongs its duration of action, ultimately elevating the central cholinergic activity to improve cognitive function. The use of donepezil seems to have a positive effect on the functioning and enhancements in cognition [
 <xref rid="B5-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].
</p>
