<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Ferula ammoniacum</italic> (D. Don) 
 <italic>Spalik</italic>, 
 <italic>M. panahi</italic>, 
 <italic>Piwczynski</italic> and 
 <italic>Puchalka</italic>, is an important members of family Apiaceae also known as 
 <italic>Dorema ammoniacum</italic> (D. Don) [
 <xref rid="B15-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], has a wide variety of traditional uses, for example, it produces gum which exude from stem, roots, and petioles that is medicinally used to treat a number of diseases. This gum resin is traditionally used as a carminative, diaphoretic, mild diuretic, expectorant, stimulant, cardiovascular, anthelmintic, antiepileptic, asthmatic, and antitussive. 
 <italic>D. ammoniacum</italic> gum resin has anti-helminthic potentials and has been used to treat gastrointestinal disorders and as anti-inflammatory agent in Iranian traditional medicine [
 <xref rid="B16-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Its latex has also medicinal uses like expectorant, bronchitis, and stomach-ache [
 <xref rid="B17-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Ghasemi et al. (2018) elucidates the electrophysiological mechanism of the effect of 
 <italic>D. ammoniacum</italic> gum on a cellular model of epilepsy, using intracellular recording method [
 <xref rid="B18-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. 
 <italic>D. ammoniacum</italic> gum resin has shown a significant anticonvulsant activity in pentylentetrazole model (in mice) in a dose dependent manner via involvement of GABAergic and opioid systems [
 <xref rid="B19-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The gum resin has exhibited significant acetylcholine esterase inhibitory potential [
 <xref rid="B20-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and antimicrobial activities [
 <xref rid="B21-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Apart from the mentioned potentials, 
 <italic>D. ammoniacum</italic> have also exhibited other pharmacological effects, including anxiolytic, anti-inflammatory, anti-coagulation, anti-epileptogenic and anticonvulsant [
 <xref rid="B17-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In Persian traditional medicine textbooks, 
 <italic>D. ammoniacum</italic> is one of the materia medica that is frequently used for stroke and paralysis as it opens the blood vessels and is also considered as a thrombolytic agent. In traditional medicines, it is used as a remedy by itself and sometimes it is used in combination with other drugs to treat health complications like stroke and paralysis [
 <xref rid="B22-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The essential oil of 
 <italic>D. ammoniacum</italic> leaf, fruit, and stem have already been reported to have antioxidant, antimicrobial, and low cytotoxicity activities [
 <xref rid="B23-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Chemical composition of essential oil and toxicological studies like acute and sub-acute toxicity of 
 <italic>D. ammoniacum</italic> oleo-gum-resin has also been reported [
 <xref rid="B25-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Antibacterial and vasodilatory effects of this herbal plant have also been reported [
 <xref rid="B26-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. 
 <italic>D. ammoniacum</italic> aerial part extract has been used as a mediator in the synthesis of silver nanoparticles that have displayed antimicrobial activities [
 <xref rid="B27-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The 
 <italic>Dorema</italic> other species are also traditionally used as anticancer, antimicrobial, insecticidal, and as antioxidant agents [
 <xref rid="B28-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. However, its effect as nootropic agent has not been investigated yet. 
</p>
