<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par36">A synoptic table of inventoried medicinal plants and their use in Kisantu and Mbanza-Ngungu territories is presented in an additional file, available on 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.mendeley.com/datasets/4cf2p3mgpc/1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://data.mendeley.com/datasets/4cf2p3mgpc/1</ext-link>. MS Excel 2013 was used to process the data. Differences of traditional medicinal knowledge between Kongo social groups were analyzed using SPSS 25. Mann-Whitney and Kruskal-Wallis non-parametric tests as well as Poisson regression were employed to analyze differences in disease and medicinal plant knowledge between different social groups (distinguished according to gender, age, experience, education, marital status, categories, and residence). Results of Poisson regression, Mann-Whitney, and Kruskal-Wallis tests were considered as statistically significant for 
 <italic>p</italic> values &lt; 0.05. For ethno-cultural comparison between Kisantu (inhabited mainly by the Ntându ethnic group) and Mbanza-Ngungu (inhabited mainly by the Ndibu ethnic group) and between urban and rural respondents, we used the Rahman similarity index (RSI), which indicates the similarity of species used for treating the same diseases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. We assume that two communities are culturally closer if they use the same species to treat the same diseases. 
 <disp-formula id="Equ5">
  <label>5</label>
  <alternatives>
   <tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$ RSI\ \left(\%\right)=\frac{d}{a+b+c-d} $$\end{document}</tex-math>
   <math id="M10" display="block">
    <mi mathvariant="italic">RSI</mi>
    <mspace width="0.25em"/>
    <mfenced close=")" open="(">
     <mo>%</mo>
    </mfenced>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mfrac>
     <mi>d</mi>
     <mrow>
      <mi>a</mi>
      <mo>+</mo>
      <mi>b</mi>
      <mo>+</mo>
      <mi>c</mi>
      <mo>−</mo>
      <mi>d</mi>
     </mrow>
    </mfrac>
    <mspace width="0.25em"/>
   </math>
   <graphic xlink:href="13002_2020_428_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula>in which “a” is the number of unique species in community A, “b” is the number of unique species in community B, “c” is the number of common species in both A and B communities, and “d” is the number of common species in both A and B communities that are used to treat the same disease; 
 <italic>a</italic> and 
 <italic>b</italic> ≠ 0 and 
 <italic>c</italic> and 
 <italic>d</italic> ≥ 0.
</p>
