<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The identified relevant endpoints of concern for NMs (i.e., chronic, longer term and mechanistic) and a list of appropriate testing methods [
 <xref rid="B68-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], should in principle also be applicable to NBMs, as long as the required adaptations are included as suggested by Hund-Rinke et al., 2016 [
 <xref rid="B76-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>] and Amorim et al., 2018 [
 <xref rid="B77-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. For the latest update including the recommended adaptations to OECD guidelines for testing the environmental hazard of NBMs please see Amorim et al., 2020 [
 <xref rid="B22-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. To increase the efficiency of testing, these methods should be implemented onto IATAs, where grouping and read-across approaches are combined with testing methods and non-testing in silico models to generate data for ERA according to a tiered approach [
 <xref rid="B78-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B79-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. A wide number of in silico tools for NMs have been developed in recent years [
 <xref rid="B81-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>] and can be applied to derive data of relevance for risk assessment. Moreover, omics-techniques, including key initiating events and pathway analyses, hold great potential [
 <xref rid="B70-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. These techniques are highly relevant for NBMs used in MD and ATMP, as they have been developed with a specific biological purpose and therefore prior information on their mode of toxic action is available. Further, in vitro approaches in environmental organisms have also gained increasing interest, as they allow for a quick identification of relative toxicity, of possible mode of action and of what happens with a NBM when in contact with environmental media and after uptake by organisms, e.g., corona formation [
 <xref rid="B83-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. The latter will not only inform on possible mode of action, but also be highly relevant for supporting read-across between species. Furthermore, since MDs and ATMPs will obviously be, in most cases, in contact with human tissues, excreted NBMs will have a biological corona formed that will influence their behaviour and toxicity, and therefore their environmental risks.
</p>
