<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>This study isolated and identified endophytic bacteria from the leaves of 
  <italic>Crinum macowanii</italic> and investigated the potential of the bacterial endophyte extracts as antibacterial and anticancer agents and their subsequent secondary metabolites. Ethyl acetate extracts from the endophytes and the leaves (methanol: dichloromethane (1 : 1)) were used for antibacterial activity against selected pathogenic bacterial strains by using the broth microdilution method. The anticancer activity against the U87MG glioblastoma and A549 lung carcinoma cells was determined by the MTS (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-5-(3-carboxymethoxy-phenyl)-2-(4-sulfophenyl)-2H-tetrazolium) assay. Bacterial endophytes that were successfully isolated from 
  <italic>C. macowanii</italic> leaves include 
  <italic>Raoultella ornithinolytica</italic>, 
  <italic>Acinetobacter guillouiae</italic>, 
  <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp., 
  <italic>Pseudomonas palleroniana</italic>, 
  <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic>, 
  <italic>Bacillus safensis</italic>, 
  <italic>Enterobacter asburiae</italic>, 
  <italic>Pseudomonas cichorii</italic>, and 
  <italic>Arthrobacter pascens</italic>. 
  <italic>Pseudomonas cichorii</italic> exhibited broad antibacterial activity against both Gram-negative and Gram-positive pathogenic bacteria while 
  <italic>Arthrobacter pascens</italic> displayed the least MIC of 0.0625 mg/mL. 
  <italic>Bacillus safensis</italic> crude extracts were the only sample that showed notable cell reduction of 50% against A549 lung carcinoma cells at a concentration of 100 
  <italic>μ</italic>g/mL. Metabolite profiling of 
  <italic>Bacillus safensis</italic>, 
  <italic>Pseudomonas cichorii</italic>, and 
  <italic>Arthrobacter pascens</italic> crude extracts revealed the presence of known antibacterial and/or anticancer agents such as lycorine (1), angustine (2), crinamidine (3), vasicinol (4), and powelline. It can be concluded that the crude bacterial endophyte extracts obtained from 
  <italic>C. macowanii</italic> leaves can biosynthesize bioactive compounds and can be bioprospected for medical application into antibacterial and anticancer agents.
 </p>
</abstract>
