<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ginseng is a traditional medicinal herb and is consumed worldwide due to its broad pharmacological activity. Ginsenosides are the main active compounds in ginseng and have unique biological activities and medicinal values. There are various processed ginseng products (such as fresh ginseng, white ginseng, boiled ginseng, steamed ginseng, acid-processed ginseng, and fermented ginseng). The variation in the ginsenoside compositions of ginseng products may be a function of the processing method and may underlie the differing pharmacological properties of ginseng products. The diversity of the main ginsenosides in different ginseng species may also reflect the environments and regions where ginseng plants are grown. In particular, PPT- and PPD-type ginsenosides are abundant in 
 <italic>Panax ginseng</italic>, 
 <italic>P. quinquefolius,</italic> and 
 <italic>P. notoginseng</italic>; and 
 <italic>P. japonicasi,</italic> while 
 <italic>P. vietnamensis</italic> contains OT-type ginsenosides as the main saponins. In contrast, OA-type saponins are rich in other species of ginseng (
 <italic>P. zingiberensi, P. stipuleanatus, P. bipinnatifidus</italic>, and 
 <italic>P. sokpayensis</italic>). In addition, chemical reactions during the physical and chemical processing of ginseng, such as demalonylation, deglycosylation, acetylation, hydrolysis, addition reactions, and dehydration, may result in the generation of more biologically active saponins compared to fresh ginseng. Moreover, several minor and unnatural ginsenosides are formed during biological processing of ginseng by enzyme/microbial biotransformation or glycosylation catalyzed by various glycosyltransferases. Processed ginseng products may contain a diverse array of main ginsenosides and biological activities; therefore, future studies addressing the use of a combination of several processing methods to increase the concentrations of minor ginsenosides may enhance the pharmaceutical value of the resulting ginseng products.
</p>
