<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Objective</title>
  <p class="p">This study was to investigate the nutrient ileal digestibility of dried mealworm (
   <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic>) larvae and compare with those of three animal protein by-products in growing pigs.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p class="p">A total of 12 crossbred ([Landrace×Yorkshire]×Duroc) growing pigs with average body weights of 24.12±0.68 kg were surgically equipped with simple T-cannulas after being deprived of feed for 24 h according to published surgical procedures. These pigs had a recovery period of two weeks. A total of 12 pigs were assigned to individual metabolic crates and allotted to one of four treatments with 3 replicates in a fully randomized design. Dietary treatments included the following: i) Fish meal, corn-vegetable by-product basal diet+9.95% fish meal; ii) Meat meal, corn-vegetable by-product basal diet+9.95% meat meal; iii) Poultry meal, corn-vegetable by-product basal diet+9.95% poultry meal; iv) 
   <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic>, corn-vegetable by-product basal diet+9.95% dried 
   <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic> larvae.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p class="p">Results showed that the apparent ileal digestibility (AID) of Lys was higher (p&lt;0.05) in pigs fed 
   <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic> diet than that in pigs fed fish meal diet. Pigs fed 
   <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic> diet showed increased (p&lt;0.05) AID of His and Arg compared to pigs fed Fish meal or Meat meal diet. The AID of Cys was increased (p&lt;0.05) in pigs fed poultry meal and 
   <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic> diets compared to that in pigs fish meal diet. Pigs fed meat meal, poultry meal, and 
   <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic> diets showed higher (p&lt;0.05) standardized ileal digestibility (SID) of total energy compared to pigs fed fish meal diet. The SID of Arg was higher (p&lt;0.05) in pigs fed 
   <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic> diet than that in pigs fed fish meal or meat meal diet. Furthermore, pigs fed poultry meal or 
   <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic> diets showed increased (p&lt;0.05) SID of Cys compared to pigs fed fish meal diet.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusion</title>
  <p class="p">In conclusion, providing pigs with diets that contained 
   <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic> larvae meal improved AID and SID of nutrients as well as essential and non-essential amino acids. The digestibility of dried mealworm larvae protein and its utilization 
   <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> are also good. Therefore, dried mealworm larvae protein can be used as protein source at 10% level in growing pigs.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
