<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> is a gram-positive bacterium that has been responsible for a broad spectrum of diseases, ranging from food poisoning and superficial skin and soft tissue infections to life-threatening infections such as bacteremia, endocarditis, osteomyelitis, pneumonia, or toxic shock syndrome [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It is notorious for its ability to quickly become resistant to any antibiotic, which makes this bacterium one of the most serious pathogens in humans, and its treatment is often difficult [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. In humans, 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> can occur as both a benign commensal and a harmful pathogen. Besides being a common colonizer of the skin, it also asymptomatically and permanently colonizes the anterior nostrils of up to 30% of the normal human population [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], which is widely considered to be a predisposition of invasive infection [
 <xref rid="B5-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Since 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> is a microorganism that is associated with a broad spectrum of infections affecting the respiratory tract, taking up antibiotics through inhalation could be one of its possible treatments. Moreover, the combination of two or even more antibiotic agents may be used as a possible strategy for increasing efficiency in fighting 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>-related diseases, including respiratory infections. An example of such treatment is a combination of fosfomycin and tobramycin that is currently in the late-stage development of an inhalation therapy of cystic fibrosis [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. It was demonstrated that fosfomycin synergistically enhances the activity of tobramycin against a wide range of bacteria, including 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. However, inhalation of solid antimicrobial agents, as well as the use of inhaler devices, may often be problematic, especially in children and the elderly [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Therefore, there is a need to search for new antimicrobial agents to combat bacteria affecting the respiratory tract and for easier ways how to deliver antimicrobials into the lower respiratory tract.
</p>
