<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although PTSD is caused by a psychologically traumatic environmental event and consequently it is considered a psychological phenomenon, many studies have indicated biological abnormalities, not observed in controls, which have been regarded either as risk factors for the development of the disease or as potential targets for therapeutic interventions. There have been detected changes across different stress hormones and neurotransmitter systems in the pathophysiology of PTSD. Serotoninergic, noradrenergic, glutamatergic, GABAergic, neuro-peptidergic systems and dysfunctions of the hypothalamus-adrenal axis have been reported to contribute to the disease onset and progression, even if no alteration of a single system taken individually can explain by itself the complex pathobiology underlying the disorder. In this context, and mainly based on findings from preclinical studies, a growing interest in terms of neurochemical interactions has been attracted by the endocannabinoid system (eCBS), since it makes up an extensive interconnected network of neuromodulators that controls synaptic neurotransmitter release. As it has been involved in several physiological and pathophysiological processes including synaptic plasticity, pain, memory processes, stress, and emotion regulation, its potential implication in the pathophysiology of PTSD has been regarded of considerable interest [
 <xref rid="B6-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Indeed, the eCBS plays an important role in regulating anxiety and stress and is involved in the modulation of cognitive and emotional responses [
 <xref rid="B7-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], as well as in the extinction of aversive memories [
 <xref rid="B8-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This system is essential for the development of synaptic plasticity in response to endogenous and environmental salient events [
 <xref rid="B9-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], determining specific learning and emotional responses related to traumatic experiences [
 <xref rid="B11-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Endocannabinoids regulate affective and emotional states and participate in memory consolidation, retrieval, and extinction [
 <xref rid="B12-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. It has been demonstrated that the learning processes regarding aversive memories are dysregulated after a traumatic event, as occurs in subjects affected by PTSD [
 <xref rid="B14-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Evidence suggests that the hypothalamic–pituitary–adrenal (HPA) system, which is essential for stress adaption, also plays a role in the pathophysiology of the disorder. Indeed, the HPA axis is chronically activated in patients with PTSD [
 <xref rid="B15-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. There is a bidirectional and functional interplay between eCBS and HPA systems: the eCBS can modulate the HPA axis function restraining the effects of severe stress on its activation [
 <xref rid="B16-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], whilst the release of glucocorticoids in response to a stressor contributes to eCBS signaling deficiencies, thus facilitating PTSD symptoms [
 <xref rid="B19-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. 
</p>
