<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In vivo study by Menon et al. focuses on cardioprotective activity of 70% methanolic extract of 
 <italic>O. indicum</italic> root bark against doxorubicin induced cardiomyopathy rats [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-25-05677" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Doxorubicin is an anthracycline antibiotic used in chemotherapy for hematological malignancies and some types of tissue sarcomas and carcinomas, but it is reported to cause side effects such as heart damage through oxidative stress, mitochondrial dysfunction, increase the susceptibility of cardiac tissue to lipid peroxidation and reduce levels of antioxidant defences associated with the heart tissue. In that study, doxorubicin treated animals were found to exhibit elevated levels of cardiac injury markers such as lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), creatine phosphokinase (CPK), serum glutamate oxaloacetate transaminase (SGOT) and serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase (SGPT) and exhibited arrhythmia when examined using electrocardiogram (ECG). Interestingly, after the doxorubicin-treated animals were given the treatment using extract from root bark of 
 <italic>O. indicum</italic>, all the cardiac injury markers were successfully reduced and the animals resumed back to normal ECG pattern. Furthermore, the cardiac tissue histological examination also showed amelioration of myofibrillar disorganization, reduced focal loss of tissue and fragmentation, lesser necrotic bodies, scattered cytoplasmic vacuolation and decreased lymphocyte infiltration in 
 <italic>O. indicum</italic> treated group. The protective effects of 
 <italic>O. indicum</italic> root bark extract on doxorubicin induced cardiomyopathy rats may be credited to its ability in enhancing the tissue antioxidant status, indicated by the significant (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) elevation of cardiac tissue antioxidant profile in 
 <italic>O. indicum</italic> treated group in a dose-dependent manner. These findings presented the capability of this plant in shielding the damaging and devastating effects of cumulative administration of doxorubicin in murine models.
</p>
