<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Arabian flora is a rich source of bioactive compounds. In this study, we investigated three aromatic plant species with the aim of finding valuable sources of antimicrobial agents against common pathogenic microorganisms. We focused especially on microorganisms, which cause outbreaks of infectious disease during mass gatherings and pilgrimages season in Saudi Arabia. The essential oils of three aromatic plant species were hydrodistilled from flowering aerial parts of 
  <italic>Lavandula pubescens</italic> Decne. and 
  <italic>Pulicaria incisa</italic> subsp. 
  <italic>candolleana</italic> E.Gamal-Eldin, and from leaves, stems, ripe and unripe fruits of 
  <italic>Juniperus procera</italic> Hochst. Ex Endl. They were subsequently analyzed by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry
  <monospace> (</monospace>GC-MS). The main constituents of 
  <italic>L. pubescens</italic> were found to be carvacrol (55.7%), methyl carvacrol (13.4%), and β-bisabolene (9.1%). 
  <italic>P. incisa</italic> subsp. 
  <italic>Candolleana</italic> essential oil was rich in linalool (33.0%), chrysanthenone (10.3%), eugenol (8.9%), and 
  <italic>cis</italic>-chrysanthenol (8.0%); the major components of 
  <italic>J. procera</italic> essential oil were α-pinene (31.3–62.5%) and δ-3-carene (7.3–30.3%). These essential oils were tested against thirteen American Type Culture Collection (ATCC) strains of Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria using the agar diffusion assay. The only effective essential oil was that of 
  <italic>L. pubescens</italic> and the most sensitive strains were 
  <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>, 
  <italic>Salmonella typhimurium, Shigella sonnei</italic>, 
  <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> and 
  <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic>. Carvacrol, the major constituent of 
  <italic>L. pubescens</italic>, was tested on these strains and was compared with vancomycin, amikacin, and ciprofloxacin. The Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) and Minimum Bactericidal Concentration (MBC) assays of 
  <italic>L. pubescens</italic> essential oil and carvacrol revealed that Gram-negative strains were more susceptible than the Gram-positive ones.
 </p>
</abstract>
