<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="abs0010">
 <p>
  <italic>Naja haje</italic> envenoming could activate multiple pathways linked to haematotoxic, neurological, and antioxidant systems dysfunctions. 
  <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> has been used in the management of different snake venom-induced toxicities, but there is no scientific information on its antivenom effects against 
  <italic>Naja haje</italic>. This study thus, investigated the antivenom activities of different extract partitions of 
  <italic>M. oleifera</italic> leaves against 
  <italic>N. haje</italic> envenoming
  <italic>.</italic> Forty five male rats were divided into nine groups (n = 5). Groups 2 to 9 were envenomed with 0.025 mg/kg (LD
  <sub>50</sub>) of 
  <italic>N</italic>
  <italic>. haje</italic> venom while group 1 was given saline. Group 2 was left untreated, while group 3 was treated with polyvalent antivenom, groups 4, 6 and 8 were treated with 300 mg/kg
  <sup>−1</sup> of N-hexane, ethylacetate and ethanol partitions of 
  <italic>M. oleifera,</italic> respectively. Groups 5, 7 and 9 were also treated with 600 mgkg
  <sup>−1</sup>of the partitions
  <italic>,</italic> respectively. Ethanol extract and ethyl acetate partition of 
  <italic>M. oleifera</italic> significantly improved haematological indices following acute anaemia induced by the venom. Likewise, haemorrhagic, haemolytic and anti-coagulant activities of 
  <italic>N. haje</italic> venom were best inhibited by ethanol partition. Envenoming significantly down-regulated Nuclear factor erythroid 2-related factor 2 (Nrf2) with the consequent elevation of antioxidant enzymes activities in the serum and brain. Treatment with extract partitions however, elevated Nrf2 levels while normalising antioxidant enzyme activities. Furthermore, there were reduction in levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines (TNF-α and interleukin-1β) in tissues of treated envenomed rats. This study concludes that ethanol partition of 
  <italic>M. oleifera</italic> was most effective against 
  <italic>N. haje</italic> venom and could be considered as a potential source for antivenom metabolites.
 </p>
</abstract>
