<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par51">In summary, quality control of TCM is very important in TCM application and the complexity of TCM promotes difficulties in quality control and quality standards establishment for TCM. But even so, working parties in EP and ChP have managed to assess TCM quality by regulating the origins, identification, quality parameters (such as moisture content and impurities) and active components contents in TCM. However, there are differences between the pharmacopoeias in Europe and China, including the source of TCM herbs, tests required for TCM, marker selection and assay methods etc. because of the different systems in quality control of TCM, and the application habits of TCM between Europe and China. Nevertheless, improvements may be made in the pharmacopoeias from the experience of the two parties. For example, although ChP (2020 edition) has removed the TCM containing aristolochic acids including Aristolochiae Herba and Aristolochiae Fructus, there are some TCM easily confused with the herbal drugs from 
 <italic>Aristolochia</italic> species, such as Akebia Stem, Aucklandiae Radix, Clematidis Armandii Caulis, Stephaniae Tetrandrae Radix and Sinomenii Caulis. Including the test for aristolochic acids in these TCM as EP may be necessary and important to avoid the adulteration or misuse of aristolochic acids-containing drugs. On the other hand, in EP, HRS has been used for system suitability assessment of LC assay, it may be utilized for TLC identification as well, specially for the TCM without suitable active markers or lack of commercial available CRS. EP may also include methods of molecular identification and standards for residue of sulfur dioxide for more comprehensive quality control of TCM. Therefore, discussion about these issues and cooperation between different parties are urgently needed to improve and harmonize the quality standard of TCM. With the development in analytical techniques and quality control methods such as improvements in chromatography techniques as well as the application of molecular identification, new quality control measures are very likely to be used in the future for better quality assessment of herbal drugs.
</p>
