<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This pattern may result from their high infection and easy release of spores from the monoculture A. adenophora host into the surrounding air. Species of Didymellaceae mainly cause leaf and stem lesions [64,65] and produce many small conidia, which is conducive for spreading through the air [66]. We also verified that A. adenophora harbored abundant leaf spot pathogens from Didymellaceae in this study (see S2Table). The data suggest that there may form a feedback between the pathogenic fungi associated host and the airborne spores, i.e., the monoculture hosts support high load of pathogenic fungal infection, which will develop into a pathogenic-fungus-dominant canopy air and in turn further worsen their infection on hosts. Such a feedback cycle may partially contribute to the prevalence of Didymellaceae fungi on A. adenophora. Here we reasoned that the co-occurrence pattern of the dominant airborne fungal pathogen may be a label in the monoculture plant, including invasive plants, as well as economic crops. Janzen-Connell hypothesis indicates that diverse host-specific pathogen is important to maintain plant diversity [67, 68]. For native vegetation, higher plant diversity promotes higher diversity of fungal pathogens [69], it thus is expected that the airborne fungal co-occurrence become more abundant in native vegetation than in the monoculture plant. Although it remains to have such a conclusion due to the lack of air samples above native vegetation in this study, our data indirectly indicate that the diverse hosts and the diverse airborne pathogen co-occurrence network may partially contribute to high diversity of pathogens in native vegetation and thus decreases pathogen infection per plant [69]. Previously, increasing host diversity has been verified to help reduce the disease severity of airborne pathogens for monoculture crops. For example, Zhu et al. (2000) reported that planting disease-susceptible rice varieties in mixtures increased crop yield by 89% and reduced blast severity by 94% when comparing with those in monocultures [70]. Therefore, it is worthwhile to verify the commonness of such fungal co-occurrence patterns in other invasive systems as well as in crop systems, and the study of airborne fungal co-occurrence networks represents a promising field of plant pathology.” (Lines 392-437)</p>
