<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="s2001">
  <title>Objective</title>
  <p>This narrative review aims to identify alternative ways to improve the symptoms of primary dysmenorrhea (PD).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2002">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>PD refers to endometrial painful cramps during the premenstrual period. This condition affects a lot of women worldwide and is accompanied with absenteeism and high economic costs, thus, risk-free, and effective therapeutic approaches are needed. Pharmacological agents such as non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) and oral contraceptive pills (OCPs), which are widely prescribed for these women, demonstrate adequate efficacy in alleviating pain and discomfort. The long natural course of the disease dictates remedies that focus on lifestyle changes and on improvement of Quality-of-Life (QoL) for women suffering with PD.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2003">
  <title>Materials and Methods</title>
  <p>Five major search engines, namely MEDLINE, PubMed, EMBASE, and Cochrane Library were searched for articles published prior to October 2020 focused in PD. A total of 74 paper were included.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2004">
  <title>Discussion</title>
  <p>Physical activity, for instance yoga, aromatherapy massage, and other forms of relaxation, vitamins and dietary changes, acupressure and acupuncture,a and some psychological interventions are just few of the proposed health behavior targeted approaches in cases of PD. This review focuses on lifestyle changes and alternative methods that could potentially result in minimizing symptoms of PD and in improving overall QoL for these patients, by providing current scientific evidence on their efficacy.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2005">
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p>Complementary and alternative medicine practices (CAM) are widely accepted by women. International literature provides controversial scientific evidence, thus further studies need to be conducted in order to prove or disregard their efficacy in cases of PD.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
