<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">In the past few years, several molecular strategies have been attempted to increase oil production in oilseed crops. One strategy is to increase fatty acid assembly into triacylglycerols by overexpressing acyl-CoA acyltransferase in the Kennedy pathway. For instance, overexpression of lysophosphatidic acid acyltransferase (LPAAT) or DGAT1 significantly increases oil contents in seeds. Fatty acid profile in the oil is determined by substrate specificity of acyl-CoA acyltransferases used for fatty acid acylations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>]. Another strategy is to increase the synthetic efficiency of fatty acids prior to the assembly by overexpression of enzymes directly involved in the biosynthetic process. For instance, overexpression of 
 <italic class="italic">ACCase</italic> resulted in an increase in oil content [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>]. In this strategy, fatty acid profile of the oil would be similar to that of wild type. In the present study, expression of the KS domain from the PUFA synthase significantly enhanced oil content in transgenic lines and at the same time the fatty acid profile of seed oil was also altered to the higher proportion of unsaturated fatty acids. This result indicates the condensation process, particularly the condensation steps from C4 to C16, during the fatty acid biosynthesis might be the limiting step, and overexpression of the KS domain of the 
 <italic class="italic">Thraustochytrium</italic> PUFA synthase, although it only shares about 20% amino acid identity to 
 <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis</italic> KASI, can increase seed oil and seed mass simultaneously in 
 <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis</italic>. The reason why the unsaturated level of fatty acids was also increased in the transgenics remains to be determined. It is probably due to the unique activity of the KS domain of microbial origin. Overexpression of the domain may not only enhance the main condensation reactions in fatty acid synthesis, but also stimulate the activity of downstream fatty acid-modifying enzymes such as acyl-ACP and phospholipid desaturases and FAE-type elongases. Collectively, our research in the enhanced condensation activity by overexpression of the KS domain from protist PUFA synthase resulting in significantly increased seed weight and seed oil offers a new approach to increase oil production in oilseed plants.
</p>
