<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Access to adequate medical care is a basic human right (Article 25, Universal Declaration of Human Rights) and universal health coverage (UHC) is core to achieving Sustainable Development Goal three (SDG 3) of the UN Agenda 2030 (
 <xref rid="B451" ref-type="bibr">UN General Assembly, 1948</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B452" ref-type="bibr">UN General Assembly, 2015</xref>). The World Health Organization (
 <xref rid="B477" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2013</xref>) highlighted the need for integrating traditional and complementary medicine (T&amp;CM) in national health systems in order to achieve UHC while respecting consumers’ choice. A comprehensive knowledge base is fundamental for establishing policies that allow people to “access T&amp;CM in a safe, respectful, cost-efficient and effective manner” (
 <xref rid="B477" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2013</xref>, p. 7). Lack of research data is seen as the number one challenge faced by member states for implementing the WHO’s T&amp;CM strategy. The lack of systematic reviews of the available evidence on T&amp;CM in Mesoamerica is reflected in insufficient policies and culturally sensitive health materials, representing critical barriers to care (
 <xref rid="B291" ref-type="bibr">Lozoya and Zolla, 1984</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B341" ref-type="bibr">Nigenda et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B476" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">Caceres Guido et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B323" ref-type="bibr">Mokdad et al., 2015</xref>). Recent emphases shifts in public health discussions stemming from debates around ‘Epistemologies of the South’ (
 <xref rid="B144" ref-type="bibr">De Sousa, 2011</xref>) propose that the route toward UHC in Mesoamerica is dependent on promoting “health sovereignty,” fostering a decolonial turn in favor of intercultural approaches that reflect the particular epidemiologies of the peoples (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Basile, 2018</xref>). According to 
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr">De Sousa (2010)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="B274" ref-type="bibr">Laurell (2010)</xref> the neglected consideration of emic epistemologies in the shaping of public health policies should be contrasted with a turn toward an “ecology of knowledge-systems.” This perspective includes traditional medicine, particularly herbal medicine, which has been recognized as playing a key role toward providing culturally pertinent and accessible health coverage (
 <xref rid="B390" ref-type="bibr">Rocha-Buelvas, 2017</xref>) and is in line with the WHO’s guidelines, which pin-point acceptability as a factor fostering increased access to health provision services in diverse cultural settings (
 <xref rid="B477" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2013</xref>).
</p>
