<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Malassezia</italic> furfur is recognized as one of the main causative agents of PV, from among the 14 recognized 
 <italic>Malassezia</italic> species [
 <xref rid="B134-molecules-26-01093" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>,
 <xref rid="B135-molecules-26-01093" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. The EO applied in this study was isolated from 
 <italic>Myrtus communis</italic> (Myrtaceae), which has been widely used in various medicinal remedies. To date, this myrtle EO is known to contain 1, 8-cineole and α-pinene. Its antifungal activity against several species (e.g. 
 <italic>Rhizoctonia solani, F. solani, A. flavus</italic>, 
 <italic>Colletotrichum lindemuthianum</italic>, 
 <italic>F. culmorum</italic>, 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B137-molecules-26-01093" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-molecules-26-01093" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B139-molecules-26-01093" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>,
 <xref rid="B140-molecules-26-01093" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>] has been documented. In this prospective case-series study, clinical isolates of PV were collected from 41 patients that had been deprived of treatment for at least two weeks. The clinical samples revealed the presence of 86 yeast colonies with seven identified species: 
 <italic>M. furfur</italic> (42.5%), 
 <italic>M. sympodialis</italic> (23.5%), 
 <italic>M. sllooffiae</italic> (13.9%), 
 <italic>M. globose</italic> (7.5%), 
 <italic>M. obtusa</italic> (6%), 
 <italic>M. japonica</italic> (4%) and 
 <italic>M. restricta</italic> (2.5%). The antifungal inhibition revealed excellent activity of 
 <italic>M. communis</italic> against 
 <italic>Malassezia</italic> sp., especially 
 <italic>M. furfur</italic> and 
 <italic>M. sympodialis</italic>, at 96% and 83%, respectively. The findings of this study suggest the potential of 
 <italic>M. communis</italic> EO as an alternative to conventional antifungal drugs, especially in the treatment of PV. Such an approach was considered cheaper, safe and nonhepatotoxic or nonnephrotoxic. Nevertheless, this study also addressed its limitations, and proposed the need for in vivo studies to confirm the effectiveness of this EO [
 <xref rid="B97-molecules-26-01093" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>].
</p>
