<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0037">Adding to the above mentioned reports, 
 <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al. (2006)</xref> investigated the role of triterpene glycosides screened from 
 <italic>Heteromorpha, Bupleurum</italic> and 
 <italic>Scrophularia scordonia</italic> against coronavirus 229E by averting the attachment and invasion into the host. Moreover, 
 <italic>Artemisia annua, Lindera aggregata, Lycoris radiate, Isatis indigotica</italic>have been known to exhibit anti-SARS-CoV effects (
 <xref rid="bib0118" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2005a</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0119" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). Similarly, naturally occurring repressors have been recognised such as scutellarein, phenolics, myricetin etc. from 
 <italic>Isatis indigotica</italic> and 
 <italic>Torreya nucifera</italic> respectively against SARS-CoV enzymes. Another study was reported in 
 <italic>Houttuynia cordata</italic> against SARS-CoV through inhibition of 3CL-proteases and RNA-polymerases (
 <xref rid="bib0259" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2012</xref>). Further, 
 <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> have also been demonstrated to possess multifaceted properties due to the presence of thymoquinone against H9N2 and cytomegaloviral diseases (
 <xref rid="bib0223" ref-type="bibr">Tavakkoli et al., 2017</xref>). More recently, the role of 
 <italic>Piper Betel</italic> in combating COVID-19 infections have also been explored (
 <xref rid="bib0202" ref-type="bibr">Sengupta, 2019</xref>). According to their study, 'Aurantiamide', an active metabolite from 
 <italic>Piper aurantiacum</italic> has chymotrypsin like-proteases like activities that is a ratified agent for inhibiting coronavirus. In addition to this, it also encompassespiperol, eugenol, catechol, caryophyllene, etragol, chavibetol, betlol, quercetin etc. that also grows body's self-defense mechanism either through reception of viruses or in waning off the viral load within the infected hosts (
 <xref rid="bib0202" ref-type="bibr">Sengupta, 2019</xref>).Alongside, studies have been depicted the role of herbal drug Gene-Eden-VIR/Novirin against many noxious viruses and this drug is mainly comprised of quercetin, green tea, cinnamon, licorice and selenium (
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">Polansky and Lori, 2020</xref>). They found that it disrupts the viral entry, infection, replication, viral proteases, viral quasi-speciesand triggers the immunity, thereby, can be evidently utilised against SARS-CoV-2 respectively (
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">Polansky and Lori, 2020</xref>).
</p>
