<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float" class="table-wrap">
 <label class="label">Table 1</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">The role of principal macronutrients in fish metabolism.</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" class="table">
  <thead class="thead">
   <tr class="tr">
    <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="th">
     <bold class="bold">Nutrient</bold>
    </th>
    <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="th">
     <bold class="bold">Major role in fish</bold>
    </th>
    <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="th">
     <bold class="bold">Importance for fish metabolism</bold>
    </th>
    <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="th">
     <bold class="bold">References</bold>
    </th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody class="tbody">
   <tr class="tr">
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">
     <italic class="italic">Carbohydrates (CHO)</italic>
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Stored as glycogen that can be mobilized to satisfy energy demands when necessary. In fish, CHO seems to play only a minor role compared to lipids and proteins.
     <break class="break"/> Fish are in general unable to rapidly lower circulating glucose levels following a glucose load or a high CHO meal, thus leading to the interpretation that fish are glucose-intolerant.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Great importance to the metabolism of all fish species, since they act as an oxidative substrate to some cells and tissues.
     <break class="break"/> Control of glucose levels exists in tissues relying on glucose such as the brain. Numerous studies carried out in recent years have also demonstrated the existence of glucose sensing mechanisms in such tissues.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">(
     <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>, 
     <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>–
     <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>)
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">
     <italic class="italic">Lipids</italic>
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Storage and provision of metabolic energy in the form of ATP provided through the β-oxidation of fatty acids. They also play an important role as precursors for the synthesis of many hormones and in the formation of cell membranes.</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Together with their constituent fatty acids, they are the main nutrients playing important functions as sources of metabolic energy for growth and reproduction. In fish diet, they are particularly important the 
     <italic class="italic">n</italic>-3 and 
     <italic class="italic">n</italic>-6 unsaturated fatty acids (“omega 3” and “omega 6”), which are not synthesized by animals, and therefore must be supplied in the diet.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">(
     <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>–
     <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>)
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">
     <italic class="italic">Proteins</italic>
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Amino acids are an essential component of the diet of all animals. Fish require a balanced combination of the 20 amino acids, of which 10 are not synthesized by fish and adequate amounts must be provided through their diet. These essential amino acids are methionine, arginine, threonine, tryptophan, histidine, isoleucine, lysine, leucine, valine and phenylalanine.</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Proteins and amino acid requirements differ between fish species since they develop different roles. Some proteins are enzymes, catalyzing a wide range of chemical reactions; other proteins have essential functions in muscle contraction, the transport of specific molecules or as structural elements. In carnivorous fish, proteins also have an important role as a source of energy.</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">(
     <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>, 
     <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>, 
     <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>)
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">
     <italic class="italic">Vitamins</italic>
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Are necessary for normal fish growth and health. They are usually not synthesized by fish and must be supplied in the diet. Vitamin deficiency results in scoliosis, dark coloration and/or, most commonly, reduction in growth rate.</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Are highly important in the proper functioning of the metabolism since some of them are enzymatic co-factors.</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">(
     <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>)
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">
     <italic class="italic">Minerals</italic>
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Fish can absorb many minerals directly from the water through their gills and skin, allowing them to compensate in some degree, mineral deficiencies in their diet.
     <break class="break"/> Some are incorporated into the bones, while others have a major function in acid-base balance, electron transfer or the maintenance of cell homeostasis.
    </td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">They can be divided into two groups based on the quantity required in the diet. Macro-minerals such as sodium, chloride, potassium or phosphorous, regulate osmotic balance and are integrated into the skeletal structure. Micro-minerals are required in small amounts as components in enzyme and hormone systems.</td>
    <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">(
     <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>, 
     <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>, 
     <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>)
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
