<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We studied the effect of storm and hurricane activities on the growth of patches of common reed, 
 <italic>Phragmites australis</italic>, in the coastal wetlands of the eastern United States of America. Indigenous and/or introduced haplotypes (based on a microsatellite analysis of chloroplast DNA) of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> are found on all continents except for Antarctica, and in some cases the introduced haplotypes are recognized as aggressive invaders 
 <xref rid="pone.0098478-Saltonstall1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0098478-Guo1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Historically, 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> has been an uncommon species of the wetlands of North America for millennia 
 <xref rid="pone.0098478-Niering1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. In the past 150 years, an introduced Eurasian haplotype has spread rapidly in both coastal and inland marsh ecosystems of North America, particularly near the Atlantic Coast 
 <xref rid="pone.0098478-Saltonstall1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. An additional haplotype that most likely originated in Africa and is present in all of the Gulf Coast states (Gulf-Coast haplotype) 
 <xref rid="pone.0098478-Lambertini1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> is also spreading locally and expanding its range to the southwestern US 
 <xref rid="pone.0098478-Meyerson1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0098478-Williams1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. It is unclear whether this haplotype’s appearance into the Gulf Coast region was facilitated by human activities or the result of a natural range expansion from Central and South America. Other non-native haplotypes of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> are present in North America, but they appear to have very restricted distributions (particularly, within the Mississippi River Delta) 
 <xref rid="pone.0098478-Lambertini1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Marshes that have been invaded by 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> have been characterized by the loss of native plant species, reduced diversity and altered composition of associated faunal communities, and changed ecosystem processes such as nutrient cycling and hydrological regimes 
 <xref rid="pone.0098478-Windham1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0098478-Dibble1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>.
</p>
