<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dried aerial parts (50 g) for each location were hydrodistilled for three hours using Clevenger-type apparatus. For each sample, we collected lipophilic (extracted in the pentane part in the inner tube of the Clevenger apparatus) and hydrophilic volatile compounds (extracted in the water part in the inner tube of the Clevenger apparatus) fractions and stored in fridge until analysis. Both phases were analyzed with GC and GC-MS. GC was performed by gas chromatograph (model 3900, Varian Inc., Lake Forest, CA, USA) that is supplied with a flame ionization detector (FID), mass spectrometer (model 2100T; Varian Inc.), non-polar capillary column VF-5ms (30 m × 0.25 mm inside diameter, coating thickness 0.25 µm, Palo Alto, CA, USA) and polar capillary column CP-Wax 52 CB (30 m × 0.25 mm i.d., coating thickness 0.25 µm, Palo Alto, CA, USA). The chromatographic conditions for the analysis of lipophilic fraction (essential oils) were: FID detector temperature 300 °C, injector temperature 250 °C. The gas carrier was helium at 1 mL min
 <sup>−1</sup>. The conditions for the VF-5ms column were: temperature 60 °C isothermal for 3 min, and then increased to 246 °C at a rate of 3 °C min
 <sup>−1</sup>, and held isothermal for 25 min. Conditions for the CP Wax 52 column were: temperature 70 °C isothermal for 5 min, and then increased to 240 °C at a rate of 3 °C min
 <sup>−1</sup> and held isothermal for 25 min. The injected volume was 2 μL and the split ratio was 1:20. The MS conditions were: ion source temperature 200 °C, ionization voltage 70 eV, mass scan range 40–350 mass units [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-09-01646" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The individual peaks for all samples were identified by comparing their retention indices of n-alkanes with those of authentic samples and literature [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-01646" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The chromatographic conditions for the analysis of hydrophilic fraction (hydrosols) were the same, however the injection was done with a headspace injection needle and there was no split ratio (splitless mode). The procedure for each hydrosol sample was as follows: 2 g of hydrosol was added in the glass bottle and closed with a metal cap with septum. The headspace needle was injected in the glass bottle closed with metal cap with septum. The glass bottle was first placed with the hydrosol sample in water at 40 °C and left there for 20 min without the needle to allow volatile compounds to evaporate from the water. The needle was then injected and left there for 20 min so that the volatile compounds could be adsorbed on the resin needle. The injection needle was then inserted into a GC inlet and left there for 20 min to ensure that all volatile compounds from the resin were resorbed into the injection liner. The MS conditions were the same as for volatile compounds from EO and the individual peaks for all samples were identified by comparing of their retention indices of n-alkanes with those of authentic samples and literature [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-01646" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The results for all samples were measured in three independent analyses and expressed as percentage (%) of each compound in a total EO or hydrosol (
 <xref rid="plants-09-01646-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). All values were calculated as the mean of three independent results with standard deviation.
</p>
