<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23" class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Yarrowia</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Candida</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodotorula</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodosporidium</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Cryptococcus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Trichosporon</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Lipomyces</italic> were reported as genera of oleaginous yeast [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>] and each are also known as single-cell oil (SCO). Meng [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>] reported that some species of 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodosporidium</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodotorula</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Lipomyces</italic> are able to accrue lipids to more than 70% of their dry weight. The accumulation of fat in yeast is affected by several parameters that may be grouped as physical (e.g., pH, temperature, light) and chemical (e.g., carbon and nitrogen sources) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>]. However, the TAGs synthesized by oleaginous yeasts consist primarily of C16 and C18, such as C16:0, C16:1, C18:0 C18:1 and 18:2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>], with varying amounts of shorter (C14) and longer (C26) fatty acid chains, which have key roles in protein modification [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>]. The fatty acid (FA) composition of the microbial lipids was found to be similar to vegetable oil, which is commonly used in biodiesel production. Thus, microbial lipids can be used as a potential raw material for biodiesel production [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>]. To enhance lipid and FA content in yeast, several techniques were developed including the classical random metagenesis. For such a purpose, ethyl methanesulfonate (EMS) is amongst the most common alkylating agents used in yeast as mutation-inducing agents. Thus, EMS has been used to induce the over-production of metabolites in microalgae, including eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>], astaxanthin, carotenoids [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>] and hydrogen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>]. In contrast, EMS-random mutagenesis has also been used to develop mutant strains of microalgae devoid of EPA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>].
</p>
