<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">All strains and plasmids constructed in this work are listed in 
 <xref rid="molecules-24-01753-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>. The primers used for genetic modifications are listed in 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-molecules-24-01753" class="xref">Table S1</xref>. Standard protocols were followed for DNA manipulation, and all constructed plasmids were verified by sequencing [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-24-01753" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. The 
 <italic class="italic">Y. lipolytica</italic> strains used in this study were derived from the wild-type strain 
 <italic class="italic">Y. lipolytica</italic> W29 (ATCC 20460). The auxotrophic Po1g (Leu
 <sup class="sup">−</sup>) and Po1h (Ura
 <sup class="sup">−</sup>) used in all transformations were kindly provided by Prof. Catherine Madzak (Institute National de la Recherche Agronomique/AgroParisTech, Paris, France). All cloning procedures were carried out in 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> strain Top10 (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). The genes 
 <italic class="italic">DGA1</italic> (GenBank No. YALI0E32769g) and 
 <italic class="italic">GPD1</italic> (GenBank No. YALI0B02948p, 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-molecules-24-01753" class="xref">Table S2</xref>) were amplified from 
 <italic class="italic">Y. lipolytica</italic> Po1h’s genomic DNA by the Rapid Yeast Genomic DNA Isolation Kit (Sangon Biotech., Shanghai, China). The 
 <italic class="italic">DGA1</italic> was flanked by 
 <italic class="italic">Pml</italic> I and 
 <italic class="italic">Kpn</italic> I restriction sites at the 5′ and 3′ ends, respectively and was amplified by PCR using PrimerSTAR MAX DNA polymerase (Takara Biotech, Co., Ltd., Dalian, China). After digestion, the fragments were ligated at the 
 <italic class="italic">Pml</italic> I/
 <italic class="italic">Kpn</italic> I sites of the pINA1312 expression vectors to yield the pINA1312-DGA1 and pINA1312-GPD constructs, respectively.
</p>
