<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Another processing parameter determining the antimicrobial effectiveness of NTAP is the gas moisture content. In fact, it has been occasionally observed (Dobrynin et al., 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>) that the use of completely dry gases is ineffective for 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> inactivation, and there are several studies which show that an increase in the water content of the gas improves its effectiveness (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Thus, Ragni et al. (
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>) reported that an increase in the air relative humidity from 35 to 65% increased the inactivation of 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. Enteritidis and 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. Typhimurium from 2.5 to 4.5 log cycles, and attributed this effect to a higher concentration of hydroxyl radicals in the plasma. Similar results were found by Patil et al. (
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) for 
 <italic class="italic">B. atrophaeus</italic> spores. These authors used plasmas with different moisture content (3, 10, 30, 50, and 70%), and obtained a 5 to 6 log reduction at humidities of 3 and 10%, while a complete inactivation was observed at higher humidities. These authors related this higher antimicrobial activity to the increased generation of numerous reactive species, such as N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">5</sub>, H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, HNO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, or hydroxyl radicals, and, especially, to the decomposition of ozone in the presence of water, with the consequent formation of highly oxidizing species, such as hydroxyl and hydroperoxyl radicals, superoxide anion and H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. On the contrary, a recent study by Lai et al. (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>) has shown that when the relative air humidity increased from 52 to 81% or from 62 to 81%, the inactivation efficiency of NTAP against 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> decreased by 87 and 58%, respectively, which was linked to a decrease in the concentration of negative ions in plasma. These apparently contradictory results could be explained by the existence of an optimum moisture value for achieving a maximum antimicrobial activity. For instance, in the particular case of 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus niger</italic>, a progressive increase in microbial inactivation was observed up to a moisture content of 70%, which was the optimum moisture content for NTAP generation (Muranyi et al., 
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>).
</p>
