<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0255">The immune response is the main factor between the functional balance of the cells and the possible mechanisms of functional unbalance, which can lead to complex clinical conditions. In cases of viral infections, the appropriate immune response helps to balance the level of pro-inflammatory substances and the cell recovery cycle. However, an exaggerated immune response is at the center of numerous problems such as organ damage and failure of vital functions (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Barbosa, dos Santos Freitas, da Silva Martins &amp; de Carvalho Junior, 2020</xref>). It is easy to understand how the immune system is important, making a brief example. Individuals with clinical allergies have several imbalances in the immune system, in which case the immune system cannot accurately identify foreign bodies and therefore the immune response is compromised. In cases of people infected with COVID-19, especially in severe cases, the role of the immune system is evident. In these cases, as discussed in the previous topic, the immune response is so exaggerated that complex hyperinflammation is observed, in addition to serious side effects, such as hypercoagulation and multiple organ failure (
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Wrapp et al., 2020</xref>). As already highlighted in the previous topic, there are several polysaccharides that stimulate the immune system through indirect ways, mainly by regulating the expression of pro-inflammatory substances. These polysaccharides are ideal for use in long-term immunity-enhancing therapies. However, these polysaccharides could not be used in patients with severe cases of COVID-19, as they could help to worsen the conditions of hyperinflammation. However, there are polysaccharides, which activate immunosuppression pathways, and could be used to stimulate the production of anti-inflammatory substances, which can be applied in the treatment of severe cases. From now on, we will take a targeted approach to the polysaccharides that activate the immunosuppression pathways.
</p>
