<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0265">Extracellular stimuli lead to the activation of three pathways, namely the MAP Kinase pathway (Mitogen Activated Protein Kinases), the MyD88 protein pathway and the direct pathway with mitochondria activation, both of which induce the production of inflammation, proliferation, differentiation and apoptosis. The MAPk activation pathway initiates the regulation of a series of biological processes, especially through the action of the kinase JNK, p38 and ERK 1/2. At the end, the signaling kinases activate the AP-1 protein (activator protein 1), responsible for the regulation of gene expression. The stimulus of the TRL4 receptor can activate the domain of the MyD88 protein, which in turn activates IκB kinase, an enzyme complex responsible for the propagation of the cellular response to inflammation (
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Wrapp et al., 2020</xref>). The IkB kinase complex induces a cascade of signal transduction mediated by phosphorylation processes until activation of the nuclear factor kappa B (NF-kB), a protein complex that performs functions as a transcription factor of genetic material and induction of protein synthesis. Finally, signaling of the direct pathway mediated by mitochondria can also occur, which initiates the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS), initiating an apoptosis cycle. On the other hand, the ROS pathway can also induce the nuclear factor kappa B (NF-kB) signaling pathway, which has functions as a transcription factor for genetic material and induction of protein synthesis. Therefore, as already observed in case of serious infections by COVID-19, where the side effects of hyperinflation are clear, the inhibition of inflammatory responses mediated by macrophages or other cells of the immune system, must suppress or control the signaling pathways (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Barbosa, dos Santos Freitas, da Silva Martins &amp; de Carvalho Junior, 2020</xref>). All the mechanisms described can be seen in (
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> ), in addition to the possible polysaccharide signaling mechanisms that contribute to the immunosuppression of the pro-inflammatory substances production pathways.
</p>
