<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In contrast to a steadily increasing body of in vitro data that evaluates the interplay of diet or certain nutrients with bacteriophages as discussed in the chapters above, there are still only a few in vivo studies available. However, the possibility to modulate the microbiome by phage application is currently starting to attract more and more attention, especially in the field of inflammatory and malignant diseases. For instance, Zheng and colleagues covalently linked irinotecan-loaded dextran nanoparticles to azide-modified phages that were able to inhibit the growth of 
 <italic>Fusobacterium nucleatum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B153-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. After i.v. or oral administration, these phage-guided irinotecan-loaded nanoparticles increased the chemotherapeutic efficacy in mice with colorectal tumors. In another study, a single injection of a lytic bacteriophage cocktail was effective as a rescue treatment for murine severe septic peritonitis, resulting in a significant improvement of the disease state without harming the microbiome [
 <xref rid="B154-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>]. Wild-type phage T4 and the according substrain HAP1, which is characterized by enhanced affinity to melanoma cells, were able to reduce lung metastasis of murine B16 melanoma cells by 47% and 80%, respectively [
 <xref rid="B28-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Moreover, the modulation of the intestinal microbiome and metabolome was investigated using cognate lytic phages in gnotobiotic mice that were colonized with defined human gut commensal bacteria. This approach directly impacted susceptible bacteria, but phage predation also regulated additional bacteria via interbacterial interactions, yielding strong cascading net effects on the gut metabolome [
 <xref rid="B58-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. In a gnotobiotic pig model, it was shown that bacteria species are able to affect intestinal morphology as well as the expression of proinflammatory cytokines such as IL-1β and IL-6. Therefore, it can be hypothesized that a modulation of, e.g., neonatal bacterial colonization would have strong implications for a healthy development of the intestine [
 <xref rid="B4-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. On the other hand, intestinal inflammation and ulcerative colitis can be aggravated by high levels of certain bacteriophages that induce interferon-γ release [
 <xref rid="B17-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Different phage cocktails (
 <italic>ShigActive</italic>™ [
 <xref rid="B155-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>] and 
 <italic>ListShield</italic> [
 <xref rid="B156-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]) have been shown to reduce shigella colonization of the murine gut and to decrease 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> in the gastrointestinal tract, respectively. 
 <italic>ShigActive</italic>™ was found to have comparable therapeutic effects to ampicillin but without the harmful effects on the gut microbiota exerted by the antibiotic [
 <xref rid="B155-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>]. 
 <italic>ListShield</italic> was applied via oral gavage before mice were orally infected with 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>. Consequently, 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> concentrations were found to be reduced in the liver, spleen, and intestines when compared to controls. Even though, this phage therapy was as effective as the treatment with an antibiotic, it did not result in weight loss of the animals in contrast to infected controls and antibiotic-treated mice [
 <xref rid="B156-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. In another study, mice with antibiotic-induced perturbed microbiomes were treated with autochthonous virome transfer and viable phages were effective in reshaping the murine gut microbiota in a way that closely resembled the pre-antibiotic situation [
 <xref rid="B157-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>]. In vivo targeting of specific bacterial pathogens with recombinant or wildtype phages was also investigated for 
 <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infections [
 <xref rid="B158-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>], Vancomycin-resistant 
 <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> infections [
 <xref rid="B159-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>], Crohn’s disease [
 <xref rid="B160-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>] and even for the attenuation of alcoholic liver disease [
 <xref rid="B161-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. The human Bacteriophage for Gastrointestinal Health (PHAGE) study and PHAGE-2 study demonstrated that an application of therapeutic doses of bacteriophages was both safe and tolerable [
 <xref rid="B162-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>,
 <xref rid="B163-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>,
 <xref rid="B164-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>]. The double-blinded, placebo-controlled crossover PHAGE trial with adults consuming bacteriophages for 28 days (32/43 participants finished the study) also demonstrated that bacteriophages are able to selectively decrease the amount of target organisms, without disrupting the gut microbiome globally [
 <xref rid="B162-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>]. In the randomized, parallel-arm, double-blinded, placebo-controlled PHAGE-2 study (68 participants, four weeks), it could be shown that adding supplemental bacteriophages (PreforPro) to the probiotic 
 <italic>Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>lactis</italic> enhanced positive effects on gastrointestinal health [
 <xref rid="B164-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>]. Taken together, there is increasing evidence, in initial in vivo studies, for the high potential of treating different diseases with bacteriophages and for the ability to reshape the gut microbiome via tailored phage cocktails. Still, however, more in vivo studies are needed that investigate the complex interplay between diet and bacteriophages, especially in the context of the prevention and treatment of inflammatory diseases and cancer.
</p>
