<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The poultry industry was and is still suffering from severe challenges because of the increasing prices of soybean meal and yellow corn which are mainly used in formulating poultry diets. Therefore, there is an urgent need for nutritious and affordable alternatives. To reduce costs, the best strategy is to formulate diets using alternative and locally available ingredients such as distillers dried grains with soluble. Distillers dried grains with solubles (DDGS) is a co-product of ethanol-producing plants that use corn and wheat for manufacturing [
 <xref rid="B1-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. It is a rich source of crude protein, amino acids, crude fat, and minerals [
 <xref rid="B3-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>], as well as non-starch polysaccharides (NSP) in poultry diets. However, monogastric animals do not efficiently digest feedstuffs that are high in NSP. As a result, the metabolizable energy of DDGS is lower than that of corn (2820 vs. 3420 kcal/kg, respectively) on an as-fed basis [
 <xref rid="B6-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. The fiber content of DDGS is another common reason for low digestible energy compared with other feed ingredients. The fiber content is not converted to ethanol, so DDGS has about 35% insoluble and 6% soluble dietary fiber [
 <xref rid="B2-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. The apparent digestibility of dietary fiber is about 43.7% in a monogastric animal, which negatively reflects on dry matter digestibility [
 <xref rid="B2-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. However, supplementing monogastric diets with exogenous enzymes could improve the available energy of DDGS by degrading the fiber content of DDGS and increasing the digestibility of other components [
 <xref rid="B8-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. The use of a multi-enzyme complex (enzyme cocktail) aims to deal with more than the problems in the feedstuff used; it may contain enzymes to improve the digestibility of NSP, fibers, or other components [
 <xref rid="B3-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Eggs are a staple food in human diet and have a natural balance of essential nutrients. Eggs have a high nutritional value and provide consumers with cheaper animal protein than other foodstuffs (e.g., meat and milk). Measurements of external and internal egg quality can be beneficial to producers since they provide information on the outcome of the egg production process, and reflect the health condition of the flock. Yolk color is of great importance in terms of consumer expectations in different European countries, with varying demands for yolk color between light yellow and deep orange. Yolk color is affected by various components provided in feed ingredients and feed additives [
 <xref rid="B10-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Roberson et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>] claim that yolk color density increased linearly with increasing the dietary DDGS up to 15%. Cholesterol content can range from 11 to 15 mg/g of yolk, which constitutes around 5% of total yolk lipids. Besides this, the high dietary fiber content of DDGS diets might affect cholesterol levels in eggs. The present study hypothesized that the simultaneous use of DDGS will provide an alternative feedstuff and decrease amounts of yellow corn and soybean meal in layer diets without adverse effects on productive performance or egg characteristics. Additionally, the use of the exogenous enzyme mixture (EEM) may improve the digestibility of low-digestible nutrients in DDGS. Moreover, studies investigating the effect of DDGS and enzyme cocktail on egg yolk fatty acids are scarce, so this is one of the major goals of the present study.
</p>
