<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Several studies provided evidence for the high antioxidant potential of chia seeds. Sargi et al. [
 <xref rid="B59-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>] showed that chia seeds are capable of deactivating ABTS cation radicals. However, a higher activity was recorded for seeds of brown and golden flax. Those authors also showed that chia seeds exhibit the capacity to scavenge synthetic DPPH radicals and reduce iron ions. Results obtained in both tests indicate a higher antioxidant activity of chia seeds in comparison to flaxseed [
 <xref rid="B59-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. Antioxidant activity of chia seeds was also confirmed by Coelho and Salas-Mellado [
 <xref rid="B39-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. They showed that extracts from chia seeds are capable of quenching DPPH radicals and they cause their neutralisation by over 70%. Additionally, they showed that these extracts inhibit enzymatic oxidation of guaiacol [
 <xref rid="B39-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. In turn, Segura-Campos et al. [
 <xref rid="B55-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>] confirmed that protein hydrolysates from chia seeds are also capable of reducing ABTS cation radicals. They suggested that the tested protein hydrolysates could act as electron donors [
 <xref rid="B55-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. A major indicator of antioxidant potential in biological samples is provided by the value of ORAC (Oxygen Radical Absorbance Capacity). It was shown that ORAC of chia seeds is comparable to that of prunes and hazelnuts (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nutrients-11-01242-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>). Antioxidant activity of compounds contained in chia seeds was also confirmed in the fat emulsion system. Reyes-Caudillo et al. [
 <xref rid="B25-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] assessed the effect of chia seed extract addition on the degradation rate of beta-carotene in a model system of linoleic acid/beta-carotene in the course of heating at 50 °C. They observed that extracts from chia seeds exhibit antioxidant properties in the model emulsion amounting to 73.5% and 79.3%. They also confirmed the capacity of chia seeds to inhibit lipid peroxidation [
 <xref rid="B25-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. 
</p>
