<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The ORAC assay was carried out using a Fluoroskan Ascent FL microplate reader (Thermo, Waltham, MA, USA) using the method described previously [
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-26-00224" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-26-00224" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] with minor modifications. Antioxidants can scavenge the peroxyl radicals generated by AAPH, which prevent the degradation of the fluorescein and, therefore, prevent the loss of the fluorescence of fluorescein. Briefly, fluorescein sodium salt (117 nM) and AAPH (40 mM) were freshly prepared in 0.1 M phosphate-buffered saline (PBS, pH 7.4). For reaction, 120 µL of fluorescein sodium salt (117 nM) and 20 µL of sample (dissolved in methanol, extract 10–20 µg/mL; compounds 10–160 µM) were mixed in a black 96-well plate and pre-incubated for 15 min at 37 °C. Next, 60 µL of AAPH (40 mM) was added, and the fluorescence was measured 100 times (interval 1 min) at excitation and emission wavelengths of 485 nm and 538 nm, respectively, by the microplate reader maintained at 37 °C. Trolox was used as a positive control, which showed a linear net AUC (the area under the curve) values cure within concentrations of 0.50 µg/mL (2.00 µM) and 4.00 µg/mL (16.00 µM), whereas the net AUC was calculated by subtracting the AUC of the blank group (without samples) from that of a sample group. The relative ORAC values are expressed in µg Trolox equivalents/µg extract or µM Trolox equivalents/µM compound. The AUC is calculated using Equation (2):
 <disp-formula id="FD2-molecules-26-00224">
  <label>(2)</label>
  <math id="mm2">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>AUC</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mn>1</mn>
     <mo>+</mo>
     <msubsup>
      <mstyle mathsize="90%" displaystyle="true">
       <mo>∑</mo>
      </mstyle>
      <mrow>
       <mi>n</mi>
       <mo>=</mo>
       <mn>1</mn>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mi>n</mi>
       <mo>=</mo>
       <mn>99</mn>
      </mrow>
     </msubsup>
     <msub>
      <mi>f</mi>
      <mi>n</mi>
     </msub>
     <mo>/</mo>
     <msub>
      <mi>f</mi>
      <mn>0</mn>
     </msub>
     <mo>,</mo>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <italic>f</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> is the initial fluorescence of the fluorescein reading at 0 min and 
 <italic>f
  <sub>n</sub>
 </italic> is the fluorescence reading at time 
 <italic>n</italic>.
</p>
