<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As anticipated, the performance in the PC group was most adversely affected. These results are consistent with those of [
 <xref rid="B66-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] who showed that 
 <italic>Eimeria</italic>-infected birds exhibited a significant reduction of body weight and feed consumption compared with uninfected birds due to coccidiosis infection, resulting in poor nutrient absorption and decreased immune response and consequently intestinal tissue injury [
 <xref rid="B67-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. However, the results indicated that the BW, FCR, PI, and the production efficacy of the RN- and Sacox-treated groups were negatively affected (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) by the coccidia challenge compared to those in the NC group that resulted in reduced weight gain due to coccidiosis. Fortunately, the performance parameters were positively affected in the RN- and Sacox-treated groups compared to those in the PC group, which are in agreement with the results reported by [
 <xref rid="B27-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]; however, the present study values were not significant. The non-significant findings observed in both groups in this study were incompatible with those reported by [
 <xref rid="B27-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] who reported high values for BWG, BW, and PEF in the group treated with a synthetic anti-coccidial drug (Elancoban). In the present study, the performance was not dependent on the dose. In contrast to the result of [
 <xref rid="B57-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], it was observed that the performance increased linearly with an increase in dose, excluding feed consumption. The synthetic drug Sacox used as a control in this study had an intermediate anti-coccidial effect. Here, the birds in the Sacox treated group were consumed with higher feed compared to the birds in other infected groups, resulting in the worst feed conversion and feed efficiency due to the reduced gain and higher feed intake of birds. Our findings differ from those of [
 <xref rid="B12-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-animals-11-00167" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] which found that Sacox was the best performing groups.
</p>
