<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Metabolomic profiles from organisms in the Plantae and other kingdoms have been used to distinguish samples from different species and ecotypes, as well as aid in their classification (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dettmer et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Allwood et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Aliferis et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jing et al., 2015</xref>). In the case of plants, much attention has been given to one of the largest group of metabolites they produce, the terpenoids. In a study similar to ours which explored the chemodiversity of 
 <italic class="italic">Selaginella</italic> in the context of evolution, 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Weng and Noel (2013)</xref> suggest that monoterpene and sesquiterpene synthases are derived from conserved diterpene synthases, based off of phylogenetic analyses of plant terpene synthases done by 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bohlmann et al. (1998)</xref>. Thus, it appears that monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes are frequently used as chemical markers for distinguishing between genera. For example, in the 
 <italic class="italic">Lantana</italic> (Verbenaceae) genus, β-caryophyllene was the major compound suggested as a chemical marker (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sena Filho et al., 2010</xref>), while in 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic>, both cyclic (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>-(+)-limonene and α-terpinene) and bicyclic monoterpenes (
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-pinene and sabinene) were dominant in fruit essential oils and therefore proposed as markers for those species/varieties (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jing et al., 2015</xref>). Worldwide, the volatile metabolomics composition of 
 <italic class="italic">Vitex</italic> species has been poorly investigated, likely due to their accessibility and phenotype, namely, their size and bad odor. From a total of 250 species, only about 35 are reported in the literature with in-depth chemical characterizations. Many of them are difficult to identify due to endemism, e.g., 
 <italic class="italic">Vitex rufences</italic> A. Juss, 
 <italic class="italic">Vitex capitata</italic> Vahl, 
 <italic class="italic">Vitex gardneriana</italic> Schauer, which are found only in areas in the northeast of Brazil.
</p>
