<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Topical anti-inflammatory activity was assessed as inhibition of xylene-induced ear edema in mice [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-03671" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Male Swiss mice were divided into groups of 5 mice each. Thirty min after the dermal application of LSEO, 10 µL acetone solution containing 10% xylene was carefully applied to the anterior and posterior surfaces of the left ear. The right ear remained untreated. Vehicle (sweet almond oil), doses of LSEO diluted in almond oil (82, 410, and 820 mg/kg), and positive controls (Voltaren
 <sup>®</sup> Emulgel 1% and Betasone
 <sup>®</sup> 0.05%) were applied topically to the left ear about 30 min before the xylene application. At the maximum of the edematous response (4 h later), mice were sacrificed and a plug (5 mm in diameter) was removed from both treated (left) and untreated (right) ears. The edema response was calculated as the weight difference between the two plugs. LSEO anti-inflammatory potential was expressed as percentage of the edema weight reduction in treated mice in comparison to the control group, and calculated using the following formula:
 <disp-formula id="FD4-molecules-25-03671">
  <math id="mm4">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mo>%</mo>
      <mtext> </mtext>
      <mi>Inhibition</mi>
      <mtext> </mtext>
      <mi>of</mi>
      <mtext> </mtext>
      <mi>edema</mi>
      <mtext> </mtext>
     </mrow>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mrow>
      <mo>(</mo>
      <mrow>
       <mn>1</mn>
       <mo>−</mo>
       <mfrac>
        <mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mo>Δ</mo>
          <mi>Wt</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mo>Δ</mo>
          <mi>Wc</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mrow>
       </mfrac>
      </mrow>
      <mo>)</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mo>×</mo>
     <mn>100</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where ΔWt is the change in weight of ear tissue in the treated mice, and ΔWc is the change in weight of ear tissue in the control mice.
</p>
