<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0105">One of the great current challenges is to understand the role of the immune system in the face of SARS-CoV-2 infection. So far we know that the protective effects of immunity against SARS-CoV-2 suffer widespread failures. However, the real causes and mechanisms by which the immune response is compromised in individuals with SARS-CoV-2 are still unclear. In addition, the picture of infections is very varied, as has been discussed previously, several types of patients can be observed, from asymptomatic patients to severe cases, with a wide spectrum of impaired vital functions. However, we know that immunity remains the Holy Grail of COVID-19 research. Although the immunity of individuals appears to have a central role, we know that there is still some mechanism to be identified that acts as an immune response imbalance system. This has been observed and shows that even patients with good immunity can progress to severe clinical conditions, although the highest mortality rate can be observed in patients with comorbidities and advanced age (
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Ghinai et al., 2020</xref>). The central role of immunity against SARS-CoV-2 infection is no different than that seen for other viral infections. As already described by 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Gorbalenya et al. (2020)</xref>, immunity acts directly, initially controlling and managing an innate immune response against viral infection, then, if innate immunity manages to overcome the infection, a new immune response is achieved, that is, the acquired immune response. The innate immune response acts directly after the identification of an infectious process, by stimulating the natural mechanisms of protection against the penetration of pathogens, such as the skin, enzymes and antiviral peptides. However, in several cases, of individuals with SARS-CoV-2 infection, the immune system itself already suffers serious damage and its functionality is impaired, even at the beginning of the innate immune response. What has been the subject of many discussions about, what are the mechanisms for activating an inadequate immune response? Therefore, in these cases, the majority of infected individuals have several clinical signs of inflammation and, in several cases, processes of hyperinflammation and serious impairment of vital organs. On the other hand, Individuals who manage to overcome all infections properly, that is, with the immune system acting in a balanced way, obtain the acquired immune response. Although it is not clear how long the immune response acquired due to SARS-CoV-2 infection can prevent new infections, we know that the immune system after the infection has recovered is prepared to deal with possible new infections in a more balanced way (
 <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2020a</xref>). To understand in more detail about immune system failures in patients infected with SARS-CoV-2, we will address the recent findings by 
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Lucas et al. (2020)</xref>, in 
 <xref rid="tbox1" ref-type="boxed-text">Box 1</xref> .
 <boxed-text id="tbox1">
  <label>Box 1</label>
  <caption>
   <title>Immune system failures in patients infected with SARS-CoV-2.</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="p0340">
   <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Lucas et al. (2020)</xref>, in a study published on August 17 by the journal Nature, performs extensive analyzes on the immune response of patients infected with COVID-19, using a longitudinal study methodology. The study evaluated 113 people hospitalized with COVID-19 and a similar number of healthy patients as a control. Blood plasma molecules were monitored in both groups, in particular, immune cells such as peripheral blood mononuclear cells, CD4 T cells, CD8 T cells, and B cells. The longitudinal study allowed researchers to draw important conclusions about the evolution of phenomena in the immune system. Therefore, a summary of these conclusions is presented below:
   <list list-type="simple" id="ulist0015">
    <list-item id="u0035">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0345">The authors identified that some immunological signaling molecules, known as cytokines, are expressed in people with moderate or severe clinical conditions of COVID-19.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0040">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0350">The level of cytokines, such as IFN-λ, increased dramatically in patients who progressed to more severe clinical conditions.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0045">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0355">Pro-inflammatory cytokines such as TNF-α, increased dramatically and correlated positively with viral load in the nasal passages.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0050">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0360">Some cytokines not associated with the defense system against viral infections, such as IL-5 that aid in the defense against parasites and allergic reactions are regulated positively according to the disease progression.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0055">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0365">The levels of CD4 and CD8 T cells, which are responsible for the immune response against viral infections, have been drastically reduced in both patients with moderate disease and in critically ill patients.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <p id="p0370">Based on these results, the authors divide patients into three groups based on the course of clinical evolution and the severity of the disease. Therefore, we have patients with moderate, severe and very severe clinical conditions:
   <list list-type="simple" id="ulist0020">
    <list-item id="u0060">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0375">Patient with moderate clinical condition: in general, these patients after infection have low levels of inflammatory markers and an increase in the level of proteins associated with tissue repair.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0065">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="p0380">Patients with severe and very severe clinical condition: these patients have high levels of IFN-α, IL-1Ra and proteins associated with T H 1-, T H 2- and T H, even after the final phase of viral replication.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <p id="p0385">Lucas and his collaborators fill an important gap in understanding the role of the immune system in the face of COVID-19 infection. This study provides an understanding of the signature of the immune response and helps to clarify how the disease has progressed to severe cases. However, the role of the immune system in the face of COVID-19 infection is not yet clear. However, this study helps to clarify the basic principles by which the immune system has suffered cascades of failures that result in severe illness. Therefore, new efforts should focus on understanding the reasons for failures and how they can be avoided.</p>
  <notes notes-type="alt-text" specific-use="for-accessibility" id="alttext0035">
   <p>Alt-text: Box 1</p>
  </notes>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
