<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0140">Antioxidant enzymes like catalase, glutathione, glutathione-S-transferase, and superoxide dismutase are primarily responsible for the reduction of free radicals in the body. Abdel-Gabbar et al. (2019) assessed the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> activity of these enzymes by the administration of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. aqueous extract on the experimental rabbits, where the levels were found to be increased by 14.12%, 27.69%, 98.75% and 78.29%, respectively (p &lt; 0.05) compared with that of the control (water). Total antioxidant capacity was increased at 100 mg/kg and 50 mg/kg concentration in rabbits, with no adverse effects on kidney and liver function parameters [
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Similarly, the levels of alanine aminotransferase, aspartate aminotransferase, and alkaline phosphatase were also significantly increased (2 units/ml) upon the administration of 500 mg/kg of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. aqueous extract for 14 days. In combination with paracetamol, (200 mg/kg), the enzyme levels increased by 15–20 units/ml, compared with that of the control (p &lt; 0.01) [
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. In addition, the antioxidant potential of the aqueous extract was also assessed using conventional methods. The aqueous extract of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. leaf and stem was analysed with 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) resulting in the free radical scavenging activity (92.0%) at a concentration of 1.5 mg/ml, in accordance with butylated hydroxyanisole (BHA-95.7%) and butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT-96.6%). The potential benefits observed in the study were attributed to the presence of polysaccharides like starch, homogalacturonan, rhamnogalacturonan I (RG-I) and cellulose in 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. leaves. The binding of RG-I with bovine serum albumin (BSA) indicated the formation of water-soluble complexes that further induces antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].
</p>
