<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Biomass resources have been frequently used to produce PVC plasticizers as low-cost raw materials. Bio-based plasticizers designed for different application are mostly based on chemical structure of biomass resources. Cardanol is a promising alternative to traditional petrochemical-based 
 <italic class="italic">o</italic>-phthalate plasticizers due to its benzene ring structure and active hydroxyl group. Vegetable oil contains flexible long fatty acid chains and rich unsaturated bonds and can be used to produce epoxy plasticizer. Epoxidized soybean oil (ESO) has been industrialized and used as primary plasticizer in food packing materials. Vegetable oil-based flame-retardant plasticizers provide rich carbon combined with flame-retardant elements to improve flame retardancy of PVC product by promoting the formation of char residue. Cardanol and vegetable oil have been the two most important biomass feedstocks for producing plasticizers. Internally plasticized strategy produces excellent polymer materials with plasticity and flexibility but without plasticizer migration. Thermal stability, migration stability, biodegradability and plasticizing efficiency of bio-based plasticizers have been widely investigated and discussed in the literature. However, research on biological toxicity of bio-based plasticizers on human body and animal such as experimental mice and fish is scant. From an industrialization point of view, biological toxicity of bio-based plasticizers should be taken into account. Considerable efforts should be devoted to investigating the relationship between biological toxicity and chemical structure of bio-based plasticizers. Then, we can design non-toxic and environmentally-friendly biomass-based plasticizers to replace reproductive toxicity of o-phthalate plasticizers. Biomass raw materials, synthesis strategy, performances of PVC materials plasticized with bio-based plasticizers, and recent development in plasticizer field, as discussed in this article, might be used for the commercialization of bio-based, low-cost, environmentally-friendly plasticizers for numerous applications.
</p>
