<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Among these products, bullfrog oil stands out as an animal oil extracted by the biotechnological reuse of the adipose tissue from the amphibious 
 <italic class="italic">Rana catesbeiana</italic> Shaw. Bullfrog oil presents in its chemical composition a pool of saturated and unsaturated fatty acids responsible for potential antimicrobial and antibiofilm activities [
 <xref rid="B16-pharmaceutics-10-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-pharmaceutics-10-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Nevertheless, the in natura use of this oil shows some disadvantages, such as unpleasant organoleptic characteristics and undesirable biopharmaceutical properties, which may compromise its use and leads to a low patient compliance [
 <xref rid="B16-pharmaceutics-10-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-pharmaceutics-10-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. To overcome these drawbacks, the development of an emulsified system to deliver the bullfrog oil and to allow its adherence to the buccal mucosa could be a technological approach that enables its use for treatment of OC. Examples of emulsified systems are microemulsion [
 <xref rid="B18-pharmaceutics-10-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>], topical nanoemulsion for external use [
 <xref rid="B17-pharmaceutics-10-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], and oral nanoemulsion [
 <xref rid="B19-pharmaceutics-10-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>], already developed by our research group. Indeed, such systems, composed of aqueous and oily phases stabilized by a surfactant blend [
 <xref rid="B20-pharmaceutics-10-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>], allow the internalization of bullfrog oil in its droplets and, through the use of pharmaceutical excipients, may increase the adherence of this oil into the buccal mucosa, allowing contact to the microorganisms of the oral cavity, and consequently improving its antimicrobial activity [
 <xref rid="B21-pharmaceutics-10-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>].
</p>
