<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="molecules-25-05414-f003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>(
   <bold>A</bold>) Solubility of bruceine D (BD) in different excipients; (
   <bold>B</bold>) Schematic diagram of BD in the self-nanoemulsifying drug delivery system, which was termed BD-SNEDDS and consisted of BD in medium-chain triglyceride (MCT) oil and encapsulated within PEG-15-hydroxystearate (HS-15) and propylene glycol cosurfactants; (
   <bold>C</bold>) Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) image of BD-SNEDDS nanoemulsions; (
   <bold>D</bold>) In vitro release profiles of BD in BD-SNEDDS nanoemulsions and in an aqueous suspension in simulated intestinal fluid comprising phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) (pH 6.8) and in simulated gastric fluid comprising HCl (pH 1.2) conditions; (
   <bold>E</bold>) Mean concentration of BD in rat plasma at different time points following oral administration of BD-SNEDDS nanoemulsions and aqueous BD. The inset shows a magnified view between 0 and 6 h postadministration. ** indicates 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. BD-suspension group; (
   <bold>F</bold>) Colon lengths of rats in an experimental colitis model with the following test groups: Intact: no treatment; Vehicle: treatment without drug; AZA: treatment with azathioprine; BD-suspension: BD in PBS; BDL-SNEDDS, BDM-SNEDDS, and BDH-SNEDDS are treatments with low, medium, and high doses of BD-SNEDDS, respectively. 
   <sup>##</sup> indicates 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. Intact group. * and ** indicate 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 and 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. Vehicle group, respectively. 
   <sup>☆</sup> and 
   <sup>☆☆</sup> indicate 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 and 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. BD-suspension group, respectively. Reproduced with permission from [
   <xref rid="B69-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="molecules-25-05414-g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
