<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HTs have owned their name as they can be hydrolyzed by weak acids/bases, producing carbohydrates and phenolic acids because of the reaction [
 <xref rid="B3-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. They are formed by glycosylated gallic acid units [
 <xref rid="B9-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], which can be either ellagic acid (EA) or gallic acid (GA), forming ellagitannins (ETs) and gallotannins (GTs), respectively [
 <xref rid="B3-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. ETs are formed by simple to multiple units of hexahydroxydiphenol (HHDP) connected to a polyol core. After hydrolysis and the breakdown of C-C bonds between suitably orientated galloyl residues of glucogalloyl molecules of HHDP, they are converted into EA units [
 <xref rid="B2-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The abundant variety of structure has been observed within this group, due to the different possibilities in the formation of oxidative linkages [
 <xref rid="B7-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. On the other hand, GTs are considered as simpler HTs and are formed by galloyl or digalloyl units coupled to a polyol, catechin or triterpenoid unit, in the form of pentagalloyl glucose (PGG). They can yield GA from the hydrolysis reaction [
 <xref rid="B2-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. HTs can be mainly found in fruits, berries, legumes, leafy vegetables and different tree species [
 <xref rid="B3-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. They have been widely employed in the leather industry and they have been studied for their antioxidant and antimicrobial properties [
 <xref rid="B3-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].
</p>
