<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Saffron is an extraordinarily rich source of nutraceutical and pharmaceutical properties that exhibit numerous health benefits and pharmacological effects [
 <xref rid="B42-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In the present study, we have evaluated the analgesic, anti-inflammatory, anticoagulant, and antidepressant activities of saffron ethanolic extracts in mice. The selection of 80% ethanol and/or ethanolic extracts was chosen for the study due to their efficiency against cancer [
 <xref rid="B43-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], blood pressure [
 <xref rid="B45-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], inflammation [
 <xref rid="B47-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], and nociception [
 <xref rid="B48-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. None of the orally administered saffron extracts (800 mg/kg) caused any mortality or prominent behavioral abnormalities in mice during the 7-days acute toxicity study. In literature, toxicological reports regarding saffron safety are not uniform. Iranshahi et al. [
 <xref rid="B50-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] assessed the toxicity level of 800 mg/kg SEE, PEE, stigma aqueous extract (SAE), and petal aqueous extract (PAE) and found no toxicological signs on mice. In another study, the maximum non-toxic dose of SEE and PEE was reported as 2 and 8 g/kg, respectively [
 <xref rid="B48-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Furthermore, LD
 <sub>50</sub> values of intraperitoneal administered petal and stigma extracts in mice were 6 and 1.6 g/kg, respectively [
 <xref rid="B51-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Similarly, no mortality of mice was reported within 2 days of study with high oral and intraperitoneal doses (3 g/kg) of the active constituent of saffron, crocin, in mice [
 <xref rid="B52-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].
</p>
