<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Studies from Shahidi et al. [
 <xref rid="B50-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] indicated for the first time that the antinociceptive effects of 
 <italic>V. officinalis</italic> are mediated by the serotonergic and dopaminergic systems. Monoamine neurotransmitters in the central nervous system, mostly serotonin (5-hydroxytryptamine, 5-HT) and norepinephrine, are crucial in regulating cognition, emotion, and mood. These neurotransmitters also play an essential role in the stress response and the mechanism of antidepressant action. It was observed that 
 <italic>V. officinalis</italic> extract can suppress physical and psychological stress responses by controlling the variations in these neurotransmitters turnover in the hippocampus and amygdala [
 <xref rid="B22-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and reduces the plasma corticosterone levels in D-galactose-induced aging mice [
 <xref rid="B49-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Dichloromethane extracts from 
 <italic>V. wallichii</italic> significantly improve norepinephrine and dopamine amounts with no changes in serotonin amounts [
 <xref rid="B59-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. The effects of 
 <italic>V. adscendens</italic> extracts on the central nervous system have been associated with the interaction with serotoninergic, dopaminergic, and noradrenergic receptors [
 <xref rid="B95-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. On the other hand, studies from Lee et al. [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] suggest that the antinociceptive effects of 
 <italic>V. fauriei</italic> can be related to modulatory effects on the BDNF signaling pathway in the hippocampus and medial prefrontal cortex. Recently, Choi et al. [
 <xref rid="B96-plants-10-00846" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>] demonstrated that this species exerts antidepressant effects through its anti-inflammatory and antioxidant effects by inhibiting BDNF expression.
</p>
