<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0170" class="p">Inspired by the original concept of the surfactant-assisted self-assembly approach, a modified process was developed to fabricate self-assembled porphyrin nanocrystals (
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bai et al., 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bai et al., 2011</xref>). Some porphyrins, such as zinc meso-tetra (4-pyridyl) porphyrin (ZnTPyP), are hard to dissolve in common organic solvents such as chloroform and toluene. Therefore it is impossible to apply the surfactant-assisted self-assembly directly. Bai et al. modified the method through an acid-base neutralization process in the aqueous phase instead of forming microemulsions. In this case, they were able to self-assemble ZnTPyP into more favorable arrangements via coordination of its peripheral pyridine groups to its core Zn ions, whereas most porphyrins form H-aggregates in a face-to-face manner via π-overlap (
 <xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhong et al., 2014a</xref>). First, they protonated ZnTPyP with positive charges through an acidic solution to prepare a water-soluble precursor. Then, they mixed the acidic aqueous solution with a basic surfactant solution under vigorous stirring with a range of volume ratios. Once mixed, acid-base neutralization reaction occurred and deprotonated the charged ZnTPyP precursor. This produced insoluble neutral ZnTPyP molecules that were automatically trapped into the hydrophobic micellar interiors. Through confined noncovalent interactions within surfactant micelles, such as metal-ligand axial coordination (Zn-N) and π-π interactions, nucleation and growth was initiated for the formation of nanocrystals with a series of morphologies with controlled sizes and dimensions. The role of the surfactants is to essentially encapsulate hydrophobic porphyrins within the surfactant micellar interiors, which further confines the self-assembly of the ZnTPyP nanocrystals. Using this modified method, various 1D–3D porphyrin nanocrystals such as NPs, nanooctahedra, hexagonal rods, tetragonal nanorods, nanotubes, nanowires, and nanodisks have been produced through kinetic control (
 <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 11</xref>) (
 <xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhong et al., 2014a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wang et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wang et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wang et al., 2018b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhang et al., 2018</xref>). For example, the nanocrystal dimension increases with increasing surfactant concentrations and pH value.
</p>
