<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0145">Antigen-antibody reactions, decomposition of tissues, parasitism or a wide variety of chronic diseases involving continuous degranulatiom of mast cells and causing release of histamine, mostly induce eosinophilia [
 <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. All the treated rats in the sub-chronic toxicity studies gained weight, although not dose dependently. This may be as a result of the nutritional components of the crude plant materials like carbohydrate, crude protein and lipid that are contained in the extracts of this plant [
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Quantification of enzymes activities in body fluids is crucial in disease investigation and diagnosis. Tissue enzyme activities are frequently used as a 'marker' to establish toxic effects of administered compounds to experimental animals. Chalasani et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] reported that regardless of the mechanism involved, reduce serum activities of aminotransferases have not been shown to correlate with the toxicologically significant outcome on the liver. Therefore, the decrease in the activity of AST as seen between the control group and 750 mg/kg bark ethyl acetate fraction treated group may not be attributed to toxic effect of the plant extract, as indicated by the result of histopathology of the liver. The insignificant difference observed in ALT, ALP, total bilirubin, conjugated bilirubin, total protein, urea and creatinine in the treated groups as compared with the control was an indication that the extract is relatively not toxic at the tested doses and period used in this study. One may conclude that based on the results of liver and kidney functions and histopathology of these organs, the extract had no overall significant toxicity in rats. Cellular morphological changes resulting from non-fatal injury are labeled degenerations and these are reversible disorders if the cause of the injury is removed [
 <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Therefore the focal areas of hepatic degeneration that were observed in rats treated with leaf ethyl acetate extract at 500 mg/kg in the sub-chronic toxicity studies and congestion in rats treated with leaf ethyl acetate fraction at 750 mg/kg, were reversible pathological lesions, suggesting that the extracts, even at those doses are relatively safe. Body responses to this degenerative change include active hyperaemia and, consequently, congestion as seen in rats administered leaf ethyl acetate fraction at 750 mg/kg in the sub-chronic toxicity studies. The hyperaemia was as a result of increase in capillary blood to the liver. This was caused by increased physiological demand for blood, in response to challenges caused by the wound. This led to congestion as seen in the liver of rats administered the highest dose of 750 mg/kg in the sub-chronic study [
 <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Lower doses of 250 mg/kg and 500 mg/kg of leaf ethyl acetate fraction gave no visible lesion in the sub-chronic toxicity studies. This is in agreement with earlier observation [
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] who reported that toxicity of substances may be directly related to the doses exposed to, since every substance may be toxic if given in large enough doses, as the difference between medicine and poison is the dose, with toxicity increasing with increase in dose. The kidney, skeletal muscles and the heart tissues of all the rats in all experimental groups in the sub-chronic toxicity studies showed no visible lesions.
</p>
