<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">P. marginatum</italic> leaves and stems are used in Brazil, especially in Paraíba State, against snake bites and as a sedative [
 <xref rid="B146-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">146</xref>] while in north-eastern Brazil and in the northern region, especially in the Amazon, 
 <italic class="italic">P. marginatum</italic> is commonly used for the treatment of inflammatory diseases, snake bites, as well as the liver and bile duct diseases [
 <xref rid="B87-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>]. In addition, the indigenous communities in Central America, the Antilles, and South America used 
 <italic class="italic">P. marginatum</italic> for gastrointestinal problems [
 <xref rid="B147-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">147</xref>]. Other than that, Almeida et al. [
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] also reported the uses of 
 <italic class="italic">P. marginatum</italic> as a tonic, carminative, stimulant, diuretic, and sudorific agents against stomach, liver and gall-bladder pain, toothaches, and snake and insect bites while da Silva et al. [
 <xref rid="B119-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">119</xref>] reported 
 <italic class="italic">P. marginatum</italic> to have antispasmodic actions. A preparation made from the leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">P. marginatum</italic> is used in French Guyana to treat malaria while in Trinidad and Tobago, Puerto Rico and Surinam, 
 <italic class="italic">P. marginatum</italic> has been used to treat female disorders and to help during childbirth [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Furthermore, 
 <italic class="italic">P. marginatum</italic> is also traditionally used in Brazil to treat asthma, erysipela, problems of the urinary system, vesicle and liver diseases, and to control blood pressure [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>].
</p>
