<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26" class="p">Some medicinal and aromatic plants (MAPs) are a rich source of essential oils, which have proven to possess a wide variety of biological activities such as antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory, antiseptic, anticancer, analgesic and sedative effects (Bhalla et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2013</xref>; Dhifi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">2016</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">Origanum vulgare</italic> L. (OV), which is also known as oregano or marjoram is a widespread flavoring culinary herb belonging to family Lamiaceae (Kokkini et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">2003</xref>). Traditionally, the plant has been employed as a remedy for different ailments like gastrointestinal disorders, colds, whooping and convulsive coughs, menstrual problems, headaches, depression and pruritis (Fleisher and Sneer 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">1982</xref>; Krishnakumar and Potty 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2012</xref>). The plant’s essential oil and different extracts have been reported as antioxidant, antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory as well as hypolipidemic (Bhat et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">2018</xref>; Elshafie et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2017</xref>; Leyva-López et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">2017</xref>; Milos et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2000</xref>; Morshedloo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">2018</xref>; Soliman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">2016</xref>). The essential oil composition varied widely according to the geographical area and growth conditions (Gong et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2014</xref>; Hernández-Hernández et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">2014</xref>; Morshedloo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">2017</xref>). Studies show that OV EO mostly contains phenolic compounds, mono-and sesquiterpene hydrocarbons, as well as their oxygenated derivatives. Major identified compounds in Chinese OV EO were thymol (42.9%) and 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cymen-2-ol (37.5%), while OV EO collected in Pakistan contained mainly β-citronellol (78.7%) and citronellol acetate (5.9%) (Gong et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2014</xref>). Essential oil of Saudi Arabia OV contained mainly carvacrol (70.2%) and γ-terpinene (5.6%) (Khan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">2018</xref>). On the other hand, Mexican OV EO had major its major compounds thymol (66.3%) and γ-terpinene (9.6%) (Hernández-Hernández et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">2014</xref>) and the Brazilian one contained thymol (21.9%) and carvacrol (4.7%) as major constituents (Pradebon Brondani et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">2018</xref>). OV cultivated in Spain contained in its essential oil 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-sabinene hydrate (37%) and terpinene-4-acetate (16.2%). This compositional variation may be attributed to difference in growth conditions, origin of plant collection, stage of plant maturity, physiological modifications in response to various environmental factors and stresses, harvesting time, drying methods, method of essential oil isolation or even the solvents used for the GC/MS analysis (Arranz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2015</xref>; Moghaddam and Mehdizadeh 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">2017</xref>).
</p>
