<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Constituent analysis of DPK revealed its enrichment in polyphenolic compounds, like gallic acid, neochlorogenic acid, cryptochlorogenic acid, vanillic acid, ellagic acid, corilagin, and rutin, which are very effective against oxidative stress, inflammation, and associated immunological responses (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Cholet et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Jantan et al., 2019</xref>). Gallic acid is a very potent antioxidant that can inhibit lipid peroxidation. Its triple phenolic structure helps in metal ion chelation (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Badhani et al., 2015</xref>). Gallic and ellagic acids can inhibit production of inflammatory cytokines, particularly LPS-induced IL-6. Besides, ellagic acid can normalize the activities of antioxidative enzymes (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">BenSaad et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2018</xref>). Gallic acid is also known to reduce symptoms of inflammation like, pain and swelling (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Choubey et al., 2015</xref>). Both neochlorogenic and cryptochlorogenic acids suppress inflammation through activation of the AMPK/Nrf2/HO1 pathway (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B122" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2020</xref>). Vanillic acid can reduce inflammatory pain by inhibiting neutrophil recruitment, oxidative stress, cytokine production, and NF-κB activation (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Calixto-Campos et al., 2015</xref>). The flavonoid rutin provides neuroprotection through its antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, and immune-modulating capabilities by inhibiting the p38 mitogen–activated protein kinase pathway (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Enogieru et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">Song et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">da Silva et al., 2020</xref>). Corilagin is a potent free radical scavenger that can also inhibit production of pro-inflammatory cytokines and effectors by blocking the NF-κB pathway (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2018</xref>). Thus, compositional analysis of DPK showed that it is enriched with several antioxidants and anti-inflammatory phytometabolites.
</p>
