<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>From the data reported in this miniature review, we have shown that a growing interest towards 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin has been recorded over the last decade with the characterization of novel plant sources and further insights into its biological activities and associated mechanisms of action. Thus, the idea that 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin may be regarded as a novel biologically active natural product with a great potential for the future has been enforced. It also has to be considered that this compound is nowadays very easy to synthesize in very high yields and could be available on the gram scale to perform further phytochemical and pharmacological studies, which surely deserve to be accomplished, to outline a more complete profile with designation of its biological targets, mechanism of action, and patterns of main and side effects. It is clear how 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin can nowadays effectively be regarded as an additional, although less abundant, component of the phytochemical pool of several plant species belonging to numerous families. The well-characterized biological effects so far assessed for this coumarin both in vitro and in vivo, in particular as an antitumor, cancer chemopreventive, and neuroprotective agent, reported herein do underline and enforce the role of the 7-isopentenyloxy-containing plants and their phytopreparations as beneficial means for human and animal health. In these respective “phytochemical contexts”, this coumarin may display a synergism of action with already reported phytochemicals such as flavonoids and phenolic acids with proven nutraceutical properties. Such a potential synergy surely deserves to be further detailed in the future, as does the search for other plant sources with a particular reference to food ones. Finally, it is noteworthy to highlight, discovered in the course of the new pharmacological investigations performed across the last decade, the importance of the biological activity in terms of structure activity relationship of the 3,3-dimethylallyl side chain, which confirms previously acquired data [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].
</p>
