<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since diabetes mellitus is characterized by insulin resistance, and β-cell dysfunction, therapeutic medications should be involved in improving insulin resistance, enhancing glucose uptake, decreasing blood glucose concentration, and protecting/regenerating β-cell from pancreatic islets. Many researchers have been investigated the anti-diabetic activities on the root of 
 <italic>Panax ginseng</italic> in vitro and in vivo experiments [
 <xref rid="B62-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. The most important group of phytochemicals f 
 <italic>Panax ginseng</italic> is ginseng-specific saponins called ginsenosides. Among them, Ginsenosied Rb2 was the most effective constituent treated for streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats by decreasing blood glucose level [
 <xref rid="B65-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Moreover, in fermented red ginseng extracts, the content of ginsenoside Rg2, Rg3, and Rh2 are higher than normal ginseng so that those extracts significantly reduced blood glucose levels and increased plasma insulin levels in streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats by orally-administered 100 or 200 mg/kg extracts dissolved in water, at 10 a.m. daily in three weeks [
 <xref rid="B66-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. These mechanisms have been displayed in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-09-00252-f006">Figure 6</xref>. In general, saponins, which were isolated from ginseng that has been proven significant antidiabetic activity. The mechanism of these components in antidiabetic treatment is to moderate the enzyme activity [
 <xref rid="B50-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] to influence glucose metabolism and control insulin secretion [
 <xref rid="B67-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>].
</p>
