<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Antioxidant capacity of 
 <italic>Semecarpus anacardium</italic> is also worth noting. Barman et al. (
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>) reported that 
 <italic>S. anacardium</italic> nut ethanol extract had high antioxidant activity as assessed by DPPH and ABTS radical scavenging and metal chelating assays. It should be noted that antioxidant activities of plants can be affected by manufacturing process (
 <xref rid="B154" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>). Tan and Chan (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) reported that up to 30% decrease can be obtained in phenolic content and antioxidant activity of 
 <italic>A. occidentale</italic> after blanching. However, no changes due to microwave treatment was observed. Interestingly, Trox et al. (
 <xref rid="B155" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>) reported that bioactive content of cashew nut kernels decreased after conventional shelling techniques, such as oil-bath roasting, steam roasting, drying, and open pan roasting; and they recommended flores hand-cracking method to minimize losses. Moreover, the contents of vitamin C, flavonoids, and polyphenols in cashew apple juice were increased after cold plasma treatment. Yet decreases in bioactive contents were observed at excessive exposure (
 <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>). Liao et al. (
 <xref rid="B157" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>) reported that antioxidant activity of cashew nut kernels were not affected by hot air-assisted radio frequency roasting. Moreover, sonication treatment improved the bioactive compound extraction yield from cashew apple bagasse compared to conventional heat treatment, and the optimum conditions were recommended as treatment for 6 min at an intensity of 226 W/cm
 <sup>2</sup> and 1:4 bagasse-to-water ratio resulting the highest vitamin C and total phenolic contents (
 <xref rid="B158" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>). In addition, total phenolic and tannin contents of 
 <italic>A. occidentale</italic> were increased by gamma-irradiation (
 <xref rid="B159" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>).
</p>
