<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CMG and mastic oil have been associated with a variety of biological functions and have been extensively studied regarding their antimicrobial, anticancer, anti-indigestion, and anti-inflammatory effects [
 <xref rid="B15-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. More particularly, mastic oil has effectively attenuated the development of 
 <italic>Salmonella enteritis</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas fragi</italic>, 
 <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic>, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B12-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Additionally, its anticancer potential has been demonstrated in a variety of studies. For instance, mastic oil exhibited proapoptotic and antiproliferative properties against the human leukemic cell line K562 in a time- and dose-dependent manner [
 <xref rid="B19-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Accordingly, treatment with mastic essential oil resulted in higher apoptosis, lower vascularization, and downregulation of chemokine expression in an immunocompetent mouse model of Lewis lung carcinoma [
 <xref rid="B20-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The anticancer activity of mastic oil was previously analyzed in colon carcinoma. The oil attenuated the proliferation of a panel of colon cancer cell lines (CT26, Caco-2, HT29), while its oral administration inhibited tumor growth of colon carcinoma in a BALB/c transplantable mouse model. Interestingly, its major components, myrcene and 
 <italic>α</italic>-pinene, did not exhibit the same anticancer activity as the mastic essential oil [
 <xref rid="B17-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. 
</p>
