<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While several studies describe the health-promoting properties of either CMG or its oil, few data are currently available regarding its antioxidant capacity or its cytoprotective or regenerative effects under oxidative conditions. Oxidative stress plays a leading role in the aging and pathogenesis of degenerative diseases such as atherosclerosis, cardiovascular disease, diabetes, and cancer [
 <xref rid="B21-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Antioxidants can counterbalance the damaging effects of oxidation on tissues and are characterized by their ability to inhibit the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) or their direct scavenging activity [
 <xref rid="B22-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Through this process, the antioxidants turn themselves into active molecules, but they are much less harmful, preventing significant damage to cell biomolecules [
 <xref rid="B23-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. However, antioxidant activity also extends to numerous other cellular physiological processes, such as regulation of signal transduction and regulation of gene expression of detoxifying or antioxidant enzymes [
 <xref rid="B24-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. It is also interesting that antioxidants can play a role as pro-oxidants. The same antioxidant molecules that remove active free radicals can cause mild oxidative stress, leading to the induction of cellular signaling to enhance antioxidant defense [
 <xref rid="B25-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Mild stress can turn the level of cellular defense against oxidative stress to a higher steady state, thereby contributing to an adaptive benefit to cell survival. Based on this information, the analysis of the antioxidant activity of bioactive compounds should include the study of all of these fundamental actions [
 <xref rid="B26-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
