<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Essential oil is a secondary metabolite, whose production depends on conditions such as individual plant chemotypes, geographical location, date of harvest and harvest frequency, growing conditions, water deficit, proportions of plant parts and type of drying, as well as hydrodistillation time [
 <xref rid="B14-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B79-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>]. Given the difference in composition of essential oil shown in 
 <xref rid="plants-08-00055-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>, some authors divide sage into several chemotypes depending on the concentration of the components. The most commonly used method is proposed by Tucker and Maciarello [
 <xref rid="B81-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>]. They have divided 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia officinalis</italic> essential oils into five groups based on four main components in the following order: (1) camphor &gt; α-thujone &gt; 1,8-cineole &gt; β-thujone; (2) camphor &gt; α-thujone &gt; β-thujone &gt; 1,8-cineole; (3) β-thujone &gt; camphor &gt;1,8-cineole &gt; α-thujone; (4) 1,8-cineole &gt; camphor &gt; α-thujone &gt; β-thujone; and (5) α-thujone &gt; camphor &gt; β-thujone &gt; 1, 8 cineole [
 <xref rid="B81-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>]. However, components like α-humulene, viridiflorol, or manool are highly abundant in sage essential oil. Therefore, Jug-Dujaković et al. [
 <xref rid="B82-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>] carried out a hierarchical cluster analysis based on the most common components (α-thujone, camphor, β-thujone, 1,8-cineole, β-pinene, camphene, borneol, and bornyl acetate) on samples from Croatia, in the Dalmatian region. Three clusters were created: (A) α-thujone &gt; camphor &gt; 1,8-cineole &gt; β-thujone were able to be separated; (B) β-thujone &gt; α-thujone &gt; camphor ≈ 1,8-cineole; and (C) camphor &gt; α-thujone &gt; 1,8-cineole &gt; camphene ≈ borneol. Hierarchical cluster analysis was also performed by Lakušić et al. [
 <xref rid="B18-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] who showed that the chemotype also depended on the age of the leaves. The young leaves belonged to α-humulene chemotypes, while the old leaves belonged to camphor or a thujone chemotype depending on the country of origin (Serbia or Croatia). Craft, Satyal, and Setzer [
 <xref rid="B83-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>], based on a cluster analysis of volatile components, divided the essential oil of sage leaves into 5 chemotypes. The first of them, as the authors have called it C1, is α-thujone/camphor chemotype, which is divided into 3 subgroups that are identical to those of the aforementioned authors. The third subgroup, C1c, has the best composition of 8.0% α-thujone, 18.6% camphor, 10.5% 1.8-cineole, and 6.4% β-thujone. The second group, called C2, is an α-humulene-rich group that is also divided into three subgroups. The third group, C3, is a β-thujone-rich chemotype that is divided into two subgroups. The fourth group, C4, known as 1,8-cineole/camphor chemotype, is also divided into two subgroups. The fifth chemotype (C5) is a sclareol/α-thujone type. Perry et al. [
 <xref rid="B75-plants-08-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>] found three chemotypes that differ in the content of α- and 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-thujone, and, hence, divided sage into high (39%–44%), medium (22%–28%), and low (9%) content of thujone. Also, they showed that there was a difference between the flowering parts of sage and leaves. The flower parts contained a higher proportion of β-pinene (27% versus 10%) and a smaller of thujone (16% versus 31%).
</p>
