<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We found a wide richness of insect families at fennel edges with 38 different families trapped, showing that 
 <italic>Foeniculum vulgare</italic> is susceptible to attracting a large diversity of insects. An overview of the few papers published about the flower-visitors of fennel illustrates that it can indeed attract bee, wasp, syrphid fly, moth, butterfly and coleopteran species [
 <xref rid="B13-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In our pan traps, the western honeybee (
 <italic>Apis mellifera</italic>) was the most abundant insect, representing 21% of the total abundance. This is consistent with intense beekeeping activity on the “
 <italic>Plateau de Valensole</italic>” due to the abundance of lavender (
 <italic>Lavandula hybrida</italic>) crops in the area. To produce an economically profitable lavender honey, many beekeepers install their hives during the lavender’s flowering period, which overlaps with the beginning of the fennel flowering. 
 <italic>Lavandula hybrida</italic> is known to produce nectar but no pollen because it is a sterile hybrid. Honeybees looking for pollen grains (for the development of their brood) can find this resource on fennel flowers. This high number of honeybees could be under-evaluated, as pan trapping is known to poorly capture honeybees. Previous studies have shown that several 
 <italic>Apis</italic> species (
 <italic>A. florea, A. cerana, A. dorsata, A. mellifera</italic>) could visit and pollinate the fennel [
 <xref rid="B14-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and we hypothesize here that the presence of 
 <italic>Apis mellifera</italic> could be profitable for the fennel yield. It could be interesting to explore the complementarity between fennel and lavender crops in future studies, both for the feeding requirement of honeybees and the pollination of fennel. Many wild bees were also found in traps, especially Halictidae and Andrenidae, showing that fennel might be attractive for wild bees too. Previous studies have shown that fennel is visited by a wide diversity of wild bees [
 <xref rid="B20-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and future studies could investigate their relative efficiency for the pollination of fennel and its yield. 
</p>
