<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Alginate is a linear anionic polysaccharide extracted from marine algae containing β-
 <sc class="sc">d</sc>-mannuronate and α-
 <sc class="sc">l</sc>-guluronate residues linked by (1,4)-glycosidic bonds. This biopolymer has found a variety of applications in biomedical science and the food industry due to its biocompatibility and gelation capability [
 <xref rid="B177-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">177</xref>,
 <xref rid="B178-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">178</xref>]. Several strategies have been followed in the last few years to confer an antimicrobial character on alginate-based materials. In recent investigations, sodium alginate/poly(ethylene glycol) hydrogels with antimicrobial activity were prepared by grafting the cysteine-terminated antimicrobial peptide HHC10–CYS, at different proportions, into the structure through a thiol-ene click reaction [
 <xref rid="B179-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">179</xref>]. Microbiological studies of the hydrogel against 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> bacteria revealed that the activity increased with the content of peptide in the hydrogel. In addition to the strong antibacterial activity, the hydrogel showed good cytocompatibility. Nevertheless, most of the works related to alginate-based materials with an antibacterial character use approaches that are mainly centered on the incorporation of antimicrobial agents into the alginate material without any chemical reaction. In fact, there is a huge number of publications on the preparation of nano- and microcapsules of alginate for the encapsulation of antimicrobial components, such as essential oils [
 <xref rid="B180-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">180</xref>,
 <xref rid="B181-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">181</xref>], nisin [
 <xref rid="B182-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">182</xref>,
 <xref rid="B183-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">183</xref>], ZnO NPs [
 <xref rid="B184-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">184</xref>], and AgNPs [
 <xref rid="B185-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">185</xref>]. In this respect, a common strategy is the preparation of capsules by the formation of complexes between anionic alginate and cationic polysaccharides, such as chitosan [
 <xref rid="B186-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">186</xref>], or cationic peptides, such as nisin [
 <xref rid="B187-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">187</xref>], with inherent antimicrobial properties. Besides this, antimicrobial films based on alginate have also been prepared by incorporating the antimicrobial agents [
 <xref rid="B142-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">142</xref>,
 <xref rid="B188-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">188</xref>,
 <xref rid="B189-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">189</xref>,
 <xref rid="B190-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">190</xref>].
</p>
