<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since parasitic plants selectively depress the biomass of preferred host taxa that may be competitively dominant within a community, plant parasitism can alter the competitive balance between preferred and nonpreferred hosts (Pennings &amp; Callaway, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). As a result of this indirect effect, parasitic plants can alter plant community biomass, species composition, and dynamics (Pennings &amp; Callaway, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). For instance, field observations and experimental removal of 
 <italic>C. salina</italic> from a Northern Californian salt marsh found that the parasite reduced the abundance of dominant host species in the community and facilitated plant species evenness, richness, and diversity (Grewell, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Pennings &amp; Callaway, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>). A perturbation field experiment at two sites in England (Holme and Strumpshaw) found that 
 <italic>R. minor</italic> structured a grassland community by selectively parasitizing components of the flora and modifying competitive interactions between plants (Gibson &amp; Watkinson, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>). Empirical studies have shown that the direction and magnitude of effects of parasitic plants may be influenced by environmental contexts like plant community composition, nutrient and moisture availability, and mycorrhizal fungi present (Le, Tennakoon, Metali, Lim, &amp; Bolin, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Matthies &amp; Egli, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>; Pennings &amp; Callaway, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>; Stein et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0077" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Těšitel, Těšitelová, Fisher, Lepš, &amp; Cameron, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0081" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Because of the biotic and abiotic complexity inherent in ecological communities, the present results of a pot and mesocosm study should be corroborated by studies that are conducted under more complex ecological conditions in the field.
</p>
