<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Permanent hyperglycemia in diabetes condition leads to increase expression of inflammatory markers like IL-6 and TNF-
 <italic>α</italic> [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] as observed in this study. These cytokines are produced by immune and nonimmune cells when challenged by various environmental or inflammatory insults. Chronic exposure to proinflammatory mediators stimulates the activation of cytokine signaling proteins which ultimately block the interaction between the activation of insulin signaling pathway, biological function of pancreatic 
 <italic>β</italic>-cells [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], and conduce to insulin resistance [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Studies have also indicated that inflammatory cytokines such as IL-1
 <italic>β</italic>, TNF-
 <italic>α</italic>, and IL-6 which are increased in obesity and diabetes conditions modulate insulin signaling [
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Cytokines such as IL-1
 <italic>β</italic> are upregulated in pancreatic islets of patients with type 2 diabetes and regulate numerous other cytokines and chemokines, consequently increasing its production in 
 <italic>β</italic> cells, engendering a vicious cycle [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>–
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. A potential role of TNF-
 <italic>α</italic> has been reported in the pathogenesis of insulin resistance and type 2 diabetes [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. In the present study, the administration of nicotinamide/streptozotocin resulted in an insulin resistance and an increase in the rate of IL-1
 <italic>β</italic> and TNF-
 <italic>α</italic>, confirming their involvement in the pathogenesis of type II diabetes. Indeed, the plant extract may act as antagonist of TNF-
 <italic>α</italic> and IL-1
 <italic>β</italic> leading to the reduction of insulin resistance and to antihyperglycemia effects as observed in the study. In contrary to the study of Acharya et al. [
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] where a depletion of IL-10 was observed, it was noticed in the present study, a high level of IL-10 in diabetic control group compared to normal control. In fact, IL-10 is a multiple effects cytokine acting in immunoregulation. It has been demonstrated in an in vitro study that IL-6 can cooperate with TGF-
 <italic>β</italic> to induce IL-10 production in Th17 cells [
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. 
 <italic>Bridelia atroviridis</italic> was able to reduce significantly the production of IL-10 but not that of the IL-6 level. IL-6 is produced by different immune and nonimmune cells [
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] suggesting the implication of other factors in its synthesis. The increase in IL-6 and TNF-
 <italic>α</italic> observed in diabetes state also acts as antierythropoietic factors expressed in the present study by the decrease in erythrocytes count, hematocrit, and mean corpuscular of haemoglobin values, which are some conventional signs of anemia [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The proinflammatory cytokine depletion induced by the extract could justify the protective effect from anemia. The leukocytosis observed in the diabetes control is well described as diabetes complications that could result from glycation end products activation, oxidative stress, and both macrovascular and microvascular injuries caused by hyperglycemia [
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. The decrease of leukocyte counts in treated groups indicates the ability of 
 <italic>B. atroviridis</italic> extract to reduce diabetes complications. The decrease in lymphocyte count observed in diabetic control group has already been reported and could be due to apoptosis induced in hyperglycemia situation [
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. The administration of the plant extract for 15 days significantly improved the cells level, indicating an inhibitory effect of 
 <italic>B. atroviridis</italic> on proapoptosis factors or the scavenging properties against free radical agents in lymphocytes.
</p>
