<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Most of the decoctions were effective at inhibiting microbial growth at low concentrations, with liquid dilution MIC values against the bacterial species that they inhibited generally substantially &lt;1000 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL, indicating the noteworthy antimicrobial activity of these preparations. Interestingly, the tested decoctions were generally effective against both Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria, with similar efficacies. The ability of plant extracts to inhibit the growth of both Gram-positive and Gram negative-bacteria has been previously reported for other plants that have a history of medicinal usage for the treatment of microbial diseases. The antiseptic properties of the 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> spp. [
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], 
 <italic>Leptospermum</italic> spp. [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], and 
 <italic>Syzygium</italic> spp. [
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>–
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] have been studied extensively and shown to inhibit the growth of a wide variety of bacteria. However, the equal or greater susceptibility of the Gram-negative bacterial species towards the plant extracts is noteworthy. This is in contrast to other previous studies which have reported a greater susceptibility of Gram-positive bacteria towards solvent extracts for South American [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], African [
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], and Australian plant extracts [
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], although other examples of Australian plant extracts which have a greater effects on Gram-negative bacteria have also been reported [
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The 
 <italic>T. carpentariae</italic> and 
 <italic>V. vexillata</italic> decoctions were particularly good antibacterial agents, with MIC values generally &lt;1000 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL against most of the tested bacterial pathogens.
</p>
