<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Antiproliferative activity against Caco2 (colorectal) and HeLa (cervical) carcinoma cell line cells was also noted for several of the decoctions, although the 
 <italic>T. carpentariae</italic> decoction was the most potent inhibitor of proliferation against both cell lines, with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values generally approximately 885 and 85 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL against Caco2 and HeLa cells, respectively. The antiproliferative activity of the 
 <italic>T. carpentariae</italic> decoction was particularly noteworthy as colorectal cancers cause substantial mortality globally. Notably, anticancer activity has also been reported for related 
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> spp. A recent study reported potent antiproliferative activity for 
 <italic>T. ferdinandiana</italic> extracts, with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of approximately 100 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL against Caco2 cells, which is nearly an order of magnitude stronger than 
 <italic>T. carpentariae</italic> screened in these studies [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Fruit and leaf extracts were tested in the 
 <italic>T. ferdinandiana</italic> study, whereas cambium decoctions were tested in this study, which may account for these broad differences. Interestingly, the 
 <italic>T. ferdinandiana</italic> study determined that the extracts induced their anticancer activity by elevating caspase-3 activity and inducing apoptosis. It is yet to be determined whether the same mechanisms are involved in the antiproliferative activity reported for the 
 <italic>T. carpentariae</italic> decoction tested herein, and future studies are required to address this. Similarly, the 
 <italic>T. ferdinandiana</italic> study also identified a diversity of tannins and flavonoids as contributing to the anticancer activity of those extracts [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Further study is required to determine if similar compounds contribute to the activity of the 
 <italic>T. carpentariae</italic> extracts. The 
 <italic>C. equisetifolia</italic> (450 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL)
 <italic>, E. tetrodonta</italic> (588 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL), and 
 <italic>V. vexillata</italic> (126 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL) decoctions were also good inhibitors of HeLa proliferation but were substantially less effective against Caco2 cells.
</p>
