<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Seed material and soil samples from five 
 <italic>V. thapsus</italic> populations each were sampled in January and April 2014 in the exotic (New Zealand = NZ) and native (Germany) range, respectively. Populations were selected out of a pool of 17 and eight populations (in NZ and Germany, respectively) with a minimum distance of 5 km between populations. Populations from sites with extremely low or high soil pH were excluded in order to sample populations from comparable abiotic/edaphic site conditions. Populations chosen for the study experienced a mean annual temperature from 7.3 to 9.2°C (in Germany) and 8.7 to 10.3°C (in NZ), while having an annual average precipitation ranging from 485 to 708 mm in Germany and 503 to 2,208 mm in New Zealand (Table 
 <xref rid="ece36894-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Seed material was kept dry at 4°C until the beginning of the experiment. Within each population, five topsoil samples were randomly taken in the upper 10 cm of the mineral horizon and subsequently pooled by population to more encompass the heterogeneity of the site (Gundale et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Soil samples were collected during the hemispheres' respective vegetation period, that is, in January 2014 in New Zealand and in May 2014 in Germany. Subsequent to sampling, all soils were transported in cool boxes and immediately stored at −80°C in the laboratories at Lincoln University (NZ) and Martin Luther University Halle (Germany), respectively. Samples from New Zealand were transported to Germany in April 2014 by maintaining the cold chain with dry ice and stored together with German samples at −80°C to stop microbial activity. After 3 (NZ) and 6 months (Germany), respectively, soil was gradually thawed. To reduce effects of differences in nutrient availability and soil structure, we used standard soil (see below) inoculated with soil washes from the different origins. Fresh soil from each of the ten populations was used to transfer soil‐borne fungi and bacteria into a solution following Wagg et al. (
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0080" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). For this purpose, 100 ml of fresh soil was mixed with 500 ml deionized water and shaken by hand for 10 min. Subsequently, the mixture was filtered through a 500‐μm soil sieve. This procedure was run two times for each soil origin to increase the final amount of extracted solutions. The solutions obtained from this process were divided into four equal parts and subjected to treatments of chlortetracycline (80 µg/L), cycloheximide (80 µg/L), a combination of both (80 µg/L), or that served as a control in order to reduce the total amount of bacteria (B), fungi (F), bacteria and fungi (BF), or none, respectively. To differentiate between possible direct physiological effects of the biocides and the true soil biota‐mediated effect, the biocides were additionally applied to plants in sterilized soil without adding soil biota and compared with a control treatment with sterilized water.
</p>
