<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this regard, Mezei et al. [
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] reported that isoflavonoids exhibit antidiabetic and hypolipidemic effects through the PPAR pathway in obese Zucker rats. Shen et al. [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] also found that isoflavonoids viz. formononetin and calycosin isolated from 
 <italic>Astragalus membranaceus</italic> (Fisch.) Bunge exerted significant activation of PPARα and PPARγ. Formononetin showed higher activity, which was comparable to what had been observed for some synthetic dual PPAR-activating compounds, further supporting its antidiabetic potential to be used in regulating lipid metabolism. Furthermore, this study was in line with the study carried out by Qiu et al. [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], who reported that red clover extract containing biochanin A and formononetin ameliorated dyslipidemia in streptozotocin-induced diabetic C57BL/6 mice by activating hepatic PPARα as well as significantly downregulating hepatic APOC3 expression. The therapeutic potential of the active fraction containing isoflavonoids, namely calycosin, formononetin, ononin, and calycosin-7-
 <italic>O</italic>-β-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucoside from the same plant was validated. Continuous administration of the fraction considerably improved the glycemic control, reduced the levels of serum triglyceride, and also alleviated insulin resistance and glucose intolerance in db/db obese mice. These effects were the result of its anti-inflammatory activity [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Wang et al. [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] also attributed the hypoglycemic effect of biochanin A and genistein to stimulation of the PPARα and PPARγ receptors. Additionally, biochanin A was also found to induce an in vitro adipocyte differentiation stimulation through PPARγ as measured by gene activity [
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Genistein and daidzein have also been reported to activate PPARα and PPARγ as well as modulate adipocyte differentiation in vitro [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Cho et al. [
 <xref rid="B55-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] reported that equol, which is a metabolite of daidzein, enhances adipocyte differentiation and PPARγ transcriptional activity. This study was further supported by Cheong et al. [
 <xref rid="B56-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], who reported that equol exerted an in vitro antidiabetic effect in cultured L6 myocytes by promoting glucose uptake, AMPK phosphorylation, and GLUT4 translocation detected by western blotting analyses in L6 myotubes under a condition of insulin absence. In the same study, an in vivo antidiabetic effect of equol in obese-diabetic model ob/ob mice was also investigated. Equol (0.05% in diet) suppressed the rise in serum glucose, cholesterol, triglyceride, and lipid peroxide concentrations and the hepatic triglyceride level compared with those in the control group. Furthermore, equol treatment was found to suppress the rise in fasting blood glucose level and improve the impaired glucose tolerance in ob/ob mice. Moreover, equol treatment was also found to improve the expression of hepatic gluconeogenesis- and lipogenesis-related genes in terms of glucose and lipid metabolism. The hypoglycemic effect of equol was found to be related to the GLUT4 translocation increment in the plasma membrane through AMPK activation. In addition, equol was also found to suppress the fasting blood glucose level and gene expression of hepatic enzymes related to glucose metabolism. These results strongly support equol in its role as an antidiabetic agent.
</p>
