<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The varied effects of different classes of dietary fatty acids on cutaneous carcinogenesis suggest that fatty acid composition is an important determining factor in tumor development. In the previous study [
 <xref rid="B76-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>], the association between dietary n-3 and n-6 fatty acid intake and the risk of SCC was explored. The results taken from a population-based case-control study demonstrated a consistent tendency toward a lower SCC risk with higher omega-3 PUFA consumption. The risk of SCC decreased following the increase of omega-3/omega-6 ratio fatty acid intake. In another case-control study of melanoma patients [
 <xref rid="B77-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>], the higher uptake of fish oil rich in omega-3 fatty acids was defined as more than one portion a week and was associated with a lower risk of melanoma development. This result was based on the participants’ completion of a food frequency questionnaire. A phase 2 open-label clinical study was performed to investigate the response rate and safety of DHA-paclitaxel conjugate in metastatic melanoma patients [
 <xref rid="B78-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>]. Paclitaxel is an anti-melanoma drug with a narrow therapeutic window. DHA-paclitaxel is a covalent conjugate showing a greater therapeutic index than paclitaxel alone [
 <xref rid="B79-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>]. This conjugate had been successfully targeted to the tumor with minimal deposition in normal tissue [
 <xref rid="B80-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>]. Thirty patients were enrolled to receive a DHA-paclitaxel intravenous infusion at 500 mg/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>/week for 5 weeks. The median survival period could be prolonged to 14.8 months. It is indicated that the weekly DHA-paclitaxel is a solidly tolerable single agent for melanoma patients.
</p>
