<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Drought stress is a major constraint to be achieved higher yields in crop plants, especially in the arid and semi-arid regions of the world (Kumar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2020</xref>; Mahdavi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2020</xref>; Naservafaei et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2021</xref>; Rad et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2020</xref>; Reza Yousefi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>). The intensity and frequency of drought are likely to increase as a result of the predicted future climate change (Wassmann et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2009</xref>; Aghajanlou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2021</xref>). The global average of yield decrease due to drought projected to be more than 50% (Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2003</xref>). Moisture deficiency induces various physiological and metabolic responses like stomatal closure limiting decline in growth and photosynthesis rate (Flexas and Medrano 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2002</xref>). In addition, both cell expansion and cell division, two primary processes involved in plant growth, can be influenced by relatively mild drought stress, even before photosynthesis or respiration is affected critical processes, such as germination, emergence, leaf expansion, root and shoot development, dry matter accumulation, floral initiation, pollination, fertilization, seed growth and seed yield (Morgan 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">1984</xref>; Roberts 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">1988</xref>). Among them, leaf expansion is the most sensitive processes (Alves and Setter 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2004</xref>). Indeed, drought decrease cell size and cell number and thus can lead to decreased leaf area, stem growth and plant height (Randall and Sinclair 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">1988</xref>; Simonneau et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">1993</xref>; Tardieu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">2000</xref>). In addition, Baher et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2002</xref>) showed that moderate drought can decrease the length of time from floral initiation (Cruz and O'Toole 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1984</xref>). Colom and Vazzana (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2002</xref>) reported that drought reduced total fresh and dry weight of 
 <italic>Satureja hortensis</italic>. Similar results showed that the number of stem per plant and total dry weight was negatively related to water stress in 
 <italic>Eragrostis curvula</italic>. Drought stress during flower development decrease seed numbers (Wheeler et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2000</xref>; Prasad et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2006</xref>). In addition, drought decreases the seed-filling duration, leading to smaller seed size and seed yield (Frederick et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1991</xref>; De Souza et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1997</xref>; Wardlaw and Willenbrink 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2000</xref>).
</p>
