<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par46">In recent LC analysis of TCM, more and more research are done by using UHPLC and LC–MS, which propose a more advanced option for more efficient, accurate and feasible quality control of herbal drugs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. UHPLC is an advanced LC technique, which could achieve better separation and performance with shorter runtime compared to conventional HPLC, through revolutionary development in LC system especially in the pumps, column and valves, etc. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. At present, UHPLC has been included in both pharmacopoeia for component determination in TCM or TCM prescriptions. For example, EP has included UHPLC method for the determination of the total contents of 7 flavonoids in Typhae pollis. ChP has also included UHPLC method for multiple components determination for several Chinese patent medicines, such as Qishen Yiqi dripping pill, Fufang Danshen dripping pill and Hugan capsule. Moreover, hyphenation of LC especially UHPLC with MS, which can provide the structural information of components, could greatly enhance the efficiency and performance in qualitative and quantitative analysis of herbal drugs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. For example, LC–MS is utilized for the determination of toosendanin in Toosendan Fructus and Meliae Cortex in ChP. Xiao et al. used UHPLC–MS to identify 131 compounds and quantify seven of them in the fruits, leaves and root barks of 
 <italic>Lycium barbarum</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Zeng et al. employed UHPLC-triple quadrupole-MS/MS to determine 20 major constituents including salvianolic acids, tanshinones, flavonoids and triterpenes in different parts of 
 <italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Furthermore, other than active components determination, LC–MS has also been applied in analysis of toxins such as pesticide residue [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>] and mycotoxins [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. In ChP, LC–MS has been used for the test of adonifoline, a toxic alkaloid in Senecionis Scandentis Herba. EP has included UHPLC-MS method in confirmatory test for aristolochic acid I of herbal drugs. As the promotion and popularization of UHPLC and LC–MS, they may be more and more adopted for TCM and herbal drugs in pharmacopoeias.
</p>
