<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this review, we chose examples of shrubs (
 <italic>Hakea</italic>), herbs (
 <italic>Oxalis</italic> and 
 <italic>Phytolacca</italic>) and a succulent plant (
 <italic>Carpobrotus</italic>) to illustrate the varied chemical and pharmaceutical potential of invasive plants. Although poorly studied from the perspective of beneficial attributes, as most invasive species are, the extracts of these species show interesting biological activities, ranging from antioxidant, antimicrobial and antifungal, to neuroprotective and neuritogenic, including antiproliferative and cytotoxic, anticholinesterase, allelopatic and inhibition of viral growth. We thus clearly demonstrate the chemical potential of several kinds of invasive species, potential that should be further explored—invasive plants pose an up to date problem that should be turned into a profitable resource. The use of invasive species as a source of active metabolites could help reduce the actual and future costs of control and management, becoming that added value resource. As such, additional efforts should be directed towards the phytochemical study of these species in their invasive habitat. These studies should be complemented with a large scope analysis of bioactivities of isolated products, such as antimicrobial, antioxidant, anticancer/antiproliferative, and anti-inflammatory activities, among others. This of course is only the beginning—time will tell if there is in fact any use for the isolated bioactive metabolites: the discovery of pharmaceutical lead compounds is long, and substantial toxicity studies will also have to be made. We hope, however, to encourage the development of chemical studies of invasive species in the EU and worldwide, since they are most probably a source of active metabolites, and possibly of new active principle scaffolds. As such, we want to stimulate the scientific community to proceed with the thorough and detailed chemical analysis of invasive species at the same time eradication measures are being maintained. We want to alert the scientific community to the possibility of taking advantage of the metabolites produced by invasive species while eradicating them. We have no intention of valuing these species in order to delay or discourage their eradication, but rather to conduct studies on chemical composition and pharmacological application at the same time as control actions are being maintained.
</p>
