<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The antioxidant potential of flavonoids is associated with the molecular structure, and more precisely, with the location and total number of the –OH groups, the conjugation and resonance effects, the surrounding environment which modifies the thermodynamically favored antioxidant site, and the particular antioxidant mechanism for a compound [
 <xref rid="B79-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. The most commonly used supplemented antioxidants are vitamins C and E. The antioxidant potential of flavonoids is more robust than vitamin C and vitamin E [
 <xref rid="B81-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. It is therefore important to regularly include those fruits and vegetables that are rich in flavonoids in daily food intake. For example, due to enhanced and well-known antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties, flavonoids improve bone health. The utilization of flavonoids in biomaterials has great prospects for bone tissue engineering [
 <xref rid="B82-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. This showed that flavonoids should be supplemented in food of aged people. Quercetin, an antioxidant flavonoid, when present in the blood stream, improves vascular health and reduces risk of cardiovascular disease in its conjugated form [
 <xref rid="B83-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. The quercetin and its derivatives prevents thrombosis or blood clotting and prevents chances of stroke [
 <xref rid="B83-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Hesperidin and hesperetin are two flavonoids present in citrus fruits and mushrooms that showed antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, antimicrobial and anticancer effects [
 <xref rid="B84-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Propolis has been used as a folk medicine for many years and is now used in the pharmaceutical industry. It contains many compounds, including flavonoids which are responsible for their pharmacological properties such as antioxidant, antimicrobial, healing, and anti-proliferative activities [
 <xref rid="B85-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Rutin, a flavonol, showed a number of biological activities that includes anticancer, antioxidant and cytoprotective etc [
 <xref rid="B86-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Sorghum has a high antioxidant activity in vitro [
 <xref rid="B87-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Flavonoids and tannins from sorghums are the best antioxidants [
 <xref rid="B88-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. These results showed that sorghums grains and the products made from these grains should be promoted for food purposes. The sorghum flavonoids have high level of absorption in the small intestine. Although the presence of tannins makes its grains unsuitable for consumption but alkaline cooking reduces the level of tannins by 73% [
 <xref rid="B89-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. It is therefore important to genetically modify the tannin production pathways in sorghum, so that its grains are free from tannins. This crop is also suitable for arid conditions and can grow in harsh environmental conditions. Through this way a flavonoids rich sorghum grains will be available to the human population across the globe. Carotenoids are a class of polyphenols that possess antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B92-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Fisetin (3, 3′, 4′, 7–tetrahydroxy flavone) is a flavonoid which shows antioxidant activity along with anti-inflammatory effects [
 <xref rid="B93-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. The aerial parts like bulbs, leaves, and flowers of 
 <italic>Eleutherine bulbosa</italic> (Mill.) Urb. have high flavonoid content, and showed antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B94-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. 
 <italic>Allium cepa</italic>. L (onion) showed antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B95-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Dill (
 <italic>Anethum graveolens</italic> L.) and parsley (
 <italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic> Mill.) are the medicinal aromatic herbs whose phenolic and flavonoid content made them effective antioxidant agents with the ability to reduce ROS species and prevent ROS mediated diseases such as cancer and cardiovascular ailments. The antioxidant potential of these species may be brought about by different mechanisms and that includes shattering peroxides, and chelating metal ions, which catalyze the oxidation process. This antioxidant activity is related to the phenolic (PC) and flavonoid content (FC); in general, the greater the PC and FC, the greater the antioxidant activity shown by the herbal plant [
 <xref rid="B96-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Utilization of these herbs in daily meals will not only provide aroma and taste but it will improve the nutritional value of food.
</p>
