<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the last 20 years, many studies have attempted to accurately detect the spatial extent of invasive alien plant species (IAPS) to map their spread over time or model their potential invasion area. They have used a variety of environmental, bioclimatic, and/or earth observation data, and applying classification or regression methods. More recently, machine learning algorithms (MLAs) have gained high popularity in ecology and earth science because of their ability to model highly dimensional and non‐linear data with complex interactions and deal with data gaps (Thessen, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0091" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Good performances of MLAs have been obtained in several fields, including remote sensing classifications (Mountrakis, Im, &amp; Ogole, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>) and species distribution modeling (Cutler et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Elith &amp; Leathwick, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). However, for quantifying the impact of IAPS and developing spatially explicit management strategies, accurate information is crucial not only on the current or projected distribution of IAPS but also on their cover across the invaded range (Le Maitre, Gush, &amp; Dzikiti, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Shackleton, Le Maitre, van Wilgen, &amp; Richardson, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0084" ref-type="ref">2015a</xref>; Shackleton, Le Maitre, van Wilgen, &amp; Richardson, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0085" ref-type="ref">2015b</xref>). A few studies attempted to estimate fractional IAPS cover using remotely sensed data either applying spectral unmixing techniques (Frazier &amp; Wang, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Vilà et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0093" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>) or using very high‐resolution remotely sensed data, mostly in combination with machine learning classifiers (Cho, Malahlela, &amp; Ramoelo, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Masocha &amp; Skidmore, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). The use of coarser resolution remote sensing resulted in accurate binary maps of presence and absence of IAPS (Chen, Yi, Qin, &amp; Wang, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Wakie, Evangelista, Jarnevich, &amp; Laituri, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0094" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Only recently, more promising mapping of IAPS at finer fractions of cover was obtained using a combination of medium or high‐resolution satellite data and powerful machine learning classification algorithms (Ng et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0072" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Rembold, Leonardi, Ng, Gadain, &amp; Meroni, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0081" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Such fine‐scaled and accurate quantification of the local fractional cover of IAPS allows understanding their impacts through cover‐impact curve analysis. Furthermore, it allows to identify areas with early stages of invasion where the control of satellite populations maybe halted or at least slow down further spread of IAPS (Vilà et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0093" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>).
</p>
