<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The correct method to reduce technical variability throughout a sampling procedure is essential to stop cell metabolism and to avoid leaking of metabolites during the various preparation steps before the actual metabolite extraction. Therefore, three biological replicates from each of the six fresh parts were immediately frozen on dry ice. In the laboratory, the frozen three biological replicates from each of the three fresh part samples were homogenized with a mortar and pestle in liquid nitrogen, after which the plant material (ca. 10 g) was directly soaked in 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hexane as a solvent in Amber storage bottles, 60 ml screw-top vials with silicone/PTFE septum lids (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sigmaaldrich.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.sigmaaldrich.com</ext-link>) were used to reduce loss of volatiles to the headspace then incubated with shaking at 37 °C and 200 rpm for 72 h. Afterward, the solvent was transferred using a glass pipette to a 10-ml glass centrifuge tube with screw-top vials with silicone/PTFE septum lids and centrifuged at 5,000 rpm for 10 min at 4 °C to remove plant debris. The supernatant was pipetted into glass vials with a screw cap, and oil was concentrated until remaining 1.5 ml of concentrated oils under a stream of nitrogen gas in a nitrogen evaporator (Organomation) with a water bath at room temperature (Toption-China-WD-12). The concentrated oils transferred to a fresh crimp vial amber glass, 1.5 ml screw-top vials with silicone/PTFE septum lids were used to reduce a loss of volatiles to the headspace. For absolute oil recovery, the remaining film crude oil in the internal surface of concentrated glass vials was dissolved in the minimum volume of 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hexane, thoroughly mixed and transferred to the same fresh crimp vial amber glass, 1.5 ml. And the crimp vial was placed on the auto-sampler of the gas chromatography-mass spectrometer (GC-MS) system for GC-MS analysis, or each tube was covered with parafilm after closed with screw-top vials with silicone/PTFE septum lids and stored at −20 °C until GC-MS analysis.
 <xref rid="dsy028-B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">6</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
