<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In a similar way to what is reported in the nutrient digestibility section, the most frequently investigated insect species in fish and shellfish growth trials have been found to be TM and HI (
 <xref rid="animals-09-00170-t004" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 4</xref>). As far as the dietary utilization of TM meal is concerned, some of the performed nutritional trials were carried out on juvenile fish with initial body weights ranging from 3 to 20 g, and the tested TM was a full-fat meal with a CP content ranging from 52 to 56% on a DM basis [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. In juvenile rockfish (
 <italic class="italic">Sebastes schlegeli</italic>) fed experimental diets containing TM levels up to 32%, the fish weight gain (WG) and specific growth rate (SGR) increased with increasing TM dietary inclusions up to 16%, while they then tended to decrease for higher levels in comparison with those fed FM-based diet [
 <xref rid="B41-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. In another trial, performed on mandarin fish (
 <italic class="italic">Siniperca scherzeri</italic>) juveniles fed full-fat TM at inclusion levels up to 30%, the results revealed an increase in fish growth rates and in the efficiency of nutrient utilization for up to 20% of TM inclusion, while a decline was observed when the dietary TM level increased from 20 to 30% compared to those fed the FM-based diet [
 <xref rid="B40-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. Similar conclusions were found by Gasco et al. [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>] for European seabass (
 <italic class="italic">Dicentrarchus labrax</italic>) juveniles fed a diet with 25 and 50% TM inclusion levels. In the same study, the final body weight, WG, SGR, and feeding rate were comparable in the 25% TM group, with respect to the control FM based diet, while these parameters worsened for the highest inclusion level (50%) [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. The TM meal utilization in shellfish, particularly in Pacific white shrimp (
 <italic class="italic">Litopenaeus vannamei</italic>) diets, was also investigated by Panini et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], who found that WG, SGR, feed intake (FI), feed conversion ratio (FCR), survival, and protein retention were not affected when FM was partially or totally replaced in diets containing up to 305 g/kg of a full fat TM meal. However, few studies are available on the use of a defatted TM meal. On juvenile pearl gentian grouper, Song et al. [
 <xref rid="B42-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>] tested a TM meal with a 65% CP content in a feeding trial that lasted 50 days. The fish were fed up to 31.5 % of graded levels of TM meal and the authors found a lower final weight and WG rate in the control fish and in the 6.25% inclusion level groups, while the FCR of the fish fed 12.5 and 18.75% TM diets showed no significant difference compared to the control diet. In order to obtain a maximum WG rate and according to a broken-line model, authors recommended a TM inclusion level of 4.92%, corresponding to a FM substitution of 12.3% [
 <xref rid="B42-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>].
</p>
