<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Previous HPLC research [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>] exhibited presence of salicylate-like components such as salicin and others in 
 <italic class="italic">P. nigra</italic> buds, however salicin is absent in black poplar propolis. In our work, PDA peak of this substance (UVλ
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> = 210, 260–265) was not observed for black poplar bud extracts, which is in full agreement with the above-mentioned author. However, some lower concentration ions in some peaks show similarity to salicin (M/Z for ESI-NEG = 285.1) and other salicylate-like compounds. This result was probably due to low concentration of salicin-like substances in poplar buds, extraction procedure and HPLC division condition [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. It is also noteworthy that salicylic compounds characteristic for aspens (e.g., tremuloidin or tremulacin) were not observed [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Nevertheless, the presence of some higher mass ions (accompanying others peaks) in ESI-NEG mode may suggest their presence in samples, albeit at trace levels (such as in 
 <italic class="italic">P. nigra</italic> buds case). Low concentration of salicylate-like substances in aspen buds is probably related to specific composition [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-23-01262" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] and protective function of bud exudates. In our opinion, these components were a contamination from green tissues of the buds, but not the exudates themselves. Their presence in samples was likely caused by our extraction methods and not their function in exudates.
</p>
