<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In vivo assays are predominantly conducted to evaluate EOs potential to replace antibiotics both in animals and humans. An overview of publications that monitored the effects of EOs in vivo is given in 
 <xref rid="animals-09-00352-t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>. EOs are most commonly associated with hepatotoxicity, nephrotoxicity, changes in the blood vessels, and oxidative stress that occur as a result of acute intoxication. Some EOs have also been associated with reproductive toxicity. It was found that 
 <italic class="italic">Origanum vulgare</italic> EOs at a concentration of 27% 
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic> affected the size of the genitals. The authors suggested a connection with the possible formation of metabolic syndrome and a decrease in testosterone levels. The highest dose also reduced sperm concentration and induced changes in Leydig cells. Thus, male rat fertility decreased as in a dose-depended manner of the EOs [
 <xref rid="B95-animals-09-00352" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>]. These results were positively correlated with Shama A. J., who confirmed the contraceptive effects of 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha arvensis</italic> at a dose of 10 mg/day/mice treated for 20–60 days. It is also known that some other EOs or their components affect the reproductive system. A new study demonstrated the prenatal toxicity of Verbena EOs. Embryo-fetotoxicity retardation was observed as evidenced by the decrease in foetal weight, head cranium, tail length, and higher incidence in the pre-and post-implantation loss. Some foetal skeleton abnormalities such as incomplete ossification of the skull, sternebrae, and metatarsal bones were observed in foetuses of the 2000 and 3000 mg/kg groups. Flavonoids such as apigenin and luteolin have been identified as major toxicants for the reported prenatal developmental toxicity [
 <xref rid="B96-animals-09-00352" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>].
</p>
