<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It was reported that 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> invasion modified the soil microbial communities [
 <xref rid="B35-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], particularly the bacterial communities [
 <xref rid="B21-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], including several specific soil microbial taxa associated with nitrification [
 <xref rid="B37-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. However, the research on 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> invasion on soil microbial in mangrove ecosystems is still limited, and the current research is mainly focused on the diversity and community structure of bacterial communities [
 <xref rid="B20-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In contrast, the response of soil fungal communities and soil microbial ecological functions to the invasion of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> remains unclear. In this study, we selected three different communities (i.e., 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> community (SC), 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic>–mangrove mixed community (TC), and mangrove community (MC)) in the Zhangjiangkou subtropical Mangrove Nature Reserve in China using the research approach of space-for-time [
 <xref rid="B38-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. High-throughput sequencing technology was used for analysis to address the following problems: (i) How does the invasion of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> affect the diversity and structure of soil bacterial and fungal communities? (ii) What functional groups in the soil bacterial and fungal communities have been affected by the invasion of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic>? Assessing the impact of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> invasion on soil bacterial and fungal communities in mangrove ecosystems can provide a microbiological basis for studying the impact of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> invasion on mangrove ecosystems.
</p>
