<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Limited by the weather, tides, and expensive cost of filed work at this saltmarsh, we were not be able to collect spectra daily, weekly, or even bi-weekly. However, with samples collected on those 12 single days (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0067315-t001">table 1</xref>), we can still infer the best periods for classification based on the fact that these vegetation change phonological stage gradually. This study clearly demonstrates that May 5, May 31, and September 20 achieved the best separability to classify or mapping distribution of 
 <italic>Spartina</italic> in the Yangtze River Estuary. The corresponding phonological stages are the germination, early vegetative growth, and flowering stages of 
 <italic>Spartina</italic>, which are about in late spring and early autumn of a year (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0067315-t007">Table 7</xref>). The withering stage of 
 <italic>Spartina</italic> (late autumn and early winter of a year, represented by samples collected on November 25 and December 22) may also be a good period for mapping its spatial extent; however, it may need to take advantage of proper VIs. Yet, this late-autumn or early winter period should never be good timing for 
 <italic>Scirpus</italic> monitoring because aboveground biomass has been washed away by tidal water and its spectra mixes with background water and mud (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0067315.s001">Figure S1</xref>). In an ecology view, 
 <italic>Scirpus</italic> is as important as 
 <italic>Spartina</italic> to be monitored because it is more preferred by waterfowls but has been forced to populate a narrow zone close to the sea due to competitive disadvantage 
 <xref rid="pone.0067315-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. As a result, it is even more difficult to map 
 <italic>Scirpus</italic> by remote sensing as the tidal waters regularly influence its relatively short and sparse canopy. We collected 
 <italic>Scirpus</italic> spectra samples in some depression plots where water remains after the tide and found that its spectral characteristic was much different than that without a water background at its early growing and withering stages, but not its peak growing stage (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0067315-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). Moreover, our analysis has suggested that the peak growing stage is the worst timing for vegetation discrimination. Thus, it is very important to consider timings with minimum tidal water influence for 
 <italic>Scirpus</italic> monitoring. The information provided here would be helpful to collect, process, and classify images by guiding investigators toward suitable periods for dynamically monitoring 
 <italic>Spartina</italic> as well as the other two saltmarsh species. Some of our previous studies that validated the proposed periods are qualified for 
 <italic>Spartina</italic> monitoring in the Yangtze River Estuary 
 <xref rid="pone.0067315-He1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0067315-Ouyang1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. However, as the spectra were collected from roughly 0.5 m square canopy areas, it would be difficult to directly extrapolate these reflectance signatures to real canopy cover reflectance captured by a remote sensor.
</p>
