<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The infectious pandemic COVID-19 has emerged as a massive threat to humankind. The main challenges are to control the spread of the disease, developing immunity as the preventive as well as prophylactic, and discovering therapeutics in a feasible time. Nature has always blessed us with plentiful remedies like herbs and medicinal plants for numerous ailments. Therefore, the virtual screening based on molecular docking was executed to identify potential bioactives from medicinal plants as effective inhibitors of M
 <sup>pro</sup>, S-protein and ACE2. We found many bioactives from the medicinal plants have shown either comparable or better binding affinity with targets of SARS-CoV-2 with desirable pharmacological properties over the standard drugs. Further, we also observed that the selected bioactives have better intestinal and GI absorptions and lower toxicity than the standard drugs used. Therefore, these selected bioactives may further be developed as pharmacological inhibitors against SARS-CoV-2 target proteins involved in viral replication, propagation and transmission. Among them, taraxerol from 
 <italic>Clerodendrum</italic> has shown potential anti-viral activities with desirable pharmacological features (Sharma &amp; Zafar, 
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Verma &amp; Baranwal, 
 <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">1983</xref>). Further, withanolide A from 
 <italic>Withania somnifera</italic> has shown the highest binding affinity with S-protein and ACE-2 receptor. The active constituents of ayurvedic herb 
 <italic>W. somnifera</italic> have shown promising anti-influenza properties by targeting neuraminidase of H1N1 influenza (Cai et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). AYUSH Ministry of Health, India, has further recommended the use of the aqueous extract of this plant as a preventive and prophylactic for treating COVID-19. Withametelin, from the 
 <italic>Datura innoxia</italic> plant, has shown a better binding affinity against M
 <sup>pro</sup>, S-protein and ACE2. However, the pharmacological analysis revealed its toxicity to health. Instead, daturaolone, another compound from 
 <italic>D. innoxia,</italic> have shown lower toxicity and higher HIA with potent anti-viral and anti-inflammatory activities. Overall, the selected medicinal plant bioactives can be further developed and assessed as phytoformulations against SARS-CoV-2 infection.
</p>
