<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17" class="p">In general, biofilm formation is an example of bacterial adaptation to a changing environment, occurring primarily for four reasons: (i) defense; (ii) colonization; (iii) community; and (iv) the default mode of bacterial growth [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118" class="xref">118</xref>]. In particular, biofilm formation is a stage of microbial development and a part of the mechanism of establishment of chronic bacterial infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119" class="xref">119</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121" class="xref">121</xref>]. More than 40 years have already passed from the first mention of tangled fibers of polysaccharides that extend from the cell surface and form “glycocalyx” around the individual cells or a colony of bacteria. The glycocalyx-mediated adhesion was described as a major determinant in the initiation and progression of the wide spectrum of bacterial diseases, from dental caries to pneumonia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122" class="xref">122</xref>]. The new description defines biofilms as a microbial-derived sessile community of cells irreversibly attached to a substratum, interface or to each other, embedded in a matrix of extracellular polymeric substances (EPS) secreted by them and exhibit an altered phenotype of growth and gene transcription [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119" class="xref">119</xref>]. Biofilms are complex structures, highly resistant to environmental and therapeutic pressure. The primary polymeric compound of extracellular polymeric substance is alginate, a non-sulfated mucopolysaccharide described as a major biofilm component for multiple bacterial species, including those from the order Spirochaetales, 
 <italic class="italic">Leptospira biflexa</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Treponema denticola</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123" class="xref">123</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124" class="xref">124</xref>] and 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" class="xref">96</xref>]. Even though the chemical structure of mature biofilms is diverse and includes phospholipids, polysaccharides, proteins, glycoproteins, embedded calcium and extracellular DNA (eDNA), alginine, calcium and eDNA are considered as a typical markers of biofilms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" class="xref">96</xref>]. The compilation of genes, conducted by K. Jefferson, that are required for biofilm formation (the cause genes) and those differentially expressed in an established biofilms (the effect genes) in multiple bacterial species include numerous genes involved in adhesion, quorum sensing, cell wall synthesis, metabolism, stress response division and motility [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118" class="xref">118</xref>]. Biofilms might be formed by a single bacteria species or represent a multi-species community attached to biotic or abiotic surfaces [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121" class="xref">121</xref>]. The physical characteristic of surfaces influence bacterial attachment only to a minor extent, showing that smooth surfaces are colonized with the same success as rough ones [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125" class="xref">125</xref>]. Once attached to the surface bacteria go through a series of changes that are required for adaptation to the life on surface. Extensive production of EPS is a common adaptation step; it protects the biofilms and might result in biocide resistance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126" class="xref">126</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127" class="xref">127</xref>]. The changes of environmental conditions triggers the transition of free-living bacteria to life on a surface that starts with the early stages that includes cell-surface and cell-cell interactions, followed by the development of mature biofilms and the return to a planktonic mode of growth. Those environmental signals vary and might differ among bacterial species, but in general what might influence the biofilms formation is the media composition/nutrition, temperature, pH, osmolarity, iron or oxygen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121" class="xref">121</xref>]. Surface-attached bacteria are often associated with an increased synthesis of EPS and the development of antibiotic resistance, the feature that makes mature biofilms a serious clinical problem. It is known that EPS prevents the access of antibiotics to bacterial cells in the biofilm using different mechanisms that include physical or chemical diffusion barriers to antibiotic penetration, slow growth of the biofilms, activation of the stress response or appearance of a biofilm-specific phenotype [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128" class="xref">128</xref>].
</p>
