<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Caesalpinia sappan</italic> (
 <italic>C. sappan</italic>) belongs to the family of 
 <italic>Caesalpiniaceae</italic> and it is usually known as Brazil or Sappan wood [
 <xref rid="B219-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">219</xref>]. It is mostly found in Southeast Asian regions and is traditionally used for the treatment of various diseases such as tuberculosis, diarrhea, dysentery, skin infections, anemia, etc. [
 <xref rid="B219-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">219</xref>,
 <xref rid="B240-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">240</xref>]. 
 <italic>C. sappan</italic> is effectively considered as an antiviral, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, antibacterial, antifungal, and anti-complementary [
 <xref rid="B219-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">219</xref>,
 <xref rid="B240-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">240</xref>,
 <xref rid="B241-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">241</xref>]. Its bioactive constituents include xanthone, coumarin, chalcones, flavones, homoisoflavonoids, and brazilin [
 <xref rid="B240-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">240</xref>]. Tewtrakul et al., 2015, extracted nine compounds from the roots of 
 <italic>C. sappan</italic>. The results showed that, out of those nine, sappanchalcone (IC
 <sub>50</sub> 2.3 µM) and protosappanin A (IC
 <sub>50</sub> 12.6 µM) presented the strongest effect against HIV-1 IN [
 <xref rid="B240-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">240</xref>]. On the other hand, Liu et al., 2009 also investigated the role of this medicinal plant against influenza virus. The in vitro study showed that 3-deoxysappanchalcone and sappanchalcone component isolated from 
 <italic>C. sappan</italic> exhibited the highest activity against influenza virus (H3N2), with IC
 <sub>50</sub> 1.06 and 2.06 μg/mL, respectively [
 <xref rid="B239-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">239</xref>]. Therefore, sappanchalcone from 
 <italic>C. sappan</italic> should also be considered for further examination against SARS-CoV-2.
</p>
