<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4-metabolites-07-00065" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec4dot1-metabolites-07-00065" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1. Plant Material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Initial plant material used in this work consisted of 
   <span class="italic">Lavandula latifolia</span> Med (spike lavender) mature seeds, provided by Intersemillas SA (Valencia, Spain) and in vitro grown transgenic HMGR5 plants overexpressing the HMG1 cDNA, encoding the catalytic domain of 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl CoA reductase (HMGR1S) previously obtained in our group [
   <a rid="B37-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-metabolites-07-00065">37</a>]. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seeds were sterilized and germinated in vitro as previously described [
   <a rid="B59-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-metabolites-07-00065">59</a>]. After germination, seedlings were first transferred to pot-trays with a mixture of peat moss and perlite (7:3) and after 30 days, plantlets were transferred to pots (15 cm) and kept in the greenhouse for 4 months. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The in vitro HMGR5 and no transgenic wild type (WT) control plants were acclimatized to ex vitro conditions and planted in pots (15 cm) with peat moss and perlite (1:1) as substrate and maintained in a culture chamber for 2 months until used.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4dot2-metabolites-07-00065" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2. 
   <span class="sup">13</span>CO
   <sub>2</sub> Labelling Experiments
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Labelling experiments were performed with controls and transgenic HMGR5 plants. For 
   <span class="sup">13</span>CO
   <sub>2</sub> feeding, three or four potted plants were simultaneously placed in a closed gas incubation chamber (Biobox; GWS, Berlin, Germany) at 25 °C and illuminated with white light (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="metabolites-07-00065-f010" href="#metabolites-07-00065-f010">Figure 10</a>). Prior to the labelling period (pulse phase), the chamber was flushed with synthetic air containing oxygen and nitrogen until CO
   <sub>2</sub> was fully removed. The plants were then fed with synthetic air containing 700 ppm of 
   <span class="sup">13</span>CO
   <sub>2</sub>. During this pulse period, the concentration of 
   <span class="sup">13</span>CO
   <sub>2</sub> and 
   <span class="sup">12</span>CO
   <sub>2</sub> was typically detected at a ratio of 9:1. Subsequently, the plants were transferred to the laboratory.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In preliminary experiments, performed with 5-month-old WT plants, pulse and chase periods adequate to produce detectable 
   <span class="sup">13</span>C enrichments were determined. To this end, pots were feed for six different pulse periods beginning with 1.0 h up to 8.8 h. Chase periods varied from 0 to 264 h. The time settings for each experiment are listed in 
   <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-metabolites-07-00065" href="#app1-metabolites-07-00065">Table S1</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Labelling experiments with transgenic HMGR5 plants and their respective controls were performed with 5 h pulse period and chase periods for 96, 168, 240 and 264 h.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Subsequently, leaf essential oils were extracted and the samples were analysed to detect the labelling pattern of camphor and cineole using NMR and/or GC/MS techniques, as described below. Samples indicated with the same lower-case letter belonged to the same plant. </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4dot3-metabolites-07-00065" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3. Essential Oil Extraction from Labelled Material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Depending on the analytical method (GC/MS or 
   <span class="sup">13</span>C NMR), two different extraction protocols were employed. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Samples for GC/MS analysis were extracted as follows: leaf samples (100–200 mg) were introduced into 10 mL glass tubes and 2 mL of chloroform-d (CDCl
   <sub>3</sub>) was added. After a gentle shake, the tubes were maintained for 15 min at room temperature; subsequently, a spatula of anhydrous sodium sulfate was added and tubes were left for 1 h at room temperature. Finally, 1000 μL of chloroform-extract were placed into a 1.5 mL autosampler vial suitable for GC/MS measurements.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For 
   <span class="sup">13</span>C NMR analyses, the plant material (600–1000 mg) was split into 3 different 10 mL glass tubes. Then, 2 mL of chloroform-d was added to the first tube, shacked gently and left at room temperature for 15 min. The chloroform was then transferred into the second tube and the whole process repeated. This procedure was also performed for the third tube. After drying with magnesium sulphate, finally 600 μL of the chloroform extract were placed in a NMR tube for 
   <span class="sup">1</span>H and 
   <span class="sup">13</span>C analyses.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4dot4-metabolites-07-00065" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.4. GC/MS Measurements</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Gas Chromatograph (GC-17A and GC-2010), mass spectrometer (QP-5000 and GCMS-QP 2010 Plus), auto injector (AOC-20i) and software (Class 5000 and GCMS solution) used for these measurements were acquired from Shimadzu (Duisburg, Germany). The column used was a silica capillary column Equity TM-5 (30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm film thickness) from Supelco Inc. (Bellefonte, PA, USA).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The measurements were performed as follows: the injector and interface temperature were 230 °C and 250 °C respectively. The temperature settings of the oven were: 70 °C for 2 min, then 70–90 °C with 2 °C/min, then 90–130 °C with 5 °C/min and finally 250 °C for 1 min. The pressure program started at 76.1 kPa with a linear velocity of 40.0 cm/s. The flow control was set to linear velocity. The total flow was 16.1 mL/min while the column flow stayed at 1.19 mL/min. The split ratio was 1:10. The detector volts were approx. 0.8 keV (according to the last tuning result of the MS). The solvent cut was adjusted at 4 min and the sampling rate at 0.15 s. The micro scan width was fixed at 0.1 u.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each sample was analyzed three times in SIM (single ion monitoring) mode. The relative intensities of the standards (camphor and 1,8-cineole) and the samples obtained from GC/MS analysis (peak integration) were processed according to previous publications [
   <a rid="B60-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-metabolites-07-00065">60</a>,
   <a rid="B61-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-metabolites-07-00065">61</a>,
   <a rid="B62-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-metabolites-07-00065">62</a>,
   <a rid="B63-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63-metabolites-07-00065">63</a>]. This evaluation results in the molar excess of carbon isotopologues of the main components camphor and 1,8-cineole only due to the enrichments from the 
   <span class="sup">13</span>C precursor.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC/MS analysis of the essential oil fraction was performed: (i) to determine the composition of all samples; and (ii) to determine the 
   <span class="sup">13</span>C enrichment and isotopologue profiles of the main components in each sample. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4dot5-metabolites-07-00065" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.5. NMR Measurements</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">NMR analyses were performed as follows: For 
   <span class="sup">1</span>H spectra, an Avance I 500 (UltraShield 500 MHz, SEI 500 S2 probe head (5 mm, inverse with Z-gradient), Autosampler B-ACS 60) from Bruker Instruments (Karlsruhe, Germany) was used. The software installed was TopSpin 2.1 (Bruker Instruments, Karlsruhe, Germany). For 
   <span class="sup">13</span>C spectra, either an Avance I 500 (Cryomagnet BZH 500 MHz, Autosampler B-ACS 60) or an Advance III 500 system with an UltraShield PLUS 500 MHz magnet and a cryo probe head (5 mm CPQNP, 
   <span class="sup">1</span>H/
   <span class="sup">13</span>C/
   <span class="sup">31</span>P/
   <span class="sup">19</span>F/
   <span class="sup">29</span>Si (Z-gradient), Autosampler B-ACS 120) both from Bruker Instruments (Karlsruhe, Germany) were used. The software installed was TopSpin 3.0, respectively (Bruker Instruments, Karlsruhe, Germany). The measurements were performed at magnetic fields of 11.75 Tesla. The resonance frequencies of 
   <span class="sup">1</span>H and 
   <span class="sup">13</span>C were 500.13 MHz and 125.77 MHz, respectively, and the temperature was 300 K. Data analysis was performed with the MestReNova Software (Mestrelab Research, Santiago de Compostela, Spain), TOPSPIN or XWIN NMR. The one-dimensional 
   <span class="sup">1</span>H and 
   <span class="sup">13</span>C NMR spectra, and the two-dimensional COSY (magnitude mode or phase-sensitive), HSQC, HSQC-DEPTedited, HSQC-TOCSY, NOESY (with 1 s mixing), TOCSY (with 60 ms mixing) and HMBC spectra were measured with standard Bruker parameter sets.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
