<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0035">Dye produced during the hair dyeing procedure, is formed through chemical reaction in hair shafts. Under oxidation condition, a precursor agent such as PPD reacts with a coupler agent such as resorcinol, to produce a colored polymerized compound with high molecular weight [
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Conversely, in the process of PPD oxidation Bandrowski’s base (BB) well known as mutagenic compounds inducing allergic reaction, also could be formed by autooxidation in the presence of air, or by promoting the oxidation reaction with oxidants including hydrogen peroxide [
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Although, skin functions as the first line of defense system against toxic chemicals and foreign substances, PPD exposed through skin epidermal layer can be absorbed by percutaneous absorption during hair dyeing or a tattooing process, resulting in allergic contact dermatitis [
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>]. Additionally, many previous studies reported that PPD possessed mutagenic, cytotoxic and carcinogenic effects on human organs including liver, kidney and bladder [
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>]. Despite the cytotoxic effect of PPD, hair dye products are sold directly to untrained customers for self-application over the counter. Some case studies reported that PPD was used as a means of ideal suicidal poison because of easy availability in households, and low cost in India and Sudan [
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. 
 <italic>Rhus semialata</italic> M., synonym of 
 <italic>Rhus chinesis</italic> Mill, is widely distributed in China, Korea and India. Galls produced on the plant are known treatment for cough, diarrhea, dysentery and uterine bleeding. However, other parts of the plant including stems, leaves, fruits, and roots are also used as traditional medicines as well as a functional ingredient in foods [
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Many previous studies reported that the extract of 
 <italic>Rhus semialata</italic> M. possesses various pharmacological effects such as anti-bacterial, anti-viral, anti-oxidant and anti-inflammation activities [
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>]. In the present study, we evaluated the protective effect of 
 <italic>Rhus semialata</italic> M. on PPD induced cytotoxicity and investigated the mechanism of action of 
 <italic>Rhus semialata</italic> M. in human keratinocytes, major target cells exposed to PPD in the process of hair dyeing or tattooing.
</p>
