<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The significance of antioxidant compounds from GLs in minimizing the harmful effects of free radicals has been shown by numerous studies. Essential oils extracted from GLs were found to function as moderate antioxidants with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of ~460.37 ± 1.33 μg/mL, as demonstrated by a DPPH assay [
 <xref rid="B27-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The reduction of linoleic acid oxidation and the scavenging effect on peroxyl radicals were revealed by other such analyses on GL extract. The study also showed that there was a linear association between the antioxidant’s potency, the ability to scavenge free radicals, and the phenolic content of GL extract [
 <xref rid="B8-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The protective effect of GL polysaccharide was studied in zebrafish. The authors revealed that GL polysaccharides exerted a protective effect against oxidative stress induced by hydrogen peroxide by inhibiting the formation of reactive oxygen species (ROS), reducing lipid peroxidation and cell death [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In another study, it was revealed that GL extracts at 4000 ppm or higher can prevent the oxidation of fresh pork sausages, suggesting its application as a functional food ingredient [
 <xref rid="B63-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. To release insoluble bound polyphenol components, GLs were co-fermented with yeast and bacterial strains and it was observed that fermentation enhanced the antioxidant ability of soluble guava leaf polyphenols [
 <xref rid="B43-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. In an advanced study, silver nanoparticles were synthesized by utilizing crude polysaccharides of GLs, and showed high DPPH radical- and ABTS radical cation-scavenging activity [
 <xref rid="B64-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. It is evident from the findings that GL extracts can be a useful antioxidant material in the food preservation and cosmetic industries.
</p>
