<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Due to the hydrophilic properties of chia seeds, they are used as substitutes for eggs and fat [
 <xref rid="B43-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>]. Chia seeds can absorb water in amounts as much as 12-fold greater than their own mass [
 <xref rid="B68-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>]. They provide food with characteristic consistency. At present, chia seeds are used whole, ground and in the form of gel and oil. Gel of chia seeds may be used as a substitute of oil or eggs in baked products. Such application facilitates reduced calorie and fat contents of products. Furthermore, in the case of baked goods, the final product has a greater content of omega-3 acids, which are major biological compounds of great importance for human health. Borneo et al. [
 <xref rid="B69-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>] showed that chia seed gel may replace as much as 25% oil or eggs in cakes. They confirmed that the level of this substitution has an advantageous effect on sensory attributes of the product, such as colour, taste, texture and overall acceptance. However, in the case of replacement of 50–75% oil in dough, an adverse change was observed in density and overall quality of the baked product [
 <xref rid="B69-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>]. As shown by Oliveira et al. [
 <xref rid="B70-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>], flour from chia seeds may also be used to produce pasta as a substitute of wheat flour. In that experiment, they found that pasta prepared with a share of chia flour had a greater nutritive value than the control pasta. It had statistically significantly greater contents of protein, minerals and dietary fibre. It was recorded that pasta with 7.5% wheat flour replaced with chia flour exhibited very good technological properties and received the highest acceptance index in terms of taste [
 <xref rid="B70-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. Menga et al. [
 <xref rid="B42-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>] proposed adding chia seeds and mucilage to rice flour for gluten-free fresh pasta. They demonstrated that concentration of 10% of mucilage or chia seeds resulted in nutritious and healthy gluten free pasta with cooking characteristics equivalent to commercial product as confirmed by its firmness.
</p>
