<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">High acceptance of breads with the addition of chia flour or chia seeds was reported in a study by Coelho and Salas-Mellado [
 <xref rid="B71-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>]. They showed that the introduction of chia flour to breads at 7.8 g/100 g and in the second variant chia seeds at 11.0 g/100 g provided a final product exhibiting a more advantageous ratio of polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA) to saturated fatty acids (SAT) than that of the control bread. For traditional bread, the PUFA:SAT ratio was 1.01, while for breads with an addition of chia flour or chia seeds it was 3.1 and 3.9, respectively [
 <xref rid="B71-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>]. Fernandes and Salas-Mellado [
 <xref rid="B72-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>] examined chia mucilage incorporation on the technological quality of breads and pound cakes with a reduced fat content, and showed it to be an effective fat substitute, preserving quality attributes of food products. A positive effect of chia flour addition on the nutritive value and sensory attributes of chips was observed by Coorey et al. [
 <xref rid="B73-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>]. They stated that a 5% substitution of potato flour and rice flour with chia flour is the most advantageous for appearance, colour, aroma, texture, taste and overall acceptability of the final product. In turn, Campos et al. [
 <xref rid="B74-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>] showed that gruel made from chia seeds may be used as a substitute of emulsifiers and stabilisers in the production of ice-cream. However, an adverse change observed in that case of a change of ice-cream colour resulting from the dark colour of chia gel [
 <xref rid="B74-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>]. In turn, Pintado et al. [
 <xref rid="B75-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>] investigated potential substitution of a part or all added fat in frankfurters with chia flour or with an oil in water emulsion prepared by mixing chia flours with water and oil olive. Introduction of chia to frankfurters provided a product enriched with dietary fibre, minerals (potassium, magnesium, calcium, and manganese) as well as mono- and polyunsaturated fatty acids. At the same time, the final product had calorie content reduced by approximately 26% and sensorily acceptable [
 <xref rid="B75-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>]. Ding et al. [
 <xref rid="B43-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>] examined processing properties of chia seed on restructured ham-like products and found that concentration of 1.0% decreased lipid and protein oxidation and improved not only physicochemical and sensorial properties but also added the nutritional value on low fat meat products. The advantageous effect of chia seeds on nutritive value was also shown indirectly when investigating the composition of eggs laid by hens fed a feed with chia seeds. Contents of omega-3 acids (mainly alfa-linoleic acid) increased in their eggs. Addition of chia seeds also caused a reduction of the ratio of omega-6 to omega-3 acid contents as well as the ratio of monounsaturated to polyunsaturated fatty acids [
 <xref rid="B76-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>]. 
</p>
