<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Furthermore, 
 <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr">Rashed et al. (2014)</xref>, evaluated the antioxidant capacity of extracts from the aerial parts of 
 <italic>T. bellerica</italic> (Gaertn.) Roxb. on carbon tetrachloride-intoxicated mice. Preliminary antioxidant assays by the DPPH and ABTS tests showed that ethanolic extracts had a higher antioxidant activity with values of 2883.38 and 2414.81 TEAC/mg against the radicals, respectively. Moreover, 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies showed that 
 <italic>T. bellerica</italic> (Gaertn.) Roxb. extracts at a concentration of 300 mg/kg ameliorated in a dose-dependent manner, the production of 4-hydroxynonenal and 3-nitrotyrosine (
 <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr">Rashed et al., 2014</xref>). 
 <italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> Retz. plant extracts obtained by ultrasonic-assisted extraction optimized using response surface methodology were reported by 
 <xref rid="B180" ref-type="bibr">Sheng et al. (2018)</xref>. The authors report the optimal factors for phenolic extraction of 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> Retz. were 68% ethanol concentration, the ultrasonic intensity of 3.6 W/cm
 <sup>2</sup>, the particle size of 0.18 mm, extraction temperature and time of 20 min for 2 times at 70°C, and the liquid-solid ratio of 23 mg/mL. Optimized results yield higher DPPH and ABTS antioxidant capacity in a dose-dependent manner, ultrasound-assisted extracts showed higher antioxidant activity than ascorbic acid by the FRAP method at 0.010-0.013 mg/mL, and by the DPPH method at concentrations from 0.003–0.011 mg/mL. An HPLC-DAD-ESI-MS analysis showed the presence of (114) shikimic acid; (3) gallic acid; (115) 5-O-galloylshikimic acid; (5) corilagin; (116) 3,4,8,9,10-pentahydroxydibenzo (b,d) pyran-6-one; and (4) ellagic acid, could be responsible for the antioxidant properties of 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> Retz. fruit extracts (
 <xref rid="B180" ref-type="bibr">Sheng et al., 2018</xref>). A summary of the antioxidant potential of different 
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> species is shown in 
 <xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">
  <bold>Table 6</bold>
 </xref>. The chemical structures of some bioactive compounds from 
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> species with antioxidant potential is shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">
  <bold>Figure 4(iv)</bold>
 </xref>.
</p>
