<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Aside from the quassinoids, other compounds of 
 <italic class="italic">Ailanthus</italic> may have allelopathic activity. The volatile oil and phenolic constituents of leaves and the phytotoxic properties of extracts were studied by Albouchi et al. [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. In total, 139 substances were identified in leaves’ essential oils, which were mainly non-terpenic compounds (tetradecanol, heneicosane, tricosane, and docosane) and sesquiterpene hydrocarbons (α-curcumene and α-gurjunene). The composition of the essential oils depended on the part of the plant, the stage of its development and the geographical area where it was collected. Methanol extracts inhibited the germination and growth of the roots of 
 <italic class="italic">Daucus carota</italic> L. The phytotoxic effect correlated better with extracts with a higher content of phenols. The reason for that can be such putative allelochemicals as gallic acid, chlorogenic acid, glucosylated quercetin, and glucosylated luteolin [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. In another study, the composition of essential oils from various organs of 
 <italic class="italic">A. altissima</italic>—roots, stems, leaves, flowers, and samaras was evaluated [
 <xref rid="B171-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">171</xref>]. The essential oils’ content varied from 0.012 (roots) to 0.083% (stems). There were identified 69 compounds, the content of which strongly depended on the plant organ. Although in this and previous work, the assessment was carried out on 
 <italic class="italic">Ailanthus</italic> plants from Tunisia, only 17 compounds were the same in both studies and only four in essential oils’ leaves. The reason may be genetic differences, environmental factors, and various metabolic pathways [
 <xref rid="B171-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">171</xref>]. Essential oils from various organs of 
 <italic class="italic">A. altissima</italic> inhibited the germination and growth of 
 <italic class="italic">Lactuca sativa</italic>. The observed phytotoxic effect can be associated with caryophyllene oxide, b-caryophyllene, germacrene D, and hexahydrofarnesyl acetone (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01636-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>), which prevailed in essential oils from flowers and leaves, stems, roots and fruits, respectively [
 <xref rid="B171-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">171</xref>].
</p>
