<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lavender oil is characterized by a variety of pharmacological activities ranging from anti-inflammatory to antioxidant, antibacterial, antifungal, antiseptic, antiviral, antidepressive, sedative, immune-stimulating, and even anticancer effects [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-02458" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-02458" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. It has a strong bactericidal effect on many strains of bacteria (e.g., 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus, Enterococcus faecalis</italic>), accompanied by a weak fungicidal activity (e.g., 
 <italic>Botrytis cinereal</italic>, 
 <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>). Formulations containing lavender oil are used to treat inflammation in the mouth and throat and upper respiratory tract infections. In dermatology, the essential oil preparations help to relieve skin inflammation, psoriasis, or eczema [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-02458" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Moreover, the oil is a component of ointments used to treat wounds and burns. According to the literature, pure lavender oil was used to treat wounds after burns during World War I [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-02458" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Due to its antimicrobial properties, it causes the purulent states of the skin to subside and it improves the healing rate of the wounds. It should be noted, however, that the direct contact of essential oils with the skin can lead to irritation and allergic reactions [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-02458" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In aromatherapy, lavender oil acts as a remedy with a potential sedative, sleeping, anxiolytic, and mood-enhancing effect [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-02458" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In the cosmetic industry, it is used to produce bath salts, shampoos, skin tonic, cosmetic face masks, and for aromatizing naturally manufactured creams, balsam, or toilet waters [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-02458" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The essential oil may also be used to preserve cosmetic products as an effective alternative for synthetic preservatives such as DMDM hydantoin, which acts as formaldehyde releaser [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-02458" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
</p>
