<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Basically, the biological activities of plant samples are depended on their chemical composition. Therefore, the detection and identification of phytocompounds are required in the research on plant bioactivity. In the present study, the total phenolic (TPC) and flavonoid (TFC) contents were firstly screened. Among fractional extracts, ethyl acetate contains the highest TPC and TFC. The most abundant compounds identified in the extract belong to flavonoids and flavonoid glycosides. Theoretically, such compounds express a higher affinity to water fraction or butanol fraction. Therefore, previous studies tended to select the polar solvents and extraction protocols such as hexane, ethyl acetate, butanol, 50% ethanol, and water, which were more effective in flavonoid glycoside extraction, and their solubility in ethyl acetate was rather law [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In fact, the identification and characterization of phytocompound composition of each plant sample are influenced by various factors such as plant species and extraction methods. The TPC and TFC in ethyl acetate extract were found to be equal or higher than aqueous and butanol extracts in case of several species like 
 <italic>Euphorbia splendida</italic> [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] or 
 <italic>Ziziphus jujube</italic> [
 <xref rid="B38-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. On the other hand, this study used the Soxhlet extraction with organic solvents (methanol and ethyl acetate 2:8, 
 <italic>v/v</italic>), which could obtain flavonoid glycoside components. This suggests that the mentioned extraction protocol may be appropriate to extract flavonoid glycosides from 
 <italic>A. virginicus</italic> sample. However, further extraction and isolation methods should be applied to optimize the purification of potential compounds from this species. 
</p>
