<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The detected flavonoids in the 
 <italic>A. virginicus</italic>’s total crude and ethyl acetate extracts may be also the primary agents for the cytotoxic activities against K562 and Meg-01 cell lines. According to the previous studies including laboratory bioassays, epidemiological investigations, and clinical trials, flavonoids have shown important chemotherapy roles for cancer. The anticancer property of flavonoids has been comprehensively explained through various biological pathways such as antioxidants, enzymatic activities, genetic factors, and cell-related mechanisms, or synergic effects of these mentioned factors [
 <xref rid="B49-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Remarkably, the antioxidant activity of flavonoids is closely associated with anticancer regulation [
 <xref rid="B50-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Meanwhile, phytoflavonoids are not harmful to normal myeloid, peripheral blood, and epithelial cell lines [
 <xref rid="B51-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. In our research, we also find a strong correlation between total phenolics and flavonoids, antioxidant and cytotoxic capacities in the ethyl acetate extract (
 <xref rid="plants-10-00069-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). On the other hand, the hexane extract’s cytotoxic activity against Meg-01 cell line may be due to the presence of phytol and γ-sitosterol or the combined influence of the found compounds in this extract (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00069-f003">Figure 3</xref> and 
 <xref rid="plants-10-00069-t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Particularly, phytol is a popular anticancer agent, which has been mentioned in numerous recent studies. The inhibition of this compound on different types of cancer cells and relevant modes of action have been globally published [
 <xref rid="B52-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Whilst γ-sitosterol has been also known to be an antitumor agent, its specific mechanism has been reported in other studies [
 <xref rid="B58-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].
</p>
