<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>FTIR spectrum is an effective tool for differentiating, classifying and discriminating closely related plants and other organisms (Maitera and Chukkol 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). It is perhaps the most powerful tool for identifying the types of chemical bonds (functional groups) present in compounds (Murugesh and Vino 
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). FTIR spectroscopic study revealed the presence of various functional groups in SMF1. The strong peak at 2924.18 cm
 <sup>−1</sup> is ascribed to the C–H stretching of alkane compounds which are present in rare medicinal plants (Starlin et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). A strong absorption peak at 1033.88 cm
 <sup>−1</sup> assigned to C–O of phenols is seen on the finger print region of the spectra, and phenols are known to modulate inflammation as they contain aromatic and alcohol groups. According to Owolabi et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), phenols modulate inflammation by reducing the synthesis of reactive oxygen and nitrogen species, hindering the activity of cyclooxygenase (COX) and inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS), suppressing inflammatory cytokines and chemokines synthesis and controlling NF-κβ signalling. The presence of phenols was confirmed in the phytochemical analysis of MESM and its partitions. Other medium and weak peaks observed from the spectra indicate the presence of amines, carboxylic acid, esters, aldehydes and alkenes. Carboxylic acids help in maintaining the cell membrane which is one of the underlining mechanisms by which plants inhibit PLA
 <sub>2</sub> activity and inflammation (Krishna and Mohan 
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Absent of a peak at 2260 cm
 <sup>−1</sup> region indicates absence of cyanide group in SMF1 which shows the non-toxic nature of the plant (Ranjana and Vijay 
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).
</p>
