<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec6.1.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">6.1.3. Anticarcinogenic</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anticarcinogenic activity is the ability of a specific substance to counteract or completely inhibit the development of carcinogen. The traditional anticancer therapy, such as multichemotherapeutic drugs, is often compromised of the development of drug resistance and the serious irreversible side effects [
  <a rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60">60</a>]. As pointed out recently, natural products from medicinal plants represent a fertile ground for the development of novel anticancer agents. However, the utilization of plant EOs as anticancer agents is under daily diagnosis for designing the best natural alternative, which could have selectivity towards the target cells of various tumours.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the current review, some revealing examples of plant EOs and their constituents that have been used effectively as antitumour agents have been discussed. The detailed discussion will also be reported regarding the possible mechanisms and the multiple pathways involving apoptosis, DNA repair modulation, cell cycle arrest, and antiproliferative activity through the increase of reactive oxygen and nitrogen levels (ROS/RNS) in cancer cells [
  <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">61</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some EOs showed a potential anticancer activity against liver, lung, colon, and prostate cancer such as
  <span class="italic"> Artemisia lavandulaefolia</span> DC and its main single constituent 1,8-cineole against a subline of the ubiquitous KERATIN-forming tumour cell line HeLa which derived from an epidermal carcinoma of the mouth [
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">62</a>]. Jayaprakasha et al. (2013) [
  <a rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63">63</a>] found that
  <span class="italic"> C. limettioides</span> Tan EO inhibited colon cancer (SW480) by inducing the cells-apoptosis. Zu et al. (2010) [
  <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">64</a>] noted that the
  <span class="italic"> T. vulgaris</span> EO exhibited the strongest cytotoxicity towards three human cancers: PC-3 from human prostate, A549 from human lung, and MCF-7 from breast adenocarcinoma.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Further studies demonstrated that some single constituents like carvacrol [
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>], thymol [
  <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">66</a>], limonene, and citral [
  <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">67</a>] have shown a promising cytotoxic effect against different human cancer cell lines mainly due to the induction the mitochondrial dysfunction [
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>–
  <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">67</a>]. Elshafie et al. [
  <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">68</a>] have pointed out the effectiveness of
  <span class="italic"> O. vulgare</span> EO and its main single constituents (carvacrol, thymol, citral, and limonene) on tumour liver cell line (HepG2) following the MTT viability assay. The results showed that the above treatments illustrated a great effect as anticancer therapeutic agents especially thymol and carvacrol (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The general mechanism of cytotoxic effect of plant EOs is mostly due to the presence of phenols, aldehydes, and alcohols. In particular, the toxicity towards mammalians decreases significantly with the increase of average lipophilicity of EO components [
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>], while the toxicity against bacteria and fungi simultaneously increases significantly with increasing lipophilicity [
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>]. This mode of action refers to the extraordinary role of EOs among natural compounds, especially of their highly lipophilic constituents. The cellular mechanisms of carcinogenic prevention by EO treatments were also considered to be due to the induction of cell-apoptosis [
  <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">61</a>]. There is also a suggestion that the pathway of cancer cells is sensitive to the inhibitory actions of plant isoprenoids by reducing tumour cell-size in patients [
  <a rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69">69</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
