<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">idr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">idr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Infection and Drug Resistance</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1178-6973</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8071092</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">305503</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S305503</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Coadministration of Ginger Extract and Fluconazole Shows a Synergistic Effect in the Treatment of Drug-Resistant Vulvovaginal Candidiasis</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Khan et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Khan et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Arif</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Azam</surname><given-names>Mohd</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6486-9835</contrib-id><name><surname>Allemailem</surname><given-names>Khaled S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0850-5500</contrib-id><name><surname>Alrumaihi</surname><given-names>Faris</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1491-6402</contrib-id><name><surname>Almatroudi</surname><given-names>Ahmad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0151-8309</contrib-id><name><surname>Alhumaydhi</surname><given-names>Fahad A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>Hafiz Iqtidar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Masih Uzzaman</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4031-4189</contrib-id><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Masood Alam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="ft0001">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Basic Health Sciences, College of Applied Medical Sciences, Qassim University</institution>, <addr-line>Buraydah</addr-line>, <addr-line>51452</addr-line>, <country>Saudi Arabia</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Medical Laboratories, College of Applied Medical Sciences, Qassim University</institution>, <addr-line>Buraydah</addr-line>, <addr-line>51452</addr-line>, <country>Saudi Arabia</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Tashreeh Wa Munafeul Aza, Faculty of Unani Medicine, Aligarh Muslim University</institution>, <addr-line>Aligarh</addr-line>, <addr-line>202002</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry &#x00026; Pharmacognosy, Unaizah College of Pharmacy, Qassim University</institution>, <addr-line>Buraydah</addr-line>, <addr-line>51452</addr-line>, <country>Saudi Arabia</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Masood Alam Khan <institution>College of Applied Medical Sciences, Qassim University</institution>, <addr-line>Buraydah</addr-line>, <addr-line>51452</addr-line>, <country>Saudi Arabia</country><phone>Tel +966-507059437</phone> Email a_khan@qu.edu.sa</corresp><fn id="ft0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><fpage>1585</fpage><lpage>1599</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2021 Khan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Khan et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution &#x02013; Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="s2001"><title>Background</title><p>Azoles are the most common antifungal drugs used in the treatment of vulvovaginal candidiasis (VVC). The frequency of azole-resistant <italic>Candida</italic> isolates has increased dramatically in the last two decades. Here, we assessed the antifungal activity of a combination of fluconazole (FLZ) and methanolic extract of ginger (Meth-Gin) against drug-resistant vulvovaginal candidiasis (VVC) in a murine model.</p></sec><sec id="s2002"><title>Methods</title><p>The in vitro activity of FLZ or a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin was determined against <italic>Candida albicans</italic> by the agar well diffusion, macrodilution, time-kill and the biofilm eradication methods. The therapeutic efficacy of the formulations was assessed by analyzing the fungal load, pro-inflammatory cytokines, percent apoptotic cells and the histological changes in the vaginal tissues of the mice. Moreover, the renal toxicity the drug formulation was evaluated by analyzing the levels of the blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and creatinine.</p></sec><sec id="s2003"><title>Results</title><p>The results of in vitro study demonstrated that FLZ did not show any activity against <italic>C. albicans</italic>, whereas a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin demonstrated greater activity as shown by the data of the zone of growth inhibition, MIC and time-kill assay. FLZ or Meth-Gin treatment could not completely cure VVC, whereas a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin was greatly effective in the treatment of VVC. The vaginal tissue from mice of the infected control group had the highest fungal load of 155370 &#x000b1; 20617 CFUs. Treatment with FLZ at a dose of 40 mg/kg reduced the fungal load to 120863 &#x000b1; 10723 CFUs. Interestingly, the mice treated with a combination of FLZ (40 mg/kg) and Meth-Gin (200 mg/kg) had a fungal load of 256 &#x000b1; 152 CFUs. Besides, FLZ and Meth-Gin combination effectively reduced the pro-inflammatory cytokines (IL-1&#x003b2;, TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-17) and the percentage of apoptotic cells in the vaginal tissues. Likewise, the histological analysis revealed the epithelial necrosis, shedding and ulceration in the vaginal tissue, whereas treatment with FLZ and Meth-Gin combination reversed the histopathological changes in the vaginal epithelium and lamina propria.</p></sec><sec id="s2004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The findings of the current study suggest that the co-administration of Meth-Gin and FLZ may have a potential therapeutic effect in the treatment of azole-resistant candidiasis.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>fluconazole</kwd><kwd>candidiasis</kwd><kwd>ginger extract</kwd><kwd>inflammation</kwd><kwd>cytokines</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>any funding agency</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This study is not supported by any funding agency.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="10"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="60"/><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>The occurrence of <italic>Candida</italic> infections has lately amplified due to a sharp rise in the numbers of immunocompromised patients.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1&#x02013;3</xref>
<italic>Candida albicans</italic> is the most common fungal pathogen that causes a vaginal infection called &#x0201c;Vulvovaginal candidiasis (VVC)&#x0201d;. Beside <italic>C. albicans, C. glabrata</italic> induced VVC has increased about 27% from 1990 to 2009.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Azoles are the most frequently used antifungal drugs that target enzyme 14&#x003b1;&#x02013;demethylase and lower the levels of ergosterol in <italic>C. albicans</italic>.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Moreover, azoles also increase the reactive oxygen species (ROS) levels in the fungal biofilm.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> But their extensive use has resulted in the emergence of azole-resistant <italic>Candida</italic> isolates<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Besides attempting to search the new antifungal chemotherapeutics, the rejuvenation of the existing antifungal drugs also becomes important to compensate the depleted armory of the antifungal drugs.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> The use of antibiotic combinations seems to be an important strategy to counter the phenomenon of drug resistance.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11&#x02013;13</xref> Chloroquine (CQ) and fluconazole (FLZ) exhibited a synergistic effect against FLZ-resistant isolates of <italic>C. albicans</italic>.<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> We earlier showed that liposomal-CQ increased the efficacy of FLZ against less susceptible isolate of <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic>.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p><p>In recent years, the use of plant-derived medicines has been extensively explored in the treatment of infectious diseases.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16&#x02013;18</xref> A combination of phytochemicals with standard antibiotics has been shown to be very beneficial to fight drug-resistant pathogens.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19&#x02013;22</xref> The combination of menthol with nystatin and itraconazole showed a synergistic effect against the clinical isolates of <italic>Candida</italic> spp.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Moreover, the essential oil of <italic>Mentha suaveolens</italic> exhibited activity against the murine vaginal candidiasis.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Donadu et al demonstrated that <italic>Helichrysum microphyllum</italic> and <italic>Hypericum perforatum</italic> oils demonstrated antifungal activity against <italic>Candida</italic> isolates taken from the patients of candidiasis.<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Moreover, essential oils from <italic>Hornstedtia bella</italic> and <italic>Atalantia sessiflora</italic> have shown their activity against <italic>Candida</italic> spp.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Ginger (<italic>Zingiber officinale</italic>) is an important spice and a medicinal herb that possesses the antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and hepatoprotective properties.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> An aqueous extract of ginger exhibited an anti-biofilm formation in bacteria, including <italic>Escherichia coli, Salmonella typhimurium</italic> and <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Ginger contains many constituents that are blended with many antimicrobial activities<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30&#x02013;35</xref> (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Ginger components such as 6-gingerols and 6-shogaol have shown their efficacy in inhibiting the biofilm and hyphae formation in <italic>C. albicans</italic>.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Moreover, an ethanolic extract of ginger showed the inhibitory effect against the biofilm formation in <italic>C. albicans</italic> and <italic>C. krusei</italic>.<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> In the present study, we have evaluated the effect of methanolic extract of ginger (Meth-Gin) in combination with FLZ against VVC in a mouse model. The findings of the present study demonstrated that coadministration of Meth-Gin remarkably augmented the activity of FLZ against murine VVC.<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Principal Constituents of Ginger and Their Antimicrobial Activity</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">S. No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constituent</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Functions</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-Gingerol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-Gingerol reduced the biofilm formation at the concentrations of 10, 50 and 100 &#x000b5;g/mL. It also inhibited the hyphae formation in <italic>C. albicans</italic>.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lee et al, 2018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10-Gingerol and 12-Gingerol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10-Gingerol and 12-Gingerol show antibacterial activity against oral pathogens in the range of 6 to 30 &#x000b5;g/mL.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Park et al, 2008</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-Shogaol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-Shogaol at a concentration of 10 &#x000b5;g/mL inhibited the biofilm formation in <italic>C. albicans</italic>.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lee et al, 2018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zingerone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibits the biofilm formation and increase the activity of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kumar et al, 2013</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gingerenone-A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shows inhibitory effect against <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rampogu et al, 2018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ginger essential oil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;-terpinene and citral components showed antifungal activity against <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic>.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moon et al, 2018</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Materials</title><p>Fluconazole was purchased from the Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Dallas, TX, USA). Sabouraud dextrose agar and Tryptic soya broth were obtained from Hi Media (Mumbai, India). Estradiol valerate and other chemicals were bought from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, USA). ELISA kits for IL-1&#x003b2;, TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-17 were purchased from Abcam (Cambridge, UK).</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Preparation of Methanolic Extract of Ginger</title><p>The dried ginger powder was defatted by using cyclohexane followed by stirring for 3 hours. The powder was placed in the Soxhlet extraction system (Buchi laboratories, Flawil, Switzerland) for 48 hours, adding the methanol as a solvent in the collecting beaker. The remaining solvent was evaporated completely under the reduced pressure using vacuum controlled rotary evaporator to remove the traces of methanol.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>Test Strain</title><p>An isolate of <italic>C. albicans</italic> (KFH 121) was obtained from the Microbiology Laboratory of the King Fahad Hospital, Buraydah, Saudi Arabia. The isolate was maintained on Sabouraud Dextrose Agar (SDA). The identification of <italic>C. albicans</italic> was confirmed by the germ tube induction test.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>Antifungal Susceptibility Testing</title><p>The in vitro activity of FLZ or Meth-Gin or a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin was determined by the agar well diffusion and macrodilution methods.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
<italic>C. albicans</italic> was seeded on the SDA plates and the holes of 8 mm diameter were made to load 100 &#x000b5;L of FLZ (100 &#x000b5;g) or Meth-Gin (500 &#x000b5;g) or FLZ (100 &#x000b5;g) + Meth-Gin (250 &#x000b5;g) and FLZ (100 &#x000b5;g) + Meth-Gin (500 &#x000b5;g). The plates were incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C for 24 hours and the zone of growth inhibition was measured. The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of FLZ and Meth-Gin were determined by the broth macrodilution antifungal susceptibility method according to the guidelines of the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI), Wayne.<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> The concentrations of FLZ were taken in the range of 0.5 to 256 &#x000b5;g/mL, whereas Meth-Gin was taken in the range of 20 &#x000b5;g/mL to 4 mg/mL. A 100 &#x003bc;L of yeast suspension containing 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> CFUs of <italic>C. albicans</italic> was inoculated in the test tubes containing 3 mL of Tryptic soya broth (TSB) with various concentrations of FLZ or Meth-Gin. The MIC of FLZ or Met-Gin was considered the lowest drug concentration that showed 50% inhibition in <italic>C. albicans</italic> growth. In order to assess any synergy between FLZ and Meth-Gin, a combination of above mentioned concentration of FLZ and Meth-Gin were taken and their activity against <italic>C. albicans</italic> was determined. The concentration of FLZ and Meth-Gin in which there was 50% growth inhibition was considered the MIC value.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>To Analyze a Synergy Between FLZ and Meth-Gin</title><p>The fractional inhibitory concentration index (FICI) was used to evaluate the interaction of FLZ and Meth-Gin. The concentration ranges of FLZ and Meth-Gin were same as mentioned above to determine the MIC value. The FIC index was expressed using the following equation:</p><p>&#x001a9;FIC = FIC-FLZ + FIC-Meth-Gin = MIC<sub>FLZ</sub><sup>comb</sup>/MIC<sub>FLZ</sub><sup>alone</sup> + MIC<sub>Meth-Gin</sub>
<sup>comb</sup>/MIC<sub>Meth-Gin</sub>
<sup>alone</sup></p><p>where MIC<sub>FLZ</sub>
<sup>alone</sup> and MIC<sub>Meth-Gin</sub>
<sup>alone</sup> are MIC values for FLZ and Meth-Gin used alone. MIC<sub>FLZ</sub><sup>comb</sup> and MIC<sub>Meth-Gin</sub>
<sup>comb</sup> are MICs of FLZ and Meth-Gin when used in combination. The MIC values of FLZ and Meth-Gin alone or in combinations were determined as the lowest concentrations of the drug that showed 50% reduction in <italic>C. albicans</italic> growth as compared to the growth in the absence of any drug.</p><p>The interaction between FLZ and Meth-Gin was interpreted as a synergistic when FIC index was less than 0.5. When FIC index was between 0.5 and 4, the interaction was considered indifferent, and as an antagonist when FIC index was more than 4.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2006"><title>Time-Kill Assay</title><p>After overnight culture, <italic>C. albicans</italic> was diluted with YPD medium and the culture was incubated at 37&#x000b0;C until the log-phase of growth was achieved. <italic>C. albicans</italic> suspension (5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> CFUs) was transferred to the flasks containing 20 mL of YPD and FLZ (8 &#x003bc;g/mL) or Meth-Gin (2 mg/mL) or a combination of FLZ (8 &#x003bc;g/mL) and Meth-Gin (0.25, 0.5, 1 and 2 mg/mL). The flasks were kept in a shaker bath and samples (0.5 mL) were taken in duplicates at baseline and 1, 3, 6, 12, 24 hours. Samples were centrifuged at 5000 rpm for 15 minutes and reconstituted with sterile PBS to the original volumes to minimize any drug carryover effect. The numbers of CFUs were quantified by plating the serial dilutions onto SDA plates and incubated for 48 hours. The fungal density of each sample was determined by counting the CFUs.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2007"><title>Analysis of <italic>C. albicans</italic> Death by Confocal Microscopy</title><p><italic>Candida albicans</italic> (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> CFUs) was cultured in TSB in the presence or absence of FLZ (16 &#x003bc;g/mL) or Meth-Gin (500 &#x003bc;g/mL) or a combination of FLZ-8 &#x003bc;g/mL + Meth-Gin-500 and FLZ-16 &#x003bc;g/mL + Meth-Gin-500 for 24 hours. After gentle washing with PBS, the cells were stained with propidium iodide (PI) and washed with PBS. The cells were observed and analyzed by confocal microscopy using 20&#x000d7; magnification objective as described earlier.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2008"><title>Effect of FLZ or Meth-Gin or a Combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin on the Preformed <italic>C. albicans</italic> Biofilm</title><p>The effect of FLZ or Meth-Gin or a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin on the preformed biofilm by <italic>C. albicans</italic> was analyzed as described earlier.<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>
<italic>C. albicans</italic> was cultured in TSB to obtain the density of approximately 1&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup> CFUs/mL. <italic>C. albicans</italic> (100 &#x000b5;L) was inoculated into 96-well plate and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 24 hours. Without disrupting the biofilm, the culture medium was replaced with a fresh TSB containing FLZ (8, 16, 32 and 64 &#x000b5;g/mL) or Meth-Gin (250, 500, 1000 and 2000 &#x000b5;g/mL) or a combination of FLZ (8 &#x003bc;g/mL) and Meth-Gin (500, 1000 and 2000 &#x000b5;g/mL). The plates were incubated for 24 hours at 37&#x000b0;C, gently washed with sterile phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and dried at room temperature for 20 minutes. The crystal violet solution (0.1%) was added to each well for 20 minutes to stain the biofilm followed by washing with PBS. After drying, 100 &#x000b5;L of 95% ethanol was added into each well in order to solubilize the stain. The optical density (OD) was measured at 595 nm (BIO-TEK EL310 Microplate Auto-Reader, Biotek instruments).</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2009"><title>Mice</title><p>Female Swiss mice were obtained from the College of Applied Medical Sciences, Qassim University, Saudi Arabia. Mice were kept in the hygienic and pathogen-free conditions. The study was authorized by the ethical committee of the College of Applied Medical Sciences, Qassim University. The experiments were conducted following the guidelines of the University of London Animal Welfare Society, Wheathampstead, England.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2010"><title>Infection Model</title><p>A dose of 500 &#x000b5;g of estradiol valerate was dissolved in 100 &#x000b5;L of sesame oil and injected subcutaneously into each mouse. On 3 day post estradiol valerate injection, each mouse was infected with 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> CFUs of <italic>C. albicans</italic> through the intravaginal route as described in our earlier study.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2011"><title>Therapeutic Efficacy of FLZ Against VVC</title><p>After 48 hours of infection, the mice in various groups were orally treated with FLZ at the doses of 10, 20 and 40 mg/kg for a week. Mice were divided into four groups and each group contained ten mice (n = 10).</p><p>1. Infected</p><p>2. FLZ-10 mg/kg</p><p>3. FLZ-20 mg/kg</p><p>4. FLZ-40 mg/kg</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2012"><title>Therapeutic Activity of Meth-Gin in the Treatment of VVC</title><p>In a different experiment, infected mice from each group were treated with a daily dose of 50, 100 and 200 mg/kg of Meth-Gin through the oral route for a week. On day 8 post infection, three mice from each group were sacrificed and the vaginal tissues were excised to quantify the fungal load.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> Mice were divided into five groups and each group contained ten mice (n = 10).</p><p>1. Infected</p><p>2. Meth-Gin-50 mg/kg</p><p>3. Meth-Gin-100 mg/kg</p><p>4. Meth-Gin-200 mg/kg</p><p>5. Meth-Gin-400 mg/kg</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2013"><title>To Assess the Efficacy and Safety of FLZ or Meth-Gin in the Treatment of VVC</title><p>On day 8 post-treatment, three mice from each group were sacrificed to take the vaginal tissue and blood. In order to determine the fungal burden, the vaginal tissues were homogenized in cold-PBS and various dilutions of tissue homogenates were spread on SDA plates. After 48 hours of incubation, the CFUs were counted and multiplied by the dilution factor.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> The levels of the blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and creatinine were determined to investigate the toxic effects of the treatment on kidney.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2014"><title>Co-Administration of Meth-Gin and FLZ in the Treatment of VVC</title><p>Mice were treated with a single daily dose of a combination of Meth-Gin (100 mg/kg) and FLZ (20 and 40 mg/kg) for a week. On day 8 post infection, three mice from each group were sacrificed and their vaginal tissues were excised to determine the fungal load. Mice were divided into six groups and each group contained ten mice (n = 10).</p><p>1. Infected</p><p>2. Meth-Gin-200 mg/kg</p><p>3. FLZ-20 mg/kg</p><p>4. FLZ-40 mg/kg</p><p>5. Meth-Gin-200 mg/kg + FLZ-20 mg/kg</p><p>6. Meth-Gin-200 mg/kg + FLZ-40 mg/kg</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2015"><title>To Assess the Efficacy and Safety of a Combination of Meth-Gin and FLZ</title><p>On day 8 post-treatment, three mice from each group were sacrificed and their vaginal tissue was taken out. The vaginal tissues were homogenized in cold-PBS and various dilutions of tissue homogenate were spread on SDA plates. The plates were incubated for 48 hours and the numbers of CFUs were counted.<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> To understand the effect of treatment on the renal toxicity, the levels of blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and creatinine were analyzed in the blood as described earlier.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2016"><title>Determination of Inflammatory Cytokines in the Vaginal Tissues</title><p>The vaginal tissues were homogenized in ice-cold lysis buffer containing protease inhibitor cocktail. The samples were centrifuged at 5000 rpm for 15 minutes. The supernatant was used to analyze IL-1&#x003b2;, TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-17 by the ELISA as described in our earlier study.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2017"><title>Analysis of Apoptotic Vaginal Cells by Flow Cytometric Analysis</title><p>Cell apoptosis was identified by the flow cytometry using FITC-conjugated annexin V and propidium iodide (PI) staining. The single-cell suspension of vaginal tissue was prepared by using gentleMACs<sup>TM</sup> Dissociator (Miltenyi Biotec, Bergisch Gladbach, Germany). The cells were filtered through 70 um mesh cell strainer followed by centrifugation, and then suspended in the binding buffer. The vaginal cells were stained with Annexin V-FITC/PI apoptosis staining kit (Miltenyi Biotec, Germany). The samples were acquired by MACSQuant Analyzer 10 and the data were analyzed using FlowJo software v10.7.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2018"><title>Histopathological Analysis</title><p>The vaginal tissues from mice were fixed into 10% neutral-buffered formalin. Paraffin-embedded blocks were prepared and serial sections of 5 &#x003bc;m thickness were cut. They were stained with Hematoxylin and Eosin (H and E) staining as described earlier.<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> In brief, the tissue sections were deparaffinised, hydrated and stained with hematoxylin for 45 seconds. The slides were rinsed and stained with eosin for 45 seconds. Again, the slides were rinsed thoroughly and mounted with DPX. The histopathological changes in tissues were observed by examining the slides under a light microscope (Leica, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2019"><title>Statistics</title><p>The fungal load data and hematological and cytokine parameters were analyzed by one-way ANOVA followed by a Bonferroni post test using GraphPad Prism software, version 6.0 (La Jolla, CA, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Susceptibility of <italic>C. albicans</italic> to FLZ and Meth-Gin</title><p>The SDA plate containing vehicle did not show any zone of inhibition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1A</xref>), whereas the SDA plate containing Meth-Gin (500 &#x000b5;g) showed 10 mm size of the inhibition zone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1B</xref>). However, the plate containing FLZ (100 &#x000b5;g) did not show any clear zone of inhibition, but showed some fungistatic effect around the well (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1C</xref>). Interestingly, a synergy was observed between FLZ and Meth-Gin as the well containing a combination of FLZ (100 &#x000b5;g) with 250 and 500 &#x000b5;g of Meth-Gin showed inhibition zones of 30 and 35 mm, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">E</xref>).<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Activity of Meth-Gin or FLZ or a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin against <italic>C. albicans</italic> by the agar well diffusion method. (<bold>A</bold>) Vehicle control (<bold>B</bold>) Meth-Gin-500 &#x000b5;g (<bold>C</bold>) FLZ 100 &#x000b5;g (<bold>D</bold>) Meth-Gin-250 + FLZ 100 &#x000b5;g (<bold>E</bold>) Meth-Gin-500 + FLZ 100.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1585-g0001"/></fig></p><p>In the current study, the MIC of FLZ for <italic>C. albicans</italic> was found to be 64 &#x000b5;g/mL. <italic>Candida albicans</italic> with MIC value &#x02265;64 &#x000b5;g/mL of FLZ has been categorized as a resistant strain according to the CLSI guidelines. The MIC for Meth-Gin against the present <italic>C. albicans</italic> isolate was found to be 3 mg/ ml. The MIC of FLZ and Meth-Gin in combination were considerably reduced and found to be 16 &#x000b5;g/mL and 1 mg/mL, respectively. The mean FIC index for a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin was calculated to be 0.416 that indicates a synergistic interaction between FLZ and Meth-Gin.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>The Confocal Microscopy Analysis Revealed a Synergistic Effect of FLZ and Meth-Gin Against <italic>C. albicans</italic></title><p>The antifungal effect of FLZ alone or in combination with Meth-Gin against <italic>C. albicans</italic> was measured by the confocal microscopy after staining with propidium iodide (PI). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>, there was no significant difference in the viability of the cells, which were exposed to FLZ as compared to vehicle-treated <italic>C. albicans</italic>. Whereas, a continuous decrease was observed in the viability of <italic>C. albicans</italic> treated with Meth-Gin alone or a combination of Meth-Gin and FLZ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>)<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The effect of FLZ or Meth-Gin or a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin on cell viability of <italic>C. albicans</italic> by confocal microscopy using propidium iodide staining.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1585-g0002"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003"><title>Synergism of FLZ and Meth-Gin Against <italic>C. albicans</italic> by Time-Kill Studies</title><p>The antifungal effect of FLZ alone or in combination of Meth-Gin against <italic>C. albicans</italic> was analyzed by time kill studies. The extent of <italic>C. albicans</italic> killing was determined by a decrease in the numbers of CFUs at different time points. The findings of the present study demonstrated that there was a time-dependent effect of FLZ and Meth-Gin combination against <italic>C. albicans</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>). FLZ (8 &#x000b5;g/mL) alone exhibited very meager activity against <italic>C. albicans</italic> at 24 hour time point. However, FLZ (8 &#x000b5;g/mL) in combination with Meth-Gin (1 and 2 mg/mL) reduced &#x02265;3 log10 CFUs/mL of <italic>C. albicans</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>). Nevertheless, the combination of FLZ (8 &#x003bc;g/mL) and Meth-Gin (0.5 mg/mL) produced a 2.1-log10 CFUs/mL reduction as compared to the vehicle treatment at 24 hour time point. It suggested that a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin showed an augmented antifungal activity against <italic>C. albicans</italic>. Interestingly, Meth-Gin (2 mg/kg) also reduced &#x02265;3 log10 CFUs/mL of <italic>C. albicans</italic>. FLZ (8 &#x000b5;g/mL) in combination with 1 or 2 mg/mL of Meth-Gin killed 99.99 of <italic>C. albicans</italic> as compared to FLZ (8 &#x000b5;g/mL) treatment alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>).<fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Time-kill curves of Meth-Gin or FLZ or a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin against <italic>C. albicans</italic> Control (&#x025cf;), FLZ-8 &#x000b5;g/mL (&#x025a1;), FLZ-8 &#x000b5;g/mL + Meth-Gin-0.25 mg/mL (&#x025b2;), FLZ-8 &#x000b5;g/mL + Meth-Gin-0.5 mg/mL (&#x025bc;), FLZ-8 &#x000b5;g/mL + Meth-Gin-1 mg/mL (&#x02666;), FLZ-8 &#x000b5;g/mL + Meth-Gin-2 mg/mL (&#x025cb;), Meth-Gin-2 mg/mL (&#x025ca;). The data are represented as mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1585-g0003"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2004"><title>FLZ and Meth-Gin Combination, Not FLZ Alone, Effectively Eradicated Preformed Biofilm</title><p>We tested various concentrations of FLZ (8, 16, 32 and 64 &#x000b5;g/mL) against the preformed <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilm. FLZ at the highest concentration (64 &#x000b5;g/mL) eliminated 29% of the preformed biofilm as compared to the vehicle treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4A</xref>), albeit it is found to be statistically significant (P&#x0003c;0.001). Simultaneously, we tested the concentration-dependent effect of Meth-Gin in the elimination of biofilm. Meth-Gin treatment eradicated 41% of the biofilm at a dose of 2000 &#x000b5;g/mL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4B</xref>), which was significant as compared to the vehicle treatment (P&#x0003c;0.001). For FLZ treatment could not effectively remove the preformed biofilm. To understand whether the treatment with FLZ and Meth-Gin combination is effective to eliminate the biofilm, the results demonstrated that a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin efficiently removed the preformed <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4C</xref>). FLZ (8 &#x000b5;g/mL) in combination with Meth-Gin at the doses of 500, 1000 and 2000 &#x000b5;g/mL reduced the biofilm to 59.6%, 37.6% and 17.3%, respectively, as compared to vehicle control (P&#x0003c;0.001). Moreover, the anti-biofilm activity of FLZ and Meth-Gin was also found to be significantly greater as compared to FLZ treatment (P&#x0003c;0.001).<fig id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The activity of various doses of (<bold>A</bold>) FLZ, or (<bold>B</bold>) Meth-Gin, or (<bold>C</bold>) Meth-Gin + FLZ against <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilm. A P value &#x0003c;0.05 was considered to be significant. *(<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05), ***(<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001), Infected control vs Treatment groups. <sup>###</sup>P&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, FLZ-treated group vs Treatment groups. The data are represented as mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1585-g0004"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2005"><title>Treatment with FLZ Did Not Cure Murine VVC</title><p>The therapeutic efficacy of FLZ was assessed by analyzing the fungal load in the vaginal tissues of <italic>C. albicans</italic> infected mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5A</xref>). FLZ at the doses of 10 and 20 mg/kg did not significantly reduce the vaginal fungal burden as compared to the fungal burden in the untreated infected mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5A</xref>). However, FLZ at a dose of 40 mg/kg significantly decreased the fungal burden to 92230 &#x000b1; 8416 CFUs as compared to 133010 &#x000b1; 17289 CFUs in the untreated infected mice (P&#x0003c;0.05).<fig id="f0005" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>The effect of FLZ treatment on (<bold>A</bold>) fungal load, (<bold>B</bold>) BUN and (<bold>C</bold>) creatinine in <italic>C. albicans</italic> infected mice. A P value &#x0003c;0.05 was considered to be significant. *(<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05), **(<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01), Infected control vs Treatment groups. The data are represented as mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1585-g0005"/></fig></p><p>In order to evaluate FLZ-induced renal toxicity, the BUN and creatinine levels were analyzed in the blood of the treated mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">C</xref>). FLZ therapy at a dose of 10 mg/kg elevated the BUN level from 22.67 &#x000b1; 7 to 34 &#x000b1; 5.3 mg/dl (P&#x0003e;0.05), whereas FLZ treatment at the doses of 20 and 40 mg/kg significantly raised the BUN level to 49.33 &#x000b1; 7 and 68.33 &#x000b1; 14.6 mg/dl, respectively (P&#x0003c;0.05 and P&#x0003c;0.001). On the other hand, there was no significant rise in creatinine level in mice treated with FLZ at the above mentioned doses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5C</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2006"><title>Meth-Gin Treatment Was Effective in Reducing the Severity of VVC</title><p>The activity of Meth-Gin against VVC was analyzed by determining the fungal burden in the vaginal tissue. Meth-Gin reduced the fungal burden in a dose-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6A</xref>). Meth-Gin at a dose of 400 mg/kg was the most effective against VVC and reduced the fungal burden to 17031 &#x000b1; 11259 as compared to 154037 &#x000b1; 10053 CFUs/gm of the vaginal tissue in the untreated mice (P&#x0003c;0.001). Noteworthy, a treatment with Meth-Gin, at the doses of 100 and 200 mg/kg, reduced the fungal burden to 108040 &#x000b1; 15294 and 62897 &#x000b1; 15893 CFUs/gm (P&#x0003c;0.05 and P&#x0003c;0.001, respectively). However, Meth-Gin at a dose of 50 mg/kg was not effective against VVC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6A</xref>). The toxicity of Meth-Gin was assessed by evaluating the BUN and creatinine levels in the blood. The results demonstrated that Meth-Gin at the doses of 50, 100, 200 and 400 mg/kg did not induce any significant elevation in the BUN and creatinine levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">C</xref>).<fig id="f0006" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The effect of Meth-Gin treatment on (<bold>A</bold>) fungal load, (<bold>B</bold>) BUN and (<bold>C</bold>) creatinine in <italic>C. albicans</italic> infected mice. A P value &#x0003c;0.05 was considered to be significant. *(<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05), ***(<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001), Infected control vs Treatment groups. The data are represented as mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1585-g0006"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2007"><title>Coadministration of Meth-Gin and FLZ Showed a Synergistic Effect Against VVC</title><p>The activity of FLZ in combination with Meth-Gin was assessed against murine VVC. The results demonstrated that FLZ at the doses of 20 and 40 mg/kg was not effective to cure VVC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7A</xref>), whereas the administration of FLZ in combination with Meth-Gin was found to be very effective to treat VVC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7A</xref>). The coadministration of FLZ (40 mg/kg) and Meth-Gin (200 mg/kg) substantially decreased the fungal load (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7A</xref>), which was highly significant lower as compared to FLZ treatment alone (P&#x0003c;0.001). Like to this, FLZ (20 mg/kg) along with Meth-Gin (200 mg/kg) reduced the fungal burden to 8523 &#x000b1; 3226 CFUs as compared to the fungal burden of 140373 &#x000b1; 15475 CFUs in the vaginal tissue of mice treated with FLZ (20 mg/kg) (P&#x0003c;0.001).<fig id="f0007" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>The effect of a combination of Meth-Gin and FLZ treatment on (<bold>A</bold>) fungal load, (<bold>B</bold>) BUN and (<bold>C</bold>) creatinine in <italic>C. albicans</italic> infected mice. A P value &#x0003c;0.05 was considered to be significant. **(<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01), ***(<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001) Infected control vs Treatment groups. <sup>#</sup>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>###</sup>P&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, FLZ-treated group vs Treatment groups. The data are represented as mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1585-g0007"/></fig></p><p>The renal toxicity of FLZ or a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin treatment was assessed by analyzing the BUN and creatinine levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">C</xref>). Treatment with FLZ at a dose of 40 mg/kg elevated the BUN level from 24 &#x000b1; 8.5 to 80 &#x000b1; 12.5 mg/dl (P&#x0003c;0.001). Mice treated with a combination of FLZ (40 mg/kg) and Meth-Gin (200 mg/kg) had the BUN level of 48.67 &#x000b1; 10 mg/dl, which was significantly lower as compared to the BUN level in mice treated with FLZ (40 mg/kg) (P&#x0003c;0.05). Like to the BUN level, the creatinine level was significantly elevated to 1.33 &#x000b1; 0.12 mg/dl in the mice of FLZ treated group (40 mg/kg) as compared to 0.633 mg/dl in mice from the untreated group (P&#x0003c;0.001). Interestingly, the treatment with a combination FLZ (40 mg/kg) and Meth-Gin reduced creatinine level to 0.9 &#x000b1; 0.11 mg/dl (P&#x0003c;0.05).</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2008"><title>Treatment with a Combination of Meth-Gin and FLZ Reduced the Secretion of Pro-Inflammatory Cytokines in the Vaginal Tissues</title><p>The levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines, including IL-1&#x003b2;, TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-17 were determined in the vaginal tissue homogenates. Mice in the untreated group exhibited a substantial increase in the levels of IL-1&#x003b2;, TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-17 as compared to their levels in normal mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">Figure 8A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">8B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">C</xref>). IL-1&#x003b2; in the vaginal tissue from the normal control mice was found to be 71 &#x02009;&#x000b1; 18 pg/mL that was increased to 362 &#x000b1; 113 pg/mL in the infected mice (P&#x0003c;0.01). Treatment with a combination of FLZ (40 mg/kg) and Meth-Gin (200 mg/kg) significantly reduced IL-1&#x003b2; to 115 &#x000b1; 31 pg/mL (&#x0003c;0.05).<fig id="f0008" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Treatment with a combination of Meth-Gin and FLZ reduces the levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines in the vaginal tissues. Vaginal tissues were excised and homogenized to determine the levels of cytokines (<bold>A</bold>) IL-1&#x003b2;, (<bold>B</bold>) TNF-&#x003b1; and (<bold>C</bold>) IL-17. A P value &#x0003c;0.05 was considered to be significant. The data are represented as mean &#x000b1; SD of two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1585-g0008"/></fig></p><p>TNF-&#x003b1; was also found to be substantially raised in the vaginal tissue of VVC-inflicted mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">Figure 8B</xref>). TNF-&#x003b1; in the untreated mice was found to be 748 &#x000b1; 68 pg/mL that was significantly higher as compared to 161 &#x000b1; 38 pg/mL in the vaginal tissue from the normal control mice (P&#x0003c;0.001). Treatment with a combination of FLZ (40 mg/kg) and Meth-Gin (200 mg/kg) reduced TNF-&#x003b1; level to 249 &#x000b1; 72 pg/mL (P&#x0003c;0.001). Moreover, a combination of FLZ (20 mg/kg) and Meth-Gin also reduced TNF-&#x003b1; to 388 &#x000b1; 121 pg/mL (P&#x0003c;0.01). However, FLZ at the doses of 20 and 40 mg/kg did not significantly decrease TNF-&#x003b1; in the vaginal tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">Figure 8B</xref>). Interestingly, the treatment with Meth-Gin decreased TNF-&#x003b1; level to 434 &#x000b1; 134 pg/mL, which was significantly lower as compared to TNF-&#x003b1; level in the untreated mice (P&#x0003c;0.05).</p><p>Like to IL-1&#x003b2; and TNF-&#x003b1;, IL-17 was increased to 275 &#x000b1; 62 pg/mL as compared to 31 &#x000b1; 17 pg/mL in the normal mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">Figure 8C</xref>, P&#x0003c;0.001). Treatment with FLZ (20 and 40 mg/kg) did not significantly decrease IL-17 level in the infected mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0008">Figure 8C</xref>, P&#x0003e;0.05). However, a combination of FLZ-40 and Meth-Gin decreased IL-17 level from 275 &#x000b1; 62 to 84 &#x000b1; 27 pg/mL (P&#x0003c;0.01). Furthermore, FLZ-40 and Meth-Gin combination was more effective in reducing IL-17 level as compared to FLZ-40 treatment alone (P&#x0003c;0.05).</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2009"><title>A Combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin Protected the Vaginal Cells Against VVC-Induced Apoptosis</title><p><italic>Candida albicans</italic> infection induced apoptosis in the vaginal cells. A total of 40.6% cells showed apoptosis in the vaginal tissue from the untreated mice as compared to 2.35% in the infected mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">Figure 9A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">G</xref>) (P&#x0003c;0.001). Mice treated with FLZ had 35.9% apoptotic cells (P&#x0003e;0.05) in the vaginal tissues, whereas Meth-Gin treatment reduced the percentage of apoptotic cells to 27.7% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">Figure 9C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">G</xref>) (P&#x0003c;0.01). A combination of FLZ (20 and 40 mg/kg) and Meth-Gin (200 mg/kg) was found to be very effective and reduced the apoptotic cells to 15.77% and 13.13%, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">Figure 9E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">F</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">G</xref>), which were significantly reduced as compared to the untreated or FLZ-treated mice (P&#x0003c;0.001).<fig id="f0009" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Flow cytometric analysis of apoptotic cells in the vaginal tissues from the mice of various treatment groups. A single cell suspension of the vaginal tissue was prepared and cells were stained by using Annexin V-FITC/PI apoptosis staining kit. (<bold>A</bold>) Normal control, (<bold>B</bold>) untreated infected, (<bold>C</bold>) FLZ-40 mg/kg, (<bold>D</bold>) Meth-Gin-200 mg/kg, (<bold>E</bold>) FLZ-20 mg/kg + Meth-Gin-200 mg/kg, (<bold>F</bold>) FLZ-40 mg/kg + Meth-Gin-200 mg/kg (<bold>G</bold>) % Apoptotic cells in various groups. A P value &#x0003c;0.05 was considered to be significant. ***(<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001) Infected control vs Normal control, <sup>##</sup>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 and <sup>###</sup>P&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, Infected group vs Treatment groups, <sup>&#x025cf;&#x025cf;&#x025cf;</sup>P&#x0003c;0.001 FLZ-40 vs FLZ-20 + Meth-Gin or FLZ-40 + Meth-Gin. The data are represented as mean &#x000b1; SD of two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1585-g0009"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2010"><title>Treatment with FLZ and Meth-Gin Combination Ameliorated Histopathological Changes in the Vaginal Tissues</title><p>In order to assess the therapeutic effect of FLZ or a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin in the treatment of VVC, we analyzed the histological alterations in the vaginal tissues from the mice in the untreated or FLZ or Meth-Gin or FLZ + Meth-Gin treated mice. The vaginal tissue from the control normal mice revealed non-keratinized stratified squamous epithelium and normal lamina propria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0010">Figure 10A</xref>). Whereas, the vaginal tissues from the infected mice showed epithelial necrosis, shedding and an extensive ulceration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0010">Figure 10B</xref>). Moreover, the presence of C. albicans hyphae can be seen in the vaginal tissue of the untreated mice (red arrow). FLZ or Meth-Gin treatment showed moderate recovery with numerous scattered inflammatory cells and leukocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0010">Figure 10C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0010">D</xref>). Treatment with a combination of FLZ (20 and 40 mg/kg) and Meth-Gin (200 mg/kg) showed regenerative alterations, including the mild epithelial necrosis with few scattered inflammatory cells in the lamina propria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0010">Figure 10E</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0010">F</xref>).<fig id="f0010" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Treatment with a combination of Meth-Gin and FLZ reversed VVC-induced histopathological changes in the vaginal tissues. Vaginal tissues were excised from the mice and the tissues were processed for H &#x00026; E staining as described in the methodology section. Vaginal tissue from (<bold>A</bold>) normal control mice (<bold>B</bold>) Infected mice (<bold>C</bold>) FLZ-40 mg/kg (<bold>D</bold>) Meth-Gin-200 mg/kg, (<bold>E</bold>) FLZ-20 mg/kg + Meth-Gin-200 mg/kg, (<bold>F</bold>) FLZ-40 mg/kg + Meth-Gin-200 mg/kg.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1585-g0010"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>Azoles are front-line antifungal drugs that are widely used in the treatment of Candidiasis. The massive use of FLZ has resulted in the emergence of drug-resistant <italic>Candida</italic> isolates. The target of FLZ is lanosterol 14-&#x003b1; demethylase, an enzyme that is coded by ERG11 gene. An over-expression of multi-drug resistant genes, including MDR1, CDR1 or CDR2 or ERG11 contributes to FLZ-resistance in <italic>C. albicans</italic> isolates.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Several toxic manifestations, including hypokalemia, respiratory failure and liver inflammation are associated with the use of FLZ treatment.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> A rapid emergence of resistance against FLZ has rendered these antifungals ineffective. Thus, it is very important to formulate a strategy to keep these antifungal drugs effective and alive. In the current work, we investigated the therapeutic effect of Meth-Gin to increase the antifungal activity of FLZ against drug-resistant VVC.</p><p>In recent years, many approaches for the combination therapy have been proposed to treat infectious diseases.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11&#x02013;15</xref> This is very important, particularly, to counter the phenomenon of the multi-drug resistance. Various phytochemicals have been suggested to show a synergistic effect with multiple antibiotics.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Many plant-derived substances have shown their effectiveness to fight <italic>Candida</italic> infections, particularly those less susceptible to current antifungal drugs.<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> The use of alcoholic extract of <italic>Flos rosae chinensis</italic> has been shown to increase the activity of FLZ against the drug-resistant <italic>C. albicans</italic>.<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> The extract of <italic>Punica granatum</italic> and its purified compound punicalagin showed a synergistic effect with FLZ.<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> Giordani et al showed that essential oil of <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> potentiated the activity of amphotericin B against <italic>C. albicans</italic>.<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> Furthermore, <italic>Allium sativum</italic> has been reported to increase the antifungal activity of ketoconazole against Trichophyton spp.<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> In another study, <italic>Pelargonium graveolens</italic> components, geraniol and citronellol, were reported to exert the additive effects with amphotericin B and ketoconazole against <italic>Aspergillus</italic> spp.<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></p><p>Ginger showed anti-inflammatory and antioxidant effects when used in combination with anti-tubercular therapy in patients.<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> Ginger and its bioactive component 6-shogaol have been effective to alleviate the lung inflammation in an asthma model.<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> In this study, we investigated the synergistic effect of methanolic extract of Ginger (Meth-Gin) and FLZ against <italic>C. albicans</italic> both in in vitro and in a mouse model of VVC. The results of the present study demonstrated that FLZ alone did not exhibit any visible activity against <italic>C. albicans</italic>. Moreover, FLZ was ineffective to eradicate the preformed biofilm and to cure murine VVC. However, Meth-Gin showed some efficacy against <italic>C. albicans</italic>, but it did not completely cure VVC. Earlier reports demonstrated that the components of Ginger, 6-shogaol and 6-gingerol, had an anti-biofilm activity against <italic>C. auris</italic> and <italic>C. albicans</italic>.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> The biofilm formation is considered one of the most important virulence strategy of <italic>C. albicans</italic> in the pathogenesis of VVC.<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> Moreover, it reduces the susceptibility of the pathogens to antibiotics and contributes to broaden the phenomenon of antibiotic-resistance. The results of the current study demonstrated that FLZ alone was not effective to eradicate the preformed biofilm. However, FLZ in combination with Meth-Gin almost completely eradicated the preformed biofilm. It suggests that Meth-Gin can increase the susceptibility of <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilm to FLZ.</p><p>None of the past studies showed the activity of Ginger extract alone or in combination with antifungal drug against VVC. The findings of the present study demonstrated that FLZ treatment not only was ineffective to cure VVC but also induced renal toxicity in mice. Earlier, Ginger administration has been shown to alleviate <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic> infection-induced deleterious effects by modulating inflammatory cytokines and liver inflammation enzymes.<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Moreover, Ginger has been shown to possess protective effects against cadmium- and lead-induced nephrotoxicity.<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> The administration of Meth-Gin not only increased the activity of FLZ against VVC but also reduced FLZ-induced renal toxicity in the treated mice. Proinflammatory cytokines, including IL-1&#x003b2;, TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-17 play an important role in protecting against various pathogens. However, the excessive secretion of inflammatory cytokines exaggerates the pathogenesis of VVC by increasing the severity of inflammation. It reduces the clearance of the pathogen from the host.<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> Earlier, the role of pro-inflammatory cytokines have been documented in a mouse model of VVC.<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> Ginger possesses anti-inflammatory properties and inhibits the production of TNF-&#x003b1;, IL-6 and other inflammatory markers.<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref> Here, we investigated the effect of Meth-Gin and FLZ combination on the secretion of IL-1&#x003b2;, TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-17 in the vaginal tissues. The levels of IL-1&#x003b2;, TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-17 were found to be elevated in the vaginal tissue of the infected mice. Treatment with Meth-Gin or a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin substantially decreased the levels of IL-1&#x003b2;, TNF-&#x003b1; and IL-17. Contrarily, FLZ at the doses of 20 and 40 mg/kg did not effectively reduce the levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines. In a recent report, Roselletti et al showed the apoptosis of vaginal epithelial cells in the clinical samples from the women affected by vaginal infection.<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> The findings of the present study showed that vaginal tissue from the untreated mice had a remarkably increased percentage of apoptotic cells, whereas mice treated with a combination of Meth-Gin and FLZ showed significantly lower numbers of apoptotic cells.</p><p>The polymorphonuclear neutrophils (PMNs) are important cells of the innate immune system as the first line of defense against the fungal pathogens, including <italic>C. albicans</italic>. A symptomatic VVC is related to the recruitment of PMNs that contributes to the symptoms of inflammation. The results of the present study demonstrated that the vaginal tissues from the untreated infected mice showed higher numbers of leukocytes. Whereas, the mice treated with a combination of FLZ and meth-Gin showed reduced infiltration of leukocytes in the vaginal tissue. The data of pro-inflammatory cytokines and the fungal load were supported by the histological findings. The vaginal tissue from the untreated infected mice showed the vaginal wall degeneration, epithelial necrosis and ulceration. Whereas, the treatment with a combination of FLZ and Meth-Gin reversed the VVC-induced pathological alterations in the vaginal tissues.</p><p>Keeping into consideration the findings of the present study, it may be concluded that coadministration of Meth-Gin and FLZ may be highly effective to treat drug-resistant VVC. Moreover, the administration of Ginger extract may alleviate VVC-induced inflammation and apoptosis. Thus, the use of Ginger extract may prove to be an effective herbal formulation to increase the activity and reduce the toxicity of FLZ against candidiasis.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We would like to thank the Deanship of Scientific Research, Qassim University, Buraydah, Saudi Arabia for the support.</p></ack><sec id="s0005" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest to declare.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Martins</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferreira</surname>
<given-names>IC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barros</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Silva</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henriques</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Candidiasis: predisposing factors, prevention, diagnosis and alternative treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mycopathologia</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>177</volume>(<issue>5&#x02013;6</issue>):<fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>240</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11046-014-9749-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24789109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fatima</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hameed</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Predisposing factors endorsing Candida infections</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infez Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>223</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26397289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Spampinato</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leonardi</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Candida infections, causes, targets, and resistance mechanisms: traditional and alternative antifungal agents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Res Int</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>2013</volume>:<fpage>204237</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/204237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23878798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Martins</surname>
<given-names>HP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Da silva</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paiva</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Svidzinski</surname>
<given-names>TI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Consolaro</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Efficacy of fluconazole and nystatin in the treatment of vaginal Candida species</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Acta Derm Venereol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>78</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2340/00015555-1194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21918792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nakamura-Vasconcelos</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fiorini</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zanni</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Emergence of Candida glabrata in vulvovaginal candidiasis should be attributed to selective pressure or virulence ability?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Gynecol Obstet</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>296</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>519</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>526</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00404-017-4465-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28730269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sae-Tia</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fries</surname>
<given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title><italic>Candidiasis</italic> and Mechanisms of Antifungal Resistance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antibiotics (Basel)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>312</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics9060312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Delattin</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cammue</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thevissen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Reactive oxygen species-inducing antifungal agents and their activity against fungal biofilms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Future Med Chem</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4155/fmc.13.189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24358949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Younus</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allemailem</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Potential of methylglyoxal-conjugated chitosan nanoparticles in treatment of fluconazole-resistant <italic>Candida albicans</italic> infection in a murine model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Nanomedicine</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>3681</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3693</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJN.S249625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32547022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Whaley</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berkow</surname>
<given-names>EL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rybak</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nishimoto</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barker</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Azole antifungal resistance in <italic>Candida albicans</italic> and emerging non-<italic>albicans Candida</italic> species</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>2173</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.02173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28127295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Arastehfar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gabald&#x000f3;n</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia-Rubio</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Drug-resistant fungi: an emerging challenge threatening our limited antifungal armamentarium</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antibiotics (Basel)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>877</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics9120877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chaturvedi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chaturvedi</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> evaluation of antifungal drug combinations against multidrug-resistant candida auris isolates from New York outbreak</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Agents Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e02195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.02195-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31932367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Gentamicin synergises with azoles against drug-resistant Candida albicans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Antimicrob Agents</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>114</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2017.09.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28943366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Denardi</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keller</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oliveira</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mario</surname>
<given-names>DAN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santurio</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alves</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Activity of combined antifungal agents against multidrug-resistant candida glabrata strains</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mycopathologia</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>182</volume>(<issue>9&#x02013;10</issue>):<fpage>819</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>828</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11046-017-0141-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28493006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wan</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Synergistic activity of chloroquine with fluconazole against fluconazole-resistant isolates of Candida species</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Agents Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1369</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.04417-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25512426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jabeen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohammad</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prophylactic role of liposomized chloroquine against murine cryptococcosis less susceptible to fluconazole</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pharm Res</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2212</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11095-004-7672-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15648251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aljarbou</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Younus</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Liposomal thymoquinone effectively combats fluconazole-resistant Candida albicans in a murine model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Biol Macromol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>208</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2015.02.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25709021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Langeveld</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veldhuizen</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burt</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Synergy between essential oil components and antibiotics: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Crit Rev Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/1040841X.2013.763219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23445470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Duan</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comparative efficacy of Chinese herbal injections combined with azithromycin for mycoplasma pneumonia in children: a Bayesian network meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Pharm Ther</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>675</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>684</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jcpt.12855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31119782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effectiveness of Chinese herbal medicine combined with antibiotics for extensively drug-resistant enterobacteria and nonfermentative bacteria infection: real-life experience in a retrospective cohort</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biomed Res Int</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>2897045</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2017/2897045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29159177</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ayaz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ullah</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sadiq</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Synergistic interactions of phytochemicals with antimicrobial agents: potential strategy to counteract drug resistance</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chem Biol Interact</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>308</volume>:<fpage>294</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>303</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbi.2019.05.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31158333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Salih</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Synergistic effects of plant extracts and antifungal drugs on C. albicans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Dev Drugs</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4172/2329-6631.1000165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rolta</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharma</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sourirajan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mallikarjunan</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dev</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Combination between antibacterial and antifungal antibiotics with phytocompounds of Artemisia annua L: a strategy to control drug resistance pathogens</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Ethnopharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>266</volume>:<fpage>113420</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2020.113420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32998023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sharifzadeh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khosravi</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shokri</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tari</surname>
<given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Synergistic anticandidal activity of menthol in combination with itraconazole and nystatin against clinical Candida glabrata and Candida krusei isolates</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microb Pathog</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>390</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>396</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2017.04.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28431915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pietrella</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Angiolella</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vavala</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Beneficial effect of Mentha suaveolens essential oil in the treatment of vaginal candidiasis assessed by real-time monitoring of infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Complement Altern Med</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6882-11-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21356078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Donadu</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Usai</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marchetti</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Antifungal activity of oils macerates of North Sardinia plants against <italic>Candida</italic> species isolated from clinical patients with candidiasis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Prod Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>3280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3284</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14786419.2018.1557175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30676066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Donadu</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trong</surname>
<given-names>LN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Viet</surname>
<given-names>HD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Phytochemical compositions and biological activities of essential oils from the leaves, rhizomes and whole plant of <italic>Hornstedtia bella</italic> &#x00160;korni&#x0010d;k</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antibiotics (Basel)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>334</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics9060334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Le</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Donadu</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>DV</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Biological activities of essential oil extracted from leaves of Atalantia sessiflora Guillauminin Vietnam</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect Dev Ctries</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1054</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1064</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3855/jidc.12469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33031096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rahmani</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shabrmi</surname>
<given-names>FMA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aly</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Active ingredients of ginger as potential candidates in the prevention and treatment of diseases via modulation of biological activities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Physiol Pathophysiol Pharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>136</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25057339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>HD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ginger extract inhibits biofilm formation by Pseudomonas aeruginosa PA14</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>76106</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mao</surname>
<given-names>QQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>XY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Bioactive compounds and bioactivities of ginger (<italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> Roscoe)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Foods</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>185</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/foods8060185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>YG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ham</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antibiofilm and antivirulence activities of 6-gingerol and 6-shogaol against <italic>Candida albicans</italic> due to hyphal inhibition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Cell Infect Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2018.00299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30211127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bae</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antibacterial activity of [10]-gingerol and [12]-gingerol isolated from ginger rhizome against periodontal bacteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Phytother Res</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1446</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1449</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ptr.2473</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18814211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chhibber</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harjai</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Zingerone inhibit biofilm formation and improve antibiofilm efficacy of ciprofloxacin against Pseudomonas aeruginosa PAO1</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Fitoterapia</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2013.06.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23831483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rampogu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baek</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gajula</surname>
<given-names>RG</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Ginger (Zingiber officinale) phytochemicals-gingerenone-A and shogaol inhibit SaHPPK: molecular docking, molecular dynamics simulations and in vitro approaches</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Clin Microbiol Antimicrob</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12941-018-0266-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29609660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Moon</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Inhibitory effects of three monoterpenes from ginger essential oil on growth and aflatoxin production of <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic> and their gene regulation in aflatoxin biosynthesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Appl Biol Chem</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>250</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13765-018-0352-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aghazadeh</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zahedi Bialvaei</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aghazadeh</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Survey of the antibiofilm and antimicrobial effects of zingiber officinale (in Vitro Study)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Jundishapur J Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e30167</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5812/jjm.30167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27127591</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</collab>. <article-title>Reference method for broth dilution antifungal susceptibility testing of yeasts; approved standard-third edition; CLSI document M27-A3</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Wayne, PA, USA</publisher-loc>:<publisher-name>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</publisher-name>; <year>2008a</year>. <comment>CLSI</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alhumaydhi</surname>
<given-names>FA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alwashmi</surname>
<given-names>ASS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Diallyl sulfide-mediated modulation of the fatty acid synthase (FASN) leads to cancer cell death in bap-induced lung carcinogenesis in Swiss mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Inflamm Res</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1075</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1087</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/JIR.S284279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33324084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Balasamy</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ravinayagam</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alomari</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al., <article-title>Cisplatin delivery, anticancer and antibacterial properties of Fe/SBA-16/ZIF-8 nanocomposite</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">RSC Adv</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<issue>9</issue>:<fpage>42395</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42408</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C9RA07461A</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ahmad</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alam</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shehbaz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Antimicrobial activity of clove oil and its potential in the treatment of vaginal candidiasis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Drug Target</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<page-range>555&#x02010;561</page-range>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10611860500422958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0041"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Laskar</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rahmani</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fatima</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Younus</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Thymoquinone, an active constituent of Nigella sativa seeds, binds with bilirubin and protects mice from hyperbilirubinemia and cyclophosphamide-induced hepatotoxicity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biochimie</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>213</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biochi.2016.05.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27265787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0042"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Coadministration of liposomal methylglyoxal increases the activity of amphotericin B against <italic>Candida albicans</italic> in leukopenic mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Drug Target</italic></source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>78</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1061186X.2020.1803333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32723117</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0043"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zaoutis</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dvorak</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of caspofungin vs fluconazole prophylaxis on invasive fungal disease among children and young adults with acute myeloid leukemia: a Randomized Clinical Trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>322</volume>:<fpage>1673</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1681</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2019.15702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31688884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0044"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guevara-Lora</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bras</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karkowska-Kuleta</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Plant-derived substances in the fight against infections caused by <italic>candida</italic> species</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Mol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>6131</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms21176131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0045"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Antifungal activity of the ethanol extract from <italic>flos rosae chinensis</italic> with activity against fluconazole-resistant clinical <italic>candida</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<fpage>4780746</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28303159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0046"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Endo</surname>
<given-names>EH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cortez</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ueda-Nakamura</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakamura</surname>
<given-names>CV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dias Filho</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Potent antifungal activity of extracts and pure compound isolated from pomegranate peels and synergism with fluconazole against Candida albicans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>161</volume>:<fpage>534</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>540</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resmic.2010.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20541606</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0047"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Giordani</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Regli</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaloustian</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mika&#x000ef;l</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abou</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Portugal</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antifungal effect of various essential oils against Candida albicans. Potentiation of antifungal action of amphotericin B by essential oil from Thymus vulgaris</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Phytother Res</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>990</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>995</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ptr.1594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15742351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0048"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pyun</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antifungal effects of the volatile oils from Allium plants against Trichophyton species and synergism of the oils with ketoconazole</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Phytomedicine</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>394</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>400</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phymed.2005.03.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16716908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0049"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Anti-Aspergillus activities of plant essential oils and their combination effects with ketoconazole or amphotericin B</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arch Pharm Res</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>393</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02976696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12785735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0050"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kulkarni</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deshpande</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Anti-inflammatory and antioxidant effect of ginger in tuberculosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Complement Integr Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>206</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/jcim-2015-0032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27089418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0051"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yocum</surname>
<given-names>GT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hwang</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mikami</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Danielsson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuforiji</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Emala</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ginger and its bioactive component 6-shogaol mitigate lung inflammation in a murine asthma model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>318</volume>:<fpage>L296</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>L303</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajplung.00249.2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31800263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0052"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Muzny</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schwebke</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Biofilms: an underappreciated mechanism of treatment failure and recurrence in vaginal infections: table 1</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>601</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>606</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/civ353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25935553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0053"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aly</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mantawy</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Efficiency of ginger (<italic>Zingbar officinale</italic>) against Schistosoma mansoni infection during host-parasite association</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Parasitol Int</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>380</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>389</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.parint.2013.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23583317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0054"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reddy</surname>
<given-names>YA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chalamaiah</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramesh</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Balaji</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Indira</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ameliorating activity of ginger (Zingiber officinale) extract against lead induced renal toxicity in male rats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Food Sci Technol</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>908</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>914</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13197-011-0568-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24803697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0055"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gabr</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alghadir</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghoniem</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Biological activities of ginger against cadmium-induced renal toxicity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Saudi J Biol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>382</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>389</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2017.08.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31485182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0056"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Romani</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fallarino</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Luca</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Defective tryptophan catabolism underlies inflammation in mouse chronic granulomatous disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>451</volume>:<fpage>211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>215</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18185592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0057"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tian</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of perillaldehyde on prophylaxis and treatment of vaginal candidiasis in a murine model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1466</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.01466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31333606</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0058"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ezzat</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ezzat</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Okba</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Menze</surname>
<given-names>ET</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdel-Naim</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The hidden mechanism beyond ginger (Zingiber officinale Rosc.) potent in vivo and in vitro anti-inflammatory activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Ethnopharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>214</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>123</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2017.12.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29253614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0059"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roselletti</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sabbatini</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perito</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mencacci</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vecchiarelli</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monari</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Apoptosis of vaginal epithelial cells in clinical samples from women with diagnosed bacterial vaginosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1978</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-58862-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32029862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0060"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yano</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noverr</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fidel</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>. <article-title>Novel mechanism behind the immunopathogenesis of vulvovaginal candidiasis: &#x0201c;Neutrophil Anergy&#x0201d;</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Immun</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e00684</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e00717</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00684-17</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>