<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent articles have demonstrated that various plant byproducts, such as fruit or vegetable pomace, bran/husk/seed coat, seeds, peel, and leaves, are important source of phytochemicals and can be utilised as innovative ingredient in foods [
 <xref rid="B6-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Extracts obtained from various sections of the 
 <italic>Annona squamosa</italic> plant, such as its bark, roots, leaf, stem, fruit, peel, and seeds, have been utilised in traditional pharmacological applications in different countries to cure a variety of diseases, such as dysentery, epilepsy, haemorrhage, fever, and tumours [
 <xref rid="B2-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. 
 <italic>Annona squamosa</italic> seed powder is utilised to abolish lice, leaf extract is used to pacify boils and treat ulcers, and the fruit acts as a sedative in cases involving heart ailments and can be used to alleviate vomiting and treat tumours [
 <xref rid="B18-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Phytochemical studies have revealed that custard apple contains numerous phenol-based compounds, e.g., proanthocyanidins, with 18 different phenolic compounds, mainly alkaloids or flavonoids [
 <xref rid="B19-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Apart from fruit, large amounts of leaves are generated during pruning, which causes complications related to their disposal for farmers. 
 <italic>Annona squamosa</italic> leaves (ASLs) possess valorisation potential owing to their extensive pharmacological properties and biological activities, such as antioxidant, antimicrobial, antidiabetic, antiviral, anticancer, and hepatoprotective activities. 
 <italic>Annona squamosa</italic> fruit and leaf are shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biomolecules-11-00614-f001">Figure 1</xref>. These activities are caused by the presence of glycosides, phytosterols, carbohydrates, oils, saponins, tannins, alkaloids, phenols, flavonoids, peptides, and various acetogenin compounds [
 <xref rid="B5-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Phytochemical assessments have emphasised that numerous active compounds, such as acetogenins and flavonoids, present in 
 <italic>Annona squamosa</italic> also give rise to plant cytotoxic, antimalarial, antidiabetic, and immunosuppressive activities. Extract of ASLs helps maintain plasma insulin and lipid profiles and can significantly reduce blood glucose and lipid peroxidation [
 <xref rid="B5-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The existing literature on 
 <italic>Annona squamosa</italic> lacks extensive compilation of pivotal information on its phytochemical, nutraceutical, and biological activities. Hence, the present review is a sincere effort to aggregate crucial information regarding the nutritional, pharmacological, and biological aspects and activities of ASLs.
</p>
