<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Origanum compactum</span> essential oil
  </div>
  <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">O. compactum</span> (obtained from flowering aerial parts) was kindly supplied by Pranarôm International (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pranarom.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.pranarom.com</span>). Its analysis was achieved on an Agilent 6890 N gas chromatograph equipped with a 5973-N mass spectrometer (MS). The settings for the MS were as follows: EI mode, 70 eV, and mass to charge ratio (
   <span class="italic">m/</span>z) scan between 35 and 400. A HP-5 MS capillary column (30 m × ID 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm film thickness, J &amp; W Scientific, Folsom, CA, USA) using helium gas flow (1.0 ml/min) was used for separation. The GC temperature program was as follows: initial 50 °C for 5 min, then increasing with 20 °C/min to 300 °C. The injector temperature was 150 °C. Quali-quantitative analysis of the essential oil was performed according to the work of Benelli et al. (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2017</a>). Thymol and carvacrol were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Madrid, Spain).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Anisakis simplex</span> from blue whiting
  </div>
  <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Anisakis simplex</span> L3 larvae were isolated from the intermediary host 
   <span class="italic">Micromesistius poutassou</span> (Risso) (blue whiting) purchased from the fishmonger in Villanueva de Gállego (Zaragoza, Spain). The worms were washed several times on sterile solution of 0.9% NaCl and identified under light microscope according to morphological features. Only larvae with length &gt; 2.0 cm were used for the larvicidal assays.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anthelmintic activity against 
   <span class="italic">Anisakis simplex</span> L3 larvae
  </div>
  <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This assay was performed in 6 well plates. Ten larvae were introduced in each well of polystyrene plates with a final volume of 2 ml sterile saline solution containing different concentrations of the test solution (Gómez-Rincón et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2014</a>). 
   <span class="italic">O. compactum</span> essential oil was tested against 
   <span class="italic">Anisakis</span> in the range of 0–1 μl/ml. The major constituents carvacrol and thymol were tested in the same range of concentrations. Appropriate control wells without treatments were also carried out in each experiment. The parasites were incubated at 37 °C for 24 and 48 h. Levamisole was used as the reference antiparasitic drug. Larvae were examined at 24 and 48 h under microscope, and immobile L3 was considered dead.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inhibition of acetylcholinesterase</div>
  <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inhibition of acetylcholinesterase (AChE) was determined in 96 microplates using the method by Ellman et al. (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">1961</a>) with some modifications. Each well contained 25 μl of 15 mM ATCI in Millipore water, 125 μl of 3 mM DTNB in buffer C (50 mM Tris–HCl, pH 8, 0.1 M NaCl, 0.02 M MgCl2 6 H2O), 50 μl buffer B (50 mM Tris–HCl, pH 8, 0.1% bovine serum), and 25 μl of test compound or extract. Every concentration was tested in triplicates. Then, 25 μl and 0.22 U/ml AChE were added and the absorbance was measured eight times every 13 s at 405 nm. Galantamine was used as reference.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Penetration assays</div>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Agar block plates were prepared in 12-well plates to study the capacity of the living larvae to penetrate. The agar solution was made with the following reagents: 0.75% agar in RPMI 1640 medium solution (pH 4, Sigma, USA) with 20% FBS (Lonza, USA). One millilitre of the solution was poured into each well. Then, 100 μl of supernatant, RPMI-1640 (RPMI-1640, 20% FBS, 1% commercial pepsin, pH 4.0), was placed into each well. 
   <span class="italic">A. simplex</span> L3 larvae were incubated with a sub-lethal concentration (0.125 mg/ml) of 
   <span class="italic">O. compactum</span> essential oil for 24 h. Five larvae were placed on each control or simple well. The plates were incubated for 24 h, and the number of L3 larvae that penetrated the solid agar block was counted after that period.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All experiments were performed in triplicates in different weeks using new 
   <span class="italic">A. simplex</span> larvae. LD
   <sub>50</sub> (median lethal dose) and IC
   <sub>50</sub> (half maximal inhibitory concentration) values for larvicidal and mechanistic assays were calculated using non-linear regression (GraphPad Prism 5).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
