<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As mentioned above, medicinal mushrooms refer to all macroscopic fungi whose extracts or powder form from any stages of the mushroom development have shown documented beneficial effects on health [
 <xref rid="B13-jof-06-00269" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. These beneficial effects may have been shown in the forms of in vitro, ex vivo, or in vivo activities. Their effects may cover different groups of organisms such as antagonistic effects against human pathogens and parasites, and/or beneficial effects for human and animal cell lines, or animal and human individuals [
 <xref rid="B11-jof-06-00269" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Since many edible mushrooms and their products have shown to be a beneficial component of the human diet, some of these edible mushrooms are also commonly included as medicinal mushrooms [
 <xref rid="B7-jof-06-00269" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In our literature search, a large number of MMs have been documented. For example, terpenes and terpenoids from 
 <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> could stimulate the expressions of genes coding for proteins in the nuclear factor (NF)–kB pathway and modulate immune system functions [
 <xref rid="B14-jof-06-00269" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Heteroglycan and heteroglycan-peptide from the mushroom of 
 <italic>Hericium erinaceus</italic> can modulate the immuno-effects by inducing nitric oxide production and increasing expression of tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α, interleukin (IL)-1β, IL-12 [
 <xref rid="B15-jof-06-00269" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. These mushrooms belong to two fungal phyla, Ascomycota and Basidiomycota. Most of the MMs are in phylum Basidiomycota. 
 <xref rid="jof-06-00269-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows the major medicinal mushrooms, including their taxonomy and geographic/ecological distributions. As can be seen, some of these mushrooms are broadly distributed (e.g., the button mushroom 
 <italic>Agaricus bisporus</italic>) while others are geographically more restricted (e.g., the Himalayan caterpillar fungus 
 <italic>Ophiocordyceps sinensis</italic>). Some of the mushrooms included in the table e.g., 
 <italic>Amanita phalloides</italic> are highly poisonous when consumed by humans. However, the dilutions of an 
 <italic>A. phalloides</italic> extract that contains the toxin amanitin have shown to be effective as an anti-tumor therapy [
 <xref rid="B16-jof-06-00269" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
</p>
