<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another implication of 
 <italic>Eimeria</italic> infection, besides the direct consequences on animal health and welfare, is its impact on the enteric microbiota. Recently, it has been shown that the severity of pathology caused by 
 <italic>E. tenella</italic> infection of broiler chickens as quantified by intestinal lesion scoring can be linked with changes in enteric microbial occurrence and population structure (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). In our trial, the diversity of microbial composition within caecal and jejunal microbiomes showed a potentially more beneficial composition in broilers fed the mixture of oregano and garlic oil compared with control chickens. The current study evaluated the composition and structure of specific caecal and jejunal bacteria in the absence of a defined 
 <italic>Eimeria</italic> challenge. A significant increase in 
 <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> was found in the jejunum of the essential oil-supplemented birds, but this effect was not repeated in the caeca. 
 <italic>Clostridium perfringens</italic> is a ubiquitous organism, widely distributed in nature and in human and animal intestinal tracts where it presents in high numbers when specific predisposing factors influence digestive system integrity (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). Here, oregano and garlic essential oil supplementation lowered 
 <italic>C. perfringens</italic> counts in the jejunum, a site where it has been associated with intestinal epithelium inflammation and stimulation of bacterial dysbiosis. However, no statistically significant variation was noted for 
 <italic>C. perfringens</italic> occurrence in the caeca. In the literature, it has also been well-described that coccidiosis and stress are predisposing factors for alterations in the intestinal microflora and in 
 <italic>C. perfringens</italic> occurrence (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>).
</p>
