<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The metabolite profiling requires methods that facilitate the identification and quantification of hundreds of metabolites in a single or a complex plant mixture. Several approaches such as gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS), liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry (LC-MS), gas chromatography time-of-flight mass spectrometry (GC-TOF-MS) have been established as highly accurate and sensitive methods for the analysis of highly complex mixtures of compounds [
 <xref rid="B17-metabolites-11-00021" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Furthermore, the sample preparation techniques also play a vital role in achieving higher optimal results and obtaining consistent data in the later stages of analysis [
 <xref rid="B18-metabolites-11-00021" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The simple and appropriate sample preparation method using small amounts of samples are expected for the precision and improvement of VOCs analysis. The headspace (HS) sampling method, as a solvent-free sample preparation technique, has been playing a fundamental role in studying the composition of the volatile fractions emitted from plants [
 <xref rid="B19-metabolites-11-00021" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-metabolites-11-00021" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The solid-phase microextraction (SPME) technique has been proved for quick screening of VOCs in a wide range of products with the possibility to isolate trace compounds of different substrates [
 <xref rid="B21-metabolites-11-00021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-metabolites-11-00021" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Thus, the HS-SPME method can be used to extract multifarious volatile or semi-volatile organic compounds from a wide range of matrices, including air, water, and soil, which has been reported two decades ago [
 <xref rid="B21-metabolites-11-00021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Recently, the HS-SPME approach has widely been applied in the phytochemical study of plant species such as 
 <italic>Raphanus sativus</italic>, 
 <italic>Brassica juncea</italic> [
 <xref rid="B23-metabolites-11-00021" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], 
 <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> L. among others [
 <xref rid="B24-metabolites-11-00021" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. 
</p>
