<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par38" class="p">Although different fish species have different tolerance on exogenous fat-intake, natural selection endows fish with the abilities to store lipid in different organs when dietary fat is abundant, on the other hand, it accelerates lipid mobilization for providing energy. Generally, with the increasing dietary fat-intake, the lipid content of fish body was also increased progressively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>]. Interestingly, the priority site of fat deposition was species-specific in fish. Several fish species stored lipid (mainly TG) in mesentery and viscera preferentially, like grass carp (
 <italic class="italic">Ctenopharyngodon idella</italic>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>] and Nile tilapia (
 <italic class="italic">Oreochromis niloticus</italic>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>], while Atlantic salmon (
 <italic class="italic">Salmo salar</italic>) would prefer storing lipid in muscle but not liver [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>]. The selective strategy could contribute to reduce the potential risk of fat deposits in liver. Besides, the homeostasis of hepatic lipid could depend on the hepatic mitochondrial and peroxisomal oxidation capacities. Because the activation of hepatic mitochondrial oxidation could accelerate the degradation of free fatty acids (FFAs) via carnitine palmitoyltransferase I (CPT1) and then release adenosine triphosphate (ATP) for providing energy through the tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>].
</p>
