<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another important issue that deserves to be highlighted in this manuscript is that the combination of PEL and LAT exerted higher antimicrobial activity than LAT alone, well-known to be important during breast feeding [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. PEL+LAT were able to statistically reduce 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> growth, effect that was longer than that observed for penicillin/streptomycin. The administration of the single compounds still reduced bacteria growth; however, this effect was observed at 6 h rather than at 5 h. Moreover, this effect was not due to antioxidant activity of the single compounds as already reported [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Indeed, the sole compounds were not able to exert antioxidant activities, rather, they showed bacteriostatic activity although at later time points. It has already been reported that LAT has strong antimicrobial activities against Gram positive and Gram negative bacteria as well as fungi, yeasts, viruses and protozoa [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The antimicrobial activity of LAT is generally associated to two mechanisms: the first is based on iron absorption in the site of infection, leading to the deprivation of nutrients to microbes; the second one is the direct contact of LAT with pathogens which interferes with microbial physiology [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In the latter case, the presence of positive amino acids in LAT chemical structure allows it to interact with negatively charged molecules on some bacterial, viral, fungal and parasite surfaces, causing cell lysis [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. On the other hand, we already proved that PEL alone can exert antimicrobial activities [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Here, the combination of PEL and LAT led to an additive bacteriostatic activity, especially in the case of 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>. In addition, due to the recent emergency and spread of multidrug resistant pathogens, the combination of PEL and LAT could prove of innovative potentiality for the actual antimicrobial therapy.
</p>
