<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparing the chemical composition of hydrodistilled of flower- and leaves-derived oil of 
  <span class="italic">F. tingitana</span>, α-thujene, α-terpinoline, decanal, fenchyl acetate, elemol, cadinol, and eudesmol were present in both samples in comparable amounts. Carene, ocimene, myecene, and caryophyllene were detected in flower-derived oil not detected in leaves-oil.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An alternative goal of the hereby presented study was to draw conclusion as to the presumed disparities between our observation and previously published data concerning the chemistry of 
  <span class="italic">F. tingitana</span>. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report on the chemical composition of the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">F. tingitana</span> flower and leaves growing in Libya. Nevertheless, the composition of the essential oil from 
  <span class="italic">F. tingitana</span>, cultivated in different regions of Turkey, was previously studied.[
  <a rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref49">49</a>] It was rich in monoterpenes represented by Naphthalene (15%), α-Pinene (11%). Meanwhile, sesquiterpenes were predominated by Daucene (6%) (Z)-
  <span class="italic">β</span>-Farnesene (5%) Germacrene D (5%).[
  <a rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref49">49</a>
  <a rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref50">50</a>] On the contrary, naphthalene (absent in the Libyan sample). Moreover, the hydrocarbons, 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene, elemene, a-humulene, and eudesma − 3, 5 diene were present Libyan samples. Moreover, the hydrocarbon, α-pinene were present in both Turkish[
  <a rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref49">49</a>] and Libyan 
  <span class="italic">Ferula</span> in comparable amounts. α-pinene and 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-pinene are reported as a major constituent of most studied 
  <span class="italic">Ferula</span> taxa, and considered as chemotype of 
  <span class="italic">Ferula</span>.[
  <a rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref14">14</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Elemol, cadinol, α-thujene, and α-terpinoline, the major components of the flower- and leaves-derived oil in the present work and, respectively, were not detected in the Turkish sample.[
  <a rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref49">49</a>] The differences may be due to climatic and other extrinsic conditions such as where and when the samples were collected.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When screened for antimicrobial activity, the flower- and leaves-derived oil of 
  <span class="italic">F. tingitana</span> exhibited a mild effect against all tested Gram-negative and Gram-positive microorganisms as compared to the standard antibacterial drug, tetracycline [
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">Table 3</a>]. However, tested essential oils not displayed growth inhibitory effect against the fungus 
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> as compared to the standard antifungal drug, amphotericin B. The leaves-derived oil is slightly more effective against Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria than oil of flower. Antimicrobial activity of essential oil is difficult to correlate to a specific compound due to their complexity and variability and in general, is attributed to phenolic hydroxyl groups able to form hydrogen bonds with active site of target enzymes, although other active terpenes, alcohols, aldehydes, and esters can contribute to the overall antimicrobial effect of essential oil.[
  <a rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref51">51</a>] The oil samples showed moderate antibacterial activity on 
  <span class="italic">B. subtilis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">N. gonorrhoeae. B. subtilis</span>, which are multiple antibiotic bacteria, because it is a biogenic amine procedure in food.[
  <a rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref52">52</a>] Furthermore, 
  <span class="italic">B. subtilis</span> has become an important agent of nosocomial infection.[
  <a rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref53">53</a>] The essential oil also inhibited the growth of multiple antibiotic resistant Staphylococcus strain, tested. The effect of essential oil on 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. aeruginosa</span> were high. 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> is a one of the most common causes of both hospital and community-acquired infection worldwide.[
  <a rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref54">54</a>] 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> is a major cause of cutaneous infections, furunculosis, impetigo and arthritis, and toxinoses, such as food poisoning, septic shock, scalded skin syndrome, and toxic shock syndrome. The presence of antibiotic resistant Staphylococci is of concern due to the possible spread of resistance determinants among the 
  <span class="italic">staphylococcus</span> species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On assessing the cytotoxic activity, the flower- and leaves-derived oil exhibited specific and significant effects on the viability of the selected human cell lines, 
  <span class="italic">namely</span>., hormone-responsive breast carcinoma cell line (MCF7), cervical carcinoma cell line (HeLa), and liver carcinoma cell line (HePG2). IC
  <sub>50</sub> was 4.8 μg/ml, 4.2 μg/ml, and 10.9 μg/ml for the leaves-derived oil of 
  <span class="italic">F. tingitana</span> on breast, liver, and cervical carcinoma cell line, respectively, which is comparable to the standard cytotoxic drug, doxorubicin [
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T4" href="#T4">Table 4</a>]. Lower effects were obtained on testing the flower-derived oil. The previous studies revealed that many essential oil components exhibited cytotoxic activity. The cytotoxic effect of the leaves-derived oil could be attributed to its relatively high content of oxygenated sesquiterpenes (46.5%) including γ-cadinol (13.8%) which has been reported to exert cytotoxic activity.[
  <a rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref55">55</a>] Alpha-cadinol has been reported to have cytotoxicity against human colon adenocarcinoma cell line HT-29.[
  <a rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref56">56</a>] Compounds which are similar in structure (oxygenated sesquiterpenes) as eudesmol and γ-cadinol may possess the same effect. α-Cadinol was said to act as antifungal agent[
  <a rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref57">57</a>] and as hepatoprotective[
  <a rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref58">58</a>] and was proposed as a possible remedy for drug–resistant–tuberculosis.[
  <a rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref59">59</a>]
 </p>
</sec>
