<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIALS AND METHODS</div>
 <sec id="sec2-1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Samples of the flower and leaves of 
   <span class="italic">F. tingitana</span> L., collected in April 2013 from Mislata city which far away from Tripoli by 100 km. Libya, and identified by Dr. Reem Samir Hamdy, Lecturer of Plant Taxonomy, Botany Department, Faculty of Science, Cairo University, Giza, Egypt. A specimen of the plant was deposited at the Faculty of Pharmacy, Cairo University as a reference material (2142013).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Preparation, characterization, and analysis of the essential oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The flower and leaves of 
   <span class="italic">F. tingitana</span> L. (500 g) of each were subjected to hydrodistillation. The percentage yield was calculated on fresh weight basis according to the Egyptian Pharmacopœia (2005).[
   <a rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref27">27</a>] The essential oil was dried over anhydrous sodium sulfate and kept refrigerated until analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample preparation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aliquots (5 μl, each) of the dehydrated essential oils were, separately, mixed with approximately 1 ml of CH
   <sub>2</sub>Cl
   <sub>2</sub> in autosampler vials.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography/mass spectrometry analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography/mass spectrometry (GC/MS) analysis of the essential oil was performed using a Thermo Trace GC 2000 (Thermo Quest, TX, USA)/MS Finnigan mat SSQ7000 system. The instrument was equipped with a DB-5 column (30m × 0.25 mm i.d., 0.25 μm film thickness); J&amp;W Scientific, USA.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Operating conditions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Injection volume, 1 μl of CH
   <sub>2</sub>Cl
   <sub>2</sub> solution of tested samples; oven temperature programming: initial temperature, 40°C (isothermal for 3 min), then increased (4°C/min) to 160°C, followed by further increased to final temperature 280°C (10°C/min); injection temperature: 220°C carrier gas: helium at a flow rate of 1 ml/min; mass spectrometer, electronic ionization mode; ion source, 70 eV; mass range: 40–500 amu.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identification of the essential oil constituents</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This was achieved by library search on a Wiley 275 L GC/MS database, observed Kovats index and by comparing the retention indices and mass fragmentation patterns to those of the available references as well as of published data.[
   <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">28</a>] The quantitative estimation was carried out by peak area measurement. A series of authentic 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes was subjected to GC under the same experimental conditions, and the retention indices of the oil constituents were calculated. The individual components were determined by computerized peak area measurement. Compounds of the essential oil, their retention indices, and relative percentage composition are compiled [Tables 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">1</a> and 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T2" href="#T2">2</a>].
  </p>
  <div id="T1" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Yield and physical characters of volatile oil of 
     <span class="italic">Ferula tingitana</span> L
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="PM-13-446-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="T2" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Identified components in the hydrodistilled essential oil of flower and leaves of 
     <span class="italic">Ferula tingitana</span> L
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="PM-13-446-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evaluation of antimicrobial activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The disc agar diffusion method[
   <a rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref29">29</a>] was adopted, and zone of inhibitions measured in mm. Results are recorded in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">Table 3</a>. Potencies relative to the appropriate antibiotic tetracycline and amphotericin B are represented in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">Table 3</a>.
  </p>
  <div id="T3" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Results of the antimicrobial testing of the essential oil of 
     <span class="italic">Ferula tingitana</span> L
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="PM-13-446-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microorganisms, culture media, and standard antimicrobial agents</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antimicrobial activity was performed against a set of 8 representative Gram-positive and negative bacterial and two fungal strains of standard properties [
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">Table 3</a>]. These were maintained in the Micro Analytical Center, Faculty of Science, Cairo University. The tested Gram-positive bacteria were (
   <span class="italic">Bacillus subtilis</span> ATCC 6051, 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> ATCC 12600 and 
   <span class="italic">Streptococcus faecalis</span> ATCC 19433). The Gram-negative bacteria included (
   <span class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> ATCC 10145, 
   <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span> ATCC 11775, and 
   <span class="italic">Neisseria gonorrhea</span> ATCC 19424), and fungi (
   <span class="italic">Aspergillus flavus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span> ATCC 26555). The tested bacteria were grown on nutrient agar (Oxoid, England) and fungi on Sabouraud's glucose agar (Oxoid, England). Tetracycline (Oxoid, UK) and Amphotericin B (Sigma Chemical Co., St. Louis, MO, USA) were used as standard antibacterial and antifungal agents.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antimicrobial assay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The prepared essential oil of the flower and leaves were separately tested against the selected strains at concentration of 20 mg/ml adopting the disc agar diffusion method.[
   <a rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref29">29</a>] Discs were impregnated with tetracycline and amphotericin B as antibacterial and antifungal standards, respectively. Test solutions were prepared by dissolving in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) at a concentration of 20 mg/ml; aliquots, 10 ml each, were aseptically transferred into sterile discs of Whatman filter paper 8 mm diameter. Results are recorded [
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">Table 3</a>] as a Mean zone of inhibition in mm.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evaluation of cytotoxic activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Potential cytotoxicity of the essential oils of 
   <span class="italic">F. tingitana</span> was tested using sulforhodamine B (SRB) method of Skehan 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
   <a rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref30">30</a>
   <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">31</a>
   <a rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref32">32</a>] Human tumor cell lines: hormone-responsive breast (MCF7), cervical (HeLa), and liver carcinoma (HePG2) were used and maintained in the laboratory of the Cancer Biology Department of National Cancer Institute, Cairo, Egypt.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">In vitro</span> cytotoxicity screening
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Samples of flower-, leaves-derived oil at different concentrations (0.0–50.0 μg/ml) in DMSO were tested for cytotoxicity, against the aforementioned human tumor cell lines adopting SRB stain assay. The relation between surviving fractions and oil concentration was plotted to get the survival curve of each tumor cell line after the application of the specific concentration. The results were compared to those of the standard cytotoxic drug, doxorubicin (10 mg Adriamycin hydrochloride, in 5 ml intravenous injection, Pharmacia, Italy) at the same concentrations. The dose of the test solutions which reduces survival to 50% (IC
   <sub>50</sub>) was calculated [
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T4" href="#T4">Table 4</a>].
  </p>
  <div id="T4" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>IC50% of the essential oil of flower and leaves of 
     <span class="italic">Ferula tingitana</span> L. compared to standard doxorubicin
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="PM-13-446-g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
</sec>
