<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>
   <bold>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST:</bold> Dr Jakhongir F. Alidjanov reports on fees from Bionorica SE and OM-Pharma/Vifor for his consultancy work.
  </p>
  <p>Dr Andre Overesch, Dr Dimitri Abramov-Sommariva, Dr Martina Hoeller, and Dr Hubert Steindl are employees of Bionorica SE, Neumarkt, Germany.</p>
  <p>Dr Florian M. Wagenlehner reports personal fees and other from Bionorica, during the conduct of the study; personal fees and other from Achaogen, personal fees from AstraZeneca, personal fees and other from Bionorica, other from Enteris BioPharma, other from Helperby Therapeutics, personal fees from Janssen, personal fees from LeoPharma, personal fees from MerLion, personal fees from MSD, personal fees and other from OM Pharma/Vifor Pharma, personal fees from Pfizer, personal fees from RosenPharma, personal fees and other from Shionogi, personal fees from VenatoRx, personal fees from GSK, other from Deutsches Zentrum für Infektionsforschung (DZIF) (Giessen-Marburg-Langen site), outside the submitted work.</p>
  <p>Dr Kurt G. Naber reports personal fees from Adamed, personal fees from Allecra, personal fees from Apogepha, personal fees from Aristo, personal fees from Bionorica, personal fees from Biomerieux, personal fees from Enteris, personal fees from GlaxoSmithKline, personal fees from Gruenenthal Mexico, personal fees from Helperby, personal fees from MerLIon, personal fees from Medice, non-financial support from Mission Pharmacal, personal fees from MSD Sharp &amp; Dohme, personal fees from OM Pharma/Vifor, personal fees from Paratek, personal fees from Roche, personal fees from Saxonia, personal fees from Zambon, during the conduct of the study.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con">
  <p>
   <bold>AUTHORS' CONTRIBUTIONS:</bold>
   <list list-type="simple">
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Research conception and design:</bold> all authors.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Data acquisition:</bold> Andre Overesch, Dimitri Abramov-Sommariva, Martina Hoeller, and Hubert Steindl.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Statistical analysis:</bold> Jakhongir F. Alidjanov, Andre Overesch, and Hubert Steindl.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Data analysis and interpretation:</bold> all authors.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold> Jakhongir F. Alidjanov, Andre Overesch, Martina Hoeller, and Kurt G. Naber.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Critical revision of the manuscript:</bold> all authors.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Administrative, technical, or material support:</bold> Dimitri Abramov-Sommariva and Martina Hoeller.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Supervision:</bold> Dimitri Abramov-Sommariva, Hubert Steindl, Florian M. Wagenlehner, and Kurt G. Naber.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Approval of the final manuscript:</bold> all authors.
     </p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <p>Jakhongir F. Alidjanov and Andre Overesch (shared first authorship), Florian M. Wagenlehner and Kurt G. Naber (shared last authorship). Andre Overesch, Dimitri Abramov-Sommariva, Martina Hoeller, and Hubert Steindl are employees of Bionorica SE.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Copyright and Translations of the ACSS in other languages:</bold> The ACSS is copyrighted by the Certificate of Deposit of Intellectual Property in the Fundamental Library of Academy of Sciences of the Republic of Uzbekistan, Tashkent (Registration number 2463; 26 August 2015) and the Certificate of the International Online Copyright Office, European Depository, Berlin, Germany (Nr. EU-01-000764; 21 October 2015). The rightsholders are Jakhongir Fatikhovich Alidjanov (Uzbekistan), Ozoda Takhirovna Alidjanova (Uzbekistan), Adrian Martin Erich Pilatz (Germany), Kurt Guenther Naber (Germany), and Florian Martin Erich Wagenlehner (Germany).
  </p>
  <p>Translations of the ACSS in other languages are available on the website: 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.acss.world/downloads.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.acss.world/downloads.html</ext-link>.
  </p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
