<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Antioxidants are compounds that can prevent or slow down oxidation reactions producing free radicals, that ultimately cause cell damage in organisms. Oxidative stress, which is related with an increased formation of oxidizing species or a significant reduction of natural antioxidant levels, is involved in different human diseases (cellular necrosis, cardiovascular disease, cancer, neurological disorder, ageing) [
 <xref rid="B109-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Non-toxic antioxidants from natural sources, particularly medicinal plants, are known to prevent oxidative damage due to their richness in polyphenolics and bioactive compounds [
 <xref rid="B110-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>,
 <xref rid="B112-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,
 <xref rid="B113-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. The antioxidant activity of 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> has been reported by various authors [
 <xref rid="B115-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. Cordycepin has been reported to significantly increase the levels of antioxidant enzymes such as superoxide dismutase and glutathione peroxidase activities in 6-OHDA-treated cells. Moreover, the results showed that cordycepin prevents 6-OHDA-induced neurotoxicity in adrenal pheochromocytoma cells (PC12 cells) via its potent antioxidant action [
 <xref rid="B117-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. In addition, cordycepin containing protein-bound polysaccharide causes a reduction in lipid peroxidation as well as an increase in the activity of antioxidant enzymes in the liver like catalase and superoxide dismutase [
 <xref rid="B118-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. Other authors have suggested the potential of cordycepin in reducing lipid peroxidation in mouse liver [
 <xref rid="B119-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. Therefore, per these reports, cordycepin could be considered as a potential antioxidant. A few studies have even suggested that the antioxidant potential of 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> is close to that of ascorbic acid [
 <xref rid="B120-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>].
</p>
