<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Curdione, is a monoterpene isolated from the essential oils of turmeric and has been clinically used for the treatment of cervical cancer in China. Prostaglandins are known to promote carcinogenic processes and curdione has been found exorbitantly efficient enough to inhibit prostaglandin biosynthetic enzyme cyclooxygenase. This facilitated the repression of COX-2 mRNA expression and inhibition of the fabrication of prostaglandin (PG)-E2 in the lipopolysaccharide (LPS) stimulated (RAW-264.7) mouse macrophages in a dose-dependent manner [
 <xref rid="B107-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">107</xref>]. Kong et al. studied MCF-7 and MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cell proliferation both alone, as well as in combination to find that an unpredictable intra herb interaction exist that should be considered while formulating curdione, germacrone, and furanodiene, isolated from 
 <italic class="italic">C. wenyujin</italic>. In addition, germacrone and curdione showed no antiproliferative activity while furanodiene reacted oppositely, which were identified with the changes in mitochondrial membrane and morphological changes. Moreover, germacrone enhanced antiproliferative effect of furanodiene. Curdione showed no effect on antiproliferative effect of furanodiene, however, had some combined effects on the antiproliferative effect of germacrone and furanodiene [
 <xref rid="B108-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">108</xref>]. Further, the inhibition of breast cancer cell proliferation in nude xenograft mouse elucidated the anticancer effect of curdione in a dose-dependent manner. This study utilized various tests like Jc-I assay, MTT, flow cyclometry, and Western blot and analyzed the cleavage of protein like caspase3 and caspase 9, followed by the increase in Bax and impairment of mitochondrial membrane potential, that brought about apoptosis in a concentration-dependent manner. These observations concluded that curdione induces apoptosis and is an effective chemotherapeutic agent [
 <xref rid="B109-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">109</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biomolecules-09-00013-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>I). Li et al. successfully validated the pharmacokinetic parameters of curdione and curcumol from 
 <italic class="italic">C. longa</italic> extracts in rat’s blood and liver by micro-dialysis coupled with rapid resolution tandem mass spectrometry and liquid chromatography (RRLC). Thus, this pharmacokinetic study provided a promising and useful platform for future studies related to its application in anticancer and anti-inflammatory activities [
 <xref rid="B110-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">110</xref>]. Hence, these studies suggest that curdione give promising results when taken with other non-curcuminoids. Additionally, they work excellently on breast cancer cells, which provide knowledge on their predominant anticancer potential.
</p>
