<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pathological changes in the liver</div>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Table 
  <a rid="Tab7" ref-type="table" href="#Tab7">7</a> includes the results of the histopathological examination of the livers. The results indicated that the livers of rats fed a high-fat diet were severely degenerated compared with the rats in the NC group. Liver histopathological examinations showed that there were different extents of cell steatosis in the hepatic lobules in rats from the groups fed a high-fat diet. In the NC group rats, there were no lipid droplets distributed in the hepatic lobule, and no cell steatosis or necrosis was found, meaning that the integrity of the lobular structure was maintained. The rats in the HFD-A and HFD-B groups, however, suffered from cell steatosis of the hepatic lobule, cell puffing, and inflammatory cell infiltration in the hepatic lobule and portal area, as shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>. It could therefore be concluded from Table 
  <a rid="Tab7" ref-type="table" href="#Tab7">7</a> and Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> that the garlic oil and onion oil alleviated the hepatic steatosis of the hyperlipidemia model in rats.
  <div id="Tab7" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 7</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The histopathologic observations of the liver of rats under a microscope (HE staining)</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Group</th>
      <th rowspan="2">N</th>
      <th colspan="4">Numbers for different situations of steatosis</th>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <th/>
      <th>Null
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </th>
      <th>Little
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </th>
      <th>Middle
       <span class="sup">c</span>
      </th>
      <th>Serious
       <span class="sup">d</span>
      </th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>HFD-A</td>
      <td>11</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>8</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>HFD-B</td>
      <td>11</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>9</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>GO-L</td>
      <td>10</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>6</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>GO-M</td>
      <td>12</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>5</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>GO-H</td>
      <td>11</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>2</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>OO-L</td>
      <td>12</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>5</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>OO-H</td>
      <td>12</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>6</td>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>2</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>
     <span class="sup">a</span>“Null” means that the liver has no apparent disease
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="sup">b</span>“Little” means that cell steatosis of the hepatic lobule is within 25%
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="sup">c</span>“Middle” means that cell steatosis of the hepatic lobule is within 50%
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="sup">d</span>“Serious” means that cell steatosis of the hepatic lobule is greater than 50%
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Effects of garlic essential oil and onion essential oil on the liver shown by histological analysis of livers from rats in different groups (liver sections were stained with hematoxylin and eosin; magnification_400)</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12986_2018_275_Fig1_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
