<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RO was shown to reduce blood pressure in ways that could be related to inhibition and/or modulation of angiotensin-converting enzyme or promotion of NO production and downregulation of endothelin-1 production (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Karthik et al., 2011</xref>). The mechanisms involved in the endothelium-dependent vasodilating effect of RO remain unknown. Nevertheless, this effect can be explained by the fact that RO is a polyphenolic compound that has a vasodilating activity, through activation of NO pathway, EDHF, and prostacyclin (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Fernandes et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Ersoy et al., 2008</xref>). There is evidence claiming that RO can improve both cardiovascular and metabolic problems in hypertensive conditions, which is confirmed by the results of a study that evaluated the acute and chronic effects of RO in hypertensive rats. The acute and chronic treatment with RO reduced blood pressure and fasting plasma glucose levels, while the acute RA treatment increased skeletal muscle glucose transport activity along with extracellular signal–regulated kinase activity (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">Prasannarong et al., 2019</xref>). Cardioprotective effects of the treatment with RO were also shown in a model of doxorubicin-induced cardiotoxicity and pressure overload–induced cardiac dysfunction in mice. Possible explanation of these effects may be reflected in the fact that RA alleviates cardiomyocyte apoptosis via cardiac fibroblast (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Preconditioning with RO could strongly prevent cardiac hypertrophy, lipid peroxidation, weakness in myocardial contractility and relaxation, and stretch-induced arrhythmias after acute myocardial infarction induced by supramaximal administration of isoproterenol in rats. The cardioprotective effect of RO, which was reflected through the reduction of cardiac hypertrophy, may be related to the inhibition of the isoproterenol-induced cardiac hyperactivity, resulting in inhibition of oxidative stress and lipid peroxidation (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Javidanpour et al., 2018</xref>). In addition, 2 week application of RO exerted the beneficial effects on heart electrophysiology of rats with myocardial infarction. Namely, RO induced QRS complex voltage increment and dramatic lowering of ST elevation, especially via the highest dose applied (30 mg/kg) compared to non-treated animals with myocardial infarction. These results suggest the protective effect of RO on plasma membrane. RO pretreatment diminishes almost all harmful heart alterations in isoproterenol-induced myocardial infarction. This refers to antioxidants boosting antioxidant activity and up-regulation of gene expression of RyR2 and SERCA2, which are involved in Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> homeostasis and possibly through RA antiadrenergic effect (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Javidanpour et al., 2017</xref>). Considering these facts, application of RO isolated from MO may also be a useful tool for cardioprotection. Nonetheless, the synergistic action of all compounds present in MOE may provide even better effects.
</p>
