<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Ecotype of 
 <italic class="italic">A. thaliana</italic> plant seeds Columbia-0 (Col-0) were pre-germinated by adding 1 ml sterilized water on some seed at 1.5 ml Eppendorf tube, then incubated at 4 °C for three days at the refrigerator. After that 
 <italic class="italic">A. thaliana</italic> seeds had been growing in our Key Lab growth chamber at a temperature of 22 °C day/20 °C night with humidity of 50–70%, and photoperiod at 16 h day/8 h night, with a light density of 100–150 μmoles m 
 <sup class="sup">−</sup>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> s 
 <sup class="sup">−</sup>
 <sup class="sup">1</sup> using fluorescent bulbs. After 2 months plants were ready for floral-dip transformation, and one week after the primary inflorescences were clipped. Plant watering was stopped 3 days prior to transformation for improved and increase the transformation efficiency. In addition, the constructs of pB2GW7 vectors with all inserted genes were introduced into 
 <italic class="italic">Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain EHA105 by direct electroporation. Recombinant 
 <italic class="italic">A. tumefaciens</italic> was grown for 2 days at 28 °C in solid LB media supplemented with 50 μg/ml each of rifampicin and spectinomycin. An individual colony of each sample was inoculated into 1.0 ml of liquid medium and grown at 28 °C under 200 rpm agitation overnight with the same media composition. After 24 h, 1.0 ml of each sample of liquid medium was transferred to a 250-ml conical flask containing 50 ml of LB media supplemented with the same compositions; the samples were grown at 28 °C in a shaker overnight until an optical density of 0.6–8.0 (OD 600) was reached. Overnight cell cultures were harvested by centrifugation at 5,000 rpm for 10 min at 4 °C, and the pellet was resuspended in the floral-dip inoculation medium contained 5% sucrose and 0.05% Silwet. 
 <italic class="italic">A. thaliana</italic> was transformed by soaked the secondary inflorescences in the inoculation medium and stirred gently to allow the intake of 
 <italic class="italic">Agrobacterium</italic> harbouring the pB2GW7 vector into the flower gynoecium. The transformed plants were kept in the dark and wrapped with plastic cover overnight to maintain humidity. The next day, the plants were returned back to their normal growth conditions. The transformation was repeated after 1 week to increase the transformation efficiency. Plants were grown for additional 4–5 weeks until all of the siliques became brown and dry. The seeds were harvested and stored at 4 °C under desiccation.
 <xref rid="dsy028-B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">15</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="dsy028-B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">16</sup>
 </xref> BASTA was used for selection of transformant seedlings which were also confirmed with PCR for positive transgenic lines, more than 10 positive plant lines from each gene were analysed for terpenoid profiling and target gene expression.
</p>
