<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Two mechanisms by which the components of olive oil modulate the endothelial activation were proposed in respect of their antioxidant activity, namely (i) direct inhibition and/or scavenging of ROS, and (ii) activating cellular signaling pathways that would provide the immune defenses against OS (
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>). A number of authors reported 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> experiments evaluating and confirming the antioxidant and scavenging activities of olive oil and its isolated constituents (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>). Thus, it was shown that oleuropein is a potent antioxidant and scavenger for superoxide (O2–) anion in neutrophils (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>). The reduction in free radical formation by oleuropein arises through its ability to chelate metal ions, such as Cu
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> and Fe
 <sup class="sup">3+</sup>, which catalyze reactions generating free radicals as well as via its inhibitory capacity on several inflammatory enzymes like lipoxygenases (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>). Besides, by inhibiting the production of O2– as well as other ROS, olive oil components protected endothelial cells from monocyte adhesion (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>). Some authors described that hydroxytyrosol inhibited the rapid release of ROS (O2– anion and hydrogen peroxide) from human granulocytes and monocytes, and also, the production of pro-inflammatory mediators in LPS-stimulated RAW 264.7 macrophages (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>). Moreover, β-sitosterol was described inhibiting intracellular release of ROS (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>). Also, β-sitosterol decreased O2– radical levels modulating the function of antioxidant enzymes, such as Mn superoxide dismutase and glutathione peroxidase, the important antioxidant defense enzymes (
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">97</xref>). Interestingly, the polyphenol actions became more potent in the presence of β-sitosterol. A synergistic effect of polyphenols of olive oil and wine and β-sitosterol of olive oil was observed that resulted in the modulation of the oxidative effects of oxLDL and prostaglandin E2 (PGE2) synthesis in RAW 264.7 macrophages (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">98</xref>). Moreover, tocopherols and phenolic compounds oleuropein and hydroxytyrosol showed potent antioxidant activity by scavenging intracellular ROS and free nitric oxide, reducing the formation of other powerful oxidants such as peroxynitrite (
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>). In addition, olive oil compounds can modulate eNOS uncoupling by scavenging free radicals, hence preventing oxidative stress and improving vascular endothelial dysfunction (
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>).
</p>
