<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A number of studies revealed that olive oil phenolic compounds can amend endothelial function by increasing NOS expression levels, including iNOS and eNOS, hence increasing nitric oxide bioavailability. Thus, oleuropein has both the ability to scavenge nitric oxide and trigger an increase in iNOS expression in cells (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>). Accordingly, it was found that oleuropein increased the production of nitric oxide in macrophages stimulated with LPS through the induction of iNOS expression, thus increasing the functional activity of these immunocompetent cells (
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>). Moreover, a group of researchers pointed out that consumption of olive oil rich in triterpenes induced an increase in eNOS expression levels and improved endothelial function in spontaneously hypertensive rats, compared to normotensive controls (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>). Similarly, prolonged intake of diets rich in oleanolic acid contained in pomace olive oil improved endothelial dysfunction in the aorta of spontaneously hypertensive rats by mechanisms associated with the enhanced eNOS expression (
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>). Also, oleic acid was able to induce nitric oxide-dependent endothelial vasorelaxation in the aorta of normotensive and hypertensive rats 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>). In addition, several studies showed that regular ingestion of oleanolic acid can lead to nitric oxide release by calcium-independent phosphorylation of eNOS (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>). Moreover, oral hydroxytyrosol administration was tested on nitric oxide production and platelet function in animal models with rats. The study results showed that an oral hydroxytyrosol administration of 100 mg/kg/day increased vascular nitric oxide release by up to 34.2% (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.01) and inhibited platelet aggregation for 50% at an inhibitory dose of 48.25 mg/day (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), compared to the control group (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>). However, animal dose translation to humans permitted the assumption that the 350 effective hydroxytyrosol doses tested would be above the expected daily intake of olive oil (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>).
</p>
