<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="abstract" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <sec id="st1" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Objective:</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of this study is to determine the phytochemical composition, antifungal activity of 
   <span class="italic">Mentha piperita</span> essential oil (MPE) against 
   <span class="italic">Fusarium sporotrichioides</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st2" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods:</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The phytochemical composition was conducted by gas chromatography mass spectrometry (GC MS) analysis and mycelia growth inhibition was determined by minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) and minimum fungicidal concentration (MFC), the morphological characterization was observed by scanning electron microscopy. Finally, the membrane permeability was determined by the release of extracellular constituents, pH, and total lipid content.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st3" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Result:</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In GC MS analysis, 22 metabolites were identified such as menthol, l menthone, pulegone, piperitone, caryophyllene, menthol acetate, etc. The antifungal activity against targeted pathogen, with MIC and MFC 500 μg/mL and 1000 μg/mL, respectively. The MPE altered the morphology of 
   <span class="italic">F. sporotrichoides</span> hyphae with the loss of cytoplasm content and contorted the mycelia. The increasing concentration of MPE showed increase in membrane permeability of 
   <span class="italic">F. sporotrichoides</span> as evidenced by the release of extracellular constituents and pH with the disruption of cell membrane indicating decrease in lipid content of 
   <span class="italic">F. sporotrichoides</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st4" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion:</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observed results showed that MPE exhibited promising new antifungal agent against 
   <span class="italic">Fusarium sporotrichioides</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st5" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SUMMARY</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>
      <span class="italic">F. sporotrichioides</span>, filamentous fungi contaminate to corn and corn--based products
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>
      <span class="italic">F. sporotrichioides</span> mainly responsible for the production of T-2 toxin
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Phytochemical composition was conducted by gas chromatography--mass spectrometry analysis</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>
      <span class="italic">Mentha piperita</span> essential oil (MPE) is commonly known as peppermint
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>The 
      <span class="italic">F. sporotrichioides</span> growth was inhibited by MPE (minimum inhibitory concentration, minimum fungicidal concentration)
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Morphological observation by scanning electron microscope.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span xlink:href="PR-9-74-g001.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="bold">Abbreviations Used</span>: Cfu: Colony forming unit; DMSO: Dimethyl sulfoxide, °C: Degree celsius; 
   <span class="italic">F. Sporotrichoides</span>: 
   <span class="italic">Fusarium sporotrichioides</span>; EOs: Essential oils; M: Molar, g: Gram/gravity, mg: Milligram; μg: Microgram, ml: Milliliter; mm: Millimeter, min: Minutes; 
   <span class="italic">M. piperita</span>: 
   <span class="italic">Mentha piperita</span>, MIC: Minimum inhibitory concentration; MFC: Minimum fungicidal concentration; MAE: 
   <span class="italic">Mentha arvensis</span> essential oil; Na
   <sub>2</sub>SO
   <sub>4</sub>: Sodium sulfate; pH: Potential Hydrogen; PDB: Potato Dextrose Broth; SEM: Scanning electron microscope
  </p>
 </sec>
</div>
