<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Changes in muscle development in fish are a biological reality affected by both external and endogenous hormonal influences, and fish weights correlate with high mRNA expression of 
 <italic>IGF-1</italic> and 
 <italic>GH</italic> in fish under the same conditions [
 <xref rid="B34-animals-11-01431" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-animals-11-01431" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Muscle development is inversely proportional to fish growth. In this study, the gene expression showed upregulated 
 <italic>GH</italic> and 
 <italic>IGF-1</italic> results in carp muscle tissue. A previous study conducted by [
 <xref rid="B36-animals-11-01431" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] reported high levels of 
 <italic>IGF-1</italic> in liver tissue fish fed with 400 and 600 ppm limonene-supplemented diets. As a different finding, our results showed decrease in 
 <italic>GH</italic> and 
 <italic>IGF-1</italic> expression in muscle tissue due to increasing NO levels in diets. This suggests that using 0.25 percent NO in diets enhances the potency of NO and improves the common carp’s growth efficiency in a dose-dependent manner. Similarly, changes in gene expression levels depending on the dose were reported by [
 <xref rid="B37-animals-11-01431" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] when common carp were fed with olive leaf extract. In animals, cytokines are markers of inflammation, and stress causes inflammation in fish [
 <xref rid="B38-animals-11-01431" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The present results clearly showed that dietary NO had anti-inflammatory effects on common carp fed with 0.25% supplemented diets as an indicator of boosted health. In general, the incorporation of immunostimulants such as essential oil or extract in diets of different fish species can beneficially improve the expression of 
 <italic>IL-8 IL-1β</italic> and 
 <italic>TNF-α</italic> [
 <xref rid="B39-animals-11-01431" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-animals-11-01431" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-animals-11-01431" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. These findings are not surprising, since antioxidant compounds in herbal products have been shown to shield cells from the adverse effects of reactive oxygen species such as superoxide, peroxyl radicals, hydroxyl radicals and peroxynitrite [
 <xref rid="B42-animals-11-01431" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].
</p>
