<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plant invasions occur across a wide range of bioclimatic conditions. In relatively isolated montane tropical rainforest in Hawaii Volcanoes National Park, the N-fixing tree 
 <italic>Morella faya</italic> (originally from the Azores, Canary Islands and Madeira) invades young volcanic substrates where the growth of native plants (e.g., 
 <italic>Metrosideros polymorpha</italic>) is limited by low N availability [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12-sensors-09-04869">12</xref>]. 
 <italic>Morella faya</italic> significantly enhances soil N availability and alters fundamental ecosystem processes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13-sensors-09-04869">13</xref>]. In the Southwest USA, invasions by African grasses have had substantial impacts on drylands during the past century [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14-sensors-09-04869">14</xref>]. 
 <italic>Eragrostis lehmanniana</italic>, a tufted perennial South African bunchgrass, and one of the most troublesome species in this arid region, was introduced into Arizona in 1932 to prevent soil erosion and to provide forage for livestock [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15-sensors-09-04869">15</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16-sensors-09-04869">16</xref>]. By 1984, 
 <italic>E. lehmanniana</italic> had proliferated throughout 1,450 km
 <sup>2</sup> of drylands, yet only half of the area was directly sown [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17-sensors-09-04869">17</xref>]. An environmental modeling study indicated that 
 <italic>E. lehmanniana</italic> could potentially inhabit over 70,000 km
 <sup>2</sup> in the Southwest USA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18-sensors-09-04869">18</xref>]. In the arctic alpine eco-region of Alaska, despite harsh climatic conditions and low densities of human population and anthropogenic perturbations, 59 non-native plants are recorded and three of them (
 <italic>Poa pratensis</italic>, 
 <italic>Trifolium hybridum</italic>, 
 <italic>Trifolium repens</italic>) are widely distributed and considered highly invasive [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19-sensors-09-04869">19</xref>].
</p>
