<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="fsn3918-abs-0001" class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Abstract</title>
 <p class="p">
  <italic class="italic">Moringa oleifera</italic> is a tropical plant with high nutritional and medicinal value. Recent studies have reported its remarkable effects in inflammatory, antioxidative, and anti‐diabetes modulations, but there was no significant report on its role in animal breeding. In this study, we investigated the effects of dietary 
  <italic class="italic">Moringa oleifera</italic> leaf (MOL) on reproductive performances in mice. We studied the reproductive performance of mice for six consecutive gestations. Mice fed with 4% MOL diet showed improved litter size, litter birth weight, and litter survivals until weaning age compared to control mice fed with normal diet (
  <italic class="italic">p </italic>&lt;
  <italic class="italic"> </italic>0.05). Mice fed with MOL diet did not change weight and organ coefficients. Serum malondialdehyde (MDA) concentrations in both male and female mice were significantly decreased by dietary MOL (
  <italic class="italic">p </italic>&lt;
  <italic class="italic"> </italic>0.05), but glutathione peroxidase (GSH‐PX) and superoxide dismutase (SOD) were unchanged. For male, dietary MOL significantly reduced sperm abnormality rate (
  <italic class="italic">p </italic>&lt;
  <italic class="italic"> </italic>0.05) and Bcl2‐associated X protein (Bax) expression in testis (
  <italic class="italic">p </italic>&lt;
  <italic class="italic"> </italic>0.05), but did not affect serum testosterone and the expression levels of androgen receptor (AR), phosphoglycerate kinase 2 (Pgk2), protamine2 (Prm2), and B cell leukemia/lymphoma 2 (Bcl2) in testis. For female, dietary MOL did not change serum estradiol and the expressions of estrogen receptor beta (ERβ), Bcl2, Bax, and vascular endothelial growth factor receptor (VEGFR) in ovary. In summary, MOL increased litter size and antioxidant ability, reduced the rate of sperm abnormality and the expression of Bax. Therefore, MOL may serve as a functional feed addictive for improving animal reproductive performance.
 </p>
</abstract>
