<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The artemisinin compounds are mainly converted into dihydroartemisinin (DHA) directly after its absorption and are thus transformed to inactive metabolites by hepatic cytochrome P-450 and other systems for enzymes and the elimination half-life of DHA was about 45 min. The level of conversion to DHA varies between artemisinin derivatives as artemisinin itself is not metabolized to DHA, while artesunate is rapidly hydrolyzed to DHA in few minutes. Whereas arteether and artemether are more gradually converted to DHA [
 <xref rid="B142-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. The thujone metabolism was studied in vitro in mouse, rat, and human liver cells and in vivo in rabbits, mice, and pigs. Two neutral urinary metabolites have been reported as 3-β-hydroxy-α-thujane and 3-β-hydroxy-β-thujane following oral administration of a mixture of α- and β-thujone at a dose level of about 650–800 mg/kg body weight to male rabbits [
 <xref rid="B143-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. α-Thujone was rapidly metabolised to 7-hydroxy-α-thujone, 4-hydroxy-α-thujone, 4-hydroxy-β-thujone, two other hydroxy-thujones and 7,8-dehydro-α-thujone by mouse hepatic microsomes [
 <xref rid="B80-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Jiang et al. [
 <xref rid="B144-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>] as well as Abass et al. [
 <xref rid="B145-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>] stated that cytochrome P450 2D6 (CYP2D6) and CYP3A4 were the most effective cytochrome P450 (CP450) enzymes, generating 7-hydroxy-α-thujone, 4-hydroxy-thujone, suggesting that α-thujone is a liver blood–dependent compound. Artemisinin and artesunate can be administered in various dosing routes, including intramuscular (i.m.), rectal, intravenous (i.v.), and oral, while artemether can be used by i.m., oral, or rectal route. Medhi et al. [
 <xref rid="B146-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>] documented that the high first-pass metabolism is the key reason for poor oral bioavailability of artemisinin, artesunate and artemether, whereas artemether reaches peak levels in 2–6 h and artesunate reaches peak levels in only few minutes. They revealed that artesunate and artemether possess a moderate plasma protein binding ranging from 43 to 81.5 percent. Artesunate, as well as artemether, are thoroughly metabolized and converted to DHA with a plasma half-life of 1–2 h. Artenimol is another artemisinin metabolite [
 <xref rid="B147-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>]. Morris et al. [
 <xref rid="B148-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>] indicated that i.v. administration of artesunate yields a significantly higher C
 <sub>max</sub> than that observed with any other route of administration. They reported that the average clearance values of artesunate and DHA are 2–3 L/kg/hr and 0.5–1.5 L/kg/hr, respectively, with the approximate volume of 0.1–0.3 L/kg for artesunate and 0.5–1.0 L/kg for DHA, whereas the i.m. administration of artesunate showed high bioavailability. Intramuscular artesunate shows similar pharmacokinetics to IV artesunate, however, it produces lower C
 <sub>max</sub>, higher volume of distribution, and longer half-life values for artesunate, and longer T
 <sub>max</sub> values for DHA than IV administration [
 <xref rid="B149-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>]. Navaratnam et al. [
 <xref rid="B150-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>] recorded the pharmacokinetic parameters of rectal artesunate administration. They reported that rectal artesunate was similar to those obtained with oral administration, but artesunate T
 <sub>max</sub> is delayed and its half-life is extended. Moreover, the population pharmacokinetic analyses of artesunate, as well as DHA after oral and rectal administration of artesunate, indicate that weight and pregnancy are important indicators of the pharmacokinetics of DHA following artesunate administration [
 <xref rid="B148-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>].
</p>
