<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Ceramics have been used for a century in dentistry [
 <xref rid="B2-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. This group includes lithium disilicate ceramics (Li
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>Si
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">5</sub>) that were introduced in dentistry in 1998. In 2006, the IPS e.max CAD (Ivoclar Vivadent, Schaan, Liechtenstein) was introduced to the market, on which our study was carried out [
 <xref rid="B4-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. The blocks of this material are supplied in a pre-crystallized blue state. This ceramic contains metasilicate and lithium disilicate cores in its interior, which has excellent mechanical properties (flexural strength of 130 ± 30 MPa). In this state, the block can be easily milled, and then the structure is crystallized in a ceramic oven at 850 °C under vacuum for 20–25 min. During this process, the metasilicates dissolve, leaving lithium disilicate crystals that will be glazed, thus producing the desired color change. The material can then achieve a strength of up to 360 MPa according to the manufacturer [
 <xref rid="B4-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. This monolithic restoration material is not only suitable for the manufacture of implant crowns but also for the manufacture of inlays, onlays, crowns and veneers [
 <xref rid="B4-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. 
</p>
