<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">When selecting an implant material, it is important to take its biocompatibility into account, as well as its cellular behavior around these surfaces. After the osseointegration period of the implants, transgingival abutments are inserted to reshape the gingival tissues. The healing of both the bone tissue and soft tissues surrounding the various surfaces of the implants is essential for clinical success [
 <xref rid="B10-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. These prostheses connect the internal environment of the soft tissue with the oral environment, which is required to create a hermetic structure where cell proliferation is generated that prevents the passage of bacteria to the peri-implant zone [
 <xref rid="B8-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. After implant placement and insertion of implant abutments, the marginal gingiva is often irritated and has to regenerate. First of all, the wound healing starts with the inflammatory phase, which is followed by a proliferative phase, during which fibroblasts migrate, accumulate into the wound and produce a collagen matrix. This phase ends with the keratinocytes migration. These two cell types create the barrier. The cells’ adhesion depends on various components such as lipids, carbohidrats and bound proteins [
 <xref rid="B6-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-polymers-11-00744" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. 
</p>
