<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Currently, there are six main classes of modern medicines used all over the world for controlling blood glucose levels and two classes of injections [
 <xref rid="B12-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The tablets are known as biguanides (metformin), sulfonylureas, thiazolidinediones (glitazones), meglitinides (glinides), alpha-glucosidase inhibitors and DPP-4 inhibitors. The classes of medications given by injection are incretin mimetics and insulin [
 <xref rid="B17-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-biology-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Mechanisms of these medications have been reported. However, most modern drugs have many side effects and adverse effects, causing some serious medical problems during medication processing. Metformin is one medicine of biguanides which can inhibit the production of glucose molecules in the liver of human and increase insulin sensitivity. However, metformin also causes some main side effects such as gastrointestinal on the initial state, including dyspepsia, nausea and diarrhea. Metformin should be avoided in those with severely compromised renal function, de-compensated heart failure, severe liver disease other serious medical problems. The beneficial effects of thiazolidinediones in diabetes treatment are to improve the sensitivity of insulin, decrease insulin resistance and also decrease cardiovascular risks. However, the most common adverse effects of thiazolidinediones are weight gain and fluid retention, leading to peripheral edema and heart failure. The drugs were avoided to use for patients in similar situations, including heart failure and severe liver problems. Rosiglitazone may have cardiovascular risks, and increase the risk of a heart attack. Pioglitazone has not been available in some countries due to concerns about an increased risk for bladder cancer.
</p>
