<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>
  <italic>Datura metel</italic> Linn is used traditionally for the treatment of various diseases including relaxation of smooth muscles, relief of fever, as well as gastrointestinal disorder. This study deals with the bio-guided isolation of an active, amyrin-type triterpenoid, namely 3-oxo-6-
  <italic>β</italic>-hydroxy-
  <italic>β</italic>-amyrin (daturaolone; 
  <bold>1</bold>), from the chloroform fraction of 
  <italic>Datura metel</italic> L. (Angel’s trumpet) fruits and its gastrointestinal motility, antipyretic, and muscle relaxation effects in animal models. The chemical structure of daturaolone (
  <bold>1</bold>) was elucidated by NMR spectroscopy and crystallography techniques. The chloroform fraction and daturaolone (
  <bold>1</bold>) were assessed for the GIT motility test. Data exhibited in charcoal meal GI transit test show that chloroform fraction and daturaolone (
  <bold>1</bold>) significantly reduce GIT motility and increased intestinal transit time, comparable to the standard (atropine), a muscarinic receptor blocking agent. Muscle relaxant potency of the extract and daturaolone (
  <bold>1</bold>) was assessed in various animal paradigms. In the inclined plane screening test, it produced a significant (P &lt; 0.05) muscle relaxation potential in a dose-dependent manner after 30, 60, and 90 min. Likewise, the muscle relaxation potential of the extract and daturaolone (
  <bold>1</bold>) was strongly complemented by the chimney and traction test, representing a dominant effect after 60 min of sample administration. The chloroform fraction showed good antipyretic activity, and while daturaolone (
  <bold>1</bold>) exhibited significant activity at a higher dose, the maximum effect (84.64%) was at 20 mg/kg i.p. In acute toxicity screening test, the chloroform extract (100, 250, 500, and 1,000 mg/kg) and daturaolone (
  <bold>1</bold>) (5, 10, 20, and 50 mg/kg) were found safe. In conclusion, the chloroform extract and daturaolone (
  <bold>1</bold>) exhibited strong gastrointestinal motility, muscle relaxation, and antipyretic activity in different animal models and intestinally, was found safe at higher tested doses.
 </p>
</abstract>
