<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Being abundant in nature, isatins have been found in fluids and tissues of mammals, in addition to natural products that are produced by a range of bacteria, plants, and invertebrates
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref>. Isatin motif is a central privileged scaffold in a large number of bioactive natural and synthetic products that possess a spectrum of bioactivities such as antioxidant
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> and anticancer activities
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>12–14</sup>
 </xref>. On the other hand, the natural spirooxindole alkaloids were first isolated from plants of the 
 <italic>Apocynaceae</italic> and 
 <italic>Rubiacae</italic> families
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref>. Thereafter, spirooxindole motif stands out as a privileged heterospirocyclic scaffold that represents the core for a wide range of naturally isolated products such as alstonisine
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref>, horsfiline
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref>, coerulescine
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref>, and chitosenine
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> with diverse bioactivity profiles. Strychnofoline, spirotryprostatin A and spirotryprostatin B (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>) are other examples for natural spirooxindoles possessing anticancer activities
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref>. Isolation and identification of such bioactive spirooxindole alkaloids have inspired the researchers and paved the way to design and synthesise various spirooxindole-based small molecules with promising biological activities such as antioxidant
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref> and anticancer
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23–25</sup>
 </xref> activities.
</p>
