<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> seed oil used in the study by 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Asgary et al. (2013)</xref> contained predominantly terpenoids, including 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene 9) (37.3%) and thymoquinone 8) (13.7%). In other studies, 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> seeds extracts contained thymoquinone (8), which were standardized (0.05–0.06% extract weight) (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Enayatfard et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abbasnezhad et al., 2019</xref>). In fact, thymoquinone has demonstrated very good cardioprotective benefits and antihypertensive effects (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Enayatfard et al., 2018</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al. (2019)</xref> reported that thymoquinone has protective effects against cardiac damage in BALB/c mice via multiple mechanisms including reduction in intestinal histological alterations, suppressions of p62, NLRP3, IL-1β, TNF-α, caspase-1, IL-6 and 18, as well as MCP-1 expressions, inhibition of troponin-T levels in serum, enhancement in ATP, improvement in IL-10 and beclin 1 levels, and decrement in phosphatidylinositide 3-kinase level. Convincingly, thymoquinone effectively modulates pyroptosis, autophagy, and pro-inflammatory markers in cardiac stress (
 <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2019</xref>). Likewise, thymoquinone reverted doxorubicine-induced cardiotoxicity when administered to mice. of the administration of thymoquinone (10–20 mg/kg p.o) significantly ameliorated oxidative stress markers involving lipid peroxidation, creatine kinase (CK)-MB, lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), and AST. Alongside, meaningful improvement in antioxidant enzymes like SOD, catalase, glutathione reductase, and glutathione-S-transferase has also been noticed (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Alam et al., 2018</xref>). Another recent study reported by 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Atta et al. (2018)</xref> showed the protective role of thymoquinone on diabetes-caused cardiac complications in Wistar male rats. 
 <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al. (2018)</xref> reported that thymoquinone (8) provides shield against myocardial ischemia/reperfusion (I/R) injury in isolated rat hearts and neonatal rat cardiomyocytes models via: improving left ventricular function, lowering myocardial infarct size, attenuating mitochondrial oxidative damage, producing LDH, and lowering MDA levels and H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> concentrations, alongside improving antioxidant enzymes levels. Additionally, the cardioprotective role of this compound was also linked to the up-regulation of sirtuin 1 (SIRT1) expression and inhibition of p53 acetylation (
 <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al., 2018</xref>). Thymoquinone 8) showed prophylactic effect from myocardial I/R injury in Langendorff perfused rat hearts. It encouraged autophagy, favored cardiac function, lowered infarct size, LDH and CK-MB levels, and suppressed oxidative stress (
 <xref rid="B214" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2018</xref>). Finally, Salahshoor and their co-workers highlighted that the supplementation of thymoquinone (4.5–18 mg/kg) in mice significantly increased the mean diameter of central hepatic vein, blood serum NO level, and liver enzymes level, while it decreased the liver weight (
 <xref rid="B175" ref-type="bibr">Salahshoor et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
