<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The qualities of medicinal plants are determined by the combination of active substances that they synthesize. This in turn depends on both the species itself and environmental factors such as temperature, light condition, and water status [
 <xref rid="B21-plants-10-00045" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Regarding the influence of these factors on the flavonoid composition of plants from the genus 
 <italic>Scutellaria</italic>, the information in the available literature is mainly for species 
 <italic>baicalensis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B22-plants-10-00045" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-plants-10-00045" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-plants-10-00045" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. 
 <italic>Scutellaria</italic> species growing in different areas at the foot of the Rhodope Mountains have been selected for the present study. It is noteworthy that 
 <italic>S. altissima</italic> from both regions Mezek and Bachkovo and 
 <italic>S. galericulata</italic>(P) show a higher total amount of polyphenols and flavonoids compared to 
 <italic>S. albida</italic> (
 <xref rid="plants-10-00045-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The amount of polyphenols in the order of about 3000 mg GAE/100 g dry plant material obtained by us is similar to the results of Karolak et al., who studied cultured 
 <italic>S. altissima</italic> [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-10-00045" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, they detect twice as many flavonoids as us. Higher total polyphenolic and flavonoid content in the dry extract of 
 <italic>S. altissima</italic> compared to 
 <italic>S. albida</italic> was also found by Vaiday et al., who studied 16 
 <italic>Scutellaria</italic> species cultivated in Georgia [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-10-00045" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Şenol et al. studied 33 
 <italic>Scutellaria</italic> species from Turkey and reported a similar relationship between the amount of these biologically active substances in dry extracts of 
 <italic>S. galericulata</italic> and 
 <italic>S. albida</italic> [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-10-00045" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In support of this, our results for specific flavonoids (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00045-f001">Figure 1</xref>) show that only 
 <italic>S. altissima</italic>(M) and 
 <italic>S. galericulata</italic>(P) contain baicalein and almost 100 times more baicalin than the other samples tested. Interestingly, we recorded 31,250 µg/g baicalin in the aerial part of 
 <italic>S. altissima</italic>(M), while Karolak et al. found 22,570 µg/g in the roots and only 270 µg/g in the stems (shoots) from 2-year-old plants from 
 <italic>S. altissima</italic> [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-10-00045" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, scutellarin is the one that is characteristic and present in all species studied by us, regardless of their habitat. In the plant material of 
 <italic>S. albida</italic> from both regions, in addition to significant amounts of scutellarin, we also find the phenylethanoid glycoside-verbascoside, which was also identified by Matsa et al. [
 <xref rid="B27-plants-10-00045" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] as well as luteoline—determined by Bardakci et al. [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-10-00045" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] in 
 <italic>S. albida subsp velenovskyi</italic> from the Karabük region of Turkey.
</p>
