<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0035" class="p">For the antifungal bioassays, eight fungi were used: 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> Fresenius (ATCC 1022), 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus niger</italic> van Tieghem (ATCC 6275), 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus ochraceus</italic> Wilhelm (ATCC 12066), 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus versicolor</italic> (Vuillemin) Tiraboschi (ATCC 11730), 
 <italic class="italic">Penicillium funiculosum</italic> Thom (ATCC 8725), 
 <italic class="italic">Penicillium ochrochloron</italic> Biourge (ATCC 9112), 
 <italic class="italic">Penicillium verrucosum</italic> var. 
 <italic class="italic">cyclopium</italic> (Westling) Samson, Stolk &amp; Hadlok (food isolate), and 
 <italic class="italic">Trichoderma viride</italic> Pers. (IAM 5061). Microorganisms were obtained from the Mycological Laboratory, Institute for Biological Research ‘Siniša Stanković’, University of Belgrade, Serbia. Fungi were kept on malt extract agar (20 g/L) and the cultures stored at 4 °C and subcultured once a month.
 <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">19</sup>
 </xref> In order to investigate the antifungal activity of the compounds, a modified microdilution technique was used.
 <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0355" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref> The fungal spores were washed from the surface of agar plates with a sterile 0.85% saline solution containing 0.10% polysorbate-80 (v/v). The spore suspension was adjusted with sterile saline solution to a concentration of 1 × 10
 <sup class="sup">5</sup> in a final volume of 100 μL per well. The inocula were stored at 4 °C for further use. Dilutions of inocula were culture on solid malt agar to verify the absence of contamination and to check the validity of each inoculum. Minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) determinations were performed by a serial dilution technique using 96-well microtiter plates. The investigated compounds were dissolved in 5% dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) solution containing 0.1% polysorbate-80 (v/v) (1 mg/mL) and added in broth malt extract medium with inoculum. The microplates were incubated in a rotary shaker (160 rpm) for 72 h at 28 °C. The lowest concentrations without visible growth under the microscope light were defined as MIC. The minimum fungicidal concentration (MFC) was determined by serial subcultivation of 2 μL of tested compounds dissolved in culture medium and inoculated for 72 h onto microtiter plates containing 100 μL broth per well and with further incubation for 72 h at 28 °C. The lowest concentration with no visible growth was defined as MFC indicating 99.5% killing of the original inoculum. A solution of 5% DMSO was used as a negative control. Commercial fungicides bifonazole (Srbolek, Belgrade, Serbia) and ketoconazole (Zorkapharma, Šabac, Serbia) were used as positive controls (1–3500 μg/mL). All experiments were performed in duplicate and repeated three times.
</p>
