<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0470">Tuberculosis (TB) is one of the most infectious deadly diseases. The main aetiology of 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> (MTB) infection can occur in anyone without distinction amongst sex, age or localisation (
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Adaikkappan et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Akintola et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0775" ref-type="bibr">Sabran et al., 2016</xref>). In 1993, the World Health Organisation (WHO) declared TB as a public health emergency (
 <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Abdallah and Ali, 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0750" ref-type="bibr">Rennie et al., 2011</xref>). Even though TB is endemic in all countries worldwide, in developing countries, it is more likely to cause deaths than other infectious diseases (
 <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Akintola et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0360" ref-type="bibr">Gan et al., 2019</xref>). The WHO reported numerous deaths due to TB in 2018; approximately 1.2 million (1.1–1.3 million) out of the 10.0 million (9.0–11.1 million) people afflicted with this disease are found in endemic countries. In 2018, 53,620 cases of TB were identified in the Middle Eastern and North African (MENA) region; most of these cases were detected in three countries, namely, Iraq, Egypt and Sudan (
 <xref rid="b0950" ref-type="bibr">World Helath Organisation and Geneva, 2019</xref>). The MENA region includes the following countries: Algeria, Bahrain, Djibouti, Egypt, Iran, Iraq, Jordan, Kuwait, Lebanon, Libya, Malta, Morocco, Oman, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Syria, Tunisia, Turkey, United Arab Emirates, Palestine, Yemen, Ethiopia and Sudan; all of these countries have a long history of plant use for traditional medicine (
 <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Azaizeh et al., 2003</xref>). The estimated incidences of TB in the MENA region vary due to gaps in case detection because of under-reporting and under-diagnosis (
 <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed et al., 2016</xref>).
</p>
