<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7429836</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32796914</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">70949</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-70949-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Improving growth properties and phytochemical compounds of <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> (L.) medicinal plant using novel nitrogen slow release fertilizer under greenhouse conditions</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>Fatemeh</given-names></name><address><email>fa.ahmadi@urmia.ac.ir</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Samadi</surname><given-names>Abbas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>Amir</given-names></name><address><email>e.rahimi@urmia.ac.ir</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412763.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0442 8645</institution-id><institution>Department of Soil Science, Faculty of Agriculture, </institution><institution>Urmia University, </institution></institution-wrap>Urmia, Iran </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412763.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0442 8645</institution-id><institution>Department of Plant Production and Genetics, Faculty of Agriculture, </institution><institution>Urmia University, </institution></institution-wrap>Urmia, Iran </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>13842</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Medicinal plant production is most important than other agricultural plants due to their phytochemical compounds effects on human health. Paying attention to plant nutrition requirement is so important. In order to assess the effect of nitrate (NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>) dosage supplies from two types of fertilizers on growth and phytochemical properties of <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus, an experiment with completely simple design was carried out under greenhouse conditions. Two types of fertilizers (new invented nitrogen (N) slow release fertilizer and urea chemical fertilizer) at three dosages (50, 100, and 150&#x000a0;mM) were applied. Plant growth parameters and total phenolic (TPC), total flavonoids (TFC), polysaccarides content, essential oil content, caffeic acid derivatives, and anti-radical scavenging activities of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> were assessed. The results showed the significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.01) differences among treatments, both in growth and phytochemical properties. Using of N slow release, especially in 150&#x000a0;mM dosage, significantly increased all the plant growth and phytochemical properties. The dried <italic>E. purpurea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus contained more caftaric acid (max 12.56&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW) and chicoric acid (max 7.56&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW) than other derivatives. Despite the impact of heavy metals on yield and growth of <italic>E. purpurea</italic>, the concentration of all heavy metals and micronutrients (boron (B), cadmium (Cd), copper (Cu), iron (Fe), manganese (Mn), molybdenum (Mo), nickel (Ni), lead (Pb), and zinc (Zn)) in studied soil and fertilizer samples was less than United States Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA) limits of contamination. Based on the results, using of N slow release fertilizers can improve phytochemical properties of the plant due to its polymeric structure and can be a suitable substitution of chemical fertilizers, especially in medicinal plants growth.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Plant sciences</kwd><kwd>Environmental sciences</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Many of researchers are pay attention to herbal and medicinal plants as natural remedies due to their bioactive compounds recently<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> (L.) Moench is one of the most important medical plants of <italic>Asteraceae</italic> family with various pharmacological effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. The major three species of <italic>Echinacea</italic> are known as <italic>Echinacea angustifolia</italic>, <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic>, and <italic>Echinacea pallida</italic>. <italic>E. purpurea</italic> is native to much of the United States and its morphological properties are also known as purple coneflower with orange and cone-shaped flowering head that change to purple, rose, or white petals during June to September<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. It has a narrow leaves and three feet height stem with dark, thick and pungent rhizomata cum radicibus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. In the environment, <italic>E. purpurea</italic> grows randomically along water canals with low densities for affective harvest for commercial purposes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Comparing of other <italic>Echinacea</italic> species, <italic>E. purpurea</italic> is the most able species to adjust to new conditions. It is resistance to heat or cold weather conditions, easy to grow, and flaunt high efficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Numerous scientific researches demonstrated the useful effect of <italic>Echinacea</italic> immunomodulatory functions and human health<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. The doctors explored that the alcohol extract of <italic>Echinacea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus immediately increased phagocytic activity and leads to high production of white blood cells, as well as, various in vitro researches has confirmed the phagocytosis, and antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity effects of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus extracts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Decreasing of severity and symptoms of the common cold by using <italic>E. purpurea</italic> extracts was reported in several clinical studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. According to immunological studies, <italic>E. purpurea</italic> enhanced activation of the nonspecific cellular and increased humoral immunity by increasing the activation and production of monocytes, lymphocytes, leukocytes and cytokines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Based on the studies, the immune&#x02010;stimulatory property is the most important property of the species that involves the immune system based on the dose level<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Although the rhizomata cum radicibus of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> is very beneficial, purple coneflower of the species was known to be useful for the improvement of the various illnesses, such as sore throats, coughs, and snake bite<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Meanwhile, <italic>E. purpurea</italic> has been used to treat viral, bacterial and fungal infections<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> and the healing of the burns and wounds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Various chemical components of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> were associated with its biological activities and medicinal effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. For instance, the main phenolic compounds of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> were found as caffeic acid esters and chicoric acid, as well as, polysaccarides was dominant in <italic>E. purpurea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus extracts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Recent studies demonstrated that the polysaccharide content leads to enhance the macrophage activity and the cytokine production<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Also, the antifungal and antiviral properties of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> were related to certain groups of the phenolic compounds and alkamides<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Scavenging of the free radicals and lipid peroxidation assay were related to the antioxidant properties of leaves and rhizomata cum radicibus extracts of <italic>E. purpurea</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Higher concentration of isobutyl amide was affects the <italic>Echinacea</italic>&#x02019;s anti&#x02010;inflammatory property<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Overall, good manufacturing of high quality medicinal plants is depend on precise aware of plant nutrient requirement. The study in Hungary demonstrated that application of 60&#x02013;80&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;N, 40&#x02013;60&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> phosphorus (P) and 80&#x02013;100&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> potassium (K<sup>+</sup>) lead to increase of biological yield and phenolic compounds of <italic>E. purpurea</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. The optimum nutrients ratio for plant growth depends on species and environmental conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> and soil pollution with chemical pollutants such as various heavy metals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Several studies demonstrated that soil heavy metals pollution caused to decrease of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> yield under greenhouse condition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Among all nutrients, N, due to cooperation in phytochemical compound&#x02019;s structures had very critical effect on <italic>Echinacea</italic> yield and medicinal properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. So, attention to N supply has key role in chemical and medicinal composition of <italic>Echinacea</italic>. Previous researches illustrated that the various plant growth parameters of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> are generally improved with optimum mixture ratio of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> and ammonium (NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>) in comparison with either N form alone<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> dosage can affect not only rhizomata cum radicibus morphological properties, but also the overall rhizomata cum radicibus biomass<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. The results of Verma et al. (2019) showed that phenolic compounds (caftaric acid, cholorogenic acid, cynarin, echinacoside and chicoric acid) were significantly affected by NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> dosage.</p><p id="Par6">Urea is most popular conventional fertilizers in agriculture which is partially absorbed by plants. This results in reduce N usage efficiency for crops and environmental pollution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. In recent years, slow release fertilizer has been developed. Slow release fertilizer releases nutrients according to plants requirement for physiological functions during the long time, results in increase of fertilizer efficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par7">Although there are many previous reports about growing medicinal plants in different culture media and NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> dosages, there is no prior research on comparison of phytochemical properties of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> growing in the presence of novel invited N slow release fertilizer and common chemical fertilizer. So the goal of this research was to compare the growth properties and phytochemical compounds of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> growing with various amounts of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> dosage supplied from slow release and urea fertilizers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Experimental background</title><p id="Par8">The experiment was carried out in a greenhouse complex at Urmia University, West of Azarbaijan Province, Iran. Seeds of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> obtained from Pakan Bazr Esfahan, an Iranian private joint stock company, on April. 15, 2019. The seeds were put into a mixture of perlite and peat moss substrates for initial growth. Irrigation operation was performed regularly as needed depending on greenhouse condition. Seedlings were harvested after one month when they were at 3&#x02013;4 true leaves stage and transplanted in the experimental pots which had one plant grown in a pot (2.5 L) containing a mixture of soil (2-mm sieved) and fine sand for better aeration and leaching, under greenhouse conditions. The density of production system was chosen according to Waidyanatha et al. (2020). The set point for the greenhouse temperature and humidity were 19&#x02013;21 &#x000b0;C (night&#x02013;day) and 75% respectively. Fertigation was performed based on <italic>E. purpurea</italic> nutrition need, shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Nutrition requirement of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> (Seif Sahandi et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Nutrient</th><th align="left">Attribute (mM)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Nitrogen (N)</td><td align="left">150.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Phosphorus (P)</td><td align="left">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Potassium (K)</td><td align="left">6.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Calcium (Ca)</td><td align="left">3.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Magnesium (Mg)</td><td align="left">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sulfur (S)</td><td align="left">4.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Iron (Fe)</td><td align="left">50.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Manganese (Mn)</td><td align="left">9.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Zinc (Zn)</td><td align="left">0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Copper (Cu)</td><td align="left">0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Boron (B)</td><td align="left">18.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Molybdenum (Mo)</td><td align="left">0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">pH</td><td align="left">6.5&#x02013;7.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EC (dS m<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par9">All essential elements except N were supplied from the soil adequately, but two types of N fertilizers were used for supply of enough N nutrition need including slow release N fertilizer, and Urea. Chemical composition of used various fertilizers were analysed according to standard methods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The amount of N application was determined based on the differences of plant N requirement and soil N, according to fertilizer type. In this study 50 (less than adequate), 100 (moderate), and 150 (adequate) mM N were provided from each fertilizer types. Slow release fertilizer used in this study, was invited based on a novel composition at science and technology center of Hamedan province, Iran and registered at Iranian Patent Office, Tehran on Jan. 30, 2017 (patent number 139550140003013815). Details of the novel N fertilizer and its Figure were shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> respectively.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Main properties of invited slow release fertilizer.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Properties</th><th align="left">Details</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Physical shape</td><td align="left">Compact and tablet form</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weight (g)</td><td align="left">2.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diameter (cm)</td><td align="left">1.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Height (cm)</td><td align="left">0.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Harness and solubility</td><td align="left">6.4/10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Adhesion strength (%)</td><td align="left">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Surface area (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="left">200</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Colour</td><td align="left">White</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Main composition</td><td align="left">Powdered cotton seed, Semi-solid sucrose, and water</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heavy metals</td><td align="left">None</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Nitrogen slow release fertilizer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70949_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par10">The fertilizer can control the N release during the plant grow period based on complex formation between the chelator agent and the element. The main difference that distinguish this novel fertilizer from usual and commercial slow release fertilizers is its chelator agent that is more efficient and environmental friendly. As well as, urea fertilizer was chosen as common N fertilizer among Iranian farmers. All experimental treatments were repeated as three replicates with less than 1% standard deviation. Plants were fertigated for 240&#x000a0;days, every 10&#x000a0;days, under control conditions in greenhouse. The rhizome with (rhizomata cum radicibus) of plants were harvested after growing period and dried at 23&#x02013;25 &#x000b0;C (at room temperature), then phytochemical analyses were performed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Soil analysis</title><p id="Par11">Soil chemical and physical properties were measured based on standard methods. Soil pH and electrical conductivity (EC) were measured using 1:5 w/v soil to water ratio suspension<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Organic matter (OM) was determined after oxidation of soil organic fraction with potassium dichromate (K<sub>2</sub>Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>) and sulfuric acid (H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Cation exchange capacity (CEC) was determined with 1&#x000a0;mol L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> sodium acetate solution (pH 8.2) and 96% ethanol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Calcium carbonate (CaCO<sub>3</sub>) was measured after boiling of 2.5&#x000a0;g soil with 25&#x000a0;mL of 0.5&#x000a0;N hydrochloric acid (HCl)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Three fractions (sand, silt, and clay) of soil particles were determined following the pipette method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par12">Soil calcium (Ca<sup>2+</sup>) and magnesium (Mg<sup>2+</sup>) were measured titrimetrically, K<sup>+</sup> was determined by flame photometry, sulfate (SO<sub>4</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup>) by spectrophotometric and turbidimetric methods, NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> and phosphate (PO<sub>4</sub><sup>3&#x02212;</sup>) by colorimetry with an ultraviolet&#x02013;visible (UV&#x02013;Vis) spectrophotometer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Available micronutrients (Cu, Fe, Mn, Mo, and Zn) and heavy metals (Cd, Ni, Pb) were extracted with a solution containing 0.005&#x000a0;mol L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> diethylene triamine penta acetic acid (DTPA), 0.01&#x000a0;mol L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> calcium chloride, and 0.1&#x000a0;mol L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (pH 7.3) triethanolamine (TEA), as well as, boron (B) concentration was determined based on hot water method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. The concentration of micronutrients were measured by Atomic Absorption Spectrophotometer (AAS) (Model Varian Spectra-220).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Fertilizer analysis</title><p id="Par13">The urea and sloe release fertilizer were passed through a 0.5-mm sieve after air-dried at 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1 &#x000b0;C. Total N, NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> and NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> concentrations in samples were determined according to Kjeldahl method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Heavy metals and trace elements (Cd, Cu, Fe, Mn, Ni, Pb and Zn) content in samples were determined after digestion with aqua regia based on standard method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Plant growth parameters</title><p id="Par14">After harvesting the plants, different growth parameters such as plant height (cm) and total fresh leave weight (g plant<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), fresh rhizomata cum radicibus weight (g plant<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), chlorophylls a and b (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> FW), and leaf area (cm<sup>2</sup>) were measured. Weighted 0.5&#x000a0;g of dry sample was homogenized with 10&#x000a0;mL acetone<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Homogenized samples were centrifuged at 10,000&#x000a0;rpm for 15&#x000a0;min. The supernatant was separated and the absorbance spectra were measured at 400&#x02013;700&#x000a0;nm. Maximum absorbance of chlorophylls a and b were measured in 662&#x000a0;nm and 645&#x000a0;nm, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. So that<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>,<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\text{Chlorophyll a}} = { 11}.{\text{75 A}}_{{{662}}} {-}{ 2}.{35}0{\text{ A}}_{{{645}}} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Chlorophyll a</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>11</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>75 A</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>662</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.350</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>645</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70949_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\text{Chlorophyll b }} = { 18}.{\text{61 A}}_{{{645}}} {-}{ 3}.{96}0{\text{ A}}_{{{662}}} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Chlorophyll b</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>18</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>61 A</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>645</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.960</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>662</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70949_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Essential oil content</title><p id="Par15">Essential oils were extracted from 75&#x000a0;g dry weight of rhizomata cum radicibus of the plant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The samples were oven-dried at 25 &#x000b0;C for 3&#x02013;5&#x000a0;days. Rhizomata cum radicibus samples was mixed with 1,000&#x000a0;mL deionized water in a 2-L round-bottomed flask and the essential oil was extracted based on hydrodistillation method by clevenger trap<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Polysaccharide</title><p id="Par16">The standard method was followed for determine of rhizomata cum radicibus polysaccharides. The 0.6&#x000a0;mL of sugar solution was mixed with the 0.3&#x000a0;mL phenolic solution in screw cap, capped and vortex-stirred tubes. 1.5&#x000a0;mL of H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> (1&#x000a0;M) was added slowly down the side of the tube. The tubes were incubated for 30&#x000a0;min at room temperature (20 &#x000b0;C)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. The absorbances was determined at 490&#x000a0;nm using distilled water as blank in a UV&#x02013;Vis spectrophotometer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Total phenolic content</title><p id="Par17">Dry and powder rhizomata cum radicibus was analysed for caftaric acid, cholorogenic acid, chicoric acid, cynarin and echinacoside based on standard method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. As, 40&#x000a0;mg of sample was transferred into a 15-mL centrifuge vial. The five bio active compounds were extracted with 4&#x000a0;mL of 70% methanol for 15&#x000a0;min using an ultrasonic sonicator<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. The vials were centrifuged at 3,000&#x000a0;rpm for 10 min<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. After filtration of supernatant by 0.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m nylon syringe filter, 300 &#x003bc;L of the filtered extract from each sample were transferred into a glass auto-sampler high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) vial<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The HPLC system consisting of a controller, auto-injector, and a column oven. Samples were injected onto a Phenomenex Luna Qg column (5.0&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m; 4.6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;150&#x000a0;mm) with a C<sub>18</sub> guard column (4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;3&#x000a0;mm)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. The mobile phase was 0.1% phosphoric acid (A) and acetonitrile (B) at a constant flow rate of 1.3&#x000a0;mL&#x000a0;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. The standard concentrations of 5, 25, 50, 100, and 200&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g&#x000a0;mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> was used for standard curves plotting as a function of peak area in HPLC chromatograms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. The quantifications of caftaric acid, cholorogenic acid, chicoric acid, cynarin, and echinacoside were performed on the basis of the peak area of UV absorption at 330&#x000a0;nm with comparison to the standard curves of the authentic sample<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Total flavonoids content</title><p id="Par18">The analysis of total flavonoid content in rhizomata cum radicibus extracts was performed by colorimetric method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Briefly, 30 &#x003bc;L of the extract was added to 150 &#x003bc;L of sodium nitrate (5% W/V) followed by the addition of 3&#x000a0;mL of aluminum chloride hexahydrate (10% W/V) and incubated for 5 min<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. The 1&#x000a0;mL of NaOH (1.0&#x000a0;M) was added to the mixture and diluted to the mark with distilled water. After incubation at room temperature in dark place for 30&#x000a0;min, the absorbance of the solution was measured at 415&#x000a0;nm by spectrophotometer. For the quantification of TFC, the quercetin (QE) was used as an external standard<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Anti-radical scavenging activity</title><p id="Par19">The anti-radical scavenging activity of samples was evaluated based on the colorimetric method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Briefly, 15 &#x003bc;L of methanolic extract was added to 2.0&#x000a0;mL of the 2, 2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) solution and the mixture was incubated in dark place at 20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;min<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Then the absorbance was measured at 517&#x000a0;nm. The following equation was used to calculation of DPPH inhibition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>:<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\text{Inhibition }}\left( \% \right) \, = \, [({\text{A}}_{{{\text{control}}}} - {\text{A}}_{{{\text{sample}}}} ) \, /{\text{A}}_{{{\text{control}}}} ] \, \times {1}00 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Inhibition</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>control</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>sample</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>control</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70949_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where A<sub>control</sub> and A<sub>sample</sub> are the absorbance of the control and the sample respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Super oxide anti-radical scavenging activity</title><p id="Par20">Super oxide anti-radical scavenging activity of samples was determined according to standard method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. As, 9&#x000a0;mL of 5&#x000a0;mM HCl buffer (pH 8.2) was mixed with 1&#x000a0;mL of the extract. Then, 40 &#x003bc;L of 4.5&#x000a0;mM pyrogallol was added to the mixture. The mixture was shaken for 3&#x000a0;min and the absorbance of the solution was measured at 420&#x000a0;nm by spectrophotometer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. The percentage of scavenging effect was expressed as<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>:<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\text{Super oxide radical scavenging }}\left( \% \right) \, = \, \left[ {\left( {{\text{A}}_{0} - {\text{A}}_{{1}} /{\text{A}}_{0} } \right)} \right] \, \times {1}00 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Super oxide radical scavenging</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70949_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where A<sub>0</sub> is the HCl buffer absorbance and A<sub>1</sub>is the extract absorbance.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Nitric oxide anti-radical scavenging activity</title><p id="Par21">Nitric oxide anti- radical inhibition can be estimated by using Griess Illosvoy reaction according to standard method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Briefly, 3&#x000a0;mL of 10&#x000a0;mM sodium nitroprusside and 0.5&#x000a0;mL of phosphate buffer saline solution was incubated at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 150 min<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Then, 0.5&#x000a0;mL of the solution mixed with 1&#x000a0;mL of sulfanilic acid reagent and left for 5&#x000a0;min for completing diazotization. A pink coloured chromophore is formed after addition of 1&#x000a0;mL of naphthyl ethylene diamine dihydrochloride in diffused light<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. The absorbance of these solutions were measured at 540&#x000a0;nm against. The nitric oxide radical inhabitation was expressed as following equation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>:<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\text{Nitric oxide radical inhibition }}\left( \% \right) \, = \, [({\text{A}}_{{{\text{control}}}} - {\text{A}}_{{{\text{sample}}}} ) \, /{\text{A}}_{{{\text{control}}}} ] \times {1}00 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Nitric oxide radical inhibition</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mfenced><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>control</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>sample</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>control</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70949_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where A<sub>control</sub> and A<sub>sample</sub> are the control and the extract absorbance respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>2,2&#x02032;-azino-bis 3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid (ABTS) test</title><p id="Par22">ABTS test is also a spectrophotometric method which is carried out using an improved ABTS decolourisation assay<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. It is applicable for both lipophilic and hydrophilic compounds. ABTS<sup>+</sup> was generated by oxidation of ABTS with potassium persulfate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Three milliliter of ABTS cation solution were added to 30&#x000a0;mL methanol extract solution in 1&#x000a0;cm path length disposable micro cuvette and the decrease of absorption was measured during 6 min<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par23">The statistical scheme was a completely simple design, including six treatments (50, 100, 150&#x000a0;mM slow release fertilizer and 50, 100, 150&#x000a0;mM urea) with three replications. Differences among means of treatments were analysed by Duncan&#x02019;s multiple comparison at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.01. Statistical analysis was performed using statistical analysis software (SAS). All determinations were carried out in triplicate.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Results</title><p id="Par24">Main physiochemical properties of soil sample was given in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. According to results, the soil had neutral reaction without salinity effect (EC less than 2 dS m<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) which is suitable for wide range of nutrients availability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. As well as, it had calcareous nature (more than 5% CaCO<sub>3</sub> at topsoil) with sandy clay loam texture. Soil organic matter was at moderate level (1&#x02013;1%) in agricultural calcareous soils.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Physiochemical properties of studied soil.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left" rowspan="2">pH</th><th align="left">EC</th><th align="left">OM</th><th align="left">CEC</th><th align="left">CaCO<sub>3</sub></th><th align="left">Sand</th><th align="left">Silt</th><th align="left">Clay</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Soil texture</th></tr><tr><th align="left">(dS m<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left">(%)</th><th align="left">(cmol<sub>c</sub> kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left">(%)</th><th align="left" colspan="3">(%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Soil sample</td><td char="." align="char">7.20</td><td align="left">1.03</td><td align="left">1.12</td><td align="left">17.51</td><td align="left">12.26</td><td align="left">63</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">Sandy clay loam</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par25">Macro and micro nutrient concentrations in soil solution were shown in Tables <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> and <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>.
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Soluble anions and cations concentration in studied soil extract (1:20 soil to distilled water ratio).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left">Ca<sup>2+</sup></th><th align="left">Mg<sup>2+</sup></th><th align="left">K<sup>+</sup></th><th align="left">SO<sub>4</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup></th><th align="left">PO<sub>4</sub><sup>3&#x02212;</sup></th><th align="left">NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup></th><th align="left">NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="7">(meq L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Soil sample</td><td align="left">5.50</td><td char="." align="char">3.32</td><td char="." align="char">2.51</td><td char="." align="char">3.78</td><td char="." align="char">4.93</td><td char="." align="char">0.73</td><td char="." align="char">2.45</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Available concentration and total content of trace elements in studied soil sample.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left">B</th><th align="left">Cd</th><th align="left">Cu</th><th align="left">Fe</th><th align="left">Mn</th><th align="left">Mo</th><th align="left">Ni</th><th align="left">Pb</th><th align="left">Zn</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="9">(mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Available</td><td align="left">0.65</td><td char="." align="char">0.10</td><td char="." align="char">5.04</td><td char="." align="char">102.50</td><td char="." align="char">81.57</td><td char="." align="char">0.15</td><td char="." align="char">4.36</td><td char="." align="char">1.09</td><td char="." align="char">10.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left">1.19</td><td char="." align="char">0.21</td><td char="." align="char">46.52</td><td char="." align="char">2,300.54</td><td char="." align="char">520.63</td><td char="." align="char">1.68</td><td char="." align="char">20.68</td><td char="." align="char">8.36</td><td char="." align="char">43.65</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par26">The results relevant that the different heavy metals content varied depending on the element and fertilizer type. Among heavy metals, Zn had the highest content (maximum 3.1&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), whereas Cd showed the lowest (maximum 0.21&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) in two types of N fertilizers. The results were in accordance with previous studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Iron generally does not cause toxicity to plants. However, a high concentration of Fe can decrease P plant availability due to the formation of iron-phosphate salts and it is therefore harmful to plants indirectly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. The content of various heavy metals in all N-fertilizer types were as fallowed: Fe&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;Mn&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;Zn&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;Ni&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;Cu&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;Pb&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;Cd. Among these heavy metals, Cu, Mn, Zn, and Fe are considered as nutritionally essential elements, Ni is classified as an element with possible beneficial health effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, and Cd and Pb are regarded as elements with potentially toxic and environmentally hazardous effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Slow release fertilizer contains more essential element contents than urea (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). The knowledge of trace element and heavy metals content in different chemical fertilizers is useful for estimation of the environmental potential risks resulting from high loading application of fertilizers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. In Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>, the background mean content of trace elements and heavy metals in worldwide soils are presented<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Content of trace elements in different types of fertilizers.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Fertilizer</th><th align="left">Cd</th><th align="left">Cu</th><th align="left">Ni</th><th align="left">Pb</th><th align="left">Zn</th><th align="left">NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="5">(mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th align="left">(%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Urea</td><td align="left">0.21</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td char="." align="char">2.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.5</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td><td align="left">46</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Slow release</td><td align="left">0.01</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td char="." align="char">3.8</td><td char="." align="char">0.06</td><td char="." align="char">5.4</td><td align="left">32</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Mean background contents of trace elements in surface soils (Khalaf et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Heavy metals</th><th align="left">Background content in soils</th></tr><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">(mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Cd</td><td align="left">0.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cu</td><td align="left">38.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fe</td><td align="left">45,000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mn</td><td align="left">488</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ni</td><td align="left">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pb</td><td align="left">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Zn</td><td align="left">70</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par27">Cumulative release of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> from slow release fertilizer at different concentrations during the time is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. Passing the time up to 200&#x000a0;h resulted in an increasing release of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> from slow release fertilizer. Increasing the NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> concentration leads to increase of release rate over time. The highest (130&#x000a0;mM) amount of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> released was observed in 150&#x000a0;mM slow release fertilizer (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). However, NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> from the urea chemical fertilizer showed a maximum release (125&#x000a0;mM) within 1 to 2&#x000a0;h (data not shown).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Kinetics of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> release from treated soil with slow release fertilizer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70949_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par28">Plant grow parameters of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> under different two types of fertilizers were shown in Table <xref rid="Tab8" ref-type="table">8</xref>. Increasing of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> dosage caused to increase in plant height and rhizomata cum radicibus weight significantly (Table <xref rid="Tab8" ref-type="table">8</xref>). All plant growth parameters were significantly more in slow release fertilizer treatments than urea.<table-wrap id="Tab8"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Some morphological properties of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> growing under different fertilizer treatments.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Property</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Slow release fertilizer</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Urea</th></tr><tr><th align="left">50&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">100&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">150&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">50&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">100&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">150&#x000a0;mM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Height (cm)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">74.60<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.53</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">83.10<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.82</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">105.20<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.21</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">49.30<sup>e</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.10</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">66.80<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.25</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">71.50<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total fresh leave weight (g plant<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">21.86<sup>bc</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.28</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">25.67<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.56</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">33.19<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.13</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.22<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.23<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">23.14<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fresh rhizomata cum radicibus weight (g plant<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">41.29<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.15</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">53.20<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.22</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">65.43<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.40</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.32<sup>e</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.75</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24.10<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.90</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">29.36<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chlorophyll a (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> FW)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.3<sup>6c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.23</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.24<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.32</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.10<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.56</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9.89<sup>e</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.62</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.10<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.84</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.35<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chlorophyll b (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> FW)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">4.13<sup>bc</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.14</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.21<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.16</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.54<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.10<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">4.56<sup>bc</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.14</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.19<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Leaf area (cm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">38<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.26</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">43<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.26</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">55<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.96</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">22<sup>e</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.59</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.91</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">36<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.52</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data were expressed as the mean of three replicates&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3).</p><p>Values within a row followed by different letters are significantly different at the 0.01 probability level.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par29">The effects of slow release and chemical fertilizers on total phenolic and flavonoid contents, polysaccarides and essential oil content of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab9" ref-type="table">9</xref>. The significant differences were obtained among phytochemical properties in slow release and chemical fertilizers treatments. The highest total phenol was recorded in the 150&#x000a0;mM slow release fertilizer treatment. Increasing of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> concentration in slow release fertilizer significantly leads to increase of total phenolics, flavonoids, polysaccarides, and essential oil content.<table-wrap id="Tab9"><label>Table 9</label><caption><p>Phytochemical analysis of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus under various treatments.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left" colspan="3">Slow release fertilizer</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Urea</th></tr><tr><th align="left">50&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">100&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">150&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">50&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">100&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">150&#x000a0;mM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Total phenolic compound (GAE g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">47.3<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.31</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">51.6<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.30</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">60.2<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.56</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.3<sup>f</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.52</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">30.6<sup>e</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.60</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">43.5<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total flavonoid content (QE g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.2<sup>cd</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.37</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24.9<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.48</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">32.8<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.5<sup>e</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.17</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">14.6<sup>de</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.31</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">22.6<sup>bc</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Polysaccarides (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">27.6<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.42</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">38.4<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">50.5<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.75</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.9<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.53</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">28.6<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.18</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">36.9<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Essential oil content (% w w<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.09<sup>de</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.18<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.29<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.06<sup>e</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.13<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.24<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data were expressed as the mean of three replicates&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3).</p><p>Values within a row followed by different letters are significantly different at the 0.01 probability level.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par30">The HPLC profile of a standard mixture of caffeic acid derivatives is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. Results of caffeic acid derivatives content as affected by slow release and chemical fertilizers in dry rhizomata cum radicibus of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab10" ref-type="table">10</xref>. Caffeic acid derivatives content was affected by fertilizer types and dosages. The dried <italic>E. purpurea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus contained more cichoric acid and caftaric acid than other derivatives (Table <xref rid="Tab10" ref-type="table">10</xref>). These results are in agreement with previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>HPLC profile of a standard mixture of caffeic acid derivatives. Peak 1, caftaric acid; 2, chlorogenic acid; 3, echinacoside; 4, chicoric acid; and 5, cynarin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70949_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab10"><label>Table 10</label><caption><p>Caffeic acid derivatives of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus under various treatments.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Caffeic acid derivatives</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Slow release fertilizer</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Urea</th></tr><tr><th align="left">50&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">100&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">150&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">50&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">100&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">150&#x000a0;mM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Caftaric acid (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.31<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.13<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.26<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.78<sup>e</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.06<sup>de</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.83<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chlorogenic acid (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.23<sup>cd</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.95<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.36<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.16<sup>e</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.43<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.73<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Echinacoside acid (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.89<sup>bc</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.32<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.66<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.29<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.75<sup>cd</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.96<sup>bc</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chicoric acid (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.23<sup>e</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">4.56<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.08</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">7.65<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.65</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.74<sup>f</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.03<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.44<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cynarin (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> DW)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.68<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">2.88<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">5.26<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.43<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.98<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3.28<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data were expressed as the mean of three replicates&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3).</p><p>Values within a row followed by different letters are significantly different at the 0.01 probability level.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par31">The effects of various different fertilizers on anti-radical scavenging activity of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus were shown in Table <xref rid="Tab11" ref-type="table">11</xref>. The nitric oxide, DPPH, super oxide and ABTS anti-radicals were assesses in the present study.<table-wrap id="Tab11"><label>Table 11</label><caption><p>Different anti-radical scavenging activity of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus under various treatments.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Anti-radical</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Slow release fertilizer</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Urea</th></tr><tr><th align="left">50&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">100&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">150&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">50&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">100&#x000a0;mM</th><th align="left">150&#x000a0;mM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">DPPH (%)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">25.36<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.95</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">28.95<sup>ab</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.36</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">31.22<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.33</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.62<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.36</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.31<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.18</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.12<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Super oxide (%)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.39<sup>cd</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.73</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.21<sup>bc</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.55</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">23.66<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.65</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.36<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.98</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">13.65<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.42</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">28.76<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nitric oxide (%)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">28.24<sup>bc</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.68</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">32.19<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.48</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">40.36<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">19.21<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.23</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">26.25<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.36</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">31.42<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ABTS (%)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">10.23<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.59</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15.23<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.67</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">20.95<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.29</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">8.26<sup>d</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.51</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">12.84<sup>c</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">16.63<sup>b</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.47</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data were expressed as the mean of three replicates&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3).</p><p>Values within a row followed by different letters are significantly different at the 0.01 probability level.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par32">Although there are characterized by excellent reproducibility, but all of them were different in their response to antioxidants under certain conditions. The highest nitric oxide (40.36%), DPPH (31.22%), super oxide (23.66%), and ABTS (20.95%) anti-radical scavenging activities were found in the 150&#x000a0;mM slow release fertilizer treatment, which could be due to higher phenolic content, whereas the lowest various anti-radical scavenging activities were obtained in the 50&#x000a0;mM urea treatment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par33">Previous researches showed that soil CEC was varied as affected by organic matter content<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. In fact, increasing of soil CEC results from the increasing of negative charge surface sites on soil colloids due to decomposition of organic matter in pH value above 3 (point of zero charge (PZC) of organic matter)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Increasing of soil CEC leads to increase of nutrients retention at active soil exchangeable sites which plays critical role in nutrition release and their availability for plant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par34">In comparison with <italic>E. purpurea</italic> nutrition requirement (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), most of essential nutrients (except NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>) in soil solution were in at adequate range which can supply plant essential macro and micro nutrition requirement without adding any fertilizer during the time. However, NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> concentration in soil solution was noticeably (more than 3 times) less than <italic>E. purpurea</italic> requirement that indicates the need to NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> fertilizers apply in order to increase NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> level in the studied soil.</p><p id="Par35">Nitrate leaching from agricultural soils is common due to anionic nature of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> ion and non-adsorption on negatively charged soil exchangeable sites, which leads to apply of different N fertilizers to soil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. In present study, the soil N deficiency was calculated with regard to <italic>E. purpurea</italic> N-requirement and provided the optimum level of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>concentration for the plant growth by using different N fertilizers containing various percentages of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>. Numerous research have reported the harmful influence of soil pollution and heavy metals concentration on <italic>E. purpurea</italic> growth and medicinal properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. According to Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>, the studied soil contains different heavy metals available concentration less than (more than 4 times) dangerous limit in agricultural soils<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, which reported the 0.2, 13.0, 6.0, 16.0, and 22.0&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> as acceptable limit for available Cd, Cu, Ni, Pb, and Zn in soil respectively.</p><p id="Par36">The data show the lower total concentration of heavy metals in studied soil sample than USEPA limits, which reported the 1.5, 200, 50, 200, and 400&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for Cd, Cu, Ni, Pb, and Zn respectively. So, in the present study, it can be mention that there is no risk of heavy metal pollution for <italic>E. purpurea</italic> growth. The application of mineral fertilizers which have contaminants of trace elements may impose concern regarding the entry and toxic accumulation of these elements in agro ecosystems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. So, the chemical composition of 3 types of N fertilizers was analyzed for their content of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>, HN<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>, and heavy metals (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).</p><p id="Par37">By comparing these values with the contents of trace elements in different N fertilizer types (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>), it is apparent that the content of all heavy metals in used N fertilizers in present study are lower than their natural background in soils. Therefore, in soils receiving these fertilizers, heavy metals cannot be enriched. So, in present study, the main source of these trace elements are the soil and only the soil can supply these elements for the plant growth mainly. Inspite of micro nutrients, N content of different studied fertilizers was shown in Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>. Based on obtained results, urea (46% N) had higher NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> content followed by slow release fertilizer (32%). Different NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> fertilizers varied significantly in their N content that can affect the plant growth. However, NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> content in all N fertilizers changed in narrow range, so at the relatively constant NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> content in the soil, the soil NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> content affects the plant phytochemical properties.</p><p id="Par38">The presence of polymeric compounds used in the slow release fertilizer structure leads to the gradual maintenance and release of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> from the fertilizer and these compounds are not present in the urea fertilizer. Gradual release of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> from slow release fertilizers results in degradation of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> availability for the plant and prevention of leaching and loss of soil.</p><p id="Par39">It is well known that the elasticity of the cell wall plays an important role in cell division<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. The osmotic pressure in the cell increase by increasing of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> concentration, leading to sufficient swelling pressure for cell division that affect the morphological properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Meanwhile, the NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> dosage can influence growing substrate pH, especially in nutrient recirculating systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. It has been found that an increase of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> dosage caused a significant increase of medicinal and phytochemical compounds of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> due to improve of rhizomata cum radicibus growth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Similar results were found by Sidhiq et al. (2020) in <italic>E. purpurea</italic> plants grown in floating raft system for 21&#x000a0;weeks. Nitrogen is a predominant element in chlorophyll structure. Increasing of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> dosage significantly affects the chlorophylls content<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Increasing of chlorophyll content caused to increase of leaf area due to increase of light adsorption<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. The results were in consistent with Attarzadeh et al. (2019) who found that higher NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> dosage resulted in higher leaf area, rhizomata cum radicibus and total biomass.</p><p id="Par40">According to Saeed et al. (2018), accumulation of phenolic compounds in the plant rhizomata cum radicibus prevents NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> toxicity in plants. There are some reports showing that stress conditions increase either phenylalanine ammonia lyase (PAL) synthesis or activity in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>; other authors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> have found that some stress treatments delay the increase in wound-induced PAL activity. Phenylalanine Ammonia-Lyase activity was found to vary greatly with the stage of plant development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. The results were in accommodation with Zaushintsena et al. (2019). Variation between and among the herb species also exists due to geographical location, stage of development, time of harvest, and growth conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par41">Caffeic acid derivatives are sensitive to NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> dosage, and increasing NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> concentration will result in a significant increase of caffeic acid derivatives in <italic>E. purpurea</italic> (Table <xref rid="Tab10" ref-type="table">10</xref>). Results showed high caffeic acid derivatives content with slow release fertilizers than urea. It may be due to slow release of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> during the time and more availability for plants.</p><p id="Par42">Increasing of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> dosage in slow release fertilizer leads to significant increase of all anti-radical scavenging activities. Rhizomata cum radicibus extract of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> can entrap hydroxyl radicals. This antioxidant mechanism is described as elimination of free radicals and chelating metal ions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Effective compounds of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> are alkylamids, polysacharides, glicoproteins and chicoric acid. Chicoric acid is the main phenolic compound with antioxidant effect in <italic>E. purpurea</italic>. Phenolic compounds like caffeic acid and chlorogenic acid are the most efficient naturally occurring antioxidants. As the result of the presence of chicoric acid in leaf extraction of <italic>E. purpurea</italic>, this species has the most antioxidant effect among all other<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Beside chicoric acid, typical constituents of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> extracts are echinacoside, chlorogenic acid, cynarin and caftaric acid. All of them are able affect the free radical production and lipid peroxidation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Recent studies also relevant that echinacoside and caffeic acid derivative have weak anti-bacterial and antiviral effects and are protectants against reactive oxygen species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. The antioxidant activity could be ascribed to the polyphenolic components<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, such as flavonoids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, phenolic acids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> or phenolic diterpenes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par43">It was found that the concentration of all heavy metals in soil samples and fertilizers studied was less than the USEPA limits of contamination. With this point of view, there were significant differences in morphological and phytochemical properties of <italic>E. purpurea</italic> with respect to slow release and chemical N fertilizers containing different dosages of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>. All morphological and phytochemical properties were higher in the presence of slow release fertilizer than urea chemical fertilizer. It may be due to the polymeric structure of slow release fertilizer that control the N release during the time. Increasing of morphological and phytochemical properties, caffeic acid derivations and anti-radical scavenging activities were observed by increasing of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> dosage. With regard to future growth conditions of the plant, it is important to make operational additional research projects for medicinal plants and flowers grown under greenhouse conditions, with the objective of building further confidence in the advantages of the plant cultivation and importance of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> concentration control in environmental systems.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors are thankful to the Office of Vice Chancellor for Research and Technology, Urmia University. This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>F.A. conceived the idea and wrote the paper. A.S. and A.R. reviewed the collected data. F.A. was responsible for editing, original data and text preparation. All authors took responsibility for the integrity of the data that is present in this study.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par44">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Attarzadeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Balouchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajaie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehnavi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth and nutrient content of <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> as affected by the combination of phosphorus with arbuscular mycorrhizal fungus and Pseudomonas florescent bacterium under different irrigation regimes</article-title><source>J. Environ. Manage.</source><year>2019</year><volume>231</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2018.10.040</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30342330?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30342330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balciunaite</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> (L.) Moench root LysM lectin with nephrotoxic properties</article-title><source>Toxins</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins12020088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Charest</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimpe</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Blais</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The accumulation of metals, PAHs and alkyl PAHs in the roots of <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic></article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e0208325</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0208325</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30521573?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30521573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cadiz</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Schara</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbons Johnson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> root extract increases tumor necrosis factor production by concanavalin A-activated murine splenocytes</article-title><source>J. Med. Food.</source><year>2019</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>169</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darvizheh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahedi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbaszadeh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Razmjoo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in some antioxidant enzymes and physiological indices of purple coneflower (<italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> L.) in response to water deficit and foliar application of salicylic acid and spermine under field condition</article-title><source>Sci. Horticult.</source><year>2019</year><volume>247</volume><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2018.12.037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khorasaninejad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemmati</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of silicon on some phytochemical traits of purple coneflower (<italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> L.) under salinity</article-title><source>Sci. Horticult.</source><year>2020</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>123</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Rosa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of immunomodulatory supplements based on <italic>Echinacea Angustifolia</italic> and <italic>Echinacea Purpurea</italic> on the posttreatment relapse incidence of genital condylomatosis: A prospective randomized study</article-title><source>Biomed. Res. Int.</source><year>2019</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>255</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demirci</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ak&#x000e7;ay</surname><given-names>U&#x000c7;</given-names></name><name><surname>Baydar</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of 24-epibrassinolide and L-phenylalanine on growth and caffeic acid derivative production in hairy root culture of <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> L. Moench</article-title><source>Acta Physiol. Plant</source><year>2020</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11738-020-03055-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haron</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plant microbiome-dependent immune enhancing action of <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> is enhanced by soil organic matter content</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-36907-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30659215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoang</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of nitrogen fertilizer on the mycorrhizal inoculating potential and fungal community structure in rhizosphere of medicinal plant <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L.</article-title><source>Geomicrobiol. J.</source><year>2019</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01490451.2018.1556751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sussman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of developmental and environmental factors on secondary metabolites in medicinal plants</article-title><source>Plant Physiol. Biochem.</source><year>2020</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2020.01.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31951944?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31951944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khalaf</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protective effect of <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> (Immulant) against cisplatin-induced immunotoxicity in rats</article-title><source>DARU</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>199</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kataoka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolite profiling reveals a complex response of plants to application of plant growth-promoting endophytic bacteria</article-title><source>Microbiol. Res.</source><year>2020</year><volume>234</volume><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2020.126421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maggini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tissue specificity and differential effects on in vitro plant growth of single bacterial endophytes isolated from the roots, leaves and rhizospheric soil of <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic></article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-019-1890-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31253081?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31253081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Priyadarshoni</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic>-A potent medicinal herb</article-title><source>Drug Invent. Today.</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>158</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sidhiq</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Widiyastuti</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Subositi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pujiasmanto</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yunus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological diversity, total phenolic and flavonoid content of <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> cultivated in Karangpandan, Central Java, Indonesia</article-title><source>J. Biol. Divers.</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>234</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Negative effects of the simulated nitrogen deposition on plant phenolic metabolism: A meta-analysis</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><year>2020</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>142</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheshbahreh</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehnavi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahreininejad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of irrigation regimes and nitrogen sources on biomass production, water and nitrogen use efficiency and nutrients uptake in coneflower (<italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Agric. Water Manage.</source><year>2019</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agwat.2018.10.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltanian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Moghaddam</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Asili</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of water deficit stress and fertilizer sources on morphological characteristics and phenolic compounds in medicinal plant purple coneflower (<italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Iran. J. Med. Aromat. Plants</source><year>2020</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>120</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senica</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mlinsek</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Veberic</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikulic-Petkovsek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Which plant part of purple coneflower (<italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> (L.) Moench) should be used for tea and which for tincture?</article-title><source>J. Med. Food</source><year>2019</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jmf.2018.0026</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30222488?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30222488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seif Sahandi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehrafarin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalighi-Sigaroodi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharifi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in essential oil content and composition of peppermint (<italic>Mentha piperita</italic> L.) in responses to nitrogen application</article-title><source>J. Med. Plants</source><year>2019</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>97</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vidovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasti&#x00107;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavari&#x00107;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cindri&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vladi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of green extraction process to produce antioxidant-rich extracts from purple coneflower</article-title><source>Sep. Sci. Technol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>1174</fpage><lpage>1181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01496395.2018.1527854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>PPS</given-names></name><name><surname>Padalia</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Agri</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of nitrogen, phosphorus and potassium levels on growth and yield of turmeric (<italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L.) Under the Katyur valley of western Himalayan region of Uttarakhand</article-title><source>J. Med. Plants</source><year>2019</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>122</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheshbahreh</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehnavi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahreininejad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological and yield responses of purple coneflower (<italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> (L.) Moench) to nitrogen sources at different levels of irrigation</article-title><source>Physiol. Mol. Biol. Pla.</source><year>2019</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12298-018-0611-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bensalem</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The interactive effect of nitrate/ammonium ratio and sodium chloride on Tunisian medicinal plant (<italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L)</article-title><source>J. Plant Nutr</source><year>2020</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yetilmezsoy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kocak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Akbin</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d6;z&#x000e7;imen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilization of struvite recovered from high-strength ammonium-containing simulated wastewater as slow-release fertilizer and fire-retardant barrier</article-title><source>Environ. Technol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09593330.2018.1491642</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29932016?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29932016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Degradable polyester/urea inclusion complex applied as a facile and environment-friendly strategy for slow-release fertilizer: Performance and mechanism</article-title><source>Chem. Eng. J.</source><year>2020</year><volume>381</volume><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2019.122704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rudmin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mechanochemical preparation of slow release fertilizer based on glauconite-urea complexes</article-title><source>Minerals</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/min9090507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of the growth performance, body composition and nonspecific immunity of crucian carp <italic>Carassius auratus</italic> upon <italic>Enteromorpha prolifera</italic> polysaccharide</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>163</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merajipoor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehnavi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadavi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving grain yield, water and nitrogen use efficiency of <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> with biological and chemical nitrogen under different irrigation regimes</article-title><source>Sci. Horticult.</source><year>2020</year><volume>260</volume><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2019.108869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Slow-release fertilizer improves the growth, quality, and nutrient utilization of wintering chinese chives (<italic>Allium tuberosum</italic> Rottler ex Spreng.)</article-title><source>Agronomy</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/agronomy10030381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kilic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Soylak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of trace element contaminants in herbal teas using ICP-MS by different sample preparation method</article-title><source>J. Food Sci. Technol. Mys.</source><year>2020</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>927</fpage><lpage>933</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13197-019-04125-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Serafy</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Sheshtawy</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of nitrogen fixing bacteria and moringa leaf extract on fruit yield, estragole content and total phenols of organic fennel</article-title><source>Sci. Horticult.</source><year>2020</year><volume>265</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2020.109209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahmoed</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of Chlorella vulgaris enriched diet on growth performance, immune response, antioxidant and transcriptomics RNA sequences disorders caused by deltamethrin toxicity in Nile tilapia (<italic>Oreochromis niloticus</italic>)</article-title><source>Fish Shellfish Immunol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerwick</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wangensteen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Inngjerdingen</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioactive triterpenoids and water-soluble melanin from <italic>Inonotus obliquus</italic> (Chaga) with immunomodulatory activity</article-title><source>J. Funct. Foods</source><year>2020</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jff.2020.104025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waidyanatha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A strategy for test article selection and phytochemical characterization of <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> extract for safety testing</article-title><source>Food Chem. Toxicol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>602</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sikora</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessment of the efficiency of nitrogen slow-release fertilizers in integrated production of carrot depending on fertilization strategy</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su12051982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Screening and evaluation of adventitious root lines of <italic>Panax notoginseng</italic> by morphology, gene expression, and metabolite profiles</article-title><source>Appl. Microbiol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>4405</fpage><lpage>4415</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of nutritional factors on the accretion of secondary metabolites in Malaysian ginseng adventitious root cultures</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol. Rep.</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>