<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection of Plant material and extraction of essential oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant material of 
   <span class="italic">Coccinia grandis</span> was collected from Eklagna village Jalgaon. [20° 58′ 54.3″ N, 075° 27′ 09.5′ E (elevation: 199m)] Maharashtra, identified at Botanical Survey of India, Pune and a specimen voucher number MSMI-1 was deposited in the School of Life Sciences, North Maharashtra University Jalgaon. The collected fresh leaves were cut in to small pieces and extraction was done using Clevenger apparatus for 6h (
   <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">Singh et al. 2008</a>). The extracted essential oil was subjected to dryness over anhydrous sodium sulfate (Na
   <sub>2</sub>SO
   <sub>4</sub>) to remove traces of moisture. The physical characteristics of extracted essential oil were recorded, percentage average yield was calculated and it was stored at 4 °C in amber-colored bottle in refrigerator until further analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec sec-type="methods" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC and GC-MS analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography mass spectroscopy (GC-MS) analysis of essential oil was performed using JEOL GCMS-Mate-II model gas chromatograph-mass spectrometer equipped with an AOC-20i auto injector and HP-5 capillary column (30m × 0.25mm ID × 0.25μm coating thickness) column. The injector temperature was set at 280 °C, and the oven temperature was initially set at 40 °C then programmed to increase up to 300 °C at the rate of 10 °C/min and finally held at 200 °C for 5 min. Helium gas was maintained at a flow rate 1.0ml/min as a carrier gas. One microliter of the sample diluted with acetone in 1:10 ratio was injected in the split mode. The percentage of constituents in essential oil of leaves was calculated by the GC peak areas. Data handling was made through JEOL software and the compounds were identified based on the comparison of their retention time (RT) and mass spectra of WILEY, NIST library data of the GC-MS.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mosquito larvicidal assay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mosquito larvicidal activity was performed against mosquito larvae of species 
   <span class="italic">An. stephensi</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Ae. aegypti</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Cu. quinquefasciatus.</span> Larvae of 
   <span class="italic">An.s stephensi</span> [21
   <span class="sup">0</span>00′14.3N, 075
   <span class="sup">0</span>29′39.8E (elevation: 207m)], 
   <span class="italic">Ae. aegypti</span> [2101′01.2N, 075
   <span class="sup">0</span>29′52.3E (elevation: 192m)] and 
   <span class="italic">Cu. quinquefasciatus</span> [21
   <span class="sup">0</span>00′53.5N, 075
   <span class="sup">0</span> 29′39.8E (elevation: 185m] were collected from local breeding areas of Jalgaon, India and identified using the microscopic examination as per Theodore et al. (2005). The collected mosquito larvae were brought to laboratory and maintained at 25–30 °C with 80–90% relative humidity and 12 h/d/night cycle in plastic trays containing dechlorinated water. Mosquito larvae were fed with 10% sterile sucrose solution and pet biscuits. The mosquito larvicidal activity was performed according to standard procedure recommended by 
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">WHO (1981)</a>. The extracted dried and pre weighed essential oil was dissolved in 1ml of acetone and from this different concentrations were made such as 3.125, 6.25, 12.50, 25, 50 and 100ppm in distilled water. Twenty five early fourth instar stage larvae of each of the three species of mosquito were used for larvicidal assay in 200ml beakers and three replicates were maintained for each concentration used. During the experiment, no food was given to the larvae.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec sec-type="methods" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The larval mortality rate was calculated after 12 and 24 h of exposure time. The lethal concentrations, LC
   <sub>50</sub> and LC
   <sub>90</sub> and their 95% confidence limit of the lower and upper levels were calculated by probit analysis using statistical software Stats Direct 2.8.0.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
