<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The majority of
  <span class="italic"> Mentha</span> species are considered as medicinal and aromatic plants and are also known to possess several biological and pharmacological properties, primarily due to their essential oils (EOs) contents [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>, 
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>]. A total of ten
  <span class="italic"> Mentha</span> species have been reported in the flora of Morocco [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>], two of which,
  <span class="italic"> M. suaveolens </span>subsp.
  <span class="italic"> timija</span> and
  <span class="italic"> M. gattefossei</span>, being endemic.
  <span class="italic"> M. suaveolens</span> subsp.
  <span class="italic"> timija</span> (Briq.) Harley (locally called
  <span class="italic"> timija</span>) is a perennial herb that finds natural habitat in semiarid and subhumid areas along rivers [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>]. In Moroccan folk medicine, the powder and infusion of aerial parts of this plant are also used for the treatment of whooping cough, bronchitis, and ulcerative colitis and are known for their antispasmodic and carminative properties [
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>]. On the other hand, it has been reported that the EOs isolated from the aerial parts of mint timija exhibit a variety of biological activities including antimicrobial [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>], antioxidant, and insecticidal activities [
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>, 
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mint timija, as with other aromatic and medicinal plants, is frequently collected from its natural habitat. Unfortunately, it has been reported that overharvesting is causing a dramatic reduction in the natural populations of this endemic plant and increases its extinction risk [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>]. Our previous study concluded that cultivation may constitute a rational solution to the management, conservation, and sustainable exploitation of this valuable medicinal plant [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>]. However, it has been observed that this practice has increased the amount of pulegone in the EO extracted from mint timija. This compound at higher doses is known for its toxicity and its dangerous effects to human health [
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>]. Indeed, it has been shown that the toxicity of pulegone is mainly due to its transformation into menthofuran, considered as a violent toxin against the lungs and liver [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is well known that many factors and practices related to cultivation can improve the growth and EO quality of many aromatic plants [
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>]. Among these practices, application of mineral and biological fertilizers, such as N, P, and K amendments and mycorrhizal inoculation have been recommended [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>, 
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>]. In fact, the use of these cultural practices has many advantages, which include promoting the physical and biological properties of soil [
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>], stimulating plant growth and biomass yield through improving nutrient uptake [
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>], and enhancing the content and quality of EOs via modulation of the levels of enzymes that participate in the biosynthesis of volatile terpenes [
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several studies have shown that the application of mineral fertilizers and biological agents, such as vesicular arbuscular mycorrhizae (VAM), can influence the yield, composition, and biological properties of many medicinal and aromatic plants EOs, such as
  <span class="italic"> Mentha piperita</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Mentha viridis</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Mentha arvensis</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Artemisia annua</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Rosmarinus officinalis</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Thymus maroccanus</span>, and
  <span class="italic"> Thymus leptobotrys </span>[
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>, 
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>–
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>]. However, no information is available on the influence of these treatments on the quality and quantity of EO in mint timija plants. Thus, the objective of the study described herein was to determine for the first time the possible effect of complete (N, P, and K) fertilizer and VAM inoculation on the chemical profile, and consequently on the insecticidal and antioxidant activities of EOs extracted from this Moroccan endemic plant.
 </p>
</sec>
