<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The high number of invasive species as well as the high proportion of alien species that have become invasive in the West Indies is likely a combination of (1) the historic role of these islands as a hub for the Europe–America trading routes and (2) the early and widespread degradation of their natural habitats. For more than three centuries (1500s–1890s), European colonizers used the Caribbean islands as ports of call for trading routes between the Americas and the “Old World,” facilitating intentional and accidental introductions of numerous alien species coming from Asia, Africa, Europe, and continental America (Oviedo et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32984-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Rojas‐Sandoval &amp; Acevedo‐Rodríguez, 
 <xref rid="ece32984-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Additionally, Caribbean islands have been subjected to high levels of anthropogenic disturbance first due to agriculture expansion and exploitation of their natural resources (e.g., logging), and more recently due to urban and tourism development (Acevedo‐Rodríguez &amp; Strong, 
 <xref rid="ece32984-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Dixon et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32984-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). Several studies have demonstrated that the level of disturbance (i.e., habitat quality) plays a crucial role in determining the level of invasion in invaded communities and that alien species are more likely to establish in disturbed habitats than in pristine habitats (Catford et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32984-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Lockwood et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32984-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Rojas‐Sandoval &amp; Acevedo‐Rodríguez, 
 <xref rid="ece32984-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). In the case of the West Indies, islands are not only exposed to high levels of anthropogenic disturbances but also recurrently impacted by large‐scale natural disturbances such as hurricanes and tropical storms, which may drive changes in the structure, composition, and functioning of plant communities (Bellingham, Tanner, &amp; Healey, 
 <xref rid="ece32984-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Lugo, 
 <xref rid="ece32984-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Walker, Lodge, &amp; Waide, 
 <xref rid="ece32984-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">1991</xref>). Consequently, it is plausible that the high disturbance rates prevailing on these islands are facilitating the successful establishment of invasive species populations (Lockwood et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32984-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Richardson &amp; Pyšek, 
 <xref rid="ece32984-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>).
</p>
