<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec0025" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Immunomodulatory effects of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil
 </div>
 <p id="par0055" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The immunomodulatory effects of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> may be another reason for its beneficial effects in sinusitis. Oral 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil enhanced humoral immune responses by reduction in IgA, IgM and C3 levels 
  <a rid="bib0390" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0390">
   <span class="sup">27</span>
  </a>. The immunomodulatory effects of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil is not related to the effects on Th1 and Th2 cell responsiveness to allergen stimulants 
  <a rid="bib0395" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0395">
   <span class="sup">28</span>
  </a>. 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil decreased the serum IgG1, IgG2a, IL-2, IL-12, IL-10, IFN-γ and inflammatory cells in lung tissue of murine model of allergic asthma 
  <a rid="bib0400" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0400">
   <span class="sup">29</span>
  </a>. 5 ml/kg/day injected 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil for 17 days in CD1 albino mice decreased IgG and serum IL-2 and IL-12 
  <a rid="bib0400" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0400">
   <span class="sup">29</span>
  </a>, also 4 ml/kg/day injected 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil in OVA sensitized BALB/c mice for 7 days decreased total IgE, IgG1 and OVA IgG1, mRNA expression of IL-4, IL-5, IL-6 and TGF-β1 from lung cells and nitric oxide, eosinophils, macrophages and lymphocytes 
  <a rid="bib0405" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0405">
   <span class="sup">30</span>
  </a>, Thymoquinone decreased leukotriene 
  <a rid="bib0410" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0410">
   <span class="sup">31</span>
  </a>, OVA IgE &amp; IgG1, IL-4, IL-5, IL-13, IFN-c, eosinophils 
  <a rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0415">
   <span class="sup">32</span>
  </a>, blood IFN-γ 
  <a rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0420">
   <span class="sup">33</span>
  </a> in mice animal models and cell lines. 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil can ameliorate the cellular immunological changes due to chloramphenicol 
  <a rid="bib0425" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0425">
   <span class="sup">34</span>
  </a>. Weak immune system is the cause of recurrent sinus infections that make the body vulnerable to infections, increase the mucus production, chronic swelling of the mucous membranes, that finally leads to sinus pain. Therefore, the immunomodulatory effects of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil can prevent the secondary infections, headache and other clinical signs of sinusitis.
 </p>
</sec>
