<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec0020" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The anti-histaminic, anti-oxidant and anti-inflammatory effects of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil
 </div>
 <p id="par0035" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sinusitis is associated with inflammation of sinus cavities as the result of an irritant or triggering the body's histamine responses. Therefore, the anti-inflammatory, anti-histaminic and antioxidant effects of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil may explain one of mechanisms related to its efficacy in reducing the inflammation of sinuses and respiratory airways.
 </p>
 <p id="par0040" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In animal model of allergic asthma, cyclooxygenase and 5-lipoxygenase pathways of rat peritoneal leukocytes inhibited by 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> fixed oil, by inhibition of thromboxane B
  <sub>2</sub> and leukotriene B
  <sub>4</sub> metabolites 
  <a rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0340">
   <span class="sup">17</span>
  </a>. Lung inflammation was improved and peripheral blood eosinophil count was decreased by 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> fixed oil 
  <a rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0345">
   <span class="sup">18</span>
  </a>. Oral administration of fixed oil in animal models significantly decreased the leukocyte, platelet counts 
  <a rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0350">
   <span class="sup">19</span>
  </a>.
 </p>
 <p id="par0045" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The anti-inflammatory effects of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil is related to thymoquinone, nigellone, thymohydroquinone. Low concentration of 
  <span class="italic">Nigellone</span> has been proved to inhibit the histamine release 
  <a rid="bib0355" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0355">
   <span class="sup">20</span>
  </a>. 500 mg 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil in the form of capsule is used as anti-histamine agent 
  <a rid="bib0355" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0355">
   <span class="sup">20</span>
  </a>. 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil, thymoquinone and nigellone dose dependently inhibited the formation of 5-lipoxygenase products and 5-hydroxy-eicosa-tetra-enoic acid (5-HETE) from polymorphonuclear leukocytes 
  <a rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0360">
   <span class="sup">21</span>
  </a>. Thymoquinone has exhibited anti-histaminic, anti-inflammatory and immunoboosting effects 
  <a rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0365">
   <span class="sup">22</span>
  </a>.
 </p>
 <p id="par0050" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rather than, the anti-inflammatory effects of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil in mice and rat animal models, 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil reduced the serum levels of TNF-α and high sensitivity C-reactive protein in calorie restricted obese women 
  <a rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0370">
   <span class="sup">23</span>
  </a>. Furthermore, oral administration of 1 g 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil in patients suffering from rheumatoid arthritis for 8 weeks increased the serum levels of IL-10 without any changes in TNF-α 
  <a rid="bib0375" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0375">
   <span class="sup">24</span>
  </a>. The anti-inflammatory effects of daily administration of 0.5 ml 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil for 30 days were associated with significant suppression of nasal mucosal congestion, turbinate hypertrophy, nasal itching, mucosal pollar and sneezing attacks of patients suffering from allergic rhinitis 
  <a rid="bib0380" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0380">
   <span class="sup">25</span>
  </a>. In nasal congestion, the mucosa of nose and para-nasal sinuses becomes swollen, and this condition is associated with edema, mucus secretion and difficult breathing. The inflammatory disorders like sinusitis, otitis, bronchitis or asthma may be the reason of nasal congestion. Therefore, the significant suppression of nasal congestion may improve the clinical sign of sinusitis. The clinical evidence about preventive and bronchodilatory effects of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil on obstructive respiratory diseases are attributed to its anti-inflammatory, and antioxidant effects of its oil or oil components 
  <a rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0385">
   <span class="sup">26</span>
  </a>. This beneficial effects of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil in sinusitis could be attributed to these anti-inflammatory and antioxidant effects. The anti-inflammatory effects of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil is attributed to its antioxidant activity. The antioxidant effects of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil were confirmed 
  <a rid="bib0335" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0335">16</a>, 
  <a rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0385">26</a>. Therefore, the antioxidant, anti-histaminic and anti-inflammatory effects of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil and main components decrease the inflammation of sinuses and respiratory airways, and inhibit the nasal congestion, edema, coryza as the clinical signs of sinusitis.
 </p>
</sec>
