<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent years have witnessed a growth in herbal medicine inquiries to replace conservative treatments or use them as supportive medications for numerous diseases [
 <xref rid="B1-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Diseases of oral and dental structures have not been an exception. Investigators have performed numerous experiments that examined the function of NS and TQ as its main active constituent in different areas of dental science [
 <xref rid="B1-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. NS and TQ display abundant potential therapeutic properties on diverse oral conditions. Besides its anticariogenic effects [
 <xref rid="B1-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], NS and its constituent TQ play a significant role in the prevention and treatment of periodontal diseases as previewed in the current evaluation [
 <xref rid="B62-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Frequent examinations have evaluated the sensitivity of periodontal and oral pathogens against NS extracts and TQ, and displayed outcomes equal to or enhanced than the antibiotics regularly used during treatment or regular periodontal treatment only [
 <xref rid="B67-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Moreover, several studies conducted on animals [
 <xref rid="B64-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], as well as humans [
 <xref rid="B62-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-antioxidants-09-01260" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], have reported the palpable advantages of using NS and TQ for periodontal disease prevention and treatment, besides the regular scaling and root planning, on clinical, molecular and histological levels. As explained in the current review, such periodontal health favoring effects of TQ and NS extracts seem to be encouraged through the distinct antibacterial, antioxidant/inflammatory and potentially regenerative mechanisms of these rich natural compounds. However, further detailed studies on NS and TQ-mediated periodontitis treatment are required at the cellular and molecular levels to investigate the exact mechanisms of action of NS and its constituents, as well as to provide an extended overview on the effects of these compounds in combinations with other periodontal-related therapies and medications. According to the current status of periodontal studies investigating TQ and NS, the authors of this review would recommend an intra-pocket TQ gel application (0.1–0.2%) as a natural adjunctive procedure to regular periodontal therapy. As topical administration of (0.1–0.2%) TQ has presented beneficial results of periodontal health in almost all available studies on in vivo (animal), in vitro and RCT levels (
 <xref rid="antioxidants-09-01260-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), this mode of TQ application seems to be the currently safest and most beneficial to periodontal patients. Overall, the reports that examined the role of 
 <italic>NS</italic> and TQ are still initial and might need further elaboration and expansion, especially on RCT level, but the current outcomes revealed an extraordinary potential of future therapeutic integration of these natural compounds into the regular periodontal therapy.
</p>
