<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Fermentation is a metabolic process in which carbohydrates are oxidized to liberate energy in the absence of external electron acceptor. This process is one of the oldest and most economical techniques applied in food preservation and processing (
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">124</xref>). Fermented foods, produced and consumed since the development of human civilizations, form part of normal human diet (
 <xref rid="B125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">125</xref>). The original purpose of fermentation was the preservation effect. Subsequently, with the development of numerous available preservation technologies, plenty of fermented foods were therefore manufactured because of their unique flavors, aromas, and textures that are much appreciated by consumers. The fermentation of cereals plays a vital role in the production of compounds of great influence on the organoleptic characteristics (such as aroma, taste, and texture) and on the improvement of nutritional properties with a final positive impact on human health (
 <xref rid="B126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">126</xref>). Microorganisms are found in almost all ecological niches; cereals and pseudocereals are, in general, a good medium for microbial fermentations. They are rich in polysaccharides, which can be used as a source of carbon and energy by microorganisms during fermentation. Besides carbohydrates, they also contain minerals, vitamins, sterols, and other growth factors (
 <xref rid="B127" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">127</xref>). Fermented products prepared from more common cereals (such as rice, wheat, corn, or sorghum) and pseudocereals are widespread around the world (
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">128</xref>–
 <xref rid="B130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">130</xref>). In certain developing countries such as Asia and Africa, high consumption of cereals was reported where these grains are mixed with legumes to improve overall protein quality of the final fermented products (
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">131</xref>). Cereal and pseudocereal grains normally have an indigenous microbiota composed by molds, LAB, enterobacteria, aerobic spore formers, etc., which compete for nutrients. The type of microbiota present in each fermented food depends on the pH value, water activity, salt concentration, temperature and composition of the food matrix (
 <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">132</xref>).
</p>
