<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Mitochondrial lipid composition is mostly shared by all different mammalian cells and tissues and is characterized by: (i) Low PL to protein ratio and sterol to protein ratio versus other subcellular fractions. (ii) High levels of PtdCho and PtdEtn (major PL members near 80% of total PL); (iii) High CL content (10%–15% of total lipid composition), and (iv) Low sterols and SL amounts (reviewed in [
 <xref rid="B72-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>]). The bacterial origin of this membrane is revealed by the occurrence, in the IMM, of PtdGro and of CL (up to 25 mol%) and by the high PtdEtn/PtdCho ratio. In turn, those two features might be mandatory for oxidative phosphorylation [
 <xref rid="B81-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>]. Regarding the low sterol content of mitochondria, an exception is found in cells implicated in steroid hormone synthesis. The mitochondria of those cell types coordinate with the ER for the importing and metabolization of cholesterol [
 <xref rid="B82-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>]. Other exceptions are mitochondria from heart, brain and other tissues which additionally contain 5%–30% of total PL of PtdCho and PtdEtn plasmalogens [
 <xref rid="B83-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>,
 <xref rid="B84-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>]. Plasmalogens are a class of PL whose structure confers to them strong lipophilic properties. This feature of plasmalogens allows them to generate inverse hexagonal phase structures, which in turn promote membrane fusion [
 <xref rid="B85-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>,
 <xref rid="B86-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>]. Plasmalogens are the major membrane lipid in neurons [
 <xref rid="B86-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>,
 <xref rid="B88-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>] and, in specific tissues, they are crucial for the function of several transmembrane proteins and for membrane-related cholesterol transport both at the intracellular and extracellular levels [
 <xref rid="B86-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>,
 <xref rid="B88-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>].
</p>
