<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <p id="Par1">Medicinal plant production is most important than other agricultural plants due to their phytochemical compounds effects on human health. Paying attention to plant nutrition requirement is so important. In order to assess the effect of nitrate (NO
  <sub>3</sub>
  <sup>−</sup>) dosage supplies from two types of fertilizers on growth and phytochemical properties of 
  <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus, an experiment with completely simple design was carried out under greenhouse conditions. Two types of fertilizers (new invented nitrogen (N) slow release fertilizer and urea chemical fertilizer) at three dosages (50, 100, and 150 mM) were applied. Plant growth parameters and total phenolic (TPC), total flavonoids (TFC), polysaccarides content, essential oil content, caffeic acid derivatives, and anti-radical scavenging activities of 
  <italic>E. purpurea</italic> were assessed. The results showed the significant (
  <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.01) differences among treatments, both in growth and phytochemical properties. Using of N slow release, especially in 150 mM dosage, significantly increased all the plant growth and phytochemical properties. The dried 
  <italic>E. purpurea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus contained more caftaric acid (max 12.56 mg g
  <sup>−1</sup> DW) and chicoric acid (max 7.56 mg g
  <sup>−1</sup> DW) than other derivatives. Despite the impact of heavy metals on yield and growth of 
  <italic>E. purpurea</italic>, the concentration of all heavy metals and micronutrients (boron (B), cadmium (Cd), copper (Cu), iron (Fe), manganese (Mn), molybdenum (Mo), nickel (Ni), lead (Pb), and zinc (Zn)) in studied soil and fertilizer samples was less than United States Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA) limits of contamination. Based on the results, using of N slow release fertilizers can improve phytochemical properties of the plant due to its polymeric structure and can be a suitable substitution of chemical fertilizers, especially in medicinal plants growth.
 </p>
</abstract>
