<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we tested whether the geographic distribution structure and invasion success of the plant 
 <italic>Parkinsonia aculeata</italic> L. (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032323-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>) could be explained by a 
 <italic>JT</italic>, a 
 <italic>MS</italic> or a 
 <italic>JM</italic> plastic strategy. Genetic variation in 
 <italic>P. aculeata</italic> is low in Australia following its introduction, possibly as a single introduction from Venezuela, in the late 1800s 
 <xref rid="pone.0032323-Hawkins1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. However, it is now invasive in diverse habitats and its distribution spans a wide climatic gradient from the arid centre of Australia to the wet-dry tropics in the north. We tested whether phenotypic plasticity, acting through one or more of the proposed plastic strategies, contributed to this successful invasion. First we tested whether the allocation of resources between seed mass and seed number responded plastically to annual rainfall across a 
 <italic>ca.</italic> 1000 km rainfall gradient (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032323-g001">Fig. 1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032323.s001">Table S1</xref>) and between years for successions of abnormally wet and dry conditions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032323-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032323.s001">Table S1</xref>). We then tested whether increasing seed mass resulted in higher seed and seedling survival rates. A matrix population model (see life-cycle in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032323-g003">Fig. 3</xref>) 
 <xref rid="pone.0032323-Caswell2" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, which incorporated the observed plastic response, was then used to test whether the average plastic response could influence the geographic distribution (shape, breadth, dynamic) through 
 <italic>JT</italic>, 
 <italic>MS</italic> or 
 <italic>JM</italic> strategies, as predicted by theory. Finally, we assessed whether selection on the phenotypic response might result in further modifications in the species geographic distribution.
</p>
