<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">The increasing development of resistance of 
  <italic class="italic">Candida</italic> species to traditional drugs represents a great challenge to the medical field for the treatment of skin infections. Essential oils were recently proposed to increase drug effectiveness. Herein, we developed and optimized (2
  <sup class="sup">3</sup> full factorial design) Mediterranean essential oil (
  <italic class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Lavandula</italic> x 
  <italic class="italic">intermedia</italic> “Sumian”, 
  <italic class="italic">Origanum vulgare</italic> subsp. 
  <italic class="italic">hirtum</italic>) lipid nanoparticles for clotrimazole delivery, exploring the potential synergistic effects against 
  <italic class="italic">Candida</italic> spp. Small sized nanoparticles (&lt;100 nm) with a very broad size distribution (PDI &lt; 0.15) and long-term stability were successfully prepared. Results of the in vitro biosafety on HaCaT (normal cell line) and A431 (tumoral cell line), allowed us to select 
  <italic class="italic">Lavandula</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">Rosmarinus</italic> as anti-proliferative agents with the potential to be used as co-adjuvants in the treatment of non-tumoral proliferative dermal diseases. Results of calorimetric studies on biomembrane models, confirmed the potential antimicrobial activity of the selected oils due to their interaction with membrane permeabilization. Nanoparticles provided a prolonged in vitro release of clotrimazole. In vitro studies against 
  <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Candida krusei</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">Candida parapsilosis</italic>, showed an increase of the antifungal activity of clotrimazole-loaded nanoparticles prepared with 
  <italic class="italic">Lavandula</italic> or 
  <italic class="italic">Rosmarinus</italic>, thus confirming nanostructured lipid carriers (NLC) containing Mediterranean essential oils represent a promising strategy to improve drug effectiveness against topical candidiasis.
 </p>
</abstract>
