<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Insect FA profiles may vary greatly according to the insect species and the substrates used for their rearing [
 <xref rid="B12-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>], which can in turn influence the fish product FA. Insect larva lipid profiles are rich in saturated fatty acids (SFA) and poor in polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA), the most important ones for human health being eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA). As a consequence of the high content of SFA that characterizes HI larvae, freshwater fish fed increasing levels of HI meal showed increased contents of SFA (mostly lauric acid, C12:0) and decreased contents of valuable PUFA (both n-3 and n-6) [
 <xref rid="B18-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B86-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="B88-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>]. However, different results have been reported for HI-fed Atlantic salmon. Increasing levels of HI meal inclusion in their diets in fact led to either a decrease [
 <xref rid="B84-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>] or an increase [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] in the n-3/n-6 ratio, as well as an increase in the EPA and DHA contents [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. TM larvae are characterized by high oleic, linoleic and palmitic acid contents [
 <xref rid="B87-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>]. Therefore, fish-fed diets with high levels of TM meal showed increased n-6 PUFA contents, to the detriment of the n-3 PUFA contents, with a consequent reduction in the Σn-3/Σn-6 FA ratio and a worsening of the atherogenicity and thrombogenicity indexes [
 <xref rid="B10-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>].
</p>
