<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Since insect meal utilization in fish diets may lead to remarkable changes in the FA composition of the fillets, the sensory properties of fish products may also vary (in particular the aroma and flavor, which are closely related to the dietary lipid-volatile components) [
 <xref rid="B89-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>]. The training of panelists may significantly affect their capability of perceiving sensory differences, even though the so-far performed panel tests have led to similar results between trained and untrained panelists. The first available data revealed unaffected sensory parameters (perceived by both trained and untrained panelists) for rainbow trout [
 <xref rid="B44-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] and Atlantic salmon [
 <xref rid="B84-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>] fed HI pre-pupa and larva meals, respectively. Untrained panelists also identified no significant differences in terms of taste and odor in HI-fed rainbow trout, while a darker fillet color was perceived in fish fed insect meal than in the fish of the control diet [
 <xref rid="B43-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. On the contrary, small to significant changes in the odor, flavor, color and texture characteristics were identified by trained panelists for rainbow trout [
 <xref rid="B89-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>] and Atlantic salmon [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] fed HI larva meal. Moreover, the fillets from HI-fed rainbow trout (inclusion levels ranging from 20 to 40%) were characterized by the onset of a dominance of a metallic flavor [
 <xref rid="B89-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>], whereas a prominent rancid odor was observed for baked fillets of Atlantic salmon fed the highest inclusion level (100%) of HI larva meal in their diets [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>].
</p>
