<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent years, clinical researches of natural polysaccharides on anti-HBV have increased gradually; they have been proved to have significant anti-HBV effect [
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Lentinan polysaccharide has a prominent effect on antiviral and immune regulation and is also used as an auxiliary drug for cancer and HBV [
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Zhao et al. [
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>] obtain two polysaccharide fractions (LEP-1 and LEP-2) from 
 <italic>Lentinus edodes</italic> (Berk.) sing. They found that LEPs possess potent anti-HBV activity 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. In addition, the polysaccharides from 
 <italic>Hedyotis caudatifolia</italic> Merr.et Metcalf (50, 100, and 200 mg/L) significantly inhibited the secretion and expression of HBV-DNA on HepG 2.2.15 cells and effectively inhibited the secretion of HBsAg and HBeAg. Its mechanism may be related to the activation of JAK/STAT signaling pathway and the promotion of antiviral protein expression [
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Zhan et al. [
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>] found that snail polysaccharides have a certain inhibitory effect on the replication of HBV-DNA (
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01), which indicated that the maximum inhibition rate of HBsAg and HBeAg in HepG 2.2.15 cells is 42.8% and 52.1%, respectively, slightly below the positive control group (
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and the inhibition effect of snail polysaccharide on HBeAg was better than that of HBsAg. The results of real-time fluorescence quantitative PCR test showed that snail polysaccharide had a certain inhibitory effect on the replication of HBV-DNA (
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.011). The anti-HBV effect of polyporus polysaccharide may be related to the regulation of the body's immune function, breaking the body's immune tolerance or low state [
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. 
 <italic>Angelica sinensis</italic> polysaccharide [
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>] could promote DC mature of HBV transgenic mice, raise its coordinated stimulus molecules on the surface, enhance its promoting lymphocyte proliferation and secretion, strengthen its antigen oral ability, induce cellular immune response, reduce serum concentrations of HBsAg, and play a role in antiviral immunity. Liu et al. [
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>] extracted Chinese whelk polysaccharide by water extraction and transfected human hepatocellular carcinoma cells with HBV-DNA cloning as an experimental model. The results showed that PCC significantly inhibited HBV-DNA in HepG 2.2.15 cells at 0.1 mg·mL
 <sup>−1</sup> and 1 mg·mL
 <sup>−1</sup>. Xia et al. [
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>] investigated the effect of polysaccharides of 
 <italic>Sipunculus nudus</italic> Linnaeus on anti-HBV; the results showed that polysaccharide with different dose groups were different degree of inhibition of HBV-DNA replication (
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and the effects of high, middle dose group were similar to acyclovir.
</p>
