<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The isolated pathogen was inoculated in the surface-sterilized and healthy kiwifruit. The results showed that the sample was attacked after inoculating 24 h at 25°C because of brown dots on the surface of fruit. Then the lesion rapidly expanded and showed drying shrinkage and depression on the 5th day. The color of pericarp turned to dim and pink, and then sticky particulates on pathogenic sites, which were the conidial heaps. Finally, as the decay spread out, the whole of fruit was brown rot and even dried. According to the morphological and molecular identification, the pathogen from ‘Hongyang’ kiwifruit was further determined as 
  <span class="italic">C. acutatum.</span> Previous studies found that 
  <span class="italic">C. musae</span> occurring anthracnose could cause the development of black circular/ lenticular spots during ripening in banana (
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">Barrera-Necha et al., 2008</a>). So far, to best of our knowledge, there were no reports on 
  <span class="italic">C. acutatum</span> from ‘Hongyang’ kiwifruit.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oil showed a superior antimicrobial activity that the growth of tested organisms was inhibited more efficiently by gaseous contact than by solution contact (
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">Inouye et al., 2003</a>; 
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">Oonmetta-Aree et al., 2006</a>). Therefore, in this study, the antifungal activity of CEO was carried out with its volatile substances, and the antifungal effect was good. The results showed that CEO exhibited antifungal activity against 
  <span class="italic">C. acutatum</span> as a volatile 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span>. Both MIC and MFC of CEO were 0.200 μL/mL. These results confirmed other findings on antifungal activity of CEO against several fungal pathogens including 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus flavus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Penicillium expansum</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Zygosaccharomyces rouxii</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Zygosaccharomyces bailii in vitro</span> (
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">Manso et al., 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">Ribeiro-Santos et al., 2017</a>; 
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">Ribes et al., 2017</a>). CEO had a strong antifungal effect against 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus flavus</span>, with a MIC of 0.05–0.10 mg/mL, and a MFC of 0.05–0.20 mg/mL (
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">Manso et al., 2013</a>). The MIC of CEO against 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus flavus</span> strains and 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus oryzae</span> were 0.125 μL/mL and 0.250 μL/mL, respectively (
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">Kocevski et al., 2013</a>). CEO could effectively inhibit the growth of 
  <span class="italic">Botryosphaeria parva</span> in the dilution method, and both MIC and MFC of CEO were 0.078 μL/mL (
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">He et al., 2015</a>). Volatiles of CEO obviously affected appressorium formation, while in control treatment germinal spores formed one or more appressoria. Results showed that inhibitory activity of CEO was significantly correlated with the concentration of CEO. In present study, the spore germination was more sensitive to CEO treatment than mycelial growth, which was in accordance with previous studies (
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">Duduk et al., 2015</a>). CEO had a fungistatic effect against mycelial growth of 
  <span class="italic">C. acutatum</span> isolated from strawberry anthracnose at 0.667 μL/mL. Meanwhile, CEO completely prevented the spore germination and appressorium formation at 0.00153 μL/mL (
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">Duduk et al., 2015</a>). In addition, CEO strengthens its merits as a post-harvest fungicide against food-borne pathogens. Moreover, the MIC and MFC of CEO against 
  <span class="italic">Colletotrichum</span> sp. were lower than those of some earlier reported EO viz., 
  <span class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</span> L. (
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">Zambonelli et al., 1996</a>), clove [
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> (L.)] (
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">Ranasinghe et al., 2002</a>) and tea tree oil (
  <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">Szczerbanik et al., 2007</a>). These results indicated that CEO had high potential of economic exploitation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The potential mechanisms underlying the antifungal activity of plant essential oils are not fully understood, but a number of possible mechanisms have been proposed. The results of TEM indicated that the CEO destroyed not only the CW, but also the PM, by interacting with the structures of cytoplasmic organelles in comparison with untreated samples. The degree of damage had dose-effect relationship, and that destructiveness of 2MFC was stronger than MFC. The CEO showed antifungal activity against 
  <span class="italic">C. acutatum</span> causing cellular damages and irreversible morphological changes. Previous studies revealed morphological alterations in 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus flavus</span> by TEM observations (
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">Nogueira et al., 2010</a>). Results showed that a marked disruption of membranes of major organelles such as nuclei, mitochondria and endoplasmic reticulum, indicated that 
  <span class="italic">Ageratum conyzoides</span> EO passed not only through the CW, but also through the PM and then interacted with membranous structures of the cytoplasmic organelles. Studies also reported irreversible damage to CW, CM and organelles of 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus flavus</span> by 
  <span class="italic">Cinnamomum jensenianum</span> essential oil (CJEO) (
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">Tian et al., 2012</a>). In the CJEO-treated hyphae, the fibrillar layers had gradually lost their integrity, becoming thinner, and eventually failing to deposit on the CW. In addition, the mitochondria suffered a severe disruption of the internal structure with complete lysis. Indeed, studies demonstrated that the TTO could destruct for organelles of 
  <span class="italic">Botrytis cinerea</span> by TEM observation (
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">Yu et al., 2015</a>). The PM appears to be the main target of the EO according to TEM data. Furthermore, FMS observation showed that the propidium iodide could permeate CM into intracellular cytoplasm while cells were destroyed. Then CEO was responsible for a fungicidal effect, resulting in extensive lesion to the plasmatic membrane, either from a direct effect or as a secondary result of metabolic impairment. Results showed that CEO could be used as a fungicide to damage membrane integrity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to confirm the CEO targets in the PM, the amount of ergosterol was assessed. Ergosterol is the major sterol component of the fungal CM, helping to maintain cell function and integrity (
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">Vale-Silva et al., 2010</a>). It is a sterol with a CM specific of fungi and microalgae with the advantage of indicating only viable biomass, since it is quickly degraded after the cell’s death (
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">Gutarowska and Zakowska, 2009</a>). The correlation between ergosterol and biomass of several fungal species has been confirmed (
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">Khan et al., 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">Silva et al., 2010</a>). Previous studies suggested that the PM was the main target of EOs against fungi, and that the oil caused dose-dependent reduction in ergosterol quantity (
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">Tian et al., 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">Yu et al., 2015</a>). Our results supported a model in which cellular membranes were the primary targets for CEO with different concentrations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The lipophilicity of EOs enable them to preferentially part from an aqueous phase into membrane structures of the fungi, resulting in expansion of membrane, and then increase of membrane fluidity and permeability, disturbance of membrane-embedded proteins and soluble sugars, and other cellular contents. The electric conductivity was examined to express the changes of CM permeability. Our results showed that the extracellular conductivity rose with the increasing of CEO concentration and treatment time. The results clearly indicated that there was a leakage of electrolytes due to the disruption of cell permeability caused by CEO. Excessive electrolyte loss would cause the death of 
  <span class="italic">C. acutatum.</span> This slight increase for control might be due to regular fungal cytolysis and death, just as 
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">Diao et al. (2014)</a> and 
  <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">Zhang et al. (2016)</a>. The integrity of the cytoplasmic membrane is a critical factor to fungal growth. Analyzing the leakage of cell constituents could therefore give further insight into the mechanism of antifungal action. The ability of CEO to disturb the integrity of the PM of fungal cells was also assessed by measuring the protein, sugar, and nucleic acid released in cell suspensions. Results showed that the leakage increased with the extension of treatment time.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antifungal property of EO may be contributed to its major components. 1, 8-cineole (56%) was the major component in 
  <span class="italic">Callistemon lanceolatus</span> (Sm.). Sweet essential oil, which showed great inhibitor effect against fungi (
  <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">Shukla et al., 2012</a>). (
  <span class="italic">E</span>)-cinnamaldehyde was found as the major component in cinnamon leaf volatile oil, which possessed crucial inhibitory activity (
  <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">Singh et al., 2007</a>). The compositions of CEO are greatly influenced by the species, part of plant used, geographic origin, time of harvest, stage of development, age of plants and extraction method (
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">Lee et al., 2005</a>). Twenty components in CEO extracted from bark was identified, and twenty-one components of CEO extracted from leaf was identified. The major components of bark EO are methyl cinnamate (81.87%), linalool (3.90%) and α-pinene (2.41%). The major components of leaf volatile oil are linalool (67.60%), methyl cinnamate (17.32%) and α-pinene (2.74%) (
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">Malsawmtluangi et al., 2016</a>). Previous studies have validated that the major components of CEO are 
  <span class="italic">trans</span>-cinnamaldehyde or cinnamaldehyde (
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">Goñi et al., 2009</a>), which were consistent with our results (
  <span class="bold">Table 
   <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">1</a>
  </span>). Furthermore, the content of 
  <span class="italic">trans-</span>cinnamaldehyde (86.16%) in our study was much higher than that of previous studies (
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">Lv et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Li et al., 2013</a>). It remains to be further defined whether major components are the main antifungal composition.
 </p>
</sec>
