<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Isolation and Identification of Pathogens</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the tissue separation method (
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">Jogee et al., 2017</a>), the surface of the spoiled ‘Hongyang’ kiwifruits was washed with sterile double-distilled water (SDW), and disinfested in 75% ethanol for 30 s and in 1% sodium hypochlorite for 30 s, and then rinsed three times in SDW. Then, pieces of kiwifruit sarcocarp about 4 mm
  <span class="sup">2</span> were excised from diseased berries with a sterile scalpel from the marginal area between the diseased and healthy tissue. The pieces were incubated on PDA. After isolation, the purified fungi were cultivated on PDA. After incubation at 25°C for 7 days, colonial morphology including micromorphological features, viz., color of colony on both of dorsal and ventral sides, growth diameter and texture of colony, and some microscopic features like mycelial size and conidial shape were measured. The isolated pathogen was assayed its pathogenicity in ‘Hongyang’ kiwifruit. Further, the pathogen was isolated again from diseased kiwifruits using the above tissue separation method. Finally, the pathogen was subcultivated on PDA and stored at 4°C for consequent identification. The isolated pathogen was coded as WQ1. The pathogen was deposited in Agricultural Culture Collection of China, and the accession number was ACCC 
  <span ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="39342" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">39342</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The isolate was grown on potato dextrose broth (PDB) with 140 r/min at 25°C for 5 days. The genomic DNA of mycelia was extracted by kit (Eppendorf, Holstein City, Germany). The internal transcribed spacer (ITS) regions and the small subunit (ITS1-5.8S-ITS2) of the rDNA genes were amplified using the primer set ITS1 (5′-TCCGTAGGTGAACCTGCGG-3′) and ITS4 (5′-TCCTCCGCTTATTGATATGC-3′) (
  <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">Zhao et al., 2010</a>). Primers were synthesized by Shanghai Sangon Biological Engineering Technology &amp; Services Co., Ltd (Shanghai, China). PCR amplification was carried out in aqueous volumes of 25 μL. The reactions contained 0.5 μL template DNA (30 ng), 0.5 μL (10 μmol/L) of each primer, 5 × PCR buffer (with MgCl
  <sub>2</sub>) 2.5 μL, 0.5 μL dNTP (2.5 mmol/L), 0.5 μL Taq polymerase (2.5 U/μL) and 20 μL ddH
  <sub>2</sub>O. PCR reactions were performed on a ABI 2720 thermal cycler (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, United States). Thermal cycling was carried out using an initial denaturation step at 98°C for 3 min, followed by 30 cycles of denaturation at 98°C for 25 s, annealing at 55°C for 25 s and extension at 72°C for 60 s. Cycling was completed by a final elongation step at 72°C for 10 min. PCR products were purified using PCR purification kit (Shanghai Sangon Biological Engineering Technology &amp; Services Co., Ltd, Shanghai, China). Sequencing was performed with an ABI 3730XL automated sequencer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, United States). Further, the sequence was analyzed and determined to search for similar sequences from the Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST) software
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn01" href="#fn01">1</a>
  </span> algorithm at National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). To construct the relevant phylogenic tree, MEGA 5.02 software was employed (
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">Saitou and Nei, 1987</a>; 
  <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">Tamura et al., 2007</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
