<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The development of vegetation in the vicinity of the “Wójcice” mine has the character of primary succession because it begins on bare ground without a plant cover. Several different directions of the succession and stages of vegetation in the vicinity of the mine can be distinguished (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00040-f004">Figure 4</xref>). These are facilitation processes that mainly result in the modification of the habitat by pioneer species [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-10-00040" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The direction of succession primarily depends on the hydration and type of substrate material, which is well illustrated by comparing not only the vegetational gradient (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00040-f002">Figure 2</xref>A) but also the effect on the species composition and differences in the fraction of floatable parts (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00040-f002">Figure 2</xref>B). The floatable parts correlated with the first CCA axis. While we did not determine moisture, its indirect proxy is the fraction of floatable parts. The higher the content of the fractionable fraction, the more the substratum absorbs water. Therefore, it is not surprising that mainly rush vegetation develops (reed and canary beds) on the clay material. On the other hand, there are sandy places that are overgrown with plants that are typical for sandy swards of the 
 <italic>Koelerio glaucae-Corynephoretea canescentis</italic> class that have a large contribution of 
 <italic>Corynephorus canescens</italic>. They develop best on sunny slopes where the soil temperature is higher. The high content of sands and gravels means that the substrate dries quickly even after heavy rains [
 <xref rid="B33-plants-10-00040" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In the area of the sandy sediments that are periodically flooded with pulp, there are places with a large fraction of floating parts, which can be seen as the outlier on 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00040-f003">Figure 3</xref>. At the bottom of the sedimentation tank, which carry a lot of clay materials, periodic rivers occur. The sandy grasslands in the vicinity of the mine are quite species poor. The plots had an average of 9.1 species and the average value of the Shannon-Wiener index was 1.5. In the review paper by Sienkiewicz-Paderewska [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-10-00040" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], the examined communities of the 
 <italic>Koelerio glaucae-Corynephoretea canescentis</italic> class were characterized by an average number of species in the phytosociological relevé between 8.0 and 18.6 and the value of the Shannon-Wiener index was 1.5 and 3.5. The observed patches of grasslands in the vicinity of the mine are close to the lower values in that paper. In the patches of the grasslands of the vicinity of the sandy mine, there are several variants of the initial stages with 
 <italic>Corynephorus canescens</italic>, 
 <italic>Saponaria officinalis</italic>, 
 <italic>Oenothera biennis</italic>, and 
 <italic>Senecio viscosus</italic>. There are also intermediate patches that contain a mosaic of the above-mentioned species. The presence of the 
 <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic> is noteworthy because it is an ephemerophyte, a species that was introduced into Poland in 1825, which probably originated in Africa. Although it is still not naturalized, it has over 30 stands in Poland mainly in sandy areas [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-10-00040" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].
</p>
