<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The requirement for productive and sustainable agriculture is highly urgent with the rapid growth of the world population [
 <xref rid="B1-polymers-11-00454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Fertilizer is one of the important input materials for crop production [
 <xref rid="B2-polymers-11-00454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. However, the nutrient utilization efficiency from pure fertilizers is markedly reduced due to the volatilization and leaching of nutrients [
 <xref rid="B3-polymers-11-00454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. According to statistics [
 <xref rid="B4-polymers-11-00454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-polymers-11-00454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>], the effective utilization of nitrogen (N) fertilizer is very low (30–50%). The wasting of N fertilizer not only causes economic losses but also negatively affects our environment [
 <xref rid="B6-polymers-11-00454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-polymers-11-00454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Therefore, great efforts have been made to develop polymer coated fertilizers (PCF) with controlled-release behaviors. Notably, PCF can not only enhance crop yield but also reduce nutrient loss to the surrounding environment [
 <xref rid="B8-polymers-11-00454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Previous research work [
 <xref rid="B9-polymers-11-00454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>] indicated that the application of PCF could increase the average utilization rate of fertilizer by 60%–80%. Especially, the nutrient components of fertilizer lost by leaching and infiltration can be reduced, and this can effectively reduce the frequency of fertilizer use compared with commercial fertilizers. In addition, the water quality will also be will improved because of the controlled-release behavior of PCF [
 <xref rid="B10-polymers-11-00454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]
 <styled-content style="color:blue" class="styled-content">.</styled-content>
</p>
