<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Nuptial gift extractions from five species of leiobunine harvestmen confirmed the presence of free amino acids in varying combinations and concentrations. The primary contributing amino acids from all five species were alanine, threonine, isoleucine, glutamine, and serine, with secondary contributors composed of glycine, cysteine, glutamic acid, valine, phenylalanine, and tyrosine. This profile is very different from what has been observed in crickets, in which the most abundant free amino acids in spermatophores were glycine and proline (Warwick et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Gershman et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Jarrige, Body, Giron, Greenfield, &amp; Goubault, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). One factor that could cause this difference in nuptial gift makeup is variation in sensory/gustatory factors; some literature reports that ability and perception of taste vary widely among taxa (Gordesky‐Gold, Rivers, Ahmed, &amp; Breslin, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Nelson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). Furthermore, if different harvestman species have gustatory preferences for different amino acids, it could account for the differences we detect between species in the current study. Trophic positions and differences in diets between crickets and harvestmen must also be considered. The chief source of nutrition in crickets comes from plant material, whereas harvestmen of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Leiobunum</italic> mainly eat small insects and worms (Acosta &amp; Machado, 
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Gaur (
 <xref rid="ece34232-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>) demonstrated that, on average, plants incorporate 5% more glycine, 3% more proline, and 5% less isoleucine into their nonmembrane proteins than invertebrates do. This pattern could account for some of the variations of free amino acid composition.
</p>
