<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As mentioned before, the inclusion of PKC at a higher level in the poultry diet decreases nutrient digestibility due to the higher fiber content of PKC [
 <xref rid="B17-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Kalmendal et al. [
 <xref rid="B71-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] reported that the presence of high levels of fiber in poultry diets negatively affect the surface, width, and height of intestinal villi, and subsequently affecting nutrient utilization negatively. This reduction in nutrient digestibility may be accompanied by an increase in feed intake [
 <xref rid="B42-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The birds’ poor performance was observed to be a result of high concentrations of neutral detergent fiber (NDF), acid detergent fiber (ADF), CF, and NSPs in the mentioned components [
 <xref rid="B17-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Additionally, increased fibers in poultry diets may also increase viscosity and passage of ingesta in the small intestines. Therefore, the utilization of nutrients such as CP, amino acids, and energy would be adversely affected [
 <xref rid="B17-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. High levels of fiber in broiler feeding diets could also negatively affect intestinal villi morphology [
 <xref rid="B71-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Hence, short villi resulted in an impaired absorption due to loss of intestinal surface area and, consequently, the overall growth performance [
 <xref rid="B2-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The increase in feed consumption by broilers feeding on higher PKC levels could be due to energy dilution in PKC that encourages chickens to consume adequate feed to meet their energy requirements [
 <xref rid="B63-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>].
</p>
