<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Except for cinnamon, other extracts had MIC values varying between 400 and 800 µg/mL. The susceptibility of screened extracts was found to be moderate to weak according to the classification of Kuete, where the activity is considered as significant (MIC &lt; 100 μg/mL), moderate (100 &lt; MIC &lt; 625 μg/mL), and weak (MIC &gt; 625 μg/mL) [
 <xref rid="B48-antibiotics-09-00790" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. There is a dearth of information on the biological activity of 
 <italic>M. urticifolia</italic>. However, it is expected to have antimicrobial activities attributed to phenolic compounds and hyaluronidase inhibitory phenylpropanoids [
 <xref rid="B32-antibiotics-09-00790" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-antibiotics-09-00790" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-antibiotics-09-00790" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. 
 <italic>Scutellaria baicalensis</italic> Georgi is used in the treatment of 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> infections, and it is advocated to be a source of new drugs against 
 <italic>H. pylori, which is</italic> closely related to 
 <italic>Campylobacter</italic> [
 <xref rid="B26-antibiotics-09-00790" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-antibiotics-09-00790" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. 
 <italic>Scutellaria baicalensis</italic> Georgi has also been reported to inhibit 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B52-antibiotics-09-00790" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Baicalein, a major compound from 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> Georgi, had a MIC of 32–64 µg/mL, which concurs with the previous report on 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B53-antibiotics-09-00790" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. 
 <italic>Mentha canadensis</italic> L., known as an antidiarrheic and antidysentery plant [
 <xref rid="B31-antibiotics-09-00790" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], has been reported to inhibit 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> and 
 <italic>C. jejuni</italic> [
 <xref rid="B30-antibiotics-09-00790" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-antibiotics-09-00790" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. It possesses monoterpenes, mainly menthol, which increases membrane permeability, leading to the loss of intracellular contents [
 <xref rid="B31-antibiotics-09-00790" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The antimicrobial activities of 
 <italic>S. plebeia</italic> on different pathogens have been extensively reported [
 <xref rid="B54-antibiotics-09-00790" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].
</p>
