<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As mentioned previously, polyphenols are natural compounds present in many vegetables and MAPs. In the human body, the majority of polyphenols have poor absorptions and they are retained in the intestine for more time where they can promote beneficial effects, specifically by affecting the gut microbiota [
 <xref rid="B96-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,
 <xref rid="B98-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. This leads to a mutual reaction between polyphenolic compounds and gut microbiota. The polyphenols are biotransformed into low-molecular-weight phenolic metabolites by gut microbiota resulting in an increase in polyphenol’s bioavailability, responsible for the health effects derived from the consumption of polyphenol-rich plants, which may differ from the native compound found in the plants [
 <xref rid="B97-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,
 <xref rid="B98-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>,
 <xref rid="B100-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>,
 <xref rid="B101-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>,
 <xref rid="B102-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. The properties of polyphenols are dependent on the bioactive metabolites produced when they are metabolised by the microbiota [
 <xref rid="B103-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. At the same time, specific polyphenols can modulate the gut microbial composition frequently by the inhibition of pathogenic bacteria and increase the growth of beneficial bacteria resulting in changes of gut microbial composition [
 <xref rid="B104-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,
 <xref rid="B106-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>,
 <xref rid="B107-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Finally, they may act as prebiotic metabolites and enhance the beneficial bacteria. It was demonstrated in animal studies that the consumption of polyphenols, especially catechin, anthocyanins, and proanthocyanidins, increases the abundance of 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, 
 <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic>, 
 <italic>Akkermansia</italic>, 
 <italic>Roseburia</italic>, and 
 <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic> spp. [
 <xref rid="B108-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. Prebiotics were defined in 1995 as “nondigestible food constituents that beneficially act in the host by selectively stimulating the growth and/or activity of one or a limited number of bacterial species, already resident in the colon” [
 <xref rid="B109-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Later, in 2010, prebiotics was defined as “a selectively fermented ingredient that allows specific changes, both in the composition and/or activity in the gastrointestinal microflora, benefits upon host well-being and health” [
 <xref rid="B110-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. Bioavailability of polyphenols is influenced by their structural characteristics, mainly by their degree of polymerisation [
 <xref rid="B111-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>,
 <xref rid="B112-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]—for example, proanthocyanidins are not absorbed by the intestinal mucosa [
 <xref rid="B112-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>], only aglycones and some glucosides can be absorbed [
 <xref rid="B113-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. Additionally, the prebiotic effect of each polyphenol can be influenced by the plant source and the characteristic of the chemical structure of the compound, along with the individual differences in gut microbiota compositions [
 <xref rid="B114-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>].
</p>
