<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To date, data are limited showing that omega-3 PUFA administration leads to benefits for behavioral disorders by modulating gut microbiota composition; the few studies on this subject, mostly completed in animal models, are summarized in 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="ijms-18-02645-t003" class="xref">Table 3</xref>. For instance, Pusceddu and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B99-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>] showed that long-term EPA/DHA administration can lead to a beneficial anti-inflammatory effect associated with a composition restoration of altered gut microbiota on maternal-separated rats. Particularly, maternal-separated rats showed an increase in 
 <italic class="italic">Bacteroidetes,</italic> and non-separated rats showed a decrease in 
 <italic class="italic">Firmicutes</italic>, in agreement with the results obtained by Jiang et al. [
 <xref rid="B88-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>] on depressed human patients. In these early-life-stressed rats, a long-term administration of EPA/DHA led to the restoration of the normal 
 <italic class="italic">Firmicutes/Bacteroidetes</italic> ratio. Furthermore, long-term EPA/DHA administration in separated mice improved the inflammatory condition typically associated with stress by increasing the abundance of butyrate-producing bacteria and decreasing the levels of pro-inflammatory bacterial genera, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Akkermansia</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Flexibacter,</italic> which have been reported to be related to an inflammatory state [
 <xref rid="B100-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>,
 <xref rid="B101-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>]. These taxa changes align with those noted in a previously-mentioned case report [
 <xref rid="B19-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Since inflammation plays an important role in depression, the gut microbiota shift observed in maternal-separated rats is likely protective of the behavioral disorders.
</p>
