<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0022">Recently, in India, it was suggested by the Ministry of AYUSH (Ayurvedic, Yoga and Naturopathy, Unani, Siddha and Homeopathy), to drink Kadha as a booster of immunity and lowering the tenderness caused during COVID-19 catastrophe (
 <xref rid="bib0153" ref-type="bibr">AYUSH Advisory, 2020</xref>). A Kadha is an extract prepared from less juicy or dry ingredients like spices and herbs. The Ministry of AYUSH with its conventional acquaintance has an extensive custom of maintenance of nation's health and its participation has augmented manifolds in this COVID-19 pandemic crisis (
 <xref rid="bib0153" ref-type="bibr">AYUSH Advisory, 2020</xref>). All ayurvedic healthcare professional generally recommend classical ayurveda medicine, however AYUSH-64 a novel formulation prepared by CCRAS provides resistance against malaria and other fevers. The decoction of sunthi (
 <italic>Zingiber officinaleRoscoe.</italic>), lavanga (
 <italic>Syzygium aromaticum</italic>) and maricha (
 <italic>Piper nigrum</italic>) have been recommended to the healthy as well as COVID-19 infected person, as it provides support in the humoral and cell mediated responses and also lowers the air way hyper responsiveness and nasal congestions (
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Carrasco et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0107" ref-type="bibr">Kim and Lee, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Bui et al., 2019</xref>). Various ayurvedic products and fatty acids in the form of ghee are implicated in the up-regulation of resistance. The resistance is enhanced in a pleiotropic manner and the bioactive compounds participate in various procedures of adaptive as well as innate immune responses (
 <xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">Shukla et al., 2014</xref>). Similarly, the bioactive constituent in 
 <italic>Curcuma longa Linn.</italic> i.e. curumin, is identified to block cytokine release, specifically interleukin-1, interleukin-6, pro-inflammatory cytokines and tumor necrosis factor-α and is directed to be consumed with milk (
 <xref rid="bib0171" ref-type="bibr">Omara et al., 2010</xref>). Inhibition of the cytokine discharge is one of the prime clinical development associated with experimental modules of flu and other infectious diseases and have also been compared to COVID-19 where similar cytokine storm play an imperative role in transience (
 <xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">Sordillo and Helson, 2015</xref>). Moreover, AYUSH has recommended certain preventive and medicinal plants for prevention and prophylactic of COVID-19 including warm extracts of 
 <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> (advised for chronic fever), 
 <italic>Andrograhis paniculata</italic> (advised for fever and cold), 
 <italic>Cydonia oblonga, Zizyphus jujube</italic> and 
 <italic>Cordia myxa</italic> (enhancing antioxidant, immune-modulatory, anti-allergic, smooth muscle relaxant, anti-influenza activity) and 
 <italic>Arsenicum album</italic> 30 (found effective against SARS-CoV-2, immune-modulator). The symptomatic management of COVID-19 was suggested to be acquired from Agastya Haritaki (prevention of upper respiratory infections and Anuthaila (sesame oil drops) recommended to prevent respiratory infections (
 <xref rid="bib0236" ref-type="bibr">Vellingiri et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
