<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0024">One of the commonly accepted traditional Chinese medicines is Kombucha, which is a concoction prepared from the culture of 
 <italic>Acetobacter</italic> and yeast. This concoction is prepared in black tea and Chinese herbal extract comprised of liquorice, green tea, chrysanthemum and 
 <italic>Grosvenor momordia</italic>, which acts as an effective probiotic (Greenwatt et al., 2000). Similar extract has been employed in treatment of foot and mouth disease virus. Moreover, their exist a wide array of reports suggesting utilization of herbal extracts in TCM such as extracts prepared from 
 <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib0111" ref-type="bibr">Kumar and Navaratnam, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0073" ref-type="bibr">Gupta et al., 2017</xref>), 
 <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib0213" ref-type="bibr">Song et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0112" ref-type="bibr">Kuzuhara et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0116" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2015</xref>), 
 <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> and 
 <italic>Agremone mexicana</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib0235" ref-type="bibr">Varshney et al., 2013</xref>), 
 <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">Shah and Krishnamurthy, 2013</xref>), 
 <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">Shah and Krishnamurthy, 2013</xref>), 
 <italic>Alium sativum</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib0108" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2006</xref>) and 
 <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">Kubiça et al., 2014</xref>) etc. for their antimicrobial potential. A corroborative suggestion was made by 
 <xref rid="bib0218" ref-type="bibr">Su et al. (2020)</xref>, that traditional Chinese herb i.e. 
 <italic>Exocarpium Citri grandis</italic> was found to be effective in preventing and treating COVID-19 pandemic. A novel approach to TCM is combination therapy in which the old traditional practices are mixed together to develop an effective formulation for treating various diseases. Combination treatment has been employed in suppression of viral hepatisis. Also liquid fermented broth of 
 <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> in combination with extract of 
 <italic>Radix Sophorae flavescentis</italic>, was affirmed to be effective against hepatitis B virus. Another vital example is glycyrrhizin a bioactive compound isolated from 
 <italic>Lycoris radiata</italic> shows a strong potential against anti-SARS-CoV activity (
 <xref rid="bib0118" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2005a</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0119" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>).
</p>
