<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A DPPH (2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl) stock solution (0.208 mM in 50% ethanol) was prepared and kept at 4°C in the dark, according to the method reported for High-Throughput RDSC assay [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Ethanol stock solutions of Trolox® (50%) (160 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>M),
 <italic class="italic"> P. carpunya</italic> EO (2 mg/mL), piperitone, limonene, 1,8-cineole, methyleugenol and thymol (20 mg/mL) were also prepared and stored at 4°C. Starting from the stock solutions, 96-well microplates were filled with 200 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L/well of the following samples progressively less concentrated (dilution ratio 1:2): (i)
 <italic class="italic"> P. carpunya</italic> EO + DPPH ethanol solution 50% (100 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L + 100 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L); (ii) Piperitone (limonene, 1,8-cineole, methyleugenol) + DPPH ethanol solution 50% (100 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L + 100 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L); (iii) Trolox® (or thymol) + DPPH ethanol solution 50% (100 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L + 100 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L; as positive control); (iv) DPPH ethanol solution 50% + ethanol 50% (100 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L + 100 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L; as negative control); (v) ethanol solution 50% (200 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L; as blank). The concentration ranges were as follows: 7.8-1000 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>g/ml for
 <italic class="italic"> P. carpunya</italic> EO, thymol, limonene, methyleugenol and 1,8-cineole; 78-10000 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>g/ml for piperitone; 0.6-80.0 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>M for Trolox and each concentration was tested in triplicate. 0.104 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>M was the DPPH concentration in all wells. The 96-well microplates were then incubated in agitation (100 rpm) for 40 min at room temperature in the dark. After incubation, the 96-microwells plates were checked with microplate reader (Microplate Reader 680 XR, Biorad) at 515 nm. Antioxidant activities were expressed as IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> (concentration providing DPPH 50% inhibition) and calculated from inhibition curves obtained by plotting inhibition percentage against EO and pure compounds concentration and as 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>mol/g of Trolox equivalent [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. All experiments were assessed in triplicate and values were reported as mean ± SD (standard deviation).
</p>
