<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>All polymerase chain reactions (PCR) for each microbial group (i.e., fungi, bacteria, oomycetes) were performed using subsamples of the same template genomic DNA sample. Genomic DNA was diluted to ensure equimolar concentration of template DNA in each PCR reaction. Bacterial amplicons were generated using primers described in Kozich et al. (
 <xref rid="ece36811-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), which target the V4 region of the 16S rRNA gene. Fungal amplicons were produced using primers described by Taylor et al. (
 <xref rid="ece36811-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), which target the ITS2 region of the 5.8S rRNA gene. Oomycete amplicons were generated using primers adapted from Riit et al. (
 <xref rid="ece36811-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>) and Taylor et al. (
 <xref rid="ece36811-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>) that also target the ITS2 region of the 5.8S rRNA gene. See Appendix 
 <xref rid="ece36811-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> Table 
 <xref rid="ece36811-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref> for specific primer sequences and PCR conditions. All PCR reactions were performed in triplicate using Phusion High Fidelity DNA Polymerase and master mix (New England BioLabs). Libraries were normalized using SequalPrep Normalization Plate Kit (Life technologies cat # A10510‐01) following the manufactures protocol for sequential elution. The concentration of the pooled samples was determined using Kapa Biosystems Library Quantification kit for Illumina platforms (Kapa Biosystems KK4824). The sizes of the amplicons in the library were determined using the Agilent Bioanalyzer High Sensitivity DNA analysis kit (cat# 5067‐4626). The final library consisted of equal molar amounts from each of the plates, normalized to the pooled plate at the lowest concentration. Amplicons were sequenced by the Microbial Systems Molecular Biology Laboratory (MSMBL) at the University of Michigan on the Illumina MiSeq platform, using a MiSeq Reagent Kit V2 500 cycles (Illumina cat# MS102‐2003), according to the manufacturer's instructions. Sequences were uploaded to the NCBI Sequence Read Archive under SRA accession number PRJNA601975.
</p>
