<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Plants from the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus</italic> are known for their antifungal properties (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Figueiredo et al., 2008</xref>). Indeed 
 <italic class="italic">T. vulgaris</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. zygis</italic> have a European Medicines Agency (EMA) monograph highlighting several effects including their antifungal ones (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">HMPC/EMA, 2010</xref>). Moreover, several thyme species are used in traditional medicine, namely 
 <italic class="italic">T. zygis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">T. mastichina</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">T. camphoratus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus carnosus</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus caespititius</italic>. These species are often employed for the treatment of infections and inflammation of the mouth, pharynx, skin, and genital tract as well as for the relief of rheumatism (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rivera and Obón, 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Carapeto, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Proença da Cunha et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Silva et al., 2011</xref>). Regarding 
 <italic class="italic">T. camphoratus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. carnosus</italic>, both species are traditionally used in Portugal for the treatment of infections of the respiratory tract (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">dos Santos, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Camejo Rodrigues, 2007</xref>). Although some studies on their essential oil composition (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Salgueiro et al., 1995</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1997</xref>) and biological effects have been reported (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Faleiro et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dandlen et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zuzarte et al., 2018</xref>), the knowledge regarding the antifungal potential of 
 <italic class="italic">T. camphoratus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. carnosus</italic> remains limited. Therefore, the present study was designed to unveil the antifungal activity of these essential oils and their major compounds against yeasts and filamentous fungi and concomitantly to elucidate the mechanisms of action underlying their potential antifungal effect. Importantly, the putative cytotoxicity of the essential oils to human keratinocytes was also assessed since this is a crucial step for further incorporation of these compounds in topical pharmaceutical formulations.
</p>
