<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">
   <italic>Kniphofia foliosa</italic> is a flamboyant robust perennial herb which has dense clumps and tick upright rhizomes with leaves at the base. In Ethiopia, it has several vernacular names including 
   <italic>Abelbila</italic>, 
   <italic>Ashenda</italic>, 
   <italic>Amelmela</italic>, 
   <italic>Yeznjero Ageda</italic>, 
   <italic>Shemetmetie</italic> and 
   <italic>Yezinjero Ageda</italic>. The plant is endemic to Ethiopian highlands, where its rhizomes are traditionally used for the treatment of malaria, abdominal cramps and wound healing. In the present study, the 80% methanol extract of 
   <italic>K. foliosa</italic> rhizomes and its constituents are tested against 
   <italic>Plasmodium berghei </italic>in mice
   <bold>.</bold>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2">Isolation was carried out using column and preparative thin layer chromatography (PTLC). The chemical structures of the compounds were elucidated by spectroscopic methods (ESI–MS, 1D and 2D-NMR). Peters’ 4-day suppressive test against 
   <italic>P. berghei </italic>in mice was utilized for in vivo anti-malarial evaluation of the test substances.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par3">Two compounds, namely knipholone and dianellin were isolated from the 80% methanolic extract of 
   <italic>K. foliosa</italic> rhizomes, and characterized. The hydroalcoholic extract (400 mg/kg) and knipholone (200 mg/kg) showed the highest activity with chemosuppression values of 61.52 and 60.16%, respectively. From the dose–response plot, the median effective (ED
   <sub>50</sub>) doses of knipholone and dianellin were determined to be 81.25 and 92.31 mg/kg, respectively. Molecular docking study revealed that knipholone had a strong binding affinity to 
   <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> l-lactate dehydrogenase (pfLDH) target.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par4">Results of the current study support the traditional use of the plant for the treatment of malaria.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
