<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, in Africa, the use of phytomedicines which is also referred to as herbal medicine or phytotherapy is well embraced in different Pan African territories where 80–90% of its rural populations rely on traditional medicines (mainly plant-based) for primary healthcare (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Elujoba et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B166" ref-type="bibr">Mahomoodally, 2013</xref>). The extensive use of the predominantly plant-derived traditional medicine in Africa otherwise referred to as Traditional African Medicine, has been described to be associated with African socio-economic and socio-cultural endowments (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Elujoba et al., 2005</xref>). For this reason, the WHO has continued to sensitize African Member states toward the integration of TAM into their health system (
 <xref rid="B166" ref-type="bibr">Mahomoodally, 2013</xref>) as the body recognizes the relevance of traditional, complementary and alternative medicine to Africa which has a long history of TAM and knowledgeable indigenous practitioners. For instance, there has been an unprecedented use of phytomedicines in Africa following the outbreak and global spread of COVID-19 pandemic, a situation which has been compounded by lack of authorized medicines that are effective, affordable and accessible to the populations coupled with a relatively weak African health sector (
 <xref rid="B159" ref-type="bibr">Lone and Ahmad, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B274" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2020</xref>). Coincidentally, available evidence from Africa Center for disease Control and Prevention (Africa CDC) suggests that the African continent is the last to be hit by the viral pandemic and least affected continent whose mortality rate (2.1%) until July 21, 2020 was less than half of the reported global mortality (5%) rate. Hence, despite the vulnerability of the African continent, it accounts for only 5% of the globally reported cases of COVID-19. While several factors may be attributable to this seeming positive trend, the near absolute dependence on the obvious potentials of the African medicinal plants for COVID-19 management may not be ruled out. As a malaria endemic region, the Sub-Saharan Africa often co-administer herbal remedies alone or combined with orthodox drugs as adjuvants and many of these plant-based medicines have since been informally repurposed by various users for COVID-19 prevention and symptomatic management as simple home remedies. Unlike the Traditional Chinese Medicine, there is a paucity of well reported studies on the impact of the widely embraced TAM adopted so far for the prevention, management and treatment of COVID-19. This review is therefore aimed at the documentation of African medicinal plants and their therapeutic potentials in the prevention and management of COVID-19. The potential risks associated with herb-drug interaction of antiviral phytomedicines when used in combination with orthodox drugs have been highlighted. In addition, we document the pharmacokinetic considerations in developing potential anti-COVID19 herbal products.
</p>
