<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Among the latest developments in antimicrobial emitters, a promising way to develop indirect contact anti-microbial packaging is the use of volatile compounds, encapsulated in RH-sensitive macromolecules that prevent release during storage in dry conditions. Once exposed to moisture, release of the molecule is triggered and then diffuses into the headspace toward the food surface where microbial growth usually takes place (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>). Although widely available on the Asian market (see for example the AITC-based Wasaouro
 <sup class="sup">TM</sup> film
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn0008" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">8</sup>
 </xref>, they are almost inexistent on the EU market (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>) because of more restrictive EU regulatory requirements (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>) and difficult efficacy optimization (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>) principally due to the complexity of the RH-triggered release mechanism. Among volatiles, organic aroma compounds from essential oil extracts such as allyl isothiocyanate (AITC) from mustard or carvacrol from oregano, have been proved to be particularly efficient on main microorganisms (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>–
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>) at doses that are below the detection threshold by sensory panel. Recently, setting up dedicated mathematical algorithms that predict the complex diffusion-reaction system and kinetic release toward headspace, Kurek et al. (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>) tailored active biodegradable material in such a way that it complies with the food requirements (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">3</xref>).
</p>
