<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Malaria is a leading cause of human mortality. In 2015, the World Health Organization (WHO)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> estimated that 212 million cases of malaria occurred, leading to 419 000 deaths – 82% of casualties are in sub-Saharan Africa. Children under the age of 5 account for 64% of victims. Malaria’s mortality rate dropped by 31% between 2010 and 2015 in Africa and the life expectancy of children under 5 increased by 1.2 years. However, in 80% of malaria endemic countries, mosquitos developed resistance to at least one insecticide. Furthermore, in Burundi, deaths have increased by 13% in the last year
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>, stunting economic growth
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> where the annual per capita income is lower than 400 USD
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span> and farmers hire labour at 1 USD a day. As with the mass drug administration of chloroquine, which contributed to the resurgence of malaria in Peru after 30 years of low incidence
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium falciparum</span> protozoa may develop resistance to artemisinin monotherapy
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. Mutations of the K13 gene are markers of artemisinin resistance but tetraoxane-based compounds have inhibitory characteristics against various strains of the protozoa
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Artesunate is more effective than quinine with fewer side effects but a child administered a high dose rectally died due to its toxicity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>. Moreover, Burke 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span> reported that 
  <span class="italic">Anopheles vaneedeni</span> became a new malaria vector complicating the fight against the disease.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Preventing rather than treating the disease is a better approach; sleeping under nets impregnated with insecticides has reduced the world mortality rate from 2 million a year; they save 5.5 per 1000 children yearly
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>. Insecticides are losing their efficacy due to increasing mosquito resistance
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, weather patterns like La Niña can cause unexpected peaks in mosquito populations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. Graves and Gelband
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span> tested SPf66, CS-NANP, RTS,S, MSP/RESA vaccines and their ability to prevent different stages of malaria. Theoretically, SPf66 and MSP/RESA protect against the asexual stages of plasmodium parasites whereas the other two target the sporozoite stages. CS-NANP and MSP/RESA offered no protection against malaria, SPf66 was ineffective and RTS,S reduced malaria episodes by 58%. Unfortunately, vaccines’ mass production and distribution is too expensive for sub-Saharan Africa
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, the mosquitos are changing their feeding patterns to adapt to the mosquito nets. Moiroux 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> demonstrated that mosquitos have adapted to insecticide treated nets by changing their biting habits. Proportion of outdoor biting increased from 45% to 68%
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. Thus, nets will be less effective for young children and pregnant women, who are the most vulnerable to the disease.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cutaneous mosquito repellents (MR) are one means to reduce the frequency of mosquito bites. N,N-diethyl-meta-toluamide (DEET) is an effective mosquito repellant
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span> but is cost prohibitive for rural sub-Saharan populations. Targeting indigenous plants as a source of mosquito repellents will stimulate local economies and at the same time protect the population. Odalo 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span> extracted and tested the topical repellency of essential oils indigenous to Kenya from 
  <span class="italic">Conyza newii (Compositae)</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Plectranthus marrubioides (Lamiaceae)</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Lippia javanica (Verbenaceae)</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Tetradenia riparia (Lamiaceae)</span>, as well as 
  <span class="italic">Tarchonanthus camphoratus (Asteraceae)</span>. The oils, under their experimental conditions (3 min, forearm exposure), repelled mosquitoes better than DEET. 
  <span class="italic">N. cataria</span>, commonly known as catnip or catmint, is a species of the Lamiaceae family. It is native to temperate and tropical zones in Asia and in Europe and is widely cultivated
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. 
  <span class="italic">Nepeta cataria</span> (
  <span class="italic">N. cataria</span>) has many uses in traditional medicine including treatment of chills, colds, constipation, headaches, infections, inflammations, rheumatism, sore throats, spasms, and stomach aches
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. 
  <span class="italic">N. cataria</span>’s essential oil possesses antibacterial and antimicrobial properties
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. Nepetalactone (NPL) is the major constituent of this oil
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. DEET, applied to the forearm, repelled 
  <span class="italic">Aedes aegypti</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Anopheles quadrimaculatus</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Anopheles albimanus</span> for 426 min, 96 min, and 87 min, respectively
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. A 25% volume fraction of DEET in ethanol repelled 
  <span class="italic">Aedes aegypti</span> for 8 h
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. Whereas, Bernier found that a dose of 0.5 mg cm
  <span class="sup">−2</span> of DEET applied to a muslin cloth patch was active for 24 h. Catnip’s oil is a better spatial repellent than DEET and demonstrated effective topical repellency properties
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">NPL is as active as DEET and its hydrogenated form – dihydronepetalactone – is two times more active than DEET when formulated with isopropyl alcohol (1% w/v)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. Among 41 different essential oils applied to skin, Catnip’s offered protection for 480 min
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Moreover, 
  <span class="italic">N. cataria</span> exhibits a more favorable safety profile than DEET
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. Local communities widely accept essential oil based MR. In Ghana, 97% of the studied population desired to continue applying the MR after the 3-month trial
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. Mng’ong’o 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span> found that six repellent plants essential oil were widely accepted by the population studied due to their efficacy.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introducing plant based mosquito repellents to vulnerable populations faces economic challenges but also societal and governmental hurdles. Furthermore, they must be nontoxic with respect to dermal and eye contact, ingestion, and inhalation. Unlike synthetic repellents, the chemical composition of essential oils, like 
  <span class="italic">N. cataria</span>, contain dozens of compounds (Supplemental information S1). The active ingredient must demonstrate its efficacy versus alternatives but they must also be stable with respect to UV exposure, oxidation and high temperature (&gt;40 °C). Moreover, to achieve the largest possible distribution at the lowest cost, local populations must grow, harvest and extract the active ingredients. Birkett and Pickett discovered the efficacy of nepetolactone and nepetolactol in repelling aphids. They distilled the catnip with steam and cyclohexane vapors then reduced the oil with NaBH
  <sub>4</sub>. In their concluding remarks, they emphasize the potential of plants as source of commercialy vailable products
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. Here we address the challenges of cultivating 
  <span class="italic">N. cataria</span> in Burundi and developing a topical mosquito repellent. We compare the composition of the essential oil versus those cultivated throughout the world and measure the thermal stability and its stability versus UV. Finally, we demonstrate that the population is ready to test the mosquito repellents formulated with vegetable oil or as Pickering emulsions based on an acceptability study we conducted in a rural and urban region of the country.
 </p>
</sec>
