<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="ab0005" class="abstract">
 <p class="p">Genetic engineering is a powerful tool to steer bio-oil composition towards the production of speciality chemicals such as guaiacols, syringols, phenols, and vanillin through well-defined biomass feedstocks. Our previous work demonstrated the effects of lignin biosynthesis gene modification on the pyrolysis vapour compositions obtained from wood derived from greenhouse-grown poplars. In this study, field-grown poplars downregulated in the genes encoding CINNAMYL ALCOHOL DEHYDROGENASE (
  <italic class="italic">CAD</italic>), CAFFEIC ACID O-METHYLTRANSFERASE (
  <italic class="italic">COMT</italic>) and CAFFEOYL-CoA O-METHYLTRANSFERASE (
  <italic class="italic">CCoAOMT</italic>), and their corresponding wild type were pyrolysed in a Py-GC/MS. This work aims at capturing the effects of downregulation of the three enzymes on bio-oil composition using principal component analysis (PCA). 3,5-methoxytoluene, vanillin, coniferyl alcohol, 4-vinyl guaiacol, syringol, syringaldehyde, and guaiacol are the determining factors in the PCA analysis that are the substantially affected by 
  <italic class="italic">COMT</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">CAD</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">CCoAOMT</italic> enzyme downregulation. 
  <italic class="italic">COMT</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">CAD</italic> downregulated transgenic lines proved to be statistically different from the wild type because of a substantial difference in S and G lignin units. The s
  <italic class="italic">CAD</italic> line lead to a significant drop (nearly 51%) in S-lignin derived compounds, while 
  <italic class="italic">CCoAOMT</italic> downregulation affected the least (7–11%). Further, removal of extractives via pretreatment enhanced the statistical differences among the 
  <italic class="italic">CAD</italic> transgenic lines and its wild type. On the other hand, 
  <italic class="italic">COMT</italic> downregulation caused 2-fold reduction in S-derived compounds compared to G-derived compounds. This study manifests the applicability of PCA analysis in tracking the biological changes in biomass (poplar in this case) and their effects on pyrolysis-oil compositions.
 </p>
</abstract>
