<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the search for ChE inhibitors with additional neuroprotective and antioxidant properties, Patel et al. reproposed the exploitation of the indole ring to build up novel multiactive structures, guided by the observation that melatonin, based on the same indole moiety, is endowed with free radical scavenging ability and neuroprotection against A
 <italic>β</italic>-induced toxicity [
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. They merged this ring with the 1,2,4-triazine scaffold, which is also a common feature for several drugs, and then explored the effects of thio- and amino-linked aryl/benzyl/aminoalkyl side chains (typified by 
 <bold>42</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14">Figure 14</xref>). All the compounds showed micromolar to submicromolar activity towards AChE and BuChE. Some of the most active analogues (IC
 <sub>50</sub> &lt; 5 
 <italic>μ</italic>M) showed antioxidant activity in the 1,1-diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) assay at concentrations ranging from 10 to 20 
 <italic>μ</italic>M, with moderate to good free radical scavenging activity (54.9-64.3%) compared to ascorbic acid. No cytotoxicity was observed in the SH-SY5Y cell line (up to 80 
 <italic>μ</italic>M) and in H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>- and A
 <italic>β</italic>-induced toxicity studies; compound 
 <bold>42</bold> exerted a substantial protection against the toxic insult in a concentration-dependent manner. Besides a very detailed computational analysis to establish the essential interactions and features required for the multitarget activity, confirming the key role of the triazinoindole core and the enhancement brought by the introduction of a basic center in the chain, the compound was tested for its cognitive improvement effect in animal models of AD. In scopolamine-induced amnesia in rodents, it showed spatial memory improvement in the Morris water maze learning test at doses of 5 and 10 mg/kg p.o. Moreover, in the A
 <italic>β</italic>-induced AD model, the lowered spontaneous alternations induced by A
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>1−42</sub> were significantly reversed at the same doses. The neurochemical analysis carried out on the scopolamine- and compound-treated animals contributed to confirm the ability of 
 <bold>42</bold> to reverse the reference and working memory deficit as well to manage the oxidative stress-induced dementia. If coupled with the notable 
 <italic>in silico</italic> ADMET properties, all these analyses highlighted the favorable potential for this analogue to be a useful treatment for AD-related deficiencies.
</p>
