<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The combination of a sulphonamide moiety with the core structure of Rutaecarpine, a well-known pentacyclic indolopyridoquinazolinone alkaloid from Chinese medicine, has been proposed by Wu et al. as a promising MTDL (
 <bold>43</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14">Figure 14</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. All these analogues had good to moderate concentration-dependent activity against BuChE in the 
 <italic>μ</italic>M range, being more potent than the parent compound but not as efficient as THA. They also resulted to be selective inhibitors of the abovementioned enzyme, with almost a null effect on AChE. At a concentration of 100 
 <italic>μ</italic>M, there was a significant effect in the DPPH free radical scavenger assay, with ascorbic acid and Donepezil used as reference antioxidants, underlying a mild scavenging activity. There was also a robust effect against intracellular ROS generation in H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>-treated SH-SY5Y and PC12 cells, where the compound treatment restored the ROS levels almost to the blank group, highlighting a neuroantioxidant potential. The same models and cell lines were used to assess neurotoxicity by measuring cell viability after incubation with increasing concentrations of the title compounds. In both of the cases, survival rate increased in a dose-dependent manner. Coincubation of A
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>42</sub> with the best performing analogue of the series resulted into interference with the peptide self-assembly process, and TEM analysis confirmed an antiaggregation effect comparable or superior to that of Donepezil at concentrations of 100 
 <italic>μ</italic>M. The presence of the carbonyl and sulfonamide groups in the compounds may have conferred chelating properties, and differences in the UV absorption at a peculiar wavelength indicated the capability to chelate Cu
 <sup>2+</sup> in a 1 : 1 stoichiometry. The newly introduced features in the Rutaecarpine scaffold led to a combination of interesting activities, placing this core and its analogues under the spotlight for further development as MTDLs against AD.
</p>
