<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For health concerns the food industry avails itself of increasingly more natural substances as food bio-additives. Due to processing and gastrointestinal conditions, there is a growing demand to initiate new processes and technologies suitable for their protection [
 <xref rid="B5-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], since these materials are commonly recognized as highly sensitive to the environment, like heat, light, oxygen, and moisture. One proposed tool that can ensure improved bioavailability, stability, and delivery of these materials is microencapsulation [
 <xref rid="B6-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], that can potentially prevent interaction with the food matrix and convert the applied ingredients into the easily handled, free-flowing, and dispersible powders. Taste masking is another aim of encapsulation. Essential fatty acids, for example, are highly valuable for health, however they have an unpleasant taste that can become a negative factor when overgoing oxidation process. This problem can be avoided by encapsulation in suitable vehicles. Pre-cooked food, for example, represents a large part of our consumption. Recomposed powders, long-term storage period, and the need for innovation have deeply changed the management of the products [
 <xref rid="B7-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. As mentioned previously, microencapsulation offers sustained and controlled release that can be prompted by different factors such as dissolution, temperature, pressure, pH, and enzymes, depending on wall material [
 <xref rid="B8-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The global food encapsulation market was estimated to account for US $9.9 billion in 2020 and is projected to surpass US $14 billion by 2025, (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="foods-10-00400-f001">Figure 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B9-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. This market is mainly driven by the rising request for encapsulated flavor and colorants. High demand for fortified and functional foods among consumers has caused a rise in demand for food additive encapsulation. Manufactures, therefore, have been adopting this technology at a high rate.
</p>
