<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10" class="p">Dairy products constitute about 25–30% of the average diet of an individual [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>] (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). Milk and milk products are nutritious food items containing numerous essential nutrients such as, oleic acid, conjugated linoleic acid, omega-3 fatty acids, vitamins, minerals and bioactive compounds such as antioxidants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>]. Antioxidants are chemical substances that can neutralize and scavenge the free radicals, which are continuously produced in the body [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>]. For the generation of energy, oxidation is indispensable to living organism for biological processes. However, oxidative stress can cause serious damage to biological systems. It is scientifically established that reactive oxygen species are unceasingly produced in human body. Uncontrolled free radicals in body can lead to oxidative stresses, which may consequence in atherosclerosis, diabetes, accelerated ageing, cardiovascular diseases and break down of vital biochemical compounds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>]. Intake of antioxidants in the form of antioxidative supplements of foods rich in antioxidants may protect the body from oxidative stress and damage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>]. Metabolic diseases are closely correlated with life style and changes in life style has a great deal of impact on disease patterns, about 20–30 years ago, infectious disease were more than non-communicable diseases, but now the non-communicable/metabolic diseases are on the higher side. In current scenario, healthy/functional foods should be selected to avoid or minimize non-communicable diseases, such as diabetes, cancers and cardiovascular diseases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>]. Demand for foods containing natural antioxidants is increasing across the globe. Large number of foods and dairy products are being supplemented with natural antioxidants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>]. Antioxidant capacity of milk and dairy products is due to sulfur containing amino acids cysteine, vitamins A, E, carotenoids, enzyme systems, superoxide dismutase, catalase and glutathione peroxidase [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>]. Milk also contains appreciable amounts of equol, a polyphenolic metabolite of daidzein, antioxidant activity of this equol is scientifically established [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>]. Superoxide radicals, hydroxyl radicals, and peroxide radicals can be inhibited by the antioxidant systems of milk [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>]. Human body has mechanisms for the neutralization and scavenging of reactive oxygen species. Significant line of defense against reactive oxygen species are comprised of enzymes such as, glutathione peroxide, catalase and superoxide dismutase, ubiquinol and uric acid [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>]. Lipid oxidation is the main reason for the chemical spoilage of food and dairy products and it leads to the production of objectionable changes in nutritional value, flavor and texture of foods [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>]. Literature review has shown that milk and dairy products have antioxidant capacity, however, information regarding the antioxidant capacity of milk and dairy products has not been previously compiled. This paper briefly describes the antioxidant capacity of milk and dairy products.
</p>
