<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">The significantly broader CR of 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> LH1 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b) is related to the high 
 <italic>δ</italic>
 <sup>13</sup>C values of this supercolony (Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>e, 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The presence of C4 plants might explain the high 
 <italic>δ</italic>
 <sup>13</sup>C values of consumers (i.e., 
 <italic>L. humile</italic>) in our study area. In general, vascular plants are broadly classified into C3 or C4 plants according to their photosynthetic cycles, and they show characteristic 
 <italic>δ</italic>
 <sup>13</sup>C distributions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. Specifically, C3 plants tend to exhibit a wide CR, from − 20 to − 35%, whereas the CR of C4 plants is narrower (− 10 to − 14%)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, since C4 plants usually have higher tolerance to drought, high temperatures, and human disturbance than C3 plants, they can more easily grow in areas such as port areas
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. In fact, based on our field observations, C4 plants mostly representing 
 <italic>Poaceae</italic> species were very dominant compared to C3 plants in sites paved with concrete of the study areas. Based on the above, the high 
 <italic>δ</italic>
 <sup>13</sup>C for the LH1 supercolony is expected to be derived from C4 plants. Another potential cause of high 
 <italic>δ</italic>
 <sup>13</sup>C in terrestrial organisms is corrosion
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>, which would be expected to lead to increases in 
 <italic>δ</italic>
 <sup>15</sup>N and NR (an indicator of trophic diversity)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. However, in this study, the lack of clear, concurrent increases in 
 <italic>δ</italic>
 <sup>15</sup>N and 
 <italic>δ</italic>
 <sup>13</sup>C for 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>e) suggests that the high 
 <italic>δ</italic>
 <sup>13</sup>C of the LH1 supercolony was not derived from a carrion diet. In light of the above, the members of the LH1 supercolony might be expected to have higher 
 <italic>δ</italic>
 <sup>13</sup>C than those of the other supercolonies through the ingestion of C4 plant-derived resources, which would lead to the broader CR. The baseline 
 <italic>δ</italic>
 <sup>13</sup>C of arthropods also indicates that LH1 supercolony can use the high-
 <italic>δ</italic>
 <sup>13</sup>C resource, which might be derived from C4 plant-based resources (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).
</p>
