<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">We found a clear intraspecific variation in the SEA of 
 <italic>L. humile</italic>, which is an index of diet breadth, among the four supercolonies in Kobe, Hyogo, Japan (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Specifically, LH1 supercolony (the most successful supercolony) showed a significantly larger SEAb than the others (less-successful supercolonies) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). On the other hand, there were no differences in the baseline SEAb of arthropods among the sampling sites (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). These results highlighted that the LH1 supercolony had more diet breadth than the other supercolonies when the diversities of the available baselines (arthropods) did not differ. Although the NR of 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> did not differ among supercolonies other than LH4 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>d), the CR of the LH1 supercolony was significantly broader than the CRs the other supercolonies (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b), indicating that the larger SEAb for 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> LH1 than for the other supercolonies (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b) might be due to the broader CR of LH1. We thought that the broader CR of LH1 might be caused by its strong foraging resource exploitation (foraging) ability. Furthermore, the positive correlation between 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> supercolony SEAb and the degree of their invasion success (i.e., distribution ranges in the world)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup> (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>) support our hypothesis that an association between the diet breadth of the targeted species and its invasion success can be implied, even within species (between supercolonies). However, it should be noted that these results did not reveal a causal relationship between the dietary breadth of each 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> supercolony and its invasion success. Monitoring future population dynamics of each 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> supercolony with different diet breadth would be a promising approach to test the effects of diet breadth on invasion success. Additionally, while the present study showed that the diet breadth of 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> differs among supercolonies, this result may have been due to the interaction between the different 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> supercolonies and the surrounding environment. Although we attempted to minimize the effect of surrounding environment on the isotope ratios (i.e., diet breadth) by limiting sampling to the local scale (i.e., Kobe Port) and by performing baseline corrections of 
 <italic>δ</italic>
 <sup>15</sup>N values, the possibility of a supercolony-environment interaction effect cannot be completely eliminated. To enable more robust comparisons among supercolonies, the effects of differences in landscape structures around sampling sites should be accounted for in future studies.
</p>
