<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To estimate the effects of mycorrhizal association type on survival and growth of tree species in 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> plantations, we established a permanent plot at the field site during winter 2006 to spring 2007. Initially, we collected seeds as many as 56 broad-leaved tree species. Those seeds were placed in plastic basins with buck soil for germination and grew for 6–8 weeks before transplantation. However, based on the quantity and quality of seedlings, we chose 20 broad-leaved tree species and transplanted them into the 
 <italic>E. urophylla</italic> plantations. According to published data (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Qiu, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Brundrett, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Akmetzhanova et al., 2012</xref>) and results of our observations on their fine roots, we classified these 20 species into four root mycorrhizal types, namely, (i) AM, (ii) EM, (iii) nitrogen-fixing (NF), and (iv) non-mycorrhizal (NM) plants (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). We cleared all understory vegetations in the 
 <italic>E. urophylla</italic> plantations and set up six parallel transects (15 m × 95 m for each) along the contours of the hillside. Each transect included six plots (10 m × 10 m) with 5 m-wide buffer zones between each plot, and 4–6 adult 
 <italic>E. urophylla</italic> trees were left in every plot. We selected 10 tree species and transplanted them into a plot, at a density of 1 seedling/m
 <sup>2</sup> (i.e., 100 seedlings per plot). In each transect, every three out of six plots was planted with the same 10 species while the other 10 species were planted into the rest of three plots (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). Thus, there were 3,600 seedlings in total in this planting experiment (i.e., 6 transects × 6 plots/transect × 100 seedlings/plot). We replaced wilted or dead seedlings during the first 30 days after planting. We tagged all seedlings and first measured the basal diameter of each seedling in February 2007. Thereafter, we recorded the survival status of each seedling for each tree species and remeasured their basal diameter every 3 months. The last survey was conducted in June 2016.
</p>
