<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anti-diabetic</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diabetes mellitus is one of the most common metabolic disorders that resulted in significant morbidity and mortality rate (Deshpande et al., 
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">2008</a>). The chronic hyperglycemia of diabetes is associated with prolonged dysfunction, damage, and failure of different organs particularly kidneys, heart, eyes, and blood vessels. There is an increasing demand for traditionally used medicinal plants to manage the diabetes mellitus and its complications since the use of insulin and oral hypoglycemic agents are associated with side effects (Holman and Turner, 
  <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">1991</a>; Rao et al., 
  <a rid="B106" ref-type="bibr" href="#B106">2001</a>). Furthermore, medicinal plants are inexpensive, easily accessible and less or no toxic. Previously, many medicinal plants including 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> were reported for hypoglycemic properties (Ahmed et al., 
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">2010</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">El-Haddad et al. (
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">2002</a>) reported the antidiabetic activity of hydroalcoholic extract fraction of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> seeds on streptozotocin induced diabetic rats. The administration of hydroalcoholic extract decreased the blood glucose level significantly at the dose of 200 mg/kg b.w. Also the chloroform and petroleum ether fractions decreased the blood glucose level. Furthermore, the histopathological study indicated that the hepatocytes of chloroform treated rats were non toxicated and regenerated the streptozotocin induced diabetic effect. The antidiabetic effect of aerial parts of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> ethanolic extract on streptozotocin induced diabetic rats was reported by Elbatran et al. (
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">2005</a>). The extract significantly decreased the levels of serum glucose, aspartate aminotransferase, and alanine aminotransferase. Also the administration of ethanolic extract of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> has decreased the serum triglycerides, cholesterol and low density lipoprotein. Whereas, the extract increased the level of high density lipoprotein. In toxicological study, the 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> extract increased the respiration rate, general depression, mucous membrane cyanoses, righting reflex loss, convulsion and death. The LD
  <sub>50</sub> value of alcoholic extract was 113.4 mg/100 g body weight.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ethanol and aqueous extracts of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> seeds were studied for their anti-diabetic potential in streptozotocin induced diabetic rats through tissue lipid peroxides and enzymatic antioxidant (Koheil et al., 
  <a rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74">2013</a>). Both the extracts were treated by oral administration at a dose of 150 mg/kg body weight. The results indicated that the blood glucose levels were reduced in the rats administrated with 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> seed extracts and glibenclamide (anti-diabetic drug) when compared to untreated diabetic rats. The results on the levels of thiobarbaturic acid reactive substances, nitric oxide, reduced glutathione and hydroperoxides in liver and kidney of treated rats proved that the administration of aqueous ethanolic extracts of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> and glibenclamide were tend to bring down the nitric oxide and reduced glutathione values near to the normal level. The enzymatic antioxidants such as catalase, superoxide dismutase, glutathione peroxidase, glutathione-S-transferase were significantly low in liver and kidney of diabetic control rats when compared to the diabetic rats administrated with ethanol and aqueous extracts of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> seeds and glibenclamide. The diabetic rats administrated with the extracts of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> and glibenclamide showed a decreased level of glycosylated hemoglobin, increased levels of total hemoglobin and plasma insulin when compared to the diabetic control level.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The hydro-alcoholic extract from the dried leaves of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> showed inhibitory potential against three 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> model enzyme assays 
  <span class="italic">viz</span>. α-glucosidase, α-amylase, and dipeptidyl peptidase IV (Ullah et al., 
  <a rid="B139" ref-type="bibr" href="#B139">2015</a>). The results on pancreatic α-amylase inhibitory activity of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> extract suggested that the enzyme responded to the extract when the concentration was increased. The IC
  <sub>50</sub> value of the extract was 1335.89 μg/mL. 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> extract demonstrated moderate mammalian intestinal α-Glucosidase enzyme inhibitory potential with the IC
  <sub>50</sub> value of 3256.68 μg/mL. Whereas, the extract gradually inhibited the activity of mammalian DPP IV enzyme in a dose dependent manner (IC
  <sub>50</sub> value of 1218.12 μg/mL).
 </p>
</sec>
