<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antimicrobial</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Globally, infectious diseases are the predominant cause of the loss of life. Currently, synthetic antibiotics are widely used to prevent or cure several infectious diseases. The indiscriminate use of synthetic antibiotics poses a serious threat to humans (Lin et al., 
  <a rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78">2018</a>) as multidrug resistance is developed among the disease causing microbes. Therefore, scientists are more focused on plant based drugs which are no/least toxic to treat the infectious diseases. Moreover, it may help to overcome the emergence of multidrug resistance problem. Therefore, extracts of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> were studied for antiviral, antibacterial and antifungal activities.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 1997, Mehdi et al. studied the 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> anti hepatitis B viral activity of ethanol extract of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> together with 18 other plants parts against HepG2.2.15 cell line (Mehdi et al., 
  <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">1997</a>). The results showed that the extract of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> did not inhibit the cell line and survival rate was 100%. Whereas, Soltan and Zaki (
  <a rid="B131" ref-type="bibr" href="#B131">2009</a>) screened 42 Egyptian medicinal plants including 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> for their antiviral activity and the authors found that the hydro-alcoholic extract of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> demonstrated antiviral potential against herpes simplex-1 virus at concentrations range between 50 and 100 μg/mL with Rf 104. But, the extract inhibited the host cells growth though the experiment was conducted at the maximum concentration of 100 μg/mL. 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> extract was found to be inactive against poliomyelitis-1 and vesicular stomatitis viruses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Disk diffusion method and the determination of minimum inhibitory concentrations were employed to study the antimicrobial potential of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> seed oil against 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis, Staphylococcus aureus, Escherichia coli, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Enterobacter cloacae, Klebsiella pneumoniae, Candida albicans, C. tropicalis</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">C. glabrata</span>. The activities were compared with the standard antibiotics. The results indcated that the oil was effective against all the tested microorganisms. 
  <span class="italic">C. glabrata</span> was observed as a most resistant strain among the bacterial and fungal strains. The MIC values of the above mentioned microorganisms were 3.35, 3.50, 4.95, 4.38, 4.80, 4.30, 5.70, 3.30, and 3.25 mg/ml, respectively (Lalas et al., 
  <a rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" href="#B76">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antimicrobial activity of ethanol extract of leaves, seed coat and endosperm of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> were studied by agar well diffusion assay against bacterial (
  <span class="italic">Bacillus subtilis, Micrococcus luteus, S. aureus, E. coli, P. aeruginosa</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">K. pneumonia</span>) and fungal strains (
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus flavus, Aspergillus fumigatus, Aspergillus niger</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span>; Hajar and Gumgumjee, 
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">2014</a>). The leaf extract of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> showed good antibacterial activity (
  <span class="italic">B. subtilis</span> = 20.0 mm; 
  <span class="italic">M. luteus</span> = 23.67 mm
  <span class="italic">; S. aureus</span> = 27.66 mm; 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> = 19.67 mm; 
  <span class="italic">P. aeruginosa</span> = 26.67 mm; and 
  <span class="italic">K. pneumonia</span> = 20.67 mm) followed by seed coat (
  <span class="italic">B. subtilis</span> = 18.67 mm; 
  <span class="italic">M. luteus</span> = 20.33 mm
  <span class="italic">; S. aureus</span> = 24.0 mm; 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> = 19.33 mm; 
  <span class="italic">P. aeruginosa</span> = 20.67 mm; and 
  <span class="italic">K. pneumonia</span> = 13.33 mm) and endosperm (
  <span class="italic">M. luteus</span> = 13.33 mm
  <span class="italic">; E. coli</span> = 17.67 mm; and 
  <span class="italic">P. aeruginosa</span> = 16.33 mm. The ethanol extract of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> endosperm had no activity against 
  <span class="italic">B. subtilis, S. aureus</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">K. pneumonia</span>. The ethanolic leaf extract also showed good antifungal activity against the tested fungal strains (Leaf extract—
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> = 23.33 mm
  <span class="italic">; A. fumigatus</span> = 22.67 mm; 
  <span class="italic">A. niger</span> = 18.67 mm; and 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> = 24.67 mm: seed coat—
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> = 21.67 mm
  <span class="italic">; A. fumigatus</span> = 22.33 mm; 
  <span class="italic">A. niger</span> = 17.67 mm and 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> = 22.67 mm: and endosperm—
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> = 17.33 mm
  <span class="italic">; A. fumigatus</span> = 21.33 mm; 
  <span class="italic">A. niger</span> = 14.67 mm; and 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> = 20.67 mm). El-Awady et al. (
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">2015</a>) reported the comparative antibacterial activity of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> and 
  <span class="italic">M. oleifera</span> leaf extracts. The methanol and ethanol extracts of both the plants showed antibacterial activity against 
  <span class="italic">E. coli, S. aureus, Enterococcus sps, Aeromonas hydrophila</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. aeruginosa</span>. But, when compared to 
  <span class="italic">M. oleifera</span> leaf extracts, 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> had less activity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antibacterial activity of ethanol extracts of leaves, roots and seeds of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> extracts were investigated against 
  <span class="italic">E. coli, S. aureus</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Klebsiella pneumonia</span> (Majali et al., 
  <a rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" href="#B79">2015</a>). The results on the inhibition of studied bacterial strains were concentration dependent. The root extract showed good antibacterial activity against 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> (18–42 mm), 
  <span class="italic">K. pneumonia</span> (44–59 mm), and 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> (34–45 mm) followed by ethanol extract of leaf (
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> = 14–30 mm; 
  <span class="italic">K. pneumonia</span> = 8–19 mm; and 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> = 9– 22 mm) and seed extract (
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> = 16–38 mm; 
  <span class="italic">K. pneumonia</span> = 6–32 mm; and 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> = 6–18 mm). The minimum inhibitory concentrations values of the 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> extracts were 12.0 (
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span>), 15.0 (
  <span class="italic">K. pneumonia</span>) and 18 mg/ml (
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span>) for leaf extract, 13.0 (
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span>), 7.0 (
  <span class="italic">K. pneumonia</span>), and 9.0 mg/ml (
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span>) for seed extract and 3 (
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span>), 5.0 (
  <span class="italic">K. pneumonia</span>), and 2.0 mg/ml (
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span>) for roots extracts.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Different extracts (
  <span class="italic">viz</span>. acetone, methanol, ethanol, and aqueous) of both 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> plantlets and field grown samples were studied for their antibacterial activity against 
  <span class="italic">K. oxytoca, Salmonella typhimurium</span>, Methicillin resistant 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus, K. pneumonia, Proteus vulgaris, Proteus mirabilis, Enterobacter aerogenes, P. aeruginosa, E. coli</span> O157:H7, 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus, Salmonella paratyphi</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> ATCC 29522. The results revealed that 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> plantlets of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> showed significant antibacterial potential when compared to field grown samples. At a concentration of 40 mg/100 μl, the ethanol extract of 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> plantlets of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> showed the highest zone of inhibition against 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> (Alrayes et al., 
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">2016</a>). Aqueous extract of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> seeds was investigated for antibacterial activity against clinically isolated multidrug resistant 
  <span class="italic">Salmonella</span> species (Saleh et al., 
  <a rid="B119" ref-type="bibr" href="#B119">2017</a>). The results showed that the extracts exhibited good antibacterial activity against the multidrug resistant 
  <span class="italic">Salmonella</span> isolates. The minimum inhibitory concentration of the extract ranged between 109.37 and 437.5 mg/mL. These results support the use of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> as disinfectant in the folk medicine and further studies can be focused on the isolation of novel antimicrobial molecules to treat the infections caused by microbes.
 </p>
</sec>
