<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hypertension</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hypertension is a cardio vascular disease and it is one of the leading causes of death worldwide. Various anti-hypertensive drugs have been developed for the treatment of hypertension. But the drugs showed efficacy along with associated side effects (Alamgeer et al., 
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">2017</a>). Investigations on edible and medicinal plants remain important since it has potential benefits (Kalia, 
  <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">2005</a>). Based on the edible importance as well as the traditional uses, the hydroalcoholic extract of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> was investigated on blood pressure and oxidative status in hypertensive rats induced with dexamethasone. Systolic blood pressure, thymus weight, body weight, plasma hydrogen peroxide concentration, plasma ferric reducing antioxidant power were measured after the treatment. The results of the prevention study proved that the extract of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> prevents the rise of systolic blood pressure at 400 mg/kg dose level. Whereas, the reversal study indicated that 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> extract failed to lower the SBP in dexamethasone induced hypertension in rats. The oral administration of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> extract had no significant effect on the loss of thymus weight and also the extract was botched to prevent the body weight changes. In contrast, Rouhi-Broujeni et al. (
  <a rid="B112" ref-type="bibr" href="#B112">2013</a>) reported that the hydroalcoholic extract from the seeds of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> decreased the mean body weight. In the prevention study, treatment with 200 and 400 mg/kg of extract prevented the rise of H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> concentration. Whereas, in the reversal study, a dose of 400 mg/kg 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> extract reduced the elevated plasma hydrogen peroxide concentration. In prevention as well as reversal study, the rats administrated with 400 mg/kg of 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span> extract significantly reduced the plasma ferric reducing antioxidant power (Safaeian et al., 
  <a rid="B116" ref-type="bibr" href="#B116">2015</a>). So, the antihypertensive activity might be linked with the availability of antioxidant molecules present in 
  <span class="italic">M. peregrina</span>. The antioxidant molecules showed significant role in reducing the level of blood pressure (Duarte et al., 
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">2001</a>; Jalili et al., 
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">2006</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
