<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For plants, it is known that most of the lead taken up remains in the roots (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kumar et al., 1995</xref>). In our experiment we saw that the lead concentration significantly decreased in the shoots but not in the roots inoculated with AMF (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" class="xref">4</xref>). Different effects were described in the shoots for mycorrhizal plants growing on contaminated soil. 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rydlová and Vosátka (2003)</xref> observed that mycorrhizal 
 <italic class="italic">Agrostis capillaris</italic> took up more lead, whereas 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yang et al. (2016)</xref> showed that different mycorrhizal plant species took up less lead when contamination is very high. For 
 <italic class="italic">Origanum majorana</italic> it was shown that the lead content was reduced in shoots and roots when inoculated with the AM fungi 
 <italic class="italic">F. mosseae</italic>, but lead content increased when infected with 
 <italic class="italic">Claroideoglomus claroideum</italic> (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hristozkova et al., 2015</xref>). Surprisingly, in our experiment the lead concentration in the inoculated sweet basil roots increased, when both heavy metals were present in the soil. This effect was more significant in mycorrhizal roots than in roots inoculated with 
 <italic class="italic">S. indica</italic>. The ability of 
 <italic class="italic">S. indica</italic> to lower the pH in the surrounding media is also known for the rhizosphere in general (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lin et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ngwene et al., 2016</xref>). A decrease of the pH might lead to a higher absorption of lead, as shown for 
 <italic class="italic">Oryza sativa</italic> (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lin et al., 2004</xref>). In contrast, the lead availability is reduced in the 
 <italic class="italic">Pelargonium hortorum</italic> rhizosphere, when other heavy metals with antagonistic effects, such as copper, are present (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Orroño et al., 2012</xref>). Since there are no results in the literature on the interaction between mycorrhizal fungi and 
 <italic class="italic">S. indica</italic>, we can only speculate that in our experiments both fungi have an additive effect to decrease the uptake of lead by the shoots. Further investigations are needed to verify this conjecture.
</p>
