<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_HLY6292 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 docx ?><?FILEsi1 svg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7900702</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2405-8440(21)00397-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e06292</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e06292</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Chemical analysis and anticancer activity of sesterterpenoid from an endophytic fungus <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic> Zg15SU and its host <italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> Baker</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Lutfia</surname><given-names>Anisa</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Munir</surname><given-names>Erman</given-names></name><email>erman@usu.ac.id</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Yurnaliza</surname><given-names>Yurnaliza</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Basyuni</surname><given-names>Mohammad</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Biology, Faculty of Mathematics and Natural Sciences, Universitas Sumatera Utara, Medan, 20155, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Forestry, Faculty of Forestry, Universitas Sumatera Utara, Medan, 20155, Indonesia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>erman@usu.ac.id</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e06292</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2021 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p><italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> Baker is one of the native Zingiberaceous species in a tropical forest of North Sumatra, Indonesia. Zingiberaceous species have been intensively studied and reported as herbal ingredients in ethnomedicine and currently their endophytic fungal associates were studied for pharmacological importance. Fifteen endophytic fungi were isolated from <italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> following morphological and molecular characterization. All isolates exhibited antibacterial properties to at least one of the tested pathogenic bacteria <italic>Staphylococcus aureus, Escherichia coli</italic>, Methicilin-resistant <italic>S.&#x000a0;aureus</italic> (MRSA), and Enteropathogenic <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> (EPEC). The isolate, identified as <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic> strain Zg15SU (syn. <italic>Hypoxylon monticulosum</italic> Mont.) based on its rDNA/ITS sequence, displayed antibacterial activities to all tested pathogens. The EtOAc extract of the <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosum</italic> Zg15SU showed the highest activity for gram-negative bacteria, the <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> and <italic>EPEC</italic>, while the extract of <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> rhizome displayed activity only for <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic>. The gas chromatography-mass spectrometry analysis (GC-MS) indicated a major portion of similar compounds found in both the endophytic fungus and plant extract, revealing the compounds of oleic acid, cyclononasiloxane, octadecamethyl, and eicosanoic acid Furthermore, purification and structural elucidation on the EtOAc extract of both <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> rhizome and <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulos</italic><italic>a</italic> Zg15SU yielded two bioactive compounds: a novel compound, griffithiiene, a terpenoid-alkaloid bearing the skeleton of a scalarane (1) and scalaradial (2) which were confirmed by <sup>1</sup>H- (500 MHz) and <sup>13</sup>C-NMR (125 MHz) spectroscopy. Importantly, the elucidated compounds showed a cytotoxicity activity against cancer cell lines, the Panc-1, NBT-T2, and HCT116 based on in vitro MTT proliferation assay. This is the first report of <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> harboring an endophytic fungus, <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosa</italic>, which produced potential antibacterial and anticancer metabolites along with its host to be utilized for future prospects.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0015"><p>Anticancer, <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic>, North Sumatra, Sesterterpenoid, <italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> Baker</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Anticancer</kwd><kwd><italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic></kwd><kwd>North sumatra</kwd><kwd>Sesterterpenoid</kwd><kwd><italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> Baker</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Plant materials have been considered the most promising source of biologically active compounds. Numerous plant species have been utilized in the local, regional and global scope as an isolation source of medicinal ingredients which have been studied thoroughly in pharmacological fields. A majority of medicinal plants have been reviewed to initiate and preserve symbiotic association with some endophytic fungi intensively involved in the co-synthesis of bioactive compounds (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Strobel 2018</xref>). The fungi may have also been bestowed in the effectivity of phytochemical compounds produced by the plants for their defence against pathogen. The endophytic fungi are variably present in the plant parts by having ubiquitous symbiosis as slightly parasitic microorganisms for all, or at least some, part of their life cycle (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Strobel 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Strobel and Daisy 2003</xref>). The endophytic fungi are also considered to be a prominent producer of bioactive metabolites which can be developed in future drugs (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Deshmukh et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>).</p><p id="p0015">Zingiberaceae is a medicinal plant family regularly used in traditional remedies and as herbal medicine, especially in Indonesia (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Fernando and Nursyahra, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hartanto et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Juwita et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). The associative endophytes have been reported from various sources leading to the progressive development of study and exploration of diverse endophytic fungi harbouring different habitats (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Ginting et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Anisha and Radhakrishnan, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Hastuti et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). A vast number of endophytic fungi in Zingiberaceaen species may also indicate an inter-relationship among the fungi within the plant tissue in the way of the co-synthesis of desired phytochemicals. However, studies of its phytochemical constituents produced by both the endophyte and its host are in progress to reveal the whole stable and mutual relationship (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Aly et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>).</p><p id="p0020"><italic>Hypoxylon</italic> is a genus belonging to a family, Xylariaceae with identified 16 genera and 130 species (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Sanchez-Ballesteros et&#x000a0;al., 2007</xref>). The genus is the largest member within the family primarily distributed in diverse marine and terrestrial habitats, along with its potential as a producer of various bioactive compounds (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Stadler et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Recent investigations have been reported on natural products produced by <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosum</italic>. The strain of <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosum</italic> isolated from a sponge, <italic>Sphaerocladina</italic> in Tahiti, produced four novel phenolic acid derivates, namely Sporochartines B-E to its culture broth. The purified compounds showed significant biological activities against human cancer cell lines in cytotoxic bioassays (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Leman-Loubi&#x000e8;re et&#x000a0;al., 2017a</xref>). In other reports, a similar strain also produced two sporothriolide-related compounds, later named Sporochartine A, Sporothriolide and Deoxysporothic acid (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Leman-Loubi&#x000e8;re et&#x000a0;al. 2017b</xref>). Both compounds were monocyclic acid precursors and reported as potential anti fungi without any inhibitory activity against bacteria. Based on recent taxonomical studies and polyphasic approaches, the species is now placed into its own clade as <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic> (Mont.) Sir, L. Wendt &#x00026; C. Lambert suggesting different family taxa or Hypoxylaceae (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Lambert et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>). Moreover, until now, the bioprospecting study of <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosa</italic> metabolite is still limited and worth investigating.</p><p id="p0025">In this study, an endophytic fungal isolate later identified as <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic> was isolated from <italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> Baker rhizome<italic>,</italic> in a tropical forest of Tongkoh Bukit Barisan, North Sumatra. The strain was identified based on its ITS-DNA region and exhibits potential antibacterial activities against pathogenic bacteria and multidrug-resistant strains. To our understanding, this is the first report on endophytic <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosum</italic> from Zingiberaceous species, specifically from <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> Baker. In addition, the rhizome itself contained an unknown compound, proposed as a novel compound in the group of alkaloid-terpenoid with the potential as anticancer against cancer cell lines.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Plant material</title><p id="p0030">The fresh rhizome of <italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> Baker was sampled from the forest area of Tahura Tongkoh Bukit Barisan, North Sumatra, Indonesia. The rhizome was collected and preserved in a sterile Ziploc bag, containing ice (4 &#x000b0;C) and transported or processed within 48 h. Voucher specimens were collected for authentication by the service from Herbarium Medanese, Department of Biology, Universitas Sumatera Utara, Medan, Indonesia.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Isolation of endophytic fungi from the rhizome interior</title><p id="p0035">The procedure of fungal isolation followed method as described by <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Yurnaliza et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</xref>. Rhizomes (1&#x02013;2 cm in length) were cleaned with tap water to remove dirt and soil particles. The rhizomes were sterilized by being immersed in sterilizing agents: 75% ethanol, 5.3% NaOCl, and 75% ethanol, for 2 min, 5 min, and 30 s, respectively. Thereafter, the sterilized fragments were washed in sterile distilled water to remove surface sterilization solutions. Each fragment was divided into smaller pieces (0.5 cm) and plated on Potato Dextrose Agar (Oxoid&#x02122;) supplemented with 0.1% (w/v) chloramphenicol to suppress the bacterial growth. Cultures were incubated in an ambient condition for 3 days. Then, any visible fungal growth from each piece was sub-cultured into a new medium to maintain the strains. Each fungal strain was differentiated preliminary based on morphological features.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Antagonism assay</title><p id="p0040">PDA agar supplemented with 1% (w/v) yeast extracts (Merck, Germany) medium was used for the antagonism assay. <italic>S.&#x000a0;aureus</italic> ATCC&#x000ae; 29213&#x02122;, Methicilin-resistant <italic>S.&#x000a0;aureus</italic> ATCC&#x000ae; 43300&#x02122;, <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> ATCC&#x000ae; 25922&#x02122;, and Enteropathogenic <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> K11 were of collections of the Hospital of Universitas Sumatera Utara, Medan, Indonesia. The antagonism assay of endophytic fungi was performed by dual culture assay (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Balouiri et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). Direct bacterial suspensions were made by swabbing colonies and dipping them in a sterile saline solution (0.95% NaCl) to obtain OD<sub>600</sub>: 0.5 &#x02248; 1.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mL. One mL of cell suspension was inoculated into 15 mL molten PDA (45 &#x000b0;C), and then plated to get microbial lawns. Three agar plugs of fungal mycelium were placed over the medium. The plates were incubated for 2 days in ambient temperature. Clear zones indicating inhibitory activities around mycelial plugs indicating antagonism were measured in millimetre unit (mm) using the standard caliper.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Molecular identification</title><p id="p0045">The selected endophytic fungus, isolate Zg15SU, was identified based on its ITS-rDNA sequence region. The fungal DNA genome was extracted following the procedure as supplied by Wizard&#x000ae; Genomic DNA Purification Kit Protocol (United States). The ITS-rDNA sequence was amplified using the universal primer for fungi: ITS1 (5&#x02032;-CTTGGTCATTTAGAGGAAGTAA-3) and ITS4 (5&#x02032;-TCCTCCGCTTATTGATATGC-3&#x02032;) (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Manter and Vivanco 2007</xref>) with a reaction mixture composed of: 12 &#x003bc;L nuclease-free water (NFW), 20 &#x003bc;L GoTaq DNA Polymerase solution, 2 &#x003bc;L ITS-1F primer solution, 2 &#x003bc;L ITS-4 primer solution, 4 &#x003bc;L DNA template solution with a total volume of 40 &#x003bc;L in Eppendorf tube. The PCR was conditioned as: 95 &#x000b0;C for 3 min, followed by 35 cycles of 95 &#x000b0;C for 45 s, 55 &#x000b0;C for 45 s, 72 &#x000b0;C for 45 s, and final extension at 72 &#x000b0;C for 7 min. The ITS-DNA amplicons were commercially sequenced to Macrogen, Inc. Korea. The molecular identity from isolate Zg15SU was compared with other fungal ITS sequences obtained from databases of the <italic>National Centre for Biotechnology Information</italic> (NCBI). The sequences were searched using the <italic>Basic Local Alignment Search Tool</italic> for nucleotide (BLASTn) (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et&#x000a0;al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Morgulis et&#x000a0;al. 2008</xref>). Furthermore, the sequence data were aligned using MUSCLE in software MEGA ver.7.0 (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Edgar 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). A phylogenetic tree is constructed based on the neighbour-joining method with bootstrap replication 1000x (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Felsenstein 1985</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Saitou and Nei 1987</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Fermentation condition</title><p id="p0050">An endophytic fungus, <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa,</italic> which exhibited the strongest and most wide-spectrum antibacterial activity during preliminary screening was subjected to liquid-state fermentation (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Marcellano et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). Three pieces of the mycelial plug were inoculated into each 100 mL Potato Dextrose Broth (PDB) and incubated at an ambient temperature for 4 weeks without agitation. Biomass or mycelial mats were washed using sterile distilled water, collected, and dried at room temperature after the incubation period. Mycelial mats were manually macerated using 100 mL EtOAc for 3 days under agitation. The EtOAc extract was separated using a buchner funnel placed with a Whatman # 1 filter paper. The extract was then concentrated <italic>in vacuo</italic> and stored at 4 &#x000b0;C for further experimentation.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Metabolite extraction of the <italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> Baker rhizome</title><p id="p0055">The extraction of metabolites from <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> rhizome used a similar solvent, EtOAc by maceration (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Harborne 1987</xref>; <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Altemimi et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). Five-hundred grams of rhizome powder obtained from air-dried rhizome parts were submerged and macerated using EtOAc (w/v) for 3 days under agitation. The macerates were filtered and separated using a separatory funnel and filter paper Whatman # 1. The extract was concentrated using a rotary evaporator at <italic>in vacuo</italic> and stored in 4 &#x000b0;C for further experiments.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><label>2.7</label><title>Antibacterial assay</title><p id="p0060">The EtOAc extracts from <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosa</italic> mycelium and <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> rhizome were assayed for their antibacterial activities based on the standard disk diffusion assay (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Balouiri et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). Suspensions of bacteria were prepared from 24 h old culture. The suspensions were prepared (OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.08&#x02013;0.10) approximately 1.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mL based on the 0.5 McFarland solution. The cell suspensions were inoculated on top of Mueller-Hinton Agar (MHA). The dried crude extracts were diluted into 10% (v/v) dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO), and then 10&#x003bc;L of extracts were pipetted to a 5-mm sterile disk (Whatman Paper no. 1). A paper disk eluted with chloramphenicol (30&#x003bc;g) was included as a positive control in the MHA plates. All plates were incubated at room temperature for 24 h and any visible zones of inhibition were measured using regular millimetre-unit caliper (mm).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><label>2.8</label><title>GC-MS analysis</title><p id="p0065">The EtOAc extracts of <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosa</italic> mycelium and <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> rhizome were determined for its chemical composition using GCMS-QP2010 (Shimadzu Europa GmbH, Dusseldorf, Germany) instrument fitted with RTX-5MS (30 &#x000d7; 0.25 &#x000d7; 0.10 m) column. The volume of injection was 1 &#x003bc;L. The oven temperature was maintained at 80.0 &#x000b0;C for 1 min and programmed to increase until 250 &#x000b0;C at the rate of 5 &#x000b0;C/min. The total flow was 6.0 mL/min within the pressure of 102.5 kPa. Helium was used as the carrier gas with a flow rate of 1.50 mL/min at a linear speed of 45.1 cm/s. The samples were injected in splitless mode. The scanning range of the spectral mass was set at 30 to 600 (<italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic>). The identification of potentially bioactive compounds present in the extract was done by comparison to the library of the National Institute of Standard and Technology, NIST, US. All identified compounds were summarized in terms of the percentage relative peak area.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><label>2.9</label><title>Structural elucidation</title><p id="p0070">Optical rotations were recorded on a polarimeter Jasco DIP-1000. The IR spectra were measured on the spectrophotometer of Hitachi T-2001. HRESIMS-ESI spectra was recorded on a Jeol Mass spectrometer. The <sup>1</sup>H, <sup>13</sup>C NMR, DEPT, COSY, HMBC, and HSQC were recorded on a Bruker 500 MHz. Column chromatography was carried out on Merck silica gel 60. HPLC was conducted in reversed phase on a Hitachi L-4000H apparatus.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.10"><label>2.10</label><title>HPLC purification</title><p id="p0075">Crude ethyl acetate extract of <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> rhizome was partitioned using EtOAc: H<sub>2</sub>O (v/v). The EtOAc layer (24.2 mg) was separated by open column chromatography on silica gel using <italic>n-</italic>hexane: EtOAc gradient to produce 9 fractions. The major fraction was purified by HPLC RP-C<sub>18</sub> using MeOH: H<sub>2</sub>O (10:1) yielded the novel compound <bold>(1)</bold>. Meanwhile, the crude extract of <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosa</italic> Zg15SU partitioned following a similar procedure to yield the EtOAc portion (16.3 mg) was separated using open column chromatography producing 4 fractions. The major fraction was purified by HPLC NP-SiO<sub>2</sub> using <italic>n-</italic>hexane: EtOAc (6:2) yielded the known compound <bold>(2)</bold>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.11"><label>2.11</label><title>Cytotoxicity assay</title><p id="p0080">The cytotoxic effect of compounds <bold>1</bold> and <bold>2</bold> was determined by 3-(4, 5-dimethylthiazole-2yl)-2, 5-diphenyl tetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay using TACS&#x02122; MTT Cell Proliferation Assay (MTT-CPA) kit (Trevigen&#x000ae;, USA) in different human tumour cell lines viz. Panc-1 (pancreatic cancer), NBT-T2 (bladder cancer), and HCT116 (colon cancer). Briefly, 100 &#x003bc;L cells of known concentration (1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> cell density) were placed into triplicate wells for each diluted concentration of compounds. Ten microlitres of MTT reagent was added to each well and incubated for 2&#x02013;4 h at 37 &#x000b0;C. Subsequently, 100 &#x003bc;L of detergent were added into each well following the presence of purple precipitate. The plate was incubated in the dark at 18&#x02013;24 &#x000b0;C from 2 h to overnight. Negative control was prepared from untreated cells, MTT, and solubilizing buffer (10% SDS in 0.1 HCl). The absorbance was then determined by an ELISA reader at 570 nm. The inhibitory concentration (IC<sub>50</sub>) value was extrapolated from the concentration-response plot using linear regression analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Antagonistic activity of endophytic fungi</title><p id="p0085">The endophytic fungi isolated from <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> rhizome were sampled from a forest area of Tahura Tongkoh Bukit Barisan, Karo regency, North Sumatra. The forest was categorized as a montane secondary forest (&#x0003e;1,000 masl) harbouring diverse flora and fauna. The sample was collected by exploring the entire forest (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>). A total of 17 endophytic fungal isolates were isolated from <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> rhizome and subjected to preliminary antagonism assay or dual culture assay (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>). All isolates were found to inhibit the growth of pathogenic bacteria to at least one of the tested pathogens (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). From those 17 antagonistic strains, all of them inhibited <italic>S.&#x000a0;aureus</italic> by 100% (17/17) while the majority of them inhibited <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> by 94% (16/17). MRSA was inhibited by 3 strains, namely Zg03SU, Zg14SU, and Zg15SU by 17% (3/17) while EPEC was inhibited by only two strains, namely Zg10SU and Zg15SU by 11% (2/17). Therefore, an isolate encoded Zg15SU showed a wide spectrum activity, inhibiting both Gram-positive/&#x02013;negative bacteria and was subjected to further assays.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Wild <italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> Baker in Tahura Tongkoh Bukit Barisan, Karo regency, North Sumatra, Indonesia. Scale bar: 10 cm.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Figure&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Dual culture antagonistic test on PDA+1% (w/v) yeast extract agar medium. Three agar plugs of isolate Zg15SU (A) was inoculated on top of a lawn of Methicilin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC&#x000ae; 43300&#x02122; (&#x000b1;1.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mL). Following incubation at 25&#x02013;28 &#x000b0;C, a clear zone around fungal plugs indicated a presence of inhibition (B) against bacterial law. This is compared to control agar plug without inoculation (C).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Figure&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Antagonistic activity of endophytic fungi isolated from <italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> rhizome.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Table&#x000a0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">No</th><th rowspan="2">Isolate code</th><th colspan="4">Inhibition zone (mm)<xref rid="tbl1fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#x02217;</xref>,<xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref><hr/></th></tr><tr><th><italic>S.&#x000a0;aureus</italic></th><th><italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic></th><th>MRSA</th><th>EPEC</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>Zg01SU</td><td>20.00 &#x000b1; 1.20</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>Zg02SU</td><td>22.27 &#x000b1; 1.71</td><td>14.67 &#x000b1; 1.04</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Zg03SU</td><td>21.77 &#x000b1; 2.87</td><td>13.33 &#x000b1; 1.17</td><td>12.43 &#x000b1; 0.49</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Zg04SU</td><td>19.13 &#x000b1; 0.55</td><td>15.07 &#x000b1; 1.72</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Zg05SU</td><td>19.90 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td>21.20 &#x000b1; 4.08</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>Zg06SU</td><td>30.60 &#x000b1; 2.45</td><td>18.47 &#x000b1; 1.56</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>Zg07SU</td><td>24.73 &#x000b1; 3.49</td><td>11.13 &#x000b1; 1.86</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>Zg08SU</td><td>25.67 &#x000b1; 2.06</td><td>17.53 &#x000b1; 0.32</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>Zg09SU</td><td>21.07 &#x000b1; 1.85</td><td>18.33 &#x000b1; 2.90</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>Zg10SU</td><td>22.50 &#x000b1; 1.64</td><td>22.07 &#x000b1; 2.35</td><td>n.d</td><td>20.46 &#x000b1; 0.95</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>Zg11SU</td><td>17.40 &#x000b1; 2.86</td><td>16.77 &#x000b1; 2.97</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>Zg12SU</td><td>23.73 &#x000b1; 1.20</td><td>17.27 &#x000b1; 3.98</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>Zg13SU</td><td>24.70 &#x000b1; 1.30</td><td>17.70 &#x000b1; 3.59</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>Zg14SU</td><td>26.50 &#x000b1; 2.82</td><td>19.13 &#x000b1; 3.30</td><td>9.70 &#x000b1; 5.29</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td><bold>Zg15SU</bold></td><td><bold>24.00 &#x000b1; 3.96</bold></td><td><bold>26.83 &#x000b1; 1.56</bold></td><td><bold>13.63 &#x000b1; 1.17</bold></td><td><bold>18.23 &#x000b1; 0.12</bold></td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>Zg16SU</td><td>24.03 &#x000b1; 2.39</td><td>24.53 &#x000b1; 1.50</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>Zg17SU</td><td>23.10 &#x000b1; 0.87</td><td>15.20 &#x000b1; 5.00</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tspara0015"><p>n.d: no detectable inhibition zone.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0015a"><p>This is to highlight the potential of our isolate for the next experimentation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fnlowast"><label>&#x02217;</label><p id="ntpara0010">mean diameter of inhibition zone &#x000b1;S.D. (n = 3).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0015">agar plug diameter of 6 mm.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Molecular identification of isolate Zg15SU</title><p id="p0090">The potential isolate, Zg15SU was identified for its species identity using the ITS-rDNA region. The ITS sequence was then checked for similarity using the nucleotide database retrieved from NCBI. Based on the similarity percentage, the isolate Zg15SU was recognized as <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic>, an Ascomycetous fungus with a percentage of 99% (data not shown). The ITS sequence was submitted into GenBank and given an accession code, MN718862.1. The phylogenetic relationship among members in Hypoxylaceae was confirmed by constructing a phylogenetic tree (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>). The phylogenetic tree was constructed using the neighbour-joining method and analysed using the Kimura 2-parameter method with the gamma distribution model as the best DNA model predictor in MEGA7.0.<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree showing the relationship between an isolate <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic> Zg15SU (&#x0039f;) and related Xylarian species bootstrap value (BV) &#x02265;70%; the tree was inferred using neighbour-joining and Kimura 2-parameter method, modelled with a gamma distribution.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Figure&#x000a0;3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Antibacterial assay</title><p id="p0095">Both the <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> rhizome and <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosa</italic> mycelium were extracted using an organic solvent, EtOAc. The EtOAc extracts were tested for its antibacterial activity against the same pathogens using standard disk diffusion assay (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>). Chloramphenicol as positive control produced antibacterial activity to all bacteria, except MRSA. A crude extract of <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosa</italic> was observed to inhibit <italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic> EPEC and <italic>S.&#x000a0;aureus</italic> with no inhibition against MRSA, indicating that the extract has a considerably wide spectrum of antibacterial activity.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Antibacterial activity of EtOAc extracts from <italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> rhizome and <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic> Zg15SU mycelial extracts.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Table&#x000a0;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">No</th><th rowspan="2">Extract</th><th colspan="4">Inhibition zone (mm)<xref rid="tbl2fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">&#x02217;</xref>,<xref rid="tbl2fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref><hr/></th></tr><tr><th><italic>S.&#x000a0;aureus</italic></th><th><italic>E.&#x000a0;coli</italic></th><th>MRSA</th><th>EPEC</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td><italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosa</italic></td><td>10.25 &#x000b1; 1.18</td><td>20.90 &#x000b1; 0.93</td><td>n.d</td><td>12.75 &#x000b1; 3.50</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td><italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic></td><td>n.d</td><td>10.35 &#x000b1; 2.10</td><td>n.d</td><td>n.d</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Chloramphenicol</td><td>25.10 &#x000b1; 2.56</td><td>40.90 &#x000b1; 0.60</td><td>n.d</td><td>17.92 &#x000b1; 1.52</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>n.d: no detectable inhibition zone.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fnlowast"><label>&#x02217;</label><p id="ntpara0020">mean diameter of inhibition zone &#x000b1;S.D. (n = 3).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl2fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0025">agar plug diameter of 6 mm.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>GC-MS analysis</title><p id="p0100">The mass spectra profiles from the EtOAc extract of <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> rhizome and <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosa</italic> mycelium were analysed using GC-MS. The peak constituting different chemicals were detected and identified according to their relative peak area, RT-based on NIST library databases (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4</xref>). The chemical composition was summarized and discussed descriptively to point out the similarity among chemicals produced by both the host and endophyte (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>). Oleic acid, Cyclononasiloxane, octadecamethyl-, and Eicosanoic acid were detected as the highest proportion of chemicals from both extracts while indicating a relationship between organisms through co-synthesis.<fig id="fig4"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>The GC-MS diagram of EtOAc extract from <italic>Zingiber griffthii</italic> rhizome and <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic> Zg15SU mycelium.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Figure&#x000a0;4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>The identified compounds and their relative peak area percentage of EtOAc extracts of <italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> rhizome and <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic> Zg15SU mycelial extracts.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Table&#x000a0;3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">No.</th><th rowspan="2">Identified compounds</th><th colspan="2">Peak area percentage (%)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th><italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> rhizome</th><th><italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosa</italic> Zg15SU</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>1,2-Benzenedicarboxylic acid, ditridecyl ester</td><td>8.81</td><td>2.23</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>Cyclononasiloxane, octadecamethyl-</td><td>2.32</td><td>30.44</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Diethyl Phthalate</td><td>1.92</td><td>4.56</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Eicosanoic acid</td><td>1.12</td><td>14.09</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Heptasiloxane, hexadecamethyl-</td><td>21.18</td><td>1.20</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>Isopropyl Palmitate</td><td>0.17</td><td>0.08</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>Nonanal</td><td>0.08</td><td>0.14</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>Octasiloxane</td><td>1.09</td><td>0.02</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>Oleic acid</td><td>22.89</td><td>34.00</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>Oleoyl chloride</td><td>3.10</td><td>2.61</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>Tridecanoic acid, methyl ester</td><td>0.04</td><td>0.26</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>Structural elucidation and cytotoxicity properties</title><p id="p0105">Compound <bold>1</bold> was isolated as an amorphous powder, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x003b1;</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>D</mml:mtext><mml:mn>25</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>= +65.6<sup>o</sup> (CHCl<sub>3</sub>, <italic>c</italic> 0.65). Compound was isolated as a yellowish/reddish powder and given a molecular formula of C<sub>23</sub>H<sub>38</sub>N<sub>1</sub>NaO<sub>3</sub> (<italic>m/z</italic> = 376.54380 with = &#x00394;-0.09 mmu). IR absorptions were observed at 3389, 1731 and 1374 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, suggesting the presence of hydroxyl, ester and aromatic tertiary amine. Analysis of 2D NMR data (COSY, HMQC, HMBC) revealed that compound <bold>1</bold> is a Terpenoid-Alkaloid which has a skeleton of scalarane but having nitrogen atom in the cyclic skeleton that has double bond with C16. Since the carbonyls and C=N account for two out of the six degrees of unsaturation required by the formula, compound 1 must be tetracyclic. The proton NMR spectrum of compound <bold>1</bold> that measured in CDCl<sub>3</sub> (C<sub>6</sub>D<sub>6</sub>) revealed the presence of typical spectrum of steroid/terpenoid, i.e. five singlet methyl groups (sp3), at 0.80, 0.82, 0.86, 0.87, 0.94 (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;4</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>The NMR data of compound <bold>1</bold> at <sup>1</sup>H (500 MHz) and <sup>13</sup>C (125 MHz).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Table&#x000a0;4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">No</th><th rowspan="2"><sup>13</sup>C (CDCl<sub>3</sub>)</th><th rowspan="2"><sup>1</sup>H (CDCl<sub>3</sub>)</th><th rowspan="2">Mult in <italic>J</italic></th><th colspan="4">DEPT<hr/></th><th rowspan="2">HSQC</th><th rowspan="2">HMBC</th><th rowspan="2">COSY</th></tr><tr><th>CH<sub>3</sub></th><th>CH<sub>2</sub></th><th>CH</th><th>C</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">1</td><td>39.7</td><td>1.56</td><td>2H, m</td><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>CH2</td><td/><td>2</td></tr><tr><td/><td>0.68</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">2</td><td>18.4</td><td>1.58</td><td>2H, m</td><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>CH2</td><td/><td>1&#x02013;3</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1.35</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">3</td><td>41.9</td><td>1.33</td><td>2H, m</td><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>CH2</td><td>5</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1.14</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>33.28</td><td/><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td/><td>C</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>56.4</td><td>0.85</td><td>1H, m</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td><td>CH</td><td/><td>6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">6</td><td>17.9</td><td>1.39</td><td>2H, m</td><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>CH2</td><td>8&#x02013;10</td><td>5&#x02013;7</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1.58</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">7</td><td>41.4</td><td>1.70</td><td>2H, m</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>CH2</td><td>9</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1.12</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>36.8</td><td/><td>1H, m</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td/><td>C</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>52.3</td><td>1.25</td><td>1H, m</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td><td>CH</td><td/><td>11</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>37.7</td><td/><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td/><td>C</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">11</td><td>22.3</td><td>1.79</td><td>2H, m</td><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>CH2</td><td/><td>9</td></tr><tr><td/><td>1.66</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>74.4</td><td>4.87</td><td>1H, br t; 2.9 Hz</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td><td>CH</td><td>22</td><td>11</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>37.6</td><td/><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td/><td>C</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>49.5</td><td>1.40</td><td>1H, m</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td><td>CH</td><td/><td>15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">15</td><td>24.0</td><td>2.36</td><td>2H, m</td><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>CH2</td><td/><td>14</td></tr><tr><td/><td>2.13</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>135.5</td><td>6.84</td><td>1H, d; 4.9; 3.5 Hz</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td><td>CH</td><td/><td>17</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>51.0</td><td>3.14</td><td>1H, br q; 8.6, 4.8 Hz</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td/><td>X</td><td>CH</td><td/><td>16</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>21.33</td><td>0.80</td><td>3H, s</td><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>CH3</td><td>3-4-5-19</td><td/></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>33.2</td><td>0.86</td><td>3H, s</td><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>CH3</td><td>3-4-5-18</td><td/></tr><tr><td>20</td><td>16.2</td><td>0.82</td><td>3H, s</td><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>CH3</td><td>7-8-9</td><td/></tr><tr><td>21</td><td>15.0</td><td>0.87</td><td>3H, s</td><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>CH3</td><td>12-13-14-17</td><td/></tr><tr><td>22-OAc</td><td>169.9</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>23</td><td>21.39</td><td>1.96</td><td>3H, s</td><td/><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>X</td><td>CH3</td><td>23</td><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0110">The signal at &#x003b4; 6.84 ppm (1H, d, 4.9; 3.5 Hz) was assigned to an olefinic proton of the unsaturated carbon (C=C) at C-16. The <sup>13</sup>C NMR and DEPT spectra indicated the presence of 23 carbon signal including a carbonyl carbon at 169.9 ppm; six olefinic carbons at 41.9, 33.28, 56.4, 17.9, 135.5, 51.0; five quartenary carbon at 33.28, 17.9, 36.8, 37.6, 169.9; five methine carbons at 56.4, 52.3, 74.4, 49.5 and 135.5. The COSY and HSQC analysis led to assignment of the following spin systems: CH<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;CH<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;CH<sub>2</sub> (C-1&#x02212;C-3), CH&#x02013;CH<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;CH<sub>2</sub> (C-5&#x02212;C-7), CH&#x02013;CH<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;CHOH (C-9&#x02212;C-12), CH&#x02013;CH<sub>2</sub> (C-14&#x02212;C-15), CH&#x02013;CH (C-16&#x02013;C-17). The attachment of the hydroxy group at C-17 was deduced from the proton signal at &#x003b4; 3.14 (1H, brq, 8.6; 4.8 Hz). The acetoxy group at C-12 was assigned from the proton signal (H-12) at &#x003b4; 4.87 in coupling with H-11 by COSY, as well as from HMBC correlations to C-9 (52.3) and C-17 (51.0). Furthermore, the presence of nitrogen moiety was confirmed at C-15 (2H, 2.36; 2.13, m), the COSY signal indicated that the C-15 cross peak at C-14/C-15 (see supplementary Fig S1&#x02013;S7).</p><p id="p0115">Upon further analysis of compound <bold>2</bold>, the signal at &#x003b4; 4.87 ppm (1H, brt, 2.9 Hz) was typical of the proton geminal to an acetoxy moiety at C-12, indicating an axial orientation for this functionality and suggesting the configuration at this carbon position as scalaradial <bold>(2)</bold> (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;5</xref>). The difference in <sup>1</sup>H NMR data of 1 was the presence of a hydroxy group at &#x003b4; 3.14 ppm (1H, brq, 8.6; 4.8 Hz) at C-17 and were confirmed by HMBC and COSY with the cross peak at C-22/C-17, C-12/C-17, and C-16/C-17, respectively. Furthermore, the presence of nitrogen moiety as detected by HRESIMS was confirmed at C-15 (2H, 2.36; 2.13, m). The COSY signal indicated that the C-15 cross peak at C-14/C-15 indicated compound <bold>1</bold> as an unknown compound.<fig id="fig5"><label>Figure&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>The HMBC, <sup>1</sup>H&#x02013;<sup>1</sup>H COSY correlation and chemical structure of Compound <bold>(1)</bold> and <bold>(2)</bold>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Figure&#x000a0;5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p><p id="p0120">The IC<sub>50</sub> or cytotoxicity activities from compound <bold>1</bold> against cancer cell lines: Panc-1, NBT-T2, and HCT116 were 0.05, 0.75, and 0.05 ppm, respectively. Furthermore, the IC<sub>50</sub> value for compound <bold>2</bold> was 0.71, 0.30, and 0.67 ppm against respective cell lines.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0125">Endophytic fungi isolated from the medicinal plant have drawn much attention from researchers. Through exhaustive isolation and genome mining, some natural compounds may be yielded from the laboratory assay by using the diversity of endophytic fungi. Moreover, the synthesis of novel compound may be initiated by modifying the growth condition of an isolate or so called OSMAC (One Strain, Many (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">VanderMolen et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>). Prior to a deeper investigation of compound analysis, we conduct a preliminary investigation upon selecting potential endophytic fungal isolates.</p><p id="p0130">Members of Zingiberaceae have been reported to be colonized by beneficial endophytes which may co-synthesize a similar metabolites or bioactive compounds from its host as reported from previous study, mostly as antioxidant due to its medicinal nature. An endophytic fungus, <italic>F.&#x000a0;oxysporum</italic> isolated from <italic>Zingiber zerumbet</italic> was reported to synthesize a high antioxidant compound in its culture extract possessing similar properties as its host extract (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Nongalleima et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>). The mutualistic relationship exposed that plants have their own population structuring organization to certain fungal species, conferring benefits to both organisms (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Aly et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Jia et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>).</p><p id="p0135">Based on our results, we may also expect the wide spectrum of biological activities possessed by Zingiberaceous species to be the antimicrobials or at least antagonistic to certain pathogenic microbes. Previous studies have reported that different Zingiberaceous species may harbour different endophytic fungal isolates (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Uzma et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Munir et&#x000a0;al. 2019</xref>). Moreover, antagonistic fungi have been isolated from <italic>Hedychium coronarium</italic> healthy rhizome, yielding 12 fungal morphotypes, which were strong antagonists to <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC&#x000ae; 29213&#x02122; (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Lutfia et&#x000a0;al. 2019a</xref>). In a similar study, endophytic fungal isolates from <italic>Globba pendula</italic> were also strong antagonists to the same tested pathogen. In this study, we evaluated the antibacterial properties of antagonistic fungi through screening with clinical and resistant pathogenic bacteria (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Lutfia et&#x000a0;al. 2019b</xref>). In addition, five endophytic fungi isolated from a wild ginger <italic>Amomum centrocephalum</italic>, e.g. <italic>Aspergillus aculeatus, Clonostachys rosea, Daldinia caldariorum</italic>, and two strains of <italic>Trichoderma</italic> were potential antagonists against bacterial pathogens and phytopathogenic fungi (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Lutfia et&#x000a0;al. 2019c</xref>).</p><p id="p0140">The potential isolate, Zg15SU is then identified as <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa,</italic> an ascomycetous fungus with the former name <italic>Hypoxylon monticulosum</italic> in an on-going study of its natural compounds. <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic> isolated from marine origin was reported to synthesize a class of chemicals called Sporothriolide along with other minor constituents (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Leman-Loubi&#x000e8;re et&#x000a0;al., 2017a</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Leman-Loubi&#x000e8;re et&#x000a0;al. 2017b</xref>). The endophytic <italic>Hypoxylon</italic> has also been reported from various plant species that can synthesize oil-based or volatile organic compounds. Another study reported that an endophytic <italic>Hypoxylon</italic> sp. isolated from <italic>Persea americana</italic> was known to synthesize monoterpene, 1,8-Cineole, which may be utilized and developed as fuel additives (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Tomsheck et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>). The terpenoid compound also possessed antifungal properties against phytopathogenic fungi, i.e., <italic>Botrytis cinerea, Phytophthora cinnamoi, Cercospora beticola,</italic> and <italic>Sclerotinia sclerotium</italic>. Other studies also supported the finding of VOCs produced by <italic>Hypoxylon</italic> to be used as a preservative agent. Endophytic <italic>H.&#x000a0;anthochroum</italic> isolated from Burseraceae, Fabaceae, Celastraceae, and Euphorbiaceae were reported to produce sesquiterpene and monoterpene compounds with potential anti fungi to <italic>Fusarium oxysporum,</italic> causing infection in cherry tomatoes (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Mac&#x000ed;as-Rubalcava et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). Other findings also reported the mycodiesel potential of <italic>Hypoxylon</italic> sp. CI-4 due to its abundant VOCs produced at a laboratory scale (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Ul-Hassan et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>).</p><p id="p0145">To date, isolation efforts of <italic>Hypoxylon</italic> spp. are still limited to certain medicinal plant species. A bioprospection study of <italic>H.&#x000a0;investiens</italic> isolated from stems of <italic>Litsea akoensis</italic> var. <italic>chitouchiaoensis,</italic> a Taiwanese species, reported that BuOH extract of fungus exhibits biological activities, i.e., Nitric Oxide (NO) and Interleukin-6 (IL) inhibitory activities with medical importance (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Chang et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). In addition, Taiwanese <italic>Ilex formosana</italic> harbored endophytic <italic>Hypoxylon</italic> sp. 12F0687 with similar biological properties as reported previously (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chen et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>). Hence, the <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic> strain Zg15SU isolated from <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> may provide valuable information through the study of its natural products and bioactivities. The confirmation of natural product co-synthesis between <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosum</italic> and <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> rhizome was analysed based on the composition percentage of similar compounds detected in GC-MS. Oleic acid was detected as the highest proportion of compounds produced by both endophytic fungus and its host. Other studies also supported our findings. Endophytic fungi isolated from four ginger cultivars (<italic>Zingiber officinale</italic>) were known to produce a myriad of bioactive fatty acids, one of which was oleic acid. It was assumed that a different composition of fatty acids among ginger cultivars was structured by native endophytic fungi (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Anisha and Radhakrishnan, 2017</xref>). Oleic acid along with linoleic acid and sciadonic acid were the shared components identified by GC-MS between lipid-producing endophytic fungus and its host, the Chinese <italic>Torreya grandis</italic> (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Yang et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>).</p><p id="p0150">The GC-MS analysis of an Indian medicinal plant, <italic>Ocimum sanctum,</italic> and its endophytic fungus <italic>Macrophomina phaseolina</italic> revealed a high proportion of Oleic acid in crude extracts from both organisms. The extract was known to possess antifungal activity against phytopathogenic fungi (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Chowdhary and Kaushik 2015</xref>). We also tested the antibacterial activity of the crude extract against clinical pathogenic bacteria. The results showed minor differences in inhibition with greater and broader antibacterial activity by <italic>H.&#x000a0;monticulosa</italic> extract than the <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> rhizome extract. It was proposed that antibacterial activity possessed by oleic acid and other unsaturated fatty acids initiated a disruption of fatty acid synthesis by bacteria led by the expression of Fab1 (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et&#x000a0;al. 2005</xref>).</p><p id="p0155">Although oleic acid was detected in the highest portion of compounds from both extracts, other constituents may also contribute to the antibacterial activity or even cross-inhibit the effectiveness of extracts. The other portion, e.g. Cyclononasiloxane, octadecamethyl-was also detected during a GC-MS analysis between endophytic fungus, <italic>Nigrospora sphaerica</italic> and <italic>Parthenium hysterophorus</italic> with other derivatives of polysiloxane compounds. Cyclononasiloxane, octadecamethyl-was also reported to act as antifungal according to the previous study of <italic>Argemone ochroleuca</italic> latex against pathogenic fungi (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Moustafa et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>).</p><p id="p0160">Based on the identification of purified compounds and NMR data, we conclude that the purified bioactive compound <bold>(2)</bold> derived from our endophytic strain belongs in the group of terpenoids or scalaradial. Scalaradial is a member of scalarane sesterterpenoid which is a ubiquitous secondary metabolite synthesized across organismal taxa, from fungi, marine organisms, and plants (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Dewick 2009</xref>). Scalarane sesterterpenoids are currently being used as chemotaxonomic markers among sponge species which also possessed potential anticancer activities based on laboratory evidences (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Gonz&#x000e1;lez, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Chang et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>). Endophytic fungi produce various forms of terpenoids, but mainly the sesquiterpenoids which displayed multifarous biological activities, such as anticancers, antimicrobials, antitumors, and enzyme inhibitions (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">de Souza et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>). Majority of sesterterpenoids produced by fungi were reported as ophiobolin-type derivatives in the Chinese region dominantly produced by <italic>Aspergillus</italic> and <italic>Bipolaris</italic> which also showed diverse biological activities (<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et&#x000a0;al. 2020</xref>). Asperophioboloins A-K were isolated from a mangrove fungus, <italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp. ZJ-68 which displayed inhibition against <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> and LPS-induced nitric oxide production (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Cai et&#x000a0;al. 2019</xref>). Bipolarins A-H were isolated from an endophytic fungus in wheat plant, <italic>Bipolaris</italic> sp. TJ403-B1 which displayed inhibition against <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Liu et&#x000a0;al. 2019</xref>). In a more recent study, five sesterterpenes were isolated from an endophytic fungus <italic>Aplosporella javeedii</italic> which exhibit a range from moderate to strong-level anticancer activities against cell lines through apoptotic cell death (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Gao et&#x000a0;al. 2020</xref>). In addition, fungal sesterterpenoids were also reported as phytotoxic compounds involved in the chemical defense by allelopathic plants (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Cimmino et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>).</p><p id="p0165">Although sporothriolides have been assigned as chemotaxonomic markers for the species of <italic>Hypoxylon</italic> or <italic>Hypomontagnella</italic> spp; here, we report that different strains may possess different capability in metabolite synthesis during fermentation (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Surup et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). Moreover, we assumed previously that we would find novel chemical compounds produced by our endophytic strain but instead we found an unknown compound of terpenoid-alkaloid <bold>(1)</bold> from its host, <italic>Z.&#x000a0;griffithii</italic> which was also described as an uncommon Zingiberaceous species. The compound was then proposed as a novel compound since only a few thousand molecules originating from terpenoid-alkaloids reported so far, especially those derived from Zingiberaceous sources (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Cherney and Baran 2011</xref>). The compound may be an interesting subject and motivation to reveal the significance of finding other terpenoid-alkaloids from uncommon Zingiberaceous species which may be potential in bioprospective study. Therefore, we claim that this is the first report on the identified scalaradial compound produced by <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic> strain Zg15SU as well as the unknown terpenoid-alkaloid from <italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> from North Sumatra, Indonesia.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0170">Isolation of endophytic fungi residing within the rhizome of <italic>Zingiber griffithii</italic> from North Sumatran forest has revealed an endophytic fungus, identified as <italic>Hypomontagnella monticulosa</italic> producing bioactive metabolites as an antagonistic strain. The antimicrobial activity of both the fungus and rhizome extract were potential against human pathogenic bacteria. Chemical composition based on GC-MS analysis revealed that some portion of bioactive chemicals were observed from both fungus and plant MeOH extracts, indicating a possible co-synthesis between endophyte and its host. Structural elucidation of the highest portion chemicals from both extracts showed that the purified compounds were members of Terpenoid-Alkaloid <bold>(1)</bold> and Sesterterpenoid <bold>(2)</bold> with bioactive properties as anticancer against Panc-1, NBT-T2, and HCT116 cell lines.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec6.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0175">Anisa Lutfia: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments;&#x000a0;Analyzed&#x000a0;and interpreted the data.</p><p id="p0180">Erman Munir: Analyzed&#x000a0;and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0185">Yurnaliza Yurnaliza: Analyzed&#x000a0;and interpreted the data.</p><p id="p0190">Mohammad Basyuni: Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data.</p></sec><sec id="sec6.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0200">This work was supported by <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100009509</institution-id><institution>Ministry of Research, Technology and Higher Education</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, Republic of Indonesia under of PMDSU Research Grant (contract number: 11/E1/KP.PTNBH/2019).</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec6.3"><title>Data availability statement</title><p id="p0205">Data will be made available on request.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec6.4"><title>Declaration of interests statement</title><p id="p0210">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec6.5"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0215">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aly</surname><given-names>A.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debbab</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Proksch</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal endophytes: unique plant inhabitants with great promises</article-title><source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>90</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>1829</fpage><lpage>1845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21523479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altemimi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakhssassi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baharlouei</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>D.-G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lightfoot</surname><given-names>D.-A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemicals: extraction, isolation, and identification of bioactive compounds from plant extracts</article-title><source>Plants</source><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>E42</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28937585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anisha</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname><given-names>E.-K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolite analysis of endophytic fungi from cultivars of <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> Rosc. identifies myriad of bioactive compounds including tyrosol</article-title><source>3 Biotech</source><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balouiri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadiki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibnsouda</surname><given-names>S.-K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods for in vitro evaluating antimicrobial activity: a review</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Pharm. Anal.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29403965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>She</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ophiobolin-type sesterterpenoids from the mangrove endophytic fungus <italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp. ZJ-68</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Nat. Prod.</source><volume>82</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>2269</fpage><lpage>2278</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>H.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>M.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>S.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>G.-F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>I.-S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitory effects of constituents of an endophytic fungus <italic>Hypoxylon investiens</italic> on nitric oxide and interleukin-6 production in RAW264.7 macrophages</article-title><source>Chem. Biodivers.</source><volume>11</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>961</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24934680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>S.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>Y.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>J.-H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytotoxic sesterterpenoids from a sponge <italic>Hippospongia</italic> sp</article-title><source>Mar. Drugs</source><volume>10</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>987</fpage><lpage>997</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22822351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>M.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>H.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>S.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>H.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>I.-S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical constituents of the endophytic fungus <italic>Hypoxylon</italic> sp. 12F0687 isolated from Taiwanese <italic>Ilex formosana</italic></article-title><source>Helv. Chim. Acta</source><volume>98</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1167</fpage><lpage>1176</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cherney</surname><given-names>E.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baran</surname><given-names>P.-S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terpenoid-Alkaloids: their biosynthetic twist of fate and total synthesis</article-title><source>Isr. J. Chem.</source><volume>51</volume><issue>3-4</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26207071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chowdhary</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaushik</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal endophyte diversity and bioactivity in the Indian medicinal plant <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> Linn</article-title><source>PloS One</source><volume>10</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cimmino</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andolfi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evidente</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytotoxic terpenes produced by phytopathogenic fungi and allelopathic plants</article-title><source>Nat. Prod. Comm.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>408</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deshmukh</surname><given-names>S.-K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verekar</surname><given-names>S.-A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhave</surname><given-names>S.-V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endophytic fungi: a reservoir of antibacterials</article-title><source>Front. Microbiol.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>43</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>J.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>I.-J.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues-Filho</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Braz-Filho</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terpenoids from endophytic fungi</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>16</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>10604</fpage><lpage>10618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22183885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dewick</surname><given-names>P.-M.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Medicinal Natural Products - A Biosynthetic Approach</chapter-title><year>2009</year><publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R.-C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>32</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>1792</fpage><lpage>1797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Confidence limits on phylogenies&#x000a0;: an approach using the bootstrap</article-title><source>Evolution</source><volume>39</volume><issue>4</issue><year>1985</year><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28561359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernando</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nursyahra</surname><given-names>Rizki</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studi pemanfaatan tumbuhan familia Zingiberaceae yang berkhasiat obat di Kecamatan luhak nan duo kabupaten pasaman barat</article-title><source>Pendidik. Biol.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuhldreier</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wesselborg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>W.-E.-G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalscheuer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Proksch</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sesterterpenes and macrolide derivatives from the endophytic fungus <italic>Aplosporella javeedii</italic></article-title><source>Fitoterapia</source><volume>146</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>104652</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32512149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ginting</surname><given-names>R.-C.-B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukarno</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Widyastuti</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Darusman</surname><given-names>L.-K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanaya</surname><given-names>S.-K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity of endophytic fungi from red ginger (<italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> Rosc.) plant and their inhibitory effect to <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> plant pathogenic fungi</article-title><source>HAYATI J. Biosci.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>137</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>M.-A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scalarane sesterterpenoids</article-title><source>Curr. Bioact. Comp.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>210</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harborne</surname><given-names>J.-B.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Phytochemical Methods: A Guide to Modern Techniques of Plant Analysis</chapter-title><year>1987</year><publisher-name>Chapman &#x00026; Hall, Inc</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartanto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitmawati Sofiyanti</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studi etnobotani famili Zingiberaceae dalam kehidupan masyarakat lokal di Kecamatan pangean kabupaten kuantan singingi, Riau</article-title><source>Biosaintifika</source><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>108</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hastuti</surname><given-names>U.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahmawati</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sari</surname><given-names>R.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitri</surname><given-names>R.-D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Asna</surname><given-names>P.-M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of endophytic fungi isolated from a medicinal plant, <italic>Hedychium acuminatum</italic> Roscoe</article-title><source>AIP Conf. Proc.</source><volume>50002</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>H.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>L.-P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;friendly relationship between endophytic fungi and medicinal plants: a systematic review</article-title><source>Front. Microbiol.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26834723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juwita</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Puspitasari</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>I.M.</surname></name><name><surname>Levita</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Torch ginger (<italic>Etlingera elatior</italic>): a review on its botanical aspects, phytoconstituents and pharmacological activities</article-title><source>Pak. J. Biol. Sci.</source><volume>21</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30311471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGA7: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 7.0 for bigger datasets</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><volume>33</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1870</fpage><lpage>1874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27004904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hladki</surname><given-names>A.-I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sir</surname><given-names>E.-B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Hypomontagnella</italic> (Hypoxylaceae): a new genus segregated from <italic>Hypoxylon</italic> by a polyphasic taxonomic approach</article-title><source>Mycol. Prog.</source><volume>18</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>201</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leman-Loubi&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>G.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debitus</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouazzani</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Sporochartines A&#x02013;E, a new family of natural products from the marine fungus <italic>Hypoxylon monticulosum</italic> isolated from a <italic>Sphaerocladina</italic> sponge</article-title><source>Front. Mar. Sci.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>399</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leman-Loubi&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>G.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Retailleau</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debitus</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouazzani</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sporothriolide-related compounds from the fungus <italic>Hypoxylon monticulosum</italic> CLL-205 isolated from a <italic>Sphaerocladina</italic> sponge from the Tahiti coast</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Nat. Prod.</source><volume>80</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>2850</fpage><lpage>2854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29043802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.-T.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z.-X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.-H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bipolarins A-H, eight new ophiobolin-type sesterterpenes with antimicrobial activity from fungus Bipolaris sp. TJ403-B1</article-title><source>Chin. J. Nat. Med.</source><volume>17</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>935</fpage><lpage>944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31882049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lutfia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Munir</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yurnaliza</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Antagonistic endophytic fungi of <italic>Hedychium coronarium</italic> Roxb. From hutan sibayak and Taman hutan Raya, North Sumatra against <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC&#x000ae; 29213&#x02122;</article-title><source>IOP Conf. Ser. Earth Environ. Sci.</source><volume>305</volume><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">012002</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lutfia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Munir</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yurnaliza</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Antagonistic endophytic fungi of <italic>Globba pendula</italic> Roxb. From Taman hutan Raya, North Sumatra against <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC&#x000ae; 29213<sup>TM</sup></article-title><source>IOP Conf. Ser. Earth Environ. Sci.</source><volume>305</volume><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">012003</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lutfia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Munir</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yurnaliza Hartanto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antagonistic fungal endophytes colonizing rhizome of <italic>Amomum centrocephalum</italic> A.D. Poulsen from North Sumatera, Indonesia</article-title><source>Int. J. Adv. Sci. Eng. Inf. Technol.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1427</fpage><lpage>1433</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mac&#x000ed;as-Rubalcava</surname><given-names>M.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>R.-E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roque-Flores</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappe-Oliveras</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina-Romero</surname><given-names>Y.-M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volatile organic compounds from <italic>Hypoxylon anthochroum</italic> endophytic strains as postharvest mycofumigation alternative for cherry tomatoes</article-title><source>Food Microbiol.</source><volume>76</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30166162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manter</surname><given-names>D.-K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivanco</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of the ITS primers, ITS1F and ITS4, to characterize fungal abundance and diversity in mixed-template samples by qPCR and length heterogeneity analysis</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Microbiol. Methods</source><volume>71</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17683818</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcellano</surname><given-names>J.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Collanto</surname><given-names>A.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>R.-G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity of endophytic fungi isolated from the bark of <italic>Cinnamomum mercadoi</italic></article-title><source>Pharmacogn. J.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>409</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morgulis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulouris</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raytselis</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>T.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwala</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;ffer</surname><given-names>A.-A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Database indexing for production MegaBLAST searches</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>24</volume><issue>16</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>1757</fpage><lpage>1764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18567917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moustafa</surname><given-names>M.-F.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alamri</surname><given-names>S.-A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taha</surname><given-names>T.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alrumman</surname><given-names>S.-A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro antifungal activity of <italic>Argemone ochroleuca</italic> sweet latex against some pathogenic fungi</article-title><source>Afr. J. Biotechnol.</source><volume>12</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1132</fpage><lpage>1137</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munir</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lutfia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yurnaliza</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Records of culturable endophytic fungi inhabiting rhizome of <italic>elettaria</italic> in hutan sibayak, North Sumatera</article-title><source>IOP Conf. Ser. Earth Environ. Sci.</source><volume>305</volume><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">012004</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nongalleima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>C.-B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thongam</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Devi</surname><given-names>H.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Devi</surname><given-names>S.-I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endophytic fungus isolated from <italic>Zingiber zerumbet</italic> (L.) Sm. inhibits free radicals and cyclooxygenase activity</article-title><source>Int. J. PharmTech Res.</source><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>307</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saitou</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The neighbor-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><year>1987</year><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3447015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez-Ballesteros</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salazar</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acero</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Portal</surname><given-names>M.-A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Juli&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic study of <italic>Hypoxylon</italic> and related genera based on ribosomal ITS sequences</article-title><source>Mycologia</source><volume>92</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>964</fpage><lpage>977</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000e6;ss&#x000f8;e</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lechat</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tichy</surname><given-names>H.-V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piepenbring</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition of hypoxyloid and xylarioid <italic>Entonaema</italic> species and allied <italic>Xylaria</italic> species from a comparison of holomorphic morphology, HPLC profiles, and ribosomal DNA sequences</article-title><source>Mycol. Prog.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quang</surname><given-names>D.-N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asakawa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in secondary metabolism during stromatal ontogeny of <italic>Hypoxylon fragiforme</italic></article-title><source>Mycol. Res.</source><volume>110</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16876700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strobel</surname><given-names>G.-A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endophytes as sources of bioactive products</article-title><source>Microb. Infect.</source><volume>5</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>544</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strobel</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daisy</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioprospecting for microbial endophytes and their natural products</article-title><source>Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev.</source><volume>67</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14665674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strobel</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The emergence of endophytic microbes and their biological promise</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Fungi</source><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>57</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Surup</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhnert</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heitkamper</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>K.-D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sporothriolide derivatives as chemotaxonomic markers for <italic>Hypoxylon monticulosum</italic></article-title><source>Mycology</source><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25379335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomsheck</surname><given-names>A.-R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strobel</surname><given-names>G.-A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geary</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spakowicz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knighton</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Floerchinger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liarzi</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezra</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Hypoxylon</italic> sp., an endophyte of <italic>Persea indica</italic>, producing 1,8-cineole and other bioactive volatiles with fuel potential</article-title><source>Microb. Ecol.</source><volume>60</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>903</fpage><lpage>914</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20953951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ul-Hassan</surname><given-names>S.-R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strobel</surname><given-names>G.-A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knighton</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Floerchinger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of volatile organic compound formation in the mycodiesel-producing endophyte <italic>Hypoxylon</italic> sp. CI-4</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><volume>158</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22096148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uzma</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Konappa</surname><given-names>N.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdappa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity and extracellular enzyme activities of fungal endophytes isolated from medicinal plants of Western Ghats, Karnataka</article-title><source>Egypt. J. Basic Appl. Sci.</source><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>342</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>VanderMolen</surname><given-names>K.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>H.-A.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Elimat</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oberlies</surname><given-names>N.-H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of culture media for the production of secondary metabolites in a natural products screening program</article-title><source>AMB Express</source><volume>71</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and fatty acid analysis of lipid-producing endophytic fungi from wild Chinese <italic>Torreya grandis</italic></article-title><source>Microbiology</source><volume>84</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>710</fpage><lpage>716</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yurnaliza Artyantha</surname><given-names>I.-N.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Esyanti</surname><given-names>R.-R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Susanto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antagonistic activity assessment of fungal endophytes from oil palm tissues against <italic>Ganoderma boninense</italic> Pat</article-title><source>Plant Pathol. J.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>267</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>H.-F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>Y.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H.-W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scalarane sesterterpenes from the Chinese sponge <italic>Phyllospongia foliascens</italic></article-title><source>Helv. Chim. Acta</source><volume>92</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>762</fpage><lpage>767</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;greedy algorithm for aligning DNA sequences</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Comput. Biol.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10890397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progress on terpenoids with biological activities produced by plant endophytic fungi in China between 2017 and 2019</article-title><source>Nat. Prod. Commun.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>J.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T.-G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>H.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W.-G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid synthesis is a target for antibacterial activity of unsaturated fatty acids</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><volume>579</volume><issue>23</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>5157</fpage><lpage>5162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16146629</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0225">The following is the supplementary data related to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ec1"><caption><p>HELIYON-D-20-01023 REV-4 _spl_Clean_spl_</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p></sec></back></article>