<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="st1">
  <title>Background and Purpose:</title>
  <p> Aromatic waters (AWs) are therapeutic distillates, which harbor both essential oil and water-soluble components of a plant. Due to the dispersion of the light amount of essence through the AWs, they have their specific pleasant smell, taste, and medicinal properties. In Iranian traditional medicine, 
   <italic>Trachyspermum ammi</italic> AW is used to treat gastrointestinal disorders. The present study was conducted to determine the chemical composition of the essential oil extracted from 
   <italic>T. ammi</italic> AW and its antifungal activities against 
   <italic>Candida</italic> species.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st2">
  <title>Materials and Methods:</title>
  <p> The composition of the essential oil extracted from 
   <italic>T. ammi</italic> AW was analyzed by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry. In addition, the evaluation of the antifungal activity of AW against 
   <italic>Candida</italic> species was performed using broth microdilution methods as recommended by the Clinical Laboratory Standard Institute. Moreover, the biofilm formation inhibition, antioxidant properties, and experimental activity of AW were determined in an animal model.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st3">
  <title>Results:</title>
  <p> According to the results, thymol (78.08%) was the major compound of EO, followed by carvacrol (8.20%) and carvotanacetone (6.50%). Furthermore, 
   <italic>T. ammi</italic> AW exhibited antifungal activities against the examined fungi and inhibited the biofilm formation of C. albicans at a concentration of up to 0.25 V/V. Histopathological analyses revealed that 
   <italic>Candida</italic> colonization declined in the mice following the administration of
   <italic>T. ammi</italic> AW in a therapeutic trial.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st4">
  <title>Conclusion:</title>
  <p> It seems that the presence of phenolic monoterpenes in AW has resulted in antifungal effects. Pleasant odor and antioxidant properties are extra bonuses to the antimicrobial effects of this plant. Based on the findings, AW might have the potential to be used in the management of alimentary candidiasis or oral hygienic products.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
