<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Eucalyptol, a major component of eucalyptus oil and a minor component of tea tree oil, is a saturated monoterpene known by a variety of synonyms, such as 1,8-cineole, 1,8-epoxy-p-menthane, and cajeputol. This PSM has been demonstrated to retain strong biological activities, including anti-inflammatory, antifungal, antibiofilm, and antiseptic properties toward a range of bacteria [
 <xref rid="B145-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">145</xref>,
 <xref rid="B146-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">146</xref>,
 <xref rid="B147-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">147</xref>,
 <xref rid="B148-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">148</xref>]. The retention of the natural bio-active groups of the 1,8-cineole oil was also achieved using plasma polymerization. Fabricated at 20 W, moderate hydrophobic coatings were achieved, with the ability to reduce the attachment of 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> cells by 98% and 64%, respectively, compared to unmodified glass. In addition, the 1,8-cineole plasma films resisted biofilm formation after 5 days of incubation in the presence of bacterial cells. The polymer surface and any products that may be released from the film were also found not to be cytotoxic to mammalian cells [
 <xref rid="B149-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">149</xref>]. In the same way, Mann and Fisher (2017) used a range of applied RF powers (P = 50–150 W) and H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">(v)</sub> plasma-treatment during the plasma fabrication of 1,8-cineole polymers. The fabricated films retained some antimicrobial behaviors characteristic of the precursor, in addition to the desired properties, such as being highly adherent to the substrate, conformal, and with smooth surfaces. The in vitro studies showed that 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> were largely nonviable and unable to colonize the plasma–cineole surface over the 5 day biofilm development assay period. The biofilm coverage on these surfaces was significantly lower (&lt;10%) than the glass control [
 <xref rid="B150-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">150</xref>].
</p>
