<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A hydroxy-methyl-naphthoquinone is also among of the main compounds (5.3%) found in the essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">rosmarinifolia</italic>. It was recognized as a naphotoquinones belonging to hydroxy-methyl-naphthoquinone since its mass spectrum and its linear retention indices are very similar to those of other known isomers of hydroxyl-methyl-naphthoquinones (e.g. plumbagin, 7-methyl-juglone). It is interesting to note that naphthoquinones are biosynthesized in several plant families (e.g. Plumbaginaceae, Juglandaceae, Boraginaceae, Iridaceae, Verbenaceae, Scrophulariaceae, Gentianaceae, Droseraceae, and Euphorbiaceae, among others) as well as in algae, fungi, some animals and also as products of the metabolism in some bacteria [
 <xref rid="pone.0196947.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. From an ecological point of view, naphthoquinones act as chemical defense for many plants and several naphthoquinones are essentials in the biosynthesis of many molluscicidal and insecticidal compounds (e.g. 2-hydroxy-1,4-naphthoquinone derivatives) [
 <xref rid="pone.0196947.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Furthermore, naphthoquinones and their derivatives are compounds with important pharmacological activities such as anticancer, antibacterial, antifungal, antiviral and anti-parasitic (e.g. antimalarial and antileishmania) [
 <xref rid="pone.0196947.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0196947.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Pharmacological activities showed by naphthoquinones and derivatives can be explicated through two mechanisms: (1) as pro-oxidants, reducing oxygen to reactive oxygen species (ROS); and (2) as electrophiles, forming covalent bonds with tissue nucleophiles [
 <xref rid="pone.0196947.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0196947.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. According to López 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0196947.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>], hydroxy-naphthoquinones and their derivatives are promising compounds for treating disease and for pest control. Several natural compounds exert its antitumor activity through anti or pro-oxidant mechanisms. In the present study, 
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">rosmarinifolia</italic> essential oil induces a strong suppressive growth effects in all tested cancer cell lines, probably through an increase in free radical generation due to diterpenes and hydroxy-methyl-naphthoquinone (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0196947.t001" class="xref">Table 1</xref>) which are the main compounds found in this oil [
 <xref rid="pone.0196947.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0196947.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0196947.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>].
</p>
