<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite its importance for understanding biological invasion, determining the extent of a species' ecological range over time is problematic, since even a dataset based on many field populations may by chance lack infrequent types of sites that would enlarge the range. Indeed, the only 
 <italic>absolutely</italic> definitive way to characterize a species' ecological range at a given time point is to sample every possible location within its geographic distribution and to measure all possible environmental parameters within each of them. A feasible alternative is to construct a set of natural populations, based on a broad sampling of field habitats, that collectively encompass the 
 <italic>full range of environmental conditions</italic> (i.e. the highest and lowest resource levels) in which the species occurs and forms viable populations (
 <xref rid="PLV038C4" ref-type="bibr">Colwell and Futuyma 1971</xref>; see 
 <xref rid="PLV038C27" ref-type="bibr">Sultan 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 1998
 </xref>). This type of population sample, specifically designed to include the environmental extremes in which the species is found, will be more informative for delimiting ecological range than a random population sample (
 <xref rid="PLV038C27" ref-type="bibr">Sultan 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 1998
 </xref>). Moreover, using a smaller number of field sites makes it possible to comprehensively measure environmental variability within each site and to assess the distribution of individuals among different microsites. Such microsite data are critical because they make it possible to distinguish environmental shifts in a species' realized distribution from changes that could possibly result simply from increased dispersal. A final element in this strategy is to focus on certain key environmental variables; such as light, soil moisture and nutrient availability. Using this approach at two or more time points, it is possible to statistically test for changes in ecological range for the specified variables. Despite the inevitable interpretive limitations of a finite field sample, such environmental comparisons can provide useful insights to this critical dimension of invasive spread.
</p>
