<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assessment of decay</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The assessment of decay in different treatment groups required observation of the external and internal features of the flies in the resin, for which we used phase contrast synchrotron tomography, following standard methods for fossil inclusions in amber [
  <a rid="pone.0195482.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref010">10</a>]. We imaged the experiments using different tree resins at 18 months post-entombment. At this point, the flies in 
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">sylvestris</span> resin lacked all internal anatomy, so subsequent experiments to test gut microbiota and dehydration (flies in 
  <span class="italic">W</span>. 
  <span class="italic">nobilis</span> resin) were analysed after 2 weeks to capture possible variations in early-acting decay. Both sets of experiments (resin type and gut biota/dehydration) included untreated flies in 
  <span class="italic">W</span>. 
  <span class="italic">nobilis</span> resin; these directly comparable treatment groups showed very similar amounts of decay at both 2 weeks and 18 months. This suggests, that after a short burst of early decay, decay proceeds extremely slowly. Importantly, for the assessment of decay sufficient morphological loss and modification to distinguish between treatments groups occurs within a 2 week timeframe.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The synchrotron scans were analysed in the program VGStudios Max. For each fly, we noted the presence or absence of cuticle, internal tissues and ruptured abdomens. These data provide a direct indication of morphological decay. The presence of internal bubbles was also noted and provides a proxy for decay. Where bubbles occur the fly cuticle shows no significant expansion, but because bubbles take up space within the body margin internal tissues must be lost, severely diminished and/or distorted by being pushed aside by bubble formation. It was difficult from the synchrotron images to distinguish between loss or distortion of tissues, but either way preservation fidelity of internal tissues is reduced through bubble formation.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The preservation state of fruit flies in resin in each treatment group is based upon the percentage of flies showing features consistent with decay such as: loss of cuticle, loss of internal tissues, presence of bubbles within body margin, and presence of ruptured abdomens. We use Fisher Exact tests to determine if the different treatment groups are significantly associated with differences in decay. Analyses were carried out using the online calculator available at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.physics.csbsju.edu/stats/exact_NROW_NCOLUMN_form.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.physics.csbsju.edu/stats/exact_NROW_NCOLUMN_form.html</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0195482.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref049">49</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
