<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">General experimental design</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We designed experiments to examine whether resin type, dehydration prior to entombment and gut microbiota, influenced decay. To mimic as closely as possible natural entombment of insects in resin flies (
   <span class="italic">Drosophila melanogaster</span>) were embedded in freshly exuded resin, while alive but unconscious; all flies entombed in resin were stored at room temperature (~23°C) for the duration of the experiments. 
   <span class="italic">Wollemia nobilis</span> trees were purchased from wollemipine.co.uk and 
   <span class="italic">Pinus sylvestris</span> trees were purchased from Cole’s Plant Centre in Leicester, UK; fresh resin was collected from cuts on the trunk of each tree. The volume of resin for each experiment was not measured but was approximately equal. Flies were rendered unconscious through brief exposure to freezing temperatures, but importantly fly tissues were not frozen, as evinced by their revival after exposure if they were not quickly entombed. In all treatment groups, the fly is considered to be entrapped when it is stuck to the surface of resin, and entombed when it is entirely covered in resin [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref001">1</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Resin type experiments</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two species of resin-producing trees, with distinct resin chemistries, were used: 
   <span class="italic">Wollemia nobilis</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Pinus sylvestris</span>. 
   <span class="italic">Wollemia nobilis</span> is an Araucariacean, a family of trees whose resin (belonging to Class 1b in the mass spectroscopy resin chemistry classification scheme) is generally characterized by the presence of labanoid terpenoids and the absence of succinic acid [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref001">1</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref020">20</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref021">21</a>]. There is evidence of Araucariacean resin production from the Cretaceous to the Recent [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref020">20</a>]; a number of well-known fossiliferous amber assemblages are thought to have been produced by Araucariaceans, including Burmese amber, Lebanese amber, Spanish amber and French Charentes amber [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref030">30</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref037">37</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Pinus sylvestris</span> is a Pinaceaen, a family of trees whose resin (belonging to Class 5 in a mass spectroscopy resin chemistry classification scheme) is characterized by diterpenoids such as abietane and pimarane [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref001">1</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref022">22</a>]. Class 5 resin in general, and 
   <span class="italic">Pinus</span> resin in particular, does not polymerize well and is therefore very uncommon in the fossil record [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref001">1</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref009">9</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref021">21</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on taxonomy, we expected that the two resin chemistry variable states in this experiment were significantly different; we confirmed this through solid phase microextraction gas chromatography mass spectrometry (SPME GC-MS) to characterise the volatile and semi-volatile components in the resin following previous methods [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref038">38</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref041">41</a>]. A 0.5 g sample of resin from each tree species was dried and powdered. Prior to analyses each vial of resin powder was equilibrated at 80°C for one hour and exposed to a 65 μm Polydimethylsiloxane/Divinylbenzene (PDMS/DVB) SPME fibre for one hour, and analysed on a Thermo Scientific Trace 1310 GC. A liquid injection of a standard mixture containing a series of 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes was used to calibrate retention indices to aid in identifying the peaks. The chromatograms for each sample were imported into the program AMDIS and the major peaks in each chromatogram were identified through a National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) MS database search.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chemical characterization of the 
   <span class="italic">P</span>. 
   <span class="italic">sylvestris</span> and 
   <span class="italic">W</span>. 
   <span class="italic">nobilis</span> resins confirms that they are distinct (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s001" href="#pone.0195482.s001">S1 Fig</a>, 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s007" href="#pone.0195482.s007">S1 Table</a>). Of the 52 identified compounds, 18 were only found in one of the two resins (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s007" href="#pone.0195482.s007">S1 Table</a>, bolded compounds). Of the remaining 34 compounds, eight were found in much higher concentrations in one resin than the other (the difference in the total percent of that compound in the two resins &gt; 5%, 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s007" href="#pone.0195482.s007">S1 Table</a>). In total we found twenty-three compounds that differ between 
   <span class="italic">P</span>. 
   <span class="italic">sylvestris</span> and 
   <span class="italic">W</span>. 
   <span class="italic">nobilis</span> resin (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s008" href="#pone.0195482.s008">S2 Table</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gut microbiota and dehydration experiments</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The variables dehydration prior to entombment and gut microbiota and were tested on flies in 
   <span class="italic">W</span>. 
   <span class="italic">nobilis</span> resin. This resin was selected because it is a better proxy for amber in the fossil record and because decay in pine resin was so rapid that capture of data on decay would have been difficult using available synchrotron intervals.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the gut microbiota treatment group we used untreated wild-type flies and flies treated with an antibiotic to alter their bacterial composition and abundances. Wild-type 
   <span class="italic">Drosophila melanogaster</span> were collected in October 2015 by netting after the harvest in a vineyard in Market Harborough (UK). Immediately, fertilized females were isolated to generate isofemale lines. The isofemale lines were continuously maintained at 18°C in a 12hr:12hr Light:Dark (LD) cycle on standard corn meal food until the time of the experiment. Groups of 10 males (3–4 days old) were collected from 28 isofemale lines and housed in 20 antibiotic treated or 20 untreated vials (for the antibiotic treatment groups and wild type treatment groups, respectively). A solution of Ampicilin and Cloranphenicol (7mg/ml each in 50% Ethanol) was dropped (100ul) on the surface of the food in the antibiotic treated vials. Treated vials were also exposed to UV O/N. The vials were replaced every 2 days for a total of 10 days in LD12:12 at 25°C. The flies were then collected 3 hours after light on (Zeitgeber Time ZT 3) in UV treated 15ml falcon tube in ice, and were then entombed in resin.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We confirmed that the antibiotic treatment altered the wild-type fruit fly gut microbiotas, and investigated the gut microbiota composition in more detail, through 16S rRNA ion torrent sequencing of the V1 region of the gut microbiotas of ten untreated flies and nine antibiotic treated flies from the same isofemale lines as the flies used in the experiments. Operational taxonomic units were binned by 97% similarity and classified using the GreenGenes 13_8 reference database. The gut microbiota composition of the wild-type and antibiotic-treated flies were compared using nonmetric multidimensional scaling on three metrics [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref042">42</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref043">43</a>]: weighted UniFrac distance; unweighted UniFrac distance; and the Jaccard index. Diversity distributions (based on the Shannon index [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref044">44</a>] for alpha diversity and the Jaccard index [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref043">43</a>] for beta diversity) were assessed and statistically compared using Kruskal-Wallis tests [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref045">45</a>]. All bioinformatics sequence processing up to OTU table generation was conducted using QIIME version 1.9.1 [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref046">46</a>]. Statistical analyses and graphical output were performed with Rstudio version 0.99.484. The primary R package used for analysis of the OTU table was Phyloseq 1.12.2 [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref047">47</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unweighted NMDS cluster analysis with either UniFrac or Jaccard distance measurements completely separates the two treatment groups (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s003" href="#pone.0195482.s003">S3 Fig</a>). In particular, there is a significant difference in alpha diversity (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s005" href="#pone.0195482.s005">S5 Fig</a>), based on the Shannon index (p = 0.04). There are similarities in microbiota community distribution of genera and phyla (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s002" href="#pone.0195482.s002">S2 Fig</a>) between the wild-type and antibiotically-treated groups. All flies, both wild-type and antibiotic-treated, had microbiotas dominated by the genus 
   <span class="italic">Wolbachia</span> (with a relative abundance of 96% and 98%, respectively, 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s002" href="#pone.0195482.s002">S2 Fig</a>, 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s009" href="#pone.0195482.s009">S3 Table</a>), an endoparasitic bacterium common in the cell bodies of fruit flies and other insects [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref048">48</a>]. 
   <span class="italic">Wolbachia</span> is not part of the gut microbiota, but is an internal bacterium that may contribute to microbial decay. The next most common genera in both groups are 
   <span class="italic">Lactobacillus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Acetobacter</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">Streptococcus</span> (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s002" href="#pone.0195482.s002">S2 Fig</a>, 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s009" href="#pone.0195482.s009">S3 Table</a>), all of which are commonly reported as dominant genera in fruit fly gut microbiotas [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref019">19</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To summarize, 16S rRNA sequencing of both types of fly showed differences in the minor components of the gut microbiome. Differences in these less-abundant genera are sufficient to separate the untreated and antibiotic treated flies into two distinct gut biota groups, which are cohesive and significantly different from each other. The antibiotic treated flies have a less diverse gut biota, containing 25 genera compared to the 44 genera in the wild-type flies (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s003" href="#pone.0195482.s003">S3</a>–
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s005" href="#pone.0195482.s005">S5</a> Figs, 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s009" href="#pone.0195482.s009">S3 Table</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effect of dehydration on decay was investigated using both untreated wild-type flies and antibiotic treated flies (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0195482.g001" href="#pone.0195482.g001">Fig 1</a>). Three states of dehydration were tested: not dehydrated; dehydrated at 50°C for three days while entrapped on the resin surface, but before entombment; and dehydrated isolated from the resin at 50°C for three days before entombment.
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0195482.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0195482.g001</span>
   <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Experimental schematic.</div>
    <p>Schematic representing the variables tested (resin type, gut microbiota and dehydration state) and treatment groups in experiments. The number in each resin circle represents the number of replicates.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0195482.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec007" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assessment of decay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The assessment of decay in different treatment groups required observation of the external and internal features of the flies in the resin, for which we used phase contrast synchrotron tomography, following standard methods for fossil inclusions in amber [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref010">10</a>]. We imaged the experiments using different tree resins at 18 months post-entombment. At this point, the flies in 
   <span class="italic">P</span>. 
   <span class="italic">sylvestris</span> resin lacked all internal anatomy, so subsequent experiments to test gut microbiota and dehydration (flies in 
   <span class="italic">W</span>. 
   <span class="italic">nobilis</span> resin) were analysed after 2 weeks to capture possible variations in early-acting decay. Both sets of experiments (resin type and gut biota/dehydration) included untreated flies in 
   <span class="italic">W</span>. 
   <span class="italic">nobilis</span> resin; these directly comparable treatment groups showed very similar amounts of decay at both 2 weeks and 18 months. This suggests, that after a short burst of early decay, decay proceeds extremely slowly. Importantly, for the assessment of decay sufficient morphological loss and modification to distinguish between treatments groups occurs within a 2 week timeframe.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The synchrotron scans were analysed in the program VGStudios Max. For each fly, we noted the presence or absence of cuticle, internal tissues and ruptured abdomens. These data provide a direct indication of morphological decay. The presence of internal bubbles was also noted and provides a proxy for decay. Where bubbles occur the fly cuticle shows no significant expansion, but because bubbles take up space within the body margin internal tissues must be lost, severely diminished and/or distorted by being pushed aside by bubble formation. It was difficult from the synchrotron images to distinguish between loss or distortion of tissues, but either way preservation fidelity of internal tissues is reduced through bubble formation.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The preservation state of fruit flies in resin in each treatment group is based upon the percentage of flies showing features consistent with decay such as: loss of cuticle, loss of internal tissues, presence of bubbles within body margin, and presence of ruptured abdomens. We use Fisher Exact tests to determine if the different treatment groups are significantly associated with differences in decay. Analyses were carried out using the online calculator available at 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.physics.csbsju.edu/stats/exact_NROW_NCOLUMN_form.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.physics.csbsju.edu/stats/exact_NROW_NCOLUMN_form.html</span> [
   <a rid="pone.0195482.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195482.ref049">49</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
