<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The molecular markers used for population genetics studies are currently essentially of two kinds: genome-wide Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms (SNPs) identified by next-generation-sequencing-based techniques such as Restriction site Associated DNA sequencing (RAD-seq) or genotyping-by-sequencing [
 <xref rid="pone.0176197.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], and Simple Sequence Repeats (SSR) markers (microsatellites). Some limitations of SSR markers are low density throughout the genome, complex mutational patterns and possible presence of homoplasy and null alleles [
 <xref rid="pone.0176197.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. However, SSR markers are easy to score, highly polymorphic and thus highly informative and the theory and practice of SSR marker analysis and their afferent bias are well known [
 <xref rid="pone.0176197.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], making them still the markers of choice for ecological and evolutionary studies. In comparison to SNPs, SSRs are especially well suited for analyzing processes occurring at small temporal or spatial scales and have proven highly relevant for revealing recent expansion and recent admixture or analyzing parentage and kinship [
 <xref rid="pone.0176197.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0176197.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Next-generation sequencing technologies now allow to rapidly develop large sets of SSRs [
 <xref rid="pone.0176197.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In addition, the ever-increasing availability of transcriptome sequences (Expressed Sequence Tags, EST) in public databases enables fast and cost-effective development of genic SSRs marker (EST-SSRs). EST-SSRs are expected to be less polymorphic than gSSRs but also to display fewer null alleles and be more transferable among related species [
 <xref rid="pone.0176197.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0176197.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. As their polymorphism may be influenced by selective processes, EST-SSRs may reveal somewhat different genetic patterns than gSSRs [
 <xref rid="pone.0176197.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
</p>
