<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A liquid chromatograph (Merck-Hitachi, LaChrom Elite) containing a DAD detector (L-2455) was used for the chromatographic analyses. A Purospher RP-18e column (250 × 4 mm; 5 μm, Merck) was used with a mobile phase: A—methanol, and B—0.5% acetic acid and methanol 1:4 (v/v), in a gradient program: 0–20′ 100% B; 20–35′ 100–80% B; 35–55′ 80–60% B; 55–70′ 60–0% B; 70–75′ 0%; 0–100% B for 75–80′; 80–90′ 100% B (1 ml/min). The injection volume of the sample was 20 µL, temperature was set at 25 °C and wavelengths were from 210 to 400 nm. Qualitative and quantitative analyses were read at 254 nm. The method was validated former by our group [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-01086" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-plants-09-01086" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Retention times and UV spectra were compared to standards to identify the compounds investigated in the methanolic extracts. Calibration curves were used to detect the chemical compounds. Calibration equations of detected compounds were as follows: chlorogenic acid (y = 44790418.3x − 45222.5), caffeic acid (y = 59811859.9x − 145632.3), 
 <italic>p</italic>-coumaric acid (y = 31143463.3x + 37623.6), ferulic acid (y = 60949159.6x + 44967.3), rutoside (y = 59420774.2x + 66560.0), quercetin (y = 67269930.4x − 813339.4), rosmarinic acid (y = 36295528.6x − 232028.2), quercitrin (y = 57911264.5x − 1446794.6), trifolin (y = 80650805.9x − 583711.0), protocatechuic acid (y = 135776068.2x − 259871.0), hydrocaffeic acid (y = 5883705.0x + 30869.7), cynaroside (y = 100536033.3x +- 3483461.8). All 38 standards used for analyses were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (Berin, Germany). We screened for 22 phenolic acids including: benzoic acid and some derivatives (ellagic, 3,4-dihydroxyphenylacetic, protocatechuic, 
 <italic>p</italic>-hydroxybenzoic, gallic, vanillic, gentisic, syringic and salicylic acids); cinnamic acid and some derivatives (sinapic, 
 <italic>o</italic>-, 
 <italic>m</italic>-, 
 <italic>p</italic>-coumaric acid, isoferulic, ferulic, hydrocaffeic and caffeic acids); and depsides (neochlorogenic, rosmarinic and chlorogenic acids); seven flavonoid aglycones (naringin, quercetin, cynaroside, rhamnetin, luteolin, myricetin and kaempferol); and nine flavonoid glycosides (trifolin, vitexin, apigetrin, cynaroside, robinin, rutoside, hyperoside, quercitrin and isoquercetin). 
</p>
