<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28" class="p">Sea buckthorn (
 <italic class="italic">Hippophae</italic>) is a hardy bush of the 
 <italic class="italic">Elaegnaceae</italic> family classified into nine subspecies, from which 
 <italic class="italic">Hipopphae rhamnoides L. subsp sinensis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Hippophae rhamnoides L. subsp rhamnoides</italic> are the most applied to commercial purposes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>]. It is a deciduous spiny species distributed all over the temperate zone of Asia and Europe, as well as over subtropical zones at high altitude [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>]. Its products, particularly the oil obtained from the seed and the soft parts of the plant, contain an interesting composition of lipophilic compounds. In relation to the oil composition, sea buckthorn is characterized by a unique mixture of bioactive components, being one of them the fatty acids. In general, the oil obtained from seed is rich in omega-3 and omega-6 fatty acids, while in the pulp oils are predominantly fatty acids from the omega-7 group [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>] (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). Although the prevalence of fatty acids in the different parts is well established, there could be variations depending on the subspecies, harvesting time and method of isolation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>]. Several mechanisms of oil extraction are used, solvent extraction using hexane and supercritical CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> being the most common in industrial and laboratory scale [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>]. In any case, several studies of fatty acids contained in sea buckthorn oil reveal that it may play an important role in very different aspects in relation to the human body, such as cardiovascular disorders, as a stimulator of the immune system, as well as promoting cognitive functions and bone health [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>]. Moreover, it may be important to improve various skin conditions such as atopic dermatitis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>], acne skin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>] or psoriasis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>].
</p>
