<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par50">The Libyan flora is spread over a diversity of geomorphologic regions which in return gives rise to a variety of climatic conditions suitable for the growth of different types of plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. One of the widespread plants in Al Jabal Al Akhdar region in Libya are members of family Lamiaceae like 
 <italic>Satureja</italic> genus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. 
 <italic>Satureja</italic> comprises more than 200 species of popular herbs or shrubs that are often aromatic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In Al Jabal Al Akhdar, two main species of 
 <italic>Satureja</italic> dominate, 
 <italic>S. thymbra</italic> and 
 <italic>S. fortii</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. 
 <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> L.
 <italic>,</italic> known as pink savory, is an aromatic plant with oregano-like smell that is endemic to the Mediterranean region. The main chemical classes identified in the essential oil include monoterpene hydrocarbons such as 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene and γ-terpinene, oxygenated monoterpenes, especially phenolic constituents as thymol and carvacrol. Also, sesquiterpene hydrocarbons were detected as β-caryophyllene and α-humulene as well as oxygenated sesquiterpenes such as caryophyllene oxide [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The plant is also rich in other phenolic constituents like flavonoids and flavonoid glycosides as well as tannins, acids and exudates [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Due to the presence of these compounds, 
 <italic>S. thymbra</italic> L. has been evaluated as antibacterial, antifungal and antiviral agent [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. 
 <italic>The essential</italic> oil proved an antimicrobial activity against several bacteria and fungi like 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic>, 
 <italic>Shigella sonnei</italic>, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and some resistant strains such as 
 <italic>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic>, 
 <italic>S. maltophilia</italic>, and 
 <italic>Chryseomonas luteolaas</italic> as well as the yeast 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The essential oil of 
 <italic>S. thymbra</italic> (1%) has also been reported to possess a strong bactericidal activity against bacterial biofilms formed on stainless steel by some pathogenic bacteria [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The oil has also shown an in-vitro inhibitory activity against SARS-CoV and HSV-1 replication by visually scoring of the virus-induced cytopathogenic effects post-infection with a high selectivity index (SI) against HSV-1 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The oil also had a high SI when tested for its cytotoxicity in Vero cells using MTT assay [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Essential oil of 
 <italic>S. thymbra</italic> has also been reported to possess an insecticidal activity against the mosquito 
 <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> biotype 
 <italic>molestus</italic>, acaricidal effect against 
 <italic>Hyalomma marginatum</italic>, genotoxic activity against 
 <italic>Drosophila</italic> as well as insecticidal activity against three stored-product insects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Other reported activities for the oil included improving circulation and thus being used in the treatment of arthritis, rheumatism, as a wound healing promoter and in painful joints and muscles [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Being evaluated for cholinesterase inhibitory and antioxidative effects, the essential oil is suggested to treat amnesia and Alzeheimer’s diseases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Traditionally, it has been used in food flavoring, perfumery and in local home remedies as antiseptic and diuretic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].
</p>
