<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0005">Plants and phytocompounds contribute the requirements for food, clothes and renewable sources for pharmaceutical agents with great potential of antimicrobial and anticancer agents. Plants extract including, roots, leaves and stems can be used as raw drugs with different medicinal properties (
 <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Mahesh and Satish, 2008</xref>) and phytocompounds showed a broad spectrum of anticancer with low side effects (
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Cragg and Newman, 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Newman and Cragg, 2016</xref>). Several strategies, including searching for new antimicrobials from natural products are highly recommended to combat antibiotic resistance (
 <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Enioutina et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Ngezahayo et al., 2015</xref>), in addition to the high cost of synthetic antibiotics and their harmful side effects for infection treatment (
 <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Elizabeth, 2005</xref>). These imply searching for new alternative antibiotics from medicinal plants which can be used as a desirable tool to eradicate the population of pathogenic strains, particularly in the treatment of infectious and dreadful diseases (
 <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Enioutina et al., 2017</xref>). The antimicrobial drugs from natural products are getting greater interest in many research projects (
 <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Aliero and Afolayan, 2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Eloff et al., 2005</xref>). Cancer diseases attributed to a human colorectal, liver and breast carcinoma are common in our zone (middle east and Arab countries), and hence finding compounds having potential activity against the referred cancer cell lines is highly recommended (
 <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Abu-Darwish and Efferth, 2018</xref>). Furthermore, plant extracts and phytocompounds have been reported to bear more than 60% of the common anticancer drugs (
 <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Seelinger et al., 2012</xref>). 
 <italic>Euphorbia balsamifera</italic> belongs to family Euphorbiaceae, which is characterized by a broad spectrum of medicinal properties (
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Ben Jannet et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Ernst et al., 2015</xref>). The latex of 
 <italic>Euphorbia balsamifera</italic> is effective as a pulpal devitalizing agent (
 <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Yam, A. A., Gaye, F., Dieme, F. A., Bassene, E., &amp; Ba, 1997</xref>). In addition, the plant’s leaves, stems and roots showed antimicrobial activities against some pathogenic microorganisms (
 <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Kamba and Hassan, 2010</xref>). Wound healing activity was observed for methanol extract of the plant which is identical with the standard drug Povidone-iodine (
 <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed et al., 2016</xref>), although its phytochemical screening revealed the presence of different classes of secondary metabolites. Isolation and structure assigning of these metabolites were not reported previously so far. Therefore, the aim of the present study is to evaluate the antibacterial and cytotoxic activity of the plant fractions and identify the chemical constituents for the most active fractions using different chromatographic and spectroscopic means, and then investigating their antibiotic and cytotoxic activities intensively.
</p>
