<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Za’atar must have special flavor and odor without any external flavors and odors that may come from molds, rancidity, or any other substances. Additionally, the color of za’atar mix products should be normal and consistent with the color of such products. All ingredients used for the preparation of za’atar mix products should meet their Codex Alimentarius standards. They should not contain any living insects or spiders, and should be reasonably free from any noticeable molds, dead insects, parts of insects, or rodents, birds, and snail waste. Za’atar mix products must not be in a powder form to guarantee that all the main ingredients of the mix can be seen at a microscopic level or by the naked eye. This will ensure avoiding frauds and impurities concealment. It will also maintain a higher level of essential oil. If the product contained straws, they should not make more than 5% of the mass of the products, and they should not be more than 10 mm in length and 2 mm in diameter. Any non-vegetable origin substance such as soil, dust, sand, etc., or non-food vegetable substance such as wood or dry leaves found in za’atar mix products, should make more than 1% of the mass of the product. 
 <xref rid="plants-10-01001-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows Codex Alimentarius specific chemical composition requirements for each za’atar mix category products. Only regular za’atar mix can contain the additive citric acid in a quantity that does not exceed 4 mg/kg [
 <xref rid="B10-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The International Organization for Standardization (ISO) established a specification for whole or ground-dried 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> species and sub-species leaves in both processed and semi-processed products, and published it in the ISO 7925 report in 1999. The ISO requirements included: oregano odor and flavor must be aromatic, warm, fragrant, pungent, and bitter, and be free of foreign flavors; oregano products should be free from insects, molds, etc.; extraction matter should not exceed 1% by mass in processed products and 3% in semi-processed products; and oregano plant parts such as stalks should not exceed 3% in the products. Ground oregano must completely pass through a sieve with a 500 μm nominal aperture size. 
 <xref rid="plants-10-01001-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the ISO chemical requirements for dried oregano. Oregano product packs should be sound, dry, clean, and made from materials that protect the product against foreign bodies, loss or ingress of moisture, and volatiles loss without affecting it. The label of the product must include the following: product name, type, trade name, producer or packer address, trademark, batch code or number, net mass, produced country, any other consumer-required information such as harvesting year and packing date, any treatments of the product, and the reference to the ISO standard [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
</p>
