<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Both SL and sterols will eventually concentrate on the PM. This, together with a remodeling of PL acyl chains to a more saturated pattern, generates a tight lipid packing of sterols with PL. This packing is indeed responsible of the rigidity and thickness of this barrier isolating the intracellular from the extracellular milieu. The trans-Golgi is critical in the transition from the thin and loosely packed membrane found in the ER to the thick and rigid bilayer found at the PM. This transition, mediated by SL and sterols, is easily recognized following the single-spanning membrane proteins involved in the secretory pathway. Those membrane proteins contain transmembrane domains (TMDs) whose length and composition vary during the transition from the ER to the PM. Thus, for ER and Golgi-resident proteins, TMDs are considerably shorter than those for PM proteins [
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. Both TMD length and volume decide the fate of these proteins, i.e., Golgi retention or export to the PM [
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Since selective associations between matching lipids and TMDs have proven sufficient to drive their co-segregation in model membranes [
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>], the preservation of the distinctive mixtures of membrane proteins and lipids that allow the ER and PM to execute their fundamentally unique tasks might be achieved by the Golgi exploiting physical principles such as hydrophobic mismatch and packing density. In turn, the outlined different TMD features in ER and PM exert temporal and spatial control over the main events governing the secretory pathway. Hence, early secretory organelles contain proteins bearing neutral amphipathic lipid packing sensor (ALPS) motifs. Those proteins show bulky hydrophobic residues that easily accommodate into lipid-packing imperfections. In contrast, late secretory organelles concentrate peripheral membrane proteins bearing polybasic motifs [
 <xref rid="B40-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>].
</p>
