<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Fibrogenesis is a multicellular wound healing process that occurs as a frequent consequence of many chronic liver injuries [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Regardless of its etiology, hepatic fibrosis is generally characterized by oxidative tissue damage, inflammatory cells infiltration, HSCs activation, and excessive collagen deposition [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Accumulating clinical and experimental evidences have shown that the halting of the fibrogenic process may allow the reversal of liver fibrosis. Indeed, resolution of liver fibrosis or even cirrhosis may occur upon eradication of the causative insult [
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Oxidative stress has been proposed as a conjoint pathological mechanism in the initiation and progression of fibrosis [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Thereby, inhibition of ROS-mediated fibrogenesis might yield great potential therapeutic benefits. In this context, attention is progressively shifting towards herbal products and their antioxidant constituents [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. 
 <italic>M. piperita</italic> has been known for its great multipharmaceutical benefits [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The active phytocompounds of MPEO contribute to many of its profound therapeutic actions. Although the hepatoprotective effect of MPOE was previously demonstrated [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], its antifibrogenic influence against hepatic fibrosis has not been investigated yet. The present study aimed to evaluate the potential of MPOE to ameliorate CCl
 <sub>4</sub>-induced hepatic fibrosis in rats and to elucidate some aspects of its underlying molecular mechanisms.
</p>
