<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">Accumulating scientific evidence demonstrates the important role that omega-3 long-chain (&gt;C
 <sub class="sub">20</sub>) polyunsaturated fatty acids (n-3 LC-PUFA) play in conditions such as cardiovascular disease, certain cancers and other diseases
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>. Chen 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup> suggested that both dietary and circulating LC-PUFA were inversely associated with all-cause mortality. In another study, Stark 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup> found that most of the countries and regions of the world having very low to low range of blood n-3 LC-PUFA were associated with an increased risk of chronic diseases. Therefore, the consumption of adequate n-3 LC-PUFA is crucial to maintaining a healthy body and for the prevention of chronic diseases. However, humans like all other mammals, cannot synthesise n-3 LC-PUFA because they lack the necessary Δ12 and Δ15-desaturase enzymes. Therefore, these health-benefitting fatty acids must be supplied in the diet
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>
 </sup>. Humans can obtain n-3 LC-PUFA or their C
 <sub class="sub">18</sub> PUFA precursors from various sources including aquatic (fish, crustaceans, and mollusks), farm livestock products (meat, egg, and milk), oilseeds, fruits, herbs, cyanobacteria and microorganisms (bacteria, fungi, microalgae, and diatoms)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup>. Ruminant meat research has drawn considerable attention because ruminant meat contains some bioactive lipids (including n-3 LC-PUFA) and the fatty acid profiles of ruminant meat can be enhanced through dietary supplementation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup>. In this regard, the manipulation of fatty acid profiles in sheep meat via dietary n-3 LC-PUFA supplementation has yielded some promising results. Flakemore 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup> reported that supplementation of degummed crude canola oil to lambs improved n-3 LC-PUFA contents in meat. Supplementing prime lambs with 5% flaxseed or canola oil pellets increased n-3 LC-PUFA in the liver, heart, kidney and 
 <italic class="italic">longissimus thoracis et lumborum</italic> muscle tissue
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>. Boles 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup> found that supplementation of safflower oil at up to 6% of sheep diet on as-fed basis, increased levels of PUFA and conjugated linoleic acids (especially the cis-9, trans-11 isomer) in the lean tissue. However, the studies described above emphasised the need to find new n-3 LC-PUFA feed sources and associated optimal supplementation levels. There are only a handful of published comparative studies into different dietary oil sources and their ability to elevate the level of n-3 LC-PUFA in lamb, especially under feedlot finishing systems. Feeding lambs in an intensive finishing system, such as a feedlot, has rapidly become a specialised component of the prime lamb industry with the number of lambs being grain finished steadily increasing. This increase in intensive feeding can be mainly attributed to the export demand for a consistent supply of lambs that meet market specifications. This is particularly so when quality pasture feed is unavailable or during drought conditions. Therefore, we hypothesised herein that the fatty acid profiles of the 
 <italic class="italic">longissimus dorsi</italic> muscle, liver, kidney and heart of Australian prime lambs would differ in response to supplementation with various dietary PUFA sources under a typical intensive, in-door feedlot management system. It was intended that this study would provide outcomes that can be used as guidelines for lamb producers for a better utilisation of available dietary n-3 LC-PUFA sources for enhancing lamb nutritional quality and beneficial human health outcomes.
</p>
