<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant material</div>
  <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aerial parts of 
   <span class="italic">Zanthoxylum acanthopodium</span> were collected from 33 families of plants in the Ailao Mountains, Yunnan Province, China, in May 2013. Plant specimens were identified by Dr. Yin-zhang Zhou. The plants were dried under shade (at room temperature). The voucher specimen (No. IBSC/0387990) was deposited in the South China Botanical Garden, Chinese Academy of Sciences.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Isolation of the essential oil</div>
  <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The air-dried plant materials (2000
   <span class="italic">g</span>) of 
   <span class="italic">Zanthoxylum acanthopodium</span> were chopped and subjected to hydrodistillation for 6 h using a Clevenger type apparatus. The obtained oils were dried over hydrous sodium sulfate for 24 h, filtered, and then stored at 4 °C in brown sealed glass vials until tested.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC analysis</div>
  <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An Agilent HP-6890 gas chromatograph (Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA, USA) with a HP-5 5% phenylmethylsiloxane capillary column (30 m × 0.25 mm i.d., 0.25 μm film thickness) and an FID detector was used for GC–FID analysis. Helium gas (1 mL/min) was used as the carrier gas. Injector and mass transfer line temperatures were set at 250 and 280 °C, respectively. The EO solution (1 μL) in hexane was injected and analysed under the following column conditions: initial column temperature of 40 °C for 1 min, increased to 250 °C at a 3 °C/min, and maintained at 250 °C for 20 min.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC–MS analysis</div>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The oils were quantitatively and qualitatively analysed using a GC–MS 6890-5975 system (Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA, USA) equipped with a HP-5 MS fused silica capillary column (30 m × 0.25 mm i.d., 0.25 μm film thickness). For GC–MS detection, an electron ionization system with ionization energy of 70 eV was used. Helium gas (1 mL/min) was used as carrier gas. Injector and mass transfer line temperatures were set at 250 and 280 °C, respectively. EO solution (1 μL) in hexane was injected and analysed under the following column conditions: initial column temperature at 40 °C for 1 min, increased to 250 °C at a 3 °C/min heating ramp, and maintained at 250 °C for 20 min. Kovats indices were calculated for all of the volatile components by using a homologous series of 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes (C
   <sub>8</sub>–C
   <sub>25</sub>) in an HP-5 MS column. The major oil components were identified by co-injection with standards (whenever possible) and confirmed using the Wiley (V.7.0) and National Institute of Standards and Technology V.2.0 GC–MS library on the basis of Kovats indices. The relative concentration of each compound in the oil was quantified on the basis of the peak area integrated in the analysis program.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mosquito larvicidal assay</div>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The eggs of 
   <span class="italic">An. sinensis</span> and 
   <span class="italic">An. anthropophagus</span> were received from Centre for Disease Control and Prevention of Guangdong Province, China. Twenty-five larvae were reared in 250 mL glass beaker and fed with Brewer’s yeast/dog biscuit (1:3) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. The beaker with larvae were maintained at 27 ± 2 °C, 75 ± 2% relative humidity and photoperiod of 14:10 (L:D) h. Larvicidal activity of the essential oil and of the main compounds (estragole and eucalyptol) isolated from the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">Zanthoxylum acanthopodium</span> were evaluated according to the standard procedures suggested by the WHO [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. The essential oil and compounds were dissolved in 1 mL of DMSO solution and prepared into different concentrations (25, 50, 75, 100 125, and 150 ppm) using distilled water. For comparison commercial larvicide Pylarvex (Pyrethrum Board of Kenya) was used as a positive control. Twenty larvae of early fourth-instar stage were used in the larvicidal assay and five replicates were maintained for each concentration. During this experiment no food was offered to the larvae. The larval mortality was calculated after the 24 h exposure period.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The average larval mortality data were subjected to probit analysis for calculating LC
   <sub>50</sub>, LC
   <sub>90</sub> and other statistics at 95% fiducial limits of upper confidence limit and lower confidence limit, and Chi square values were calculated by using the software using Statistical Package of Social Sciences (SPSS) 13.0 for windows, the significance level was set at P &lt; 0.05.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
