<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To determine the stereochemistry-activity relationship on the growth inhibitory effects of the kielcorins C-E, chiral liquid chromatography (cLC) methods were developed for their enantioseparation, using polysaccharide-based chiral stationary phases (CSPs) and multimodal elution conditions, in 2004 [
 <xref rid="B131-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]. Later, the enantiomers of the kielcorins C-E were efficiently separated on a multimilligram scale using an amylose 
 <italic>tris</italic>-3,5-dimethylphenylcarbamate CSP [
 <xref rid="B132-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. A solid-phase injection system was developed and combined with a closed loop recycling system to increase the productivity and recovery of the preparative process. The enantiomeric purity was also evaluated being higher than 99%, except for 
 <italic>trans-</italic>kielcorin C (
 <bold>61</bold>) [
 <xref rid="B132-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. It must be highlighted that the development of methods to obtain and analyse both pure enantiomers has been acquired crucial importance, as are required for biological and pharmacological activity evaluation of both enantiomers [
 <xref rid="B133-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>]. The inhibitory activity of the racemates C-E as well as of the corresponding enantiomers on in vitro growth of the human breast adenocarcinoma cell line MCF-7 was evaluated and compared. The most evident enantioselectivity was found between the racemate of 
 <italic>trans</italic>-kielcorin D (
 <bold>62</bold>) (inactive) and the active enantiomers (+)-
 <bold>62</bold> and (−)-
 <bold>62</bold> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00431-f016">Figure 16</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B134-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>,
 <xref rid="B135-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>,
 <xref rid="B136-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>].
</p>
