<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Considering that carboxyxanthone derivatives are appropriate chemical substrates to perform molecular modifications to obtain diverse derivatives and analogues [
 <xref rid="B138-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>], we selected different compounds, comprising one or more carboxylic groups, to perform the referred syntheses [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B135-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>,
 <xref rid="B136-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>,
 <xref rid="B137-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. Both enantiomers of a variety of amino alcohols, amines, and amino esters were chosen as chiral building blocks, containing a primary amine as reactive group for amide formation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00431-f017">Figure 17</xref>). Until now, 
 <italic>O</italic>-(benzotriazol-1-yl)-
 <italic>N</italic>,
 <italic>N</italic>,
 <italic>N</italic>’,
 <italic>N</italic>’-tetramethyluronium tetrafluoroborate (TBTU) was demonstrated to be the best coupling reagent to synthesize CDXs, All products have no tendency towards racemization or enantiomeric interconversion. TBTU has been broadly used as an effective reagent for the synthesis of varied classes of compounds [
 <xref rid="B139-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>] however, our group reported for the first time the use of this coupled reagent to synthetize CDXs [
 <xref rid="B137-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. All coupling reactions were carried out at room temperature, showing short reactions times (ranging from 20 min to 6 h) and excellent yields (ranging from 92% to 99%) [
 <xref rid="B135-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>,
 <xref rid="B136-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>,
 <xref rid="B137-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. The synthetic methodology proved to be very efficient, with broad-scope applicability, and simple operationally. Moreover, it was found that the synthesis of the CDXs was easily scaled-up to obtain available quantities for biological and pharmacological assays as well as other applications [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].
</p>
