<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pbio.3000863.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3000863.g007</object-id>
 <label>Fig 7</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Maximising the probability to detect a pathogen is achieved not by selecting the highest-risk patches, but by spreading surveillance across all clusters of risk.</title>
  <p>For ease of communication, we consider patch status as a dichotomous variable (which can be infected, shown in red, or uninfected, shown in green), rather than considering dynamic trends over time. We wish to sample the 2 patches that maximise the probability of detecting infection over all realisations (selected patches are shown with a blue dashed outline). The 2 ‘strategy’ diagrams on the top each show 3 possible realisations of patch infection status, with the status of the upper 2 host patches correlated due to their proximity. We consider 2 selection strategies: one in which patches are selected based on their mean risk (Strategy 1) and one in which only one high-risk patch is selected and the remaining resources placed in the low risk patch (Strategy 2). If our detection method is perfect, we demonstrate that Strategy 2 outperforms Strategy 1 (being able to detect infection in each of the 3 realisations). The plot on the bottom shows how this is affected by the ability to detect infection in the patch (that is, the diagnostic sensitivity), with the detection probability under Strategy 1 shown in orange and that under Strategy 2 shown in red, for all sensitivity estimates between 0 and 1. In this particular example, the mean probability to detect under Strategy 1 is calculated as 2 * (1 − (1 − sensitivity)
   <sup>2</sup>)/3, whereas for Strategy 2 it is equal to the sensitivity. When the sensitivity is low, selection of a single high-risk patch is insufficient to reliably detect infection, and since infection is more common in the uppermost sites, the optimal strategy is therefore to place all the resources amongst these sites (that is, Strategy 1). However, this strategy will never detect the infection in Realisation 3. This limitation becomes more apparent as the diagnostic sensitivity is increased, and beyond a sensitivity of 0.5, Strategy 2 outperforms Strategy 1, with the difference in performance increasing as the sensitivity is increased.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pbio.3000863.g007" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
