<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Noticeably, 
 <italic>LIS-like</italic> shared a high sequence identity (&gt;99%) with some of the identified linalool synthases in the Lauraceae family. The conserved DDxxD and NSE/DTE motifs for Mg
 <sup>2+</sup> or Mn
 <sup>2+</sup> ion binding as well as the predicted D562 active site cleft were all properly distributed in the LIS-like protein (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS4">Supplementary Figure S4</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS7">Supplementary Table S7</xref>). However, caution should be used when assigning protein functions to terpenoid synthase genes predicted based on sequence similarities as it has been reported that point mutations alone were sufficient to significantly change the kinetic activity of a linalool synthase gene in 
 <italic>Cinnamomum osmophloeum</italic> (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2014</xref>). Additionally, alternative splicing has been shown to alter linalool biosynthesis, as reported in 
 <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2018</xref>). Higher levels of monoterpene production could potentially lower production of other terpenes and isoprenoid derivatives due to the competition for common precursors. Indeed, four unigenes in the “carotenoid biosynthesis pathway” and two unigenes in the “steroid biosynthesis pathway” were down-regulated in the comparison (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS6">Supplementary Table S6</xref>). Similar examples can be seen in tobacco plants producing monoterpene where lower levels of β-caryophyllene were detected in the flowers of these plants (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Lücker et al., 2004</xref>). Additionally, both transgenic tomato and 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants producing a phytoene synthase and the strawberry linalool/nerolidol synthase separately had significant growth retardation due to the severe inhibition of gibberellin biosynthesis (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Fray et al., 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Aharoni et al., 2004</xref>).
</p>
