<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The material morphology was studied by scanning electronic microscopy (SEM) using a LEO (Carl Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany) GEMINI-1530 microscope. Textural characterization was carried out by N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> adsorption at −196 °C using Quadrasorb SI equipment (Quantachrome instruments, Boynton beach, FL, USA). Prior, the carbon samples were degassed overnight at 100 °C. The Brunauer–Emmett–Teller (BET) equation was applied to the N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-adsorption isotherms to determine the surface area (S
 <sub class="sub">BET</sub>). The Dubinin–Radushkevich equation was used to determine the micropore volume (V
 <sub class="sub">mic</sub>) and the mean micropore width (L
 <sub class="sub">mic</sub>). Furthermore, the Barrette-Joynere-Halenda (BJH) method was used to calculate the mesopore volume (V
 <sub class="sub">meso</sub>) and the mean mesopore width (L
 <sub class="sub">meso</sub>). The total pore volume (V
 <sub class="sub">0.95</sub>) was considered to be the volume of N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> adsorbed at P/P
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> = 0.95 [
 <xref rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00500" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Mercury porosimetry was carried out using Micromeritics (Norcross, GA, USA) AutoPore IV 9510 equipment up to a pressure of 60,000 psi to obtain the mesopore volume V
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (dpore 6 to 50 nm), macropore volume V
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> (dpore 50 to 10,000 nm) and mean macropore width (L
 <sub class="sub">macro</sub>). Pore size distributions (PSD) were obtained by coupling the BJH and mercury porosimetry results. The material chemical characterization was analyzed by X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS), and information about the material acidity was obtained by measuring the pH
 <sub class="sub">PZC</sub>, according to the methodology described by Perez et al. [
 <xref rid="B26-nanomaterials-09-00500" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. 
</p>
