<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The strongest effects of the warming treatment were seen for the total number of vegetative growing days, with 12.1 fewer days of vegetative growth with warming in the CV4 experiment, 9.2 fewer days in the CV2 experiment, and 6.3 fewer days in the M2 experiment. By advancing the timing of the later phenological stages (flowering and senescence) without a corresponding shift in the timing of germination, the vegetative growing season of 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> was effectively shortened under warmer conditions. Here too the effects of warming scaled with the magnitude of the temperature treatment, with larger effects in the +4°C treatments compared with plant responses in the +2 °C treatment (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The trends of shorter vegetative growing seasons under warmer conditions were also seen in our soil microclimate analysis across years, with significant negative relationships between mean annual soil temperature and growing season length in all experiments (
 <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Although 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> can cope and persist with increased temperatures, a shorter growing season in warmer environments may be evidence of increased stress in a warmer world, which could reduce 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> success relative to ambient conditions. For example, in a Great Basin Desert study, shorter vegetative growing seasons led to decreased seed production (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Mack and Pyke, 1983</xref>). Additionally, in a global meta-analysis, herbaceous species that flowered earlier were shown to exhibit shorter heights, decreased seed sizes, shallower roots, and smaller less dense leaves, showing that earlier phenology is tied with metrics that determine a plant’s success (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">Wolkovich and Cleland, 2014</xref>). Future research elucidating the interactive controls of phenology, growing season length, plant fitness, and seed production, as well as explorations of competitive interactions between 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> and native plants under altered climate, would improve predictions of climate change’s effect on this common invasive grass. In light of 
 <italic>B. tectorum’s</italic> large negative effects on invaded ecosystems (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">Young et al., 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Melgoza and Nowak, 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Anderson and Inouye, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Humphrey and Schupp, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Svejcar and Sheley, 2001</xref>) and of the substantial resources used attempting to control the invasive plant, an improved understanding of how and where 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> will be affected by climate change would be of great value.
</p>
