<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Contrary to the strong effects of warming, the altered precipitation treatments in our experiments did not significantly affect any of 
 <italic>B. tectorum’s</italic> phenological stages in the years the experimental watering occurred (2009–2012) or in the years following. Additionally, in the microclimate analysis, mean annual 10 cm soil moisture was only significantly related to one phenophase in one experiment (senescence in CV4; 
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Determining how precipitation affects phenology is difficult, in part due to the strong interactions between temperature and soil moisture (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Cleland et al., 2007</xref>). However, greenhouse experiments have shown no effect of watering amount on phenological differences for multiple source populations of 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic>, except for a delay in senescence (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">Rice et al., 1992</xref>). Conversely, the timing of water application has been shown to have strong effects on 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> phenology, with winter moisture being particularly important (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Prevéy and Seastedt, 2014</xref>). With this in mind, the lack of altered precipitation treatment effects in our study may have been due to the fact that the treatment was designed to ask questions about the monsoon and thus water was applied in summer months, which are effectively outside the 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> growing season. Additionally, altered precipitation treatments occurred only in two of the years used for this analysis and therefore the analysis is better suited to examine legacy altered precipitation effects, and no legacy effects were seen. It is also possible that, although water is clearly a dominant driver of numerous ecological patterns in water-limited drylands, temperature may exert larger controls over 
 <italic>B. tectorum’s</italic> phenology. Invasive plant phenology may be more strongly tied to temperature in systems where precipitation is variable, sporadic, and difficult to predict (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Marushia et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">Winkler et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
