<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In exploring drivers of 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> phenological plasticity across years, we found soil temperature to be significantly associated with the timing of germination, flowering, and senescence, and with the length of the vegetative growing season. Mean annual soil temperature was significantly related to the timing of all phenophases except germination in M2. In contrast, mean annual soil moisture was only significantly linked to senescence timing in CV4 (
 <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Additionally, the marginal r
 <sup>2</sup> values showed that mean annual soil moisture and temperature do not explain a large portion of the variation in timing of all phenophases, suggesting additional controls. Here it is important to note that by estimating soil temperature and moisture at the annual scale, we are almost certainly missing cues and events that play an important role in promoting phenological advance. This is particularly important in the context of seasonal rain events that would not be captured well by an annual average. For instance, multiple studies have shown that the timing of germination is tied with large precipitation events, and that late season precipitation can delay senescence (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">Sakai et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">Winkler et al., 2018</xref>). Soil moisture is likely a component driving phenological responses in our experiments, but this relationship was difficult to detect, in part because for most of the year the soils in these dryland experiments were dry. However, while the experimental warming effects on soil moisture did not lead to significant deviations from ambient soil (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>), there is the likelihood that warming-induced soil drying could contribute to the warming effects on 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> phenology and previous research at the CV site showed that warming dried soils at 5 cm depths in both the CV4 and CV2 experiments during 2010 and 2011 (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Wertin et al., 2015</xref>). Nevertheless, more work elucidating climate controls on and predictions for finer-scale patterns of 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> phenology would improve forecasts of how future temperature and precipitation patterns will alter 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> phenology.
</p>
