<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We also observed differences across the two sites in the responses of 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> phenology to experimental warming and annual microclimate variation. When comparing the +2 °C warming effects in the CV2 experiment with the +2 °C warming effects in the M2 experiment, we found that the flowering advances with warming were nearly 1.5 times higher in the CV2 experiment, while advances in senescence were five times greater in the M2 experiment (5 day warming treatment-induced advance in M2 vs. a 1 day advance in CV2). Similarly, senescence in the M2 experiment was more sensitive to natural inter-annual temperature fluctuations than senescence in the CV2 experiment: a 1°C increase was related to a 3.5 day advance in M2 and only a 1.28 and 0.75 day advance in CV4 and CV2, respectively (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). This suggests different sites will vary in not only the magnitude of their 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> phenology response to warming, but also in the degree to which specific aspects of phenology are affected (i.e., warming had a larger effect on flowering phenology in CV2 than M2, but a smaller effect on senescence). Soil texture may help explain the between-site variation in the controls of soil moisture and temperature. The limited water-holding capacity of coarse, sandy soils, such as those found at the M2 site, often drive higher variability in soil moisture and may lead to greater variability in soil temperature between rain events (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">Santos et al., 2019</xref>). It has been suggested that 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> abundance and cover are higher in finer-textured soils compared to more coarse, sandy soils (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Belnap et al., 2016</xref>) and the increased variation of soil moisture in sandy soils may help explain this preference. A better understanding of how 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> phenology responds to changing temperatures across multiple sites and texture gradients is necessary for predicting the future success of the invasive plant.
</p>
