<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although our data point to a shortened 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> growing season with both 2 and 4°C increases in temperature, the large phenological flexibility we observed suggest warmer conditions could also afford 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> a competitive advantage over the perennial plants it lives amongst if those perennial plants are not able to respond to changing climate as quickly. We did not analyze phenological responses to warming of co-occurring species here, however, previous research in these experiments has shown a dominant native perennial species has experienced dramatic declines in cover in response to warming, potentially enabling 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> to take advantage of this newly opened space and further invade the site (
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">Winkler et al., 2019</xref>). Due to the large effect of 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> on native perennials, any climate change effects on the invasive grass could, in turn, affect the success of native plants (
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">Willis et al., 2010</xref>). For example, 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> winter growth has been shown to inhibit germination success of co-located native perennials (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Harris, 1977</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Aguirre and Johnson, 1991</xref>). 
 <italic>Bromus tectorum’s</italic> roots also develop rapidly after fall germination, and as temperatures cool in the winter the plant becomes semi-dormant (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Klemmedson and Smith, 1964</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Aguirre and Johnson, 1991</xref>). If increased warming is sufficient to cancel dormancy effects of colder winter temperatures, warming could allow 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> to stay metabolically active, and continue root growth, permitting increased exploitation of resources before natives are active (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Ashbacher and Cleland, 2015</xref>). Although we did not find advances in the timing of fall germination with experimental warming, the substantial advance of flowering suggests that 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> shifted its life stages earlier in response to increased temperatures. Such a shift would be expected to include the uptake of limited soil resources, and thus these changes could affect plant competition. In all, the large flexibility we observed in 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic> with warming and across years suggests a strong potential to track climate in way that may support the plant’s success even in the face of climate change.
</p>
