<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to the solvent, the temperature and ultrasound power may strongly affect the efficiency of UAE. High temperature and ultrasound power levels may improve the extraction process by reducing the viscosity of the solvent and by increasing the kinetic energy of the molecules in the solution. However, they may also lead to degradation of sensitive phytochemicals, including phenolic compounds [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-05142" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Similarly, long extraction times may increase the amount of the extracted target compounds. However, long extraction times can also increase the chances of degradation of sensitive molecules. In this work, high temperature positively affected extraction. This is possibly related to the reduction of the glycerol viscosity and increase of the kinetic energy of the solvent molecules. Such an effect was observed in previous UAE glycerolic extractions of phenolics from 
 <italic>G. glabra</italic> [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-05142" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The extraction using the highest glycerol concentration seemed to be a relatively slow process. This was evidenced by the observation that the duration of the extraction exerted a positive influence on the extraction efficiency, as well as by the positive influence of the interaction of glycerol content and time. Other researchers also reported similar findings. For example, previous kinetic studies of eggplant peel extractions suggested that diffusion of phenolics in water–glycerol mixtures was slower compared with that attained with water–ethanol, but both systems had the ability to recover essentially the same levels of total polyphenols [
 <xref rid="B39-molecules-25-05142" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Similar results were presented in a study of the glycerolic UAE of caffeic acid derivatives from spent filter coffee [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-25-05142" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. It was noted in this work that the interaction of the glycerol concentration, temperature, and higher ultrasonication power exerted a negative effect on the phenolic acid extraction. This effect may be due to the generation of hydroxyl radicals, whose production is initiated by ultrasonication, especially at high temperatures [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-25-05142" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], and their subsequent reaction with caffeic acid derivatives [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-25-05142" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].
</p>
