<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In treating the formation of ENSDs as an open or semi-open system, three fluxes are considered to operate in a quasi-steady state: the input of sulfate from dissolution is matched by the precipitation of native sulfur and the removal of residual sulfate by transport out of the system, by precipitation as a sulfate mineral, or by capture as CAS. Similarly, there must be a match between the isotope composition of sulfur that enters the system as sulfate and the sulfur that leaves the system and precipitated native sulfur, whereby the latter two are offset by the sulfur isotope fractionation (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" class="xref">6</xref>). If most of the sulfate that enters the system also leaves, the δ
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S value of the residual sulfate matches the δ
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S value of original sulfate and the δ
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S value of native sulfur is strongly offset to low values. If essentially all sulfate that enters the system is converted to native sulfur, the δ
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S value of native sulfur matches the δ
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S value of original sulfate, and the δ
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S value of the residual sulfate is strongly offset to isotopically heavy values. If half of the sulfate entering the system is converted to native sulfur, native sulfur and residual sulfate will have the same absolute isotopic offset from residual sulfate. It is important to note that in such an open system, the isotopic offset between native sulfur and residual sulfur is approximately equal to the sulfur isotope fractionation by sulfate-reducing organisms, which should have a maximum of approximately 75‰ (e.g., 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brunner and Bernasconi, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sim et al., 2011a</xref>). In the closed, Rayleigh-type system the difference could be much larger because residual sulfate becomes exponentially enriched in 
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S, while accumulated sulfide and native sulfur approach the δ
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S value of original sulfate. Remarkably, for the available data sets, the spread between residual sulfate and native sulfur remains within the 75‰ range (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" class="xref">5</xref>). In this view, it becomes evident that in the majority of the studied native sulfur deposits, sulfate conversion to native sulfur exceeded the loss of sulfate, which implies that fluid transport in and out of the system during sulfide generation must have been restricted. In cases where the δ
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S value of native sulfur approaches the value of original sulfate, external fluid input must have been almost cut off. Such a scenario is not compatible with concomitant supply of oxygenated water.
</p>
