<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It can be argued that celestine and barite only form during late stage sulfate reduction in an essentially closed system when enough barium and strontium have built up but sulfate has not been consumed to a degree where precipitation can no longer occur. Then their δ
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S values would only record a specific segment of the isotope trends, which could be taken as an argument why the difference between the residual sulfate and native sulfur remains limited to the 75‰ range. For this reason, analysis of the δ
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S values of CAS may be more appropriate, because authigenic carbonates are expected to keep precipitating as long as carbonate production through hydrocarbon oxidation proceeds. A compilation of values from ENSDs from the United States Gulf coast, Poland, and Sicily, Italy shows that the sulfur isotope offset between native sulfur and CAS, barite, and celestine is well within the 75‰ range (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" class="xref">5</xref>). For example, at Damon Mound, the highest δ
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S value of CAS is 55.8‰, and the lowest δ
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S of native sulfur is −1.5‰, which results in an offset of 57.3‰ (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" class="xref">5</xref> and Table 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). Using this offset as our sulfur isotope fractionation value, applying it to the highest measured δ
 <sup class="sup">34</sup>S value of native sulfur of 4.9‰, and assuming a value of 16‰ for gypsum from Louann Salt formation that is the likely sulfate source (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Feely and Kulp, 1957</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Claypool et al., 1980</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kyle and Agee, 1988</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Prikryl et al., 1988</xref>), we find that more than 80% of the sulfate was converted to native sulfur and less than 20% of residual sulfate was removed, either into a solid phase or as dissolved compound. Thus, at Damon Mound fluid flow must, at least intermittently, have been sluggish. Accumulation of sulfide, due to the lack of O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> supply would have been a likely consequence.
</p>
