<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The base is usually made of refined wheat flour, and 
 <italic class="italic">zaatar</italic> is composed of ground oregano leaves, sesame seeds, sumac spices, and salt, mixed in the following percentages, respectively: 35.86%, 43.04%, 17.93%, and 3.15%. In the present study, three types of 
 <italic class="italic">mankoushe</italic> were made in which the base was modified and the topping was maintained: regular 
 <italic class="italic">mankoushe</italic> with 100% refined wheat flour, as a control; “chickpea-30” 
 <italic class="italic">mankoushe</italic>, containing dough made up of a mixture of refined wheat/processed chickpea flour (70/30); and “chickpea-50” 
 <italic class="italic">mankoushe</italic>, in which the dough was made up with a mixture of refined wheat/processed chickpea flour (50/50). Afterward and upon use, sunflower oil was added to the topping mixture based on the following percentages: 31.70% topping mixture and 68.30% oil. As for the dough, the three types were prepared under controlled conditions, according to the formulation given in 
 <xref rid="foods-08-00151-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>. Dry ingredients and water were first mixed at speed 1 (60 rpm) for 1 min in an industrial electrical mixer (KitchenAid KSM75WH Classic Plus Series); then 50 g of oil was added, and mixing proceeded at speed 2 (104 rpm) for 3 min. Finally, the rest of the oil (30 g) was added, and the dough was mixed until optimal development. Doughs were kept in the fermentation cabinet (Bread fermentation oven proofer, HR-15, Huaer, Guangdong, China) at a temperature of 40 °C for 30 min. Thereafter, doughs were flattened via a mini dough sheeter machine (BDQ-520C, Bossda, Guangzhou, China), portioned (15 g), panned, topped with the already prepared mixture (oil and herbs topping mixture), and left for final proofing for 10 min. The three types of 
 <italic class="italic">mankoushe</italic> were baked in an electric oven (INEO BK-SCO10-E, INEO Kitchen Equipment Co., LTD, Guangzhou, China) for 6 min at 300 °C. Food samples were prepared just before the sensory test.
</p>
