<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Kalashnikova et al. have demonstrated highly stable emulsions with unmodified CNC isolated from cotton, green algae, and bacterial cellulose (
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>
 </xref>a,b).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45" class="xref">45</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref63" class="xref">63</xref>
 </sup> The possibility of producing functional emulsions with modified CNC was also demonstrated.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref73" class="xref">73</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref84" class="xref">84</xref>
 </sup> We prepared thermoresponsive O/W emulsions with CNC grafted with 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>-isopropylacrylamide (NIPAM), namely, CNC-
 <italic class="italic">graft</italic>-poly(NIPAM).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref71" class="xref">71</xref>
 </sup> The CNC-
 <italic class="italic">graft</italic>-poly(NIPAM) aligned and layered at the oil/water interface, which contributed to the stability during a four-month observation time. When the emulsions were heated above the lower critical solution temperature of poly(NIPAM), the emulsions broke down. The demonstrated production of emulsions with controllable stability using naturally abundant resources is potentially useful for biomedical and cosmetic applications. Low et al. prepared dual responsive (pH and magnetic) emulsions using Fe
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>–CNC composites for stabilization.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref85" class="xref">85</xref>
 </sup> The fabricated emulsions were proposed for application as smart nanotherapeutic carriers. Ojala et al. studied the stabilization of marine diesel O/W emulsions with bifunctionalized CNC for application as oil-spill response agents.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref86" class="xref">86</xref>
 </sup> Apart from chemical modification of CNC, Pickering emulsions have also been produced via synergistic stabilization by CNC and water-soluble polymers (e.g., hydroxyethyl cellulose (HEC) and methyl cellulose (MC)). By adding MC to CNC-HEC stabilized emulsions, followed by heating above 70 °C, viscoelastic emulsion gels were achieved (
 <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7</xref>
 </xref>a).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref87" class="xref">87</xref>
 </sup> The emulsion gels were stable within multiple cycles of heating–cooling. Kedzior et al. exploited a synergistic effect between CNC and surfactants for miniemulsion polymerization (
 <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7</xref>
 </xref>b).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref88" class="xref">88</xref>
 </sup> The resulting latexes showed tunable properties (morphology, surface charge, and molecular weight), which bear potential applications for coatings, adhesives, and household products. Tasset et al. used CNC-stabilized O/W emulsions for the preparation of highly porous foams.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref89" class="xref">89</xref>
 </sup> The preparation of composite foams was demonstrated by the addition of chitosan to the corresponding emulsions.
</p>
