<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig2" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Fig. 2</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Illustration of single-photon and two-photon fluorescence, Rayleigh and Raman scattering and CARS. Fluorescence (
   <bold class="bold">a</bold> and 
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>): Absorption of light at a frequency ω
   <sub class="sub">i</sub> excites the molecule to a higher electronic energy level. The molecule can revert to the electronic ground state by non-radiative transitions and the emission of fluorescence at frequency ω
   <sub class="sub">f</sub>, which is lower than ω
   <sub class="sub">i</sub> (red-shifted). In two-photon fluorescence (
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>) the molecule is simultaneously excited by two photons of approximately half the energy necessary for one-photon excitation (ω
   <sub class="sub">i</sub>/2). The resulting two-photon fluorescence signal is blue-shifted compared to the incident light. Light scattering (
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>): Light at a frequency ω
   <sub class="sub">i</sub> excites a molecule to a virtual state. The molecule can revert to the ground state by elastic light scattering (Rayleigh scattering) or inelastic scattering with an energy loss at frequency ω
   <sub class="sub">s</sub> (Stokes Raman scattering) or energy gain at frequency ω
   <sub class="sub">as</sub> (anti-Stokes Raman scattering). CARS (
   <bold class="bold">d</bold>): The CARS process is driven by three photons from at least two different laser sources. A pump beam at frequency ω
   <sub class="sub">p</sub> excites a molecule from the ground state to a virtual state, which subsequently is depopulated by a Stokes beam at frequency ω
   <sub class="sub">s</sub>. The last photon from the probe beam ω
   <sub class="sub">pr</sub> excites the molecule to a higher virtual state. In our setup the pump and probe photon are provided by the same laser at ω
   <sub class="sub">p</sub>. The resulting signal at frequency ω
   <sub class="sub">as</sub> is blue-shifted compared to the incident laser light and – if the conditions are met – coherently amplified [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>]
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="12870_2018_1481_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
