<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Farnesyl pyrophosphate synthase (FPPS) condenses one molecule of DMAPP and one molecule of IPP to form GPP, then condenses GPP with one molecule of IPP to form FPP in 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). It is reported that FPPS of 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> is encoded by the gene 
 <italic>ERG20</italic>, which is responsible for the biosynthesis of GPP and FPP. GPP is usually closely bound to the catalytic pocket of FPPS and results in the low content of free GPP (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Dai et al., 2013</xref>). Therefore, the precursor GPP for monoterpenoid synthesis was insufficient, which greatly restricted the biosynthesis of monoterpenoids. In addition, 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> also lacks specific and efficient GPP synthase (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Herrero et al., 2008</xref>). Sequence alignment of FPPS from different organisms showed that there were two ASP rich sequences in the conserved region of this enzyme. The first ASP rich sequence is DDXXD or DDXXXXD, which could bind DMAPP, GPP, and FPP in catalytic reaction. The second ASP rich sequence is DDXXD, which is mainly responsible for binding IPP. Previous studies showed that site directed mutagenesis in the conservative region of FPPS can cause GPP released from the binding site of FPPS, which increased the intracellular free GPP content (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>). By mutating the catalytic residue K197 of yeast farnesyl diphosphate synthase erg20p and expressing heterologous geraniol synthetase gene in engineered 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, the yield of geraniol increased significantly, suggesting that the regulation of 
 <italic>ERG20</italic> gene can increase the GPP amount and balance GPP and FPP ratio for geraniol production (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Fischer et al., 2011</xref>). Sabinene is seen as a potential component for the next generation of aircraft fuels (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Rude and Schirmer, 2009</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Ignea et al. (2014)</xref> identified that erg20p is an rate-limiting enzyme for monoterpene production, and integrating erg20p with a geranyl diphosphate synthase increased sabinene titer (17.5 mg/L). Compared with the canonical GPP-based monoterpenoid biosynthetic pathway, a synthetic orthogonal monoterpenoid pathway using neryl diphosphate as substrate was designed, and further dynamic regulation of some engineered enzymes in the synthetic monoterpenoid improved monoterpenoid production by seven-fold (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Ignea et al., 2019</xref>).
</p>
