<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">When identifying an appropriate reinforcing agent, silica-based materials offer some benefits over the other types of materials. To begin, there are a wide range of commercially available products, which include silsesquioxanes and various sized particles, that can be used as received. Additionally, silica-based materials can be readily synthesized in-house, using slightly modified solution-gelation (sol-gel) conditions from inexpensive, commercially-available materials. This is a very straightforward synthetic route when compared to those used for other stabilizing agents, which generally require harsh reaction conditions, tedious purifications, and complex processing techniques [
 <xref rid="B26-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Furthermore, the sol-gel method offers a simple platform for introducing additional functionalities, which is key for tailoring material properties. Silica-based materials are also chemically stable, thermally robust, and compatible with a variety of fluorinated-organic based materials and polymers [
 <xref rid="B29-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. They can also be physically blended or covalently attached to a fluorinated component in order to obtain specialty composites. Within the arena of silica-based reinforcing agents, silica nanometer-sized particles (SiNPs) are ideal candidates, as not only do they exhibit the aforementioned attributes, but there is also a profound effect on the properties of the particles, due to their nanometer size range. With a large surface area-to-volume ratio, and as the size of the particles decrease, more atoms reside at the surface, and surface properties tend to dominate. These properties can then be imparted to the material they are incorporated into. Furthermore, when nanometer sized fillers are utilized, they are known to yield materials and composites with micro- and nanotextured surfaces. Although explained in more detail in the subsequent sections, the production of nanotextured surfaces give rise to enhanced surface roughness and are an essential property for many of the specialized applications for F-SiNPs. Silica nanometer-sized particles have also been found to disperse better than other reinforcing agents [
 <xref rid="B30-nanomaterials-09-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. The particles can be purchased or synthesized with discrete and uniform dimensions, which is important for maintaining consistency throughout a functional material. Furthermore, with the ease in which covalent attachment can be achieved via sol-gel techniques, the ability to obtain F-SiNPs is virtually unmatched.
</p>
