<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7" class="p">Typically, interfaces lead to extensive protein aggregation in combination with a mechanical stress, which deforms, eliminates, or physically perturbs the interfacial protein film. The IV bag agitation study referenced above demonstrated that static storage in the IV bag, even with the air headspace present, did not result in aggregation (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>). The formation of protein aggregates during agitation of siliconized prefilled syringes stopped once the agitation halted (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>). Similarly for a mAb, halting agitation of a drug product vial also stopped aggregation (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>). A fundamental study of mAb aggregation at air–liquid interfaces determined that interfacial shear stress caused substantially more protein particulate formation compared to bulk shear stress. This study also indicated that dilatational compression of antibody films that have been exposed to air for longer, and are therefore more denatured, resulted in shedding of protein particulates into the bulk solution (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>). Similarly, repeated lateral compression and expansion of mAb adsorbed to an air–liquid interface resulted in comparable protein aggregation compared to an agitation study (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>). While these previous two studies demonstrated compression of interfacial protein films causes protein particulates, other studies showed a similar result for protein films at air–liquid (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>) and oil–liquid (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>) interfaces only when the films were repeatedly perturbed with a needle during vial rotation. The literature reports referenced here, along with many others, demonstrate that protein therapeutics can aggregate when exposed to interfaces, particularly in combination with mechanical stresses that deform or perturb the interfacial protein layer.
</p>
