<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) signaling pathway has been proposed as wound-induced signaling mechanism for the agarwood formation in 
 <italic class="italic">A. sinensis</italic>, which phosphorylates downstream transcription factors (TFs) like MYB or WRKY that eventually lead to the expression of sesquiterpene synthase genes (
 <italic class="italic">ASS</italic>s) (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Xu et al., 2013</xref>). The MAPK signaling cascade consists of three sequentially activated components [MAPK kinase kinases (MAPKKKs), MAPK kinases (MAPKKs), and MAPKs], which is highly conserved signaling mechanism in eukaryotes in mediating extracellular signals to downstream responsive genes (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sinha et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Xu C. et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Xu et al. (2013)</xref> has reported that a total of 41 unigenes from the transcriptome analysis of wounded 
 <italic class="italic">A. sinensis</italic> are annotated as being related to MAPK signaling pathway and 25 to calcium signaling pathways which may play roles in wound-induced agarwood formation. In plants, calcium ions (Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup>) are important intracellular secondary messenger molecules to regulate many signal transduction pathways reacting to the external stimuli (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tuteja and Mahajan, 2007</xref>). Earlier studies in other plants have shown that TFs are crucial regulators in stress-responsive signaling pathways to transmit signals to different cellular centers to activate plant adaptation/defense mechanisms against adverse environments, including TFs like bZIP, ERF, EIN3, MYB, MYC, and WRKY (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ambawat et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Phukan et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schmiesing et al., 2016</xref>). Overexpression of AaWRKY1 in 
 <italic class="italic">Artemisia annua</italic> was found to have positively regulated the expression of amorpha-4,11-diene synthase gene (
 <italic class="italic">ADS</italic>) and significantly increased the production of artemisinin (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ma et al., 2009</xref>). The expression of cotton TF GaWRKY was also shown to upregulate the sesquiterpene synthase genes for the biosynthesis of (+)-δ-cadinene and gossypol sesquiterpene (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Xu et al., 2004</xref>).
</p>
