<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24" class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Nepeta</italic> species producing nepetalactones are found throughout in many regions and can be cultivated in additional areas where their essential oil can be distilled to repel mosquitoes that inhabit the same regions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>. The processing of raw plants to yield essential oils is accomplished using a variety of extraction or distillation technologies including solvent, supercritical CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> or water and steam respectively. In rural communities, the same processing technologies now in commercial use that produce a wide range of essential oils can be used to procure the aromatic volatile oils from 
 <italic class="italic">N. cataria</italic> in rural regions. These communities can be protected from disease vectoring insects from the plantings of 
 <italic class="italic">Nepeta sp</italic>. that contain high amounts nepetalactones in their already established essential oil crop fields. While many catnip and catmint plants produce essential oils and of these many have nepetalactones as a component in their essential oil, overall functional agricultural yields of the total essential oil and/or the concentration of the nepetalactones is low, leading to a commercialization bottleneck. These results are exciting because these two newly developed genetic varieties produce high yields of total essential oil, and of the oil, each are rich in the bioactive nepetalactones overcoming two of the major constraints in developing a new bioactive ingredient, the cost and availability of the raw material. Individuals in rural communities can overcome the costs of purchasing 
 <italic class="italic">N. cataria</italic> essential oil by cultivating catnips that are rich in essential oil and nepetalactones and processing the essential oil themselves for protection. In this case, both CR9 and CR3 strains created offer promise to protecting individuals against 
 <italic class="italic">A. aegypti</italic> mosquitoes.
</p>
