<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par62" class="p">Total RNA was extracted from 33 finely ground flower samples using a HiPure Plant RNA Mini Kit (Magen) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The DNA was digested by DNaseI (Magen). RNA purity, concentration and integrity were determined using Nanodrop 1000 spectrophotometer, Qubit Flurometer and Agilent Bioanalyzer. Only the RNA samples with 260/280 ratio between 1.8 to 2.1, 260/230 ratio between 2.0 to 2.5 and RIN (RNA integrity number) more than 8.0, were used for sequencing. Qualified RNA was enriched with oligo (dT)-rich magnetic beads and then broken into short fragments in Fragmentation Buffer. 1st strand cDNA synthesis was performed using random hexamers primer and M-MuLV Reverse Transcriptase (RNase H). 2nd strand cDNA was synthesized by adding reaction buffer, dNTPs, RNase H and DNA polymerase I. Next, the resulting cDNAs were subjected to end-repair, insert ‘A’ base and subsequently ligate with Illumina paired end solexa adaptor. Adaptor-ligated fragments were purified by AMPure XP beads to select a size range of templates for downstream enrichment. Finally, PCR was performed to enrich and amplify the cDNA template. In total of 33 libraries including three biological replicates for each sample were constructed and then sequenced on Illumina HiSeq™ 2000 platform at Novogene Biotechnology Corporation (Beijing, China). We obtained a total of 1737,289,686 (1737 million) clean reads and at least 6.25 Gb clean data per library was generated after filtering and removing the adapter sequences from the raw data (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM14" ref-type="media" class="xref">14</xref>: Table S3). The value of Q20, Q30 and GC content was higher than 96.06, 91.54 and 46.86%, respectively. When we mapped the reads back to the assembled unigenes, the mapping rate ranged from 77.40 to 80.03% of each library (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM14" ref-type="media" class="xref">14</xref>: Table S3). RNA sequencing raw sequence data of 33 lavender flower samples generated from the present study can be found in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Short Read Archive database with accession number SRP139393.
</p>
