<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="st1">
  <title>Background:</title>
  <p>This study investigates the scolicidal effects of 
   <italic>Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic> essential oil against the protoscoleces of hydatid cysts and its toxicity in the mice model.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st2">
  <title>Materials and Methods:</title>
  <p>Gas chromatography/mass spectroscopy analyses were used to identify the constituents of essential oil. Protoscoleces were treated with different concentrations of the essential oil (6.25–100 µL/mL) in each test tube for 5–30 min. The viability of protoscoleces was confirmed using eosin exclusion test (0.1% eosin staining). Forty-eight male NMRI mice were also used to determine the toxicity of 
   <italic>C. zeylanicum</italic> essential oil (0.5–4 mL/kg).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st3">
  <title>Results:</title>
  <p>The main components were found to be cinnamaldehyde (91.8%), ρ metoxicinamate (1.57%), and α pinene (1.25%). Findings indicate that 
   <italic>C. zeylanicum</italic> essential oil with the concentrations of 100 and 50 µL/mL killed 100% of protoscoleces after 5 min of exposure. Also, the lower concentrations of 
   <italic>C. zeylanicum</italic> essential oil motivated a late protoscolicidal effect. The LD
   <sub>50</sub> value of intraperitoneal injection of 
   <italic>C. zeylanicum</italic> essential oil was 2.07 mL/kg body weight after 48 h, and the maximum nonfatal dose was 1.52 mL/kg body weight. The results also showed that there was no significant toxicity following oral administration of 
   <italic>C. zeylanicum</italic> essential oil for 2 weeks.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st4">
  <title>Conclusion:</title>
  <p>The results exhibited the favorable scolicidal activity of 
   <italic>C. zeylanicum</italic>, which could be applied as a natural scolicidal agent in hydatid cyst surgery.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st5">
  <title>SUMMARY</title>
  <p>
   <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
     <p>We evaluated the efficacy of 
      <italic>Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic> essential oil against hydatid cyst protoscoleces
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>The viability of protoscoleces was confirmed using eosin exclusion test (0.1% eosin staining)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>Forty-eight male NMRI mice were also used to determine the toxicity of 
      <italic>C. zeylanicum</italic> essential oil
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>C. zeylanicum with potent scolicidal activity could be applied as a natural scolicidal agent in surgery.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <p>
   <inline-graphic xlink:href="PM-13-652-g001.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Abbreviations used:</bold> GC/MS: Gas chromatography/mass spectrometry analysis; CE: Cystic echinococcosis; LD50: Lethal dose 50%; I.p: Intraperitoneally.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
