<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39">Our investigations reveal that GST and Car E activity in adult stage of 
 <italic>M. domestica</italic> increased on exposure to 
 <italic>O. basilicum</italic> EO and methyl chavicol and linalool. 
 <italic>M. domestica</italic> adults exposed to EO at LD 
 <sub>50</sub> values induced a higher level of GST as compared with control and constituents. Treating with LD
 <sub>50</sub> doses of linalool caused significant increase in Car E levels in adults. This agrees with earlier studies that 
 <italic>C. pipiens</italic> larvae exposed 
 <italic>O. basilicum</italic> EO at LC
 <sub>50</sub> values stimulated GST activity. The increase in degrading enzymes may be due to increase in active compounds in the insect body (Zibaee and Bandani 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">2010</xref>). Previous reports state that plant-derived products having a mixture of compounds that including triterpenoids and phenols inhibit the activity of GST and Car E (Tak et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2017</xref>; Yang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">2018</xref>). An increase in the degrading enzymes Car E and GST on exposure of insects to natural products have been reported earlier (Kumrungsee et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2014</xref>). Larvae of mosquitoes, 
 <italic>C.quinquefasciatus</italic> and 
 <italic>A. stephensi</italic> exposed to 
 <italic>Lantana camera</italic> root and 
 <italic>Anacardium occidentale</italic> exhibited a rise in GST activity. This scenario of rise in enzymes does not limit to insecticide resistance alone, and this could be due to degrading enzymes generated by reactive oxygen species (ROS) (Vontas et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2001</xref>). Induction of detoxifying enzymes due to exposure to EO may be due to synergy caused by the constituents in EO (Miresmailli et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2006</xref>; Isman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2008</xref>; Jiang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2009</xref>; Senthil-Nathan 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2013</xref>). Increase in degrading enzyme levels is clear indication that EO and its constituents possess cidal effect in 
 <italic>M. domestica</italic> and the fall out of which is the possibilities of resistance development, which needs further investigation.
</p>
