<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">An Agilent 6890N gas chromatograph equipped with a 5973N mass spectrometer was used for the determination of BEO chemical composition. A 5% phenylmethylpolysiloxane HP-5MS (30 m × 0.25 mm i.d. × 0.1 μm film thickness, Agilent, Folsom, CA, USA) and a polyethylene glycol DB-WAX (30 m × 0.25 mm i.d. × 0.25 μm film thickness, Agilent) were used as stationary phases. Helium (99.99%) was the mobile phase with a flow rate of 1.4 mL·min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>. The operative conditions (e.g., oven temperature, split ratio, injector and detector temperatures, software for data processing etc.) adopted were the same of those reported by Benelli et al. [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-24-00879" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-24-00879" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>] and Quassinti et al. [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-24-00879" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Two μL of the hexanic solution of essential oil (6 μL of essential oil in 594 μL of solvent) were injected three times and analyzed in full scan (29–400 
 <italic class="italic">m</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">z</italic>) using the electron impact (EI) mode. The peak assignment was made by using three different approaches: (i) correspondence of the RI, calculated using a mix of 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-alkanes (C8–C20 purchased from Supelco, Bellefonte, CA, USA), with respect to those reported in ADAMS [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-24-00879" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>], NIST 17 [
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-24-00879" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] and FFNSC2 [
 <xref rid="B55-molecules-24-00879" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>] libraries for apolar and polar columns; (ii) MS matching with the WILEY275, ADAMS, NIST 17 and FFNSC2 libraries; (iii) co-injection with available analytical standard (see 
 <xref rid="molecules-24-00879-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Relative abundances of peaks were obtained by peak area normalization without using response factors.
</p>
