<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mango peel has a higher polyphenol content than mango pulp at all growth stages of the fruit [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Many reports have been published on the polyphenolic content of the mango peel for various varieties available, and the variance mainly depends on the maturity stage, locality, variety, and climatic conditions in its production region. The polyphenol content in the peel ranges from 55–110 mg/gm dry weight, and higher levels are found in the ripe than in the unripe peel [
 <xref rid="B72-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Two more important phytochemicals, quercetin 3-O-galactoside and mangiferin, are also present in the peel. It was estimated that mango peel has 1.69 g of mangiferin/kg dry weight, and this content is temperature-dependent. At high temperatures, mangiferin concentration decreases as its derivatives content increases [
 <xref rid="B54-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Due to this transformation process, xanthones from the benzophenone derivative form, which is helpful in the formation of xanthone C-glycosides in the mango peel [
 <xref rid="B64-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>] (
 <xref rid="ijerph-18-00741-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). For the Uba cultivar from Brazil, the polyphenol content is 6–8% of dry weight, and the amounts of flavonoids and xanthones in the peel are 4.6 and 7.3 times greater than in the pulp [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Of the six xanthone derivatives identified in mango peel, mangiferin (C2-β-D-glucopyranosyl-1,3,6,7-tetrahydroxyxanthone), a C-glucosyl xanthine, has many pharmacological activities. Mangiferin is a glucosyl xanthone with a characteristic isomeric form (mangiferin + isomangiferin + homo-mangiferin), and was found to be in higher concentrations in mango peel than in pulp and seed [
 <xref rid="B42-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Mangiferin is a predominant bioactive compound in mango tree bark and is found in the fruits, roots, and leaves as well. The amount of mangiferin and its derivatives is higher in the peel than in the pulp (22.15 and 9.68 mg/100 g FW, respectively) and in Pica compared to Tommy Atkins mangoes (4.24 and 3.25 mg/100 g FW, respectively) [
 <xref rid="B53-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Higher concentrations of mangiferin were reported from peels of Uba and Tommy Atkins mangoes (12.4 and 2.9 mg/kg dry weight, respectively), which are cultivated in Brazil [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-18-00741" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. 
</p>
