<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Druglikeness properties of compounds screen-out promising ligands that are likely to be used as drugs based on some identified properties (Dong et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). The properties comprise those considered crucial for both kinetic and dynamic interactions inside the biological system. Essentially, harpagide 5-O-β-D-glucopyranoside displayed a potential druggable character, with the exception of a very few properties (
 <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Molecular weight indicates the mass as well as the size of a ligand and plays a greater role in determining the solubility, absorption and distribution of a given drug candidate (Doak et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Basically, the molecular weight of the new ligands reported in this work appears to fit within the acceptable range of this parameter. Hydrogen bond acceptors and donors in drug structures play an important role in water solubility, membrane transport, distribution, and drug-receptor interactions (Cheng et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Kumar et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Five hydrogen bond donors and ten hydrogen bond acceptors are required for a ligand to possess a satisfactory bioavailability and the optimum number of drug-target interactions via hydrogen bonds (Dong et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). LogP indicates a relative concentration of the solute in octanol and water (octanol-water partition coefficient). It determines the degree of hydrophobicity of a ligand and plays a role in predicting drug absorption via the phospholipid bilayer of the cell membrane (Kumar et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Generally, a more polar compound typically encounters difficulties when passing through phospholipid bilayer of the cell membrane (Yusof &amp; Segall, 
 <xref rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Harpagide 5-O-β-D-glucopyranoside demonstrated approvingly a very good partition coefficient (
 <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). This suggests that it can be efficiently transported across cell membranes, as passive diffusion through a cell membrane is a key element of transcellular absorption (Doak et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Yusof et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0075" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).
</p>
