<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>At molecular level, the viral envelope spike (S) protein of SARS-CoV-2 and angiotensin converting enzyme 2 receptor within the host are central to COVID-19 pathogenesis and response to therapeutic interventions among other biological factors (Tian et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Basically, it has been reported that envelope spike (S) protein is important for coronavirus pathogenesis as it mediates receptor binding and membrane fusion implicated in host tropism and transmission capability (He et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Mostly, the S protein is functionally divided into the S1 domain, responsible for receptor binding, and S2 domain, responsible for cell membrane fusion. Structure analysis suggests that the receptor-binding domain is composed of a core and an external subdomain. Angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) has been reported to act as a cell receptor for the S protein (Kuster et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Therefore, targeting S protein and ACE2 at transcriptomic and proteomic levels could be a novel strategy for treatment and management of COVID-19. The docking simulations revealed that harpagide 5-O-β-D-glucopyranoside binds better with the evidence of hydrogen bonding interactions with amino acid residues around the binding pocket of the host receptor target as well as the nitrogenous base and ribose sugar of the mRNA sequence of initiation and termination sequence of the viral spike protein m RNA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0005 F0006 F0007">Figures 5–7</xref>). Remdesivir in complex with SARS-CoV-2 spike protein displayed stronger molecular interactions when compared with CQ and AM (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure S3</xref>). However, it is comparable with harpagide 5-O-β-D-glucopyranoside. This can be as a result of the four hydrogen bonding interactions with four amino acid residues in the bind pocket of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein compared to three of hydrogen bonding interactions found in harpagide 5-O-β-D-glucopyranoside (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure S2</xref>). Remdesivir have been reported the recently to inhibit novel SARS-COV-2 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, which invariably corroborated our findings (
 <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>) (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The good binding potential of Harpagide 5-O-β-D-glucopyranoside can prevent or impair the recruitment of initiating and termination factors around mRNA sequence, thus affecting the ultimate translation of S protein mRNA. Equally, the strong and robust interactions were visible between the compound and S protein as well as ACE2 receptor (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0006">Figures 6</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0007">7</xref>). Thus, qualifying it as a potential inhibitor of S protein mRNA translation vis-à-vis barriers that affect S protein and ACE2 receptor interactions implicated in COVID-19 pathogenesis (Kuster et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). However, further studies are needed to evaluate the actual efficacy of HG against SARS-COV-2 at 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> levels while targeting spike protein and its receptor at transcriptomic and proteomic levels.
</p>
