<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Knowledge of the factors influencing its EO yield and chemical composition is very important for producers of Damask rose [
 <xref rid="pone.0249363.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0249363.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] Like the other aromatic plants, its EO is affected by genetic and many environmental factors including crop location characteristics [
 <xref rid="pone.0249363.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0249363.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Studies have shown that environmental factors (e.g., annual rainfall, temperature, humidity, light, soil, pruning, provision of nutrients and harvest time) considerably influence Damask rose EO [
 <xref rid="pone.0249363.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0249363.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Soil and irrigation water characteristics are among the most important factors influencing the EOs of plants in a field. Soil characteristics are effective factors in growth and development and quantitative and qualitative yields of plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0249363.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The chemical elements in the rhizosphere (such as contents of mobile phosphorus and mobile potassium) enter into the composition of the enzymes that take part in the biochemical reactions in plants. Therefore, soil chemistry can affect the composition of essential oils (such as linalool, citronellol, geraniol, eugenol, etc) and also the distribution of chemotypes [
 <xref rid="pone.0249363.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Water is also one of the very important environmental factors that affect growth, quality and quantity of the EOs of cultivated medicinal plants. It is not yet clearly known why plants produce EOs; however, EOs are generally the remaining products of the major metabolic processes in plants, especially under stress conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0249363.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0249363.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. In plants that produce EOs (complex mixtures of volatile compounds generally produced in the biosynthetic pathways of terpenoids or phenylpropanoids), interactions with the environment usually lead to changes in the compounds found in the EOs and in their contents [
 <xref rid="pone.0249363.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. These changes may contribute to the evolution of various plant genes that favor adaptation to the environmental conditions at crop sites thus leading to changes in the quantity and quality of the EOs (and hence in their biological activities) [
 <xref rid="pone.0249363.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0249363.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Therefore, evaluation of genotypes collected from cultivation locations having different environmental conditions is an important step in Damask rose breeding programs prior to selection of desirable cultivars for commercial production.
</p>
