<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Egg production and quality are greatly influenced by the physiological status of the hen—age, stress, and immune status [
 <xref rid="B155-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">155</xref>]. Egg weight varies from 50 g to 70 g depending mainly on hen’s age and genetics (See 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec4dot1-nutrients-11-00684" class="xref">Section 4.1</xref>). In modern flock, the egg weight has been restricted to 62–66 g throughout the laying cycle (20 to 80 weeks of age). Egg weight is the primary criterion used in egg grading (small, medium, large, extra-large). The increase of egg weight observed in older hens is associated with an increase in albumen and yolk average weights and in relative yolk proportion [
 <xref rid="B156-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">156</xref>]. Hen age is also associated with a decrease in eggshell strength, in albumen height (the higher albumen height, the higher the freshness grade) [
 <xref rid="B153-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">153</xref>], and a decrease in the strength of vitelline membrane that is frequently associated with a higher incidence of yolk rupture [
 <xref rid="B157-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">157</xref>]. This latter observation is likely to result from an increase in yolk proportion in older hens. However, when considering the chemical composition of eggs, the results are quite controversial, although some have shown some difference in fatty-acid composition (docosahexaenoic acid and arachidonic acid) of egg depending on hen’s age [
 <xref rid="B158-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">158</xref>]. Overall, these alterations in egg quality with age are, however, consistent with physiological changes and maybe some primary metabolic dysfunctions occurring in commercial hens at the end of the laying cycle [
 <xref rid="B159-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">159</xref>].
</p>
