<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among the proteins derived from pulse legumes (i.e., plants from the Fabaceae family with edible seeds [
 <xref rid="B207-foods-10-00376" ref-type="bibr">207</xref>]), proteins from pea (
 <italic>Pisum sativum</italic> L.) are among the most important ones. Peas contain approximately 20–30% protein with a well-balanced amino acid profile that is particularly rich in lysine [
 <xref rid="B114-foods-10-00376" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. Pea protein has a low allergenic potential and is widely available at low cost [
 <xref rid="B208-foods-10-00376" ref-type="bibr">208</xref>]. Just like soy protein isolate, pea protein isolate containing 85–90% protein is produced by wet processing using either alkali or acid solubilization, followed by isoelectric precipitation at their isoelectric point between pH 4 and 5, or ultrafiltration [
 <xref rid="B114-foods-10-00376" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. Despite having found uses in products such as cereal and bakery products, nutritional snack bars, meal replacement beverages, or baby food formulations, pea protein has rather poor techno-functional properties as an emulsifier compared to other legume proteins. The reasons for this are its low solubility, hydrophobic surface structure, and low surface charge [
 <xref rid="B209-foods-10-00376" ref-type="bibr">209</xref>]. The first studies with the goal of improving pea-protein techno-functionality were conducted around 10 years ago. However, they were not focused on techno-functional properties, but rather on susceptibility to enzymatic hydrolysis and the impact on human intestinal bacteria. Both studies showed that glycation of pea protein significantly alters their digestibility. Glycation resulted either in a higher or lower susceptibility to enzymatic protein hydrolysis depending on the used carbohydrate [
 <xref rid="B177-foods-10-00376" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>], and it promoted the growths of beneficial gut bacteria such as lactobacilli and bifidobacteria [
 <xref rid="B178-foods-10-00376" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>]. Literature on the techno-functional modifications of pea protein upon glycation is available from 2019. Zha et al. [
 <xref rid="B179-foods-10-00376" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>] showed an increase of 15.5% relative solubility after the glycation of pea protein with gum arabic. Oil-in-water emulsions stabilized by these compounds showed a smaller particle size, higher surface charge, and stronger steric hindrance leading to increased droplet stabilization against environmental stresses and lipid oxidation. The results were attributed to steric hindrance effects of the conjugates [
 <xref rid="B179-foods-10-00376" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>]. Numerous studies from recent years have repeatedly demonstrated these observations of enhanced emulsification properties [
 <xref rid="B179-foods-10-00376" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>,
 <xref rid="B181-foods-10-00376" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>,
 <xref rid="B184-foods-10-00376" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>]. Furthermore, glycation of pea protein concentrate with gum arabic was able to diminish undesired beany flavors [
 <xref rid="B182-foods-10-00376" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>].
</p>
