<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>3-Deazathiamine (DAT, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>, No. 
 <bold>2</bold>) is a compound known from the beginning of the 21st century. It was synthesised for the first time by Hawksley et al.
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref>. The main difference between thiamine and this antivitamin is that it lacks the N3 cation in the thiazolium ring, which is replaced by a carbon atom. This modification prevents the formation of ylide and thus affects the catalysis after the incorporation of the derivative into the active centre of thiamine pyrophosphate (TPP) dependent enzymes. Currently, this compound is synthesised in two ways. The first one involves the use of 2-acetylbutyrolactone as a substrate for the formation of thiazolium ring. Pyrimidine ring is synthesised from acetamidine hydrochlorine and 3-anilinopropionitrile
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref>. In the second way, the same substrate is used for pyrimidine ring synthesis, but 3-methylthiophene is used as the first compound for the formation of thiazolium ring
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref>. Studies on the impact of the DAT pyrophosphate (DATPP) on the activity of TPP-dependent enzymes have been done on 
 <italic>Zymomonas mobilis</italic> pyruvate decarboxylase (25000 times stronger binding than TPP) and 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> 2-oxoglutarate dehydrogenase complex (about 500 times stronger binding than TPP) only
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref>. Despite the great importance of PDHC in cell metabolism, no data are available showing the effect of DAT on the parameters of the enzymes from mammalian cells. Similarly, despite the proven inhibitory properties of DAT on the above mentioned TPP-dependent enzymes from bacteria
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> (properties that may indicate a potential cytostatic effect of this derivative), there is no information in the literature about the interaction of DAT with cell 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> models.
</p>
