<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Food Sci Nutr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Food Sci Nutr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2048-7177</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">FSN3</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Food Science &#x00026; Nutrition</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2048-7177</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6526652</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.1013</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">FSN31013</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity of vine tea <italic>(Ampelopsis grossedentata)</italic> extract on lipid and protein oxidation in cooked mixed pork patties during refrigerated storage</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">ZHANG et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="fsn31013-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn31013-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="fsn31013-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn31013-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="fsn31013-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Hai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn31013-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="fsn31013-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Guo&#x02010;Chuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn31013-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="fsn31013-cr-0005" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xue&#x02010;Jun</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6343-3928</contrib-id><address><email>liuxuejun@jlau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn31013-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="fsn31013-aff-0001">
<label><sup>1</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">College of Food Science and Engineering</named-content>
<institution>Jilin Agricultural University</institution>
<named-content content-type="city">Changchun</named-content>
<country country="CN">China</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold><break/>
Xue&#x02010;Jun Liu, College of Food Science and Engineering, Jilin Agricultural University, Changchun, China.<break/>
Email: <email>liuxuejun@jlau.edu.cn</email><break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>02</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.2019.7.issue-5</issue-id><fpage>1735</fpage><lpage>1745</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>04</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> &#x000a9; 2019 Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. <copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2019 The Authors. <italic>Food Science &#x00026; Nutrition</italic> published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:FSN3-7-1735.pdf"/><abstract id="fsn31013-abs-0001"><title>Abstract</title><p>To prevent oxidation and maintain the quality of meat products, it is essential to add antioxidants. The aim of this work was to investigate the antioxidant activity of vine tea (<italic>Ampelopsis grossedentata</italic>) extract (VTE) and evaluate the effects of VTE on the quality characteristics and lipid and protein oxidation of cooked mixed pork patties during refrigerated storage. VTE had a significant DPPH radical scavenging activity, and its IC<sub>50</sub> was 15.35&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml. VTE&#x02010;treated mixed pork patties had a better texture than that of the control group (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). VTE could significantly inhibit an increase in the TBARS value and the formation of carbonyl compounds (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05), and the inhibition was stronger than that of the butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) group (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05), while the amount of sulfhydryl groups significantly decreased (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). The color of VTE itself made the mixed pork patties darker (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05), but this did not affect the sensory scores and overall acceptability of the VTE&#x02010;treated patties, indicating the VTE can be incorporated into mixed pork patties. The scanning electron microscopy (<italic>SEM</italic>) results showed that the VTE inhibited the oxidation of the cooked mixed pork patties during refrigerated storage. These findings may be significant to helping extend the shelf life of meat products.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="fsn31013-kwd-0001"><italic>Ampelopsis grossedentata</italic></kwd><kwd id="fsn31013-kwd-0002">antioxidant activity</kwd><kwd id="fsn31013-kwd-0003">cooked mixed pork patties</kwd><kwd id="fsn31013-kwd-0004">lipid and protein oxidation</kwd><kwd id="fsn31013-kwd-0005">vine tea extract</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Plan of Science and Technology Development of Jilin Province of China</funding-source><award-id>20160307014NY</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="4"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="7774"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>component-id</meta-name><meta-value>fsn31013</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>May 2019</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:5.6.3 mode:remove_FC converted:20.05.2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="self-citation">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-1001">
<string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Xue</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>G&#x02010;C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X&#x02010;J</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Antioxidant activity of vine tea <italic>(Ampelopsis grossedentata)</italic> extract on lipid and protein oxidation in cooked mixed pork patties during refrigerated storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Sci Nutr</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1735</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1745</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.1013</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</p></notes></front><body><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0001"><label>1</label><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Meat products are rich in nutrients (Biesalski, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>), such as proteins, lipids, vitamins, and minerals (Choe et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). However, studies have shown that meat products are prone to oxidation during storage, resulting in food spoilage (Silva et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). The shelf life and quality of meat products are mainly affected by lipid and protein oxidation (Vuorela et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). Due to lipid oxidation, rancidity and off&#x02010;flavors will occur in meat products, which is due to the formation of the secondary oxidation end products (Lorenzo et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). The color, flavor, and texture of meat products also change (G&#x000f3;mez &#x00026; Lorenzo, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Results have shown that protein oxidation leads to an increase in carbonyl content and a decrease in sulfhydryl content (Bekhit, Hopkins, Fahri, &#x00026; Ponnampalam, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Therefore, antioxidants are usually added to meat products, which can inhibit the occurrence of oxidation and maintain product quality (Kumar, Yadav, Ahmad, &#x00026; Narsaiah, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>).</p><p>In recent years, synthetic antioxidants, such as butylated hydroxyanisole (BHA), butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT), and tertiary butyl hydroquinone (TBHQ), have been used in inhibiting meat oxidation (Fasseas, Mountzouris, Tarantilis, Polissiou, &#x00026; Zervas, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). However, continuous use of synthetic antioxidants may increase carcinogenic potential (Hathway, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">1966</xref>). Natural antioxidants have become a hot topic in recent years due to their health safety compared to that of synthetic antioxidants (Moyo, Oyedemi, Masika, &#x00026; Muchenje, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Vine tea (<italic>Ampelopsis grossedentata</italic>) is a plant belonging to Vitaceae and is widely distributed in southern China. Studies have shown that vine tea has good antioxidant activity (Gao et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Vine tea extract (VTE) has a high scavenging activity toward DPPH free radicals (Gao et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). In addition, according to reports, VTE can significantly inhibit lipid oxidation in meat products (Ye, Wang, Duncan, Eigel, &#x00026; O&#x02019;Keefe, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>).</p><p>Studies have shown that red meat is rich in nutrients and has many beneficial functions (Mafra et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). However, excessive intake of animal protein, especially red meat, can lead to increased intake of saturated fat and cholesterol, as well as excessive acid load (Mafra et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), which may increase the risk of disease, such as cardiovascular disease (Abete, Romaguera, Vieira, Lopez de Munain, &#x00026; Norat, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>), kidney disease (Mafra et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), type 2 diabetes (Pan et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>), and cancer (Lippi, Mattiuzzi, &#x00026; Cervellin, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), seriously threatening human health.</p><p>Soy protein meat analogues, as pure plant proteins, are generally obtained by special processing of protein concentrate and protein isolate (Palanisamy, T&#x000f6;pfl, Aganovic, &#x00026; Berger, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>); they have a fibrous structure and good mouthfeel (Krintiras, G&#x000f6;bel, Goot, &#x00026; Stefanidis, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>); and their amino acid composition ratio is close to that of the human body and thus can easily be absorbed and utilized. Because of their fiber texture and rich plant protein, it is necessary to add meat analogues in meat products. They can replace a portion of the animal proteins in human diets (Palanisamy et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), which not only meets the nutritional needs of people, but also reduces the intake of saturated fat and cholesterol (Kumar, Chatli, et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>
<xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>), and reduces the risk of these diseases.</p><p>To compensate for the adverse effects of eating only red meat, mixed pork patties are made by adding meat analogues to pork patties. However, it has been found that mixed pork patties were prone to oxidation during refrigerated storage, which affected their quality and greatly limited their application.</p><p>This study investigated the antioxidant activity of VTE and the effects of VTE on the quality characteristics of mixed pork patties and the inhibition of VTE on lipid and protein oxidation in mixed pork patties during refrigerated storage. This study may be helpful in maintaining the quality and extending the shelf life of mixed pork patties.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0002"><label>2</label><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0003"><label>2.1</label><title>Materials</title><p>Vine tea was collected in May 2018 from Hunan Province of China (Northern latitude 29&#x000b0;66&#x02032;, longitude 109&#x000b0;83&#x02032;, altitude: 1,198&#x000a0;m). Soy protein meat analogues were purchased from Henan Pinzheng Food Technology Co., Ltd (Wen County, Jiaozuo, China), and they contained moisture (8.9%), protein (65.9%), and ash (4%) according to data from the manufacturer.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0004"><label>2.2</label><title>Preparation of vine tea extract (VTE)</title><p>Vine tea powders were extracted with petroleum ether and dried at 40&#x000b0;C to remove impurities, such as fats and pigments. The degreased powder was refluxed in 70% ethanol at 70&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;hr. After filtering, the filtrate was concentrated to remove organic solvents and lyophilized to obtain vine tea extract (VTE).</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0005"><label>2.3</label><title>Gas chromatography mass spectrometry (GC&#x02010;MS)</title><p>The flavonoids of VTE were determined by GC&#x02010;MS using a 6,890&#x02013;5,975 gas chromatography mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific Co., Ltd, Shanghai, China). Briefly, 10&#x000a0;mg of VTE was hydrolyzed with trifluoroacetic acid (TFA, 4&#x000a0;mol/L, 2&#x000a0;ml) at 110&#x000b0;C for 3&#x000a0;hr. The hydrolysate was dried under reduced pressure at 70&#x000b0;C. The hydrolyzed VTE was added to 1&#x000a0;ml of pyridine, and 1&#x000a0;ml of silylating reagent, N,O&#x02010;bis (trimethylsilyl) trifluoroacetamide (BSTFA) and trimethylchlorosilane (TMCS) (99:1), was added quickly. After oscillating to fully dissolve, the solution was reacted in a constant temperature oven at 50&#x000b0;C for 40&#x000a0;min, and then the supernatant was measured by GC&#x02010;MS.</p><p>The flavonoids of VTE were separated on the DB&#x02010;5MS column (30&#x000a0;m&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;0.25&#x000a0;mm&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;0.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m). The inlet temperature and interface temperature were 280&#x000b0;C, and column pressure was 73.0&#x000a0;&#x003ba;. The column was set at a flow rate of 1&#x000a0;ml/min using helium as carrier gas, and the split ratio was 10:1. The column temperature was set as follows: the initial temperature was 80&#x000b0;C (for 3&#x000a0;min) and increased to 280&#x000b0;C at 10&#x000b0;C&#x0202f;/min, then was held for 5&#x000a0;min, and the injection volume was 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l. The MS conditions were that the temperature of ion source was 200&#x000b0;C and the range of M/Z was 20&#x02013;800.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0006"><label>2.4</label><title>Determination of total flavonoid content and DPPH radical scavenging activity of VTE</title><p>Total flavonoid contents were measured according to the method of Xie et al. (<xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) with some modifications. Briefly, 0.1&#x000a0;ml solution of VTE was added to a 10&#x000a0;ml volumetric bottle, 3&#x000a0;ml of 5% AlCl<sub>3</sub> solution was added, and volume was fixed with 95% ethanol. The absorbance of the sample was determined with a TU&#x02010;1901 ultraviolet&#x02010;visible spectrophotometer (Beijing Pu Analysis General Instrument Co., Ltd, Beijing, China) at 310&#x000a0;nm. The calibration curve was prepared by preparing dihydromyricetin solution with concentration of 5 to 25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml in 95% ethanol. The calibration curve was calculated as follows: <italic>y</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0571<italic>x&#x000a0;</italic>&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0106, where <italic>y</italic> and <italic>x</italic> are the absorbance value and the concentration of the sample, respectively. The correlation coefficient (<italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>) is 0.9947.</p><p>Two milliliter of various concentrations (20, 40, 100, 200, 400, and 800&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml) of the sample solutions was thoroughly mixed with 2&#x000a0;ml of freshly prepared DPPH solution (0.1&#x000a0;mmol/L). The mixture was shaken vigorously and allowed to stand for 30&#x000a0;min in the dark, and the absorbance at 517&#x000a0;nm was then measured with a vis spectrophotometer (Pagenenal, Beijing, China). Ethanol was used as the blank control, and ascorbic acid was used as positive control. All tests were carried out in triplicate. The scavenging activity of VTE on DPPH is calculated according to the following formula:<disp-formula id="fsn31013-disp-0001"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="nlm-math-1"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>DPPH radical scavenging activity(\% )</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>A</italic>
<sub>0</sub> is the absorbance of the incubation DPPH solution without addition of the sample or positive controls, <italic>A</italic>
<sub>1</sub> is the absorbance of the incubation mixture containing both the test sample and DPPH solution, and <italic>A</italic>
<sub>2</sub> is the absorbance of the sample without DPPH solution.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0007"><label>2.5</label><title>Preparation of mixed pork patties</title><p>Soy protein meat analogues were soaked with water until no hard cores remained. Excess water in the soy protein meat analogues was removed with a dehydrator, and then, the analogues were broken into pieces for use in the next step. 500&#x000a0;g of soy protein meat analogues and 500&#x000a0;g of pork back&#x02010;leg meat were used as the raw materials, and the formulation of mixed pork patties was as follows: 10% flour, 10% modified starch, 10% soy protein isolate, 3% salt, 2% white sugar, 2.5% monosodium glutamate, 0.3% pepper, and 7% water. Samples were homogenized in a chopper (Stephan, Shanghai, China) for 5&#x000a0;min after adding all the ingredients. The mixture was divided into four groups: (a) control group; (b) BHT group (0.01% BHT); (c) VTE 0.1 group (0.1% lyophilized VTE powders); and (d) VTE 0.3 group (0.3% lyophilized VTE powders). The four groups of mixtures were evenly mixed and formed into patties (length, width, and height were 10&#x000a0;cm, 5&#x000a0;cm, and 1&#x000a0;cm, respectively). The blended pork patties were baked for 20&#x000a0;min at 180&#x000b0;C and then at 210&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min in a universal oven (Rational, Beijing, China). The cooked samples were cooled and stored in oxygen&#x02010;permeable bags for 8&#x000a0;days at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1&#x000b0;C. Indicators of the samples were determined after 0, 2, 4, 6, and 8&#x000a0;days of storage.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0008"><label>2.6</label><title>Analytical methods</title><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0009"><label>2.6.1</label><title>Proximate analysis</title><p>The proximate composition (moisture, protein, and fat contents) of the mixed pork patties was measured using a FOSS FoodScan&#x02122; Meat Analyzer Near&#x02010;Infrared Spectrophotometer (Model 78,810; Foss Co., Hiller&#x000f8;d, Denmark) (Schillinga et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0010"><label>2.6.2</label><title>The pH evaluation</title><p>Ten gram samples of mixed pork patties were homogenized with 90&#x000a0;ml of distilled water for 30&#x000a0;s using a homogenizer (IKA, Shanghai, China). Then, the pH of the mixed pork patties was evaluated with a pH meter (Mettler Toledo, Shanghai, China).</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0011"><label>2.6.3</label><title>Determination of texture characteristics</title><p>The texture characteristics of the samples were determined by a texture analyzer (FTC, Hangzhou, China). The same size samples (20&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;20&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10&#x000a0;mm) were obtained from the mixed pork patties, and their texture characteristics, included hardness and springiness, were analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0012"><label>2.6.4</label><title>Colorimetric determination</title><p>The colors of the mixed pork patties were measured using a color difference meter (HunterLab, Shanghai, China). The following color indices were measured: lightness (L<sup>*</sup>), redness (a<sup>*</sup>), and yellowness (b<sup>*</sup>). The chromatometer was calibrated with a white standard before use.</p></sec></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0013"><label>2.7</label><title>Lipid oxidation</title><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0014"><label>2.7.1</label><title>Thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS)</title><p>The TBARS value was evaluated based on the method of the official standard issued in China titled &#x0201c;Determination of malondialdehyde in food&#x0201d; (GB 2016&#x02010;5009.181).</p></sec></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0015"><label>2.8</label><title>Protein oxidation</title><p>Protein carbonyls were evaluated by the method of Oliver, Ahn, Moerman, Goldstein, and Stadtman (<xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">1987</xref>). Carbonyl content was determined by the reaction between 2,4&#x02010;dinitrophenylhydrazine (DNPH) and carbonyl group. Absorption was measured at 370&#x000a0;nm with a TU&#x02010;1901 ultraviolet&#x02010;visible spectrophotometer. The carbonyl content was calculated using the protein concentration and an extinction coefficient of 21.0&#x000a0;mM<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and the protein concentration was determined by using BSA as a standard, and the results were expressed as nmol of carbonyl/mg protein. The total sulfhydryl content was measured using 5,5&#x02032;&#x02010;dithiobis (2&#x02010;nitrobenzoic acid) (DTNB) (Ellman, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">1959</xref>). Absorption was measured at 420&#x000a0;nm with a TU&#x02010;1901 ultraviolet&#x02010;visible spectrophotometer. The results were calculated using the protein concentration at 280&#x000a0;nm and expressed as nmol sulfhydryl/mg protein.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0016"><label>2.9</label><title>Scanning electron microscopy</title><p>Scanning electron microscopy (<italic>SEM</italic>) was used to analyze the microstructure of all the groups. The <italic>SEM</italic> was evaluated by the method of Palanisamy et al. (<xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). The refrigerated samples were taken out and cut into 10&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10&#x000a0;mm, then dried immediately to the full. Then, the sample surfaces were sputter coated with gold and images were taken by XL&#x02010;30 ESEM FEG scanning electron microscope (FEI, Shanghai, China).</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0017"><label>2.10</label><title>Sensory evaluation</title><p>Sensory evaluations such as flavor, color, mouthfeel, texture, and overall acceptance scores of the mixed pork patties stored for 0&#x000a0;days were evaluated. The assessment consisted of teachers and students (20&#x02013;40&#x000a0;years old, 10 male and 10 female) from Jilin Agricultural University. The evaluation was conducted using a 5&#x02010;point scale (5&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;great and 1&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;bad).</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0018"><label>2.11</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All data are shown as the mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard deviation (<italic>SD</italic>). The significant differences between groups were determined by the SPSS 24.0 system. The acceptable level for statistical significance was <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0019"><label>3</label><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0020"><label>3.1</label><title>Composition of Vine tea extract</title><p>The GC&#x02010;MS chromatograms of VTE are shown in Figure <xref rid="fsn31013-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a and b. According to the MS data, the flavonoid compounds were identified to be dihydromyricetin and dihydroquercetin. Dihydromyricetin was the main component of VTE, with an average content of 96.93%, while the average content of dihydroquercetin was 1.77%.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31013-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>GC&#x02010;MS chromatograms of flavonoid standard compounds and VTE. (a) GC&#x02010;MS chromatograms of standards and (b) GC&#x02010;MS chromatograms of VTE. (1: dihydromyricetin; 2: rutin; 3: dihydroquercetin; 4: madendrin; 5: fructose; 6 quercetin; 7 apigenin; 8: kaempferol; a: dihydromyricetin; b: dihydroquercetin)</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="FSN3-7-1735-g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0021"><label>3.2</label><title>Total flavonoid content and DPPH radical scavenging activity of VTE</title><p>Using dihydromyricetin as the standard, VTE had a high flavonoid content of 8.14&#x000a0;g per 100&#x000a0;g of VTE. The DPPH radical is commonly used to estimate the antioxidant activity of antioxidants (Xie et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). The scavenging activity of VTE against DPPH radical is shown in Figure <xref rid="fsn31013-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. VTE had a strong DPPH radical scavenging activity. When the concentration was 20 and 800&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml, the scavenging rates were 51.84% and 90.82%, respectively (Figure <xref rid="fsn31013-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The IC<sub>50</sub> for DPPH radical scavenging activity was 15.35&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml. The DPPH radical scavenging activity of VTE increased in a concentration&#x02010;dependent manner.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31013-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>DPPH radical scavenging activity of VTE. All values are presented as the mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;<italic>SD</italic> of three independent experiments</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="FSN3-7-1735-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0022"><label>3.3</label><title>Chemical composition of mixed pork patties</title><p>The protein, fat, and moisture contents of samples are listed in Table <xref rid="fsn31013-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Differences in the initial protein, fat, and moisture content of all the samples within a group were not significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;0.05).</p><table-wrap id="fsn31013-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Initial chemical compositions (protein, fat, and moisture) of the mixed pork patties. Data are presented as the mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;<italic>SD</italic> of the mean (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left" colspan="4" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1">Treatment</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BHT</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VTE 0.1</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VTE 0.3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.51&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.58&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.56</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.88&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.50&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fat (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.39&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.18&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.14&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.34&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moisture (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.22&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.46&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.39&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.21&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.58</td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0023"><label>3.4</label><title>pH analysis</title><p>As shown in Table <xref rid="fsn31013-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>, the pH values of all samples increased during refrigerated storage (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05), which may be due to the breakdown of proteins by microorganisms and enzymes (Ben Abdelmalek, Essid, Smeti, &#x00026; Atti, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>) and the nitrogenized compounds that were released by protein degradation (Zhang, Lin, Leng, Huang, &#x00026; Zhou, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). The VTE&#x02010;treated groups had a lower pH than that of the control group (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). This may be due to the antioxidant activity of VTE, which could inhibit the protein degradation.</p><table-wrap id="fsn31013-tbl-0002" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of vine tea extract (VTE) on the pH of the mixed pork patties. Data are presented as the mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;<italic>SD</italic> of the mean (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Storage time (day)</th><th align="left" colspan="4" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1">Treatment</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BHT</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VTE 0.1</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VTE 0.3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">pH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01<sup>D</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.00<sup>D</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02<sup>D</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01<sup>C</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.53&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02<sup>Ca</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.49&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01<sup>CDab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.50&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01<sup>CDab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02<sup>BCb</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.55&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01<sup>BCa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.51&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02<sup>BCb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01<sup>BCab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.49&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01<sup>BCb</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.57&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.00<sup>ABa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.53&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.00<sup>ABb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.54&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.00<sup>ABb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.51&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01<sup>ABc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.59&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.00<sup>Aa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.55&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.00<sup>Ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.56&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01<sup>Ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.53&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01<sup>Ac</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fsn31013-note-0001"><p>
<sup>a&#x02010;d</sup>Means within each row with different superscript letters are significantly different (<italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05).</p></fn><fn id="fsn31013-note-0002"><p>
<sup>A&#x02010;D</sup>Means within each column with different superscript letters are significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0024"><label>3.5</label><title>Color measurement</title><p>The L<sup>*</sup> value of the mixed pork patties significantly decreased (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) during refrigerated storage (Table <xref rid="fsn31013-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>), and the a<sup>*</sup> and b<sup>*</sup> values of the control and BHT groups significantly decreased (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). Compared to the changes in the control group, the VTE&#x02010;treated samples maintained stable a<sup>*</sup> and b<sup>*</sup> values, even at lower a<sup>*</sup> and b<sup>*</sup> values (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). This indicated that VTE had a protective effect on the color deterioration of the mixed pork patties during the storage period. Compared to those of the control group, the VTE&#x02010;treated samples showed significantly lower L<sup>*</sup>, a<sup>*</sup>, and b<sup>*</sup> values (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05), and samples with higher added amounts of VTE had lower L<sup>*</sup>, a<sup>*</sup>, and b<sup>*</sup> values. This may be due to the color (green) of the VTE.</p><table-wrap id="fsn31013-tbl-0003" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effects of vine tea extract (VTE) on the color parameters of the mixed pork patties during the storage period. Data are presented as the mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;<italic>SD</italic> of the mean (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Storage time (day)</th><th align="left" colspan="4" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1">Treatment</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BHT</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VTE 0.1</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VTE 0.3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">L<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.70&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.04<sup>Aa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.09&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06<sup>Ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.45&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.23<sup>Ac</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.63&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.11<sup>Ad</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.15&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.05<sup>Ba</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.14&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.10<sup>Bb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.67&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.08<sup>Bc</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.24&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.09<sup>Ad</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.22&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.13<sup>Ca</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.60&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.31<sup>Ca</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.55&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.12<sup>BCb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.42&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.15<sup>Bc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.23&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.05<sup>Da</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.60&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.21<sup>Da</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.17&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.13<sup>CDb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.65&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.32<sup>Cc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.06&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.12<sup>Da</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.27&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.08<sup>Da</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.02&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.16<sup>Db</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.92&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.13<sup>Dc</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">a<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.61&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.07<sup>Aa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.54&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06<sup>Ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.45&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.32<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06<sup>d</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.14&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.15<sup>Bb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.46&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.05<sup>ABa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.53&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.07<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.64&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.05<sup>d</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.09&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06<sup>Ba</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.27&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.04<sup>Ba</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.04<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.73&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.31<sup>c</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.22&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.04<sup>Cb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.85&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.19<sup>Ca</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.07<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.71&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.08<sup>d</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.11&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.03<sup>Cb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.57&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.03<sup>Da</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.39&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.28<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.58&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.20<sup>d</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">b<sup>*</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.52&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.05<sup>Aa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.64&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.07<sup>Aa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.65&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.36<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.12&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06<sup>c</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.07&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.05<sup>Bb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.44&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.14<sup>ABa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.60&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.17<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.01&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.10<sup>d</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.43&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.14<sup>Cb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.17&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.09<sup>BCa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.38&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.03<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.42&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.29<sup>d</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.18&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.08<sup>Cb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.94&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.22<sup>CDa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.43&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.14<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.27&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.15<sup>d</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.58&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.18<sup>Db</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.63&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.12<sup>Da</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.27&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.36<sup>c</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.18&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.27<sup>d</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fsn31013-note-0003"><p>
<sup>a&#x02010;d</sup>Means within each row with different superscript letters are significantly different (<italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;&#x0202f;0.05).</p></fn><fn id="fsn31013-note-0004"><p>
<sup>A&#x02010;D</sup>Means within each column with different superscript letters are significantly different (<italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;&#x0202f;0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0025"><label>3.6</label><title>Effect of VTE on lipid oxidation of mixed pork patties</title><p>A change in the amount of TBARS can indirectly reflect the degree of oxidative rancidity in meat products (Turgut, Soyer, &#x00026; I&#x0015f;&#x00131;k&#x000e7;&#x00131;, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). As shown in Figure <xref rid="fsn31013-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, lipid oxidation occurred due to a significant increase (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) in the TBARS value during refrigerated storage. The initial TBARS values of control, BHT, VTE 0.1, and VTE 0.3 groups were 1.07, 1.07, 1.02, and 1.04&#x000a0;mg MDA/kg meat, respectively. During refrigerated storage, compared to that of the control group, the other groups had lower TBARS values (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05), indicating that VTE could effectively inhibit the lipid oxidation of mixed pork patties. At the end of storage, the TBARS values of these groups were 1.97, 1.57, 1.65, and 1.54&#x000a0;mg MDA/kg meat, respectively. It was observed that VTE 0.3 group, with a higher added amount of VTE, had a higher inhibitory effect on lipid oxidation than did the BHT group (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05), and the ranking order of TBARS value was control&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;VTE 0.1&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;BHT&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;VTE 0.3 in descending order. However, at 0&#x02013;6&#x000a0;days of refrigeration, the TBARS value of VTE 0.1 group was lower than that of VTE 0.3 group (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05), while on day 8, the TBARS value of VTE 0.3 group was lower than that of VTE 0.1 group (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). This phenomenon may be due to the fact that VTE with low concentration can rapidly diffuse into the samples to inhibit lipid oxidation, but its inhibition time is short; while VTE with high concentration releases slowly, it can sustainably inhibit the occurrence of lipid oxidation. The effective inhibition of VTE against lipid oxidation may be due to the presence of dihydromyricetin. Previous studies have reported that dihydromyricetin can effectively inhibit the oxidation of soybean oil (Ye et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31013-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Effects of VTE on TBARS of the cooked mixed pork patties during refrigerated storage. <sup>a&#x02010;d</sup> Means within the same storage day between the different groups with different superscript letters are significantly different (<italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.&#x0202f;05). <sup>A&#x02010;E</sup>Means within the same group at different storage times with different superscript letters are significantly different (<italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;&#x0202f;0.05). All values are presented as the mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;<italic>SD</italic> of three independent experiments</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="FSN3-7-1735-g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0026"><label>3.7</label><title>Effects of VTE on protein oxidation of mixed pork patties</title><p>Protein oxidation can also cause meat deterioration (Lund, Heinonen, Baron, &#x00026; Est&#x000e9;vez, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). The changes of carbonyl and sulfhydryl contents can indirectly reflect the degree of protein oxidation in meat products.</p><p>As shown in Figure <xref rid="fsn31013-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a, the protein carbonyl content increased significantly (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) during refrigerated storage. The initial carbonyl contents of control, BHT, VTE 0.1, and VTE 0.3 groups were 2.09, 1.90, 1.59, and 1.54&#x000a0;nmol/mg protein, respectively. Compared with the control group, VTE showed strong inhibition on carbonyl content from the beginning of storage (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). When refrigerated for 8&#x000a0;days, the final carbonyl contents of control, BHT, VTE 0.1, and VTE 0.3 groups were 4.38, 3.31, 3.25, and 2.94&#x000a0;nmol/mg protein, respectively. It was observed that the carbonyl content in the control group was significantly higher than that in the VTE treatment group. Obviously, 0.1% and 0.3% VTE significantly inhibited the formation of protein carbonyl compounds (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) in the mixed pork patties over the entire storage period compared with that of the control group, and the inhibition was stronger than that of the BHT group (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). In addition, protein oxidation occurred more rapidly than did lipid oxidation.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31013-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Effects of VTE on carbonyl content (a) and sulfhydryl content (b) of the cooked mixed pork patties during refrigerated storage. <sup>a&#x02010;d</sup>Means within the same storage day between the different groups with different superscript letters are significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;&#x0202f;0.05). <sup>A&#x02010;E</sup>Means within the same group at different storage times with different superscript letters are significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;&#x0202f;0.05). All values are presented as the mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;<italic>SD</italic> of three independent experiments</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="FSN3-7-1735-g004"/></fig><p>The decrease in the amount of sulfhydryl groups is used as another indicator of protein oxidation (He et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). The reduction of the sulfhydryl groups is due to the oxidation of the cysteine sulfhydryl group to form a disulfide bond, which induces protein cross&#x02010;linking (Jia, Kong, Liu, Diao, &#x00026; Xia, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). As shown in Figure <xref rid="fsn31013-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b, the sulfhydryl contents of all groups were significantly reduced (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) during refrigerated storage. It could be observed that the sulfhydryl contents of the VTE&#x02010;treated samples were significantly lower than those of the control and BHT groups (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) during refrigerated storage, and the rate of decline was faster in the VTE&#x02010;treated samples, which is similar to the findings of Jongberg, Skov, T&#x000f8;rngren, Skibsted, and Lund (<xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). They found that adding white grape extract to chill stored beef patties also accelerated the sulfhydryl loss. In addition, Jongberg, T&#x000f8;rngren, Gunvig, Skibsted, and Lund (<xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>) found no protective effect of green tea extract against sulfhydryl loss in Bologna sausage. This may be due to the interactions of the sulfhydryl groups with the phenolic compounds. The ortho&#x02010;phenolic structure readily forms covalent bonds with nucleophilic sulfhydryl groups to form sulfhydryl&#x02010;oxime adducts, resulting in sulfhydryl loss. Studies have shown that phenolic substances exist in VTE (Ye et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>), and we speculate that these phenolic substances may be combined with sulfhydryl groups, resulting in the lower sulfhydryl content in the VTE&#x02010;treated mixed pork patties than in the control group.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0027"><label>3.8</label><title>Texture profile analysis</title><p>Changes in sample hardness during refrigeration are shown in Table <xref rid="fsn31013-tbl-0004" ref-type="table">4</xref>. The initial hardness of each group did not change significantly (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;0.05) during refrigerated storage. However, the hardness of the control group significantly increased (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05), and the hardness of both the BHT group and VTE 0.3 group increased, but these changes were not significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;0.05). The samples with a higher added mount of VTE had a lower hardness (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05), suggesting that VTE could inhibit the increasing hardness of the mixed pork patties during refrigerated storage. Previous studies showed that the separation of water and fat from the protein matrix caused emulsion instability, resulting in an increase in the hardness of meat products (Est&#x000e9;vez, Ventanas, &#x00026; Cava, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). Other studies suggested that protein oxidation affected protein function (Xiong, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>). Furthermore, protein oxidation affected the protein solubility, resulting in aggregation and complex formation due to protein cross&#x02010;linking (Ganh&#x000e3;o, Morcuende, &#x00026; Est&#x000e9;vez, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). The loss of protein function and the formation of cross&#x02010;linking between proteins led to an increase in the hardness of meat products. (Est&#x000e9;vez et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). The results of this experiment showed that VTE had strong antioxidant activity, which could significantly inhibit protein oxidation. VTE may inhibit the increase in mixed pork patties hardness by protecting protein function and inhibiting protein cross&#x02010;linking. In addition, natural antioxidants can maintain the membrane integrity of muscle fibers and prevent water loss, thus maintaining the texture of meat products (Maqsood, Benjakul, &#x00026; Balange, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). The results also showed that VTE could significantly inhibit lipid oxidation, so it is reasonable that VTE could inhibit the increasing hardness of the mixed pork patties. In addition, the springiness of all groups slightly decreased, but there were no significant differences (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;0.05).</p><table-wrap id="fsn31013-tbl-0004" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Effects of vine tea extract (VTE) on the hardness and springiness of the mixed pork patties during the storage period. Data are presented as the mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;<italic>SD</italic> of the mean (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Storage time (day)</th><th align="left" colspan="4" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1">Treatment</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BHT</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VTE 0.1</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VTE 0.3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Hardness (<italic>N</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">374.37&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;11.58<sup>D</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">370.23&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;17.79</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">363.20&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;13.23<sup>B</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">361.13&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;16.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">392.93&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.31<sup>CD</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">378.53&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">375.93&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.12<sup>B</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">371.25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.54</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">411.60&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.09<sup>BC</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">393.17&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;19.88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">388.83&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.45<sup>AB</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">383.96&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;18.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">433.70&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;13.39<sup>ABa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">405.83&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;15.92<sup>ab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">397.87&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;14.22<sup>ABb</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">392.27&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;14.40<sup>b</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">459.00&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.78<sup>Aa</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">409.27&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;13.75<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">416.63&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;18.94<sup>Aab</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">400.43&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;21.13<sup>b</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Springines (cm)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.41&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.43&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.32&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.34&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.38&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.36&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.27&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.26&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.27&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.22&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.21&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.15&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.23&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.19&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.14&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.11</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fsn31013-note-0005"><p>
<sup>a&#x02010;d</sup>Means within each row with different superscript letters are significantly different (<italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;&#x0202f;0.05).</p></fn><fn id="fsn31013-note-0006"><p>
<sup>A&#x02010;D</sup>Means within each column with different superscript letters are significantly different (<italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;&#x0202f;0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0028"><label>3.9</label><title>Microscopical observations</title><p>Figure <xref rid="fsn31013-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref> is the <italic>SEM</italic> images of all groups at 0 and 8&#x000a0;days of refrigeration. As shown in Figure <xref rid="fsn31013-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, the initial <italic>SEM</italic> images of all the groups were smooth and flat; when refrigerated for 8&#x000a0;days, the <italic>SEM</italic> images of all the groups were rougher and uneven. This may be due to the oxidation of the mixed pork patties at 8&#x000a0;days of refrigeration, which destroyed their original structure. In addition, when refrigerated for 8&#x000a0;days, the VTE&#x02010;treated mixed pork patties were less damaged than that of the control group, suggesting that VTE was effective for suppressing the oxidation of the mixed pork patties during refrigerated storage.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31013-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>
<italic>SEM</italic> images of all groups at 0 and 8&#x000a0;days of refrigeration. ([A&#x02013;D] is the <italic>SEM</italic> of the control, BHT, VTE 0.1, and VTE 0.3 groups at 0&#x000a0;days of refrigeration; [a&#x02013;d] is the <italic>SEM</italic> of the control, BHT, VTE 0.1, and VTE 0.3 groups at 8&#x000a0;days of refrigeration)</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="FSN3-7-1735-g005"/></fig></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0029"><label>3.10</label><title>Sensory evaluation</title><p>The sensory characteristics of the mixed pork patties on day 0, including flavor, surface color, mouthfeel, texture, and overall acceptability, are shown in Figure <xref rid="fsn31013-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>. As the added amounts of VTE increased in the mixed pork patties, the flavor scores increased, which may be due to the inhibition of oxidation in the samples by VTE. However, the higher the added amounts of VTE, the lower the color scores were, possibly due to the color of the phytochemical itself. It was found that the mixed pork patties had a higher mouthfeel score, which may be due to the addition of soy protein meat analogues. The meat analogues are fibrous and have a good chewiness and meaty feeling, which resulted in the mixed pork patties having a good mouthfeel. The VTE&#x02010;treated samples had a high texture score, which is consistent with the above hardness results. In addition, overall acceptability was not affected by the addition of VTE. These results indicated that VTE can be added to mixed pork patties without adverse effects on the sensory attributes.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31013-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Effect of VTE on the sensory attributes of the cooked mixed pork patties. All values are presented as the mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;<italic>SD</italic> of three independent experiments</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-13" xlink:href="FSN3-7-1735-g006"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0030"><label>4</label><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Previous studies have reported that natural antioxidants can significantly inhibit lipid and protein oxidation in meat products (Jiao, Zhao, Lin, &#x00026; Wang, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Rodr&#x000ed;guez&#x02010;Carpena, Morcuende, &#x00026; Est&#x000e9;vez, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). The antioxidant activity of these natural antioxidants may be related to the presence of phenolic compounds. Flavonoids, a kind of phenolic antioxidant (Mattila, Hellstr&#x000f6;m, Karhu, Pihlava, &#x00026; Vetel&#x000e4;inen, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), can scavenge free radicals (Jia et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). In this study, according to the results of GC&#x02010;MS, the main flavonoid of VTE was dihydromyricetin. This experiment found that VTE can effectively improve the quality of mixed pork patties, which may be due to the abundance of dihydromyricetin in VTE. Previous studies have reported that dihydromyricetin has a stronger antioxidant activity than that of BHA and TBHQ (Ye et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). As an antioxidant, VTE not only inhibited lipid and protein oxidation in the mixed pork patties, but also maintained the sensory properties and quality and represents a more effective utilization plant resources.</p><p>As a synthetic antioxidant, BHT is readily available and has been widely used to inhibit meat oxidation (Formanek et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). However, recent studies have shown that BHT is associated with health risks due to toxic effects (Lindenschmidt, Tryka, Goad, &#x00026; Witschi, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">1986</xref>). As a natural antioxidant, VTE not only has significant antioxidant activity (Gao et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), but can effectively improve meat quality without adverse effects. However, so far, no relevant literatures have reported the maximum permissible dosage of VTE. In this experiment, the dosage of VTE was much higher than that of BHT for the following two reasons: (a) International Food Standards stipulate that the maximum dosage of BHT in meat was 0.01% (Codex Alimentarius commission., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>); therefore, we chose the maximum dosage of BHT 0.01% to evaluate the antioxidant activity of VTE; (b) In addition, the dosage of natural extracts in meat ranged from 0.1% to 1.5% in more than half of the literatures (Falowo, Fayemi, &#x00026; Muchenje, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Ribeiro et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), so we initially selected the dosages of VTE as 0.1%, 0.3%, and 0.5%. However, we found that when the dosage of VTE was 0.5%, the color of mixed pork patties was too dark, which affected the overall acceptability of the scoring group members. Therefore, we chose 0.1% and 0.3% as our experimental dosages.</p><p>Studies have shown that the physicochemical properties of natural antioxidants, such as solubility and stability, affect their antioxidant activity. In the experiment, we found that the solubility of VTE was poor. Meanwhile, the research showed that the effect of dissolving VTE with water&#x02010;containing ethanol (20%) was not ideal, which may affect the utilization of VTE (Ye et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Currently, studies have shown that natural antioxidants have good thermal stability (Zhao et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>), but the temperature range of VTE for thermal stability is uncertain. In addition, different cooking methods can also affect the effects of natural antioxidants (Zhao et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Currently, the heat cooking mainly includes boiling, steaming, frying, baking, and microwave technology (Palermo et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Studies showed that the loss of flavonols in foods increased during boiling, frying, and microwave ovens (Moreno, L&#x000f3;pez&#x02010;Berenguer, &#x00026; Garc&#x000ed;a&#x02010;Viguera, <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Zhao et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Interestingly, different higher baking conditions did not lead to the degradation of flavonols (Yang et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). In this experiment, we used baking to cook mixed pork patties. We are not sure whether high temperature baking has an effect on the antioxidant activity of VTE. But as the main component of VTE, studies have shown that dihydromyricetin has good thermal stability, even better than TBHQ, and can be used as an antioxidant in edible oils and baked foods (Gao et al., <xref rid="fsn31013-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Therefore, we speculate that high temperature has no significant effect on the thermal stability and antioxidant activity of VTE. Of course, this still needs further research to verify. Future studies on the physicochemical properties of VTE and the effects of different cooking methods on the effectiveness of VTE can further help to assess the potential application of VTE as an antioxidant in food.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0031"><label>5</label><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>This study showed that vine tea extract had a strong antioxidant activity, and it could effectively improve the quality characteristics of mixed pork patties and delay lipid oxidation and protein oxidation in the cooked mixed pork patties during refrigerated storage. The study provides a theoretical basis for extending the shelf life of meat products and developing healthy and safe antioxidants for the meat industry, which may play a role in promoting the development of meat industry.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31013-sec-0033"><title>ETHICAL APPROVAL</title><p>This study does not involve any human or animal testing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="fsn31013-sec-0034"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</title><p>All authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p><p>Informed consent: Written informed consent was obtained from all study participants.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="fsn31013-sec-0032"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>This research was supported by the Plan of Science and Technology Development of Jilin Province of China (No. 20160307014NY).</p></ack><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="fsn31013-bibl-0001"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Abete</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Romaguera</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Vieira</surname>, <given-names>A. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lopez de Munain</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Norat</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Association between total, processed, red and white meat consumption and all&#x02010;cause, CVD and IHD mortality: A meta&#x02010;analysis of cohort studies</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">British Journal of Nutrition</source>, <volume>112</volume>(<issue>05</issue>), <fpage>762</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>775</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s000711451400124x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24932617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Bekhit</surname>, <given-names>A.&#x02010;E.&#x02010;D.&#x02010;A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hopkins</surname>, <given-names>D. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fahri</surname>, <given-names>F. T.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ponnampalam</surname>, <given-names>E. N.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Oxidative processes in muscle systems and fresh meat: Sources, markers, and remedies</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>565</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>597</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12027</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Ben Abdelmalek</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Essid</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Smeti</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Atti</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>The anti&#x02010;oxidant and antimicrobial effect of <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L. distillation residues&#x02019; intake on cooked sausages from ewes fed linseed</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Small Ruminant Research</source>, <volume>168</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smallrumres.2018.08.012</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Biesalski</surname>, <given-names>H.&#x02010;K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Meat as a component of a healthy diet&#x02010;Are there any risks or benefits if meat is avoided in the diet?</article-title>
<source xml:lang="en">Meat Science</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>524</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2004.07.017</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22063749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Choe</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jo</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jo</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Song</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Jung</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Application of winter mushroom powder as an alternative to phosphates in emulsion&#x02010;type sausages</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Meat Science</source>, <volume>143</volume>, <fpage>114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>118</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2018.04.038</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29734004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="fsn31013-cit-0007">
<collab collab-type="authors">Codex Alimentarius Commission </collab>
(<year>2015</year>). International food standards. General standard for food additives. Joint FAO/WHO. Dispon&#x000ed;vel em. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.codexalimentarius.net/gsfaonline/docs/CXS_192e.pdf">http://www.codexalimentarius.net/gsfaonline/docs/CXS_192e.pdf</ext-link> (2015). (acesso em: 16 de nov. 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Ellman</surname>, <given-names>G. L.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1959</year>). <article-title>Tissue sulfhydryl groups</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics</source>, <volume>82</volume>, <fpage>70</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-9861(59)90090-6</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13650640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Est&#x000e9;vez</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ventanas</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Cava</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Protein oxidation in frankfurters with increasing levels of added rosemary essential oil: effect on color and texture deterioration</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Science</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>c427</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>c432</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2621.2005.tb11464.x</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Falowo</surname>, <given-names>A. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fayemi</surname>, <given-names>P. O.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Muchenje</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Natural antioxidants against lipid&#x02013;protein oxidative deterioration in meat and meat products: A review</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Research International</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>181</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2014.06.022</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30011637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Fasseas</surname>, <given-names>M. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mountzouris</surname>, <given-names>K. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tarantilis</surname>, <given-names>P. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Polissiou</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Zervas</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant activity in meat treated with oregano and sage essential oils</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>106</volume>, <fpage>1188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1194</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2007.07.060</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Formanek</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kerry</surname>, <given-names>J. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Higgins</surname>, <given-names>F. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Buckley</surname>, <given-names>D. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Morrissey</surname>, <given-names>P. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Farkas</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Addition of synthetic and natural antioxidants to &#x003b1;&#x02010;tocopheryl acetate supplemented beef patties: Effects of antioxidants and packaging on lipid oxidation</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Meat Science</source>, <volume>58</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>341</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0309-1740(00)00149-2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22062422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Ganh&#x000e3;o</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Morcuende</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Est&#x000e9;vez</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Protein oxidation in emulsified cooked burger patties with added fruit extracts: Influence on color and texture deterioration during chill storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Meat Science</source>, <volume>85</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>402</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>409</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2010.02.008</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20416800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Gao</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ning</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Wu</surname>, <given-names>Q.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Characterization and antioxidant activity of flavonoid&#x02010;rich extracts from leaves of <italic>Ampelopsis grossedentata</italic>
</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Biochemistry</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>808</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>820</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1745-4514.2009.00253.x</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Gao</surname>, <given-names>Q.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ma</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cai</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Xiang</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant profiling of vine tea (<italic>Ampelopsis grossedentata</italic>): Off&#x02010;line coupling heart&#x02010;cutting HSCCC with HPLC&#x02013;DAD&#x02013;QTOF&#x02010;MS/MS</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>225</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.11.122</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28193433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>G&#x000f3;mez</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Lorenzo</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Effect of packaging conditions on shelf&#x02010;life of fresh foal meat</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Meat Science</source>, <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>520</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2012.03.007</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22475722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Hathway</surname>, <given-names>D. E.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1966</year>). <article-title>Metabolic fate in animals of hindered phenolic antioxidants in relation to their safety evaluation and antioxidants function</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Advances in Food Research</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1735</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0065-2628(08),60077-4</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>He</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Huang</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yang</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hao</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Deng</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>The effects of modified atmosphere packaging and enzyme inhibitors on protein oxidation of tilapia muscle during iced storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">LWT</source>, <volume>87</volume>, <fpage>186</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>193</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2017.08.046</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Jia</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kong</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>, <given-names>Q.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Diao</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Xia</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant activity of black currant (<italic>Ribes nigrum</italic> L.) extract and its inhibitory effect on lipid and protein oxidation of pork patties during chilled storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Meat Science</source>, <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>533</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>539</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2012.03.010</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22483714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Jiao</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lin</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>
<italic>Lonicera japonica</italic> Thunb. extract improves the quality of cold&#x02010;stored porcine patty through inhibition of lipid and myofibrillar protein oxidation</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">International Journal of Food Science and Technology</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>986</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>993</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ijfs.13673</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Jongberg</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Skov</surname>, <given-names>S. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>T&#x000f8;rngren</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Skibsted</surname>, <given-names>L. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Lund</surname>, <given-names>M. N.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Effect of white grape extract and modified atmosphere packaging on lipid and protein oxidation in chill stored beef patties</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>128</volume>, <fpage>276</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>283</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2011.03.015</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25212132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Jongberg</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>T&#x000f8;rngren</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gunvig</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Skibsted</surname>, <given-names>L. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Lund</surname>, <given-names>M. N.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Effect of green tea or rosemary extract on protein oxidation in Bologna type sausages prepared from oxidatively stressed pork</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Meat Science</source>, <volume>93</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>538</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>546</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2012.11.005</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23273462</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Krintiras</surname>, <given-names>G. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>G&#x000f6;bel</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>van der Goot</surname>, <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Stefanidis</surname>, <given-names>G. D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Production of structured soy&#x02010;based meat analogues using simple shear and heat in a Couette Cell</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Engineering</source>, <volume>160</volume>, <fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2015.02.015</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chatli</surname>, <given-names>M. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mehta</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Singh</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Malav</surname>, <given-names>O. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Verma</surname>, <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Meat analogues: Health promising sustainable meat substitutes</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition</source>, <volume>57</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>923</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>932</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10408398.2014.939739</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yadav</surname>, <given-names>D. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ahmad</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Narsaiah</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Recent trends in the use of natural antioxidants for meat and meat products</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>796</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>812</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12156</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Lindenschmidt</surname>, <given-names>R. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tryka</surname>, <given-names>A. F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Goad</surname>, <given-names>M. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Witschi</surname>, <given-names>H. P.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>The effects of dietary butylated hydroxytoluene on liver and colon tumor development in mice</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Toxicology</source>, <volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>160</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0300-483X(86)90116-2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3945967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Lippi</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mattiuzzi</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Cervellin</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Meat consumption and cancer risk: A critical review of published meta&#x02010;analyses</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Critical Reviews in Oncology Hematology</source>, <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>1735</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.critrevonc.2015.11.008</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Lorenzo</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pateiro</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dom&#x000ed;nguez</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Barba</surname>, <given-names>F. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Putnik</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kova&#x0010d;evi&#x00107;</surname>, <given-names>D. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x02026; <string-name>
<surname>Franco</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Berries extracts as natural antioxidants in meat products: A review</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Research International</source>, <volume>106</volume>, <fpage>1095</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1104</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2017.12.005</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29579903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>Lund</surname>, <given-names>M. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Heinonen</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Baron</surname>, <given-names>C. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Est&#x000e9;vez</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Protein oxidation in muscle foods: A review</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Molecular Nutrition and Food Research</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mnfr.201000453</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21207515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Mafra</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Borges</surname>, <given-names>N. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cardozo</surname>, <given-names>L. F. M. d. F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Anjos</surname>, <given-names>J. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Black</surname>, <given-names>A. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Moraes</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x02026; <string-name>
<surname>Stenvinkel</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Red meat intake in chronic kidney disease patients: Two sides of the coin</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Nutrition</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nut.2017.08.015</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29290351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Maqsood</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Benjakul</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Balange</surname>, <given-names>A. K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Effect of tannic acid and kiam wood extract on lipid oxidation and textural properties of fish emulsion sausages during refrigerated storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>130</volume>, <fpage>408</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>416</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2011.07.065</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0032">
<string-name>
<surname>Mattila</surname>, <given-names>P. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hellstr&#x000f6;m</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Karhu</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pihlava</surname>, <given-names>J.&#x02010;M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Vetel&#x000e4;inen</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>High variability in flavonoid contents and composition between different North&#x02010;European currant (<italic>Ribes</italic> spp.) varieties</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>204</volume>, <fpage>14</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.02.056</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26988470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0033">
<string-name>
<surname>Moreno</surname>, <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>L&#x000f3;pez&#x02010;Berenguer</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Garc&#x000ed;a&#x02010;Viguera</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Effects of stir&#x02010;fry cooking with different edible oils on the phytochemical composition of broccoli</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Science</source>, <volume>72</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>S064</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S068</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1750-3841.2006.00213.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17995900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0034">
<string-name>
<surname>Moyo</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Oyedemi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Masika</surname>, <given-names>P. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Muchenje</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Polyphenolic content and antioxidant properties of <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> leaf extracts and enzymatic activity of liver from goats supplemented with Moringa oleifera leaves/sunflower seed cake</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Meat Science</source>, <volume>91</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>447</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2012.02.029</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22465510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0035">
<string-name>
<surname>Oliver</surname>, <given-names>C. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ahn</surname>, <given-names>B. W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Moerman</surname>, <given-names>E. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Goldstein</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Stadtman</surname>, <given-names>E. R.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Age&#x02010;related changes in oxidized proteins</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Biological Chemistry</source>, <volume>262</volume>, <fpage>5488</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5491</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3571220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0036">
<string-name>
<surname>Palanisamy</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>T&#x000f6;pfl</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Aganovic</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Berger</surname>, <given-names>R. G.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Influence of iota carrageenan addition on the properties of soya protein meat analogues</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">LWT</source>, <volume>87</volume>, <fpage>546</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>552</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2017.09.029</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0037">
<string-name>
<surname>Palermo</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pellegrini</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Fogliano</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The effect of cooking on the phytochemical content of vegetables</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture</source>, <volume>94</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1057</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1070</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.6478</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24227349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0038">
<string-name>
<surname>Pan</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sun</surname>, <given-names>Q.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bernstein</surname>, <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Schulze</surname>, <given-names>M. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Manson</surname>, <given-names>J. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Willett</surname>, <given-names>W. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Hu</surname>, <given-names>F. B.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Red meat consumption and risk of type 2 diabetes: 3 cohorts of US adults and an updated meta&#x02010;analysis</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition</source>, <volume>94</volume>, <fpage>1088</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1096</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/ajcn.111.018978</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21831992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0039">
<string-name>
<surname>Ribeiro</surname>, <given-names>J. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Santos</surname>, <given-names>M. J. M. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Silva</surname>, <given-names>L. K. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pereira</surname>, <given-names>L. C. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Santos</surname>, <given-names>I. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>da Silva Lannes</surname>, <given-names>S. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Silva</surname>, <given-names>M. V.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Natural antioxidants used in meat products: A brief review</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Meat Science</source>, <volume>148</volume>, <fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>188</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2018.10.016</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30389412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0040">
<string-name>
<surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez&#x02010;Carpena</surname>, <given-names>J. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Morcuende</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Est&#x000e9;vez</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Avocado by&#x02010;products as inhibitors of color deterioration and lipid and protein oxidation in raw porcine patties subjected to chilled storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Meat Science</source>, <volume>89</volume>, <fpage>166</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>173</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2011.04.013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21555188</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0041">
<string-name>
<surname>Schillinga</surname>, <given-names>M. W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Phama</surname>, <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Williamsa</surname>, <given-names>J. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Xiongb</surname>, <given-names>Y. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dhowlaghara</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tolentinoa</surname>, <given-names>A. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Kin</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Changes in the physiochemical, microbial, and sensory characteristics of fresh pork sausage containing rosemary and green tea extracts during retail display</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Meat Science</source>, <volume>143</volume>, <fpage>199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>209</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2018.05.009</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29778983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0042">
<string-name>
<surname>Silva</surname>, <given-names>F. A. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Est&#x000e9;vez</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ferreira</surname>, <given-names>V. C. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Silva</surname>, <given-names>S. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lemos</surname>, <given-names>L. T. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ida</surname>, <given-names>E. I.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x02026; <string-name>
<surname>Madruga</surname>, <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Protein and lipid oxidations in jerky chicken and consequences on sensory quality</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">LWT</source>, <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>348</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2018.07.022</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0043">
<string-name>
<surname>Turgut</surname>, <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Soyer</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>I&#x0015f;&#x00131;k&#x000e7;&#x00131;</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Effect of pomegranate peel extract on lipid and protein oxidation in beef meatballs during refrigerated storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Meat Science</source>, <volume>116</volume>, <fpage>126</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>132</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2016.02.011</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26878610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0044">
<string-name>
<surname>Vuorela</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Salminen</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Makela</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kivikari</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Karonen</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Heinonen</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Effect of plant phenolics on protein and lipid oxidation in cooked pork meat patties</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>53</volume>, <fpage>8492</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8497</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf050995a</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16248543</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0045">
<string-name>
<surname>Xie</surname>, <given-names>J.&#x02010;H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dong</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nie</surname>, <given-names>S. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>Z. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shen</surname>, <given-names>M. Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Xie</surname>, <given-names>M. Y.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Extraction, chemical composition and antioxidant activity of flavonoids from <italic>Cyclocarya paliurus</italic> (Batal.) Iljinskaja leaves</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>186</volume>, <fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.06.106</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25976797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="fsn31013-cit-0046">
<string-name>
<surname>Xiong</surname>, <given-names>Y. L.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2000</year>). <chapter-title>Protein oxidation and implications for muscle foods quality</chapter-title> In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Decker</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Faustman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, &#x00026; <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lopez&#x02010;Bote</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (Eds.), <source xml:lang="en">Antioxidants in muscle foods</source> (pp. <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>111</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0047">
<string-name>
<surname>Yang</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Qiu</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yang</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ou</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Influences of stir&#x02010;frying and baking on flavonoid profile, antioxidant property, and hydroxymethylfurfural formation during preparation of blueberry&#x02010;filled pastries</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>287</volume>, <fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>175</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2019.02.053</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30857686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0048">
<string-name>
<surname>Ye</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Duncan</surname>, <given-names>S. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Eigel</surname>, <given-names>W. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>O&#x02019;Keefe</surname>, <given-names>S. F.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant activities of vine tea (<italic>Ampelopsis grossedentata</italic>) extract and its major component dihydromyricetin in soybean oil and cooked ground beef</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>172</volume>, <fpage>416</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>422</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.09.090</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25442572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0049">
<string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lin</surname>, <given-names>Y. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Leng</surname>, <given-names>X. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Huang</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>, <given-names>G. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Effect of sage (<italic>Salvia officinalis</italic>) on the oxidative stability of Chinese&#x02010;style sausage during refrigerated storage</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Meat Science</source>, <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>150</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2013.05.005</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23739264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31013-bib-0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31013-cit-0050">
<string-name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lai</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cao</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Guan</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cheang</surname>, <given-names>W. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x02026; <string-name>
<surname>Xiao</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Effects of domestic cooking process on the chemical and biological properties of dietary phytochemicals</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Trends in Food Science &#x00026; Technology</source>, <volume>85</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2019.01.004</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>