<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first successful induction of SE from the centaury leaf explants was reported by Filipović et al. [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] on media containing 
 <italic>N</italic>-(2-chloro-4-pyridyl)-
 <italic>N’</italic>-phenylurea (CPPU) and 2,4-D, applied together, where the embryogenic response increased with the increasing CPPU concentration. Synthetic urea-type cytokinin CPPU has a diverse morphogenic activity in different species [
 <xref rid="B63-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]; other tested PGRs with cytokinin activity—6-benzyladenine, kinetin, and thidiazuron—induced callus proliferation only [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. This combination of PGRs(CPPU + 2,4-D) induced somatic embryo formation in 
 <italic>Gentiana</italic> spp. leaf explants, as well [
 <xref rid="B43-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. When the centaury leaf explants are cultivated on CPPU and 2,4-D, the direction of morphogenesis depends on the light conditions: If the explants are cultivated in darkness, the indirect formation of somatic embryos (ISE) is the only process that occurs, but when the explants are kept in the light, the processes of ISE and indirect shoot development (ISD) proceeded simultaneously, and both were asynchronous [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Even though ISE can be isolated from other morphogenetic paths by culturing the explants in darkness, a higher frequency of embryogenic callus induction was obtained in the light. Thus, it can be concluded that in centaury leaf culture, light is an obligatory factor for the organogenesis, but also a factor that enhances ISE [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], which is in accordance with previous reports where light-induced SE in centaury suspension culture [
 <xref rid="B49-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], as well as the frequency of SE and the number of embryos per leaf explant of 
 <italic>Dendrobium</italic> [
 <xref rid="B64-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] and 
 <italic>Petiveria alliacea</italic> cultures [
 <xref rid="B46-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The developed somatic embryos originated from the leaf subepidermal cells [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
