<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We utilized a large (400 plots—187 plots met our criteria, see below) plant community dataset (PCAP) collected over a series of 4 years between 2010 and 2013 by Cleveland Metroparks to explore correlates of 
 <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> abundance (percent cover). Cleveland Metroparks encompasses &gt;23 000 acres with 18 reservations that are located within and surrounding the city of Cleveland, OH. The plots were established using the generalized random tessellation stratified design (
 <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Stevens and Olsen 2003</xref>), providing a spatially balanced random sample. Sampling procedure followed the North Carolina Vegetation Survey method (
 <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Peet 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2004
 </xref>) and plots were sampled from 11 June to 30 August. While 
 <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> and 
 <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> cover may be underestimated towards the end of the sampling season, plots were sampled in a geospatially balanced, stratified random sample to avoid systematic bias (
 <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Stevens and Olsen 2003</xref>). The plots that were sampled covered a 20 m × 50 m area, in which the percent cover of every plant species was recorded, as well as collecting soil samples for nutrient analysis. The presence or absence of earthworms was recorded by visual assessment, where plots with worms, castings and middens were coded as ‘present’. Field crews consisted of 2 teams with typically 4 crew members each. Each visual assessment was the responsibility of 2 crew members. Field crews received 4 weeks of complete protocol training including worm sampling prior to the start of the field season. That training included practice plots and ‘flip-flop’ assessments to ensure standardized calibration among crew members throughout the season. Because the assessment team dug a soil pit in the middle of the plot, measured leaf litter depth and humus depth at the centre of each intensive module while looking for worm evidence, and carefully removed the leaf litter in search of worm evidence, we are confident that the presence of invasive earthworms was accurately recorded (
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Loss 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2013
 </xref>). Many species of invasive earthworms are thus included in the field assessment, including but not limited to 
 <italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic>. We collected about 250 mL of soil for each plot within 10 cm of the soil surface with a soil probe. Soil samples were stored at room temperature for up to 3 months before sending to A&amp;L Great Lakes Laboratories (Fort Wayne, IN). Soil was tested for phosphorus (ppm) and nitrogen (% total). Extractable phosphorus can be broken down into two different forms, phosphorus 1 (‘weak Bray’) and phosphorus 2 (‘strong Bray’). The more commonly used measurement is phosphorus 1, which was developed to correlate with plant-available phosphorus fraction of the soil in slightly acidic soils (
 <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Tandon 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 1967
 </xref>). The phosphorus 1 test corresponds with how much phosphorus is available to plants. The phosphorus 2 test gives total soil phosphorus. If there is a big gap between these two numbers, that means much of the phosphorus in the soil is unavailable to plants.
</p>
