<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In general, anxiolytic drugs are intended to reduce anxiety or tension at doses which do not cause sedation or sleep. It is because oversedation, tremor, ataxia and confusion are the adverse effects much more common in patients consuming some anxiolytics drugs like benzodiazepines. Medicinal plants might produce its anxiolytic like activity without sedative effects at certain doses. In our study, to explore ambulatory and exploratory activities in mice at several doses was very important in order to identify if anxiolytic-like response is associated to sedative effects and at what range of doses it will be produced. Literature has reported compounds from different chemical nature, such as non-polar and polar, as responsible for the depressant-like activity of these medicinal plants, but diterpenoids have been the most diverse metabolites characterized in 
 <italic>Salvia</italic> genus. According to their structure, these are classified into abietanes, labdanes, clerodanes, pimaranes and icetexanes. Biological activities, such as antimicrobial, antibacterial and cytotoxic, have been reported from these diterpenes (Wu et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). However, there are few studies which explore their effects on the CNS, specifically for 
 <italic>neo</italic>-clerodanes diterpenes (Moreno-Pérez et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The most studied case is salvinorin A, isolated from the leaves of 
 <italic>S. divinorum</italic>, which has been reported for its therapeutic effects on Alzheimer’s or bipolar disorders (Casselman et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), as well as sedative (Fantegrossi et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>), anxiolytic (Braida et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) and antinociceptive (McCurdy et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Guida et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) activities. Salvinorin A is known as an agonist of the kappa opioid receptors, but it also possesses a partial affinity for CB1 cannabinoid receptors (Braida et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). It shows similar chemical structure than compound 
 <bold>1</bold> and it is known to produce anxiolytic-like effects at doses of 0.1, 1.0, 40, 80 or 160 μg/kg, s.c. in the plus-maze test, without effects on the ambulatory activity of mice tested at 0.01, 0.1 and 1 μg/kg, s.c., probably because of the use of a lower dosage. We have not explored mechanism of action in the present study. However, to know the doses in which an anxiolytic drug produces its effects without sedation is very important since both sedative and anxiolytic drugs produce CNS inhibitory effects. Activation of the kappa opioid receptor relieves pain, but it is also associated to dysphoria (feeling of discomfort or aversion) and sedation (McDonald and Lambert 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Whereas, it has been reported that a mild activation of CB1 receptors in the prefrontal cortex and ventral hippocampus attenuates anxiety (Rubino et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). In the future, it will be interesting to explore about the mechanisms of action of compound 
 <bold>1</bold> to produce its CNS depressant effects.
</p>
