<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6162297</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">32622</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-32622-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Vapour-Vapour Interface Observation and Appraisement of a Gas-Condensate/Supercritical CO<sub>2</sub> System</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><address><email>jiaying.syky@sinopec.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Yunqing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Lei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Jin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Rongchen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Lei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Exploration and Production Research Institute, Sinopec, Beijing 100083 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1793 5814</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418531.a</institution-id><institution>Research Institute of Petroleum Exploration and Development, </institution></institution-wrap>PetroChina, Beijing 100083 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>South West Petroleum University, Chengdu, 610500 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>14510</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Injecting supercritical CO<sub>2</sub> into gas reservoir is a novel trial to improve condensate gas recovery and decrease the hydrocarbon liquid dropout. A good understanding of the effect of supercritical CO<sub>2</sub> on the phase behavior properties of these hydrocarbons is essential for accurately forecasting the displacing performance and storing process of the reservoirs with numerical simulators. This paper presents novel phase behavior experimental procedures and phase equilibrium evaluation methodology for gas-condensate phase system mixed with supercritical CO<sub>2</sub> over a wide range of temperatures and pressures. A unique phase behavior phenomena was also reported. The mass transfer between two vapour phases was also measured. In order to interpret and identify the interface property between condensate gas and supercritical CO<sub>2</sub>, a multiphase thermodynamic VLV equilibrium model was established. Finally, taken YKL condensate gas in Northwest China as an example, the region where the conditions in terms of pressure, temperature and CO<sub>2</sub> concentration can yield VLV equilibrium was found. The calculation results of multiphase thermodynamic model for condensate-CO<sub>2</sub> system in this paper are close to the experimental data and can truthfully reflect the phase behavior of interface between CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas. The research results indicate that it is the existence of the interface between CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas that makes CO<sub>2</sub> possible be an attractive option to successfully displace condensate gas and decrease CO<sub>2</sub> emissions.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>National Key Science &#x00026;amp; Technology Special Projects of China (No. 2016ZX05048003) and the Key Program Foundation of Sinopec (No. P15031)</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Today, there is a wider energy mix that allow us to meet the energy demand however fossil fuels are the leading source of energy. Statistics show that natural gas currently provides approximately a quarter of the world&#x02019;s energy and its share is increasing significantly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. The rapid increase in the worldwide demand of natural gas has resulted in a significant growth of international gas trade and stimulated long-term contracts for its sales. Hence, it becomes important to extend the lifetime of these reservoirs and meet the desired production rates.</p><p id="Par3">Generally, natural gas resources are mainly distributed in dry gas and condensate gas reservoirs. As an essential part of Sinopec (China Petroleum &#x00026; Chemical Corporation) in China&#x02019;s hydrocarbon resources, the recovery of condensate gas is still low (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Currently, most of the condensate gas resources that have been discovered in China are distributed in Xinjiang province and offshore, of which saturated condensate content are middle-low<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. The typical development method is under primary depletion. However, the recovery of condensate gas is only around 40% and some reservoirs have entered middle/late development periods. It is necessary to explore new techniques to improve condensate gas recovery.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The statistics of recovery of different condensate gas fields<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Gas field</th><th>Country</th><th>Geological Structure</th><th>Lithology</th><th>porosity (%)</th><th>permeability (mD)</th><th>Gas recovery (%)</th><th>Oil Recovery (%)</th><th>Development method</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>QL.</td><td>Russia</td><td>Anticline</td><td>sandstone</td><td>6&#x02013;24</td><td>8.8&#x02013;391.84</td><td>95</td><td/><td>Depletion</td></tr><tr><td>Kov.</td><td>Russia</td><td/><td>sandstone</td><td>5.4</td><td>1&#x02013;100</td><td>65</td><td/><td>Depletion</td></tr><tr><td>Min.</td><td>Russia</td><td>Anticline</td><td>sandstone</td><td>11.3</td><td>0.098&#x02013;34.1</td><td>77.9</td><td/><td>Depletion</td></tr><tr><td>&#x00411; yrra-m-ope</td><td>Azerbaijan</td><td>Anticline</td><td>sandstone</td><td>14&#x02013;18</td><td>0.03</td><td>78.05</td><td>33.38</td><td>Depletion</td></tr><tr><td>J-E-B</td><td>USA</td><td>Faults and conformity trap</td><td>sandstone</td><td>27.4&#x02013;33.6</td><td>200&#x02013;1800</td><td>80</td><td>50</td><td>Cyclic Injection</td></tr><tr><td>N. Geragai G40</td><td>India</td><td>Dome</td><td>sandstone</td><td>20&#x02013;27.5</td><td>18&#x02013;900</td><td/><td/><td>Depletion</td></tr><tr><td>BZBII</td><td>China</td><td>Anticline</td><td>sandstone</td><td>23.4</td><td>240.63</td><td>48</td><td/><td>Depletion</td></tr><tr><td>YH</td><td>China</td><td>Anticline</td><td>sandstone</td><td>15.4</td><td>51.1</td><td>67</td><td>54.7</td><td>Cyclic injection</td></tr><tr><td>KKY</td><td>China</td><td>Anticline</td><td>sandstone</td><td>9&#x02013;18</td><td>5.5&#x02013;126</td><td>59</td><td>39.2</td><td>Cyclic injection</td></tr><tr><td>QK (Sinopec)</td><td>China</td><td>Fault Block</td><td>sandstone</td><td>10.8</td><td>1.1</td><td>9.01</td><td/><td>Depletion</td></tr><tr><td>BM (Sinopec)</td><td>China</td><td>Fault Block</td><td>sandstone</td><td>11</td><td>0.1&#x02013;6</td><td>22.22</td><td/><td>Depletion</td></tr><tr><td>YK (Sinopec)</td><td>China</td><td>Anticline</td><td>sandstone</td><td>12.5</td><td>88.7</td><td>43</td><td>37.92</td><td>Depletion</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par4">The low recovery is due to complex physical and chemical phase transitions in condensate gas reservoirs. Different from dry gas reservoir, a liquid hydrocarbon phase called condensate is formed when the reservoir pressure around production wells drops below the dew point pressure in gas condensate formations. The liquid accumulates and occupies the pore space that otherwise would be available for gas flow, impeding the gas flow.</p><p id="Par5">Supercritical carbon dioxide (SC-CO<sub>2</sub>) injection into gas reservoirs is considered to be a promising technology that will bring long-term mutual benefits for coupled increased productivity and CO<sub>2</sub> geosequestration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. CO<sub>2</sub> Enhanced Gas Recovery (EGR) has been studied in laboratory settings and in field-scale simulations for both tight and conventional gas reservoirs, but application in the field remains limited to a handful of cases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">Excessive mixing is a key risk associated with CO<sub>2</sub> EGR as it would result in undesirable contamination of the natural gas asset and/or early breakthrough of the injected CO<sub>2</sub> at the production wells. This risk of excessive mixing of CO<sub>2</sub> and natural gas within the reservoir has limited the practice of EGR. At present, rare literature reported the mix phenomena between CO<sub>2</sub> and natural gas under reservoir conditions and clearly revealed under what kind of conditions natural gas is not easy to be mixed by CO<sub>2</sub>. Therefore, finding suitable gas injection conditions is the key to the promotion of EGR in suitable gas fields.</p><p id="Par7">Although, CO<sub>2</sub> flooding has been discussed in dry gas reservoirs, still, it has complex challenges in condensate reservoirs. One challenge is how to enhance condensate recovery; Another challenge is how to enhance condensate gas recovery. Previous research related to enhancing recovery of condensate gas field by injecting CO<sub>2</sub> has until now focused on boosting condensate recovery. For this reason, the studied fluid of most reservoirs has been high-condensate content. Plenty of studies have been conducted to discuss the physical and chemical processes when CO<sub>2</sub> contact with condensate liquid. These experimental data revealed the possibility of improving condensate by CO<sub>2</sub> flooding and can be utilized to validate the numerical studies in modeling tools. For example, JJ Chaback <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, Ahmed <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, E. Shtepani<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, and RM Ramharack<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> observed the density and composition of CO<sub>2</sub> in the process of retrograde evaporation of condensate oil through PVT experiment, and approved that CO<sub>2</sub> can inhibit condensate precipitation and move condensate<sub>.</sub> Their studies indicated that the dew point drops, the liquid-volume percent (liquid saturation) decreases, the compressibility factor falls and the two-phase envelope diagram shrinks with the increase of CO<sub>2</sub> composition. All these trends showed the positive impact of CO<sub>2</sub> have on liquid recovery. Mill&#x000e1;n A E <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> and Al-Abri <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> quantitatively studied the condensate recovery and relative permeability with long core experiment and numerical simulation. Research showed that injecting SC-CO<sub>2</sub> can decrease capillary instability, improve mobility ratio, delay the breakthrough time of gas injection and improve the condensate sweep efficiency. Heron GM <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> and Taheri A <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> carried out experimental study of injecting CO<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>2</sub> and dry gas into fractured gas condensate reservoir. They came to conclusions opposed to each other.</p><p id="Par8">However, there has been little investigation on how CO<sub>2</sub> mix with condensate gas and whether CO<sub>2</sub> can improve the recovery of condensate gas, despite these numerous studies on mitigating condensate precipitation and enhancing oil recovery by CO<sub>2</sub> flooding. In fact, condensate gas reservoirs produce both condensate gas and condensate, and both have high profits. In order to elucidate the possibility of CO<sub>2</sub> EGR in condensate gas reserovirs, a series of experiments and model were used to analyze mixing procedure when CO<sub>2</sub> contact with condensate gas. The focus of this research is to demonstrate under what kind of conditions in terms of pressure, temperature and CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas are not easily mixed into one phase.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Experiment</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Experiment materials</title><p id="Par9">The condensate gas from Well YK1, located at north of China is composed of 87.368% methane, 3.570% ethane and 0.718% propane etc. CO<sub>2</sub> has purity up to 99.95%. The physical properties of condensate gas are listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. The experimental conditions are that in the YKL gas reservoir (at 43.5&#x02009;MPa and 132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary of YKL condensate gas used in the experiments.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Component</th><th align="left">Composition mol%</th><th align="left">component</th><th align="left">Composition mol%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>CO<sub>2</sub></td><td>1.290</td><td>nC<sub>5</sub></td><td>0.156</td></tr><tr><td>N<sub>2</sub></td><td>3.389</td><td>C<sub>6</sub></td><td>0.504</td></tr><tr><td>C<sub>1</sub></td><td>87.368</td><td>C<sub>7</sub></td><td>0.677</td></tr><tr><td>C<sub>2</sub></td><td>3.570</td><td>C<sub>8</sub></td><td>0.429</td></tr><tr><td>C<sub>3</sub></td><td>0.718</td><td>C<sub>9</sub></td><td>0.390</td></tr><tr><td>iC<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.161</td><td>C<sub>10</sub></td><td>0.295</td></tr><tr><td>nC<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.212</td><td>C<sub>11+</sub></td><td>0.694</td></tr><tr><td>iC<sub>5</sub></td><td>0.146</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">C<sub>11+</sub> molecular</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">199.5563</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">C<sub>11+</sub> relative density</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">0.8429</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Formation Volume Factor</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">1.0862</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Oil density (0.101&#x02009;MPa, 20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">0.7769&#x02009;g/cm<sup>3</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Condensate pressure</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">15.00&#x02009;MPa</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Formation pressure(MPa)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">43.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Temperature (&#x000b0;C)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">132.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Dew pressure (MPa)</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">37.62</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Experimental apparatus</title><p id="Par10">To observe and calibrate how CO<sub>2</sub> mix with condensate gas, we set up a non-equilibrium experiment with high-pressure and high-temperature laboratory. A schematic of the experimental setup is presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. A mercury-free DBR (Donald B. Robinson Company) PVT cell was used to study the phase behavior properties of the fluid samples. A transparent cylinder sapphire cell with a volume of approximately 150&#x02009;ml and a maximum working pressure of 70&#x02009;MPa at 200&#x02009;&#x000b0;C was one of the most important parts of the experimental system. A half cone piston in cylinder cell can closely calibrate the fluid change in the experiment. The test fluid sample was placed in the cell by pushing a Ruska pump connected to the top of the cell. The volume of the injected sample was monitored by a cathetometer. Incandescent lamp, which was filled with hydrogen and N<sub>2</sub>, was placed at the opposite side of the sapphire cell to observe the change of the transmittance of the system. Fluid phase change in PVT cell was recorded via the computer video acquisition camera.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of the experimental apparatus. (<bold>a</bold>) Is the overall schematic diagram of the experimental apparatus; (<bold>b</bold>) is transparent cylinder sapphire cell.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1083"/></fig></p><p id="Par11">Before the experiments, the sapphire cell was dismounted from the apparatus, washed with distilled water and dried, and then installed back into the apparatus. Subsequently, the cell was evacuated to ensure the absence of air. The desired temperature was set through the temperature chamber. After that, the right amount of the sample that was equilibrated without condensate was prepared to be injected into the sapphire cell at desired conditions of pressure and temperature.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Non-equilibrium phase measurement of CO<sub>2</sub> mixed with condensate gas</title><p id="Par12">Usually, it is difficult to survey the mixing process of CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas in experiments through visual observation, because CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas are both transparent. Inspired from the critical opalescence of CO<sub>2</sub>, critical opalescence is used to distinguish CO<sub>2</sub> from condensate gas in these experiments. Critical opalescence is a striking light scattering phenomenon, which was elegantly explained by Einstein. In the critical region the light scattering is so large that the substance appears milky white in reflected light and brownish dark in transmitted light. The phenomenon arises from the large fluctuations in the critical region of the substance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. CO<sub>2</sub> critical phenomenon around the critical temperature and pressure was reported in many literatures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The critical temperature is 31&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and critical pressure is 7.53&#x02009;Mpa. However, the pressure and temperature of reservoir conditions are much higher than the critical pressure and critical temperature of CO<sub>2</sub>. No reports were mentioned about opalescence or density fluctuation of CO<sub>2</sub> existed in high temperature and high pressure, which is far away from critical pressure and temperature.</p><p id="Par13">The non-equilibrium phase measurements are aimed at finding the existence conditions of opalescence of CO<sub>2</sub> over a wide range of temperatures and pressure, and characterizing the mix characteristic of CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas at specific pressures and temperatures.</p><p id="Par14">In the experiment, starting from a high pressure, it is gradually depressurized in the sapphire cell to observe physical changes through the glass window into the cell. Three different tests conducted: (1) Pressure and temperature search to find the opalescence of CO<sub>2</sub> existence conditions; (2) Characterization of CO<sub>2</sub> mixing with condensate gas; (3) Diffusion test of the system of condensate gas and SC-CO<sub>2</sub> with high temperature.</p><sec id="Sec6"><title>Pressure and temperature search to find the opalescence of CO<sub>2</sub> existence conditions</title><p id="Par15">When the temperature was kept constant, the pressure search method was used to determine the CO<sub>2</sub> opalescence existence conditions. The first step was to pump CO<sub>2</sub> into sapphire cell at reservoir temperature (132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) and pressure (43.5&#x02009;MPa). Then, pressure reduced from 43.5&#x02009;MPa to 18&#x02009;MPa, and CO<sub>2</sub> status in sapphire cell was recorded every 3&#x02009;minutes. To confirm the accuracy of the onset and end of the pressure of appearance and disappearance of opalescence CO<sub>2</sub>, three repetitive tests by increasing and decreasing the pressure around the appearance and disappearance of opalescence CO<sub>2</sub> were preformed. Similar to the pressure search method, the temperature search method was used.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Characterization of CO<sub>2</sub> mixing with condensate gas</title><p id="Par16">Based on the pressure and temperature range at which CO<sub>2</sub> displayed opalescence phase behavior, the pressure and temperature used to test the mixing of CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas were selected. Then at specific temperature and pressure, injecting condensate gas from the top of sapphire cell steadily, took photos of the SC-CO<sub>2</sub>-condensate gas every five seconds from the visualization window.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Diffusion test of the system of condensate gas and SC-CO<sub>2</sub> with high temperature</title><p id="Par17">One group of temperature and pressure where CO<sub>2</sub> appear opalescence phenomena were chosen. After the system standing for 30&#x02009;minute, gas was discharge from sapphire cell with no pressure fluctuation. And their composition of different parts was measured with cathetometer.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="results"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Experiment Results</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Pressure and temperature search to find the opalescence of CO<sub>2</sub> existence conditions</title><p id="Par18">Obvious phase changes of CO<sub>2</sub> was recorded when pressure drops from 25&#x02009;MPa to18MPa at 132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>CO<sub>2</sub> in PVT cell with vertical direction (132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1228"/></fig></p><p id="Par19">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2(1) and (2)</xref> shows that under the temperature and pressure of the gas reservoir (132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C 43.5Mpa), the initial state of CO<sub>2</sub> behaves like fluid with high density and stable physical properties. It is a kind of &#x0201c;liquid-like&#x0201d; supercritical fluid with the same light transmittance in the whole system. When the pressure drops to 25&#x02009;MPa, CO<sub>2</sub> opalescence appears in reservoir temperature for the first time (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2(3)</xref>). When the pressure drops continually, CO<sub>2</sub> continues presenting opalescence phenomena in sapphire cell until 18Mpa (from Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2(3) to (9)</xref>). When the pressure reaches to 18&#x02009;MPa, opalescence phenomenon disappears and light transmittance increases significantly (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2(10)</xref>).</p><p id="Par20">Similar phase changes of CO<sub>2</sub> was recorded when temperature drops from 132&#x02009;&#x000b0;C to 8&#x02009;&#x000b0;C at 30&#x02009;MPa (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>CO<sub>2</sub> in PVT cell with vertical direction (30&#x02009;MPa).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1272"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Distribution characterization of CO<sub>2</sub> mixed with condensate gas</title><p id="Par21">The pressures to test the mixing of CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas were selected based on above pressure search experiments. 25Mpa was chosen as experiment pressure for mixing CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas. Keep the temperature of this system in 132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Injecting condensate gas from the top of sapphire cell containing CO<sub>2</sub> steadily, photographs of SC-CO<sub>2</sub>-condensate gas from the visualization window were recorded very five seconds.</p><p id="Par22">The unequilirium experiment of CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas snapshots revealed that obvious phase behavior change between CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas at 25Mpa and 132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). First the pure CO<sub>2</sub> in the PVT cell, with weak background light source, was chosen as the basic condition before injecting condensate gas (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4(1)</xref>). At this point, CO<sub>2</sub> stays in opalescence state with high density. After starting to inject condensate gas from the top of PVT cell, condensate gas looks like bright light appears at the top of CO<sub>2</sub>, which shows injected condensate gas has good transmittance. There is no obvious difference of the phase and physical characteristic between condensate gas and supercritical CO<sub>2</sub> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4(2 and 3)</xref>). After keeping injecting condensate gas from the top of PVT cell, there is convection diffusion and mass transfer between condensate gas and CO<sub>2</sub>. As condensate gas was injected from the top continually, the layer between two fluids with dark color appears. Similar to the phenomena near critical region reported in literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, even temperature and pressure far away from critical point, these domains are dynamic and fluctuate strongly when the layer is between two fluids; we capture them immobilized during the transfer process(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4(4 and 5)</xref>). After keeping injecting condensate gas from the top of PVT cell, the layer between CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas becomes clear (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4(6~10)</xref>). Continuing injecting condensate gas from the top of sapphire cell, the layer between CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas shrinks and then contracts to a bright yellow opaque. There exists transparent uniform condensate gas on the top and transparent supercritical CO<sub>2</sub> phase at the bottom (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4(11 and 12)</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Unequilirium experiment of CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas graph in vertical direction (from left to right condensate gas injected from above continually at 25&#x02009;MPa 132. 18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1361"/></fig></p><p id="Par23">Similar phenomena were also recorded at 22&#x02009;MPa and 20&#x02009;MPa.</p><p id="Par24">The temperatures to test the mixing of CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas were selected based on above temperature search experiments. Similar phenomena about mixing of CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas were also recorded at 100&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 50&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C.</p><p id="Par25">The experimental data with the onset and end pressure of layer appearance with different temperature, pressure and CO<sub>2</sub> mole percentage were listed in Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. When temperature drops from 132&#x02009;&#x000b0;C to 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, there is more possibility of the layer existed between CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas. From 132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C to 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, there is a gradual declined reduction in the end pressure of layer, reaching a figure of 7.5 Mpa.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The onset pressure of layer appearance (MPa).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>CO<sub>2</sub>(mol%)</th><th rowspan="2">10</th><th rowspan="2">20</th><th rowspan="2">30</th><th rowspan="2">40</th><th rowspan="2">50</th><th rowspan="2">60</th><th rowspan="2">70</th><th rowspan="2">80</th><th rowspan="2">90</th></tr><tr><th>TEMP (&#x000b0;C)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>132.18</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>28.79</td><td>25.47</td><td>24.97</td><td>20.77</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td>100</td><td/><td>34.56</td><td>30.76</td><td>29.74</td><td>25.43</td><td>22.81</td><td>20.14</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td>50</td><td/><td>36.33</td><td>32.49</td><td>28.91</td><td>25.48</td><td>23.46</td><td>18.81</td><td>15.51</td><td>11.29</td></tr><tr><td>30</td><td>38.70</td><td>38</td><td>36.05</td><td>28.00</td><td>24.37</td><td>20.58</td><td>17.81</td><td>12.97</td><td>10.50</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The end pressure of layer (MPa).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>CO<sub>2</sub> (mol%)</th><th rowspan="2">10</th><th rowspan="2">20</th><th rowspan="2">30</th><th rowspan="2">40</th><th rowspan="2">50</th><th rowspan="2">60</th><th rowspan="2">70</th><th rowspan="2">80</th><th rowspan="2">90</th></tr><tr><th>TEMP (&#x000b0;C)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>132.18</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>25.46</td><td>19</td><td>18</td><td>20</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td>100</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>33.56</td><td>20</td><td>14</td><td>12</td><td>14</td><td>19</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td>50</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>18</td><td>12.29</td><td>10.5</td><td>9</td><td>10</td><td>10</td><td>11</td><td>12.29</td></tr><tr><td>30</td><td>16</td><td>11</td><td>8.89</td><td>7.5</td><td>7.5</td><td>7.5</td><td>7.5</td><td>7.5</td><td>7.5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Diffusion test of the system of condensate gas and SC-CO<sub>2</sub> with high temperature</title><p id="Par26">To perform a detailed assessment of the spatial distribution of CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas and discuss interface property, the diffusion test was carried out with the composition analysis of 10 equal division subdomains based on pressure search experiment. Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> shows the composition of different subdomains in Sapphire cell containing condensate gas and CO<sub>2</sub> when pressure is 25&#x02009;MPa and temperature is 132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, after mix experiment was stood still for 30&#x02009;minutes. The gas was discharged and tested with cathetometer. Composition shows that domain 1&#x02013;3 is primarily composed of condensate gas. Domain 4 to 6 see a dramatic rise of CO<sub>2</sub> content rise and changed from 3.519 to 86%; a considerable decrease of the C<sub>2</sub>~C<sub>6</sub> content occurs from 5.39% to 1.95%; as for the domain 6 to 9, the content of compositions remain still. Thus, compared with the composition of different domains, the interface between condensate gas and CO<sub>2</sub> locate at domain 4&#x02013;5, which means that the composition of interface may be a compound of CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas. Based on the definition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>, the layer between condensate gas and CO<sub>2</sub> is also called interface. Aforementioned conclusion needs further investigation.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Composition measure in PVT cell. (<bold>a</bold>) Snapshot of mixing fluid in PVT cell that is divided into 10 equal division subdomains. (<bold>b</bold>) CO<sub>2</sub> content of different domains (<bold>c</bold>) C<sub>2&#x02013;6</sub> content of different domains.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1815"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>The composition of gas condensate and supercritical CO<sub>2</sub> at different domains.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Domain</th><th rowspan="2">(1)</th><th rowspan="2">(2)</th><th rowspan="2">(3)</th><th rowspan="2">(4)</th><th rowspan="2">(5)</th><th rowspan="2">(6)</th><th rowspan="2">(7)</th><th rowspan="2">(8)</th><th rowspan="2">(9)</th></tr><tr><th>Composition (mol%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>CO<sub>2</sub></td><td>1.291</td><td>1.291</td><td>1.291</td><td>3.549</td><td>62.65</td><td>83.652</td><td>86.432</td><td>86.126</td><td>86.659</td></tr><tr><td>N<sub>2</sub></td><td>3.477</td><td>3.477</td><td>3.477</td><td>3.218</td><td>1.82</td><td>1.686</td><td>1.475</td><td>1.823</td><td>1.534</td></tr><tr><td>C<sub>1</sub></td><td>89.624</td><td>89.624</td><td>89.624</td><td>87.842</td><td>32.957</td><td>12.718</td><td>10.312</td><td>10.218</td><td>9.951</td></tr><tr><td>C<sub>2</sub></td><td>3.662</td><td>3.662</td><td>3.662</td><td>3.688</td><td>1.747</td><td>1.274</td><td>1.204</td><td>1.192</td><td>1.201</td></tr><tr><td>C<sub>3</sub></td><td>0.737</td><td>0.737</td><td>0.737</td><td>1.076</td><td>0.539</td><td>0.389</td><td>0.373</td><td>0.372</td><td>0.379</td></tr><tr><td>IC<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.165</td><td>0.165</td><td>0.165</td><td>0.131</td><td>0.059</td><td>0.051</td><td>0.046</td><td>0.046</td><td>0.049</td></tr><tr><td>NC<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.217</td><td>0.217</td><td>0.217</td><td>0.29</td><td>0.12</td><td>0.117</td><td>0.113</td><td>0.113</td><td>0.115</td></tr><tr><td>IC<sub>5</sub></td><td>0.150</td><td>0.150</td><td>0.150</td><td>0.012</td><td>0.011</td><td>0.009</td><td>0.008</td><td>0.008</td><td>0.009</td></tr><tr><td>NC<sub>5</sub></td><td>0.160</td><td>0.160</td><td>0.160</td><td>0.066</td><td>0.028</td><td>0.031</td><td>0.03</td><td>0.03</td><td>0.03</td></tr><tr><td>C<sub>6</sub></td><td>0.517</td><td>0.517</td><td>0.517</td><td>0.127</td><td>0.069</td><td>0.074</td><td>0.007</td><td>0.073</td><td>0.073</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Interface property analysis</title><sec id="Sec15"><title>Interface property at 132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C</title><p id="Par27">The onset pressure of layer/interface appearance: In the experiment, when the temperature is 132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, the onset pressure of interface appearance is 25&#x02009;MPa when 50&#x02009;mol% of CO<sub>2</sub> mixes with of 50&#x02009;mol% condensate gas. The PR equation of state, which was fitted to experiment data, was used for two-phase flashing calculation under different experimental conditions. The calculation results are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>. From the results, it can be seen that when the pressure is 25&#x02009;MPa, the system with 50&#x02009;mol% of condensate gas and 50&#x02009;mol% of CO<sub>2</sub> begin be condensed, which corresponds to the onset pressure of the interface. Therefore, it is believed that there may be an interface when condensate is condensed in CO<sub>2</sub>-condensate gas system.<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Two-phase flash with different pressure (50% CO<sub>2</sub>, 50% Condensate Gas Temperature 132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Pressure, MPa</th><th align="left">Oil Viscosity cp</th><th align="left">Gas Viscosity cp</th><th align="left">Gas Z-factor</th><th align="left">Oil Z-factor</th><th align="left">IFT dyn/cm</th><th align="left">Gas density</th><th align="left">Oil density</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>43.5</td><td/><td>0.0441</td><td>0.9872</td><td/><td/><td>426.89</td><td/></tr><tr><td>42</td><td/><td>0.043</td><td>0.9752</td><td/><td/><td>417.239</td><td/></tr><tr><td>40</td><td/><td>0.0416</td><td>0.9596</td><td/><td/><td>403.82</td><td/></tr><tr><td>38</td><td/><td>0.0401</td><td>0.9446</td><td/><td/><td>389.72</td><td/></tr><tr><td>36.07</td><td/><td>0.0386</td><td>0.9308</td><td/><td/><td>375.43</td><td/></tr><tr><td>35</td><td/><td>0.0378</td><td>0.9234</td><td/><td/><td>367.20</td><td/></tr><tr><td>30</td><td/><td>0.0339</td><td>0.8925</td><td/><td/><td>325.64</td><td/></tr><tr><td>25</td><td/><td>0.0300</td><td>0.8697</td><td/><td/><td>278.49</td><td/></tr><tr><td>24.97</td><td char="." align="char">0.296</td><td>0.0292</td><td>0.8663</td><td char="." align="char">1.2139</td><td char="." align="char">2.8472</td><td>268.03</td><td char="." align="char">786.78</td></tr><tr><td>24</td><td char="." align="char">0.298</td><td>0.0284</td><td>0.8639</td><td char="." align="char">1.1802</td><td char="." align="char">3.1018</td><td>257.64</td><td char="." align="char">786.90</td></tr><tr><td>23</td><td char="." align="char">0.300</td><td>0.0276</td><td>0.8619</td><td char="." align="char">1.1442</td><td char="." align="char">3.387</td><td>246.73</td><td char="." align="char">786.96</td></tr><tr><td>22</td><td char="." align="char">0.301</td><td>0.0268</td><td>0.8606</td><td char="." align="char">1.1069</td><td char="." align="char">3.696</td><td>235.65</td><td char="." align="char">786.93</td></tr><tr><td>21</td><td char="." align="char">0.303</td><td>0.0261</td><td>0.8598</td><td char="." align="char">1.0683</td><td char="." align="char">4.0303</td><td>224.43</td><td char="." align="char">786.82</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td char="." align="char">0.304</td><td>0.0254</td><td>0.8597</td><td char="." align="char">1.0283</td><td char="." align="char">4.3914</td><td>213.06</td><td char="." align="char">786.61</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td char="." align="char">0.306</td><td>0.0247</td><td>0.8603</td><td char="." align="char">0.987</td><td char="." align="char">4.7808</td><td>201.56</td><td char="." align="char">786.31</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td char="." align="char">0.307</td><td>0.0240</td><td>0.8615</td><td char="." align="char">0.9444</td><td char="." align="char">5.2002</td><td>189.95</td><td char="." align="char">785.92</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td char="." align="char">0.308</td><td>0.0234</td><td>0.8636</td><td char="." align="char">0.9004</td><td char="." align="char">5.6511</td><td>178.25</td><td char="." align="char">785.446</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td char="." align="char">0.309</td><td>0.0228</td><td>0.8663</td><td char="." align="char">0.8552</td><td char="." align="char">6.1352</td><td>166.49</td><td char="." align="char">784.9</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td char="." align="char">0.310</td><td>0.0222</td><td>0.8699</td><td char="." align="char">0.8088</td><td char="." align="char">6.6542</td><td>154.68</td><td char="." align="char">784.31</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td char="." align="char">0.311</td><td>0.0217</td><td>0.8742</td><td char="." align="char">0.7613</td><td char="." align="char">7.2102</td><td>142.85</td><td char="." align="char">783.73</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td char="." align="char">0.312</td><td>0.0212</td><td>0.8794</td><td char="." align="char">0.7128</td><td char="." align="char">7.8057</td><td>131.04</td><td char="." align="char">783.21</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td char="." align="char">0.314</td><td>0.0208</td><td>0.8853</td><td char="." align="char">0.6633</td><td char="." align="char">8.4436</td><td>119.27</td><td char="." align="char">782.84</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td char="." align="char">0.315</td><td>0.0204</td><td>0.8921</td><td char="." align="char">0.6131</td><td char="." align="char">9.1275</td><td>107.57</td><td char="." align="char">782.74</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td char="." align="char">0.318</td><td>0.0200</td><td>0.8996</td><td char="." align="char">0.5621</td><td char="." align="char">9.8618</td><td>95.97</td><td char="." align="char">783.07</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td char="." align="char">0.321</td><td>0.0196</td><td>0.908</td><td char="." align="char">0.5104</td><td char="." align="char">10.6518</td><td>84.51</td><td char="." align="char">784.02</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td char="." align="char">0.325</td><td>0.0193</td><td>0.9171</td><td char="." align="char">0.458</td><td char="." align="char">11.5041</td><td>73.2</td><td char="." align="char">785.81</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td char="." align="char">0.33</td><td>0.0191</td><td>0.9269</td><td char="." align="char">0.4047</td><td char="." align="char">12.4267</td><td>62.08</td><td char="." align="char">788.77</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td char="." align="char">0.337</td><td>0.0188</td><td>0.9374</td><td char="." align="char">0.35</td><td char="." align="char">13.4291</td><td>51.16</td><td char="." align="char">793.26</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td char="." align="char">0.345</td><td>0.0188</td><td>0.9486</td><td char="." align="char">0.2934</td><td char="." align="char">14.5228</td><td>40.45</td><td char="." align="char">799.786</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par28">The end pressure of layer/interface: However, with the decrease of pressure, the condensate content in the interface rise and the interfacial tension between CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate grows, and phase separation occurs. When the condensate in the interface is precipitated continuously, the interface disappears gradually due to the influence of gravity differentiation.</p><p id="Par29">In order to prove above idea, numerical simulation of slimtube in CO<sub>2</sub> drive condensate under different pressure was carried out to analyze the interfacial tension between CO<sub>2</sub> content and condensate.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Analysis of interfacial tension in rich CO<sub>2</sub> condensate</title><p id="Par30">The CO<sub>2</sub> mole percentage and interfacial tension were plotted for driving simulation of condensate. Dimensionless distance 0.375 is the CO<sub>2</sub> displacement front of in the displacement process of condensate, shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>. At the displacement front of CO<sub>2</sub>, there is low interfacial tension between CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate, which is about 0.6&#x02009;dyn/cm, when the pressure is 25&#x02009;MPa. With the pressure decreasing, the interfacial tension between CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate increases gradually (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Therefore, when the temperature is 132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and the pressure is 25&#x02009;MPa, CO<sub>2</sub> can mix with condensate and forms interface. But with the decrease of pressure, condensate in the interface is separated, and the interface begins to be unstable.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The simulated CO<sub>2</sub> mole percentage and Interfacial tension (25&#x02009;MPa 132.18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C). Dimensionless distance 0 represent injector and Dimensionless distance 1 represent producer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e2991"/></fig><fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>The simulated Interfacial tension with CO<sub>2</sub> mole percentage and pressure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e3003"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Density analysis</title><p id="Par31">The density of interface was calculated based on molar percentage of the condensate and CO<sub>2</sub>. At 132&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, the density of supercritical CO<sub>2</sub>, condensate gas and interface were plotted in the Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>. When the pressure is 24.97&#x02009;MPa, there is a stable density difference among three phases. With the pressure decreasing, the density of interface is closer to the density of supercritical CO<sub>2</sub>. When the pressure is below 10&#x02009;MPa, the densities of interface and condensate gas are exactly the same. Thus, in order to form a stable interface, it is considered that there is a certain density difference between the three phases.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>The density of three phases at different pressure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_Fig8_HTML" id="d29e3029"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Modeling Results</title><p id="Par32">Obtaining this experiment conditions including pressure, temperature and CO<sub>2</sub> concentration which can yield interface phenomena is a very labor intensive and time consuming process, especially when the components differ greatly from different gas fields. A possible solution to this problem is to develop a new approach to describe experimental data that would allow construction phase transition interface out of a limited data set. Such approach will make it possible to obtain not only reliable information on properties of mixtures, but also data on composition.</p><p id="Par33">Based on interface property analysis, novel mathematical model to model the interface phenomena during CO<sub>2</sub> mixing with condensate gas was established, in order to find the region where the conditions in terms of pressure, temperature and CO<sub>2</sub> concentration can yield VLV equilibrium containing interface, which is presented in Appendices.</p><sec id="Sec19"><title>Reliability of VLV calculation</title><p id="Par34">The accuracy of the calculations was evaluated by the absolute average relative deviation (AARD) defined as follows,<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\bf{AARD}}=\frac{{\bf{100}}}{{\bf{N}}}\sum _{{\bf{i}}={\bf{1}}}^{{\bf{N}}}\,\frac{|{{\bf{x}}}_{{\bf{i}}}^{{\bf{calc}}.}-{{\bf{x}}}_{{\bf{i}}}^{\exp {\boldsymbol{.}}}|}{{{\bf{x}}}_{{\bf{i}}}^{\exp {\boldsymbol{.}}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">AARD</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">100</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">N</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">calc</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">.</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">.</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par35">As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>, experimental pressures at which interface appear and disappear with different CO<sub>2</sub> mole percentage at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 50&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 100&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and 132&#x02009;&#x000b0;C were in well agreement with that calculated by the VLV model with AARD&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.41%, indicating that the VLV model in present work was reliable for interface envelop calculation.<fig id="Fig9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Comparison of Pressure of interface envelop of experiments and VLV model at 132&#x02009;&#x000b0;C over a CO<sub>2</sub> mole percentage range of 10&#x02013;95%.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_Fig9_HTML" id="d29e3148"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>PTX phase diagram of interface</title><p id="Par36">The PTX phase diagram of interface was drawn in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref> shows that the interface envelops looked like J column or &#x0201c;stomach&#x0201d;. At the temperatures above CO<sub>2</sub> critical temperature (31&#x02009;&#x000b0;C), interface occurs when CO<sub>2</sub> contact with condensate gas (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>). With the temperature rising, the up pressure and low pressure envelope of the interface increase gradually.<fig id="Fig10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>PTX phase diagram of interface.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_Fig10_HTML" id="d29e3178"/></fig><fig id="Fig11"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>PT phase diagram of interface.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_Fig11_HTML" id="d29e3187"/></fig></p><p id="Par37">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref> illustrates that when CO<sub>2</sub>, the content of which is between 10% and 82%, mix with condensate gas, the system shows interface characteristics in a certain pressure range; when the content of CO<sub>2</sub> is between 40 and 50&#x02009;mol%, a wide pressure range of interface appears in the system.<fig id="Fig12"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>PX phase diagram of interface.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_Fig12_HTML" id="d29e3207"/></fig></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par38">The following conclusions can be drawn from the current study:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par39">Measures show opalescence or density fluctuation of CO<sub>2</sub> in high temperature and high pressure. Opalescence phenomena of CO<sub>2</sub> in high temperature and high pressure was used to observe the mix process of CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas, which shows there is interface when CO<sub>2</sub> mix with condensate gas at high (reservoir) temperature.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par40">Thermodynamic characteristic analyses indicate the onset pressure of interface appearance between CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate gas is around dew pressure in the CO<sub>2</sub>-condensate system. With the pressure dropping, the condensate in the interface is precipitated continuously. The end pressure of interface appearance is related to gravity differentiation because of increase of the interfacial tension and phase separation between CO<sub>2</sub> and condensate.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par41">The multiphase thermodynamic model for condensate-CO<sub>2</sub> system in this paper can truthfully reflect the interface behavior during CO<sub>2</sub> injecting condensate gas over a wide range of temperatures and pressures, and calculation results of which are close to the experimental data.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par42">Our study provides the possibility to predict the enhanced condensate gas recovery with CO<sub>2</sub> injection with novel trial.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec22"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_32622_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Appendix A</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-32622-9.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank the National Key Science &#x00026; Technology Special Projects of China (No. 2016ZX05048003) and the Key Program Foundation of Sinopec (No. P15031) for providing financial support to this research work.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Ying Jia wrote the main manuscript text and carry out the experiments, Yunqing Shi guided the research and give suggestion to the whole research, Lei Huang established the Phase equilibrium model, Jin Yan and Rongchen Zheng carried out the experiments and prepared Figures 2&#x02013;7, and Lei Sun designed experiments and carried out the experiments</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">BP. Sustainability Report 2017, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bp.com/content/">https://www.bp.com/content/</ext-link> dam/bp/en/ corporate/pdf/sustainability-report/group-reports/bp-sustainability-report-2017.pdf (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Geological and distribution characteristics of condensate gas reservoir in China</article-title><source>Natural Gas Industry</source><year>1992</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Al-Hasami, A. <italic>et al</italic>. CO<sub>2</sub> Injection for enhanced gas recover and geo-storage: reservoir simulation and economics. Paper SPE 94129 presented at the SPE Europec/EAGE Annual Conference held in Madrid, Spain, 13&#x02013;16 June 2005).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Danesh, A. PVT and phase behavior of petroleum reservoir fluids. The Netherlands: Elsevier Science and Technology Books, 2003.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bondor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Applications of carbon dioxide in enhanced oil recovery</article-title><source>Energy Conversion and Management</source><year>1992</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0196-8904(92)90059-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sheng, P. P. &#x00026; Liao, X. W. The importance of carbon dioxide emission reduction and utilization, the first edition. The technology of carbon dioxide stored in geological media and enhanced oil recovery.<bold>1</bold>, 1&#x02013;4 (Beijing: Petroleum Industry Press, 2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oldenburg</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Process modeling of CO<sub>2</sub> injection into natural gas reservoirs for carbon sequestration and enhanced gas recovery</article-title><source>Energy Fuels</source><year>2001</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ef000247h</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Turta, A. T. <italic>et al</italic>. A basic investigation on enhanced gas recovery by gas-gas displacement. Paper 2007-124 presented at the Petroleum Society&#x02019;s 8th Canadian International Petroleum Conference held in Calgary, Alberta, Canada12&#x02013;14 June 2007).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li, S. L. <italic>et al</italic>. Introduction, first edition. The technology of Enhanced oil recovery with gas injection.<bold>1</bold>, 1&#x02013;25 (Chengdu: Sichuan Science and Technology Press, 2001).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EOR study of CO<sub>2</sub> injection</article-title><source>Special Oil &#x00026; Gas Reservoir</source><year>2007</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Potential Evaluation on CO<sub>2</sub>-EGR in tight and low permeability reservoirs</article-title><source>Natural Gas Industry</source><year>2017</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>69</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phase behavior of CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration and the enhanced natural gas recovery</article-title><source>Natural Gas Industry</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clancy</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of nitrogen-injection projects to develop screening guides and offshore design criteria</article-title><source>J. Petroleum Tech</source><year>1983</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1097</fpage><lpage>1104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2118/11902-PA</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Clemens, T. &#x00026; Wit, K. CO<sub>2</sub> Enhanced Gas Recovery Studied for an Example Gas Reservoir. Paper SPE 77348 presented at the SPE Annual Technical Conference and Exhibition held in San Antonio, Texas, 29 September- 2 October 2002).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Meer, L. G. H. <italic>et al</italic>. CO<sub>2</sub> storage and testing enhanced gas recovery in the K12-B reservoir. Paper presented at 23rd World Gas Conference, Amsterdam, 5&#x02013;9 June 2006).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Secklehner, S. <italic>et al</italic>. Tight Ultra-deep Gas Field Production Optimisation - Development Optimisation and CO<sub>2</sub> Enhanced Gas Recovery Potential of the Schoenkirchen Uebertief Gas Field, Austria. Paper SPE 130154 presented at SPE Deep Gas Conference and Exhibition held in Manama, Bahrain, 24&#x02013;26 Jan, Manama, Bahrain 2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chaback, J. J. &#x00026; Williams, M. L. P-x behavior of a rich-gas condensate in and mixture with CO<sub>2</sub> and (N<sub>2</sub>&#x02009;+&#x02009;CO<sub>2</sub>). Paper SPE24132 presented at the SPE DOE Eighth Symposium on Enhanced Oil Recovery held in Tulsa, Oklahoma, 22&#x02013;24 April 1992).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ahmed, T. <italic>et al</italic>. Wellbore liquid blockage in gas condensate reservoirs. Paper SPE 51050 presented at the 1998 SPE Eastern Regional Meeting held in Pittsburgh, PA, 9&#x02013;11 Nov. 1998).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shtepani, E. CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration in depleted gas/condensate reservoirs. Paper SPE102284 presented at the 2006 SPE Annual Technical Conference and Exhibition held in San Antonio, Texas, USA, 24&#x02013;27 September 2006).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ramharack, R. M. Impact of Carbon Dioxide Sequestration in Depleted Gas Condensate Reservoirs. <italic>West Virginia University Dissertation</italic> (2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mill&#x000e1;n, A. E. <italic>et al</italic>. A novel improved condensate-recovery method by cyclic supercritical CO<sub>2</sub> injection. Paper SPE 107283 presented at the 2007 SPE Latin American and Caribbean Petroleum Engineering Conference held in Buenos Aires, Argentina, 15&#x02013;18 April 2007).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Al-Abri, A. S. &#x00026; Amin, R. Enhanced natural gas and condensate recovery by injection of pure SCCO<sub>2</sub>, pure CH<sub>4</sub> and their mixtures: experimental investigation. Paper SPE124145 presented at SPE Annual Technical Conference and Exhibition, New Orleans, Louisiana, 4&#x02013;7 October 2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Abri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mobility ratio, relative permeability and sweep efficiency of supercritical CO<sub>2</sub> and methane injection to enhance natural gas and condensate recovery: Coreflooding experimentation</article-title><source>Journal of Natural Gas Science and Engineering</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jngse.2012.05.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Heron, G. M. <italic>et al</italic>. Armando, P. M. Laboratory tests with CO<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>2</sub> and lean natural gas in a naturally fractured gas&#x02014;condensate reservoir under HP/HT conditions. Paper SPE142855 presented at the SPE Enhanced Oil Recovery Conference held in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, 19&#x02013;21 July 2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Taheri, A. <italic>et al</italic>. Miscible and immiscible gas injection for enhancing of condensate recovery in fractured gas condensate reservoirs. Paper SPE164934 presented at EAGE Annual Conference &#x00026; Exhibition incorporating SPE Europec, London, UK, 10&#x02013;13 June 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gopal</surname><given-names>ESR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Critical Opalescence</article-title><source>Resonance</source><year>2000</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02837904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Critical phenomena: Fluctuations caught in the act</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>404</volume><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35006162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrabos</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rayleigh and Raman scattering near the critical point of carbon dioxide</article-title><source>The Journal of Chemical Physics</source><year>1980</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>4637</fpage><lpage>4651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.439706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vapor-liquid phase equilibrium behavior of mixtures containing supercritical carbon dioxide near critical region</article-title><source>J. of Supercritical Fluids</source><year>2008</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.supflu.2007.09.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhu, Z. Q. &#x00026; Wu, Y. T. Fluid phase equilibrium, third edition. Chemical Engineering Thermodynamics. <bold>8</bold>, 244&#x02013;295 (Beijing: Chemical Industry Press, 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li, G. Y. &#x00026; Tang, Y. W. World gas field, the first edition. World gas field map.<bold>1</bold>, 1&#x02013;95, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://wenku.baidu.com/view/b6d693ff51e79b8969022603.html?from=search">https://wenku.baidu.com/view/b6d693ff51e79b8969022603.html?from=search</ext-link> (Beijing: Petroleum Industry Press, 1984).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Status and Issues of Technologies for Development of Condensate Gas Pools</article-title><source>XinJiang Petroleum Geology</source><year>2002</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>591</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yuan, S. Y. <italic>et al</italic>. Practice and application of condensate gas fields in the world, the first edition. Theory and practice of high efficiency development of condensate gas reservoir.<bold>7</bold>, 199&#x02013;245 (Beijing: Petroleum Industry Press, 2003).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang, L. Z. Study on Potential Tapping with Horizontal well Technology in Baimiao Deep Condensate Reservoir. <italic>China University of Geosciences Dissertation</italic>.(2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recovery efficiency of condensate oil in Qiaokou Gas Reservoir</article-title><source>ACTA Petrolei Sinica</source><year>2005</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>77</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sun, L. D. Status of main condensate gas field in Tarim Basin, the first edition. Development of Gas Field in Tarim Basin. <bold>2</bold>, 7&#x02013;28 (Beijing: Petroleum Industry Press, 2003).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">A&#x00431;aco&#x00432;, &#x0041c;. T. The development of condensate gas in Azerbaijan, the first edition. The development and hydrodynamics research on condensate gas field (&#x00413;a&#x0044d;o&#x00433;&#x00438;&#x00446;&#x00440;o-&#x00446;&#x00438;&#x0043d;am&#x00438;&#x0043a;a &#x00418; &#x00420;a&#x0044d;&#x00440;a&#x00432;o&#x00442;&#x0043a;a &#x00413;a&#x0044d;o-ko&#x0043d;&#x00438;e&#x0043d;ca &#x00422;&#x0043d;&#x0044b;x &#x0041c;&#x00435;c&#x00442;opo&#x00449;&#x00446;e&#x0043d;&#x00438;&#x00438;). <bold>6</bold>, 202&#x02013;286 (&#x0041c;ock&#x00432;a: &#x0041d;&#x00435;&#x00434;pa, 1989).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michelsen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The isothermal flash problem. Part I. Stability</article-title><source>Fluid Phase Equilibria</source><year>1982</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-3812(82)85001-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michelsen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The isothermal flash problem. Part II</article-title><source>Phase-split calculation. Fluid Phase Equilibria</source><year>1982</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-3812(82)85002-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid Phase Determination in Multiple-Phase Flash Calculations</article-title><source>Computers &#x00026; Chemical Engineering</source><year>1987</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0098-1354(87)87004-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ca&#x000f1;as-Mar&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improved Two-Sided Tangent Plane Initialization and Two-Phase-Split Calculations</article-title><source>Ind. Eng. Chem. Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>5429</fpage><lpage>5436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ie061361b</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haugen</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficient and robust three-phase split computations</article-title><source>AIChE J</source><year>2011</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>2555</fpage><lpage>2565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aic.12452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name><name><surname>Firoozabadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Initialization of phase fractions in Rachford-Rice equations for robust and efficient three-phase split calculation</article-title><source>Fluid Phase Equilibria</source><year>2012</year><volume>332</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fluid.2012.06.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name><name><surname>Firoozabadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>General Strategy for Stability Testing and Phase-Split Calculation in Two and Three Phases</article-title><source>SPE Journal</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1096</fpage><lpage>1107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2118/129844-PA</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>