<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Treatment of the acne mouse model with proposed oregano nanoemulsion resulted in reduction of inflammation, bacterial load and healing of tissue superior to erythromycin. EOs’ antibacterial effects are improved through formulation as nanoemulsions [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-23-02164" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-23-02164" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-23-02164" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. The prepared emulsion had a particle size of 39.54 nm and a polydispersity index of 0.285, indicating its low size distribution; it is, therefore, considered as a nanoemulsion [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-23-02164" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. Pluronic F127 surfactant was used at a concentration of 4.5% and the oil at 0.5% 
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>. The used concentration is above Pluronic F127 critical micelle concentration (CMC), where CMC of Pluronic F127 ranges between 0.26–0.8 wt%. Oregano oil exhibited anti-inflammatory, anti-leishmanial, antioxidant, hepatoprotective and anti-tumor activities, reviewed in [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-23-02164" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to report the anti-acne effect of oregano EO. Oregano’s anti-acne effects surpass those of the commercialized over-the-counter acne tea tree EO and select EOs with documented anti-microbial effects [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-23-02164" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Most animals do not produce sufficient triglycerides to harbor 
 <italic class="italic">P. acnes</italic> [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-23-02164" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. Therefore, we standardized our acne mouse model using BALB/c mice through intradermal injection of 
 <italic class="italic">P. acnes</italic> in mice ears [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-23-02164" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-23-02164" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Based on our in vivo results, we propose BALB/c mice as another possible mouse strain for the development of an animal model of acne.
</p>
