<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The present study was conducted in the facilities of the University of Perugia, from April 2016 to June 2016 and the experimental plan was approved by the Universities of Perugia and Catania. Twenty multiparous Comisana lactating ewes at 150 ± 10 DIM were randomly assigned to two groups (n = 10), namely control (CTRL) and pomegranate pulp (PP), balanced for parity, current milk yield (486 vs. 501 g/day), and BW (64.7 vs. 66.2 kg). During the 21-day experimental period, all the ewes grazed together on a native pasture (
 <italic class="italic">Medicago arabica</italic> (L.) 
 <italic class="italic">Hudson</italic>, 35%; 
 <italic class="italic">Bellis perennis</italic> L., 25%; 
 <italic class="italic">Bromus hordeaceus</italic> L., 10%; 
 <italic class="italic">Dactylis glomerata</italic> L., 10%; 
 <italic class="italic">Brachypodium rupestre</italic> (Host) R. et S., 5%; 
 <italic class="italic">Hordeum murinum</italic> L., 5%; 
 <italic class="italic">Plantago lanceolata</italic> L., 5%; other 5%) 6 h per day using a rotational grazing system. Each pasture parcel was grazed on two consecutive days by moving electrified fence in order to provide approximately 40 m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>/ewe/day, while water was always available. After grazing, the animals were kept in sawdust bedded pens and were offered 500 g/ewe/day of chopped alfalfa hay. The animals were milked twice daily at 7.30 a.m. and 5.30 p.m. and individual milk production was recorded weekly. At each of the two daily milkings, rolled barley (100 g) and one of the two concentrates (125 g) were individually offered. The barley and pelleted concentrate that was offered were completely consumed by all the animals. The CTRL group received a corn-barley based concentrate, while the concentrate offered to the PP group contained 64.8% of dried pomegranate pulp. All the ingredients of the experimental concentrates were pelleted (5 mm diameter) at a temperature ranging from 35–40 °C using a pelleting machine (CMS-IEM, Colognola ai Colli, Verona, Italy). Over a period of 14 days, the animals were gradually adapted to the experimental concentrates, formulated to be isoproteic and according to the nutrient requirement for a ewe weighing 68 kg and producing 0.6 kg of milk at 6.5% of fat [
 <xref rid="B12-animals-09-00283" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. 
 <xref rid="animals-09-00283-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref> reports the ingredients and the chemical composition of the offered feeds. The animal and feeding management that was adopted exactly reflected the common practices used in the commercial sheep farms oriented to dairy production in the Mediterranean regions, where ewes graze all together during the day and receive concentrate supplement during the milking. No practice causing pain, suffering, distress or prolonged damage equivalent or superior to that caused by the insertion of a needle according to the good veterinary practices was followed. Therefore, this study was not regulated by the Directive 2010/63/EU on the protection of animals used for scientific purposes and the approval by the ethic committee was not needed according to the institutional and national guidelines. Nevertheless, the animals were handled by skilled personnel and in accordance with the European legislation on the protection of animals used for scientific purposes (Directive 2010/63/EU).
</p>
