<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Different medicinal plants have been reported to possess unique uses in the prevention and treatment of diseases in China. Over 5000 different medicinal plants have been reported in Chinese medical system, which mostly bear strong antifungal properties. Herbs and edible plants have a long history of being used as 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> preservatives due to their low toxicity, safety and easy acceptance by consumers. In recent years, many scholars have selected a large number of extracts from herbal medicines that inhibit the activity of 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">P. italicum.</italic> The effect of rosemary (
 <italic class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L.) extracts on the growth of the green mold of 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> was studied by Hendel et al. [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>], and in vitro antifungal assays showed a clear inhibitory effect of the rosemary essential oils and methanol extract on the growth of 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum</italic>. An aqueous crude extract prepared from lyophilized leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">Solanum nigrum</italic> showed an inhibitory effect on 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B10-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>] with a remarkable inhibition zone. 
 <italic class="italic">Solanum nigrum</italic> extracts showed an important preventive antifungal effect where 100% of inhibition was observed at 7 days of storage. Previously our lab studied the antifungal effect of ethanolic extracts of 
 <italic class="italic">Ficus hirta</italic> Vahl's fruits on 
 <italic class="italic">P. italicum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], and antifungal assays revealed the presence of a major flavonoid pinocembrin-7-O-β-D-glucoside as a strong antifungal agent. In another study which uses ethyl acetate extracts of 
 <italic class="italic">Ramulus cinnamomi</italic> plant showed resistance against several 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> pathogens and good antifungal properties for 
 <italic class="italic">P. digitatum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">P. italicum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-08-00026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>].
</p>
