<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In contrast to the high potassium concentration recorded in different yam species (
 <xref rid="foods-09-01304-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), sodium was detected at lower concentrations (0.35–380 mg/100 g dry weight). Another important macro mineral present in yam is calcium. Calcium is the most abundant mineral in the body with 99% found in bone and teeth, while 1% is found in serum. It plays a vital role in muscle functions, nerve transmission, vascular contraction, intracellular signaling, vasodilation and hormonal secretion [
 <xref rid="B113-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. The RDA of calcium (1000–1300 mg) in individuals varies depending on the age, with younger individuals requiring more calcium for the development of bone and teeth [
 <xref rid="B114-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. As with other nutrients, calcium content in yam varies with yam species and/or variety. So far, available studies revealed that 
 <italic>D. bulbifera</italic> has a higher calcium content of up to 1410 mg/100 g (
 <xref rid="foods-09-01304-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B66-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. It is important to note that metabolism of calcium involves other nutrients such as amino acids and vitamin D, as well as phosphorus. Phosphorus is important in maintaining healthy bones and teeth, acid-base balance of the body and DNA and RNA structure [
 <xref rid="B115-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. Phosphorus content was below the RDA (700 mg) recommended for healthy adults in all yam species studied except for 
 <italic>D. remotiflora</italic> (720 mg/100 g) [
 <xref rid="B74-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. In addition to the macrominerals mentioned above, yam is reported to be a good source of magnesium. Magnesium plays a vital role in the body metabolic processes, nerve transmission, appropriate muscle tasks and cardiac tempo, as well as synthesis and stability of DNA [
 <xref rid="B116-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. Shajeela et al. [
 <xref rid="B51-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] reported magnesium range of 540–634 mg/100 g in two varieties of 
 <italic>D. oppositifolia</italic>, while the authors recorded 532 mg/100 g and 578 mg/100 g of magnesium in 
 <italic>D. pentaphylla</italic> and 
 <italic>D. wallichi</italic>, respectively.
</p>
