<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">
 <italic>C. tetragonoloba</italic> bean contains common chemical components e.g. fatty acids, and amino acid. Beans of gaur contain high contents of fats, proteins and carbohydrates. A study demonstrated that the bean of gaur had a high percentage of linoleic acid and the ethanolic extract of C
 <italic>. tetragonoloba</italic> bean showed antioxidant and anticancer activity. Gaur plant has been shown to be an effective the hypocholesterolemic agent [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The 
 <italic>C. tetragonoloba</italic> showed an anti-diabetic effect, anticoagulant activity, anti-ulcer, hemolytic activity, anti-asthmatic activity, anti-inflammatory activity, antibacterial, hypoglycemic and hypolipidemic effect [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In the present study, the supercritical extract of gaur contain Hexadecanoic acid, 15-methyl-, methyl ester (24.498%), 9,12-octadecadienoyl chloride, (
 <italic>z</italic>,
 <italic>z</italic>)- (23.718), Dodecanoic acid, methyl (13.228%), are the major compounds found in SFE extract of 
 <italic>C. tetragonoloba</italic>. In previous study, the aqueous and methanol extract of 
 <italic>C. tetragonoloba</italic> contains major constituents that were more inositol and 7-tetradecenal, (Z), stigmasterol, 10,12-hexadecadien-1-ol and 9,12-octadecadienoyl chloride, (
 <italic>z</italic>,
 <italic>z</italic>) and have reported antioxidant, anti-cancerous and thyroid inhibiting properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Further research on this may help in the development of medicines against the dengue virus. Molecular docking in silico method is used in drug development. In this method, phytochemicals are matched with viral targets to find interactions between the drug and disease-producing agents by using the computational method. NS1 are essential for viral replication. NS1 is the only protein that is continuously secreted by infected host cells. NS1 is found in multi-functional in nature i.e. production of infectious virus particles, by using an innovative trans-complementation system with fully functional epitope-tagged in NS1 protein, also interacts with the structural proteins, etc. Due to multifunctional in nature, NS1 protein appears as an attractive target for antiviral therapy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The researchers have put great effort in search of effective molecules for targeting different structural or non-structural proteins of the dengue virus.
</p>
