<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Acute toxicity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Acute toxicity of AcEO was performed on the basis of the protocols conducted in previous similar studies [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>]. 25 albino mice were divided into five groups of five animals each. After 18 h of fasting with free access to water, the doses of 0.5, 1, 1.5 and 2 mg/kg of AcEO were given orally to the mice, using a solution of gelatin 5% as vehicle. The control group was fed with 0.5% gelatin solution. The use of gelatin as an emulsifier is attributed to its non-toxic and non-irritability qualities as carrier molecule [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>], besides its hydrophobic character that makes this macroprotein preferably used in pharmaceutical application and food industry as natural emulsifier and stabilizer [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>]. Also, gelatin is largely used as biodegradable macromolecule largely used for encapsulation of essential oils, mainly utilized in pharmaceutical and cosmetics to prevent eventual decomposition, evaporation or oxidation of the volatile oils [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>]. Indeed, Sutaphanit and Chitprasert (2014) demonstrated that there was no significant interaction between gelatin and basil essential oil, along the encapsulation process [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>]. General behavior and mortality were observed permanently during the four hours succeeding the dosing, and occasionally during the first 24 h. The animals were monitored daily for any additional signs of toxicity and weekly for changes in body weight. Dead animals were sacrificed just after their death and the survived animals were sacrificed at the end of the experimentation by overdose of anesthesia by ethylic ether, and the organs were examined macroscopically for any toxicological alterations. The stomach was longitudinally incised by the greater curvature and ulceration or perforations of gastric mucosa were observed. The liver and kidneys have been weighted after been cleaned from connective tissues.
 </p>
</sec>
