<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">A. campestris</span> L. is an Asteraceae plant commonly known as field wormwood; it is a perennial undershrub (30–150 cm height), with branched and ascending brownish-red stems. Leaves are green, the basal are 2–3 pinnatisects, the upper are simple. Inflorescence is an ovoid, heterogamous yellowish capitulum, with an involucral bracts; ray flowers are female, pistillate and fertile, while the disk flowers are sterile, and functionally male [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. In Morocco, 
  <span class="italic">A.campestris</span> L. known as “Allal”, is used as antidiabetic [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>], to treat digestive, respiratory, metabolic, allergic problems [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>] and cutaneous problems [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. This herb has many other ethnomedicinal uses like antihypertensive [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>], emmenaguogue [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>], and well known for treatment of liver and kidney disorders [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>] and as. Previous pharmacological studies proved that 
  <span class="italic">A. campestris</span> L. possesses antioxidant [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>], antibacterial, antifungal [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>], insecticidal [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>], antitumor [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>], antivenin [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>], hepatoprotective, nephroprotective [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>] and antidiabetic [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>] effects. Recently a clinical trial conducted on volunteers demonstrated that 
  <span class="italic">A.campestris</span> L. enhanced 33.3% to 50% decrease in arterial pressure among hypertensive smoker patients [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. In another study, the administration of 
  <span class="italic">A.campestris</span> L. extract induced antihypertensive effect on envenomed hypertensive rats, and provoked 10% to 30% of hypertension drop, while the pretreatment with the herb extract prevented the rise of hypertension [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. Nevertheless, no in-vitro study has been elaborated to evaluate the antihypertensive potential of this plant. In the aim to highlight the importance of this plant in the cardiovascular therapy, this study was performed to analyze the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">A. campestris</span> L. (AcEO) growing in oriental Morocco, to investigate its vasorelaxant and subsequent mechanism of action and to determine its antiplatelet and antioxidant effects.
 </p>
</sec>
