<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several studies have explored the anticancer activities of 
 <italic>G. morella</italic> fruit, leaf, and bark extracts and different isolated compounds such as xanthones and benzophenones (
 <xref rid="molecules-25-05690-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Choudhury et al. [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] investigated the anticancer activity of methanolic extracts of the leaf, bark, and fruit of 
 <italic>G. morella</italic> under different in vitro and in vivo experimental conditions. Their study demonstrated that the fruit extract exhibited the maximum activity. The anticancer activity was further confirmed by the results of in vivo administration of the fruit extract (200 mg/kg) for 10 days to Dalton’s lymphoma-induced mice. The fruit extract significantly increased the mean survival time of the animals, decreased the tumor volume, and restored the hematological and biochemical parameters. The authors further showed that the fruit extract exerted its anticancer effect through the induction of caspases and DNA fragmentation that ultimately led to apoptosis. In another study, Choudhury et al. [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] confirmed the effect of 
 <italic>G. morella</italic> methanolic fruit extract on breast cancer cell lines (MCF7, MDAMB231, and SKBR3). Their results of time-course analysis (at 24, 48, and 72 h) of bioactive fraction (1.56–25 µg/mL) treatment on breast cancer cell lines revealed a dose- and time-dependent antiproliferative response. Furthermore, mechanistic studies involving morphological observations and Western blotting analysis disclosed its apoptosis-inducing effect on breast cancer. P53-dependent upregulation of Bax and downregulation of B-cell lymphoma-extra large (Bcl X
 <sub>L</sub>) was suggested as the possible pathway of apoptosis followed by MCF7 cells upon exposure to the bioactive faction. Subsequently, through UHPLC and ESI-MS/MS analysis, Choudhury et al. [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] demonstrated that garcinol was the bioactive compound responsible for the anticancer activity. Hong et al. [
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] investigated the effect of garcinol on the growth of HT-29 and HCT-116 colon cancer cells, as well as IEC-6 and INT-407 cells, which are normal immortalized intestinal cells. They demonstrated that garcinol exhibited potent growth inhibitory effects on all intestinal cells, with the IC
 <sub>50</sub> values in the range of 3.2–21.4 µM after 72 h of treatment. Garcinol was found to be more effective in inhibiting the growth of cancer cells than inhibiting the growth of normal immortalized cells. In another study, Pan et al. [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] elucidated that garcinol suppressed the growth of human leukemia HL-60 cells by the induction of caspase-3/CPP32 activity and induction of the degradation of poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP) protein. More recent studies have demonstrated the activities of garcinol and isogarcinol against lung cancer, colorectal cancer, breast cancer, prostate cancer, pancreatic cancer, and cervical cancer models, and the activities were largely attributed to the inhibition of histone acetyl transferase (HATs), NF-
 <italic>k</italic>B signaling, and STAT signaling [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Several studies indicate that xanthones are cytotoxic against different types of cancer. For instance, desoxymorellin was found to inhibit the growth of human embryonic lung fibroblast and Henrietta Lacks cervical cancer cells, with a minimum inhibitory concentration of 0.39 µg/mL [
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].
</p>
