<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Utilization of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) for enhancing growth and development as well as production of essential oil in aromatic plants has been increasingly drawing research interest. In order to assess the AMF effects on different aromatic species, an open-field experiment was carried out using 
  <italic>Artemisia dracunculus</italic> (tarragon), 
  <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> (lavender) and 
  <italic>Hyssopus officinalis</italic> (hyssop). AMF stimulated the growth of tarragon and lavender plants, whereas hyssop showed a slight developmental slowing; nonetheless, a significant increase in essential oil content in the three species was seen. AMF application increased the biomass of 
  <italic>A. dracunculus</italic> and 
  <italic>H. officinalis</italic> by 20–35%. No differences in antioxidant activity and phenolics content were recorded at harvest between the control and AMF-inoculated plants, but the latter showed a significant increase in antioxidant status upon storage at high temperature and humidity compared to the untreated control. The enhancement of abiotic stress resistance during storage in plants inoculated with AMF was the highest in 
  <italic>A. dracunculus</italic>, and the lowest in 
  <italic>H. officinalis</italic>, while the untreated control plants showed a significant decrease in phenolics, ascorbic acid and chlorophyll content, as well as antioxidant activity, upon the abiotic stress. AMF inoculation differentially affected the mineral composition, increasing the accumulation of Se, I and Zn in 
  <italic>A. dracunculus</italic>, and decreasing the levels of heavy metals and Co, Fe, Li, Mn in 
  <italic>H. officinalis</italic>. Based on the outcome of the present research, AMF inoculation resulted in a significant enhancement of the overall performances of 
  <italic>A. dracunculus</italic>, 
  <italic>L. angustifolia</italic> and 
  <italic>H. officinalis</italic>, and also in the improvement of plant antioxidant status upon storage in stress conditions.
 </p>
</abstract>
