<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Thus, the key contribution of this study is the comprehensive analysis of different optics and photonics systems in agricultural applications to provide a detail idea of the advanced techniques and their future deployment in agriculture cultivation and harvesting. The review has proposed important and selective suggestions for the further technological development of optics and photonics in future agricultural applications:
 <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">The incorporation of optical sensors into photonics detection techniques that serve as an early warning for drinking water pollution.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">The characterization of canned food or bottled beverages in the NIR (&gt;1100 nm) and MIR wavebands for their optical “fingerprint” that correlates to the quality and food safety level of the product, such as preservatives concentration.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">The characterization on hazardous residual materials in food using optical spectroscopy, Raman spectroscopy and fluorescence.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">The implementation of an agricultural robot to perform better palm oil plantation management, scheduled collection of field latex and weed removal.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">The spectral imaging provides early detection of disease-causing 
    <italic class="italic">G. boninense</italic> in the oil palm.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Spectroscopy provides moisture content inspection, protein and lipid content detection, as well as improving the rubber vulcanizing process.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">The imaging technique detects external damage or bruises on organic fruits and vegetables.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
