<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">The immune system plays an important role in responding to different external exposures like infectious diseases, inflammatory agents, and even carcinogens. Recently, cancer and infectious diseases become an emerging problem, and due to drawbacks like resistance, toxicity, and lack of immune responses of some available drugs, pharmaceutical companies are more concerned with the discovery of new safe and effective immune-stimulating alternatives, polysaccharides in this regard, are considered one of the best choices. It was proved that polysaccharides isolated from traditional Chinese medicine could activate or regulate T lymphocytes and macrophages, enhance the activity of interleukin, improve the antibody level, and regulate the immune function of the organism [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Polysaccharides were also proved an important modulator since they can enhance immunity through different mechanisms, such as stimulation of macrophages, splenocytes, and thymocytes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The carbohydrate-based vaccine is intensively studied for their potentiality to become vaccine candidates. Tumor-associated carbohydrate antigens and polysaccharides located on the surface of pathogenic microorganisms can be recognized by the host immune system [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], which opens a new era in glycobiology and vaccination availability [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] since polysaccharides have a vital role in cell–cell recognition and interaction with the immune system. Many vaccine formulations contain polysaccharides-based antigens such as bacterial capsular polysaccharides or tumor-associated carbohydrate antigens which have been used in many vaccines formulations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Since the 80 s of the last century, polysaccharides vaccines were available for different infectious diseases like Pneumonia and meningitis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Unfortunately, conventional polysaccharide antigens (mainly high-purified capsular polysaccharides) have disadvantages such as short duration with a poor immunogenic response in infants and young children because of the absence of immunological memory and IgM to IgG class switch. To overcome these shortcomings, new polysaccharides vaccines are conjugated to strongly immunogenic protein carriers like diphtheria and tetanus toxins that induce T cell-dependent response and enhance the immunogenicity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] through interacting with the immune system [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]
 <italic>.</italic>
</p>
