<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the area considered, WFP are not only remnants of the past, but a treasure trove from the past, still alive today, constituting a very valuable resource for the future. We believe that the examples we have provided clearly show that WFP ethnobotany is one of the most appropriate approaches and bases for selecting candidates for new food development. Adding to this the information from Talavera’s (unpubl. res.) surveys on people’s appreciation of WFP, it is quite likely that some taxa will emerge as candidates to be counted among the foods of the future, based on current research focused on the past traditional knowledge of plants. Throughout the present paper, we have underlined some taxa (
 <italic>Apium nodiflorum</italic>, 
 <italic>Crithmum maritimum</italic>, 
 <italic>Reichardia picroides</italic>) that had already been proposed to be launched as new crops or new commercial plants on a scale larger than that of local use. Our results fully reinforce and support these proposals. Some other WFP species could be added to the proposal list, among others the few we will briefly comment now. 
 <italic>Helianthus tuberosus</italic> and 
 <italic>Portulaca oleracea</italic>, already profusely cultivated and sold in France, could enlarge their market area. 
 <italic>Salicornia patula</italic> could be introduced in markets and restaurants, probably collected from the wild, as in the case of 
 <italic>Crithmum maritimum</italic> and similarly to what we have observed to happen in France with this and related taxa. 
 <italic>Origanum virens</italic> could increase its market and could be cultivated. For this and other aromatic and condiment plants, successful cultivation tests have been performed [
 <xref rid="B126-foods-10-00061" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. 
 <italic>Chenopodium bonus-henricus</italic> and 
 <italic>Urtica dioica</italic> could constitute, either collected from the wild or cultivated, interesting commercial products. Public administrations’ help would be suitable for initiating the development of the crops and products mentioned. Apart from the economic interest for people involved, these new plants and products put on the market will contribute, in general, to food security and, particularly given their local-origin component and traditional knowledge basis, to food sovereignty.
</p>
