<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">The world faces a severe and acute public health emergency due to the ongoing global pandemic of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) (Wu and McGoogan 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2020</xref>). SARS-CoV-2 is a new strain of coronavirus that appeared in China in December 2019 (Guo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2020</xref>). Symptoms of COVID-19 can be relatively non-specific and infected people may be asymptomatic. People infected with COVID-19 generally develop signs and symptoms including mild respiratory symptoms and fever, dry cough, fatigue, shortness of breath, and loss of smell on an average of 5–6 days after infection but may range from two to fourteen days. Complications may include pneumonia and acute respiratory distress syndrome which may lead to death (Singhal 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2020</xref>; Pal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2020</xref>). There has been no noticeable progress in managing this disease so far and the patient is being given treatment based on his observable and diagnosed symptom (Organization et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2009</xref>). Until now, there is no known vaccine or specific antiviral treatment (Sheahan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2020</xref>). The Human Genome Project helped to increase the number of new therapeutic targets for drug discovery. Meanwhile, high-throughput protein purification techniques, crystallography, and nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy techniques have contributed to the structural details of proteins and protein complexes. These developments allow computational strategies to penetrate in all its aspects (Jorgensen 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2004</xref>; Bajorath 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2002</xref>; Langer and Hoffmann 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2001</xref>; Walters et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">1998</xref> and Kitchen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2004</xref>), such as virtual screening techniques (VS) (Gohlke and Klebe 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2002</xref>) to determine results and methods for improving molecules. Molecular docking, a computational technique used to estimate the affinity of association between two molecules such as ligand–protein and protein–protein. The use of molecular docking became an essential component in drug discovery. These techniques also help in predicting the side and toxic effects of compounds (Bacha et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2008</xref>). A number of conventional drugs such as chloroquine, hydroxychloroquine, remediffer have been tested and found with a specific therapeutic effect in the laboratory. However, the clinical pharmacological response is not very encouraging and toxicity remains an inevitable problem that causes serious adverse effects (Otitoloju et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2020</xref>). The lack of a specific treatment for COVID-19 led most researchers in many regions of the world, to use medicinal herbs known in the science of ethnopharmacology as an antiviral (Rajabian and Hosseinzadeh 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2020</xref>). The development of viral resistance to current antiviral agents reinforces the need for new effective compounds against viral infections (Chattopadhyay et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2009</xref>). In this study, some of the active compounds present in some medicinal plants used in Sudan traditional medicine to treat viral diseases were selected based on literature review for docking studies and the interactions of these compounds have been clarified to determine the preferred molecules for the treatment of COVID-19 via the inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 main protease enzyme, and compare the results with the proposed drugs such as chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine. Furthermore, the toxicity of these compounds was performed in order to assess their safety for human use. The study of the crystal structure of therapeutic targets is crucial for knowing how the drugs will be discovered in the future. Alkaloids are a rich source of important chemical compounds which can be used for development of new anti-viral agents. Alkaloids have a wide distribution in the plant kingdom and are mainly found in higher plants, some viral diseases can be treated with approved antiviral, but for others they still have no any vaccines or drugs available. Most of the approved antiviral are directly or indirectly related to side effects, which ultimately leads to an increased need to develop antiviral based on natural phytochemicals. Globally, antiviral are shifting toward plant-derived products because they are less toxic and have less chance of developing resistance (Ghildiyal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2020</xref>). All selected compounds from different groups were selected based on their chemical origin were used to treat many diseases such as antiviral activity. The present paper aimed to evaluate the antiviral activity of some compounds from medicinal plants against COVID-19 using Molecular Docking Analysis.
</p>
