<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">Controlling vital functions for different types of bacterial communication, such as biofilm formation or expression of virulence factor genes, relies on the quorum-sensing (QS) signalling system. It would be attractive to determine or design new powerful agents to interfere with these signalling systems to develop antibacterial drugs and new antimicrobial therapies to control bacterial infections [
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This novel inhibition in bacterial pathogens is popularly known as quorum quenching (QQ) and the agents with this action are named quorum quenchers. This process is a hot topic in microbiology because the quorum quenchers are not related to expansion of bacterial resistance and they inhibit the vital activity of bacterial cells in a unique population. Quorum quencher compounds have been isolated from various natural sources, such as many eukaryotes, different microorganisms, fruits, vegetables, and natural plants [
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. One of the best candidates to combat bacterial pathogens, especially through inhibiting the QS system, is traditional herbal medicine or natural plants. The QS systems in Gram-negative or Gram-positive bacterial populations produce and diffuse signal molecules such as acyl-homoserine lactones around the bacterial cells; identification of these signals through specific receptors occurs at high concentrations during population growth, and increases the transcription of target gene under QS system control. So, the medicinal plant compounds act as an active quorum quencher because they disrupt these pathways by interfering with signal molecule synthesis, inactivating signals by destroying them, interfering with signal receptors in bacterial cells, and blocking target genes under QS controls (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. This new approach is also appropriate to combat bacterial infections with high resistance to chemical antibiotics and it may help to design new drug, based on herbal medicines. More than 4500 species of plants have been grown from all over the world that are used for medicinal purposes. Research in various countries shows the QQ activity of the extracts of many traditional medicinal plants with numerous secondary metabolites (e.g. essential oils, alkaloids, saponins, flavonoids, tannins) and antimicrobial compounds (e.g. phenolics, quinones, flavanones and alkaloids) [
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>]. Traditionally, medicinal plants and their extracts have been the main source of medicines and in some countries they are used in pharmaceutical industries, to increase the safety of food systems, in veterinary medicine and in the treatment of different illnesses to promote the health of human society. Many people in different countries still rely on traditional herbal medicines for the treatment of many infectious diseases, so changing the focus from antibacterial studies to evaluation of the anti-QS activity of medicinal plants could expose new QQ agents to control many bacterial infections [
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Because traditional medicinal plants with antibacterial properties have played an important role in therapeutic purposes and treating bacterial infections in the Middle East, especially in Iran, we decided to perform this brief review to provide a current overview of the traditional and endemic medicinal plants with anti-QS properties in Iran. As the medicinal plant extracts with anti-QS activities could be considered as a novel anti-pathogenic drug, several studies have been completed in Iran to identify the QQ activity of different traditional medicine plant species with antibacterial properties. In this review, we summarize this information about herbal extracts that act as a quorum quenchers in Iran.
</p>
