<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0043">Inevitably, assorted dietary minerals that are essential immunity mediators should be incorporated into the diet, for example, different fruits, spices and vegetables are abundant with immuno-stimulators that in turn fortifies the innate as well as adaptive immune responses against viral elements (
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">Sarfraz et al., 2020</xref>). To elucidate, these foods contain allicin, cucumins, papain, ginsenoside, mangoosteen, chloroquine etc. that has a direct effect on dendritic cells, NK cells, lymphocytes, antibodies in imparting shield against foreign particles invading human body. Taking into account these factors, a healthy balanced diet is quintessential for proper immuno-functioning (
 <xref rid="bib0142" ref-type="bibr">Martineau et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0181" ref-type="bibr">Petric, 2020</xref>). As the diet is a summation of trace elements, mineral supplements, vitamins (A, D, C, E, K), zinc etc, it can fulfil all the repercussions such as hypovitaminosis caused due to viral attack respectively (
 <xref rid="bib0071" ref-type="bibr">Gunville et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0181" ref-type="bibr">Petric, 2020</xref>). Additionally, regular physical activities is adjuvant for boosting immunity and metabolic health specifically, if it's sunny, as ultra-violet and infra-red rays are natural virucidal elements (
 <xref rid="bib0133" ref-type="bibr">Lytle and Sagripanti, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0141" ref-type="bibr">Martin et al., 2009</xref>). However, the biological activities can also be improved by ingesting high levels of naturally existing polyphenols that not only elicit immunity against viruses but they are also comprised of receptors that identifies and permit their cellular uptake for activating signaling cascade underlying innate immunity (
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">Nieman and Wentz, 2019</xref>). To exemplify, curcumin and epigallocatechin gallate causes epigenetic alterations within cells, curb gasto-intestinal immunity and allergic responses (
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">Ding et al., 2018</xref>). These compounds predominantly include flavonoids, phenols, stilbenoids that are abundantly present in plants in the form of aglycones or glucose esters (
 <xref rid="bib0134" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2014</xref>). An 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> study reported by 
 <xref rid="bib0122" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al. (2017)</xref>, depicted the role of resveratrol from grape seeds against coronaviruses. Likewise, other antiviral components like glycyrrhizin from liquorice have been known to show some activity against coronaviruses and SARS, revealing the significance of glycyrrhizin to be used as trial drug in COVID-19 affected patients, in order to develop it as a potent cure drug (
 <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">Cinatl et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Brush et al., 2006</xref>). Nevertheless, other plants like oregano, garlic, ginger, lemon, broccoli, mint, tulsi, fennel, thyme, cinnamon, star anise etc. should be tested in the different forms so as to form an effective drug to fight against COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="bib0256" ref-type="bibr">Yasmin et al., 2020</xref>). Above all, smoking has a direct impact on immune responses through escalating pathogen immunity and dwindling the defense responses within hosts. Moreover, T-helper cells, CD4, CD25, CD8+ T-cells, memory cells, B and T cells, NK cells, macrophages etc. are also hindered by smoke.Therefore, these steps can reboot the immune system and reinforce the inner forces to battle against severe viral infections COVID-19 respectively.
</p>
