<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0030">The World Health Organization [
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] describes traditional herbal medicines as natural occurring plant-derived substances with minimal or no industrial processing, used to prevent and treat illnesses within local or regional healing practices [
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Traditional herbal medicines and their preparations have been widely used for thousands of years in developing and developed countries, owing to their natural origins and presumed less side effects [
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Physiological and Pharmacological actions exhibited by a variety of plants can be attributed to chemical compounds synthesized by these plants. Modern-day synthetic pharmacological agents were hitherto prepared as crude drugs such as tinctures, teas, powders, and other herbal formulations [
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]; and with several active drugs derived directly from plant sources. These include drugs such as aspirin (from willow bark), digitoxin (from foxglove), morphine (from the opium poppy), quinine (from cinchona bark), and pilocarpine (Jaborandi) [
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. However, huge concerns have been raised about the safety of herbal drugs, Thus, necessitated several studies aimed at emphazing the need to evaluate the toxicity of medicinal plants [
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>]. Although reports of injury or death arising from adverse reactions to plant supplements are scanty [
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Several pharmacological compounds such as alkaloids, anthraquinone glycosides, pyrrolizidine alkaloids, amongst others, synthesized by various plants, have been implicated in toxicity and damage to vital organs [
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>]. These findings further underscore the need for thorough safety evaluation of herbal preparations.
</p>
