<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0035">
 <italic>Simarouba glauca</italic>, commonly known as “Paradise tree” or “Laxmitaru”, belongs to the family 
 <italic>Simaroubaceae</italic>. The plant is also known by other names such as bitter ash, bitter damson, princess tree, and others [
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The plant is native to the Amazon rainforest and other tropical areas of Mexico, Cuba, Haiti, Jamaica, and North and Central America [
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]; exotic to India, Sri Lanka, Philippines, Myanmar, and Nigeria. In the year 2007, it was introduced to Nigeria, in Ubiaja, Esan South East Local Government Area of Edo State by Blessing Akele, Ph.D. and Osagie-Eweka; and was cultivated in 
 <italic>Cercobela</italic> Farms®. 
 <italic>Simarouba glauca</italic> has a long history of herbal medicine having many pharmacological properties that have been documented [
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>]. The major active groups of phytochemicals in 
 <italic>S. glauca</italic> are the quassinoids, which belong to the triterpene chemical family. Ailanthinone, glaucarubinone, and holacanthone are considered some of the main active quassinoids in 
 <italic>Simarouba</italic>. Other chemicals include benzoquinone, canthin, dehydroglaucarubinone, glaucarubine, glaucarubolone, melianone, simaroubidin, simarolide, simaroubin, simarubolide, sitosterol, and tirucalla [
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Some of these active compounds have demonstrated 
 <italic>in-vitro</italic> anti-tumour activity [
 <xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>], 
 <italic>in-vitro</italic> anti-viral activity [
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], 
 <italic>in-vitro</italic> anti-amoebic activity [
 <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>], 
 <italic>in-vitro</italic> anti-bacterial activity [
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], 
 <italic>in-vivo</italic> anti-malaria activity [
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>], among others (
 <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).
</p>
