<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0055">Eight 2,000-mL single-flow continuous fermenters (1,500 mL of effective volume) were used, as described in 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Mason et al. (2015)</xref>, to perform 2 fermentation runs, which lasted 9 d each with 6 d of adaptation and 3 d of sampling. In each fermentation, the rumen fluid was collected in the same slaughterhouse from 4 culled dairy cows, which were fed a TMR based on corn silage, grass hay, cornmeal, and soybean meal and were slaughtered in healthy conditions. The rumen fluid was collected immediately after the slaughter of cows (in the morning, after about 12 h from the last feeding of animals) and transported to the laboratory within half an hour in airtight glass bottles, refluxed with CO
 <sub>2</sub> and maintained at 39 °C. The fermentation substrate was a TMR composed of corn silage, cornmeal, hay, soybean meal and a micromineral and vitamin premix (370, 260, 180, 170 and 20 g/kg DM, respectively), which was dried at 60 °C (48 h) and then coarsely ground; it contained 150 and 350 g/kg of CP and NDF on DM, respectively. The treatments consisted of the daily addition of the 3 pure compounds—BOR, CAM, and EUCA—to the fermentation fluid (100 mg/L) of the fermenters (2 fermenters per treatment within each fermentation run) as well as using 2 fermenters with only ethanol (CTR) added. The pure compounds and the standard diet were provided to each fermenter twice a day in equal doses (at 09:00 and 17:00) for a total of 18 g/d of DM. Artificial saliva (
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Slyter et al., 1966</xref>) was continuously infused using a peristaltic pump at 1.3 mL/min. During the last 3 d before morning feeding, the pH was directly measured (GLP 22, Crison Instruments, S.A. Barcelona, Spain), whereas samples for the ammonia-nitrogen, SCFA, protozoa and bacterial DNA (10, 5, 5, and 1 mL sample, respectively) were collected for later analysis. The samples for the ammonia-nitrogen were stored at −20 °C, thawed at room temperature, and then analyzed using an ammonia electrode (Ammonia Gas Sensing Combination Electrode, Hach Company, 2001). Samples for SCFA analysis were mixed with 5 mL of 0.05 mol/L H
 <sub>2</sub>SO
 <sub>4</sub> and were stored at −20 °C; after thawing, they were centrifuged at 20,000 × 
 <italic>g</italic> for 30 min at 20 °C and filtered by a polypore filter (0.45 μm, Agilent Technologies, Milan, Italy).
</p>
