<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Not surprisingly, researchers have also focused on mushrooms native to North America, as avenues to discover novel antimicrobial metabolites. Grifolin, neogrifolin and confluentin isolated from 
 <italic>Albatrellus flettii</italic> collected in California were found to have strong activity against gram positive bacteria 
 <italic>B. cereus</italic> and 
 <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Another lanostane-type tripterpene isolated from 
 <italic>Jahnoporus hirtus</italic> also inhibited the growth of 
 <italic>B. cereus</italic> and 
 <italic>E. faecalis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Other anti-bacterial small molecules isolated include lanostane triterpenoids and ergostane steroid from 
 <italic>Fomitopsis pinicola</italic> collected in Oregon [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], new subclass of bisnaphthalenes from 
 <italic>Urnula craterium</italic> [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] collected in La Crosse (WI, USA) and 2-aminoquinoline from 
 <italic>Leucopaxillus albissimus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. 2-aminoquinoline showed modest antibacterial activity against multidrug resistant clinical isolates with an MIC of 8–64 μg/mL and weak antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>A. baumannii</italic>, using tetracycline as a reference antibacterial agent [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The antibacterial activity of 2-aminoquinoline was not very convincing due to its high MIC, therefore, it was not suggested for further drug screening as an antibacterial agent in its current form. The antibacterial activity of small molecules from 
 <italic>F. pinicola</italic> was compared with tetracycline [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Vancomycin and tetracycline were used as positive controls to compare the antimicrobial activity of urnucratin A-C isolated from 
 <italic>Urnula craterium</italic> [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Amongst these compounds, urnucratin A (26) was the most promising with MIC values of 2, 1, and 0.5 μg/mL against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>E. faecium</italic> and 
 <italic>S. pyogenes</italic> respectively [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. It had an IC50 value greater than 100 μM against J774A.1 murine monocyte cells, indicating that it lacks non-specific toxicity [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Supernatants from culture of 
 <italic>Lenzites betulina</italic> and 
 <italic>Haploporus odorus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] as well as extracts from 
 <italic>Pleurotus ostreatus</italic> and 
 <italic>P. levis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B39-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] also have antimicrobial activity. However, the responsible antimicrobial compounds have not been isolated from these mushrooms. In another study using extracts from 75 mushrooms collected in Oxford (OH, USA), it was found that a total of 25 samples had antibacterial activity against at least one of the bacterial strains assessed [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. From this study, extracts from 
 <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> and 
 <italic>Laetiporus sulphureus</italic> were found to have the strongest antibacterial activity [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. MIC was determined for these mushroom extracts using kanamycin as a reference antibacterial agent which has an MIC of 0.01 mg/mL against 
 <italic>S. epidermidis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Four small molecules Ramariolides A–D (22–25) were isolated from methanol extracts of 
 <italic>Ramaria cystidiophora</italic> [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. The major metabolite ramariolide A (21) was found to be active against 
 <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> and 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> with MIC of 8 μg/mL and 64−128 μg/mL respectively. This compound appears to be promising because isoniazid, a first-line antituberculosis bactericidal antibiotic also has an MIC of 8 μg/mL against 
 <italic>M. smegmatis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-26-00251" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. The authors did not report any antibacterial from ramariolides B–D (22–24), and therefore it is currently unknown whether these compounds have any biological activity.
</p>
