<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">So far, SCE berry extract has demonstrated antibacterial effects against several Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria. Oils from SCE seeds showed a good antibacterial activity against 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli, Bacillus cereus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Enterobacter aerogenes, Serratia marcescens</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Micrococcus luteus,</italic> as tested by the disc diffusion method [
 <xref rid="B43-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Teng and Lee [
 <xref rid="B43-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>] investigated the efficacy of various extraction methods, but simultaneous distillation extracted higher amounts of terpenes, β-pinene, borneol, and α-pinene, as well as limonene, than other procedures, including Soxhlet and microwave-assisted extraction. These compounds might display a strong antibacterial activity due to the penetration through the outer membrane of bacterial cells and its severe damage. Six dibenzocyclooctadiene lignans presented antibacterial activity against pathogenic 
 <italic class="italic">Chlamydia pneumoniae</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> upon their infection in human epithelial cells [
 <xref rid="B44-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. The presence and substitution pattern of methylenedioxy, methoxy, and hydroxyl groups of the lignans had a profound impact on the antichlamydial activity [
 <xref rid="B44-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. Bai et al., investigated the activity of SCE fruit ethanolic and water extracts against typical food-borne pathogens and food-spoiling organisms [
 <xref rid="B45-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. Both extracts displayed strong antibacterial activity towards 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus subtilis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">B. cereus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella enterica</italic> subsp. 
 <italic class="italic">enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium, 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Enterobacter aerogenes</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> [
 <xref rid="B45-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. It was suggested that the main constituents responsible for such activity were organic acids (such as citric and malic acids), as evaluated by ion chromatography. Mocan et al. evaluated the minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) of 
 <italic class="italic">S. chinensis</italic> fruit and leaf extracts for the Gram-positive 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">B. subtilis</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic>, and the Gram-negative bacteria 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S.</italic> Typhimurium, which ranged from 10 µg/mL to &gt;100 µg/mL [
 <xref rid="B13-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. These results indicated that Gram-positive bacteria were more sensitive to SCE extracts than Gram-negative bacteria. The same was observed by Choi et al., for methanol fractions of SCE against several Gram-negative (
 <italic class="italic">S.</italic> Typhimurium, 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli, Cronobacter sakazakii</italic>) and Gram-positive (
 <italic class="italic">B. cereus, L. monocytogenes, S. aureus)</italic> strains [
 <xref rid="B46-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. This difference may result from the difference in cell wall morphology of these microorganisms [
 <xref rid="B46-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. Reports on the stimulation of microbial growth by compounds from SCE are less abundant. In a conference report, 
 <italic class="italic">S. chinensis</italic> rhizome extract was reported to promote growth of 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus delbrueckii</italic> ssp. 
 <italic class="italic">bulgaricus</italic>, while inhibiting activity of 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus licheniformis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">B. subtilis</italic>, and the pathogenic 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> [
 <xref rid="B47-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. The mechanism of inhibition includes changing the permeability of the outer membrane of bacteria, leading to their destruction [
 <xref rid="B47-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. 
</p>
