<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our SRS spectroscopy set-up is similar to the figure shown in [
 <xref rid="pone.0216811.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>] (see also 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0216811.s001" class="xref">S1 Fig</xref>). This system is a combination of a femtosecond SRS spectroscopy set-up with an inverted optical microscope (Eclipse TE-2000-E, Nikon) equipped with mirrors scanning unit (C2, Nikon). The two pulsed laser source are: (i) a femtosecond Ti:Sa (Chameleon Ultra II) with ≈140 fs pulse duration according to manufacturer datasheet, 80 MHz of repetition rate and 680–1,080 nm emission wavelengths range; (ii) a femtosecond synchronized optical parametric oscillator (SOPO-Chameleon Compact OPO), pumped by a Ti:Sa, with ≈ 200 fs pulse duration according to manufacturer datasheet, 80 MHz of repetition rate and 1,000–1,600 nm emission wavelengths range. This combination of laser systems allows a minimum photon energy difference between Ti:Sa and SOPO beam of 2,500cm
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup>; hence, only the high frequency C–H region (2,800–3,200cm
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup>) of Raman spectra can be explored. Immediately following emission from the laser, the intensity of the Ti:Sa pulses are modulated at a frequency of 4.5 MHz (thus, faster than the typical laser noise, e.g. 1 MHz) by an EOM (CONOPTICS 350–160 KD*P) pulse selection system, allowing to have high sensitivity SRS signal detection at the moderate laser power required for our biological imaging. Additionally, due to a slightly different path of the two laser beams inside the OPO housing, they have a time delay of about 5 ns. In order to generate a high sensitivity SRS signal, the pump (Ti:Sa) and probe (SOPO) pulsed lasers have been spatially and temporally overlapped at the image plane. Therefore in the system were inserted: (i) a delay line (Newport MOD MILS200CC) between the Ti:Sa and the microscope in order to obtain a temporal overlap; and (ii) a dichroic mirror (Semrock FF875-Di01-2536) to spatially combine the collinear beams. The two beams were then focused into the specimen through a 60× multiphoton microscope objective (NA = 1.27). The output pulses are collected in transmission by a 40× high numerical aperture multiphoton microscope objective (NA = 1.25). In order to remove the pump signal, a stack of optical filters was used, while the probe signal is measured by a photodetector (PD). The PD output is connected by a 50 Ω low pass filter to a lock-in amplifier (LIA, SR844-200MHz dual phase), thus the readout of the PD is demodulated by the LIA to extract the modulation depth. The focused power was less than 10 mW for both pump and probe beams. The lock-in amplifier (LIA) time constant was set to 100 μs with a slope of 18dB/oct and a sensitivity of 10 μV.
</p>
