<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study adds to the body of work modelling the potential global distribution of 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic>
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Kluza1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Fowler1" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref>. In particular, the model presented here builds upon the previous model developed by Venette and Cohen 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Venette1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, who used CLIMEX to assess the potential climatic suitability for establishment of 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> within the contiguous United States. Stress and soil moisture parameters of the surrogate 
 <italic>Phytophthora</italic> species, 
 <italic>P. cinnamomi</italic>, were replaced with those derived from the published literature on 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic>, much of which became available after the Venette and Cohen 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Venette1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> paper was written. The modelled growth indices of our model and that of Venette and Cohen 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Venette1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> are remarkably similar (Supplementary 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0063508.s006">Fig. S6c and S6d</xref>), differing mostly in the ability to grow under dry conditions (data not shown). There were, however, significant differences in the potential range as indicated by the Ecoclimatic Indices (growth indices with stress indices applied; Supplementary 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0063508.s006">Fig. S6a and S6b</xref>), with a significantly increased area at risk under our model in the west coast states and also the north eastern states, and a projected decreased risk in the southern (stream positive) states of Mississippi, Alabama and Georgia. This comparison highlights the importance of using and updating parameter sets providing the basis for models. Pest Risk Modelling has been described as the ‘art of the possible’ 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Sutherst4" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>. Risk models should be based on the best knowledge of an organism’s distribution and ecology at the time the model is developed, with scope to update and improve the model as new evidence becomes available.
</p>
