<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Notwithstanding uncertainties about host range, no host implies no problem 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-McKenney1" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>. Furthermore, in the case of 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic>, no infectious host implies less of a problem, as rapid expansion of the pathogen’s range has been linked to “super-sporulating” hosts such as 
 <italic>U. californica</italic> (California bay laurel) in California 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Swiecki1" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref> and 
 <italic>L. kaempferi</italic> (Japanese larch) in the United Kingdom 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Brasier1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Webber2" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>. Potential host range studies of species from areas considered to be at risk of 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> invasion have indicated that susceptible and infectious hosts exist on the east coast of the USA, Asia and Australasia 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Brasier1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Brasier7" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Ireland1" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Ireland2" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Hberli1" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Tooley4" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>. Knowledge of these hosts combined with knowledge of the potential geographical distribution is important when concentrating efforts for early detection of the pathogen, or when attempting to uncover the origins of invasive species such as 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic>. The origin of 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> has been hypothesised by many to be in eastern Asia, based upon climatic variables 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Kluza1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref> and origin of hosts such as 
 <italic>Rhododendron</italic>
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Brasier7" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>. Expeditions to regions of Yunnan Province in China, the centre of diversity for 
 <italic>Rhododendron</italic> species, and Taiwan have not yet recovered 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic>
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Goheen1" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Vannini1" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Brasier8" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>. Our results contrast very strongly with that of Kluza et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Kluza1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref> with regards to eastern Asia (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0063508-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). While both models agree that the Yunnan province in South-west China is climatically favourable, elsewhere the models disagree strongly. Where the model of Kluza et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Kluza1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref> indicates that the warmer humid tropical and sub-tropical climates are highly favourable for 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> (e.g., Guangdong, Fujian, Zhejiang and Jiangxi provinces in China), our model indicates that it has a more temperate climatic preference (e.g. Guizhou, Hubei and Hunnan provinces in China). Perhaps targeting stream surveys for 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> in the cooler regions of China, Taiwan (where the closely related 
 <italic>P.lateralis</italic> has been discovered 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Brasier8" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>) or Japan may be more fruitful.
</p>
