<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While the stream positive detection originating from a nursery in Mississippi was associated with infected streamside vegetation in 2010 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-COMTF2" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>, it is unclear whether this association represents a consistent microclimate that allows summer temperatures to be moderated sufficiently for persistence, or whether it is simply an ephemeral population that established between Autumn and Spring of that year, when both the CLIMEX (Supplementary 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0063508.s002">Fig. S2</xref>) and NAPPFAST 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Magarey1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref> models indicate that conditions are likely to be favourable for population growth. Subsequent surveys in this area over the past three years have failed to detect infected streamside vegetation again, despite continued stream positive detections (Steven Oak, USDA Forest Service, personal communication). While this may indicate an ephemeral streamside establishment of the pathogen associated with a suitable microclimate for that particular point in time, it may also simply be a reflection of sampling effort, chance infection and/or detection. This uncertainty illustrates one of the challenges of relying upon single field detections or laboratory observations recorded under constant or simplified diurnal temperature regimes to define stress parameters. Stress parameters are generally best-defined by fitting them to geographical distribution data based on consistent and/or well-designed sampling methodology, using mechanisms that are informed by laboratory experiments or theoretical expectations 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Kriticos4" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>. Irrespective of the explanation for this apparent discrepancy, one would expect that 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> would be unlikely to establish a persistent population away from the streamside vegetation in this unsuitably hot region unless a favourable microclimate existed.
</p>
