<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The qualitative and quantitative profiles of particular basil varieties can differ significantly depending on their geographical origin as it can be seen, for example, for the ‘Purple Opaal’ variety [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-22-01221" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-22-01221" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] or the ‘Red Rubin’ variety [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-22-01221" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-22-01221" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Linalool is the dominant component of the oil derived from European basil varieties [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-22-01221" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-22-01221" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-22-01221" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-22-01221" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. In addition, the components that occurred in larger amounts were geraniol (12.6%), 1.8-cineole (4.1%), and epi-α-cadinol (3.8%). In other studies, the major compounds in basil oil reported were linalool, methyl chavicol, eugenol, bergamotene, and methyl cinnamate [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-22-01221" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>], or methylchavicol, camphor, citral, limonene, methylcinnamate, caryophyllen-β, anethol, terpinen-4-ol, myrcene, thymol, ocimene, and cinnamaldehyde [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-22-01221" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Chalchat and Özcan [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-22-01221" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] showed different concentrations of linalool and other important components in the basil essential oil extracted from the different parts of the herb, such as flowers, leaves, and stems. Among the main constituents of flower oil were estragole (58.26%), fenchone (10.1%), limonene + β-phellandrene (19.41%), and α-phellandrene (4.37%), while estragole (52.60%), limonene (13.64%), exo-fenchyl acetate (10.99%), fenchone (5.70%), α-phellandrene (4.15%), and endo-fenchyl acetate (1.30%) were found as the main components of basil leaf oil. Recently, the effect of elicitation with jasmonic acid (JA) on the plant yield, the production and composition of essential oils of 'Lettuce leaf' basil was evaluated [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-22-01221" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>].
</p>
