<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The results of this study revealed that a small proportion of actual species was found (15% or 199 species) of estimated (1275 species), suggesting that many of the 85% of longhorn beetle species in Thailand were not collected with support from the non-asymptotic species accumulation curve, based on Taxa S, as depicted in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="insects-12-00045-f002">Figure 2</xref>a. This tendency was similar in previous studies that reported 20–50% of the estimated number of longhorn species not being recorded [
 <xref rid="B13-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], and other insect studies showed various percentages of undiscovered species; for example, 24–44% of ant species in the western Amazonian rainforest of Ecuador [
 <xref rid="B37-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]; 10–20% of Auchenorrhyncha and Diptera in the tropical forests of Thailand [
 <xref rid="B38-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]; and 18% of the Empidoidea community in Doi Inthanon National Park, Thailand [
 <xref rid="B39-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Therefore, additional intensive survey with several combined sampling methods are necessary in order to evaluate Cerambycidae fauna in Thailand. The estimated species richness of longhorn beetle from this study had similar trends to results reported from tropical countries, which have a high biodiversity of insects [
 <xref rid="B40-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] such as Laos with 1156 species [
 <xref rid="B42-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], Borneo, Indonesia with over 1300 species catalogued and more than 2000 expected [
 <xref rid="B43-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], southern Yunnan, China, with 220 species [
 <xref rid="B16-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], India with 1536 species [
 <xref rid="B44-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], Australia with 536 Lamiinae species [
 <xref rid="B2-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], and Mexico with more than 1600 species [
 <xref rid="B14-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. 
</p>
