<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ordination analyses indicated that most species of longhorn beetles are distributed among specific regions and most of them strongly correlate with forest type located in low to middle elevation (there being little similarity between sampled communities). We conclude that cerambycids are specific to habitats with narrow distribution. However, equally, or more likely, is the possibility that these results are a consequence of the initial TIGER sampling plan being designed to specifically select dissimilar sites. Herein, the biodiversity data of cerambycids in Thailand came from malaise trap collection, which is passive, non-baited and acts as a flight barrier with no bias. The trap provided interesting data on not only the number of species and their abundance, but also their distribution data, which can be useful for agriculture and forestry including the challenge of conservation. The malaise trap is easy to use and set up and collect specimens. It is an effective trap for catching a large number and a wide variety of flying insects and is popularly used for monitoring insect diversity [
 <xref rid="B38-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], parasitoid wasp (Hymenoptera), bee communities [
 <xref rid="B64-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] and suitable for flying beetles [
 <xref rid="B66-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Although malaise trap was not used as the best tool for collecting longhorn beetle specimens, it was used in conjunction with other methods for studying the diversity of Cerambycidae, which provide complete information, for example, light traps, direct searching on trees, beating, bowl traps, and sweeping, as reported by some previous studies [
 <xref rid="B11-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. For further study, this work recommends that the malaise trap should be combined with other methods which can help in gaining a better understanding and complete information of longhorn beetle fauna. It is reasonable that study on taxonomic revision should include the DNA technique in order to clarify and confirmed species status as a necessary topic in the future because many species are adopted in morphospecies. This study collected cerambycids from forested areas where cerambycid larvae likely play an important role as initial decomposers of trees. We hope to conduct further studies on collections from orchard, rubber or economic tree plantation in order to evaluate their effects on economic plant and host plant relationships. Finally, in this study, a huge number of insects were caught by a malaise trap. We sorted only the target insects (longhorn beetles). The remaining non-target insects including three predominant insects (represented about 95% of total specimens) belong to the order Diptera, Hymenoptera, Coleoptera, and other minor orders are also collected same as other previous reports [
 <xref rid="B66-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-insects-12-00045" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. We classified these non-target insects into the order or family and kept them in the good condition under low temperature at the Entomology section, Queen Sirikit Botanic Garden, where open and welcome for all entomologists who interests in using the material for study.
</p>
