<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26">There are several cases of ant-pollinated plants. In the Western Ghats, ants were recently reported as a pollinator of 
 <italic>Syzigium occidentale</italic> inflorescence
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. In the Atlantic rainforest system, ants are a major pollinator of aggregated inflorescence
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. Although ant-visited or pollinated flowers are not rare in tropics
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>, they are mostly bisexual and have either generalist pollination syndrome or have no bee pollinators on them. We found some amount of pollen sticking onto the ants during our observation. However, as other functional traits of pumpkin flowers—monoecy and highly skewed male–female ratio in populations—did not resonate with the characters of ant pollinated flowers
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>, ants might not play a major role in the pollination of pumpkin flowers. Additionally, exposing flowers to ant body secretions could deter pollen viability
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>, which, however, is not universal for all ant species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. While they feed nectar, ants sometimes damage the pistil base affecting the seed set
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. Pumpkin is a major floral resource for specialist bees, including honey bees, bumblebees, and squash bees in different parts of the world, which perform cross-pollination in their monoecious flowers. Because they are monoecious, the visitors should travel from staminate to pistillate flowers for effecting pollination. It is doubtful that the ants switch visits between staminate and pistillate flowers in pumpkin fields as staminate flowers are abundant and pistillate flowers are not necessarily to be closer to staminate flowers. Although not investigated on all the nine species of ants in this study, Sinu et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup> found that none of the 
 <italic>A. gracilipes-</italic>only visited flowers sets fruits.
</p>
