<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Modifications of yield and composition of the spike lavender essential oil by genetic engineering may have important scientific and commercial applications. Until now, three genes involved in the first steps of the synthesis of terpenes have been overexpressed in spike lavender, the 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> HMG1, DXS and DXR genes, encoding the respective HMGR1S, DXS and DXR enzymes. As expected, the overexpression of the DXS gene produced a significant increase of the end-product monoterpenes derived from an elevated supply of precursors of the MEP isoprenoid pathway without affecting the chlorophyll and carotenoid content [
 <xref rid="B34-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Surprisingly, the overexpression of the DXR enzyme did not lead to an increase of monoterpenes or photosynthetic pigments [
 <xref rid="B35-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. In contrast, the overexpression of the HMG1 gene from 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, led to an increased yield of essential oil since transgenic T0 plants accumulated significantly more essential oil constituents as compared to controls (up to 2.1- and 1.8-fold in leaves and flowers, respectively). These transgenic plants also increased its amount of the end-product sterols, β-sitosterol and stigmasterol (average differences of 1.8- and 1.9-fold, respectively), but did not accumulate more carotenoids or chlorophylls as compared to controls. The potential of the mevalonate pathway for enhanced isoprenoid production by upregulation of HMGR and other enzymes of the pathway as well as its interaction with the MEP pathway have been updated recently [
 <xref rid="B36-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The increased levels of essential oil and sterols observed in the transgenic T0 plants were maintained in the progeny that inherited the HMG1 transgene. Therefore, genetic manipulation of the MVA pathway also increases essential oil yield in spike lavender, suggesting a contribution for this cytosolic pathway to monoterpene and sesquiterpene biosynthesis in leaves and flowers of the species [
 <xref rid="B37-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. 
</p>
