<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In addition to excrement, kitchen waste, coffee grounds, palm seed meal, agricultural waste, and other organic waste can be effectively converted by 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae [
 <xref rid="B152-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">152</xref>]. Kitchen waste contains not only large amounts of organic components, such as starch and cellulose, but also fat, salt, and abundant trace elements. This form of organic waste continuously affects the environment. Another common form of organic waste is fruit and vegetable waste from food companies or markets. At present, treatment methods for organic waste primarily include incineration, landfills, fodder, anaerobic digestion, aerobic composting, and earthworm compost [
 <xref rid="B153-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">153</xref>]. However, these treatment methods cannot satisfy the requirements of environmental protection and a high degree of resource utilization. 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae has been applied to the conversion of kitchen, fruit and vegetable waste [
 <xref rid="B13-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B146-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">146</xref>,
 <xref rid="B147-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">147</xref>,
 <xref rid="B154-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">154</xref>,
 <xref rid="B155-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">155</xref>]. Research has shown that among the larval instars of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic>, 6th instar larvae exhibited the highest survival rate and the highest conversion rate in converting kitchen residue, particularly when the moisture level was 60%. Regarding the dry matter of old mature larvae, values of 44.7% protein and 37.2% grease were obtained [
 <xref rid="B113-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>]. In addition, the NH
 <sup class="sup">4+</sup> of the kitchen waste was 5–6 times higher following treatment than before treatment; such conversion has the potential to offset the nitrogen accumulation caused by fertilization [
 <xref rid="B156-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">156</xref>]. Therefore, there are substantial prospects for the conversion and treatment of kitchen, fruit and vegetable wastes by 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae. More importantly, effective treatment and conversion of municipal organic solid waste and industrial organic waste by larvae has been achieved [
 <xref rid="B43-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B154-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">154</xref>,
 <xref rid="B157-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">157</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">158</xref>]. These advances provide a basis for the large-scale cultivation of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> and the large-scale treatment of organic wastes [
 <xref rid="B136-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">136</xref>]. In 2015, based on the effective conversion of organic wastes by 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae, a specialized 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae breeding base was established in Tieyong Town, Huidong County, Guangdong Province. In the same year, the output and the kitchen waste treatment capacity were 1.3 t/day and 7.8 t/day, respectively. The bioconversion of a mixture of rice straw and kitchen waste was investigated. A total of 2000 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae were used to convert 1.0 kg of an organic waste mixture (30% rice straw; 70% kitchen waste). After 10 days, 65.5% of the cellulose, 56.3% of the hemicellulose, 8.8% of the lignin, 91.6% of the protein, and 71.6% of the fat had been digested by 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae and converted into their own biomass. Therefore, the transformation of agricultural waste using 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae has excellent prospects.
</p>
