<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The aromatic amino acids tyrosine and phenylalanine are metabolised by intestinal bacteria to the phenolic compound, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cresol, which is a uremic toxin [
 <xref rid="B255-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">255</xref>,
 <xref rid="B256-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">256</xref>]. This compound is detoxified in the liver and colon where it is sulfated to become 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cresol-sulfate [
 <xref rid="B257-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">257</xref>,
 <xref rid="B258-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">258</xref>]. The absence of 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cresol-sulfate in the plasma of germ-free mice provides further evidence of the role of the gut microbiota in its production [
 <xref rid="B116-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>]. Under normal conditions 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cresol-sulfate enters the circulation and ends up in the urine where it is excreted from the body [
 <xref rid="B256-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">256</xref>]. Information regarding the specific intestinal microbes responsible for 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cresol generation is still unclear, but 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> studies have shown that members of the following families can produce it; 
 <italic class="italic">Clostridiaceae, Eubacteriaceae, Lachnospiraceae, Ruminococcaceae, Staphylococcaceae, Veillonaceae, Bacteroidaceae, Porphyromonadaceae, Bifidobacteriaceae,</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Fusobacteriaceae</italic> [
 <xref rid="B256-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">256</xref>]. However, in patients suffering from chronic kidney disease, excretion is impaired. Chronic kidney disease and cardiovascular disease are closely associated and risk of death from cardiovascular disease is much higher in patients with end-stage renal disease [
 <xref rid="B259-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">259</xref>] and evidence strongly indicates that 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cresol-sulfate is a causal link. 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-Cresol-sulfate has been shown to disturb the normal cell cycle in a mouse preadipocyte cell line, to induce apoptosis, inhibit differentiation of preadipocyes to mature adipocytes, and to decrease glucose uptake at baseline and after insulin stimulation [
 <xref rid="B260-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">260</xref>]. It has been shown to have a pro-inflammatory effect on unstimulated leucocytes [
 <xref rid="B261-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">261</xref>]. It induced shedding of endothelial microparticles in human endothelial cells, a marker of endothelial damage [
 <xref rid="B262-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">262</xref>]. It induced oxidative stress in both endothelial and vascular smooth muscle cells at a concentration representative of that found in dialysis patients, and it increased contraction of mouse thoracic aorta and eventually led to inward eutrophic remodelling, a feature of uremic vasculopathy, suggesting it may contribute to hypertension and cardiovascular mortality in chronic kidney disease [
 <xref rid="B263-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">263</xref>]. In nephrectomised mice, it promoted cardiac apoptosis which was at least partly attributed to the induction of NADPH oxidase activity and production of reactive oxygen species [
 <xref rid="B264-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">264</xref>]. Poesen et al. [
 <xref rid="B265-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">265</xref>] showed that intestinal uptake of 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cresol in patients with chronic kidney disease associated with cardiovascular disease independent of renal function. 
</p>
