<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In another study, Amjadi et al. produced electrospun zein/k-carrageenan (KC) nanofibers after incorporating 0.5% and 50% 
 <italic>w</italic>/
 <italic>w</italic> of zinc oxide nanoparticles (ZnO) and rosemary essential oil (REO) [
 <xref rid="B240-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">240</xref>]. The SEM image showed that after encapsulating ZnO nanoparticles in zein90/KC10/REO nanofibers, a bead-free homogeneous morphology was observed, indicating no adverse consequence of REO on the nanofiber morphology, which was improved by the ZnO nanoparticle encapsulation. The zein polymer tensile strength, Young’s modulus, elongation at break, water-contact angle, and thermal stability (revealed by DSC) were enhanced by incorporating the KC, REO, and ZnO nanoparticles. An increment in the mechanical properties, thermal stability, and hydrophobic nature of zein after ZnO nanoparticles and REO fillers was due to the hydrogen bonds between zein, KC, and ZnO nanoparticles, which enhanced the polymer chains compactness and crystallinity [
 <xref rid="B241-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">241</xref>,
 <xref rid="B242-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">242</xref>,
 <xref rid="B243-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">243</xref>,
 <xref rid="B244-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">244</xref>]. The addition of KC and REO increased zein nanofibers’ ability to eradicate free radicals easily, resulting in enhancement of antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B245-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">245</xref>,
 <xref rid="B246-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">246</xref>,
 <xref rid="B247-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">247</xref>]. Therefore, the zein90/KC10/REO and zein90/KC10/ZnO nanoparticle nanofibers had the highest DPPH scavenging activity. A biocompatibility assay revealed that in the presence of all nanofibers (zein, zein90/KC10, zein90/KC/ZnO, zein90/KC/REO, and zein90/KC/ZnO/REO), human umbilical vein endothelial cells showed more than 97% of viability, indicated that the nanofibers exhibited no toxicity toward these cells after 24 h. It was found that after increasing the incubation time from 48 h to 72 h, the cell viability decreased. However, it was higher than 80%, which proved that the nanofiber samples had excellent biocompatibility and the capability to support cell proliferation. Furthermore, it was found that the zein-based nanofibers enhanced the viability of human umbilical vein endothelial cells after incorporating the KC into them [
 <xref rid="B248-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">248</xref>]. Zein90/KC10/ZnO nanofiber displayed limited cell viability after 48 and 72 h since ZnO released Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> ions, which induced a homeostasis imbalance, resulting in unsatisfactory cellular responses such as cytotoxicity, damage to DNA, and oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="B244-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">244</xref>]. However, the cell-viability values were almost similar between zein90/KC10/ZnO/RE and the control samples. This phenomenon could be related to the compensation of the ZnO nanoparticles’ detrimental effect on cell viability by conjunction with REO. Zein90/KC10/ZnO and zein90/KC10/REO nanofibers showed a more significant inhibition zone against 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> as compared to pure zein (control) and zein90/KC10 nanofibers, which did not show antibacterial activity against these strains [
 <xref rid="B241-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">241</xref>,
 <xref rid="B242-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">242</xref>,
 <xref rid="B243-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">243</xref>,
 <xref rid="B249-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">249</xref>] Therefore, the zein90/KC10/ZnO/REO nanofibers exhibited the highest antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>. The ZnO produced reactive oxygen species and released Zn
 <sup>2+</sup>, which increased cell-membrane permeability and interrupted protein synthesis and DNA replication, resulting in the killing of bacteria [
 <xref rid="B244-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">244</xref>,
 <xref rid="B250-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">250</xref>]. Due to the presence of antibacterial components in REO, such as carnosic acid, rosmarinic acid, carnosol, and isopropanol, and rosmanol, REO-containing nanofibers showed antibacterial activity [
 <xref rid="B242-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">242</xref>]. Therefore, the prepared electrospun nanofiber zein/KC/ZnO/REO is considered an essential candidate for packaging purposes to enhance shelf-life and quality of food products.
</p>
