<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par70">Secondary outcomes include: 
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par71">Patient-determined effective dose of THC/CBD formulation, defined as the dose that achieves symptom relief with acceptable side effects.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par72">ESAS TSDS at days 7, 21 and 28.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par73">Physical and emotional ESAS scores at each time point. 
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <label/>
      <p id="Par74">Physical scores will be measured by the Australia-modified Karnofsky Performance Status (AKPS) and Resource Utilisation Groups-Activities of Daily Living Scale (RUG-ADL). The AKPS is a validated variant of the Karnofsky Performance Status. The Australian version can be applied to both in- and outpatients and is sensitive to changes in function over time [
       <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The RUG-ADL is an instrument developed for the measurement of nursing dependency. The ADL scale measures patients’ needs for assistance in activities of daily living (eating, bed mobility, transferring and toileting) [
       <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].
      </p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par75">Individual symptom scores (descriptive analysis only).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par76">Oral morphine equivalent (OME), average use at baseline and weekly.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par77">Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC), days 7, 14, 21 and 28. 
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <label/>
      <p id="Par78">This is a subjective measure of symptom change completed by the patients themselves [
       <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].
      </p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par79">Clinical Global Impressions (CGI) Scale, days 7, 14, 21 and 28. 
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <label/>
      <p id="Par80">This is a subjective measure of symptom change completed by the investigating clinician [
       <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].
      </p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par81">The Depression, Anxiety, Stress Scale (DASS-21) score baseline and days 14 and 28. 
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <label/>
      <p id="Par82">DASS-21 is a self-reported 21-item scale, 7 questions per sub-item questionnaire measuring depression, anxiety and stress. The DASS-21 will be used for assessment at baseline (day 0) and days 14 and 28 [
       <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].
      </p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par83">EORTC score QoL baseline and days 14 and 28 [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].
   </p>
   <p id="Par84">This is a QoL measure found valid for use in a wide variety of cancer populations. To reduce patient burden, we will use the 15-question subset commonly used for the palliative care population.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par85">NCI common terminology for adverse events V4.03, days 2, 4, 7, 9, 11, 14, 16, 18, 21, 23, 25 and 28 [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] 
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <label/>
      <p id="Par86">The NCI CTCAE is a severity grading system for adverse events. Adverse events relate to an unfavourable or unintended sign, symptom or disease temporarily associated with a medical treatment or a procedure which may not be related to the medical treatment or procedure. The CTCAE has a grading of 1 (mild) to 5 (death). The known common adverse events associated with cannabinoids are confusion, somnolence, paranoia, anxiety, mood changes, psychosis, hypertension, tachycardia, hyperhidrosis, nausea, vomiting and abdominal pain [
       <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].
      </p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
