<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Despite the successful isolation of some oil-degrading bacteria, most of the indigenous bacterial strains could not be isolated by conventional culture-based methods. This might be attributed to the fact that artificial culture conditions are different from the 
 <italic class="italic">in situ</italic> environment, due to the absence of symbiotic organisms and specific nutrient levels (Zengler et al., 
 <xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>). Furthermore, specific environmental conditions in deep sea (low temperature, O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> restriction and hydrostatic pressure) are always neglected or difficult to setup in the 
 <italic class="italic">ex situ</italic> experiments, which limit the isolation of oil-degrading bacteria (Scoma et al., 
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Recently, some previously uncultured microorganisms were successively grown in pure culture using newly-developed culturing techniques, including (1) supplying various chemical compounds found in their natural environment (Kaeberlein et al., 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>; Rappé et al., 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>; Zengler et al., 
 <xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>); (2) lengthening the period of incubation and protecting cells from exogenous peroxides (Stevenson et al., 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>); (3) isolating uncultived microorganisms in a simulated natural environment with specific devices (Kaeberlein et al., 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>); (4) high-throughput dilution to extinction culturing technology (HTC) (Rappé et al., 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>; Stingl et al., 
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>). The above microbiological cultivating technologies have not been used to isolate bacteria from the DWH oil spill-contaminated environment, and could be considered in microbiological investigations of future oil spills. Considering the particularity of the deep-sea environment, the method based on the simulated/real natural environment (Kaeberlein et al., 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>) can be applied in future studies. Briefly, surface sediments with 
 <italic class="italic">in situ</italic> microorganism can be mixed with warmed agar and sealed in a diffusion chamber sealed by two membranes which not only allow exchange of chemicals between the chamber and the environment, but also restrict the movement of cells. The sealed chambers can be cultivated in a marine aquarium with simulated natural environment (low temperature, O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> restriction and hydrostatic pressure) or 
 <italic class="italic">in situ</italic> in the deep-sea environment. The development of novel cultivating technologies to isolate previously uncultured bacteria could permit a more comprehensive understanding of unexplored bacterial communities, including their metabolic pathways, and functions.
</p>
