<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Before evaluating the effects of the aqueous extract of 
 <italic>D. edulis</italic> leaves on ovariectomized rats, a phytochemical analysis of that extract was performed. Results showed that the aqueous extract of 
 <italic>D. edulis</italic> contains various secondary metabolites such as alkaloids, phenols, flavonoids, triterpenoids, tannins, saponins, anthocyanins, and anthraquinones. However, we observed the absence of sterols in this extract. These results are similar to those obtained by Ogboru et al. [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] in their research work in Nigeria in which they used the aqueous extract of the stem bark of 
 <italic>D. edulis</italic>. In Ivory Coast, the fruitcake of 
 <italic>D. edulis</italic> was also found to contain same groups of molecules [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, contrary to these studies, sterols were not detectable in the aqueous extract of 
 <italic>D. edulis</italic> leaves in the present research work. These results suggest that the harvest site and the part of the plant used have a direct impact on the presence of secondary metabolites in the plant. The quantitative analysis revealed that the aqueous extract of 
 <italic>D. edulis</italic> leaves contains significant amounts of total phenols, flavonoids, and flavonols whose proportions were different (inferior) from those reported by Ogboru et al. [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] in Nigeria who worked with the stem bark and Ano-Aka et al. [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] in Ivory Coast who worked with the fruitcake of the same plant. These results suggest that the harvest site and the part of the plant used also have an impact on the amount of secondary metabolites in the plant. In addition, secondary metabolites such as anthraquinones, alkaloids, total phenols, flavonoids, and flavonols present in plants are reported to be antioxidant agents [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], which may act 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> to prevent oxidative damage to DNA, proteins, and lipids, thus reducing cell proliferation and by extension the risk of cancer development [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. To this regard, the literature reports that polyphenols such as tannins, saponins, and triterpenoids are bioactive compounds that possess antiproliferative and anticancer properties [
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>–
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Maria Graça et al. [
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] and Amoussa et al. [
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] reported the antioxidant activities of phenols, flavonoids, and flavonols. Indeed, oxidative stress was found to promote cell proliferation [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], thus contributing to the initiation and the progression of cancer [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Therefore, plant extracts containing secondary metabolites with antioxidant activities could be efficient against proliferation-related diseases.
</p>
