<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>P.gingivalis, P.intermedia, Aggregatibacteractinomycetemcomitans</italic> was cultured as per the standard protocol. The microbial were incubated with pine tar gel. After 24 hours incubation, an inhibition zone of about 12–13 mm around the 75 µl well was observed in all the four species in the agar plates. As per the microbial nomenclature, an antibiotic or an anti-microbial agent is bent to have significant inhibitory effect on microbial reproduction and considered positive if the inhibition zone of 1 mm or more around the well was observed. In this study the pine tar exhibited an inhibition zone of 12 mm (
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). The result of disc diffusion analysis was sufficient enough to illustrate that 75 µl tar oil solution produced growth inhibition of microbial strains. Serial dilution was conducted with tar oil against 
 <italic>P. gingivalis</italic> and 
 <italic>P. intermedia, A. actinomycetemcomitans</italic> species (
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The study observed a significant sensitivity for up to six serial dilutions of the tar oil solution against 
 <italic>P.gingivalis</italic> and 
 <italic>P.intermedia, A. actinomycetemcomitans</italic> species whereas 
 <italic>Streptomyces</italic> species recorded significant sensitivity for five serial dilutions of the gel. A scientific study is always important to establish the efficacy of a lethal dose to determine its anti-microbial property. In this study we postulate the efficiency of pine tar oil as a potential gum paint medicine for tropical application on infected dental gum tissues. Its usage in alternative medicinal practise for centuries, have proved its reliability and edible nature, any alternative medicine to bring in drug market needs a confirmatory and extensive repeated scientific clinical study. Based on these collected data, the drug is assembled for treatment plan (
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). This study is novel in terms of introducing pine tar as an antibiotic replacement for the management of dental periodontitis condition. The in vitro study of these four major dental plaques causing microbial species sustains the rationale for launching pine tar as gum paint product for dental caries. Furiga 
 <italic>et al.</italic> studied the effect of a pine bark extract (PBE) against artificial oral biofilms (
 <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). In a study by Sugimoto 
 <italic>et al</italic> (
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), Pycnogenol® (PYC) a standardized bark extract from French maritime pine (Pinus pinaster Aiton) was used to evaluate antibacterial inhibitory effects on alveolar bone resorption, a characteristic feature of periodontitis, induced by 
 <italic>Porphyromonas gingivalis</italic> and osteoclast differentiation, in rat models. The results revealed that PYC may prevent alveolar bone resorption through its antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>P. gingivalis</italic> and by suppressing osteoclastogenesis (
 <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). In another study, human gingival fibroblasts (HGF cells) were employed to assess the cytotoxic potential of the 
 <italic>P. tropicalis</italic> and 
 <italic>P. elliottii</italic> resins (
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).
</p>
