<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Mannoheptulose from avocado fruit was first isolated and identified by 
 <xref rid="ref71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">LaForge (1916)</xref>. Mannoheptulose and perseitol have been reported as the major soluble sugars in the phloem sap, leaf petiole exudates, seed, and mesocarp of avocado (
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cowan, 2004</xref>). Based on perseitol concentrations of 2.5-fold higher in the sap from the trunk of the avocado tree than the sap from the petioles, different sites of synthesis for D-mannoheptulose and perseitol are assumed (
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cowan, 2004</xref>). A possible route for D-mannoheptulose biosynthesis in avocado fruit involving D-arabinose-5-phosphate ↔ D-ribose-5-phosphate being both substrates converted to hexose 6-phosphate and triose phosphates 
 <italic class="italic">via</italic> intermediates that include D-mannoheptulose 7-phosphate and D-altro-heptulose 1,7-bisphosphate has been postulated by 
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cowan (2004)</xref>. Similarly, to the pathway of sedoheptulose biosynthesis, D-arabinose-5-phosphate and D-ribose-5-phosphate are then the substrates for transketolase activity and formation of D-manno-heptulose-7-phosphate and 1,7 biphosphate. Arabinose has been reported in substantial amounts in avocado (
 <xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jeong and Huber, 2004</xref>). By phosphate activity then, D-mannoheptulose would be formed. 
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cowan (2004)</xref> sustains that D-mannoheptulose is a potent inhibitor of respiration and prevents entry of glucose into glycolysis acting as a competitive inhibitor of hexokinase, thus altering the fate of sugar metabolism. Thus, to sustain fruit growth and development, it becomes crucial the effects described above of D-mannoheptulose in order to continue sugar export and phloem loading.
</p>
