<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In avocado leaves, 
 <xref rid="ref75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al. (1999a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002)</xref> reported D-mannoheptulose and perseitol as products of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> assimilation. D-mannoheptulose is formed in leaves as a phosphorylated product of sedoheptulose 1,7 biphosphate 
 <italic class="italic">via</italic> condensation of dihydroxyacetone phosphate and erythrose-4-phosphate (
 <xref rid="ref75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al., 1999a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>). Previously, 
 <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Häfliger et al. (1999)</xref> mentioned that C
 <sub class="sub">7</sub> sugars can be formed by three well-known enzymatic reactions that form C
 <sub class="sub">7</sub> intermediates: (1) erythrose-4-P + dihydroxyacetone-P sedoheptulose 1,7-bis P corresponding to an aldose reaction; (2) xylulose-5-P – ribose-5-P sedoheptulose-7-P-glyceraldehyde-3-P corresponding to a transketolase reaction; and (3) a transaldolase reaction – fructose-6-P + erythrose-4-P sedoheptulose-7-P + glyceraldehyde 3-P. All three pathways require NADPH/NADP
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>. Following, 
 <xref rid="ref123" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tesfay et al. (2012)</xref> reported conversion of D-mannoheptulose to perseitol and vice versa in dry seed, cotyledons, and mesocarp of avocado together with detection of aldolase enzymes possibly a transaldolase present in different avocado tissue types and potentially involved in the conversion of the C
 <sub class="sub">7</sub> sugar storage form (perseitol) into the C
 <sub class="sub">7</sub> sugar transport form D-mannoheptulose. But still, as reported by 
 <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cowan (2017)</xref>, the origin of sedoheptulose 7-P and mannoheptulose 7-P as precursors of heptoses and heptitols in plants remains to be elucidated. Both sedoheptulose and mannoheptulose together with sucrose are products of the reductive pentose phosphate pathway in mature source leaves being C
 <sub class="sub">7</sub> sugar formation stimulated during photosynthesis having as evidence that mature leaves of avocado incorporated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> into mannoheptulose-7-P, mannoheptulose, sedoheptulose 7-P, sucrose, and perseitol (
 <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cowan, 2017</xref>).
</p>
