<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The least ambitious aim would be to ensure aquafeeds satisfy the essential physiological requirements of the fish itself, which minimally is the level required to prevent deficiency signs, but optimally the level to ensure maximum growth and good health [
 <xref rid="B2-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. This would parallel the current situation with essential amino acids (EAA). As certain EAA are deficient in many plant meals, feeds are generally supplemented with small amounts of crystalline EAA (e.g., lysine and methionine) to ensure requirements are met [
 <xref rid="B60-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. In the same way, high proportions of vegetable oils devoid of EPA and DHA are used in more sustainable feed formulations and, while the feeds still satisfy minimum requirements to prevent EFA deficiency, they may now be approaching sub-optimal for fish health. This is exactly the situation faced by many human populations where instances of EFA deficiency are rare or virtually unknown, but many/most have dietary levels of n-3 LC-PUFA and, especially EPA and DHA, that are below dietary recommendations for optimal health [
 <xref rid="B25-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. In terms of EPA and DHA content, microalgal oil (e.g., Veramaris
 <sup class="sup">®</sup>), is the closest EFA equivalent to crystalline EAA and so it could be used in relatively small amounts to supplement current formulations with sufficient EPA+DHA to ensure optimum fish health. Of course, while basic EFA requirement levels may be known, the level of EPA+DHA required to ensure maximum growth and optimal health in fish fed modern, high performance (energy) feeds has arguably not been determined empirically for any fish species [
 <xref rid="B85-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>]. Furthermore, a strategy focussing primarily on the requirements for fish health, and using only relatively small amounts of the new EPA and DHA sources to replace some or all of the fish oil currently used in feeds, would not tackle the gap between supply and demand for human consumers.
</p>
