<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030">Botanicals such as essential oils, spices, herbs and crude extracts present outstanding alternatives for the discovery of biofungicides and nutraceuticals for mitigating mycotoxicosis and related infections. Botanicals are generally regarded as environmentally friendly and safer alternative sources of bioagents for the control of fungi and mycotoxins in food and feed (
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Iram et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Adebo et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib124" ref-type="bibr">Prakash et al., 2020</xref>). They are more affordable as opposed to other materials used for the same purpose, they provide a synergistic approach as protectants of fungal/mycotoxin contamination and further stimulate pathways that elicit the natural defence systems in plant tissues (
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">da Cruz Cabral et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Alberts et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Gacem et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">Meng et al., 2020</xref>). They contain various phytochemicals with pharmacological properties against various diseases. Recent studies have been conducted on the possible application of botanicals as bio-fungicides and nutraceuticals to ameliorate the proliferation of toxigenic fungi and mycotoxin contamination in food and feed (
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Dikhoba et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib123" ref-type="bibr">Ponzilacqua et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Kavitha et al., 2020</xref>). This review aimed to elucidate the use of botanical extracts and their phytochemical compounds to prevent and detoxify mycotoxins without any adverse effect on the nutritional value of food and feed. We also review nano-encapsulation technology which can be adopted to improve bioavailability and solubility of phytochemicals used as biofungicides and nutraceuticals to prevent growth of mycotoxigenic fungi and subsequent mycotoxin contamination.
</p>
