<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Re-colonizing dynamics in dry acidic grasslands are strongly determined by regeneration characteristics of each species, such as life cycle, dispersal abilities and germination pattern [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Thus, it can be expected that at least some vegetation pattern changes observed in field can be explained by differences in germination requirements. Low water holding capacity of the soil and possibly soil nitrogen (N) status are the main factors limiting completion of germination and seedling survival in this kind of environments [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Total N concentrations recorded in the soils of 
 <italic>Spergulo-Corynephoretum</italic> vary between 0.01 and 0.08% of soil dry weight (SDW) (equal to 100–800 mg kg
 <sup>-1</sup> SDW [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]) which suggests its poor nutritional quality. Regarding N type, there are two major mineral forms available to plants, i.e. ammonium (NH
 <sub>4</sub>
 <sup>+</sup>) and nitrate (NO
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>‒</sup>). On inland sand dunes, NH
 <sub>4</sub>
 <sup>+</sup> soil concentration is typically higher than that of NO
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>‒</sup> [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Low net N mineralization and greater concentration of NH
 <sub>4</sub>
 <sup>+</sup> than NO
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>‒</sup> are connected with N circulation process and result from halted nitrification process in pioneer sand-settled communities [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Thus, acidic soils provide NH
 <sub>4</sub>
 <sup>+</sup> as the predominant chemical form of N and, interestingly, this form of N is preferred by acidophilous plant species, while more or less calciphilous species prefer NO
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>‒</sup> [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. However, this is totally opposite to molecular basis of N uptake, where easier scavenging of NO
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>‒</sup> by plants can be observed in acidic soils due to greater availability of H
 <sup>+</sup> for NO
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>‒</sup>/H
 <sup>+</sup> symport mechanism [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
</p>
