<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To ascertain if CD4 membrane organization was correlated with fixation-mediated actin cytoskeleton disruption we repeated the live-to-fixed cell correlation using SMLM and PEM with different fixation temperatures. PEM is an ideal buffer for actin preservation (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>), and the range of temperatures provide different fixation efficiencies, with decreasing efficiency from 37°C (ideal) to 23°C (intermediate) to 4°C (lowest efficiency). We took advantage of the versatile NanoJ-Fluidics (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>) framework to correlate live and fixed cell imaging of COS7 cells (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">Figure 3A</xref>). As expected, regardless of the fixation strategy we obtain a fairly homogeneous distribution of CD4 on the surface of COS7 cells (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">Figure 3B</xref>) at an in-cell high-resolution [43–50 nm by FRC (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>)]. To further explore the nature of the CD4 organization we used SR-Tesseler (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>) to determine if the cluster sizes and cluster density of CD4 would change depending on the fixation approach (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">Figure 3C</xref>). Interestingly, despite the little changes observed by SIM (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>), both CD4 cluster size and cluster density changed with the fixation approach. Whereas, the mean CD4 cluster size in ideal conditions (PEM buffer at 37°C) is 59 nm, reducing the temperature to 23 or 4°C is enough to change CD4 organization, increasing the mean cluster size to 65 nm (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), albeit these differences are likely not biologically relevant (see section Discussion). The fixation conditions also influence the CD4 cluster density in COS7 cells, with densities of 1.3 clusters/μm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> at 37°C, 1.8 clusters/μm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> at 23°C, and 3.8 clusters/μm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> at 4°C.
</p>
