<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Traditional Chinese Medicine (TCM) originatedin ancient China and it hasa 5000-year history. Rooted in ancient Eastern philosophies such as Taoism, TCM focuses on a holistic view between humans and nature (Shahrajabian et al., 2018
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr"> ▶</xref>, Shahrajabian et al., 2019
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr"> ▶</xref>). About 5000 traditional remedies are available in China; they account for approximately one fifth of the entire Chinese pharmaceutical market.In TCM, it is believed that food and medicine come from the same origin but with different uses and applications (Shahrajabian et al., 2020a
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr"> ▶</xref>, b, c, d.) Cultivation of Chinese medicinal herbs and usage of TCM significantly help to promote sustainable agricultural development via growing demand for organic and herbal products in different regions. Chinese medicinal plants, both endemic and widespread, must be preserved since these plants are renewable sources of new drugs. On the basis of economic prospects, organic farming of goji berry may lead to increase more market opportunity, to maintain high market price, to achieve optimal quality and economic returns and to secure economic growth and social stability. In these years, since TCM has become more integrated into medical practice in the West, there is a need to bridge conceptual and practical differences between Western medicine and Chinese medicine. Goji berry (
 <italic>L. barbarum</italic>) is known as an extremely nutritious food in Asia, and it has been extensively eaten raw, consumed as juice or wine, brewed into herbal tea or prepared as a tincture, eaten as salads and used widely in other culinary preparations. Its leaves are prepared as a tea. Besides, its uses in food and culinary, goji berry has important roles in TCM. The aim of this review is to survey composition, potential health benefits and pharmacological benefits of goji berry.
</p>
